<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="70587">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02019641</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>140027</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>14-CC-0027</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02019641</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The NIH Exercise Therapy for Advanced Lung Disease Trials: Response and Adaptation to Aerobic Exercise in Patients With Interstitial Lung Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>The NIH Exercise Therapy for Advanced Lung Disease Trials: Response and Adaptation to Aerobic Exercise in Patients With Interstitial Lung Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>George Mason University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      We propose a randomized controlled trial (RCT) to determine the safety and efficacy of
      aerobic exercise for patients who have interstitial lung disease (ILD) uncomplicated by
      pulmonary hypertension. Aerobic exercise training (AET) based rehabilitation has become a
      standard of care for patients with pulmonary diseases such as COPD. In an uncontrolled
      study, we have observed more efficient cardiorespiratory function, increased physical work
      capacity, and improved health related quality of life (HRQoL), following AET, in patients
      who have ILD without pulmonary hypertension. We have also observed, in a RCT, similar
      findings in patients who have pulmonary hypertension complicated by ILD of various
      etiologies. Serious adverse events resulting from AET were not observed in these studies.
      Our work to date has established plausibility for the efficacy of AET and its safety for
      patients with ILD. A RCT is now needed to determine the efficacy of AET as a medically
      prescribed and supervised intervention in patients who have ILD. Our research team is
      uniquely qualified to undertake this research and is one of the few teams possessing the
      experience and background necessary for contributing to this novel, understudied, yet
      critical field of rehabilitation research.

      Subjects will be over the age of 21 years and living within a reasonable travel distance
      from the greater Washington D.C. area.  All tests will be conducted at the NIH Clinical
      Center and subjects will receive AET or a control regimen of patient education at the NIH
      Clinical Center. The staff are well experienced in providing exercise therapy for patients
      with ILD

      There will be two primary treatment conditions. Patients with ILD will be randomized to
      either an intervention consisting of AET plus patient education (AET+) or a control
      condition that includes patient education only (CON).  AET will consist of a 10-week regimen
      of supervised treadmill walking three times a week.  The duration of the exercise sessions
      will progress from 30 minutes to 45 minutes per session over the 10 weeks as tolerated.  The
      intensity of the exercise will be between 70 and 80% of the patient   s heart rate reserve.

      Those randomized to control will not engage in AET. There will, however, be a secondary
      study: a crossover design in which subjects in the CON group will subsequently complete the
      AET regimen.

      The primary outcome measure for our trial will be 6-minute walk test distance (6MWD).
      Secondary outcome variables will include treadmill cardiorespiratory exercise test (tCPET)
      results with, pulmonary gas exchange, central circulatory function, and muscle oxygenation.
      A number of questionnaires will also be completed including: St. George   s Respiratory
      Questionnaire, Fatigue Severity Scale, SF-36v2 Health Survey, Human Activity Profile,
      Profile of Mood States, and King   s Brief Interstitial Lung Disease Health Status
      Questionnaire. All of this data will be obtained before and after the AET+ and CON regimens
      and in both of the secondary studies.

      AET is generally safe, inexpensive, and can easily be made available and accessible to
      almost everyone. It requires no approval by regulatory agencies and is thus available as a
      medically prescribed and supervised intervention almost immediately following confirmation
      of its safety and efficacy. Six-minute walk distance is associated with improved HRQoL in
      patients with ILD and in specific subsets. Effective use of AET as a rehabilitative
      intervention could have a high degree of impact on these personal and public health outcomes
      in this advanced lung disease subset.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We propose a rand

      omized controlled trial (RCT) to determine the safety and efficacy of aerobic exercise for
      patients who have interstitial lung disease (ILD) uncomplicated by pulmonary hypertension.
      Aerobic exercise training (AET) based rehabilitation has become a standard of care for
      patients with pulmonary diseases such as COPD. In an uncontrolled study, we have observed
      more efficient cardiorespiratory function, increased physical work capacity, and improved
      health related quality of life (HRQoL), following AET, in patients who have ILD without
      pulmonary hypertension. We have also observed, in a RCT, similar findings in patients who
      have pulmonary hypertension complicated by ILD of various etiologies. Serious adverse events
      resulting from AET were not observed in these studies. Our work to date has established
      plausibility for the efficacy of AET and its safety for patients with ILD. A RCT is now
      needed to determine the efficacy of AET as a medically prescribed and supervised
      intervention in patients who have ILD. Our research team is uniquely qualified to undertake
      this research and is one of the few teams possessing the experience and background necessary
      for contributing to this novel, understudied, yet critical field of rehabilitation research.

      Subjects will be over the age of 21 years and living within a reasonable travel distance
      from the greater Washington D.C. area.  All tests will be conducted at the NIH Clinical
      Center and subjects will receive AET or a control regimen of patient education at the NIH
      Clinical Center. The staff are well experienced in providing exercise therapy for patients
      with ILD.

      There will be two primary treatment conditions. Patients with ILD will be randomized to
      either an intervention consisting of AET plus patient education (AET+) or a control
      condition that includes patient education only (CON).  AET will consist of a 10-week regimen
      of supervised treadmill walking three times a week.  The duration of the exercise sessions
      will progress from 30 minutes to 45 minutes per session over the 10 weeks as tolerated.  The
      intensity of the exercise will be between 70 and 80% of the patient   s heart rate reserve.
      Those randomized to control will not engage in AET. There will, however, be a secondary
      study: a crossover design in which subjects in the CON group will subsequently complete the
      AET regimen.

      The primary outcome measure for our trial will be 6-minute walk test distance (6MWD).
      Secondary outcome variables will include treadmill cardiorespiratory exercise test (tCPET)
      results with, pulmonary gas exchange, central circulatory function, and muscle oxygenation.
      A number of questionnaires will also be completed including: St. George   s Respiratory
      Questionnaire, Fatigue Severity Scale, SF-36v2 Health Survey, Human Activity Profile,
      Profile of Mood States, and King   s Brief Interstitial Lung Disease Health Status
      Questionnaire. All of this data will be obtained before and after the AET+ and CON regimens
      and in both of the secondary studies.

      AET is generally safe, inexpensive, and can easily be made available and accessible to
      almost everyone. It requires no approval by regulatory agencies and is thus available as a
      medically prescribed and supervised intervention almost immediately following confirmation
      of its safety and efficacy. Six-minute walk distance is associated with improved HRQoL in
      patients with ILD and in specific subsets. Effective use of AET as a rehabilitative
      intervention could have a high degree of impact on these personal and public health outcomes
      in this advanced lung disease subset.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>6MWT distance (most frequently used measured of physical performance for evaluating patients with ILD  and other advanced lung diseases).  MCID for 6MWT distance has been determined to be approximately 30 meters in ILD</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak work rate on the treadmill cardiopulmonary exercise test, and performance and perceived fatigability. We will also examine subject's acceptance onto transplant lists and patient mortality.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Interstitial Lung Disease</condition>
  <condition>Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis</condition>
  <condition>Interstitial Pneumonitis</condition>
  <condition>Desquamative Interstitial Pneumonia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aerobic Exercise Training</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        ILD Groups: Subjects in this study will include individuals with ILD who are referred for
        Pulmonary Rehabilitation.  The following list provides more specific inclusion criteria:

          -  Between age 21-80 years

          -  WHO functional class II or III, will accept WHO functional class I and IV based on 6
             minute walk test results (less than or equal to 400 meters for Class I and greater
             than or equal to50 meters for Class IV)

          -  No episodes of syncope or significant chest pain for at least one month.

          -  No prior Pulmonary Rehabilitation received within the last 6 months and not currently
             in a maintenance program.

          -  Physically inactive, no participation in a structured exercise program as defined as
             more than 30 minutes of exercise 3 or more days a week within the last 6 months.

          -  Patients may qualify if they have any one of the following conditions:

               -  Interstitial lung disease, including idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF),
                  non-specific pulmonary fibrosis (NSIP), sarcoidosis or other form of chronic
                  lung fibrosis based on clinical context via clinic note from primary
                  pulmonologist and an echo prior to enrollment showing an RVSP &lt; 40mmHg and/or
                  estimated mean &lt; 25 mmHg.  &lt; TAB&gt;

                    -  If RVSP is unable to be estimated on the echo at NIH, the absence of the
                       following abnormalities on echo will be used to rule out pulmonary
                       hypertension:  right ventricular enlargement, right ventricular
                       hypertrophy, paradoxical movement of interventricular septum and/or altered
                       pulmonary flow velocity.  If RVSP is unable to be estimated and these
                       abnormalities are absent on echo, the patient will be enrolled.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Since the goal is to examine exercise responses and adaptations as affected by ILD,
        patients will have no other medical conditions that would impair aerobic capacity or the
        ability to engage in physical activity.  These conditions would include any of those
        affecting the cardiovascular, pulmonary, metabolic, neurological, or musculoskeletal
        systems.  Specific exclusion criteria are:

        Inability to maintain a resting oxygen saturation greater than or equal to 90% SpO2,
        measured by pulse oximetry, on supplemental oxygen

          -  Inability to complete a treadmill cardiopulmonary exercise test based on the
             specified criteria.

          -  Diagnosis of ischemic heart disease

          -  Left ventricular dysfunction with the ejection fraction &lt; 50%

          -  Acute cor pulmonale

          -  Dilated or hypertrophic cardiomyopathy

          -  Non-idiopathic cardiomyopathy

          -  Significant hepatic or renal dysfunction

          -  Metastatic cancer with a life expectancy of less than one year.

          -  Disabling stroke

          -  Active substance abuse

             -Severe psychiatric disease

          -  Patients on antiretroviral therapy

          -  Uncontrolled diabetes mellitus with a history of DKA

          -  Mitochondrial disease

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Ongoing tobacco use

          -  Acceptance onto a lung transplant waiting list

          -  No participation in ongoing ILD drug trials prior to enrolling in this study and
             throughout the duration of their participation in this study.  Patients may continue
             to take any currently prescribed medications throughout the entire protocol.  However
             any changes to current medications or addition of other medications during the course
             of the study must be reported within one week to the PI or associate investigator.

          -  General medical complications that pose a risk to exercise testing or training as
             determined by the PI (eg.. Severe peripheral vascular disease, Reynaud   s Syndrome,
             etc)

        Other Exclusions:

          -  The age range of the subjects will be limited to those between 21 and 80 years
             because the normal adaptive processes to aerobic exercise are generally less well
             understood in the childhood, adolescent, and aged subset of the population, and
             reference ranges for many of the exercise response variables are less well accepted
             than in the general adult subset.

          -  Subjects will not typically include individuals in Class I because patients are
             usually in Class II or III at the time of diagnosis.

          -  Subjects in NYHA Class IV will typically be excluded as the instability of their
             symptoms is a contraindication for exercise testing or training by nearly all
             published guidelines.

          -  Subjects in Class I may be included if they are able to walk less than 400 meters.

          -  Subjects in Class IV may be included if they are able to walk at least 50 meters.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leighton Chan, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Anne B Quinn, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 443-9083</phone>
    <email>quinna@cc.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Leighton Chan, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-4733</phone>
    <email>chanle@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2014-CC-0027.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>American Thoracic Society; European Respiratory Society. American Thoracic Society/European Respiratory Society International Multidisciplinary Consensus Classification of the Idiopathic Interstitial Pneumonias. This joint statement of the American Thoracic Society (ATS), and the European Respiratory Society (ERS) was adopted by the ATS board of directors, June 2001 and by the ERS Executive Committee, June 2001. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2002 Jan 15;165(2):277-304. Review. Erratum in: Am J Respir Crit Care Med2002 Aug 1;166(3):426.</citation>
    <PMID>11790668</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>du Bois RM, Weycker D, Albera C, Bradford WZ, Costabel U, Kartashov A, Lancaster L, Noble PW, Sahn SA, Szwarcberg J, Thomeer M, Valeyre D, King TE Jr. Six-minute-walk test in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: test validation and minimal clinically important difference. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2011 May 1;183(9):1231-7. doi: 10.1164/rccm.201007-1179OC. Epub 2010 Dec 3.</citation>
    <PMID>21131468</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jones AM, Carter H. The effect of endurance training on parameters of aerobic fitness. Sports Med. 2000 Jun;29(6):373-86. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10870864</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 20, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Interstitial Lung Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary Rehabilitation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases, Interstitial</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
