<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="124401">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01902173</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2013-01320</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-01320</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>SWOG-S1221</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>S1221</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>S1221</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U10CA032102</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01902173</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>GSK2141795 and Dabrafenib in Treating Patients With Stage IIIC-IV Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I/II Study of the Safety and Efficacy of the AKT Inhibitor GSK2141795 in Combination With the BRAF Inhibitor Dabrafenib in Patients With BRAF Mutant Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I/II trial studies the side effects and the best dose of Akt inhibitor GSK2141795
      (GSK2141795) when given together with dabrafenib and to see how well they work in treating
      patients with stage IIIC-IV cancer. Akt inhibitor GSK2141795 and dabrafenib may stop the
      growth of tumor cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell growth. Giving Akt
      inhibitor GSK2141795 with dabrafenib may be an effective treatment for cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess the safety of dabrafenib in combination with GSK2141795 and select the optimal
      dose of GSK2141795 for the phase II portion in patients with v-raf murine sarcoma viral
      oncogene homolog B1 (BRAF) mutant cancer. (Phase I) II. To evaluate the objective response
      rate (confirmed and unconfirmed, complete and partial responses) in patients with BRAF^V600
      mutant metastatic melanoma who have previously progressed on BRAF^V600 inhibitor-based
      therapy. (Phase II)

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To estimate overall survival and progression-free survival. II. To assess the toxicity
      profile of the recommended phase II dose.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To explore the molecular mechanisms of acquired resistance to BRAF inhibitor therapy
      using available biopsies of lesions that progressed during prior BRAF inhibitor-based
      therapy.

      II. To explore potential drug-drug interactions between dabrafenib and GSK2141795 leading to
      changes in the expected exposure with either agent compared to prior experience. (Phase I)

      OUTLINE: This is a phase I, dose-escalation study of Akt inhibitor GSK2141795 followed by a
      phase II study.

      Patients receive dabrafenib orally (PO) twice daily (BID) and Akt inhibitor GSK2141795 PO
      once daily (QD) on days 1-28. Courses repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease
      progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 3 months for 1 year and
      then every 6 months for 2 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Temporarily stopped for assessment
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum-tolerated dose (MTD) of Akt inhibitor GSK2141795 , determined according to incidence of dose-limiting toxicity (DLT), graded using the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0 (Phase I)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (confirmed and unconfirmed, complete and partial responses) as assessed by RECIST version 1.1 (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of registration to date of death due to any cause, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated with 95% confidence interval.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival as assessed by RECIST version 1.1 (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of registration to date of first documentation of progression or symptomatic deterioration, or death due to any cause, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated with 95% confidence interval.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity rate graded by the NCI CTCAE version 4.0 (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">66</enrollment>
  <condition>Recurrent Colon Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Ovarian Epithelial Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Ovarian Germ Cell Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Colon Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Ovarian Epithelial Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Ovarian Germ Cell Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Unspecified Adult Solid Tumor, Protocol Specific</condition>
  <condition>Unspecified Childhood Solid Tumor, Protocol Specific</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (Akt inhibitor GSK2141795, dabrafenib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive dabrafenib PO BID and Akt inhibitor GSK2141795 PO QD on days 1-28. Courses repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Akt inhibitor GSK2141795</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (Akt inhibitor GSK2141795, dabrafenib)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>GSK2141795</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>dabrafenib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (Akt inhibitor GSK2141795, dabrafenib)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BRAF inhibitor GSK2118436</other_name>
    <other_name>GSK-2118436A</other_name>
    <other_name>GSK2118436</other_name>
    <other_name>Tafinlar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (Akt inhibitor GSK2141795, dabrafenib)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (Akt inhibitor GSK2141795, dabrafenib)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pharmacological studies</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  PHASE I PORTION ELIGIBILITY CRITERIA

          -  Patients must have BRAF^V600 mutant metastatic cancer irrespective of the histology
             or prior therapy; BRAF^V600 mutant status must be documented by a Clinical Laboratory
             Improvement Amendments (CLIA)-certified laboratory; use of an Food and Drug
             Administration (FDA)-approved test is preferred although other BRAF tests at a
             CLIA-certified laboratory may also be accepted

          -  Patients must have locally advanced unresectable stage IIIC or metastatic stage IV
             cancer with either progression to prior therapy or a newly diagnosed cancer that does
             not have an available treatment with curative intent

          -  Patients must have measurable or non-measurable disease; all measurable lesions must
             be assessed (by physical examination, computed tomography [CT], or magnetic resonance
             imaging [MRI] scan) within 28 days prior to registration; tests to assess
             non-measurable disease must be performed within 42 days prior to registration; all
             disease must be assessed and documented on the baseline tumor assessment form
             (Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors [RECIST] 1.1)

          -  All patients must undergo a CT or MRI of the brain within 42 days prior to
             registration; patients with asymptomatic brain metastases or previously treated brain
             metastases that are stable (i.e. not requiring corticosteroids) at the time of
             registration will be eligible

          -  Patients may have received prior systemic therapy (chemotherapy, immunotherapy,
             biologic therapy, or combination regimens); all adverse events associated with prior
             treatment must have resolved to =&lt; grade 1 prior to registration

          -  Patients progressing on a prior BRAF inhibitor-based therapy will be eligible, as are
             patients naïve to BRAF inhibitor therapy; resistance to BRAF inhibitor-based therapy
             will be defined as progressive disease by RECIST 1.1 criteria while receiving therapy
             with a BRAF inhibitor (vemurafenib or dabrafenib, alone or in combination with a
             mitogen-activated protein kinase [MEK] inhibitor); this may be innate resistance
             (patients who never achieved a tumor response while on BRAF inhibitor therapy) or
             acquired resistance (progression after having a tumor response to BRAF inhibitor
             therapy); there will not be a period of break between progression on the prior BRAF
             inhibitor-based therapy and the start of dabrafenib and GSK2141795

          -  Patients may have received prior surgery (for both the primary and stage IV disease);
             all adverse events associated with prior surgery must have resolved to =&lt; grade 1
             prior to registration

          -  Patients may have received prior radiation therapy; all adverse events associated
             with prior radiation therapy must have resolved to =&lt; grade 1 prior to registration

          -  Patients must be willing to submit blood for pharmacokinetics; sites must order S1221
             pharmacokinetic (PK) kit immediately after registration; the Southwest Oncology Group
             (SWOG) patient identification (ID) number must be provided on the S1221 PK Kit
             request form

          -  Patients must have available and be willing to submit baseline tissue taken at the
             time of disease progression to prior BRAF inhibitor-based therapy (either fresh
             frozen [preferred], or paraffin-embedded tumor blocks) OR must have a site of disease
             that can be biopsied within this study for translational medicine studies; tissue may
             be from an archival biopsy or a new biopsy after the patient has been registered to
             the protocol; since patients are referred to this protocol after progression on prior
             BRAF inhibitor-based therapy, the biopsy taken at the time of progression will be
             used as the baseline biopsy for this study; patients must be willing to submit plasma
             and whole blood for translational medicine studies

          -  Patients must have Zubrod performance status =&lt; 1

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1,500/ul

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100,000/ul

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 9 g/dL

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x institutional upper limit of normal (IULN)

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) =&lt; 2.5 x IULN (or
             &lt; 5 x IULN for patients with known liver metastases)

          -  Serum creatinine =&lt; IULN OR measured or calculated creatinine clearance &gt;= 60 mL/min

               -  Estimated creatinine clearance = (140 - age) x wt (kg) x 0.85 (if female)/72 x
                  creatinine (mg/dl)

          -  Patient must have a left ventricular ejection fraction &gt;= institutional lower limit
             of normal (LLN) by echocardiogram (ECHO) within 28 days prior to registration

          -  Patients must not have a corrected QT (corrected QT [QTc]) interval &gt;= 480 msecs
             within 28 days prior to registration

          -  Patients must not have a history of acute coronary syndromes (including unstable
             angina), coronary angioplasty, or stenting within the past 24 weeks; class II, III,
             or IV heart failure as defined by the New York Heart Association (NYHA) functional
             classification system; or history of known cardiac arrhythmias unless it has been
             stably controlled

          -  Patients with melanoma must have a serum lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) test performed
             within 28 days prior to registration

          -  Patients with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) are eligible if they are not on
             antiviral agents and have adequate cluster of differentiation (CD)4 counts (&gt;= 500
             mm^3)

          -  Patients requiring therapeutic anticoagulation must have approval from physician to
             use therapeutic level dosing of warfarin and they must have close monitoring of
             prothrombin time (PT)/international normalized ratio (INR) by the site

          -  At the time of registration, patients must not be receiving any medications or
             substances that are strong inhibitors or inducers of cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A) or
             cytochrome P4502C8 (CYP2C8); patients must not be planning to use herbal remedies
             (e.g., St. John's wort), or strong inhibitors or inducers of P-glycoprotein (Pgp) or
             breast cancer resistance protein 1 (Bcrp1)

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test within 14 days of
             registration

          -  Patients must not be pregnant or nursing; women/men of reproductive potential must
             have agreed to use an effective contraceptive method; a woman is considered to be of
             &quot;reproductive potential&quot; if she has had menses at any time in the preceding 12
             consecutive months; in addition to routine contraceptive methods, &quot;effective
             contraception&quot; also includes heterosexual celibacy and surgery intended to prevent
             pregnancy (or with a side-effect of pregnancy prevention) defined as a hysterectomy,
             bilateral oophorectomy or bilateral tubal ligation; however, if at any point a
             previously celibate patient chooses to become heterosexually active during the time
             period for use of contraceptive measures outlined in the protocol, he/she is
             responsible for beginning contraceptive measures

          -  Patient must not have uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited
             to, ongoing or active infection, previously diagnosed type 1 diabetes mellitus/type 2
             diabetes, psychiatric illness/social situations, hypertension, symptomatic congestive
             heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, that would limit
             compliance with study requirements; patients must not have any evidence of mucosal or
             internal bleeding; patients must not have received any major surgery within four
             weeks prior to registration

          -  Patients must not have an active hepatitis B virus (HBV) or hepatitis C virus (HCV)
             infection

          -  Patients must not have a history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of
             similar chemical or biologic composition to dabrafenib or other agents used in this
             study

          -  Patients must be able to swallow capsules

          -  Patients or their legally authorized representative must be informed of the
             investigational nature of this study and must sign and give written informed consent
             in accordance with institutional and federal guidelines

          -  As a part of the Oncology Patient Enrollment Network (OPEN) registration process the
             treating institution's identity is provided in order to ensure that the current
             (within 365 days) date of institutional review board approval for this study has been
             entered in the system

          -  PHASE II PORTION ELIGIBILITY CRITERIA

          -  Patients must have histologically confirmed melanoma with BRAF^V600 mutation;
             patients must have stage IIIC or stage IV disease

          -  Patients must have progressed on single agent BRAF inhibitor (vemurafenib or
             dabrafenib) or BRAF inhibitor plus MEK inhibitor therapy (dabrafenib and trametinib,
             or vemurafenib and GDC0973, or vemurafenib and trametinib); there will not be a
             period of break between progression on the prior BRAF inhibitor-based therapy and the
             start of dabrafenib and GSK2141795

          -  Patients must have measurable disease; all measurable lesions must be assessed (by
             physical examination, CT, or MRI scan) within 28 days prior to registration; tests to
             assess non-measurable disease must be performed within 42 days prior to registration;
             patients whose only measurable disease is within a previous radiation therapy port
             must demonstrate clearly progressive disease (in the opinion of the treating
             investigator) prior to registration; all disease must be assessed and documented on
             the baseline tumor assessment form (RECIST 1.1)

          -  Patients must have Zubrod performance status =&lt; 2

          -  No other prior malignancy is allowed except for the following: adequately treated
             basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer, in situ cervical cancer, adequately treated
             stage I or II cancer from which the patient is currently in complete remission, or
             any other cancer from which the patient has been disease free for five years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Antoni Ribas</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Southwest Oncology Group</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California at Los Angeles (UCLA )</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Southern California/Norris Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Cancer Center - Anschutz Cancer Pavilion</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic Foundation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clackamas Radiation Oncology Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Clackamas</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97015</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Providence Milwaukie Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukie</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97222</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Providence Newberg Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newberg</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97132</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Providence Willamette Falls Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oregon City</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Providence Saint Vincent Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97225</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Western Oncology Research Consortium</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Providence Portland Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>PeaceHealth Southwest Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98664</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 9, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 15, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Colonic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Germ Cell and Embryonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Germinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Glandular and Epithelial</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
