<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="134522">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01952379</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>mel-L1a</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01952379</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of the Inflammatory Infiltrate and the Expression of IL1a in Melasma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Study of the Inflammatory Cellular Infiltrate and the Expression of Interleukin 1 Alpha in Melasma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidad Autonoma de San Luis Potosí</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital Central &quot;Dr. Ignacio Morones Prieto&quot;</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidad Autonoma de San Luis Potosí</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Mexico: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Melasma is a pigmentary disorder that affects approximately 10% of latin-american women
      being one of the ten most common causes of dermatologic consultation in Mexico.

      Although there are clinical evidence of inflammation by non invasive methods(diffuse
      spectroscopy, TEWL) and histopathology (mast cells),the inflammatory infiltrate and its
      mediators in melasma lesions are not well characterized. It is known that inflammation
      induces melanogenesis. Therefore, it is important to analyze the inflammatory
      characteristics of this pigmentary disorder since it could be linked to its recurrent
      nature. The objective is to evaluate the characteristics of the inflammatory cellular
      infiltrate and the expression of IL1 alpha in melasma compared to unaffected skin.

      At least 30 women with melasma, phototype III-V, aged 18-50 years will be included.
      Volunteers will be evaluated by means of histological, histochemical, immunohistochemistry
      analysis, immunoassay, quantitative real-time PCR, as well as colorimetry, clinically (MASI
      scale) and by photography control.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Melasma is a frequent pigmentary disorder among latin-american women. Its etiology is not
      completely elucidated; however, there is evidence of a melanogenic paracrine cytokine
      network between the melanocyte and other skin cells, including keratinocytes, fibroblasts,
      vascular and inflammatory cells, which regulate melanocyte function.

      Previous reports in melasma skin have described increased mast cell infiltration in
      elastotic areas, presence of a moderate lymphohistiocytic infiltrate, increased vascularity
      and up-regulation of proangiogenic factors. This histological evidence of skin inflammation
      is also supported clinically by colorimetry and thermography, and by the improvement of
      pigmentation with topical anti-inflammatories.

      The exact role that  inflammatory cells plays in melasma, particularly mast cells, is
      unknown. It has also poor elucidated the activation mechanisms of this inflammatory cascade
      and its chronic nature. Previous studies suggest that interleukin 1 alpha might play a key
      role. This proinflammatory cytokine, released by damaged UVB-exposed keratinocytes
      stimulates autocrine secretion of  multiple melanogenic cytokines which in turn leads to the
      activation of inflammatory skin cells, perpetuating the inflammatory micro-environment,
      responsible of fibroblasts premature senescence, solar elastosis and pigmentation.

      The objective of our study is to evaluate the characteristics of the inflammatory cellular
      infiltrate and the expression of IL1 alpha and its receptor  in melasma through
      histochemistry, immunohistochemistry, immunoassay, and quantitative real-time PCR.

      The study population will include 30 women with melasma, phototype III-V, aged 18-50 years.
      Informed consent will be obtained from the patients, under approval by the local ethical
      committee. Volunteers will be evaluated through skin biopsies, colorimetry, clinical
      assessment(MASI scale)and photographic control.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case-Crossover, Time Perspective: Cross-Sectional</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>IL-alpha</measure>
    <time_frame>Single time measurement</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Determine the expression of Il-alpha in melasma lesions and non affected skin.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>IL-alpha receptor</measure>
    <time_frame>Single time measurement</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Determine the expression of Il-alpha receptor in melasma lesions and non affected skin.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Inflammatory cellular infiltrate</measure>
    <time_frame>Single time measurement</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Determine by immunohistochemistry common inflammatory cellular infiltrate in melasma lesions and non affected skin (i.e CD1, CD68, CD4, CD8).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between inflammation markers and pigmentation</measure>
    <time_frame>Single time measurement</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Analyze inflammation parameters and to correlate data with melanin and clinical parameters of severity.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Melasma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Melasma</arm_group_label>
    <description>Women affected by symmetric facial melasma</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      3 mm Skin punch biopsies
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Women affected melasma.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women older than 18 years under signed informed consent form.

          -  Symmetrical and bilateral lesions.

          -  Melasma with MASI scores greater than 7 points.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Melasma treatment within last 2 months.

          -  Regular use of sunscreen.

          -  Pregnant women or nursing.

          -  Miscarriage or labor in the last 6 months.

          -  Hormonal replacement treatment.

          -  Coexistence of other pigmentation disorders.

          -  Infrared radiation exposure.

          -  Personal history of keloid or hypertrophic scars.

          -  Lidocaine allergy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Juan P Castanedo-Cazares, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Central &quot;Dr. Ignacio Morones Prieto&quot;</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bertha Torres-Alvarez, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Central &quot;Dr. Ignacio Morones Prieto&quot;</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Adriana Rodriguez-Arambula, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Central &quot;Dr. Ignacio Morones Prieto&quot;</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Central Dr. Ignacio Morones Prieto</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Luis Potosi</city>
        <zip>78210</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mexico</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Navarrete-Solís J, Castanedo-Cázares JP, Torres-Álvarez B, Oros-Ovalle C, Fuentes-Ahumada C, González FJ, Martínez-Ramírez JD, Moncada B. A Double-Blind, Randomized Clinical Trial of Niacinamide 4% versus Hydroquinone 4% in the Treatment of Melasma. Dermatol Res Pract. 2011;2011:379173. doi: 10.1155/2011/379173. Epub 2011 Jul 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21822427</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Torres-Álvarez B, Mesa-Garza IG, Castanedo-Cázares JP, Fuentes-Ahumada C, Oros-Ovalle C, Navarrete-Solis J, Moncada B. Histochemical and immunohistochemical study in melasma: evidence of damage in the basal membrane. Am J Dermatopathol. 2011 May;33(3):291-5. doi: 10.1097/DAD.0b013e3181ef2d45.</citation>
    <PMID>21317614</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moncada B, Sahagún-Sánchez LK, Torres-Alvarez B, Castanedo-Cázares JP, Martínez-Ramírez JD, González FJ. Molecular structure and concentration of melanin in the stratum corneum of patients with melasma. Photodermatol Photoimmunol Photomed. 2009 Jun;25(3):159-60.</citation>
    <PMID>19438997</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hernández-Barrera R, Torres-Alvarez B, Castanedo-Cazares JP, Oros-Ovalle C, Moncada B. Solar elastosis and presence of mast cells as key features in the pathogenesis of melasma. Clin Exp Dermatol. 2008 May;33(3):305-8.</citation>
    <PMID>18419607</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Espinal-Perez LE, Moncada B, Castanedo-Cazares JP. A double-blind randomized trial of 5% ascorbic acid vs. 4% hydroquinone in melasma. Int J Dermatol. 2004 Aug;43(8):604-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15304189</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 5, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 24, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidad Autonoma de San Luis Potosí</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Juan Pablo Castanedo-Cazares</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dermatology department research director</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Melasma</keyword>
  <keyword>Interleukin 1-alpha</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphocytes</keyword>
  <keyword>Langerhans cells</keyword>
  <keyword>Macrophages</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melanosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
