<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="25037">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01878214</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201110075</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R21CA161169</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01878214</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Promoting Smoking Cessation in Carpenters</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effective Communication Strategies for Promoting Smoking Cessation in Carpenters</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to test an innovative and sustainable intervention to increase
      participation in a union-sponsored smoking cessation program among carpenters and floor
      layers. The investigators will conduct a randomized controlled trial comparing targeted
      messaging versus standard messaging. All subjects will receive information about the free,
      union-sponsored smoking cessation program. Subjects randomized to the intervention group
      will receive additional targeted materials to encourage enrollment in the union's smoking
      cessation program. The intervention will include monthly mailed and text messages. The
      investigators hypothesize that subjects who receive targeted messages will be more likely to
      enroll in the union-sponsored smoking cessation program, be more likely to show change in
      readiness to quit smoking, and be more likely to quit smoking compared to subjects who
      receive only standard messaging.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Specific Aim 1: Develop targeted health messages based on audience segmentation to encourage
      smokers to enroll in a comprehensive union-sponsored smoking cessation program.

      We will craft six specific health messages that appeal to four different audience segments:
      workers under 30 years old without children, workers under 30 with children, workers 30
      years old or older without children, and workers 30 or older with children.

      Specific Aim 2: Conduct a randomized controlled trial of targeted messaging based on
      audience segmentation versus standard smoking cessation messaging.

      After conducting baseline surveys with union carpenters and floor layers, we will randomize
      current smokers (smoked within the last 30 days) into either the intervention or control
      group.

        -  Control subjects will receive one standard mailing informing them about the free
           smoking cessation program available to union members.

        -  Intervention subjects will receive the standard mailing in addition to six targeted
           smoking cessation messages delivered monthly by mail to their homes. Messages will be
           specific to one of four audience segments determined by age and parental status. In
           addition to a segment-specific anti-smoking message, each mailing will have contact
           information for the union smoking cessation program. Intervention subjects who
           consented to text messaging will also receive one booster text message each month with
           a shortened targeted message.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Enrollment in smoking cessation program</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months after recruitment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Enrollment records from the union-sponsored smoking cessation program</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in readiness to quit smoking</measure>
    <time_frame>7 months after recruitment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subjects will answer several questions about readiness to quit (see below). We will compare answers between baseline and 7-month follow-up.
How motivated are you to quit smoking at this time? (1-10 scale)
Each rung on this ladder represents where various smokers are in their thinking about quitting. Circle the number that indicates where you are now. (0-10 scale)
Are you seriously considering quitting smoking in the next 6 months? (yes/no)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in smoking behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>7 months after recruitment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in quantity and/or frequency of smoking</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">442</enrollment>
  <condition>Smoking Cessation</condition>
  <condition>Health Behavior</condition>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Targeted messaging</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard messaging</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Targeted messaging</intervention_name>
    <description>1 informational letter plus 6 targeted mailed messages and 6 booster text messages</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard messaging</intervention_name>
    <description>1 informational letter</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Current smoker (smoked cigarettes within the last 30 days)

          -  Eligible for union health benefits

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bradley Evanoff, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barbeau EM, Krieger N, Soobader MJ. Working class matters: socioeconomic disadvantage, race/ethnicity, gender, and smoking in NHIS 2000. Am J Public Health. 2004 Feb;94(2):269-78. Erratum in: Am J Public Health. 2004 Aug;94(8):1295.</citation>
    <PMID>14759942</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barbeau EM, Li Y, Calderon P, Hartman C, Quinn M, Markkanen P, Roelofs C, Frazier L, Levenstein C. Results of a union-based smoking cessation intervention for apprentice iron workers (United States). Cancer Causes Control. 2006 Feb;17(1):53-61.</citation>
    <PMID>16411053</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bock B, Graham A, Sciamanna C, Krishnamoorthy J, Whiteley J, Carmona-Barros R, Niaura R, Abrams D. Smoking cessation treatment on the Internet: content, quality, and usability. Nicotine Tob Res. 2004 Apr;6(2):207-19.</citation>
    <PMID>15203794</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DiClemente CC, Prochaska JO, Fairhurst SK, Velicer WF, Velasquez MM, Rossi JS. The process of smoking cessation: an analysis of precontemplation, contemplation, and preparation stages of change. J Consult Clin Psychol. 1991 Apr;59(2):295-304.</citation>
    <PMID>2030191</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fagerstrom KO, Schneider NG. Measuring nicotine dependence: a review of the Fagerstrom Tolerance Questionnaire. J Behav Med. 1989 Apr;12(2):159-82. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2668531</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fjeldsoe BS, Marshall AL, Miller YD. Behavior change interventions delivered by mobile telephone short-message service. Am J Prev Med. 2009 Feb;36(2):165-73. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19135907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ham DC, Przybeck T, Strickland JR, Luke DA, Bierut LJ, Evanoff BA. Occupation and workplace policies predict smoking behaviors: analysis of national data from the current population survey. J Occup Environ Med. 2011 Nov;53(11):1337-45. doi: 10.1097/JOM.0b013e3182337778.</citation>
    <PMID>21988795</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kreuter MW, Wray RJ. Tailored and targeted health communication: strategies for enhancing information relevance. Am J Health Behav. 2003 Nov-Dec;27 Suppl 3:S227-32. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14672383</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee DJ, Fleming LE, Arheart KL, LeBlanc WG, Caban AJ, Chung-Bridges K, Christ SL, McCollister KE, Pitman T. Smoking rate trends in U.S. occupational groups: the 1987 to 2004 National Health Interview Survey. J Occup Environ Med. 2007 Jan;49(1):75-81.</citation>
    <PMID>17215716</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maibach EW, Maxfield A, Ladin K, Slater M. Translating health psychology into effective health communication: the american healthstyles audience segmentation project. J Health Psychol. 1996 Jul;1(3):261-77. doi: 10.1177/135910539600100302.</citation>
    <PMID>22011991</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nigg CR, Burbank PM, Padula C, Dufresne R, Rossi JS, Velicer WF, Laforge RG, Prochaska JO. Stages of change across ten health risk behaviors for older adults. Gerontologist. 1999 Aug;39(4):473-82.</citation>
    <PMID>10495586</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Okechukwu CA, Krieger N, Sorensen G, Li Y, Barbeau EM. MassBuilt: effectiveness of an apprenticeship site-based smoking cessation intervention for unionized building trades workers. Cancer Causes Control. 2009 Aug;20(6):887-94. doi: 10.1007/s10552-009-9324-0. Epub 2009 Mar 20.</citation>
    <PMID>19301135</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Okechukwu CA, Krieger N, Sorensen G, Li Y, Barbeau EM. Testing hypothesized psychosocial mediators: lessons learned in the MassBUILT study. Health Educ Behav. 2011 Aug;38(4):404-11. doi: 10.1177/1090198110380544. Epub 2011 Apr 7.</citation>
    <PMID>21474634</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perry RJ, Keller PA, Fraser D, Fiore MC. Fax to quit: a model for delivery of tobacco cessation services to Wisconsin residents. WMJ. 2005 May;104(4):37-40, 44.</citation>
    <PMID>16117232</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ringen K, Anderson N, McAfee T, Zbikowski SM, Fales D. Smoking cessation in a blue-collar population: results from an evidence-based pilot program. Am J Ind Med. 2002 Nov;42(5):367-77.</citation>
    <PMID>12382249</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Slater MD. Theory and method in health audience segmentation. J Health Commun. 1996 Jul-Sep;1(3):267-83. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10947364</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith DR. Tobacco smoking by occupation in Australia and the United States: a review of national surveys conducted between 1970 and 2005. Ind Health. 2008 Jan;46(1):77-89.</citation>
    <PMID>18270453</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sorensen G, Emmons K, Hunt MK, Barbeau E, Goldman R, Peterson K, Kuntz K, Stoddard A, Berkman L. Model for incorporating social context in health behavior interventions: applications for cancer prevention for working-class, multiethnic populations. Prev Med. 2003 Sep;37(3):188-97.</citation>
    <PMID>12914824</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sorensen G, Barbeau E, Hunt MK, Emmons K. Reducing social disparities in tobacco use: a social-contextual model for reducing tobacco use among blue-collar workers. Am J Public Health. 2004 Feb;94(2):230-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14759932</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sorensen G, Barbeau EM, Stoddard AM, Hunt MK, Goldman R, Smith A, Brennan AA, Wallace L. Tools for health: the efficacy of a tailored intervention targeted for construction laborers. Cancer Causes Control. 2007 Feb;18(1):51-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17186421</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Velicer WF, DiClemente CC, Prochaska JO, Brandenburg N. Decisional balance measure for assessing and predicting smoking status. J Pers Soc Psychol. 1985 May;48(5):1279-89.</citation>
    <PMID>3998990</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vladutiu CJ, Nansel TR, Weaver NL, Jacobsen HA, Kreuter MW. Differential strength of association of child injury prevention attitudes and beliefs on practices: a case for audience segmentation. Inj Prev. 2006 Feb;12(1):35-40.</citation>
    <PMID>16461418</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 11, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 22, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Health communication</keyword>
  <keyword>Smoking cessation</keyword>
  <keyword>Health behavior</keyword>
  <keyword>Construction industry</keyword>
  <keyword>Audience segmentation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Smoking</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
