<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="154794">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01999491</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013-0466</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2014-00555</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01999491</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase I Study of NC-4016</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1 Dose-Escalation and Pharmacokinetic Study of NC-4016 in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors or Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Nanocarrier Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to find the highest tolerated dose of NC-4016
      that can be given to patients with advanced solid tumors or lymphoma.  The safety of the
      drug will also be studied.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Groups:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will be enrolled in either a
      dose escalation group or the dose expansion group.

      Dose Escalation:

      If you are in a dose escalation group, you will be assigned to a dose level based on when
      you joined this study.  Up to 6 dose levels of NC-4016 will be tested and at least 3
      patients will be enrolled at each dose level. The first group of participants will receive
      the lowest dose level of NC-4016.  Each new group will receive a higher dose of NC-4016 than
      the group before it, if no intolerable side effects were seen.  This will continue until the
      highest tolerable dose of NC-4016 is found.

      Dose Expansion:

      If you are in the dose expansion group, you will receive NC-4016 at the highest dose that
      was tolerated in the escalation groups.

      Study Drug Administration:

      Each study cycle is 21 days.

      On Day 1 of each cycle, you will receive NC-4016 by vein over 2 hours.

      You will be given standard drugs to help decrease the risk of side effects.  You may ask the
      study staff for information about how the drugs are given and their risks.

      If you have a severe side effect, your dose of study drug may be delayed.

      Study Visits:

      On Day 1 of each cycle:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  Your vital signs (blood pressure, heart rate, breathing rate, and temperature) will be
           monitored every 20 minutes during the infusion and 1 hour after the end of the infusion
           during Cycle 1 and right before and at the end of the infusion for all other cycles.

        -  Blood (about 3 teaspoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

        -  You will have a neurological exam and electromyogram.

        -  You will have an EKG before the start of the infusion, at the end of the infusion, and
           1 hour after the end of the infusion (Cycle 1 and 2 only).  After Cycle 1, you will
           only have 1 EKG before dosing.

      On Days 8 and 15 of each cycle, blood (about 3 teaspoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

      On Day 2 of Cycle 1 you will have an EKG corresponding to the 24 hour PK testing.

      Every 3 cycles (every 9 weeks):

        -  You will have an x-ray, CT, MRI, or PET scan to check the status of the disease.

        -  If you have lymphoma, you will have a bone marrow biopsy to check the status of the
           disease.

        -  You will have a nerve conduction evaluation.

        -  If the doctor thinks it is needed, blood (about 1 teaspoon) will be drawn for tumor
           marker testing.

      PK Testing:

      Blood (about 1 teaspoon each time) will be drawn for pharmacokinetic (PK) testing.  PK
      testing measures the amount of study drug in the body at different time points.

        -  On Day 1 of Cycles 1 and 3, blood will be drawn before, then at 0.5, 1, and 2 hours
           during the infusion, and then 9 more times up to 12 hours after you receive the study
           drug (13 draws total each day).

        -  On Days 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, and 15 of Cycles 1 and 3, blood will be drawn 1 time after you
           receive the study drug.

        -  On Day 1 of Cycles 2 and Cycle 4, blood will be drawn 1 time before you receive the
           study drug.

      Urine Collection:

      Urine will be collected for PK testing at the following time points during Cycles 1 and 3:

        -  Before you receive the study drug

        -  0-2 hours (during the infusion)

        -  2-4 hours after you received the study drug

        -  4-8 hours after you received the study drug

        -  8-12 hours after you received the study drug

        -  12-24 hours after you received the study drug

      You will collect your urine at home over 24 hours  during the following times after you
      received the study drug:

        -  Days 1-2

        -  Days 2-3

        -  Days 7-8

        -  Days 14-15

        -  Days 21-22

      Your study doctor will provide you with urine collection bottles.  Your urine samples will
      contain a very small amount of platinum from the study drug.  This is not considered to be a
      risk to you, but as a precaution, the urine collection containers should only be handled by
      you, and the containers will be labeled as a &quot;Bio-Hazard&quot;.

      If you have a severe side effect, you may have extra tests until the side effects have
      gotten better.

      Length of Study:

      You may continue taking the study drug for as long as you are benefitting.  You will be
      taken off study early if the disease gets worse, intolerable side effects occur, you develop
      new health problems, your doctor thinks that it is no longer in your best interest to
      receive the study drug, or if you are unable to follow study directions.

      Your participation on the study will be over after the end-of-dosing visit.

      End-of-Dosing Visit:

      Within 28 days after the last dose of NC-4016:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  You will have a neurological exam and an electromyogram.

        -  You will have a chest x-ray.

        -  You will have an x-ray, CT scan, MRI scan, or PET scan, or a bone marrow biopsy if you
           have lymphoma, to check the status of the disease.

        -  Blood (about 3 teaspoons) and urine will be collected for routine tests.

        -  You will have an EKG and an ECHO or MUGA.

        -  If the doctor thinks it is needed, blood (about 1 teaspoon) will be drawn for tumor
           marker testing.

      Additional Information:

        -  Tell the study staff if you have previously had an allergic reaction to a drug
           containing platinum.

        -  Tell the study staff about any therapy you have been given by another doctor and of any
           type of drugs you are taking (prescription and over the counter).  This is very
           important because the study drug may interact with other drugs you may be taking.

      This is an investigational study.  NC-4016 is not commercially available or FDA approved.
      It is currently being used for research purposes only.  The study doctor can explain how
      NC-4016 is designed to work.

      NC-4016 will be provided during the study at no cost to you.

      Up to 30 participants will be enrolled in this study.  All will be enrolled at  MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD) of NC-4016</measure>
    <time_frame>After 2, 21 day cycles.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary study endpoint will be the determination of MTD, as judged by the occurrence of dose limiting toxicities (DLTs) during the first 2 cycles. The MTD is defined as the highest dose level at which no more than 1 of 6 DLT evaluable patients experience a DLT in the first 2 cycles of dosing.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Cancers</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NC-4016</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose Escalation Group: NC-4016 will be administered as 2-hour intravenous infusion once every 3 weeks.  Initial dose level 15 mg/m2. The dose level of NC-4016 in subsequent cohorts determined by the toxicity profile of the previous cohort, and dose level increased to 25, 30, 40, 60, and 80 mg/m2 or higher at each subsequent cycle until the highest dose level is reached or DLT prohibits further dose-level escalation. Dose level 1 will be the starting dose level (DL). If 2 out of the first 3 patients enrolled at DL1 experience a DLT during Cycle 1 or Cycle 2,then the next cohort of patients will be enrolled at DL0 (10 mg/m2).
Dose Expansion Group:  Maximum tolerated dose from Dose Escalation Group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NC-4016</intervention_name>
    <description>Dose Escalation Group Starting Dose: 15 mg/m2 by vein on Day 1 of a 21 Day cycle.
Dose Expansion Group Starting Dose:  Maximum tolerated dose from Dose Escalation Group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>NC-4016</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Have signed written informed consent prior to the initiation of any study-specific
             procedures

          2. Be a male or female 18 years or older

          3. Have a histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of advanced solid tumor or
             lymphoma

          4. Have advanced or metastatic disease refractory to standard curative or palliative
             therapy or contraindication to standard therapy

          5. Have an ECOG performance status of 0-2

          6. Have adequate bone marrow reserve: a. Absolute neutrophil count at least 1.5 x 109/L,
             b. Platelet count at least 100 x 109/L, and c. Hemoglobin at least 10 g/L
             (transfusion is allowed to achieve hemoglobin of 10 g/L)

          7. Have adequate liver function: a. Total serum bilirubin no more than 1.5 x upper limit
             of normal (ULN), and b. Alanine aminotransferase and aspartate aminotransferase&lt;= 2.5
             x ULN or &lt;= 5.0 x ULN in case of documented hepatic metastasis

          8. Have adequate renal function: glomerular filtration rate &gt;=50 mL/min (calculated
             according to the formula of Cockcroft and Gault)

          9. Be reasonably recovered from preceding major surgery as judged by the investigator or
             no major surgery within 4 weeks prior to the start of Day 1 treatment

         10. Have a negative pregnancy test for females at screening, preferably done within 1
             week before Day 1 of treatment (not applicable to patients with bilateral
             oophorectomy and/or hysterectomy)

         11. Be willing to abstain from heterosexual activity or practice physical barrier
             contraception from study entry to 6 months after the last day of treatment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Have peripheral neuropathy of Grade 3 or Grade 4 at screening, according to National
             Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE)v4.03, 14
             June 2010 scale; or TNSc score greater than 4

          2. Have an interval from previous neurotoxic platinums of less than 6 months and/or from
             previous other neurotoxic drugs less than 3 months (eg, taxanes) unless reasonably
             recovered from all grades of neurotoxicity as judged by the investigator

          3. Have a history of thrombocytopenia with complications including hemorrhage or
             bleeding &gt;= Grade 2 using NCI CTCAE v4.03, 14 June 2010 that required medical
             intervention or any hemolytic condition or coagulation disorders that would make
             participation unsafe in the opinion of the investigator

          4. Have unresolved toxicity from previous treatment or previous investigational agents;
             excluding alopecia

          5. Have known hypersensitivity to Pt compounds

          6. Have received investigational agents or systemic anticancer agents (other than
             neurotoxic compounds) within 14 days of Day 1 of treatment, or 28 days for those
             agents with unknown elimination half-lives, or known elimination half-lives greater
             than 50 hours; or 6 weeks for mitomycin C or for nitrosourea agents

          7. Be pregnant or breast-feeding

          8. Have signs or symptoms of end organ failure, major chronic illnesses other than
             cancer, or any severe concomitant conditions which, in the opinion of the
             investigator, make it undesirable for the patient to participate in the study, or
             which could jeopardize compliance with the protocol

          9. Have a history of angina pectoris, coronary artery disease or cerebrovascular
             accident, transient ischemic attack or cardiac arrhythmia requiring medical therapy

         10. Have known hepatitis B or C, or human immunodeficiency virus infection

         11. Is unwilling or unable to comply with study procedures, or is planning to take a
             vacation for 7 or more consecutive days during the treatment phase of the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vivek Subbiah, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Vivek Subbiah, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-563-0393</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Vivek Subbiah, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-792-4974</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 31, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 26, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Advanced Cancers</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Advanced Solid Tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>NC-4016</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
