<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="33655">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02141919</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU 122013-030</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02141919</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Stereotactic Ablative Body Radiation Therapy for Patients With Primary Renal Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Trial of Stereotactic Ablative Body Radiation Therapy (SABR) for Patients With Primary Renal Cancer (RCC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this phase II trial, the volume of high dose radiotherapy (&gt;10 Gy) will be restricted to
      &lt;50% of the entire kidney.  The current study will also implement fractionated stereotactic
      radiosurgery to treat a unilateral kidney tumor. Fractionated radiotherapy is advocated to
      further reduce the potential toxicity arising from a large single fraction regimen. In fact,
      fractionated radiotherapy has been the standard treatment for many tumors in variety of
      locations to reduce the toxicity associated with radiotherapy. A fractionated stereotactic
      regimen has the potential to reduce the normal tissue toxicity that often accompanies
      radiotherapy.

      Successful implementation of stereotactic radiosurgery of renal tumors may become an
      effective and the least invasive treatment modality. This study will refine the current
      understanding of the image guided conformal therapy to the kidney using stereotactic body
      radiotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Based on the published retrospective and the two prospective phase I trials, the dose
      fractionations evaluated in this trial is 8Gy x5, 10Gy x 4 and 12 Gy x 3.  In a
      retrospective study published paper by Wersäll, et al, from the Karolinska Hospital, 50
      patients with kidney cancer, both primary and metastatic, were retrospectively analyzed
      [50].  High rates of local control were achieved with doses ranging from 25 Gy to 45 Gy.
      The most common doses used were 40 Gy in 5 fractions and 45 Gy in 3 fractions.  Another
      retrospective study used the dose dose of 40Gy in 5 fractions and both studies reported
      excellent control rate [45]. Therefore 8Gy x 5 is evaluated in this study. The 4 and 3
      fraction equivalent doses to this dose levels are 10Gy and 12 Gy respectively, which are the
      two other dose levels included in this trial. Justification of the three fraction dose
      equivalent of 12Gy x 3 comes from the phase I study that did not see any failures at this
      level.

      The study population for this trial is patients with biopsy proven primary RCC that are
      candidates for active surveillance (AS). Keeping patient safety in perspective, it is
      reasonable to offer an experimental treatment such as this to a patient population that
      would have otherwise been put in AS. At any sign of progression, the patients that have
      undergone SABR in this trial will be offered the standard of care (SOC) of radical
      nephrectomy, partial nephrectomy or ablation as deemed appropriate by the treating
      urologist—which is same as what would have been offered to them had they been in AS. The AUA
      defines AS patients to be those with small renal mass (SRM) with &lt;3cm tumors. The NCCN
      recommends AS for patients with T1a tumors or tumors &lt;4 cm. A number of retrospective and
      one prospective study reported on the natural history of SRMs. A meta-analysis reviewed
      multiple retrospective studies and reported an average growth rate of 0.28 cm/year for these
      tumors [51]. They further reported a growth of 0.4 cm/year in the subset of patients that
      had biopsy confirmed RCC. Keeping clinical application in perspective, it is logical to use
      SABR only to tumors that are growing, since one third of the SRMs do not grow. Therefore,
      patients showing growth &gt;4mm in two scans will be enrolled and treated with SABR in this
      trial. The primary endpoint in this trial is local control and the hypothesis tested is that
      SABR to the SRMs will lead to an elimination of tumor growth. The local control will be
      defined using MRI or contrast CT and &lt;4mm increase in single scan or &lt;2.0mm increase in two
      different scans in the setting of an absence of radiographic  indication of tumor viability
      will constitute local control [56]. Kidney function will be monitored closely to evaluate
      radiation induced kidney toxicity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Eliminate its growth and viable tumor.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate if SABR to SRMs is able to eliminate its growth and viable tumor.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To describe the adverse events associated with the administration of SABR to SRMs</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>growth rate of SRMs</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To measure the growth rate of SRMs after SABR treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Renal function</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To measure the changes in kidney function, creatinine levels, renal perfusion and GFR after SABR treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>tumor viability</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To measure tumor viability pathologically one year after SABR treatment for patients that consents to the optional biopsy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess radiographic changes of the SRM after SABR treatment, including tumor viability, %enhancement, necrosis, T2 signal, tumor cellularity with diffusion-weighted imaging</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>progression of disease</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess local, regional and systemic progression of disease after SABR to SRM</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>time to progression</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess time to progression (TTP) of disease from the first SABR treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>progression free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess progression free survival (PFS). PFS is defined as the length of time from start of treatment to the time of loco-regional disease progression or death from any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess overall survival (OS). OS is defined as the duration of time from start of treatment to the time of death from any cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease response</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess tumor growth, local failure and indeterminate disease response</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>cytokine changes</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the cytokine changes brought on by SABR to SRM and to evaluate generation of any immune response specific to tumor cells.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>radiographic spatial-temporal tumor features</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate whether radiographic spatial-temporal tumor features extracted from CT and MRI can be used to predict treatment response of tumor to SABR.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Renal Cancers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stereotactic Ablative Radiation Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Stereotactic Ablative Radiation Therapy (SABR)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stereotactic Ablative Radiation Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Stereotactic Ablative Body Radiation Therapy (SABR): 3 fractions of 12Gy, or 4 fractions of 10Gy or 5 fractions of 8 Gy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stereotactic Ablative Radiation Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SABR</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteri

          1. Age ≥ 18 years.

          2. Renal mass ≤ 3cm

          3. Biopsy proven Renal neoplasm 3.1 All histology of renal cancers are included
             including oncocytoma

          4. Growth of renal mass &gt;4mm in radiographic scans or &gt;2mm in two different scans must
             be demonstrated within a one year period.

          5. Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent.

          6. No clinical evidence of metastatic disease

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects may not have received any treatment for the renal mass before such as RFA or
             cyroablation.

          2. Subjects must not have received previous abdominal radiation

          3. Subjects must be able to undergo either an MRI or administration of contrast agent
             for CT.

             3.1 Subjects unable to undergo either of the imaging study will be excluded. 3.2
             Subjects enrolled on the study and then became unable to undergo either of the
             imaging study will be either replaced or decided on an individual basis by the
             investigator (please see section 5.5)

          4. Subjects must not be pregnant during the course of SABR.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Raquibul Hannan, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UTSW</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Raquibul Hannan, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>214-645-8525</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jean Wu, MSN</last_name>
    <phone>214-645-8525</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas Southwestern</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Raquibul Hannan, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 15, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 12, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>renal cancer</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
