<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="131158">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01946477</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CC-4047-MM-014</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01946477</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pomalidomide in Combination With Low Dose Dexamethasone in Subjects With Relapsed and Refractory Multiple Myeloma Following Lenalidomide Plus Low Dose Dexamethasone as Second Line Treatment.</brief_title>
  <acronym>POM MM 014</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase 2, Multicenter, Single-Arm, Open-Label Study of Pomalidomide in Combination With Low-Dose Dexamethasone in Subjects With Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma Following Lenalidomide-Based Therapy in the Second-Line Setting</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Celgene Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Celgene Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This trial will evaluate the efficacy and safety of combination 3rd line treatment of
      Pomalidomide (POM) and  low-doseDexamethasone (LD-Dex) in subjects with relapsed or
      refractory multiple myeloma who have received a second line treatment of lenalidomide plus
      dexamethasone.

      This trial will test the hypothesis that the proportion  of patients will have an Overall
      Response Rate (ORR) of &gt; 30 %  to reveal that Pomalidomide is efficacious in pre-treated
      patients who are refractory to lenalidomide.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center, single-arm, open-label, phase 2 trial designed to further evaluate
      the efficacy and safety of combination Pomalidomide and Low Dose-Dexamethasone in subjects
      with relapsed  or refractory multiple myeloma who have become refractory to a second line
      treatment of lenalidomide.

      This trial will assess, Overall Response Rate (ORR), Overall Survival (OS), Progression-Free
      Survival (PFS), Duration of Response (DoR), Time to Response (TTR), Time to Progression(TTP)
      and safety.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary endpoint will be the Overall Response Rate (ORR) by modified International Myeloma Working Group (mIMWG) criteria and will be based on the best response prior to the time frame. ORR will consist of the responses of PR or better (Complete Response -CR, Very Good Partial Response-VGPR or Partial Response- PR).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall survival will be calculated as the time from start of treatment until the time of death from any cause. If no death is recorded the subject will be censored at the time the subject was last known to be alive.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Progression-free survival will be calculated as the time from start of treatment until the time of PD (as determined by the site Investigator based on the mIMWG criteria) or death from any cause on study treatment, whichever comes first. Subjects not experiencing a documented progression will be censored at the time of their last response assessment (or at the time of trial enrollment if no assessment was conducted).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Response (DoR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Duration of response, calculated for responders only, is defined as time from the initial documented response (PR or better) to the first confirmed PD or until death from any cause. Subjects without a documented progression will be censored at the time of their last response assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Response (TTR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Time to response, calculated for responders only, is calculated as the time from the start of treatment to the first documented response (PR or better) based on modified International Working Group ( mIMWG) criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to progression (TTP)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after 100% enrollment and 5 years from Last Patient First Visit</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Time to progression will be calculated as the time from start of treatment until PD (as determined by the site Investigator based on the mIMWG criteria) or death from progressive disease. Subjects not experiencing a documented progression will be censored at the time of their last response assessment (or at the time of trial enrollment if no assessment was conducted).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of participants with adverse events including secondary primary malignancies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">85</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pomalidomide + dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each subject enrolled in the study will take oral pomalidomide (4 mg) once daily on Days 1-21 and dexamethasone 40 mg/day (&lt; 75 years old) or 20 mg/day (&gt;75 years old) on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pomalidomide</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Pomalidomide + dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CC-4047</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Pomalidomide + dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>dex</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Adults ( age ≥ 18 years at the time of signing the informed consent document) with
             documented diagnosis of multiple myeloma and measurable disease (serum M-protein ≥
             0.5 dL or urine M-protein ≥ 200 mg/24 hours).

             2. Subjects must have received 2 prior treatment lines of anti-myeloma therapy. 3.
             All subjects must have received prior treatment with LEN or a LEN-containing regimen
             for at least 2 consecutive cycles as the second-line treatment regimen.

             4. All subjects must have documented disease progression during or after their last
             anti-myeloma therapy.

             5. Subjects must have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status
             score of 0, 1, or 2.

             6. Subjects must understand and voluntarily sign an informed consent prior to any
             study related assessments/procedures being conducted.

             7. Subjects must be able to adhere to the study visit schedule and other protocol
             requirements.

             8. All subjects must provide an adequate bone marrow sample at screening that
             definitively evaluates the presence or absence of myelodysplastic changes.

             9. Females with child-bearing  potential (FCBP† ) must agree to use 2 reliable forms
             of contraception simultaneously or practice complete abstinence from heterosexual
             contact for at least 28 days before starting study drug, while participating in the
             study (including during dose interruptions), and for at least 28 days after study
             treatment discontinuation and must agree to regular pregnancy testing during this
             timeframe.

             10. Females must agree to abstain from breastfeeding during study participation and
             28 days after study drug discontinuation.

             11. Males must agree to use a latex condom during any sexual contact with female of
             childbearing potential (FCBP) while participating in the study and for 28 days
             following discontinuation from this study, even if he has undergone a successful
             vasectomy.

             12. Males must also agree to refrain from donating semen or sperm during the
             treatment phase and for 28 days after discontinuation from this study treatment.

             13. All subjects must agree to refrain from donating blood while on study therapy and
             for 28 days after discontinuation from this study treatment.

             14. All subjects must agree not to share medication.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Any of the following laboratory abnormalities:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count &lt; 1,000/μL

               -  Platelet count &lt; 75,000/µL for subjects in whom &lt; 50% of bone marrow nucleated
                  cells are plasma cells; or a platelet count &lt; 30,000/µL for subjects in whom ≥
                  50% of bone marrow nucleated cells are plasma cells.

               -  Severe renal impairment (Creatinine Clearance &lt; 30 mL/min) requiring dialysis.

               -  Corrected serum calcium &gt; 11.5 mdL (&gt; 2.8 mmol/L)

               -  Hemoglobin &lt; 8 dL (&lt; 4.9 mmol/L; prior red blood cell transfusion or recombinant
                  human erythropoietin use is permitted)

               -  Serum  glutamic-oxaloacetic transaminase(SGOT)/ aspartate aminotransferase or
                  glutamic-pyruvic transaminase (SGPT)/alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &gt; 3.0 x ULN

               -  Serum total bilirubin &gt; 2.0 mdL (34.2 μmol/L); or &gt; 3.0 x ULN for subjects with
                  hereditary benign hyperbilirubinemia 2. Prior history of malignancies, other
                  than multiple myeloma, unless the subject has been free of the disease for ≥ 5
                  years.  Allowed exceptions include the following:

               -  Basal or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin

               -  Carcinoma in situ of the cervix or breast

               -  Incidental histological finding of prostate cancer (TNM [tumor, nodes,
                  metastasis]  stage of T1a or T1b) 3. Previous therapy with Pomalidomide 4.
                  Hypersensitivity to thalidomide, lenalidomide, or dexamethasone (this includes ≥
                  Grade 3 rash during prior thalidomide or lenalidomide therapy) 5. Subjects who
                  received an allogeneic bone marrow or allogeneic peripheral blood stem cell
                  transplant less than 12 months prior to initiation of study treatment and who
                  have not discontinued immunosuppressive treatment for at least 4 weeks prior to
                  initiation of study treatment and are currently dependent on such treatment.

                  6. Subjects with any one of the following:

               -  Congestive heart failure (New York Heart Association Class III or IV)

               -  Myocardial infarction within 12 months prior to starting study treatment

               -  Unstable or poorly controlled angina pectoris, including Prinzmetal's variant
                  angina pectoris 7. Subjects who received any of the following within 14 days of
                  initiation of study treatment:

               -  Major surgery (kyphoplasty is not considered major surgery)

               -  Use of any anti-myeloma drug therapy 8. Use of any investigational agents within
                  28 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer) of treatment, unless approved by
                  the sponsor.

                  9. Incidence of gastrointestinal disease that may significantly alter the
                  absorption of Pomalidomide.

                  10. Subjects unable or unwilling to undergo antithrombotic prophylactic
                  treatment 11. Any serious medical condition, laboratory abnormality, or
                  psychiatric illness that would prevent the subject from signing the informed
                  consent document.

                  12. Pregnant or breastfeeding females 13. Known Human immunodeficiency virus
                  positivity; active infectious hepatitis A, B, or C; or chronic hepatitis B or C
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yasir Nagarwala, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Celgene Corporation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Associate Director Clinical Trial Disclosure</last_name>
    <phone>1-888-260-1599</phone>
    <email>clinicaltrialdisclosure@celgene.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bay Area Cancer Research Group, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pleasant Hill</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94523</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Innovative Clinical Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Whittier</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90603</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Carroll Regional Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Westminster</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21157</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Luke's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kansas City</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>64111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hackensack University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hackensack</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Penn State Hershey Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hershey</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>17033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cancer Care Northwest</name>
      <address>
        <city>Spokane</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>99218</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 1, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 17, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Multiple Myeloma, MM, cancer, oncology, hematology, plasma, neoplasm, plasmacytoma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone 21-phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
