<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="77044">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01658345</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>87768</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01658345</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Microvascular Dysfunction in Aortic Stenosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>PRIMID-AS</acronym>
  <official_title>Prognostic Importance of Microvascular Dysfunction in Asymptomatic Patients With Aortic Stenosis (PRIMID-AS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospitals, Leicester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospitals, Leicester</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: National Institute for Health Research</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Aortic stenosis (AS), or narrowing of the aortic valve, is the commonest condition requiring
      valve surgery in the developed world. It is currently not known what determines who will go
      on to develop symptoms. Exercise testing may be able to identify these patients better than
      the severity of the narrowing itself, but with some limitations.

      The purpose of this study is to compare whether MRI scanning or exercise testing can better
      identify patients with AS who are likely to benefit from surgery.

      Design: The investigators will measure blood flow to the heart muscle with MRI scanning and
      perform exercise testing in 170 patients with AS and follow them for up to up to 2 years.
      Expected outcomes: MRI scanning will more accurately identify those patients with AS who
      will need surgery during this period. Anticipated Health Benefits: improved selection of
      patients with AS who are likely to benefit from early surgery. This is likely to reduce
      deaths in such patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Surgical AVR remains the universally accepted management for symptomatic aortic stenosis
      (AS). However, the best management of severe aortic stenosis, in the absence of symptoms,
      remains one of the most controversial areas in modern Cardiology.

      Exercise testing can identify asymptomatic patients with AS at increased risk, but with
      limited specificity.  In a BHF funded project, the investigators have identified that
      cardiac MRI measured Myocardial Perfusion Reserve (MPR) may be a novel imaging biomarker in
      AS.  MPR was the only independent predictor of aerobic exercise capacity (peak VO2) in
      patients with severe AS and was also inversely related to symptomatic status.

      In this multi-centre, observational, cohort outcome study, the investigators will follow 170
      patients with asymptomatic moderate to severe AS for a minimum of 12 months, and determine
      whether MPR is a better predictor of outcome than exercise testing,  elucidate the
      mechanisms contributing to symptom development in AS and establish the determinants of MPR
      in AS. Patients will be recruited from tertiary Cardiac centres, as well as regional
      hospitals. Comprehensive CMR with adenosine stress to determine LV mass and function, focal
      and diffuse fibrosis and MPR; cardiopulmonary exercise testing (peak VO2 and exercise
      symptoms); rest and exercise echocardiography (AS severity, valve compliance) and NT-proBNP
      will be performed. The study will be run in conjunction with the Glasgow CTU.
      Investigations will be analysed blind to patient status and data will be entered in a
      validated database.  Statistical analysis will be performed under the supervision of Prof.
      Ian Ford.  The relationship between MPR and exercise testing with 1-year outcome will be
      analysed using logistic regression.  Paired comparisons of the specificities of the two
      approaches on the same dataset will be carried out using McNemar's test.

      The primary hypothesis is that MPR will be a better predictor of adverse outcome than
      exercise testing.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Typical AS Symptoms necessitating AVR.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular death.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Major adverse cardiovascular events (MACE)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MACE: hospitalisation with heart failure, chest pain, syncope, arrhythmia or stroke</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Individual components of primary composite outcome measures.</measure>
    <time_frame>Upto 2 years.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Typical symptoms requiring referral for AVR, cardiovascular death, Major adverse cardiovascular events.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Development of typical symptoms, AVR, death from any cause or MACE during the entire study period.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">170</enrollment>
  <condition>Aortic Stenosis</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      With consent, a blood sample (up to 50ml) will be drawn and banked for prospective research
      studies.  All research projects will be related to cardiovascular disease and approved by
      the Trial Steering Committee (TSC) or a committee delegated this responsibility by the TSC.

      All tissue will be collected, stored and disposed of in accordance with the Codes of
      Practice as laid out by the Human Tissue Authority.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Cardiology outpatients department and echocardiography department.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Moderate-severe aortic stenosis (2 or more of: AVA &lt; 1.5cm2, peak PG &gt;36mmHg or  mean
             PG &gt; 25mmHg).

          2. Asymptomatic.

          3. Age &gt; 18 years and &lt; 85 years.

          4. Prepared to consider AVR if symptoms develop.

          5. Ability to perform bicycle exercise test

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of CABG, MI, angiographic CAD (&gt; 50% luminal stenosis if previously
             undertaken).

          2. Severe valvular disease other than AS.

          3. Previous Valve surgery

          4. Persistent Atrial Fibrillation or Flutter

          5. History of Heart Failure

          6. Severe Asthma.

          7. Severe renal impairment eGFR &lt; 30ml/min.

          8. Planned aortic valve replacement.

          9. Significant LV systolic dysfunction (EF &lt; 40%)

         10. Any absolute contraindication to CMR

         11. Any absolute contraindication to Adenosine

         12. Participation in an Interventional Clinical Trial at Inclusion.

         13. Other medical condition that limits life expectancy or precludes AVR.

         14. Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gerry P McCann, MBChB, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Leicester</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Anvesha Singh, MBChB</last_name>
    <phone>+44 300 303 1573</phone>
    <phone_ext>3422</phone_ext>
    <email>as707@leicester.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Glenfield Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leicester</city>
        <state>Leicestershire</state>
        <zip>LE3 9QP</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anvesha Singh, MBChB</last_name>
      <email>as707@leicester.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gerry P McCann, MBChB, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Leeds General Infirmary</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leeds</city>
        <state>West Yorkshire</state>
        <zip>LS1 3EX</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John Greenwood, MBChB, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+44 113 2432799</phone>
      <email>J.Greenwood@leeds.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Greenwood, MBChB, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Glasgow</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glasgow</city>
        <zip>G12 8QQ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Colin Berry, BSc, MBChB, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+44 1413301671</phone>
      <email>Colin.Berry@glasgow.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Colin Berry, BSc, MBChB, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steadman CD, Jerosch-Herold M, Grundy B, Rafelt S, Ng LL, Squire IB, Samani NJ, McCann GP. Determinants and functional significance of myocardial perfusion reserve in severe aortic stenosis. JACC Cardiovasc Imaging. 2012 Feb;5(2):182-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jcmg.2011.09.022.</citation>
    <PMID>22340825</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McCann GP, Steadman CD, Ray SG, Newby DE; British Heart Valve Society. Managing the asymptomatic patient with severe aortic stenosis: randomised controlled trials of early surgery are overdue. Heart. 2011 Jul;97(14):1119-21. Epub 2011 Mar 12.</citation>
    <PMID>21398695</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steadman CD, Ray S, Ng LL, McCann GP. Natriuretic peptides in common valvular heart disease. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2010 May 11;55(19):2034-48. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2010.02.021. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20447526</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Das P, Rimington H, Chambers J. Exercise testing to stratify risk in aortic stenosis. Eur Heart J. 2005 Jul;26(13):1309-13. Epub 2005 Apr 8.</citation>
    <PMID>15820999</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 6, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 6, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>aortic stenosis</keyword>
  <keyword>asymptomatic</keyword>
  <keyword>microvascular dysfunction</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiac MRI</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Aortic Valve Stenosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Constriction, Pathologic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
