<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="38671">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02130622</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>D14076</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02130622</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Promethazine for Treatment of Diabetic Gastroparesis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot, Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled Trial of Promethazine for Treatment of Diabetic Gastroparesis.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>American College of Gastroenterology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Adult diabetic patients (ages 18-65) with gastric emptying scintigraphy-confirmed delayed
      gastric emptying will be recruited to participate in the study.  Using double-blinded
      methodology, study participants will be randomly assigned to one of two treatment arms:
      promethazine 12.5 mg three times daily for 28 days or placebo three times daily for 28 days.
       The primary outcome will be the change in gastroparesis symptom severity, as measured by
      the Gastroparesis Cardinal Symptom Index (GCSI) at four weeks compared to baseline.
      Participants will be seen for a clinic evaluation at weeks 0, 2 and 4, during which symptom
      scores, adverse events and treatment compliance will be assessed. It is hypothesized
      promethazine treatment will be superior to placebo in improving symptoms of gastroparesis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in patient-reported symptoms as measured by the Gastroparesis Cardinal Symptom Index score (GCSI, 14) from week 0 to week 4.</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Use of rescue medication</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Frequency of use of the &quot;rescue medication&quot; meclizine</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The impact on work activity as measured by the Work Productivity and Activity Impairment Questionnaire. (WPAI).</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetic Gastroparesis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Promethazine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Promethazine 12.5 mg P.O. t.i.d. for 4 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar Pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo P.O. t.i.d. for 4 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Promethazine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Promethazine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Phenergan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sugar pill</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar Pill</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  adult patients 18-65 years of age

          -  clinical diagnosis of diabetic gastroparesis.

          -  EGD without evidence of gastric outlet obstruction within the past five years

          -  gastric emptying scintigraphy test demonstrating &gt;10% solid food retention at 4 hours
             within the past three years.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  the inability or unwillingness to provide informed consent

          -  currently pregnant or breast feeding

          -  prior placement of a gastric stimulator

          -  pyloric botulinum toxin injection within the past 12 months

          -  prior gastric surgery

          -  history of a connective tissue disorder

          -  use of narcotic medication within the past four weeks

          -  hemoglobin A1C &gt;12 mg/dL within the past 3 months

          -  current or recent (within past 4 weeks) use of promethazine, metoclopramide or
             domperidone

          -  hypersensitivity or prior adverse reaction to promethazine

          -  concomitant use of phenothiazines (i.e. prochlorperazine, chlorpromazine) or other
             agents likely to increase extrapyramidal reactions

          -  concomitant use of tiotropium or ipratropium

          -  narrow angle glaucoma

          -  urinary retention

          -  Parkinson's disease

          -  significant psychiatric disease

          -  history of seizure.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Benjamin N Stein, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Benjamin N Stein, MD</last_name>
    <phone>603 650 5261</phone>
    <email>Benjamin.N.Stein@Hitchcock.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lebanon</city>
        <state>New Hampshire</state>
        <zip>03756</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cherian D, Parkman HP. Nausea and vomiting in diabetic and idiopathic gastroparesis. Neurogastroenterol Motil. 2012 Mar;24(3):217-22, e103. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2982.2011.01828.x. Epub 2011 Nov 27.</citation>
    <PMID>22118574</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Janssen P, Harris MS, Jones M, Masaoka T, Farré R, Törnblom H, Van Oudenhove L, Simrén M, Tack J. The relation between symptom improvement and gastric emptying in the treatment of diabetic and idiopathic gastroparesis. Am J Gastroenterol. 2013 Sep;108(9):1382-91. doi: 10.1038/ajg.2013.118. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24005344</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ricci DA, Saltzman MB, Meyer C, Callachan C, McCallum RW. Effect of metoclopramide in diabetic gastroparesis. J Clin Gastroenterol. 1985 Feb;7(1):25-32.</citation>
    <PMID>3884697</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McCallum RW, Ricci DA, Rakatansky H, Behar J, Rhodes JB, Salen G, Deren J, Ippoliti A, Olsen HW, Falchuk K, et al. A multicenter placebo-controlled clinical trial of oral metoclopramide in diabetic gastroparesis. Diabetes Care. 1983 Sep-Oct;6(5):463-7.</citation>
    <PMID>6400707</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perkel MS, Moore C, Hersh T, Davidson ED. Metoclopramide therapy in patients with delayed gastric emptying: a randomized, double-blind study. Dig Dis Sci. 1979 Sep;24(9):662-6.</citation>
    <PMID>385260</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Snape WJ Jr, Battle WM, Schwartz SS, Braunstein SN, Goldstein HA, Alavi A. Metoclopramide to treat gastroparesis due to diabetes mellitus: a double-blind, controlled trial. Ann Intern Med. 1982 Apr;96(4):444-6.</citation>
    <PMID>7065559</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Patterson D, Abell T, Rothstein R, Koch K, Barnett J. A double-blind multicenter comparison of domperidone and metoclopramide in the treatment of diabetic patients with symptoms of gastroparesis. Am J Gastroenterol. 1999 May;94(5):1230-4.</citation>
    <PMID>10235199</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Erbas T, Varoglu E, Erbas B, Tastekin G, Akalin S. Comparison of metoclopramide and erythromycin in the treatment of diabetic gastroparesis. Diabetes Care. 1993 Nov;16(11):1511-4.</citation>
    <PMID>8299441</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McHugh S, Lico S, Diamant NE. Cisapride vs metoclopramide. An acute study in diabetic gastroparesis. Dig Dis Sci. 1992 Jul;37(7):997-1001.</citation>
    <PMID>1618070</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Feldman M, Smith HJ. Effect of cisapride on gastric emptying of indigestible solids in patients with gastroparesis diabeticorum. A comparison with metoclopramide and placebo. Gastroenterology. 1987 Jan;92(1):171-4.</citation>
    <PMID>3781184</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ehrenpreis ED, Deepak P, Sifuentes H, Devi R, Du H, Leikin JB. The metoclopramide black box warning for tardive dyskinesia: effect on clinical practice, adverse event reporting, and prescription drug lawsuits. Am J Gastroenterol. 2013 Jun;108(6):866-72. doi: 10.1038/ajg.2012.300.</citation>
    <PMID>23735907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tan PC, Khine PP, Vallikkannu N, Omar SZ. Promethazine compared with metoclopramide for hyperemesis gravidarum: a randomized controlled trial. Obstet Gynecol. 2010 May;115(5):975-81. doi: 10.1097/AOG.0b013e3181d99290.</citation>
    <PMID>20410771</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Braude D, Crandall C. Ondansetron versus promethazine to treat acute undifferentiated nausea in the emergency department: a randomized, double-blind, noninferiority trial. Acad Emerg Med. 2008 Mar;15(3):209-15.</citation>
    <PMID>18304050</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Revicki DA, Rentz AM, Dubois D, Kahrilas P, Stanghellini V, Talley NJ, Tack J. Development and validation of a patient-assessed gastroparesis symptom severity measure: the Gastroparesis Cardinal Symptom Index. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2003 Jul 1;18(1):141-50.</citation>
    <PMID>12848636</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Revicki DA, Camilleri M, Kuo B, Szarka LA, McCormack J, Parkman HP. Evaluating symptom outcomes in gastroparesis clinical trials: validity and responsiveness of the Gastroparesis Cardinal Symptom Index-Daily Diary (GCSI-DD). Neurogastroenterol Motil. 2012 May;24(5):456-63, e215-6. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2982.2012.01879.x. Epub 2012 Jan 27.</citation>
    <PMID>22284754</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reilly MC, Bracco A, Ricci JF, Santoro J, Stevens T. The validity and accuracy of the Work Productivity and Activity Impairment questionnaire--irritable bowel syndrome version (WPAI:IBS). Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2004 Aug 15;20(4):459-67.</citation>
    <PMID>15298641</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wahlqvist P, Carlsson J, Stålhammar NO, Wiklund I. Validity of a Work Productivity and Activity Impairment questionnaire for patients with symptoms of gastro-esophageal reflux disease (WPAI-GERD)--results from a cross-sectional study. Value Health. 2002 Mar-Apr;5(2):106-13.</citation>
    <PMID>11918826</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 1, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetic Gastroparesis</keyword>
  <keyword>Promethazine</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Gastroparesis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Promethazine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diphenhydramine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
