<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="89179">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02089152</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MICRO1307</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02089152</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Single-blind Stepped Wedge Cluster Randomized Controlled Behaviour Change Trial to Determine Effectiveness of Prevention Programme of Melioidosis in Diabetics in Ubon Ratchathani, Northeast Thailand</brief_title>
  <acronym>PREMEL</acronym>
  <official_title>A Single-blind Stepped Wedge Cluster Randomized Controlled Behaviour Change Trial to Determine Effectiveness of Prevention Programme of Melioidosis in Diabetics in Ubon Ratchathani, Northeast Thailand</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Thailand: Ministry of Public Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Study hypothesis:

      Prevention programme for melioidosis can reduce incidences of overall hospitalization due to
      infectious diseases and due to culture-confirmed melioidosis in diabetic population in
      northeast Thailand

      This study is a prospective single-blind multicentre stepped wedge cluster randomized
      controlled behaviour change trial in 9,000 diabetics in Ubon Ratchathani, northeast
      Thailand.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Melioidosis is an infectious disease caused by soil-dwelling Gram-negative bacilli
      Burkholderia pseudomallei. The disease is highly endemic in northeast Thailand. Diabetes
      mellitus is the major underlying risk factor for melioidosis, occurring in more than 50% of
      all culture-proven melioidosis patients. The annual incidence of melioidosis in diabetes in
      northeast Thailand is currently 244 per 100,000, and the overall case fatality rate is about
      40%. The number of people dying from melioidosis is now comparable to deaths from
      tuberculosis, and exceeds those from malaria, diarrheal illnesses and measles combined.
      Melioidosis is potentially preventable since infection occurs as a direct result of exposure
      to B. pseudomallei in the environment. Nonetheless, most of Thai people have never heard of
      melioidosis, there is currently no vaccine for melioidosis, and formal prevention guideline
      are lacking worldwide.

      The investigators recently developed new guidelines for the prevention of melioidosis in
      Thailand; including avoidance of direct contact with soil or environmental water and use of
      protective gear if contact is necessary, consumption of bottled or boiled water only, and
      avoidance of direct contact with heavy rain and dust clouds.

      The investigators aim to conduct a clinical trial to determine effectiveness of the proposed
      prevention programme of melioidosis. The investigators also predict that the prevention
      programme of melioidosis will also prevent other common infectious diseases with have
      similar routes of infection, such as leptospirosis and acute diarrhea. The outcome of the
      RCT will be crucial evidence for the Ministry of Public Health (MoPH) Thailand for their
      consideration of policy changes for the prevention of melioidosis countrywide.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall hospital admissions due to infectious diseases</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Infectious diseases will be determined by International Classification of Disease 10 (ICD10) defined by attending physicians.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Culture-confirmed melioidosis</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Culture-confirmed melioidosis is defined as presentation with clinical features of melioidosis in association with cultures from any clinical specimen positive for Burkholderia pseudomallei.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall mortality is defined as death from all causes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall melioidosis</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall melioidosis is defined as a combination of culture confirmed melioidosis and clinical melioidosis. Clinical melioidosis is defined as presentation with clinical features of melioidosis in association with cultures from all clinical specimens negative for Burkholderia pseudomallei.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">9000</enrollment>
  <condition>Melioidosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cluster A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>General education for prevention of diabetic complications in year 1, Melioidosis prevention education in years 2, 3 and 4.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cluster B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>General education for prevention of diabetic complications in year 1 and 2, Melioidosis prevention education in year 3 and 4.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cluster C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>General education for prevention of diabetic complications in year 1, 2 and 3, Melioidosis prevention education in year 4.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>An educational programme for prevention of melioidosis</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention will be randomly implemented at 10, 10 and 10 diabetic clinics at the end of years 1, 2 and 3, respectively. The education will be conducted using small group education, in which 20 to 25 participants at a time will attend group sessions conducted by the study team.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cluster A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cluster B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cluster C</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female (Include pregnant women) , aged from 18 to 65 years old

          -  Diagnosed of diabetes according to American Diabetes Association 2013 as following

               -  Fasting plasma glucose (FPG) ≥ 126 mg/dl or

               -  HbA1C ≥ 6.5% or

               -  2 hour plasma glucose (PG) ≥ 200 mg/dl during an OGTT or

               -  Classic symptoms of hyperglycaemia with a random PG ≥ 200 mg/dl

          -  Oriented and conversed normally

          -  Willingness to participate in the study, and written, informed consent obtained from
             patient

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Confused or unable to communicate

          -  Diagnosed of melioidosis and has not completed oral-eradicative treatment for
             melioidosis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Assist Prof. Direk Limmathurotsakul, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mahidol-Oxford Tropical Medicine Research Unit (MORU), Faculty of Tropical Medicine, Mahidol university, Thailand</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Assist Prof Direk Limmathurotsakul, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+662 203 6333</phone>
    <email>direk@tropmedres.ac</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sappasithiprasong Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ubon Ratchathani</city>
        <zip>34000</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pornpan Suntornsut</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Thailand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Currie BJ, Dance DA, Cheng AC. The global distribution of Burkholderia pseudomallei and melioidosis: an update. Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg. 2008 Dec;102 Suppl 1:S1-4. doi: 10.1016/S0035-9203(08)70002-6.</citation>
    <PMID>19121666</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Suputtamongkol Y, Hall AJ, Dance DA, Chaowagul W, Rajchanuvong A, Smith MD, White NJ. The epidemiology of melioidosis in Ubon Ratchatani, northeast Thailand. Int J Epidemiol. 1994 Oct;23(5):1082-90.</citation>
    <PMID>7860160</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Faa AG, Holt PJ. Melioidosis in the Torres Strait islands of far North Queensland. Commun Dis Intell Q Rep. 2002;26(2):279-83.</citation>
    <PMID>12206383</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chaowagul W, White NJ, Dance DA, Wattanagoon Y, Naigowit P, Davis TM, Looareesuwan S, Pitakwatchara N. Melioidosis: a major cause of community-acquired septicemia in northeastern Thailand. J Infect Dis. 1989 May;159(5):890-9. PubMed PMID: 2708842.</citation>
    <PMID>2708842</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leelarasamee A, Bovornkitti S. Melioidosis: review and update. Rev Infect Dis. 1989 May-Jun;11(3):413-25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2665001</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moulton LH, Golub JE, Durovni B, Cavalcante SC, Pacheco AG, Saraceni V, King B, Chaisson RE. Statistical design of THRio: a phased implementation clinic-randomized study of a tuberculosis preventive therapy intervention. Clin Trials. 2007;4(2):190-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17456522</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hayes RJ, Bennett S. Simple sample size calculation for cluster-randomized trials. Int J Epidemiol. 1999 Apr;28(2):319-26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10342698</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bursac Z, Gauss CH, Williams DK, Hosmer DW. Purposeful selection of variables in logistic regression. Source Code Biol Med. 2008 Dec 16;3:17. doi: 10.1186/1751-0473-3-17.</citation>
    <PMID>19087314</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 13, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Melioidosis</keyword>
  <keyword>stepped wedge trial</keyword>
  <keyword>behaviour change</keyword>
  <keyword>Education program</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melioidosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
