<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="154526">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01662791</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11-006817</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01662791</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Weight Loss in Parkinson's Disease and Role of Small Bowel Bacterial Overgrowth</brief_title>
  <official_title>Weight Loss in Parkinson's Disease and the Potential Role of Small Bowel Bacterial Overgrowth</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The potential role of Small bowel bacterial overgrowth (SBBO) in weight loss occurring in
      patients with PD has not previously been examined.  Our hypothesis is that SBBO is an
      important contributor to the development of weight loss in individuals with Parkinson's
      disease.  The investigators propose to 1) examine the role of SBBO in weight loss occurring
      in patients with PD and 2) determine the response to its treatment with a poorly absorbed
      antibiotic.  The investigators propose to perform a prospective, observational case-control
      study with an open-label therapeutic component.  Cases will be defined as those PD patients
      who&amp;apos;ve experienced significant weight loss while Controls will be defined as those PD
      patients who have not experienced significant weight loss.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hypothesis:  Small bowel bacterial overgrowth is an important contributor to the development
      of weight loss in individuals with Parkinson's disease.

      Specific aims:  1) To determine the prevalence of SBBO in consecutive patients seen in a
      Parkinson's disease specialty clinic, and 2) To evaluate the effect of SBBO treatment in PD
      patients with weight loss.

      Study design:  Prospective, observational case-control study with open-label therapeutic
      component.  Cases will be defined as those PD patients who've experienced significant weight
      loss while Controls will be defined as those PD patients who have not experienced
      significant weight loss.

      Part 1:

      Consecutive patients seen in the Parkinson's disease clinic at MCA will be approached to
      participate.  After the determination of their eligibility and appropriate signed informed
      consent, all PD patients (i.e., both Case and Control groups) will undergo the following:

        1. Assessment of demographic features, weight history and PD history

        2. PD and other medications

        3. Determination of PD severity using the Unified Parkinson's Disease rating scale

        4. Evaluation of gastrointestinal symptoms (GISSI and modified GISSI)

        5. Determination of usual calorie and nutrient intake (Brief Block Food Frequency
           Questionnaire)

        6. Paffenbarger physical activity questionnaire

        7. Quality of life (SF12 and PD-specific)

        8. HAD survey

        9. Glucose hydrogen breath test (SBBO test)

       10. Qualitative assessments of smell and taste

      All questionnaires will be completed during the 2 hour breath test.

      Part 2:

      All individuals in the weight loss group (i.e., only the Case group) will be offered
      open-label treatment with the poorly absorbed antibiotic, rifaximin, 550 mg PO BID for 14
      days.  Treatment will not depend upon the results of the bacterial overgrowth breath test.
      Thus, both normal and abnormal breath test subjects will receive antibiotic treatment.  The
      patient will be contacted by phone 1 month after treatment at which time the presence of GI
      symptoms will be determined and inquiry made about any adverse effects related to rifaximin
      use.  GI symptoms, quality of life, weight measurement and breath testing will be repeated
      at a 3 month study visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Small bowel bacterial overgrowth (SBBO)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 2 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>overnight fast, will ingest a solution consisting of 50 grams of glucose mixed in 150 mL of water.   laboratory staff will collect end-expiratory breath samples and will analyze them for hydrogen and methane using a Quintron SC breath microlyzer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale (UPDRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The scale consists of 4 sections that assess behavior and mood, activities of daily living, motor symptoms, and complications of therapy.  The first 3 sections comprise individual items that are rated on a 5-point scale (0 [no disability] to 4 [maximum disability]), with a maximum score of 175 for these 3 sections.  Higher UPDRS scores reflect more severe disease. The fourth section of the scale is used to evaluate patients with more advanced disease who are receiving drug treatment.  It takes about 15 minutes to complete.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gastrointestinal Symptom Severity Index (GISSI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The GISSI is a validated, self-administered, multi-dimensional instrument designed to measure the frequency, severity and bothersomeness of individual GI symptoms and to provide subscale scores for interrelated symptom clusters.  Factor analyses yielded 5 distinct symptom clusters that were labeled as Constipation/Difficult defecation; Abdominal Pain/Discomfort; Dyspepsia; Diarrhea/Fecal incontinence; and, GERD/Chest symptoms.  It takes less than 5 minutes to complete.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital Anxiety Depression Scale (HAD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The HADS is a self-administered 14-item questionnaire (seven for anxiety and seven for depression) Items are rated on a 4-point scale from 0-3.  Cut-offs for identifying psychiatric distress has been reported in the literature to be &gt;10 for anxiety and &gt;8 for depression.  It takes less than 5 minutes to complete.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight change</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Weight change after treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PD-specific quality of life questionnaire (PDQ-39)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>questionnaire designed to address aspects of functioning and well-being for those affected by Parkinson's disease.    This questionnaire is based on a multi-dimensional model of health.  Eight subscale scores may be derived from the items: mobility (10 items), activities of daily living (6 items), emotional well-being (6 items), stigma (4 items), social support (3 items), cognitions (4 items), communication (3 items), bodily discomfort (3 items).  Patients are asked to think about their health and general well-being and to consider how often in the last month they have experienced certain events (e.g. difficulty walking 100 yards).  Patients are asked to indicate the frequency of each event by selecting one of 5 options (Likert Scale):  Never/occasionally/sometimes/often/always or cannot do at all.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Paffenbarger physical activity questionnaire (PAQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>measuring 1-week physical activity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Brief Block Food Frequency Questionnaire (FFQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>assess differences in macronutrient, fiber and energy intake among the study participants.  This questionnaire contains a food list of about 70 food items and takes 15-20 minutes to complete.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rifaximin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All individuals in the weight loss group (i.e., only the Case group) will be offered open-label treatment with the poorly absorbed antibiotic, rifaximin, 550 mg PO BID for 14 days.  Treatment will not depend upon the results of the bacterial overgrowth breath test.  Thus, both normal and abnormal breath test subjects will receive antibiotic treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rifaximin</intervention_name>
    <description>All individuals in the weight loss group (i.e., only the Case group) will be offered open-label treatment with the poorly absorbed antibiotic, rifaximin, 550 mg PO BID for 14 days.  Treatment will not depend upon the results of the bacterial overgrowth breath test.  Thus, both normal and abnormal breath test subjects will receive antibiotic treatment.  The patient will be contacted by phone 1 month after treatment at which time the presence of GI symptoms will be determined and inquiry made about any adverse effects related to rifaximin use.  GI symptoms, quality of life, weight measurement and breath testing will be repeated at a 3 month study visit.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rifaximin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Xifaxin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria: Parkinson's Disease

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Wheelchair-bound, akinetic individuals

          2. Tube-fed individuals

          3. Presence of dementia

          4. Unwilling or unable to complete the tests

          5. Allergic or intolerant to rifaximin

          6. Presence of chronic upper or lower gastrointestinal disorders that have symptoms that
             may be confused with SBBO (e.g., irritable bowel syndrome, inflammatory bowel
             disease, celiac disease, functional dyspepsia, gastroparesis, and chronic
             pancreatitis)

          7. Presence of prior surgery on the gastrointestinal tract except cholecystectomy,
             appendectomy or herniorrhaphy

          8. Presence of severe concomitant acute or chronic medical condition that may interfere
             with the completion or interpretation of the test results

          9. Women of childbearing potential.  Given the age of patients with Parkinson's disease,
             we do not anticipate this being a large population.

         10. Use of antibiotics within 1 month of breath testing
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Di Baise, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Arizona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85259</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michaele Menghini</last_name>
      <phone>480-301-4319</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 7, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>John K. DiBaise</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Parkinson's Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Small Bowel Bacterial Overgrowth</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Weight Loss</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anti-Bacterial Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rifaximin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
