<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="87426">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02001051</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>140021</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>14-C-0021</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02001051</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Adrenalectomy Versus Observation for Subclinical Hypercortisolism</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Control Trial of Adrenalectomy Versus Observation for Subclinical Hypercortisolism</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>CC-OADRIS</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Adrenal tumors are a common kind of tumor. Some of these secrete extra cortisol into the
      body, which can lead to diabetes, obesity, and other diseases. Some people with extra
      cortisol will show symptoms like bruising and muscle weakness. Others will show no signs.
      This is called subclinical hypercortisolism. Some of these adrenal tumors become malignant.
      Researchers want to know the best way to treat people with subclinical hypercortisolism.
      They want to know if removing the tumor by surgery reduces the long-term effects of the
      disease.

      Objectives:

      - To see if removing an adrenal tumor by surgery improves blood pressure, diabetes, obesity,
      osteoporosis, or cholesterol, and cancer detection.

      Eligibility:

      - Adults 18 and older with an adrenal tumor and high cortisol levels.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with medical history, blood tests, and a CT scan.

        -  Participants will have a baseline visit. They will have blood and urine tests and 7
           scans. For most scans, a substance is injected through a tube in the arm. Participants
           will lie still on a table in a machine that takes images.

        -  Participants will have surgery to remove their tumor. Some will have surgery right
           away. Some will have surgery 6 months later, after 2 follow-up appointments.

        -  Participants will have 4 follow-up visits in the first year after surgery. They will
           have 2 visits the second year, then yearly visits for 3 years. At each follow-up visit,
           they will have scans and blood tests.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Adrenal incidentalomas are common and found in approximately 4-7% of the population.

        -  About 0.6 to 25% of patients with an adrenal incidentaloma are found to have
           subclinical hypercortisolism: 2.3% develop subclinical hypercortisolism during follow
           up and 0.6% develop clinical hypercortisolism during follow up.

        -  Subclinical hypercortisolism is defined as biochemical excess of cortisol without signs
           and symptoms of overt hypercortisolism but may be associated with metabolic
           complications or disease progression and malignancy.

        -  Overt signs and symptoms of hypercortisolism include facial plethora, easy bruising,
           violaceous straiae, and proximal muscle weakness.

        -  Several studies suggest that subclinical hypercortisolism may lead to long term
           consequences such as diabetes, hypertension, hypercholesterolemia, obesity, and
           osteoporosis.

        -  Thus, patients with subclinical hypercortisolism may benefit from operative
           intervention to halt or reverse metabolic complications associated with the disease and
           the risk of malignant progression.

        -  The optimal management of patients with subclinical hypercortisolism and adrenal
           incidentalomas is controversial and no large randomized trial has been conducted.

        -  We hypothesize that operative treatment would reduce the risk of long term
           complications of subclinical hypercortisolism and malignant progression, and propose a
           prospective randomized trial comparing nonoperative and operative management of
           subclinical hypercortisolism in patients with unilateral adrenal neoplasm.

      Objectives:

      Primary Endpoints:

      To determine whether adrenalectomy in patients diagnosed with subclinical hypercortisolism
      and a unilateral adrenal neoplasm results in normalization and/or improvement of
      hypertension as assessed by reduction in pharmacotherapy and/or normalization of blood
      pressure (systolic pressure &lt; =140 and diastolic pressure &lt; =90), diabetes as assessed by
      reduction or elimination of pharmacotherapy and/or improvement in A1C to &lt; 6.5%,
      osteoporosis by increase in bone formation markers indicative of increased bone formation,
      hypercholesterolemia as assessed by a reduction or elimination of pharmacotherapy and/or
      reduction in LDL levels to risk-stratified goal levels as defined by ATP III, and/or
      overweight or obesity as assessed by a 10 percent reduction in weight at 6 months.

      Eligibility:

        -  An individual with a unilateral adrenal neoplasm less than 5 cm in size with
           biochemically confirmed evidence of hypercortisolism (2 out of 3: dexamethasone
           suppression test (DST) cortisol &gt; 3 mmol/l, elevated urine free cortisol, and/or
           morning ACTH &lt; 2.2 pmol/l) without overt clinical signs and symptoms.

        -  Age greater than or equal to 18 years.

        -  Adults must be able to understand and sign the informed consent document.

        -  Patients must have laboratory and physical examination parameters within acceptable
           limits based on standard clinical practice.

      Design:

        -  Prospective randomized study comparing adrenalectomy versus observation.

        -  Patients assigned to the operative arm will undergo adrenalectomy and then followed
           postoperatively for normalization and/or improvement of metabolic complications
           associated with hypercortisolism and histologic examination of the resected tumor.

        -  Patients assigned to the non-operative arm will be monitored for possible complications
           associated with hypercortisolism for six months, at which point they will cross-over to
           the operative intervention arm.

        -  Demographic, clinical, laboratory and pathologic data will be collected for each
           patient participant. Data will be securely stored in a computerized database.

        -  Patients will have biochemical testing to determine if their adrenal neoplasm is
           functioning or nonfunctioning.

        -  Projected accrual will be 15 to 20 patients per year for a total of 5 years. Thus, we
           anticipate accruing 62 patients on this protocol.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine whether adrenalectomy in patients diagnosed with subclinical hypercortisolism and a unilateral adrenal neoplasm results in normalization and/or improvement of metabolic complications.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the risk of primary adrenal malignancy in patients with subclinical hypercortisolism and adrenal mass less than 5 cm.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine whether FDG PET/CT scan is diagnostic of subclinical hypercortisolism.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the optimal diagnostic test for subclinical hypercortisolism.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine whether patients show an improvement in quality of life after adrenalectomy compared to medical therapy.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine whether patients have an increased risk of deep venous thrombosis with subclinical hypercortisolism, regardless of treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">66</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypercortisolism</condition>
  <condition>Cushing Syndrome</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Adrenalectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>Surgical removal of one or both adrenal glands</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  An individual with a unilateral adrenal neoplasm less than 5 cm in size with
             biochemically confirmed evidence of hypercortisolism (2 out of 3: DST &gt; 3 mmol/l,
             elevated urine free cortisol, and/or morning ACTH &lt; 2.2 pmol/l) without overt
             clinical signs and symptoms.

          -  Age greater than or equal to 18 years.

          -  Adults must be able to understand and sign the informed consent document.

          -  Patients must have laboratory and physical examination parameters within acceptable
             limits by standard of practice guidelines prior to surgery as assessed by
             preoperative anesthesia assessment.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Biochemically and/or radiologically confirmed pheochromocytoma, hyperaldosteronoma,
             or adrenocortical carcinoma.

          -  Nonfunctioning adrenal neoplasm.

          -  Pre-existing cancers and/or metastatic disease to the adrenal glands.

          -  Pregnancy and/or lactation.

          -  Lack of metabolic complications.

          -  Imaging features worrisome for malignancy (heterogeneous tumor, presence of
             calcifications, necrosis, &gt; 10 Hounsfield units on an unenhanced CT scan, and delayed
             washout of contrast).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Electron Kebebew, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Candice M Cottle-Delisle, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-4395</phone>
    <email>cottlec@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Electron Kebebew, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-5049</phone>
    <email>kebebewe@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kaitlyn Chambers</last_name>
      <phone>301-402-4395</phone>
      <email>kaitlyn.chambers@nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Roxanne Merkel</last_name>
      <phone>(301) 402-4395</phone>
      <email>merkelre@mail.nih.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2014-C-0021.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Toniato A, Merante-Boschin I, Opocher G, Pelizzo MR, Schiavi F, Ballotta E. Surgical versus conservative management for subclinical Cushing syndrome in adrenal incidentalomas: a prospective randomized study. Ann Surg. 2009 Mar;249(3):388-91. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0b013e31819a47d2.</citation>
    <PMID>19247023</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reincke M. Subclinical Cushing's syndrome. Endocrinol Metab Clin North Am. 2000 Mar;29(1):43-56. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10732263</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chiodini I. Clinical review: Diagnosis and treatment of subclinical hypercortisolism. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2011 May;96(5):1223-36. doi: 10.1210/jc.2010-2722. Epub 2011 Mar 2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21367932</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 27, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Unilateral Adrenal Neoplasm</keyword>
  <keyword>Cushing Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Adrenal Incidentalomas</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Adrenocortical Hyperfunction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cushing Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
