<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="144614">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01884285</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>D4620C00001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01884285</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>AZD8186 First Time In Patient Ascending Dose Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I, Open-label, Multicentre Study to Assess the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Preliminary Anti-tumour Activity of Ascending Doses of AZD8186 in Patients With Advanced Castrate-resistant Prostate Cancer (CRPC), Squamous Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (sqNSCLC), Triple Negative Breast Cancer (TNBC) and Patients With Known PTEN-deficient Advanced Solid Malignancies, With Expansion to Assess the Pharmacodynamic Activity of AZD8186 Within Prospectively-validated PTEN Deficient Tumours</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AstraZeneca</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase I, open-label, multicentre study of AZD8186 administered orally in patients
      with advanced castrate-resistant prostate cancer (CRPC), squamous non-small cell lung cancer
      (sqNSCLC), triple negative breast cancer (TNBC) and known PTEN-deficient advanced solid
      malignancies.  The study design allows an escalation of dose with intensive safety
      monitoring to ensure the safety of the patients.

      There are two parts to this study: Part A, dose escalation, and Part B, expansion cohort(s)
      at the intended therapeutic dose(s).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A Phase I, Open-label, Multicentre Study to Assess the Safety, Tolerability,
      Pharmacokinetics and Preliminary Anti-tumour Activity of Ascending Doses of AZD8186 in
      Patients with Advanced Castrate-resistant Prostate Cancer (CRPC), Squamous Non-Small Cell
      Lung Cancer (sqNSCLC), Triple Negative Breast Cancer (TNBC) and patients with known
      PTEN-deficient Advanced Solid Malignancies, with Expansion to Assess the Pharmacodynamic
      Activity of AZD8186 within Prospectively-validated PTEN deficient Tumours
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Parts A and B: Safety and tolerability in terms of adverse events, serious adverse events (including death) and safety measures: ECG, physical examination, pulse, blood pressure, weight and laboratory variables</measure>
    <time_frame>Routine safety assessments, throughout the period that patients receive AZD8186 up to 30 days following discontinuation of last dose of study treatment.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part A: Definition of either the maximum tolerated dose (MTD), if possible, or maximum feasible dose (MFD) by measuring the number of evaluable patients with dose limiting toxicities (DLT's).</measure>
    <time_frame>DLT's assessed during the first 21 days of multiple dosing.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part A+ B: Antitumor activity by evaluation of tumour response assessments using Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumours (RECIST 1.1) or Prostate Cancer Clinical Trials Working Group (PCWG2) criteria in the case of patients with Prostate Cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 12 weeks (non Prostate patients) or every 6 weeks (Prostate patients) from baseline up to disease progression or withdrawal of constent, assessed up to 19 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>For non Prostate patients tumour response assessments will be will be every 12 weeks from baseline up to disease progression or withdrawal of constent. For Prostate patients tumour response assessments will be will be every 6 weeks from baseline up to disease progression or withdrawal of constent.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part A + B: Anti-tumour activity by measurement of changes in circulating prostate-specific antigen (PSA)</measure>
    <time_frame>PSA will be measured at mutiple timepoints: at screening; predose on first day of dosing Day1, cycle 1 day 8, cycle 1 day 15; every 28 days Cycle 2 and beyond; at study discontinuation, assessed up to 19 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part A +B: Plasma concentrations of AZD8186 and pharmacokinetic parameters (Cmax, tmax, AUC, terminal rate constant, clearance, half life, volume of distribution and mean resistance time)</measure>
    <time_frame>PartA/Day1(predose,0.25,0.5,1,1.5,2,3,4,6,8,10,12,24h);PartA/last day of dosing/Cycle1/week3(predose,0.25,0.5,1,1.5,2,3,4,6,8,10,12,24h);PartB/Cycle1/Day1(predose,0.25,0.5,1,1.5,2,3,4,6,8,10,12h);PartB/Cycle1/Day2(predose,0.25,0.5,1,1.5,2,3,4,6,8,10,12h)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected at multiple timepoints following dosing: Part A Day 1 (pre-dose, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12 and 24 hours) ; Part A last day of dosing during Cycle 1 week 3 (pre-dose, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12 and 24 hours): Part B Cycle 1 Day 1 (pre-dose, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10 and 12 hours); Part B Cycle 1 Day 2 (pre-dose, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10 and 12 hours)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part A+ B: Understanding of the CYP3A4 induction potential of AZD8186 by measuring 4 beta-hydroxy cholesterol concentration in blood samples.</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood samples will be collected from all patients for 4 beta-hydroxy cholesterol concentration measurements pre-dose day 1 and pre-morning dose day 22 in both Part A and B.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part B: Obtaining of a preliminary assessment of the antitumour activity of AZD8186 as monotherapy by evaluation of proof of mechanism biomarkers in PTEN-deficient tumour tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>Paired tumour biopsies will be collected; one prior to treatment and the other during treatment (last day of dosing in the second week of cycle 1)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Obtaining of a preliminary assessment of AZD8186 drug effect in the tumour by evaluation of pharmacodynamic biomarker changes</measure>
    <time_frame>Paired tumour biopsies will be collected; one prior to treatment and the other during treatment (last day of dosing in the second week of cycle 1)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Investigation of predictive markers and acquired resistance to AZD8186 that may be observed in tumour from patients treated with AZD8186.</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline,predose first day of dosing,last day of dosing during cycle 1 week 2,cycle 4 day 1 then every 6 weeks thereafter (for Prostate patients) or 12 weeks (for non Prostate patients),and at the time of discontinuation, assessed up to 19 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>For Prostate patients blood samples will be taken to provide one sample of plasma and one sample of serum per each of the following timepoints: at screening, predose first day of dosing, last day of dosing during cycle 1 week 2, cycle 4 day 1 then every 6 weeks thereafter (if continuing on treatment), and at the time of discontinuation. For non Prostate patients blood samples will be taken to provide one sample of plasma and one sample of serum per each of the following timepoints: at screening, predose first day of dosing, last day of dosing during cycle 1 week 2, cycle 4 day 1 then every 12 weeks thereafter (if continuing on treatment), and at the time of discontinuation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Investigation of predictive markers and acquired resistance to AZD8186 that may be observed in plasma circulating free DNA from patients treated with AZD8186.</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline,predose first day of dosing,last day of dosing during cycle 1 week 2,cycle 4 day 1 then every 6 weeks thereafter (for Prostate patients) or 12 weeks (for non Prostate patients),and at the time of discontinuation, assessed up to 19 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>For Prostate patients blood samples will be taken to provide one sample of plasma and one sample of serum per each of the following timepoints: at screening, predose first day of dosing, last day of dosing during cycle 1 week 2, cycle 4 day 1 then every 6 weeks thereafter (if continuing on treatment), and at the time of discontinuation. For non Prostate patients blood samples will be taken to provide one sample of plasma and one sample of serum per each of the following timepoints: at screening, predose first day of dosing, last day of dosing during cycle 1 week 2, cycle 4 day 1 then every 12 weeks thereafter (if continuing on treatment), and at the time of discontinuation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part A: Urine concentrations of AZD8186 and pharmacokinetic parameters (Cmax, tmax, AUC, terminal rate constant, clearance, half life, volume of distribution and mean resistance time)</measure>
    <time_frame>Urine samples will collected at multiple time points: Day 1 (predose, 15min post dose, 30min post dose); Last dosing day during Cycle 1 week 3 (predose and 15min post dose)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">96</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Castrate-resistant Prostate Cancer (CRPC);</condition>
  <condition>Squamous Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (sqNSCLC);</condition>
  <condition>Triple Negative Breast Cancer (TNBC)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AZD8186</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive a single dose on Day 1 folowed by ongoing multiple dosing. The initial schedule will use intermittent dosing of AZD8186.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AZD8186</intervention_name>
    <description>The initial schedule will use intermittent dosing of AZD8186. Dose, frequency and schedule in subsequent cohorts may increase or decrease in response to safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetic and preclinical data.</description>
    <arm_group_label>AZD8186</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Provision of signed and dated, written informed consent prior to any study specific
             procedures

          -  Male or female, aged 18 years and older

          -  Histologically or cytologically proven diagnosis of prostate cancer, squamous non
             small cell lung cancer (sqNSCLC), triple negative breast cancer (TNBC), or a known
             PTEN-deficient solid malignancy, that is refractory to standard therapies

          -  Females should be using adequate contraceptive measures (see Section 4.3), should not
             be breast feeding and must have a negative pregnancy test prior to start of dosing if
             of child-bearing potential

          -  World Health Organisation (WHO)/ECOG performance status 0 to 1 with no deterioration
             over the previous 2 weeks and minimum life expectancy of 12 weeks

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Treatment before study with  (a) Nitrosourea or mitomycin C; (b) Investigational
             agents from a previous clinical study; (c) Chemotherapy, immunotherapy or anticancer
             agents; (d) hormonal therapy (e.g., steroids)

          -  Treatment before study with  (a) Strong inhibitors and strong or moderate inducers of
             CYP3A4 (b) Radiotherapy with a wide field of radiation

          -  With the exception of alopecia or toxicities related to the use of
             gonadotropin-releasing hormone agonists any unresolved toxicities from prior therapy
             greater than Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events  grade 1 at the time of
             study treatment

          -  Spinal cord compression or brain metastases unless asymptomatic, treated and stable
             and not requiring steroids

          -  Any evidence of severe or uncontrolled systemic diseases including active liver
             disease (other than malignancy), active bleeding diatheses, or active infection
             including hepatitis B, hepatitis C and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Glen Clack</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>AstraZeneca</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lillian Sui, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Princess Margaret Hospital, Canada</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>AstraZeneca Clinical Study Information</last_name>
    <phone>800-236-9933</phone>
    <email>ClinicalTrialTransparency@astrazeneca.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>AstraZeneca Cancer Study Locator Service www.emergingmed.com/networks/AstraZeneca</last_name>
    <phone>1-877-400-4656</phone>
    <email>astrazeneca@emergingmed.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sutton</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 15, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 17, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Advanced Castrate-resistant Prostate Cancer(CRPC)</keyword>
  <keyword>Squamous Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer(sqNSCLC)</keyword>
  <keyword>Triple Negative Breast Cancer(TNBC)</keyword>
  <keyword>PTEN-deficient Advanced Solid Malignancies</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
