<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="134504">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01938079</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAM0950</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>AAAM0950-KET</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01938079</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ketamine and Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation (ECMO)</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Use of Ketamine in Patients Receiving Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In a healthy patient, the lungs provide oxygen to the blood and remove carbon dioxide.
      However, in patients with severe lung failure, blood may not adequately be delivered to the
      lungs, or the lungs may not adequately supply blood with oxygen. In this case, patients may
      require assistance from a machine to help provide this oxygen. Extracorporeal membrane
      oxygenation (ECMO) is a device that acts as an artificial lung, allowing the patient to
      recover from their illness. Patients receiving support from ECMO are often put in a
      medically induced coma while their lungs heal. Certain drugs may stick to the internal
      surfaces of the machine; therefore leading to decreased concentrations. Patients receiving
      ECMO often require high doses of both pain medications and sedatives in order to provide
      comfort. Low doses of a drug, ketamine, may help to provide additive effects to pain relief
      and allow lower doses of other pain medications. We hypothesize that patients' treated with
      continuous intravenous ketamine, will have lower requirements of other pain medications
      while receiving ECMO for acute respiratory failure while achieving the desired level of
      sedation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Purpose and Rationale:

      The administration of analgesia and sedation is common practice for patients receiving
      mechanical ventilation with extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO). Maintaining patient
      comfort and safety, while not oversedating and thereby risking prolonged mechanical
      ventilation and delirium, is an ongoing balancing act which presents a daily challenge for
      Intensive Care Unit (ICU) clinicians. Medication selection should be based on the patient's
      needs with titration to a predetermined goal in accordance with published guidelines.
      However, there are major pharmacokinetic changes that occur with the use of ECMO, including
      sequestration of medications within the circuit, increased volume of distribution, and in
      some cases decreased clearance. As a result patient's receiving ECMO often require very high
      doses of both analgesics and sedatives in order to provide comfort and ventilator synchrony.
      In patients not receiving ECMO, excess sedative exposure, especially with benzodiazepines,
      leads to increased mechanical ventilation time, prolonged ICU stay, short and long term
      neurocognitive impairments, and increased mortality. No studies address these outcomes in
      patients receiving ECMO.

      Ketamine, a non-barbiturate phencyclidine derivative, provides analgesia with relative
      hemodynamic stability and maintained airway reflexes. However, its popularity waned because
      of an undesirable side effect profile:

      Hallucinations, delirium, lacrimation, tachycardia, and potential for an increase in
      intracranial pressure (ICP) and coronary ischemia. Recent research, however, suggests that
      low doses of ketamine infusions in combination with opiates may not be associated with
      adverse sequelae and may improve outcomes in the critically ill population. To date, there
      are no studies that have compared clinical outcomes in ICU patients sedated with ketamine as
      compared with other sedative agents.

      Supplemental sedation with intravenous ketamine infusion may decrease opioid and sedative
      requirements for patients receiving mechanical ventilation and ECMO. The benefits of
      decreased opioid and sedative requirements may translate to fewer gastrointestinal side
      effects, decreased withdrawal syndromes, and a reduced rate of delirium.

      Deep levels of sedation are often required at the commencement of ECMO for acute respiratory
      failure, which correlates to a Richmond Agitation Sedation Score (RASS)of -5. Supplemental
      low doses of ketamine infusions may help the prescriber achieve this goal without having to
      use very high doses of fentanyl or hydromorphone and midazolam.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>A decrease in fentanyl or hydromorphone requirements with ketamine infusion.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Reduction in Opiate Use</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ketamine will be initiated as a one-time 40 mg bolus of ketamine followed by a continuous intravenous infusion of 5 micrograms/kg/min at the start of ECMO (RASS -5). The ketamine infusion will continue as long as the patient requires deep sedation (RASS -5) up to 14 days. The ketamine infusion will be discontinued when the medical team chooses to lighten sedation and wake the patient up (RASS -3 to 0).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fentanyl or Hydomorphone</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ketamine</intervention_name>
    <description>Ketamine will be initiated as a one-time 40 mg bolus of ketamine followed by a continuous intravenous infusion of 5 micrograms/kg/min at the start of ECMO (RASS -5).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard of Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Fentanyl or hydromorphone and midazolam infusions will be administered to all patients and titrated at the discretion of the attending physician to maintain the desired level of sedation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Receiving ECMO for acute respiratory failure

          -  Requiring deep sedation (RASS -5)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Allergy to ketamine
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel Brodie, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Daniel Brodie, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-305-9817</phone>
    <email>hdb5@cumc.columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Amy L Dzierba, PharmD</last_name>
    <phone>212-305-5852</phone>
    <email>ald9012@nyp.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NewYork-Presbyterian Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Daniel Brodie, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-305-9461</phone>
      <email>hdb5@cumc.columbia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Amy L Dzierba, PharmD</last_name>
      <phone>212-305-5852</phone>
      <email>ald9012@nyp.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 5, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 5, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Columbia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Daniel Brodie</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ECMO</keyword>
  <keyword>Ketamine</keyword>
  <keyword>Opiates</keyword>
  <keyword>Lung failure</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ketamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
