<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="119431">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02020070</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-134</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02020070</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ipilimumab and Degarelix With Radical Prostatectomy in Men With Newly Diagnosed Metastatic Castration Sensitive Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2 Study Combining Ipilimumab and Degarelix With Radical Prostatectomy in Men With Newly Diagnosed Metastatic Castration Sensitive Prostate Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ferring Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to find out what effects, good and/or bad, taking ipilimumab
      with degarelix before surgery to remove the  prostate, followed by more degarelix and
      ipilimumab after the surgery, will have on prostate cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>undetectable PSA</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12 and 20 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>An undetectable PSA at 12 and 20 months from the start of treatment among patients with non-castrate (&gt; 150 ng/ml) levels of testosterone. An undetectable PSA is defined as PSA ≤0.05 ng/mL.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Progression-free survival (PFS) is a composite endpoint defined as disease progression in bone or soft-tissue, symptoms, or death measured from study entry. Progression in soft tissue will be measured by modified RECIST per PCWG2..</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall survival is defined as death from any cause measured from study entry.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety will be evaluated for all treated patients using the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE), Version 4.0 (http://ctep.cancer.gov). Safety assessments will be based on medical review of AE reports and the results of vital sign measurements, physical examinations, and clinical laboratory tests.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">53</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Castration Sensitive Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ipilimumab and Degarelix With Radical Prostatectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Week 1: Degarelix 240 mg SQ injection and Ipilimumab at 10 mg/kg intravenously (IV). Surgery Radical prostatectomy (RP)will be performed during week 3 ± 1 week or after recovery to grade ≤ 1 adverse events experienced during the induction period related to treatment. Continued Androgen Depletion and Ipilimumab  Weeks 5, 9, 13, 17, 21, 25, and 29: Degarelix 80 mg SQ
Week 11, 14, 17 or after sufficient wound healing and recovery post RP:
Ipilimumab 10mg/kg IV Follow-up Twelve week intervals until Week 87.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Degarelix</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Ipilimumab and Degarelix With Radical Prostatectomy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ipilimumab</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Ipilimumab and Degarelix With Radical Prostatectomy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radical Prostatectomy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Ipilimumab and Degarelix With Radical Prostatectomy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Target Population Patients with castration-sensitive oligometastatic prostate cancer who
        have not received primary local therapy (radiation or surgery), and no more than 2 months
        of prior androgen deprivation therapy.

          -  The subject must be age 18 or older, and be willing and able to provide informed
             consent.

          -  The subject must have histologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of the prostate with
             tissue confirmation at selected study site.

          -  The subject must have newly diagnosed prostate cancer with a metastatic site(s).

          -  The subject must have ≤ 10 bony metastatic lesions detected by nuclear medicine bone
             scan.

          -  Distant metastatic lymph node(s) (e.g., retroperitoneal or non-regional pelvic lymph
             nodes) are allowed

          -  Regional pelvic lymph nodes (as per AJCC Cancer Staging [7th edition]) will be
             considered a metastatic site if greater than 1.5cm in shortest dimension.

          -  The subject must have Karnofsky performance status of 80-100.

          -  Normal organ function with acceptable initial laboratory values:

               -  WBC ≥ 2000/μL

               -  ANC ≥ 1000/ μL

               -  Platelets ≥ 75 x 103/μL

               -  Creatinine ≤ 2.0 x ULN

               -  AST/ALT ≤ 2.5 x ULN

               -  Bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x ULN (except patients with Gilbert's Syndrome, who must have a
                  total bilirubin less than 3.0 mg/dL)

          -  No active or chronic infection with HIV, Hepatitis B or Hepatitis C (negative
             screening tests required).

          -  The subject must be deemed to be medically fit for radical prostatectomy by the
             attending urologic surgeon at the selected study site.

          -  Men of fathering potential must be using an adequate method of contraception to avoid
             conception throughout the study [and for up to 26 weeks after the last dose of
             ipilimumab] in such a manner that the risk of pregnancy is minimized.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any other malignancy from which the patient has been disease-free for less than 5
             years, with the exception of adequately treated and cured basal or squamous cell skin
             cancer or superficial bladder cancer

          -  Major surgery within 4 weeks of enrollment (Week 1 Visit).

          -  Current or prior radiation therapy to the prostate Prior radiation to a metastatic
             site (e.g., palliative radiation) is allowed..

          -  More than 5 months of prior hormonal therapy (e.g., gonadotropin hormone releasing
             analogs, megestrol acetate, or casodex) . There is no washout period required for
             GnRH analogs. A two week washout is required for megestrol or anti-androgen.

          -  Prior use of an 5 alpha reductase inhibitor is allowed (no limit on duration of use),
             however a two week washout is required.

          -  No prior ketoconazole, abiraterone acetate, or enzalutamide for the treatment of
             prostate cancer.

          -  Current or prior investigational therapies for prostate cancer, or chemotherapy
             administered with the intent to treat prostate cancer.

          -  Concomitant therapy with any other experimental drug.

          -  Autoimmune disease: Patients with a history of inflammatory bowel disease, including
             ulcerative colitis and Crohn's Disease, are excluded from this study, as are patients
             with a history of symptomatic disease (e.g., rheumatoid arthritis, systemic
             progressive sclerosis [scleroderma], systemic lupus erythematosus, autoimmune
             vasculitis [e.g., Wegener's granulomatosis]); motor neuropathy considered of
             autoimmune origin (e.g., Guillain-Barre syndrome and myasthenia gravis).

          -  Any underlying medical or psychiatric condition, which in the opinion of the
             investigator will make the administration of ipilimumab hazardous or obscure the
             interpretation of AEs, such as a condition associated with frequent diarrhea.

          -  Patients with underlying heart conditions who are deemed ineligible for surgery.

          -  Any non-oncology vaccine therapy used for prevention of infectious diseases (for up
             to 1 month before or after any dose of ipilimumab).

          -  Note: Inactivated vaccines are allowed at any time on study.

          -  A history of prior treatment with ipilimumab or prior CD137 agonist or CTLA-4
             inhibitor or agonist.

          -  Concomitant or prior therapy with any of the following: IL-2, interferon, or other
             nonstudy immunotherapy regimens; immunosuppressive agents; ; or chronic use of
             systemic corticosteroids within 6 weeks of study entry.

          -  Persons of reproductive potential unwilling to use an adequate method of
             contraception throughout treatment and for at least 26 weeks after ipilimumab is
             stopped.

          -  Patients who have had a history of acute diverticulitis, intra-abdominal abscess, GI
             obstruction and abdominal carcinomatosis which are known risk factors for bowel
             perforation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen Autio, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karen Autio, MD</last_name>
    <phone>646-422-4632</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Howard Scher, MD</last_name>
    <phone>646-422-4330</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karen Autio, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-422-4632</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Howard Scher, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-422-4330</phone>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karen Autio, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mskcc.org/</url>
    <description>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ipilimumab</keyword>
  <keyword>Degarelix</keyword>
  <keyword>Radical Prostatectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>13-134</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
