<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="95630">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01712256</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CT-BI Vacc-4x 2012/1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01712256</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Re-boosting of HIV-1 Infected Subjects With Vacc-4x</brief_title>
  <acronym>Re-boost</acronym>
  <official_title>Re-boosting of Subjects Previously Included in the CT BI-Vacc-4x 2007/1 Study. An Open, Multicenter, Immunogenicity, Follow-up Re-boosting Study With Vacc-4x in Subjects Infected With HIV-1 Who Have Maintained an Adequate Response to ART</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bionor Immuno AS</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bionor Immuno AS</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Paul-Ehrlich-Institut</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Ethics Commission</authority>
    <authority>Italy: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Spanish Agency of Medicines</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      During the course of HIV infection the number of CD4 cells decreases, resulting in a reduced
      immunological response and eventually immune deficiency. Vacc-4x is a peptide-based HIV
      immunotherapy vaccine and is anticipated to strengthen the immune system's response to HIV.

      All patients participating in this trial have previously received the vacc-4x vaccine in
      order to reduce the amount of HIV-1 virus in the blood and increase the immune response. The
      primary objective of this study is to evaluate if a re-boost with Vacc-4x could further
      reduce the amount of HIV-1 virus and increase the immune response.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infects the cluster of differentiation 4 (CD4) subset of
      T-cells that are critical for initiating immune responses to infection. The level of CD4
      cells in the blood is a marker of a patient's immunological status. During the course of an
      HIV infection, the number of CD4 cells decreases, resulting in reduced immunological
      responsiveness and ultimately immune deficiency.

      Current management of an HIV infection includes antiretroviral therapy (ART). The advent of
      effective ART in 1996 led to a profound decrease in type 1 HIV (HIV-1)-associated morbidity
      and mortality in developed countries where ART has been available.

      Despite the ability of ART to inhibit HIV-1 replication, it cannot cure infection, making
      ART a lifelong treatment that requires sustained compliance and imposes significant
      individual and societal financial burdens on healthcare services. Furthermore, ART side
      effects (e.g., metabolic toxicity and stigmatizing body fat redistribution) often require
      medication that further increases the inconveniences and financial burdens of HIV
      management. Of additional concern is the emergence of viruses resistant to ART that can
      result in treatment failure.

      Vacc-4x is a peptide-based HIV therapeutic vaccine. The primary objective of Vacc-4x
      therapeutic vaccine is to strengthen the immune system's response to HIV p24. ART
      dramatically reduces the level of virus in circulation in the body, thereby allowing the
      immune system to focus on the therapeutic vaccine that is administered. ART also allows for
      the generation of new naïve CD4 cells that can be triggered by the therapeutic vaccine to
      generate new immune responses to HIV-1. Subjects are therefore immunized with Vacc-4x in the
      presence of ART to generate new HIV-specific immune responses that can sustain immunological
      fitness for prolonged periods when patients are removed from ART. It is likely that periodic
      boosting on ART will be required to sustain the immunotherapeutic effect - in this way ART
      may become an intermittent therapy.

      This study is a follow-up, re-boosting study of Study CT-BI Vacc-4x 2007/1 (EudraCT Number
      2007-006302-13) performed in US and Europe (UK, Germany, Spain and Italy). All subjects to
      be included have been given a therapeutic immunization with Vacc-4x during the CT-BI Vacc-4x
      2007/1 study. During the study a reduction in the viral load set-point (mean viral load at
      Week 48 and Week 52, or if Week 52 not reached, mean viral load of the last two measured
      values before restart of ART) was seen in the Vacc-4x group compared to placebo group.
      Further stimulation of the immune system by re-boosting with Vacc-4x could reduce the viral
      load set-point further.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vacc-4x effect on viral load set-point</measure>
    <time_frame>37 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The effect of Re-boost with Vacc-4x on the viral load set-point obtained following immunization with Vacc-4x in Study CT-BI Vacc-4x 2007/1 by measuring viral load before and after reboosting.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vacc-4x effect on immune response</measure>
    <time_frame>37 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Effect of Re-boost with Vacc-4x on immune response obtained following immunization with Vacc-4x in Study CT-BI Vacc-4x 2007/1</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CD4 counts</measure>
    <time_frame>37 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Effect of a re-boost with Vacc-4x on CD4 counts</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Delayed Type Hypersensitivity test(DTH)</measure>
    <time_frame>37 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In vivo immunogenicity of Vacc-4x by delayed-type hypersensitivity (DTH) and to compare the DTH response to the DTH response observed in the initial study; CT-BI Vacc-4x 2007/1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>37 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of re-boosting with Vacc-4x by number of participants with Adverse Events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CD8 counts</measure>
    <time_frame>37 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Effect of a re-boost with Vacc-4x on CD8 counts</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">33</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV-1 Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Re-boosting with Vacc-4x</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients previously participating in the CT-BI Vacc-4x 2007/1 study and completed immunization regimen with Vacc-4x active and stopped ART (at Week 28) (No re-start of ART is required).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vacc-4x</intervention_name>
    <description>Two re-boost immunisations with adjuvant and vacc-4x, one at week 1 and one at week 3.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Re-boosting with Vacc-4x</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Completed immunization regimen with Vacc-4x active and stopped ART (at Week 28) in
             the CT-BI Vacc-4x 2007/1 study. (No re-start of ART is required).

          2. Documented pre-study CD4 cell count ≥400x106/L.

          3. Documented pre-study viral load &lt; 300 000copies/mL.

          4. Signed informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Reported AIDS-defining illness within the previous year.

          2. Malignant disease.

          3. On chronic treatment with immune-suppressive therapy.

          4. Unacceptable values of the hematologic and clinical chemistry parameters, as judged
             by the Investigator, including creatinine values &gt;1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN),
             and AST, ALT and alkaline phosphatase (ALP) values &gt;2.5 x ULN.

          5. Concurrent chronic active infection such as viral hepatitis B or C or tuberculosis.

          6. Pregnant or breastfeeding women.

          7. Women of childbearing potential not using reliable and adequate contraceptive methods
             (defined as: use of oral, implanted, injectable, mechanical or barrier products for
             the prevention of pregnancy; practicing abstinence; sterile) during the 5 weeks
             re-boosting period including the DTH and for 2 weeks after the DTH test, or sexually
             active male subjects with partners of child bearing potential unwilling to practice
             effective contraception during the 5 weeks re-boosting period including the DTH and
             for 12 weeks after the DTH-test.

          8. Current participation in other clinical therapeutic studies.

          9. Incapability of compliance to treatment protocol, in the opinion of the Investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>63 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vidar Wendel-Hansen, Dr. med</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Bionor Pharma ASA, Kronprinsesse Märthas Plass 1, P.O. Box 1477 Vika, NO-0116 Oslo, Norway</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA CARE Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90035</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UC Davis Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sacramento</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95817</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>EIPMED - Gesellschaft fűr epidemiologische und klinische Forschung in der Medizin mbH Rubensstrasse 125</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>12157</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Bonn, Medizinische Klinik und Poliklinik I; Immunologische Ambulanz, Siegmund-Freud-Str. 25</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bonn</city>
        <zip>53127</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Hamburg Eppendorf</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>20246</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ifi - Studien und Projekte GmbH, an der Asklepios-Klinik St. George</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>20099</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Istituto San Raffaele</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <zip>20127</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Germans Trias i Pujol</name>
      <address>
        <city>Badalona</city>
        <zip>08916</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Unidad de VIH, Hospital de Bellvitge, Calle Feixa Llarga s/n, Hospitalet de Llobregat.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08907</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Harrison Wing St Thomas' Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SE1 7EH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kran AM, Sommerfelt MA, Baksaas I, Sørensen B, Kvale D. Delayed-type hypersensitivity responses to HIV Gag p24 relate to clinical outcome after peptide-based therapeutic immunization for chronic HIV infection. APMIS. 2012 Mar;120(3):204-9. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-0463.2011.02843.x. Epub 2011 Nov 27.</citation>
    <PMID>22339677</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lind A, Sommerfelt M, Holmberg JO, Baksaas I, Sørensen B, Kvale D. Intradermal vaccination of HIV-infected patients with short HIV Gag p24-like peptides induces CD4 + and CD8 + T cell responses lasting more than seven years. Scand J Infect Dis. 2012 Aug;44(8):566-72. doi: 10.3109/00365548.2011.653581. Epub 2012 Feb 19.</citation>
    <PMID>22339485</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jones T. Vacc-4x, a therapeutic vaccine comprised of four engineered peptides for the potential treatment of HIV infection. Curr Opin Investig Drugs. 2010 Aug;11(8):964-70.</citation>
    <PMID>20721838</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kran AM, Sørensen B, Sommerfelt MA, Nyhus J, Baksaas I, Kvale D. Long-term HIV-specific responses and delayed resumption of antiretroviral therapy after peptide immunization targeting dendritic cells. AIDS. 2006 Feb 28;20(4):627-30.</citation>
    <PMID>16470131</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 16, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CD4</keyword>
  <keyword>Clinical trial</keyword>
  <keyword>Human immunodeficiency virus-1 (HIV-1)</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunomodulary</keyword>
  <keyword>Infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Phase II</keyword>
  <keyword>Re-boost</keyword>
  <keyword>Vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>Vacc-4x</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
