<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="93998">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01786655</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB-P00003344</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01786655</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety Study of Long-Acting Local Anesthetic</brief_title>
  <official_title>Neosaxitoxin (NeoSTX) Alone and in Combination With Bupivacaine as Prolonged Duration Local Anesthetics: A Phase I Investigator-initiated Dose Escalation Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital Boston</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital Boston</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary aim of this Phase 1 study is to evaluate the safety of a new prolonged-duration
      local anesthetic (numbing agent), neosaxitoxin (NeoSTX).  The investigators hypothesize that
      a &quot;minimal adverse effect threshold&quot; NeoSTX dose for subcutaneous administration, in saline
      and in bupivacaine 0.2% respectively, can be defined for awake, young adult healthy
      volunteer subjects.  At the same time, the pharmacokinetics of the NeoSTX when delivered
      subcutaneously will be determined.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary aim of this Phase 1 study is to evaluate the systemic safety of a novel
      prolonged-duration local anesthetic, neosaxitoxin (NeoSTX), given by subcutaneous injection,
      either alone or in combination with the commonly used local anesthetic, bupivacaine. The
      hypothesis is that, using adverse events as endpoints, a &quot;minimal adverse effect threshold&quot;
      NeoSTX dose for subcutaneous administration, in saline and in bupivacaine 0.2% respectively,
      can be defined for awake, young adult healthy volunteer subjects.

      Currently available amino amide local anesthetics (e.g. bupivacaine, levobupivacaine,
      ropivacaine) do not reliably provide analgesia beyond roughly 8 hours following subcutaneous
      infiltration.  In addition, they can cause systemic toxicities such as seizures,
      arrhythmias, and cardiac arrest, as well as local tissue toxicities to muscle, cartilage and
      nerve. Therefore, there is a need for safe local anesthetics that can provide longer
      duration analgesia with low systemic and local tissue toxicities.

      The investigator team previously reported that tetrodotoxin, saxitoxin, and NeoSTX  could
      produce prolonged sensory blockade (numbness) and motor blockade (weakness) following
      injection near the sciatic nerves in rats.    In these studies, combining the site 1 toxin
      with either bupivacaine or epinephrine dramatically improved efficacy (duration of sensory
      blockade) and reduced systemic toxicity.

      NeoSTX is the most potent member of the STX series identified to date. In preliminary
      studies, investigators at the University of Chile, Santiago, and with a small biotech
      company, Proteus S.A, developed a bioreactor process to produce clinical grade NeoSTX
      efficiently, with excellent purity, stability, sterility and non-pyrogenicity.     A series
      of preclinical safety and toxicologic studies in mice, rats, and sheep were performed at CHB
      and Toxikon, Inc.

      In this proposal, the investigators plan to conduct a Phase I study to be performed under an
      Investigator-Initiated FDA IND to further establish the systemic and local safety of
      escalating doses of NeoSTX via sub-cutaneous infiltration in healthy and awake young adult
      male human volunteer subjects.

      A sequential dose escalation design will be used with groups of either 7, 11, or 15 subjects
      in each dose step.   In double blind fashion, each subject will receive two injections
      simultaneously in a 3 cm x 3cm square area on skin of the posterior aspect of the lower leg
      (calf), one on each side, in a randomized block design as outlined in Table 1.  Each subject
      receives one injection with bupivacaine 0.2% alone on one side.  On other side, they will
      receive one of 3 possible solutions:   (1) saline placebo, (2) NeoSTX in saline or (3)
      NeoSTX in combination with bupivacaine. The dose of NeoSTX will escalate in subsequent
      cohorts as follows: 5 mcg; 15 mcg; 30 mcg; 45 mcg; 60 mcg; 70 mcg

      In each dose group, only one of the injections involves placebo.    Prior to each dose
      increase, there is a safety review and confirmation that no stopping rule has been reached.

      The first cohort begins with 7 subjects (3 receiving NeoSTX in saline, 3 receiving NeoSTX in
      bupivacaine, 1 receiving saline placebo).

      The size of successive cohorts remains at 7 subjects as long as there are:

        1. 0   Grade 2, 3 or 4   FDA-AEs

        2. 0   Grade 2, 3 or 4   SD-AEs

      If there is one Grade 2 FDA-AEs or one Grade 2 SD-AEs, but no stopping rule is triggered,
      then the size of subsequent cohorts is increased to 11 subjects.

      If a stopping rule is triggered, then the dose is reduced to the previous step, defined as
      the &quot;Maximum Tolerated Dose&quot; and additional subjects are enrolled to reach a total of 15
      subjects at that dose.  Thus, for example, if 11 subjects had been enrolled at a dose of 30
      mcg, dosing was escalated to 45 mcg and then a stopping rule was triggered, then dosing of
      45 mcg would stop and 4 additional subjects would be enrolled at the 30 mcg dose.

      Specific Aims

        1. Measure the dose dependence of  FDA-AEs and SD-AEs from NeoSTX in saline;

        2. Measure the dose dependence of FDA-AEs and SD-AEs from NeoSTX  in bupivacaine 0.2%;

        3. Measure the serum and urine concentrations of NeoSTX following injections of NeoSTX
           alone or with bupivacaine 0.2%; and correlate the serum concentrations with the
           &quot;Systemic Effects&quot;;

        4. Evaluate skin integrity and other potential local reactions (edema, numbness, and
           paresthesia, erythema) in treated limbs receiving NeoSTX-saline, NeoSTX-bupivacaine, or
           plain bupivacaine.

        5. Using QST, establish  the dependence of  sensory blockade intensity and duration on
           NeoSTX dose and on presence or absence of bupivacaine;

      Hypotheses

        1. Using FDA-AEs and SD-AEs as endpoints, a &quot;minimal adverse effect threshold&quot; NeoSTX dose
           for subcutaneous administration, in saline and in bupivacaine 0.2% respectively, can be
           defined for awake, young adult healthy volunteer subjects.

        2. PK-PD analysis will define serum concentrations associated with onset of &quot;Systemic
           Effects&quot; induced by NeoSTX.

        3. NeoSTX will have a low frequency of adverse skin reactions.

        4. The intensity and duration of sensory blockade from NeoSTX in saline or NeoSTX in
           bupivacaine will vary with NeoSTX dose and with presence or absence of bupivacaine.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence or absence of Adverse Events as a function of NeoSTX dose</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 14 days of injection</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameters characterizing uptake and distribution of NeoSTX (content in serum and urine samples)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 24 hours of injection</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cutaneous sensory blockade (numbness)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 14 days of injection</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>measured by noninvasive quantitative sensory testing (QST)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Local skin reactions (edema, paresthesias and urticaria)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 14 days of injection</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">77</enrollment>
  <condition>Safety of Neosaxitoxin in Healthy Adult Male Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neosaxitoxin in saline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects receive one injection of NeoSTX in saline on the back of one calf (test side). Subjects receive NeoSTX in saline in subsequent dose escalation levels: 5 mcg, 15 mcg, 30 mcg, 45 mcg, 60 mcg, 70 mcg of NeoSTX.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neosaxitoxin + bupivacaine 0.2%</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects receive one injection of NeoSTX in combination with 0.2% bupivacaine on the back of one calf (test side). Subjects receive NeoSTX with  0.2% bupivacaine in subsequent dose escalation levels: 5 mcg, 15 mcg, 30 mcg, 45 mcg, 60 mcg, 70 mcg of NeoSTX.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Saline placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects receive one injection of saline on the back of one calf (test side).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neosaxitoxin (NeoSTX) in saline</intervention_name>
    <description>NeoSTX will be administered in sequential dose cohorts. Each subject receives one injection with bupivacaine 0.2% alone on one side. On the other side they receive NeoSTX in saline. Subjects receive NeoSTX in saline in subsequent dose escalation levels: 5 mcg, 15 mcg, 30 mcg, 45 mcg, 60 mcg, 70 mcg of NeoSTX.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Neosaxitoxin in saline</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NeoSTX with 0.2% bupivacaine</intervention_name>
    <description>NeoSTX will be administered in sequential dose cohorts. Each subject receives one injection with bupivacaine 0.2% alone on one side. On the other side they receive NeoSTX with 0.2% bupivacaine. Subjects receive NeoSTX with 0.2% bupivacaine in subsequent dose escalation levels: 5 mcg, 15 mcg, 30 mcg, 45 mcg, 60 mcg, 70 mcg of NeoSTX.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Neosaxitoxin + bupivacaine 0.2%</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Each subject receives one injection with bupivacaine 0.2% alone on one side. On the other side they receive saline placebo.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Saline placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Healthy adult males ages 18-35

          2. ASA physical status 1 or 2

          3. English or Spanish speakers

          4. Must be able to come to Boston Children's Hospital for a 24-hour stay and able and
             willing to attend 5-10 study visits

          5. Must be able to provide informed consent

          6. Must be able to understand and perform all the procedures of the study including
             self-reporting of symptom scores

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. ASA physical status 3 or greater

          2. Cognitively challenged or other inability to understand the self-report measures or
             to give informed consent

          3. Significant cardiovascular, respiratory, neuromuscular disease or other systemic
             illness(es)

          4. No known or suspected allergies to neosaxitoxin, bupivacaine, or other local
             anesthetics

          5. Subjects may not be on any pain controlling medications, or any medications that
             would alter pain tolerance

          6. Subjects may not be on any medication that would alter cognition

          7. Subjects may not have any acute or chronic pain conditions requiring ongoing
             treatment or limiting daily activities

          8. No alcohol or illicit drug abuse

          9. No current smokers
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joseph Cravero, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital Boston</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joseph Cravero, MD</last_name>
    <phone>617-355-7737</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kimberly Lobo, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>857-218-3556</phone>
    <email>kimberly.lobo@childrens.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boston Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joseph Cravero, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 21, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 6, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>local anesthetic</keyword>
  <keyword>neosaxitoxin</keyword>
  <keyword>neoSTX</keyword>
  <keyword>bupivacaine</keyword>
  <keyword>safety</keyword>
  <keyword>phase 1</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacokinetic</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics, Local</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bupivacaine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neosaxitoxin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
