<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="73962">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01973543</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UCSF-AADC-01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1302-1209</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01973543</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>AADC Gene Therapy for Parkinson's Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>AADC</acronym>
  <official_title>An Open-label Safety and Efficacy Study of AAV2-hAADC Administered by MRI-Guided Convective Infusion Into the Putamen of Subjects With Parkinson's Disease With Fluctuating Responses to Levodopa</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Krystof Bankiewicz</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oregon Health and Science University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Safety study of AADC gene transfer in subjects with Parkinson's disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Parkinson's disease is a neurodegenerative disorder involving loss of neurons that release
      dopamine in the striatum. To compensate for the loss of dopamine, patients are typically
      prescribed levodopa medication which is converted to dopamine by the enzyme Aromatic L-Amino
      Acid Decarboxylase (AADC). As Parkinson's disease progresses, levodopa therapy becomes less
      effective and is associated with motor fluctuations, involuntary movements and other
      complications.

      This study will primarily investigate the safety of increasing AADC levels in the striatum
      via AADC gene delivery. The hAADC gene is packaged into a gene transfer vector derived from
      a common, non-pathogenic virus (AAV2) to which &gt;90% of humans have been exposed. This
      investigational drug, termed AAV2-hAADC, will be injected directly into the striatum during
      a neurosurgical procedure that is performed with real-time MRI imaging to monitor delivery.

      Subjects will continue to take Parkinson's disease medications, including levodopa.

      The safety and potential clinical responses to AAV2-hAADC will be assessed by repeated
      clinical evaluations of Parkinson's disease, cognitive tests, laboratory blood tests and
      neuroimaging. Clinical evaluations will be performed over a 3 year follow-up period. A test
      to specifically assess the clinical response to levodopa will be performed once before AADC
      gene delivery and approximately 6 months after.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of AADC Gene Transfer</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Years after Gene Transfer</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety and Tolerability of AADC Gene Transfer assessed by Adverse Events and Serious Adverse Events.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parkinson's Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Years after Gene Transfer</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Effect of AAV2-hAADC on Parkinson's symptoms as recorded in subject diaries, neurological and motor assessments, quality of life surveys and changes to Parkinson's medications.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PET Scan Imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months after Gene Transfer</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Relationship between AAV2 distribution in the brain and change in AADC expression as seen in PET imaging.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AAV2-hAADC Dose 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose 1 = 7.5 x 10^11 vector genomes of AAV2-hAADC; Single dose, neurosurgically infused, bilaterally into the striatum.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AAV2-hAADC Dose 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose 1 = 2.3 x 10^12 vector genomes of AAV2-hAADC; Single dose, neurosurgically infused, bilaterally into the striatum.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AAV2-hAADC</intervention_name>
    <description>Neurosurgical delivery of AAV2-hAADC to the brain.</description>
    <arm_group_label>AAV2-hAADC Dose 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>AAV2-hAADC Dose 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosed with idiopathic Parkinson's disease and on levodopa therapy for 5 or more
             years.

          -  Modified Hoehn and Yahr Staging of III or IV off medication.

          -  Candidate for surgical intervention because of disabling motor complications.

          -  UPDRS Part III (total motor) score ≥ 25 and a maximum of 60 in the OFF state.

          -  Unequivocal responsiveness to dopaminergic therapy.

          -  Stable Parkinson's symptoms and medication regimen for at least 4 weeks prior to
             screening examination.

          -  Ability to comprehend and sign the informed consent.

          -  Normal Laboratory values prior to surgery.

          -  Neutralizing AAV2 antibody titer ≤ 1:1200

          -  Ability to travel to study visits alone or able to designate a caregiver.

          -  Subject agrees to defer any neurological surgery, including deep brain stimulation,
             until after completing the 12 month study visit (unless recommended by study
             neurologist).

          -  Subject agrees to not participate in any other therapeutic intervention study for 12
             months after surgery.

          -  Subject agrees to not have any vaccinations within 30 days of surgery.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Atypical or secondary parkinsonism, including but not limited to symptoms believed to
             be due to trauma, brain tumor, infection, cerebrovascular disease, other neurological
             disease, or to drugs, chemicals or toxins.

          -  Presence of dementia as defined by a Mattis Dementia Rating Scale-Second Edition
             (MDRS-2) of less than 130 at screening.

          -  Presence or history of psychosis, with the exception of mild, benign hallucinations
             believed in the judgment of the investigators to be related to Parkinson's
             medications.

          -  Presence of severe depression as measured by Beck Depression Inventory II  (BDI-II) &gt;
             28 or a history of a major affective disorder within 5 years of screening
             examination.

          -  Current suicidal ideation or suicide attempt within 5 years of screening examination.

          -  History of substance abuse within 2 years of screening examination.

          -  Brain imaging abnormalities in the striatum or other regions that would substantially
             increase risk of surgery.

          -  Contraindication to MRI and/or gadoteridol.

          -  Coagulopathy or inability to temporarily stop any anticoagulation or antiplatelet
             prior to surgery.

          -  Prior brain surgery including deep brain stimulation, infusion therapies or any other
             brain surgery.

          -  Prior gene transfer.

          -  History of stroke, poorly controlled or significant cardiovascular disease, diabetes
             or any other acute or chronic medical condition.

          -  History of malignancy other than treated carcinoma in situ within three years of
             screening evaluation.

          -  Clinically apparent or laboratory-detected infection.

          -  Prior or current treatment with any investigational agent within 2 months of
             screening evaluation.

          -  Chronic immunosuppressive therapy, including chronic steroids, immunotherapy,
             cytotoxic therapy and chemotherapy.

          -  Pregnant and lactating women.

          -  Subject with reproductive capacity who is unwilling to use barrier contraception.

          -  Any factors, medical or social, which would likely cause the subject to be unable to
             follow the study protocol, including geographical inaccessibility.

          -  Ongoing treatments such as, neuroleptic medications, apomorphine, or levodopa
             infusion therapy (Duodopa®).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul S Larson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marin Thompson, MS</last_name>
    <phone>415-353-9666</phone>
    <email>AADC@ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, San Francisco</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 7, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 25, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Krystof Bankiewicz</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Kinetics Foundation Chair in Translational Research and Professor in Residence of Neurological Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PD</keyword>
  <keyword>Parkinson's disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Aromatic Amino Acid Decarboxylase</keyword>
  <keyword>AADC</keyword>
  <keyword>AAV2-AADC</keyword>
  <keyword>AAV2</keyword>
  <keyword>Viral Vector</keyword>
  <keyword>Gene Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Gene Transfer</keyword>
  <keyword>MRI</keyword>
  <keyword>PET</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
