<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="97420">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01856257</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DAIT CTOT-16</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01856257</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy of a Steroid-free, Calcineurin Inhibitor-free, Belatacept-based Immunosuppressive Regimen</brief_title>
  <official_title>Steroid and Tacrolimus Avoidance Using NULOJIX® (Belatacept) in Renal Transplantation (CTOT-16)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Clinical Trials in Organ Transplantation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Transplant recipients have to take anti-rejection medications to prevent their immune system
      (the body's natural defense system against illness) from rejecting their new kidney.   Most
      patients who get a kidney transplant must take these anti-rejection medications for the rest
      of their lives, or for as long as the kidney continues to work.  Taking standard
      anti-rejection medications for a long time can cause serious side effects, including kidney
      damage. There would be a benefit to finding new anti-rejection medications that work just as
      well, but don't damage the kidney.

      The purpose of this study is to find out if NULOJIX® (belatacept), will minimize serious
      long term side effects seen with anti-rejection medications while still protecting your new
      kidney from damage.  The researchers also want to learn more about the safety of this
      treatment and long term health of your transplanted kidney.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) calculated for each treatment group using the Chronic Kidney Disease Epidemiology Collaboration equation (CKD-EPI)</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of clinically suspected and biopsy proven acute rejection within the first 52 weeks as defined by histologic evidence of rejection and graft dysfunction.</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with estimated Glomerular Filtration Rate (eGFR) &lt; 60 mL/min/1.73 m2 by Chronic Kidney Disease Epidemiology Collaboration equation (CKD-EPI)</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in chronic kidney disease (CKD) stages from baseline.</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Chronic kidney disease (CKD) stages are defined as follows:
Stage 1: glomerular filtration rate (GFR) of 90+ (normal kidney function but urine findings or structural abnormalities or genetic trait point to kidney disease)
Stage 2: GFR of 60-89 (mildly reduced kidney function point to kidney disease)
Stage 3A: GFR of 45-59 (moderately reduced kidney function)
Stage 3B: GFR of 30-44 (moderately reduced kidney function)
Stage 4: GFR of 15-29 (severly reduced kidney function)
Stage 5: GFR of &lt;15 (very severe, or endstage kidney failure)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with defined chronic kidney disease (CKD) stage 4 or 5.</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean calculated estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) using modification of diet in renal disease (MDRD) 4 variable model.</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The slope of estimated glomerular filtration Rate (eGFR) by chronic kidney disease epidemiology collaboration equation (CKD-EPI) over time based on serum creatinine collected at all visits indicated on the schedule of events</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of delayed graft function</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Delayed graft function is defined as dialysis in the first week on one or more occasions for any indication other than the treatment of acute hyperkalemia in the setting of otherwise acceptable renal function</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of acute cellular rejection grade equal to or &gt; than IA, by the Banff 2007 criteria, within the first 52 weeks.</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The severity of first and highest grade of acute cellular rejection within the first 52 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of antibody mediated rejection</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Antibody mediated rejection is defined as diffusely positive staining for C4d, presence of circulating anti-donor antibodies, and morphologic evidence of acute tissue injury.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The type of treatment of rejection.</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The concomitant medications or therapies to treat the participant's rejection will be summarized by the adverse reaction outcome status. Medications will be defined by each site's standard of care.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The prevalence of de novo anti-donor histocompatibility antigen (HLA) antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of new onset diabetes after transplant (NODAT) or impaired fasting glucose (IFG)based on criteria specified by the ADA and WHO</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of treated diabetes between day 14 and week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Treated diabetes is defined as receipt of any oral medication or insulin for the treatment of diabetes for &gt;14 days.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c) measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, days 28 &amp; 84, and weeks 28, 36 and 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Standardized blood pressure measurement and use of anti-hypertensive medications</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fasting lipid profile (total cholesterol, non-high density lipoprotein cholesterol, low-density lipoprotein, high density lipoprotein, and triglyceride) and use lipid lowering medications</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 28 and 52 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total daily prescribed pill count</measure>
    <time_frame>days 28 and 84 and weeks 28, 36 and 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of death or graft loss.</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of rejection.</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of all adverse events (AEs) and serious adverse events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of infections requiring hospitalization, or systemic therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of BK Polyoma Virus (BKV) and Cytomegalovirus (CMV) viremia (local center monitoring)</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of Epstein Barr Virus (EBV) infection as reported on the case report form</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence fever &gt; 39 degrees and blood pressure &lt; 90mm Hg within 24 hours of onset of transplant procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Kidney Transplantation</condition>
  <condition>Transplantation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Thymoglobulin + tacrolimus + MMF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Induction with Thymoglobulin, methylprednisolone, and maintenance immunosuppression with tacrolimus and mycophenolate mofetil (MMF)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Thymoglobulin + belatacept + MMF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Induction with Thymoglobulin, methylprednisolone, and maintenance with belatacept and mycophenolate mofetil (MMF)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Basiliximab + 20 weeks of tacrolimus + MMF + belatacept</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Induction with 2 doses of basiliximab, methylprednisolone, plus tacrolimus  for 20 weeks and maintenance with belatacept and mycophenolate mofetil (MMF).  Subjects participating in this arm may have tacrolimus reinstated, at a dose to be determined by the site investigator, if any of the following events occur: 1 - An acute rejection episode 2- Request of the subject or site Investigator.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anti-thymocyte Globulin (Rabbit)</intervention_name>
    <description>The target dosage is 6mg/kg total over 3 to 4 days. The recommended route of administration is intravenous infusion using a high-flow vein.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Thymoglobulin + tacrolimus + MMF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Thymoglobulin + belatacept + MMF</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Thymoglobulin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Belatacept</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive belatacept at a dose of 10mg/kg up on day 1, 5, 14, 28, 56 and 84. After 84 days, subjects will receive a maintenance dose of 5 mg/kg every 4 weeks until completion of the trial.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Thymoglobulin + belatacept + MMF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Basiliximab + 20 weeks of tacrolimus + MMF + belatacept</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NULOJIX</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methylprednisolone</intervention_name>
    <description>Methylprednisolone will be administered at a target dose of 500 mg beginning on the day of transplant, and tapered to 250 mg day 1 post-transplant, 125 mg day 2 post-transplant, 60 mg day 3 post-transplant, 30 mg day 4 post-transplant and day 5 post-transplant 0 mg if therapeutic tacrolimus level achieved for groups 1 and 3.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Thymoglobulin + tacrolimus + MMF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Thymoglobulin + belatacept + MMF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Basiliximab + 20 weeks of tacrolimus + MMF + belatacept</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Medrol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Basiliximab</intervention_name>
    <description>Basiliximab will be administered in two doses of 20 mg each.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Basiliximab + 20 weeks of tacrolimus + MMF + belatacept</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Simulect</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mycophenolate Mofetil</intervention_name>
    <description>Mycophenolate Mofetil will be administered at a target dose of 1000 mg orally twice a day. Myfortic® (mycophenolate sodium) may be used as a replacement for MMF. Mycophenolate sodium will be dosed at 720 mg PO BID. Mycophenolate sodium will be adjusted based on clinical complications.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Thymoglobulin + tacrolimus + MMF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Thymoglobulin + belatacept + MMF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Basiliximab + 20 weeks of tacrolimus + MMF + belatacept</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CellCept®</other_name>
    <other_name>MMF</other_name>
    <other_name>Mycophenolate</other_name>
    <other_name>Mycophenolate sodium</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tacrolimus</intervention_name>
    <description>The site investigator will identify a starting tacrolimus dose at their discretion, in order to achieve the target trough levels, no later than 5 days post-transplantation. The dose will be adjusted to 5-8ng/ml for the active comparator arm (thymoglobulin + tacrolimus + MMF arm) or tapered off in the experimental arm (basiliximab + 20 weeks of tacrolimus + MMF + belatacept).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Thymoglobulin + tacrolimus + MMF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Basiliximab + 20 weeks of tacrolimus + MMF + belatacept</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Prograf</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or Female, 18-65 years of age at the time of enrollment;

          2. Ability to understand and provide written informed consent;

          3. Candidate for primary renal allograft from either a living or deceased donor;

          4. No known contraindications to study therapy using NULOJIX® (belatacept);

          5. Female participants of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test
             upon study entry;

          6. Participants with reproductive potential must agree to use an appropriate method(s)
             of birth control as outlined in the CellCept® , Myfortic® or generic package labeling
             during participation in the study and for 4 months following completion of the study;

          7. No donor specific antibodies prior to transplant that are considered to be of
             clinical significance by the site investigator;

          8. Negative crossmatch or a PRA of 0% on historic and current sera, as determined by
             each participating study center.

          9. A documented negative TB test within the 6 months prior to transplant. If
             documentation is not present at the time of transplantation, and the subject does not
             have any risk factors for TB, a TB-specific interferon gamma release assay (IGRA) may
             be performed.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Need for multi-organ transplant

          2. Recipient of previous organ transplant

          3. Epstein Barr Virus (EBV) sero-negative (or unknown) recipients

          4. Active infection including hepatitis B, hepatitis C, or human Immunodeficiency Virus
             (HIV)

          5. Individuals who have required treatment with prednisone or other immunosuppressive
             drugs within 1 year prior to transplant

          6. Individuals undergoing transplant using organs from extended criteria donor (ECD) or
             donation after cardiac death (DCD) donors

          7. Histocompatibility antigen (HLA) identical living donors

          8. Individuals at significant risk of early recurrence of the primary renal disease
             including focal segmental glomerulosclerosis (FSGS) and membranoproliferative
             glomerulonephritis (MPGN) type 2 or any other disease that in the opinion of the
             investigator is at increased likelihood of recurrence and which may result in rapid
             decline in renal function

          9. Known history of thrombotic events or risk factors; including any of the following:

               1. Factor V Leiden, elevated homocysteine, positive lupus anticoagulant, elevated
                  anticardiolipin antibody, heparin induced thrombocytopenia

               2. A family history of a heritable thrombotic condition,

               3. Recurrent DVT or PE,

               4. Unexplained stillborn infant or recurrent spontaneous abortion or other
                  congenital or acquired thrombotic disorder At the discretion of the
                  investigator, a history of thrombosis of a dialysis access graft, fistula, or
                  indwelling catheter/device may not be considered an exclusion criterion

         10. Any condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, would interfere with the
             participant's ability to comply with study requirements

         11. Use of investigational drugs within 4 weeks of enrollment

         12. Known hypersensitivity to mycophenolate mofetil (MMF)or any of the drug's components

         13. Administration of live attenuated vaccine(s) within 8 weeks of enrollment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kenneth Newell, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Roslyn B. Mannon, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alabama at Birmingham</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Deana Mays</last_name>
      <phone>205-934-0035</phone>
      <email>dmays@uab.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Roslyn Mannon, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, San Francisco</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>JoAnn Zlatunich</last_name>
      <phone>415-353-8380</phone>
      <email>Joann.zlatunich@ucsfmedctr.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Stock, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Keshawna Shere</last_name>
      <phone>404-712-1737</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <email>Keshawna.sherer@emoryhealthcare.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kenneth Newell, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.niaid.nih.gov/</url>
    <description>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ctotstudies.org/</url>
    <description>Clinical Trials in Organ Transplantation (CTOT)</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 6, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 14, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Kidney Transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>Transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>NULOJIX</keyword>
  <keyword>belatacept</keyword>
  <keyword>Transplantation, renal</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antilymphocyte Serum</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycophenolate mofetil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tacrolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Basiliximab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Abatacept</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone Hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycophenolic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
