<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="8247">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01904604</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DAIT CoFAR6</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>5U19AI066738-07</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01904604</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Peanut Epicutaneous Immunotherapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Epicutaneous Immunotherapy (EPIT) for Peanut Allergy: A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Phase II Study in Children and Adults (DAIT COFAR6)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Consortium of Food Allergy Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Data and Safety Monitoring Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Food allergy happens when the immune system reacts against foods.  The immune system is the
      part of the body that protects us from illness and germs, but it can also cause allergies.
      Peanut allergy occurs in 1 - 2% of people in the United States and other Western countries.
      There is proof that allergy to peanut is increasing.  Allergic reactions to peanut can be
      severe and life threatening. The only way that you can prevent an allergic reaction is to
      avoid exposure to peanuts.  However, peanut proteins are found in a variety of foods and
      people can be accidently exposed to peanut proteins.  Treatment for accidental exposure
      include antihistamines (medications like Benadryl), and injectable epinephrine (adrenalin)
      which must be carried at all times. DBV Technologies has developed an epicutaneous delivery
      system, a patch that puts the peanut protein on the skin. The study will try to find out if
      peanut epicutaneous immunotherapy can protect people who are allergic to peanuts from having
      severe allergic reactions, when accidentally exposed to peanuts. The study also looks at the
      safety of the treatment and the effects it has on the immune system.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of subjects desensitized to peanut protein</measure>
    <time_frame>after 52 weeks of therapy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Desensitization is defined as a subject who can consume a cumulative dose of peanut protein equal to or greater than 5044 mg or at least a 10-fold increase, when compared to the dose received at the baseline oral food challenge (OFC).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of subjects desensitized to peanut protein</measure>
    <time_frame>after 30 months of therapy (week 130)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Desensitization is defined based on the starting OFC threshold as follows:
Those who successfully consumed (without dose-limiting symptoms) a cumulative dose of 0-44 mg of peanut protein at baseline must successfully consume a cumulative dose of at least 444 mg of peanut protein at the 30 month OFC;
Those who successfully consume a cumulative dose of greater than 44 mg to less than 444 mg of peanut protein at baseline must successfully consume at least a 10-fold increase in peanut protein at the 30 month OFC;
Those who successfully consume a cumulative dose of ≥444 mg of peanut protein at baseline must successfully consume at least 5,044 mg of peanut protein at the 30 month OFC.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of subjects who can successfully consume two different cumulative doses of peanut protein without dose-limiting symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>after 30 months of therapy (week 130)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Dose levels of 1044 mg and 5044 mg of peanut protein.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of desensitized subjects by dose level</measure>
    <time_frame>after 52 weeks of therapy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Desensitization will be defined by sucessful OFCs for subjects on the higher-dose DBV712 Viaskin patch and those on the lower-dose DBV712 Viaskin patch.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of desensitized subjects as measured by successful 5044 mg peanut protein OFC.</measure>
    <time_frame>after 52 weeks of therapy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of all adverse events related to therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 30 months of therapy (week 130)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of adverse events in subjects receiving the higher-dose DBV712 Viaskin patch, compared to those in the placebo group</measure>
    <time_frame>after 30 months of therapy (week 130)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of adverse events in subjects receiving the lower-dose DBV712 Viaskin patch doses compared to the placebo group</measure>
    <time_frame>after 30 months of therapy (week 130)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects who pass an OFC to 5044 mg of peanut protein</measure>
    <time_frame>after 8 weeks and 20 weeks of discontinuation of dosing</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Peanut Hypersensitivity</condition>
  <condition>Food Hypersensitivity</condition>
  <condition>Hypersensitivity</condition>
  <condition>Hypersensitivity, Immediate</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High-dose DBV712 Viaskin Patch</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Active subjects who fail the 5044 mg peanut protein OFC at 52 weeks and those who fail the off-therapy OFC at 60 or 72 weeks, will continue on active treatment dosing through 30 months (130 weeks). At the end of study, all subjects on active therapy will undergo a 5044 mg peanut protein OFC on treatment; those who pass the 5044 mg peanut protein OFC will discontinue treatment for 8 weeks and then an additional 12 weeks, for a total of 20 weeks, to assess for sustained unresponsiveness. Subjects demonstrating sustained unresponsiveness will have follow up for 6 months. Active subjects who fail the 5044 mg peanut protein OFC at the following time points: 130 weeks, 138 weeks or at 150 weeks will be given dietary advice and will have follow-up for 3 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low-dose DBV712 Viaskin Patch</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Active subjects who fail the 5044 mg peanut protein OFC at 52 weeks and those who fail the off-therapy OFC at 60 or 72 weeks, will continue on active treatment dosing through 30 months (130 weeks). At the end of study, all subjects on active therapy will undergo a 5044 mg peanut protein OFC on treatment; those who pass the 5044 mg peanut protein OFC will discontinue treatment for 8 weeks and 20 weeks, to assess for sustained unresponsiveness. These subjects will be discontinued from further study therapy and will have follow up for 6 months.   Active subjects who fail the 5044 mg peanut protein OFC at the following time points: 130 weeks, 138 weeks or at 150 weeks will be given dietary advice and will have follow-up for 3 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Viaskin Patch</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo-treated subjects who do not pass the 5044 mg peanut protein OFC at week 52 will cross-over to active treatment at a dose of 250 mcg for a total of 30 months (130 weeks) of active therapy. Placebo subjects who pass the week 52, 5044 mg peanut protein OFC will have an open feeding of 2 tablespoons of peanut butter and if passed, will be instructed to add peanut to their diet. These subjects will be discontinued from further study therapy and will have follow up for 6 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>250 microgram (mcg) DBV712 Viaskin Patch</intervention_name>
    <description>250mcg dose of peanut proteins in an epicutaneous application for 24 hours every 24 hours</description>
    <arm_group_label>High-dose DBV712 Viaskin Patch</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>100 microgram DBV712 Viaskin Patch</intervention_name>
    <description>100 mcg dose of peanut proteins in an epicutaneous application for 24 hours every 24 hours</description>
    <arm_group_label>Low-dose DBV712 Viaskin Patch</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Viaskin Patch</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Viaskin Patch</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Physician-diagnosed peanut allergy OR convincing history of peanut allergy.

          -  A skin prick test positive to peanut (wheal diameter ≥3mm greater than the saline
             control) OR detectable peanut specific Immunoglobulin E (IgE) (ImmunoCAP &gt;0.35 kUA/L)

          -  Positive reaction to a cumulative dose of ≤1044 mg peanut protein in the initial
             qualifying Oral Food Challenge (OFC)

          -  Use of an effective method of contraception by females of childbearing potential to
             prevent pregnancy and agree to continue to practice an acceptable method of
             contraception for the duration of their participation in the study

          -  Ability to perform spirometry maneuvers in accordance with the American Thoracic
             Society (ATS) guidelines (1994). Children ages 4-11 years who have documented
             inability to adequately perform spirometry may be enrolled if Peak Expiratory Flow
             (PEF) is &gt;80% of predicted

          -  Provide signed informed consent or assent where indicated

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of anaphylaxis to peanut resulting in hypotension, neurological compromise or
             requiring mechanical ventilation

          -  Participation in a study using an investigational new drug in the last 30 days

          -  Participation in any interventional study for the treatment of food allergy in the
             past 6 months

          -  Pregnancy or lactation

          -  Current or known allergy to the Viaskin Peanut/Placebo patch device or excipients

          -  Current or known allergy to the placebo allergen (oat flour)

          -  Currently in a build-up phase of any allergen immunotherapy

          -  Severe or poorly controlled atopic dermatitis or greater than a mild flare of active
             disease at enrollment

          -  Forced Expiratory Volume in 1 Second (FEV1) value &lt;80% predicted or any clinical
             features of moderate or severe persistent asthma baseline severity (as defined by the
             2007 NHLBI Guidelines) and greater than high daily doses of inhaled corticosteroids
             (&gt;500mcg of Fluticasone or equivalent)

          -  Use of steroid medications in the following manners: history of daily oral steroid
             dosing for &gt;1 month during the past year, or burst or steroid course in the past 3
             months, or &gt;1 burst oral steroid course in the past year or use of oral or parenteral
             steroids for a non-asthma indication within the past 30 days

          -  Asthma requiring &gt;1 hospitalization in the past year for asthma or &gt;1 ED visit in the
             past 6 months for asthma

          -  Any previous intubation/mechanical ventilation due to allergies or asthma

          -  Use of omalizumab or other non-traditional forms of allergen immunotherapy or
             immunomodulatory or biologic therapy in the past year

          -  Use of beta-adrenergic blockers, angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors,
             angiotensin-receptor blockers, or calcium channel blockers in the past 30 days

          -  Inability to discontinue antihistamines for skin testing and OFC

          -  History of alcohol or drug abuse

          -  History of cardiovascular disease, uncontrolled hypertension, arrhythmias, chronic
             lung disease, active eosinophilic gastrointestinal disease, or other medical
             conditions including immunologic disorders or HIV infection which, in the opinion of
             the investigator, make the subject unsuitable for treatment or at increased risk of
             anaphylaxis or poor outcome
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>25 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hugh Sampson, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Arkansas Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Denise Pearson, RN</last_name>
      <phone>501-364-2960</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stacie Jones, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Jewish Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80206</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Susan Leung, RN</last_name>
      <phone>303-398-1549</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Donald Leung, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Johns Hopkins University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Melissa Paterakis, RN</last_name>
      <phone>410-502-1711</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert A Wood, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jessica Gau, RN</last_name>
      <phone>212-241-2000</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Scott Sicherer, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lauren Herlihy, RN, MSN</last_name>
      <phone>919-962-4406</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>A. Wesley Burks, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 22, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 15, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Peanut Allergy</keyword>
  <keyword>Food Allergy</keyword>
  <keyword>Viaskin peanut patch</keyword>
  <keyword>Allergen Immunotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Epicutaneous Immunotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Whole peanut extract</keyword>
  <keyword>Allergenic product</keyword>
  <keyword>Immediate hypersensitivity</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Food Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypersensitivity, Immediate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peanut Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
