<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="67162">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01943539</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Akili-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01943539</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cognitive ADHD Videogame Exploratory Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>CAVES</acronym>
  <official_title>A Study to Assess the Feasibility of EVO Gameplay to Engage Children With Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) and to Evaluate Cognitive Interference in Children Ages 8 to 12 Years Old With ADHD Compared to Neuro-typical Children</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Akili Interactive Labs, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Akili Interactive Labs, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A study in ADHD and neuro-typical children to assess EVO game play over 29 days.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A study in children ages 8 to 12 to assess EVO cognitive game play. The study examines two
      populations, children diagnosed with ADHD (ADHD and not on medication) and neuro-typical
      children.  The investigators plan to evaluate 80 subjects (N = 40 per group) in three site
      locations over a 29 day study period. The 29 day study period includes 2 in-clinic sessions
      and 27 days of out-patient game play.  During the 27 days of out-patient game play, the
      subjects will be instructed to play EVO 5 days per week for typically 30 minutes per day

      The investigators' hypothesis is that EVO will be playable and interesting to ADHD children
      and cognitive measures, as captured by EVO, will show a difference between ADHD children and
      age-matched neuro-typical children.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Demonstrate a difference in EVO cognitive measures between neuro-typicals and ADHD subjects</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>As a primary end-point, the study will aim to show a difference in cognitive measures between neuro-typicals and ADHD subjects.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate EVO safety</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 through Day 28 of the study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Another objective of this study is to evaluate the safety of EVO game play based on treatment-emergent adverse events (TEAEs) that may occur during this 29 day period of time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EVO game play feasibility</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Demonstrate the ability of ADHD and neuro-typical children to complete EVO in-clinic diagnostic assessment (DAY 0). Demonstrate compliance (measure behavioral play patterns) of ADHD and neuro-typical children during out-patient EVO game training period (DAY 1-27). Demonstrate the ability of ADHD and neuro-typical children to complete in-clinic EVO diagnostic assessment (DAY 28).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Exploratory objective to evaluate improvements in cognitive function</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>An exploratory objective of this study is to investigate any improvements in cognitive function, as measured by EVO and standard cognitive assessments, that result from the 27 days of game training</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EVO Game Play</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Neuro-typical controls and ADHD will receive EVO game play.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neuro-typical controls and ADHD will receive EVO game play.</intervention_name>
    <description>EVO mobile video application</description>
    <arm_group_label>EVO Game Play</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 8 to 12 at the time of parental informed consent.

          2. Confirmed ADHD diagnosis at clinic per MINI-Kid (ADHD Cohort)

          3. Baseline ADHD-RS-IV score &gt;= 24 (ADHD Cohort), obtained at clinic

          4. Baseline ADHD-RS-IV score &lt;=13 (Neuro-typical Cohort), obtained at clinic

          5. Consistently off ADHD drug for 1 week.  Drugs include: Pre specified, oral
             psychostimulants (ADDERALL XR® [mixed salts of a single-entity amphetamine product],
             VYVANSE® [lisdexamfetamine dimesylate], CONCERTA® [methylphenidate HCl], FOCALIN XR®
             [dexmethylphenidate HCl], RITALIN LA® [methylphenidate HCl extended-release],
             METADATE CD® [methylphenidate HCl, USP], or FDA-approved generic equivalents )for 1
             month (Other than ADHD drud

          6. Consistently off Psychotropic drug for 1 month (Other than ADHD drug noted above)

          7. Ability to follow written and verbal instructions (English)

          8. Girls or Boys (Gender-matched - 30% girls minimum)

          9. Functioning at an age-appropriate level intellectually.

         10. Ability to comply with all the testing and requirements.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Current, controlled (requiring a restricted medication) or uncontrolled, comorbid
             psychiatric diagnosis with significant symptoms such as post-traumatic stress
             disorder, psychosis, bipolar illness, pervasive developmental disorder, severe
             obsessive compulsive disorder, severe depressive or severe anxiety disorder, conduct
             disorder, or other symptomatic manifestations that in the opinion of the Investigator
             that may confound study data/assessments (per MINI-Kid).

          2. Within the last 4 weeks, subject has entered or exited behavioral therapy.  The
             subject should inform the Investigator if they intend to change their behavioral
             therapy during the 4 weeks of the study.

          3. Subject is currently considered a suicide risk in the opinion of the Investigator,
             has previously made a suicide attempt, or has a prior history of, or is currently
             demonstrating active suicidal ideation or self-injurious behavior (per C-SSRS).

          4. History of failure to respond to an adequate trial of 2 treatments for ADHD
             (consisting of an appropriate dose and adequate duration of therapy and failure in
             efficacy in the opinion of the Investigator).

          5. Motor condition that prevents game playing

          6. Recent history (within the past 6 months) of suspected substance abuse or dependence.

          7. History of seizures (exclusive of febrile seizures), a tic disorder, significant
             tics, or a current diagnosis of Tourette's Disorder.

          8. Taken part in a clinical trial within 30 days prior to screening.

          9. Diagnosis of color blindness

         10. Regular use of psychoactive drugs that in the opinion of the Investigator may
             confound study data/assessments.

         11. Any other medical condition that in the opinion of the Investigator may confound
             study data/assessments.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrew J Cutler, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Florida Clinical Research Center, LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Scott C Kellogg, MS</last_name>
    <phone>617-456-0984</phone>
    <email>skellogg@akiliinteractive.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Florida Clinical Research Center, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bradenton</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32401</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andrew J Cutler, MD</last_name>
      <phone>941-747-7900</phone>
      <email>acutler@flcrc.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrew J Cutler, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joanne L Northcutt, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Scott H Kollins, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>919-681-0014</phone>
      <email>scott.kollins@duke.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Scottt H Kollins, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 12, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 5, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Attention Deficit Disorder with Hyperactivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperkinesis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
