<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="36951">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02081521</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>QA511</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02081521</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of a Multiple Behaviour Programme for Diarrhoea Management</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of a Multiple Behaviour Programme to Prevent and Manage Diarrhoea Among Children Under-five in Lusaka, Zambia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centre for Infectious Disease Research in Zambia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Absolute Return for Kids</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Zambia: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Control of diarrhoeal disease requires a comprehensive package of preventive and curative
      interventions. in Zambia, the Programme for Awareness and Elimination of Diarrhoea (PAED)
      aims to reduce child deaths by combating diarrhoea in Lusaka province, Zambia. The behaviour
      change component of the PAED programme seeks to change behaviours important for diarrhoea
      prevention (handwashing with soap and exclusive breastfeeding) and improved treatment
      outcomes (use of oral rehydration solution (ORS) and zinc in home management of child
      diarrhoea).

      The study aims to evaluate the feasibility of implementing a multiple behaviour change
      community programme to tackle diarrhoeal disease in children under-five and to assess the
      impact of this programme on practice of the target behaviours by caregivers of children
      under-five. The research questions will be answered through a a two-arm cluster-randomised
      trial (eight clusters per study arm).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Specific objectives of the study are as follows:

        -  Evaluate the effect of the programme on ORS and zinc uptake and usage, exclusive
           breastfeeding and handwashing with soap (primary objective)

        -  Determine the extent to which the programme has positively influenced key mediating
           factors that determine behaviour (i.e. social norms, physical infrastructure,
           attitudes, and disease and treatment perceptions)

        -  Investigate which components of the community programme (i.e. specific activities in
           clinics, community events etc.) are linked to the success of the programme (most
           acceptable, feasible etc) and in what context

           o Validate model of intervention theory that explains how the context and mechanisms of
           the intervention interact to produce behavioural outcomes

        -  Determine which target populations are more likely to uptake the desired behaviours and
           identify the supporting factors that might explain this

        -  Conduct process evaluation to assess i) if the programme has been implemented as
           intended, ii) if the desired levels of reach and coverage have been achieved, iii)
           costs of implementation, iv) the extent to which changes in behaviour are likely to be
           due to the intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in target behaviours: ORS and zinc usage</measure>
    <time_frame>six weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of under-five diarrhoeal episodes receiving ORS and zinc. The study aims to demonstrate the intervention can successfully change behaviour and therefore no health outcomes were chosen.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in target behaviours: handwashing with soap</measure>
    <time_frame>six weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of caregivers of children under-five practicing handwashing with soap at critical times (critical = after toilet use and before eating).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in target behaviours: exclusive breastfeeding</measure>
    <time_frame>six weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in median duration of breastfeeding.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">640</enrollment>
  <condition>Diarrhoeal Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Community behaviour change campaign</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be exposed to the community behaviour change intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No community behaviour change campaign</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No community intervention will take place in the control arm, although exposure to some intervention messaging (radio adverts) may take place.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Community behaviour change campaign</intervention_name>
    <description>Community campaign targeting exclusive breastfeeding, handwashing with soap, and use of ORS and zinc to manage child diarrhoea. Includes a range of activities within the community (large events and small group sessions); clinic activities (ORS preparation), radio adverts.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Community behaviour change campaign</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  caregiver with child under six months (for assessment of handwashing and exclusive
             breastfeeding outcomes - healthy volunteers)

          -  caregiver with child under five years with current or recent (last 7 days) diarrhoea
             (for assessment of ORS and zinc outcomes)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not resident in study area
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Month</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>59 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Roma Chilengi</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centre for Infectious Disease Research in Zambia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre for Infectious Disease Research Zambia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lusaka</city>
        <state>Lusaka Province</state>
        <country>Zambia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Zambia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cidrz.org/diarrhoeal-disease-control/</url>
    <description>Background information on the PAED programme within which the community behaviour change programme sits</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 5, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>behaviour change</keyword>
  <keyword>diarrhoeal disease</keyword>
  <keyword>handwashing</keyword>
  <keyword>breastfeeding</keyword>
  <keyword>diarrhoea management</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diarrhea</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
