<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="88953">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01790152</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ALTE11C2</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>COG-ALTE11C2</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-03196</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U10CA095861</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>S0004187</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01790152</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Health Effects After Anthracycline and Radiation Therapy (HEART): Dexrazoxane and Prevention of Anthracycline-related Cardiomyopathy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Health Effects After Anthracycline and Radiation Therapy (HEART): Dexrazoxane and Prevention of Anthracycline-related Cardiomyopathy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Oncology Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Leukemia and Lymphoma Society</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>St. Baldrick's Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Oncology Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      We will determine echocardiographic and serum biomarkers of cardiac injury in a study of
      long-term pediatric T-cell leukemia and Hodgkin lymphoma survivors enrolled on 3 front-line
      Children's Oncology Group (COG) clinical trials (POG 9404, 9425, 9426) between 1996-2001
      with certain features. Our primary aim will be to determine whether patients randomized to
      the experimental dexrazoxane (DRZ) arms have decreased markers of myocardial injury compared
      with patients treated without dexrazoxane (DRZ). This will include a one-time measurement of
      an echocardiographic index of pathologic left ventricular (LV) remodeling (wall
      thickness-dimension ratio), complemented by serum biomarkers and a physical examination for
      signs and symptoms of cardiomyopathy/heart failure (CHF). We will also evaluate whether
      DRZ's cardioprotective effect is modified by anthracycline dose, chest radiation, and
      selected demographic factors (age at cancer diagnosis, current age, sex).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Given the critical role anthracyclines have in many effective cancer treatments and the risk
      for subsequent cardiotoxicity associated with this class of agents, development of an
      effective cardioprotective strategy is of great importance. Although adult studies have
      shown that dexrazoxane (DRZ) is effective in minimizing cardiomyopathy/heart failure (CHF)
      after anthracycline therapy, short and long-term data in children are much more limited.
      Furthermore, concerns regarding DRZ's interaction with cancer therapies and possible
      association with an increased risk of second cancers have limited its use among children
      despite possible protection against premature CHF. To address these gaps in knowledge, using
      a cross-sectional study design, we propose to ascertain echocardiographic and serum
      biomarkers of cardiac injury in a cohort of long-term pediatric T-cell leukemia and Hodgkin
      lymphoma survivors enrolled on 3 front-line Children's Oncology Group (COG) clinical trials
      (POG 9404, 9425, 9426) between 1996-2001 that featured upfront DRZ randomization and a range
      of anthracycline exposures commonly used in contemporary therapy (100-360 mg/m2
      doxorubicin). Our primary aim will be to determine whether patients randomized to the
      experimental DRZ arms have decreased markers of myocardial injury compared with patients
      treated without DRZ. Specifically, this will include a one-time measurement of an
      echocardiographic index of pathologic left ventricular (LV) remodeling (wall
      thickness-dimension ratio), complemented by serum biomarkers and a physical examination for
      signs and symptoms of CHF. We will also evaluate whether DRZ's cardioprotective effect is
      modified by anthracycline dose, chest radiation, and selected demographic factors (age at
      cancer diagnosis, current age, sex). In secondary analysis, we will also update the overall-
      and event-free survival rates between patients on the DRZ and non-DRZ arms. Finally, we will
      determine whether projected quality-adjusted life years differed by randomization status,
      accounting for premature cardiac disease, primary disease relapse, and second cancers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case Control, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Left ventricular (LV) thickness-to-dimension ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A decrease in echocardiographically derived measure of pathologic left ventricle (LV) remodeling which has been shown to be an important earlier surrogate measure of subsequent heart failure in both anthracycline-exposed pediatric cancer survivors5 and in the general pediatric and adult cardiomyopathy/heart failure population.  This ratio can be derived from standard measurements.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences in serum biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Particularly cardiac troponins and natriuretic peptides associated with acute changes following anthracycline exposure will be examined. Analyses involving markers of inflammation (hs-CRP, TNF, IL6) and more novel markers associated with heart failure in the general population (galectin-3, ST2, growth differentiation factor-15) are exploratory.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Based on self-report instruments will be factored into QALY estimates to answer the secondary aims.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Update primary disease relapse and second cancer rates</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Given additional elapsed time since last follow-up used in the prior published analyses,11-13 primary disease relapse and second cancer rates will be updated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">420</enrollment>
  <condition>T-cell Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Intermediate Hodgkins</condition>
  <condition>Advanced Hodgkins</condition>
  <condition>Early Hodgkins</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stratum 1 with diagnostic interventions</arm_group_label>
    <description>Required observations are designed to be collected at one visit:
Diagnostic/symptom checklist Anthropometry Echocardiogram Serum biomarkers Troponins (cTnT, cTnI) Natriuretic peptides (BNP, NT-ProBNP) Inflammation (hs-CRP, IL-6, TNF, Galectin-3, ST2, GDF15) Fasting glucose, lipid profile, insulin, hemoglobin AIC DNA 6 minute walk test Participant Questionnaires: Quality of life, family history, physical activity, and smoking Fasting for at least 10 hours prior to the study blood draw.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stratum 2 Relapse and subsequent malignancy status</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients not eligible for Stratum 1 may still contribute data to the Secondary Aims:
Relapse and subsequent malignancy status</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Diagnostic/symptom checklist</intervention_name>
    <description>The local PI or their designee (e.g. clinician, research nurse, or clinical research associate) will be asked to complete a diagnostic and symptom checklist (see Forms Packet on COG website) related to study outcomes. A copy of the participant's most recent clinic note and current medication list also are requested.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stratum 1 with diagnostic interventions</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anthropometry</intervention_name>
    <description>Easily determined in-office physical exam parameters requested include:
Height
Weight
Waist circumference
Blood pressure (BP)
Heart rate</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stratum 1 with diagnostic interventions</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Echocardiogram</intervention_name>
    <description>Study participants will undergo a one-time standard 2D, M-mode, and Doppler echocardiogram per AHA/ACC task force practice guidelines at participating institutions (or their adult affiliates depending on patient age and institutional practice).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stratum 1 with diagnostic interventions</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Serum Biomarkers</intervention_name>
    <description>All participants will have the following analytes collected under standardized conditions and processed centrally.
Cardiac troponins have been associated with acute anthracycline-related cardiotoxicity, and newer high-sensitivity cTnT and cTnI assays may be predictive of late-occurring LV dysfunction. Natriuretic peptides (BNP, NT-ProBNP) are produced in response to myocardial wall stress and are used to monitor CHF progression. Levels, if persistently elevated, correlate well with echocardiographic indices of myocardial dysfunction. In exploratory analyses, we will also examine the effects of selected inflammatory biomarkers.
Fasting lipid profile (total cholesterol, HDL, LDL, triglyceride), glucose, insulin, and hemoglobin AIC)
Provide optional consent to have DNA banked for future research related to analysis of possible genetic polymorphisms associated with differential risk of cardiomyopathy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stratum 1 with diagnostic interventions</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>6 minute walk test (6MWT)</intervention_name>
    <description>Ambulatory participants will be asked to undergo this simple test of functional exercise capacity. Contraindications include: 1.) history of angina or myocardial infarction within the past month, 2.) resting heart rate &gt;120 bpm, 3.) systolic blood pressure &gt;180 mmHg or diastolic blood pressure &gt;100 mmHg. Any other reason for patient inability to perform this test should be documented in the respective Report Form.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stratum 1 with diagnostic interventions</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Participant Questionnaires (ages ≥14 years only)</intervention_name>
    <description>The time to complete questionnaires is estimated less than 45 minutes.  General health status and quality of life will be assessed using the Short-Form-36. Participants also will be administered the Minnesota Living with Heart Failure questionnaire.  Questionnaires will ascertain family history of cardiovascular and related diseases (e.g. diabetes).  Physical activity will be assessed using questions from the Centers for Disease Control &amp; Prevention's (CDC) Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System exercise &amp; physical activity modules.  Smoking history (current &amp; lifetime) will be assessed using questions from Health and Nutritional Examination surveys.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stratum 1 with diagnostic interventions</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      serum
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Long-term pediatric T-cell leukemia and Hodgkin lymphoma survivors enrolled on 3
        front-line Children's Oncology Group (COG) clinical trials (POG 9404, 9425, 9426) between
        1996-2001 that featured upfront DRZ randomization and a range of anthracycline exposures
        commonly used in contemporary therapy (100-360 mg/m2 doxorubicin).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Previously enrolled and randomized on POG 9404, 9425, or 9426

          -  Alive and in continuous first complete remission from their original cancer (T-cell
             leukemia/lymphoma [POG 9404] or Hodgkin lymphoma [POG 9425/9426])

          -  Not have been diagnosed with any subsequent malignancy, with the exception of
             non-melanomatous skin cancer(s). Patients with history of only subsequent
             non-melanomatous skin cancers remain eligible.

          -  All patients and/or their parents or legal guardians must sign a written informed
             consent (see Stratum 1 sample consent).

          -  Among patients who have relapsed or have experienced a subsequent malignancy other
             than non-melanomatous skin cancer since their original diagnosis, the study committee
             will review the available data (both from COG's Statistics and Data Center (SDC) and
             the participating institution) to determine if individual patients are to be selected
             for secondary aim arm only. The study will petition the IRB specifically for a waiver
             of consent to include any relapse and subsequent cancer data obtained from existing
             records for analysis of the secondary aims. Patients selected for Stratum 2 will be
             those for whom late relapse or subsequent cancer is reported but who lack clear
             confirmation in existing records (either at SDC or at the local institution).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eric J Chow, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eric J Chow, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>206-667-4630</phone>
    <email>heart@fhcrc.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Oncology Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Arcadia</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91006-3776</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eric J. Chow</last_name>
      <phone>206-667-7724</phone>
      <email>ericchow@u.washington.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eric J. Chow</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Children's Hospital of Southwest Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Myers</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33908</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Emad K. Salman</last_name>
      <phone>239-343-5333</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Emad K. Salman</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>All Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Petersburg</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33701</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gregory A. Hale</last_name>
      <phone>727-767-2423</phone>
      <email>HamblinF@allkids.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gregory A. Hale</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Saint Mary's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Palm Beach</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33407</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Narayana Gowda</last_name>
      <phone>888-823-5923</phone>
      <email>ctsucontact@westat.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Narayana Gowda</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Saint Jude Midwest Affiliate</name>
      <address>
        <city>Peoria</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>61602</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pedro A. De Alarcon</last_name>
      <phone>309-655-3258</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pedro A. De Alarcon</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287-8936</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kenneth J. Cohen</last_name>
      <phone>410-955-8804</phone>
      <email>jhcccro@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kenneth J. Cohen</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wayne State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Zhihong J. Wang</last_name>
      <phone>313-576-9363</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Zhihong J. Wang</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia Regional</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbia</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>65201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thomas W. Loew</last_name>
      <phone>573-882-7440</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Thomas W. Loew</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Rochester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jeffrey R. Andolina</last_name>
      <phone>585-275-5830</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jeffrey R. Andolina</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mission Hospitals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Asheville</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28801</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Krystal S. Bottom</last_name>
      <phone>828-213-4150</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Krystal S. Bottom</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Medical Center of Akron</name>
      <address>
        <city>Akron</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44308</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven J. Kuerbitz</last_name>
      <phone>330-543-3193</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steven J. Kuerbitz</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical City Dallas Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75230</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carl Lenarsky</last_name>
      <phone>972-566-5588</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carl Lenarsky</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karen R. Rabin</last_name>
      <phone>713-798-1354</phone>
      <email>burton@bcm.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karen R. Rabin</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas Health Science Center at San Antonio</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229-3900</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anne-Marie R. Langevin</last_name>
      <phone>210-567-0653</phone>
      <email>che@uthscsa.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anne-Marie R. Langevin</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 13, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 11, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>T-Cell Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Hodgkins</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor T-Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
