<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="70315">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01664741</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01 DA026823</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01664741</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nicotine Dependence, Withdrawal and Replacement Therapy Assessed by PET Imaging</brief_title>
  <official_title>Nicotine Dependence, Withdrawal and Replacement Therapy Assessed by PET Imaging</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Data and Safety Monitoring Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed research will provide significant new gender-specific information of scientific
      and clinical relevance on the function of the mu-opioid system in nicotine dependence and
      therapeutic effectiveness of nicotine replacement therapy (NRT). The studies will help to
      explain the differences in the prevalence of smoking in men and women, sex-specific
      differences in nicotine craving and withdrawal as well as the poorer therapeutic response to
      NRT. This work may pave the way to the design of improved pharmacotherapies that can more
      effectively target the endogenous opioid system in the treatment of nicotine dependence.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      While smoking prevalence has declined for both men and women over the last two decades,
      rates among women have shown a much shallower decrease and, in recent years, prevalence of
      cigarette initiation has been higher for girls than boys. Smoking among women of
      child-bearing age has significant negative health consequences for mother and child,
      increasing fetal and infant morbidity and mortality. Women are both less likely to initiate
      a quit attempt and more likely to relapse if they do quit. Nicotine replacement therapy
      (NRT), still the most widely used smoking treatment intervention in the United States, is
      less effective for women compared with men, and women report less craving reduction on NRT.
      The endogenous opioid system is involved in smoking initiation, nicotine craving and reward
      as well as nicotine withdrawal symptoms. Interestingly, research suggests that sexual
      dimorphic features of the endogenous mu-opioid system may in part explain gender differences
      in nicotine effects. To better understand the role of the mu-opioid system in poorer NRT
      responses in women, this proposal will examine NRT effects on mu opioid receptor binding
      potential (MOR BP) in female compared to male smokers during active versus placebo NRT.
      Specifically, nicotine dependent women and men in active smoking status will undergo PET
      imaging for MOR BP measurement using 11C-carfentanil. Following baseline PET measurement in
      active smoking (scan 1), smokers will be randomized to active or placebo nicotine
      replacement therapy ((A-NRT or P-NRT); 72 hours later, a second scan will be obtained. As a
      reference group, demographically-matched women and men who have never smoked will undergo
      two scans as well. Behavioral measurements of nicotine reward, craving and withdrawal will
      be obtained repeatedly across the protocol. The proposed research will provide significant
      new, gender-specific information of scientific and clinical relevance on the function of the
      mu-opioid system in nicotine dependence and therapeutic effectiveness of nicotine
      replacement therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacodynamics Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mu-opioid receptor binding potential</measure>
    <time_frame>90 minutes</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>BP provides an estimate of the product of the density of available receptors (Bmax' or the receptor density Bmax less those occupied by endogenous transmitters) and the affinity (1/KD). Based on Zhou (2003), we use reference tissue graphical analysis (RTGA) (Schmitz, 2001) to obtain regional BP values using occipital lobe as a reference region (Schad, 2002).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nicotine craving</measure>
    <time_frame>72 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Tiffany Questionnaire of Smoking Urges (QSU-brief)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nicotine withdrawal</measure>
    <time_frame>72 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Minnesota Nicotine Withdrawal Scale (MNWS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Nicotine Dependence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nicotine patch - transdermal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>21 mg nicotine patch</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo NRT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Matching placebo patch</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy non-smoker comparison</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Demographically-matched women and men who have never smoked</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nicotine patch - transdermal</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Nicotine patch - transdermal</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Habitrol, Nicoderm, Nicoderm CQ, Nicotrol, Nicotine replacement therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo NRT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  21 - 60 years old

          -  must meet DSM-IV criteria for nicotine dependence and be smoking 15 - 40
             cigarettes/day

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  BMI &lt; 18 or &gt; 30

          -  DSM-IV criteria for a current or lifetime alcohol or drug use disorder; drug use in
             the last 90 days as determined by the TLFB; current alcohol consumption &gt; 14
             drinks/week; positive urine toxicology screen at initial assessment or before study
             procedures;

          -  DSM-IV criteria for current depressive, anxiety or adjustment disorder and currently
             in need of or on psychotropic medications; we will not exclude subjects with a
             history of these disorders given the very high comorbidity of smoking and these
             psychiatric disorders.

          -  DSM-IV criteria for Axis I psychotic disorder - lifetime (e.g., schizophrenia,
             bipolar disorder)

          -  Presence of any serious medical condition; or have liver function tests more than 3 X
             normal;

          -  History of any central nervous system disorder;

          -  Abnormal MRI scan or history of significant closed head trauma;

          -  Treatment with antidepressants, neuroleptics, sedative hypnotics, glucocorticoids,
             opiates within the last six months

          -  Pregnancy, lactation, oral contraceptives or postmenopausal.

          -  At least 5th grade reading level based on Shipley
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mary E McCaul, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>JoAnna Mathena, MA</last_name>
    <phone>410-955-9524</phone>
    <email>jmathen5@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mary E McCaul, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 13, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 10, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mary E. McCaul</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Nicotine dependence</keyword>
  <keyword>cigarette</keyword>
  <keyword>smoking</keyword>
  <keyword>nicotine replacement therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>positron emission tomography</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Tobacco Use Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Nicotine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nicotine polacrilex</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
