<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="70710">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02150941</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pending</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02150941</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness Study of the BioVac Direct Suction Device in Upper Gastrointestinal Bleeding</brief_title>
  <official_title>Does the BioVac Direct Suction Device Increase Identification of the Bleeding Source in Upper Gastrointestinal Bleeding: a Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lawson Health Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Lawson Health Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Research Ethics Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Upper endoscopy is performed for upper gastrointestinal bleeding (bleeding in the esophagus,
      stomach, or part of the duodenum) to identify and potentially treat the cause of bleeding.
      However, blood clots often make visualization difficult during endoscopy.  The current
      practice is to try to wash off and suction up these blood clots with the endoscope.
      However, this is often not successful due to blood clots blocking the suction channel.

      A new device has been approved by Health Canada that attaches to the endoscope and helps
      prevent blockage.  It is believed that this device will help doctors suck out blood clots
      and potentially improve visualization, identification of the cause of bleeding, and possibly
      health outcomes, although this has never been proven.  The purpose of the investigators
      clinical trial is to test whether this device works and whether it can help patients with
      UGIB.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      STUDY DESIGN:

      This is a randomized clinical trial of BioVac direct suction device compared to standard
      endoscopy suction for UGIB.  The study will be performed at London Health Sciences Center
      Victoria Campus and University Campus with an anticipated recruitment period of three years.
       Approval from the Western University Research Ethics Board will be obtained prior to
      patient recruitment and the trial will be registered with the United States National
      Institute of Health website (www.clinicaltrials.gov).

      STUDY POPULATION:

      All patients over the age of 18 admitted to hospital with a diagnosis of UGIB will be
      considered for recruitment.  Patients already admitted to hospital with another diagnosis
      who develop UGIB will also be included.

      INTERVENTION:

      Patients with UGIB will undergo upper endoscopy as deemed clinically indicated by their
      treating physician.  If the source of bleeding is found within the first 5 minutes (timer to
      be started once the gastroscope is inserted past the upper esophageal sphincter) or there is
      no blood in the upper GI tract, the patient will be excluded from the study as additional
      suctioning will provide no benefit.

      If the source of bleeding is not found within the first 5 minutes due to blood clots, the
      patient may benefit from additional suctioning.  The patient will be randomized in random
      blocks of between 2-6 stratified by site (University Campus and Victoria Campus) to either
      BioVac device or standard endoscopy practice.  Stratification by site is necessary to
      control for different endoscopist practice patterns at each site.  Those randomized to
      BioVac device will insert the device through the gastroscope and suction as much blood as
      possible to identify the bleeding lesion.  Those randomized to standard endoscopy suction
      will use the gastroscope suction instead.  Due to the suctioning power of the study device,
      a sham device is not possible since even an identical appearing placebo device would be
      recognizable due to its lack of suction.  To address this, only objective outcomes not
      subject to operator bias were selected.  In addition, the outcomes assessor and patient will
      be blinded.  Otherwise, the endoscopy will be performed at the discretion of the
      endoscopist.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Identification of the cause of bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>Once at the time of endoscopy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visualization score</measure>
    <time_frame>Once at the time of endoscopy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A visualization score will be used as follows:
Score of 0 - 4 per location (0 = &lt;25%, 1 = 25-50%, 2 = 51-75%, 3 = 76 - 95%, 4 = &gt;95%) Scored for the following locations: esophagus, fundus, body, antrum, duodenal bulb, second part of the duodenum</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Application of any endoscopic therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Once at the time of endoscopy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Treated as a dichotomous outcome (yes, no). Endoscopic therapy include injection, electrocautery, hemostatic clip, variceal banding, or Hemospray</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rebleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured once at 7 days after endoscopy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Rebleeding is defined to have occurred for any of the following: vomiting of fresh blood, shock (systolic blood pressure &lt; 90 mm Hg or heart rate &gt; 110 beats per minute) with melena after stabilization, or a drop in hemoglobin of &gt; 20 g/L within 24 hours after a transfusion to a level &gt; 70 g/L</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Transfusion requirement</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured once at 7 days after endoscopy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Total number of units of blood transfused 7 days after endoscopy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured once at 30 days after endoscopy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Need for repeat EGD within 7 days</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured once at 7 days after endoscopy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Need for interventional radiology, surgery, or TIPS</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured once at 30 days after endoscopy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>30 day mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured once at 30 days after endoscopy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Procedure related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured once 48 hours after endoscopy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Adverse events related to the EGD will be noted, including intraprocedural hypotension, oxygen desaturation, aspiration, and perforation.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">133</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastrointestinal Hemorrhage</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BioVac Direct Suction Device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Endoscopy Suction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BioVac Direct Suction Device</intervention_name>
    <description>The BioVac Direct Suction Device (US Endoscopy) is an endoscopic device that enhances the suction power of the gastroscope.</description>
    <arm_group_label>BioVac Direct Suction Device</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Endoscopy Suction</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard Endoscopy Suction refers to the suction provided on the gastroscope (Olympus EVIS EXERA II)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Endoscopy Suction</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients presenting with fresh blood hematemesis, coffee ground emesis, or melena

          2. Patients with hematochezia and hypotension (systolic blood pressure &lt; 90 mm Hg) or
             tachycardia (heart rate &gt; 100 beats per minute)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Age &lt; 18

          2. No endoscopy was performed.

          3. Endoscopy previously performed for current episode of UGIB either at LHSC or at an
             outside hospital.

          4. Identification of a bleeding lesion within the first 5 minutes of the upper endoscopy
             or no blood noted in the upper GI tract as these patients would not benefit from
             additional suctioning.

          5. Patients who received gastric lavage or erythromycin prior to the procedure.

          6. Patients unable to consent and who do not have a substitute decision maker.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael SL Sey, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>London Health Sciences Centre-Victoria Campus, Western University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael SL Sey, MD</last_name>
    <phone>519-667-6582</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>London Health Sciences Center-Victoria Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N6A 5W9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael SL Sey, MD</last_name>
      <phone>519-667-6582</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 22, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Lawson Health Research Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael Sai Lai Sey, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Upper gastrointestinal tract</keyword>
  <keyword>Endoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>Endoscopic Hemostasis</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Gastrointestinal Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
