<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="60445">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01975935</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HUM00079381</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01975935</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy of Amlexanox vs. Placebo in Type 2 Diabetic Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Protocol to Investigate the Efficacy of Amlexanox vs. Placebo for Treatment of Glucose and Lipid Abnormalities in Obese Type 2 Diabetics</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study involves research about an investigational medicine called Amlexanox.  The reason
      for this study is to find out how Amlexanox can improve type 2 diabetes, insulin resistance,
      obesity and non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD).  In this study, Amlexanox is
      considered to be investigational (not approved by the Food and Drug Administration [FDA])
      for type 2 diabetes, insulin resistance, obesity and non-alcoholic fatty liver disease
      (NAFLD).  This is a placebo controlled study.  There is a 50-50 chance that the patient may
      either receive the study drug, Amlexanox, or a placebo (sugar pill).  Neither the patient or
      the study doctors will know if the patient is receiving the study drug or placebo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This proposal focuses on a clinical proof of concept study to evaluate a novel hypothesis.
      We propose that overnutrition, leading to obesity, represents a state of excessive energy
      storage promoted by insulin.  The stress of excessive energy storage initiates a set of
      homeostatic responses that includes the generation of adipose tissue and liver inflammation,
      which involves the secretion of proinflammatory cytokines that block energy storage in fat
      and liver by inducing insulin resistance, thus relieving stress on the adipocyte and
      hepatocyte.  However, our recent data suggest that inflammation itself is countered by a
      secondary feedback loop, which we have termed &quot;counter-inflammation&quot;.  We propose that this
      process keeps inflammation in check, ensuring that it is maintained at low levels.  At the
      same time counter-inflammation also promotes energy conservation via increased energy
      storage and decreased utilization in a manner that is insulin-independent.  We hypothesize
      that the noncanonical IkB kinases Ikke and TBK1 are &quot;counterinflammatory&quot; kinases that
      feedback inhibit inflammatory pathways while helping to support a positive energy balance.

      How can this hypothesis be addressed in human subjects?  A number of clinical trials have
      already been initiated with the intention of improving insulin resistance by attenuating
      inflammation.  Many of these have focused on the blockade of single cytokines or their
      receptors such as TNFa, IL1 and MCP1 (CCR2 antagonist).  While the record on these trials is
      mixed, the complexity of inflammatory pathways elicited during obesity suggests that
      inhibition of only a single cytokine is not likely to be sufficient.  Additionally, because
      numerous studies have implicated the NFkB pathway in obesity-induced inflammation, NFkB
      inhibitors have been contemplated. Salsalate was originally resuscitated due to its
      perceived activity to block NFkB and hence to block inflammation.  However, although
      clinical studies on this drug have been promising, precisely how salsalate works, what its
      target is, and whether it actually functions an NFkB inhibitor remains controversial (recent
      data indicate that it may act via activation of AMPK).

      We describe here a new potential therapeutic agent that is the result of an academic
      collaborative drug discovery effort carried out at the University of Michigan. Our studies
      on elucidating the role of NFkB in insulin resistance and macrophage activation led to the
      identification of Ikke and TBK1 as potential targets for therapeutic intervention in obesity
      and type 2 diabetes.  We performed a high throughput screen searching for inhibitors of
      these kinases, evaluating a group of 175,000 compounds that included a collection of
      approved drugs.  Interestingly, the most potent and specific inhibitor discovered was
      amlexanox; an older drug originally developed in Japan for the treatment of asthma and
      allergic rhinitis, and later in the US for aphthous ulcers, but without a well understood
      mechanism of action.  It has been in use since 1987, and has a favorable side effect
      profile.

      This protocol is the first proof of concept study to evaluate the possible repurposing of
      Amlexanox for the treatment of type 2 diabetes and obesity.  At the same time, we hope to
      test the hypothesis that IKKe and TBK1 may be important players in maintaining a positive
      energy balance, and also in supporting insulin resistance, during prolonged over-nutrition.
      Finally, these studies will also provide valuable insight into the validity of these two
      protein kinases as drug targets for the future development of new chemical entities useful
      in the treatment of type 2 diabetes. Therefore our specific aims are

        1. Does amlexanox treatment improve measures of type 2 diabetes, insulin resistance and
           obesity?  To address this question, we intend to treat patients with clinical Type 2
           diabetes and Grade 1/2 obesity (BMI 27 to 45 kg/m2) for a period of 3 months in a
           double-blinded placebo controlled proof-of concept study. We will enroll 40 patients
           without evidence of severe end-organ damage from chronic complications of Type 2
           diabetes who also are on metformin and/or DPPIV inhibitors or no medications, who also
           have clear-cut evidence of hyperglycemia (HbA1c&gt;6.5% and &lt;10.0%). These patients will
           be treated with either placebo or Amlexanox oral tablets at a starting dose of 25 mg PO
           tid for 2 weeks and then titrated up to a dose of 50 mg PO tid (doses used to treat
           asthma in humans and leading to serum concentrations comparable to metabolically
           effective doses in rodent studies) for the remainder of the therapy period. HbA1c is
           targeted as primary end-point in this study. Fasting lipid profiles, plasma insulin,
           HOMA-IR, clinical markers of inflammation and adipocytokine profiles will be measured
           as other parameters of interest at baseline, 6 weeks and 12 weeks. Insulin secretion as
           well as insulin sensitivity will be probed using a mixed meal test. Weight is also an
           important but secondary end-point in this study. We will determine resting energy
           expenditure with indirect calorimetry and total body composition using DEXA at baseline
           and 12 weeks. Safety monitoring with CBC, comprehensive metabolic biochemistry, CPK and
           urine analyses will be undertaken at 1, 2, 4, 6, and 12 weeks, and urinary albumin at
           baseline and 12 weeks. Measures of safety and efficacy will be repeated 4 weeks after
           the drug has been discontinued as well.

        2. Does amlexanox treatment improve measures of NAFLD in obese patients?  All participants
           in the clinical proof-of-concept study outlined in the aim above will be studied for
           the degree of steatosis in the liver with the use of MRI and MR spectroscopy at
           baseline and at 3 months of the study.

        3. Development of biomarkers for treatment of patients with type 2 diabetes by amlexanox.
           We will evaluate the phosphorylation of proteins known to be targets of IKKe and TBK1
           in blood, and adipose tissue samples.  We will use phospho-specific antibodies to
           evaluate the regulation of targets that play a role in energy metabolism, and also in
           feedback inhibition of NFkB.  These studies will pave the way for future evaluations
           probing the metabolic relevance of IKKe and TBK1 in humans using the same agent or more
           potent ones to be discovered or designed.

            
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HbA1c</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>improvement in HbA1c</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>hepatic steatosis by MRI</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>improvement in hepatic steatosis by MRI</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight</measure>
    <time_frame>12 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>weight decrease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus Type 2</condition>
  <condition>Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo tablet (TID) 2 weeks Placebo tablets (2 x TID) 10 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Amlexanox</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Solfa tablets (Amlexanox 25mg) TID for 2 weeks Solfa tablets (Amlexanox 25mg x 2) TID for 10 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Amlexanox</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Amlexanox</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Solfa tablets</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ≥ 18 years old at baseline.

          -  Is male, female not of childbearing potential, or meets all the following criteria if
             female of childbearing potential (including perimenopausal women who have had a
             menstrual period within one year):

               -  Not breastfeeding.

               -  Negative pregnancy test result (human chorionic gonadotropin, beta subunit
                  [βhCG]) at baseline (not applicable to hysterectomized females).

               -  Must practice and be willing to continue to practice appropriate birth control
                  (defined as a method which results in a low failure rate when use consistently
                  and correctly, such as implants, injectables, oral contraceptives, some
                  intrauterine contraceptive devices, sexual abstinence, tubal ligation, or a
                  vasectomized partner) during the entire duration of study period.

          -  Has physician-confirmed diabetes mellitus with a clear diagnosis or per ADA criteria
             with fasting glucose&gt;126 mg/dL or HbA1c &gt;6.4% or 2 hour GTT &gt;200 mg/dL.

          -  BMI ≥27 and &lt;45 kg/m2.

          -  On no medications or only on first line oral medications (such as Metformin and/or
             DPP IV inhibitors) for treatment of Type 2 diabetes mellitus with a stable regimen
             for &gt;12 weeks.

          -  Alcohol consumption of less than 40 grams/week.

          -  A liver US confirming presence of fatty infiltration of the liver.

          -  Is able to read, understand and sign the U of M IRBMED approved informed consent form
             (ICF), communicate with study physician and study team, understand and comply with
             protocol requirements.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  On insulin, or other injectables for treatment of Type 2 diabetes.

          -  Unable to conduct home based glucose monitoring.

          -  HbA1c  &lt;6.5% and &gt;10.0% (set to achieve uniformity in the study population).

          -  Presence of advanced liver disease (as evidenced by abnormal synthetic function,
             abnormal PT or albumin).

          -  Evidence of other etiologies of viral hepatitis.

          -  Presence of hematologic, bone marrow and/or other abnormalities.

          -  Presence of hemoglobinopathy or other hematological abnormalities that will interfere
             with accurate measurement of HbA1c.

          -  Presence of HIV infection.

          -  Inability to give informed consent.

          -  Presence of ESRD, any type of active cancer, or &gt;class 2 congestive heart failure
             ((New York Heart Association Functional Classification System), based on medical
             history and physical examination.

          -  Active chronic infection such as known chronic osteomyelitis or tb, etc. (may be
             transient).

          -  Creatinine &gt;1.5 mg/dL.

          -  Proliferative diabetic retinopathy, nonproliferative retinopathy is allowed.

          -  Unable to ambulate.

          -  Clinically relevant CAD: history of stent, CABG or cardiologist confirmed angina.

          -  Any other condition in the opinion of the investigators that may impede successful
             data collection.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Adam Neidert, MS</last_name>
      <phone>734-615-0539</phone>
      <email>aneidert@med.umich.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Elif Oral, MD</last_name>
      <phone>734-615-7271</phone>
      <email>eliforal@med.umich.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elif A Oral, MD, MS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nevin A Ajluni, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Evgenia Korytnaya, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alan Saltiel, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Thomas Chenevert, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 29, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 29, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Elif Oral</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor, Internal Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>diabetes mellitus type 2</keyword>
  <keyword>non-alcoholic fatt liver disease</keyword>
  <keyword>obesity</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fatty Liver</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Amlexanox</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
