<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="14817">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01713608</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MMV_OZ439_12_005</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-004187-22</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01713608</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Dose-escalation Study to Investigate Safety and Toleration of OZ439</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomised, Placebo-controlled, Dose-escalation Study to Investigate Safety and Toleration of OZ439 OD for 3 Days to Healthy Male and Female Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medicines for Malaria Venture</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medicines for Malaria Venture</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A randomised, placebo-controlled, dose-escalation study to investigate safety and toleration
      of OZ439 OD for 3 days to healthy male and female volunteers. The study aims:

        -  To determine the safety and tolerability of ascending doses of OZ439 OD for three days.

        -  To assess pharmacokinetic parameters of ascending doses of OZ439 given OD.

        -  To identify the maximum tolerated dose of OZ439 administered.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will be conducted in a randomised, placebo-controlled dose-escalation design with
      OZ439 OD administered with full fat milk for three days to healthy male and female subjects
      between 18 to 55 years of age, using features of an adaptive study design. The study is
      expected to have three cohorts with a total of 36 healthy male and female subjects.  An
      additional two cohorts may be used if required.  The results of this study will inform the
      maximum tolerated exposure of OZ439 following OD dosing for three days in subjects who are
      not fasted.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>• Maximum concentration (Cmax).</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood for analysis of OZ439  will be collected at the following times: pre-dose,  2, 4, 6, 8, 12, and 18  hours post-dose Day 1and Day 3, pre dose Day 2 and 4 hours post dose Day 2, and 24, 48, 72, 96 and 168 hours post 3rd dose and at follow up.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Maximum measured plasma concentration derived by non-compartmental analysis of the plasma concentration-time data</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>• Time to reach maximum plasma concentration (Tmax).</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-dose,  2, 4, 6, 8, 12, and 18  hours post-dose Day 1and Day 3, pre dose Day 2 and 4 hours post dose Day 2, and 24, 48, 72, 96 and 168 hours post 3rd dose and at follow up.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Time to reach maximum measured plasma concentration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• Area under the plasma concentration vs time curve from time zero to 24 hours post dose (AUCτ,).</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-dose,  2, 4, 6, 8, 12, and 18  hours post-dose Day 1and Day 3, pre dose Day 2 and 4 hours post dose Day 2, and 24, 48, 72, 96 and 168 hours post 3rd dose and at follow up.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Area under plasma concentration time curve from time 0 to the time of the last quantifiable concentration t calculated using a log-linear trapezoidal method</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• Area under the plasma concentration vs time curve from time zero to the time of the  last detectable drug  (AUC0-t).</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-dose,  2, 4, 6, 8, 12, and 18  hours post-dose Day 1and Day 3, pre dose Day 2 and 4 hours post dose Day 2, and 24, 48, 72, 96 and 168 hours post 3rd dose and at follow up.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Area under plasma concentration time curve from time 0 to the time of the last quantifiable concentration t calculated using a log-linear trapezoidal method</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from zero to infinity (AUC0-∞).</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-dose,  2, 4, 6, 8, 12, and 18  hours post-dose Day 1and Day 3, pre dose Day 2 and 4 hours post dose Day 2, and 24, 48, 72, 96 and 168 hours post 3rd dose and at follow up.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Area under plasma concentration time curve from time 0 extrapolated to infinity</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• Terminal half-life (t½).</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-dose,  2, 4, 6, 8, 12, and 18  hours post-dose Day 1and Day 3, pre dose Day 2 and 4 hours post dose Day 2, and 24, 48, 72, 96 and 168 hours post 3rd dose and at follow up.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• The terminal elimination rate constant</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-dose,  2, 4, 6, 8, 12, and 18  hours post-dose Day 1and Day 3, pre dose Day 2 and 4 hours post dose Day 2, and 24, 48, 72, 96 and 168 hours post 3rd dose and at follow up.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The apparent terminal elimination rate constant, determined by linear regression of terminal points of the ln-linear analyte concentration-time curve</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Safety assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-dose,  2, 4, 6, 8, 12, and 18  hours post-dose Day 1and Day 3, pre dose Day 2 and 4 hours post dose Day 2, and 24, 48, 72, 96 and 168 hours post 3rd dose and at follow up.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety assessments will include standard laboratory safety tests (haematology, biochemistry, and urinalysis), vital signs, physical examinations, 12-lead ECG, telemetry and AE monitoring.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">34</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>OZ439 Dose level 1 (300mg)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>•	Cohort 1 (12 subjects: 8 Active [A] and 4 on Placebo [P]) Active dose will consist of 300mg OZ439 drinking solution administered once daily for 3 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>OZ439 Dose level 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>•	Cohort 2 (12 subjects: 8 A, 4P).  Subjects on active will receive X amount of OZ439 (dose level to be determined based on safety and tolerability of previous dose level) drinking solution once daily for 3 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>OZ439 dose level 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 3 (12 subjects: 8 A, 4P).  Subjects on active will receive X amount of OZ439 (dose level to be determined based on safety and tolerability of previous dose level) drinking solution once daily for 3 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>OZ439</intervention_name>
    <description>OZ439 x mg once daily for 3 days with milk</description>
    <arm_group_label>OZ439 Dose level 1 (300mg)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>OZ439 Dose level 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>OZ439 dose level 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusions:

          1. healthy males or females of any race aged 18 - 55 years

          2. BMI of 18 - 30 kg/m2 inclusive at screening

          3. Agree to use acceptable methods of contraception if of childbearing potential

          4. Capable of understanding and complying with the requirements of the protocol and must
             have signed the informed consent form

          5. Females are either of child bearing potential or are confirmed as post-menopausal.
             Post-menopausal is defined as being amenorrheic for 12 months without an alternative
             medical cause with a screening FSH level ≥ 25.8 IU/L

        Exclusions:

          1. Male subjects with female partner(s) who is (are) pregnant or lactating from the time
             of the first administration of study medication

          2. Clinically significant disease or any condition or disease that might affect drug
             absorption, distribution or excretion

          3. History of allergic reactions to artemisinin-based compounds or any other clinically
             relevant allergy to drugs or food

          4. Clinically relevant history of both soya and cow's milk intolerance/allergy

          5. Clinically significant abnormal laboratory, vital signs or other safety findings as
             determined by medical history, physical examination or other evaluations conducted at
             screening or on admission

          6. Electrocardiogram (ECG) abnormalities in the standard 12-lead ECG (at screening)
             and/or 24-hour 5 lead Holter ECG (at screening)

          7. Any abnormalities in rhythm, conduction or morphology of resting ECG that may
             interfere with the interpretation of QTc interval changes

          8. Prolonged QTcF &gt;450 ms or shortened QTcF &lt;340 ms, or family history of Long QT
             Syndrome

          9. History or current evidence of any clinically relevant cardiovascular, pulmonary,
             hepatic, renal, gastrointestinal, haematological, endocrinological, metabolic,
             neurological, psychiatric, or other disease

         10. Positive results in any of the serology tests for Hepatitis B Surface Antigen
             (HbsAg), anti Hepatitis core antibody (anti HBc Ig G [and anti HBc IgM if IgG is
             positive], Hepatitis C antibodies (anti HCV), and HIV 1 and 2 antibodies (anti HIV
             1/2)

         11. Confirmed positive results from urine drug screen (amphetamines, benzodiazepines,
             cocaine, cannabinoids, opiates, barbiturates, and methadone) or from the alcohol
             breath test at screening and on admission

         12. History or clinical evidence of alcohol or drug abuse. Alcohol abuse is defined as
             regular weekly intake of more than 21 units for males and 14 units for females; drug
             abuse is defined as compulsive, repetitive and/or chronic use of drugs or other
             substances with or without problems related to their use and/or where stopping or a
             reduction in dose will lead to withdrawal symptoms

         13. Is pregnant or lactating (female subjects who are of childbearing potential must have
             negative pregnancy tests at screening and admission)

         14. Mentally handicapped

         15. Participation in a drug trial within 90 days prior to first drug administration

         16. Use of any medication (incl. over-the-counter (OTC) medication) within 2 weeks prior
             to drug administration (Day 1) or within less than 10 times the elimination half-life
             of the respective drug, or anticipated concomitant medication during the treatment
             periods, (whichever is longer), including herbal, traditional and alternative
             medications. Excluding oral contraceptives (combination oestrogen/progesterone
             pills), injectable progesterone or subdermal implants. Limited amounts (4g/day for 2
             days) of paracetamol will be permitted for the treatment of AEs

         17. Treatment with herbal supplements during the 7 days prior to drug administration, or
             use of vitamins during 48 hours prior to drug administration

         18. Is not permitted to use strong inhibitors and/or inducers of CYP450 within 21 days
             prior to the planned first drug administration

         19. Subjects have veins unsuitable for intravenous puncture or cannulation on either arm
             (e.g. veins that are difficult to locate, access or puncture veins with a tendency to
             rupture during or after puncture)

         20. Blood ALT, AST and bilirubin should be in the normal range at screening and on
             admission

         21. Donation of more than 500 mL of blood within 90 days prior to drug administration

         22. Subjects must be non-smokers for at least three months prior to first drug
             administration

         23. Any circumstances or conditions, which, in the opinion of the PI, may affect full
             participation in the trial or compliance with the protocol

         24. Legal incapacity or limited legal capacity at screening

         25. Subjects who are vegetarians, vegans or have any dietary restrictions conflicting
             with the study standardised menus
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fiona Macintyre, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Medicines for Malaria Venture</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Richmond Pharmacology Ltd</name>
      <address>
        <city>Croydon</city>
        <zip>CR77YE</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://mmv.org</url>
    <description>Company website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 19, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 22, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>malaria</keyword>
  <keyword>dose escalation</keyword>
  <keyword>safety</keyword>
  <keyword>tolerability</keyword>
  <keyword>maximum tolerated dose</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
