<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="159832">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01998594</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>00027968</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01998594</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Use of FlexHD as Post Trapeziectomy Spacer</brief_title>
  <acronym>MTF</acronym>
  <official_title>Use of FlexHD as a Post-Trapeziectomy Spacer in Patients Treated for Thumb Basal Joint Arthritis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cedars Sinai Medical Care Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Musculoskeletal Transplant Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cedars Sinai Medical Care Foundation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to show that using FlexHD® (or HADM) to fill the empty space
      created by removal of the trapezium improves the subject's outcome and subsequent
      functionality of the basilar joint arthroplasty procedure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Subjects will be followed for 24 months post basilar joint arthroplasty procedure with an
      interposition arthroplasty technique using a spacer constructed from human acellular matrix
      (HADM).  Their postoperative DASH scores, grip strength, pinch strength, pain scale scores,
      quality of life and trapezial space on radiographs are compared to their preoperative
      scores.  Study visits will coincide with standard clinical course visits including:
      Pre-operative visits and follow-up visits at day 7, day 14, day 21, week 6,  month 6, year 1
      and at year 2 post-operatively.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Functionality</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The objective of this study is to determine whether utilizing HADM will result in  increased functionality measured by:
DASH score
Pinch and grip strength
Pain scale
Quality of life scores and
Trapezial space on radiographs at designated intervals during the post-operative period</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthrosis of the Carpometacarpal Joint of the Thumb</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arthroplasty without HADM</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Thirty (30) subjects with Eaton stage III-IV thumb CMC osteoarthritis undergo the basilar joint arthroplasty procedure without using a spacer constructed from human acellular matrix (HADM).  Their postoperative DASH scores, grip strength, pinch strength, pain scale scores and quality of life questionnaires are compared to their preoperative scores. These subjects will be compared with a group of thirty (30) similar subjects who received the arthroplasty procedure with the use of the HADM spacer.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arthroplasty with HADM</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Thirty (30) subjects with Eaton stage III-IV thumb CMC osteoarthritis undergo the basilar joint arthroplasty procedure with an interposition arthroplasty technique using a spacer constructed from human acellular matrix (HADM).  Their postoperative DASH scores, grip strength, pinch strength, pain scale scores and quality of life questionnaires are compared to their preoperative scores.  These subjects will be compared with a group of thirty (30) similar subjects who received the arthroplasty procedure without the use of the HADM spacer.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Arthroplasty</intervention_name>
    <description>A longitudinal dorsoradial incision is made from the base of the first metacarpal to the radial styloid for access to the thumb CMC joint.  Trapeziectomy is performed piecemeal using sharp and blunt dissection.  The base of the first metacarpal is then decorticated with a sagittal saw.  A 4x7 cm sheet of thin FlexHD (HADM) is fashioned by a 4-0 monocryl suture imbrication into the size and shape of the subject's trapezium, keeping the dermal side exposed as much as possible. The allograft is secured with multiple interrupted 3-0 Ticron sutures and the bundle is placed into the post-trapeziectomy space.  Additional suture fixation is performed between the FlexHD and the volar capsule of the trapezium, and base of the thumb metacarpal using 4-0 Mersilene sutures.   The control treatment group will have the same trapeziectomy but without the placement of the FlexHD acellular dermal matrix.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arthroplasty without HADM</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arthroplasty with HADM</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or Female &gt;18 years of age

          -  Be willing to undergo thumb basilar joint arthroplasty with the use of acellular
             dermal matrix

          -  Basilar Joint Arthritis Eaton Stage III or IV

          -  Be in good health other than the arthritis

          -  Have realistic expectations of surgical results

          -  Understand and be willing to follow all aspects of the study protocol and have signed
             and dated the IRB-approved Informed Consent Form and the Authorization for Use and
             Release of Health and Research Study Information (HIPAA) form prior to any
             study-related procedures being performed

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Have collagen-vascular, connective tissue, or bleeding disorders

          -  Be a smoker or have smoked in last 2 months

          -  Have any disease, including uncontrolled diabetes, which is clinically known to
             impact wound healing ability

          -  Have regional sympathetic dystrophy

          -  Be pregnant, lactating or expecting to be within the next 24 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Kulber, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cedars Sinai Medical Care Foundation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sandra Rodriguez, LVN</last_name>
    <phone>(310) 423-6500</phone>
    <email>RodriguezSV@csmns.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Carolina Paniagua</last_name>
    <phone>(310) 423-1978</phone>
    <email>Paniaguac@csmns.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cedars-Sinai Department of Hand Surgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90048</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Kulber, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gangopadhyay S, McKenna H, Burke FD, Davis TR. Five- to 18-Year Follow-Up for Treatment of Trapeziometacarpal Osteoarthritis: A Prospective Comparison of Excision, Tendon Interposition, and Ligament Reconstruction and Tendon Interposition. J Hand Surg Am. 2012, Feb 3. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 25, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 13, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cedars Sinai Medical Care Foundation</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Kulber, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director Plastic Surgery, Center of Excellence, Cedars Sinai; Clinical Professor of Surgery, USC Keck School of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Thumb arthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>CMC arthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Arthroplasty</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Joint Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
