<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="38363">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01731522</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MTRI-Basic EF Study</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01731522</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Eating Frequency Study</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Tennessee</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Tennessee</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to examine the influence of two Eating Frequency prescriptions,
      meal (energy intake occurring during three meals per day) and grazing (energy intake
      occurring every two to three hours per day), on consumption during an ad libitum meal
      consumed at the end of the day, overall daily energy intake, and ratio of energy intake to
      energy expenditure.  It is hypothesized that the grazing condition will produce lower
      consumption during an evening ad libitum meal, lower daily energy intake, and a lower ratio
      of energy intake to energy expenditure than the meal condition.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      20 men and women of healthy weight will participate in this study. The complete study design
      will be a 2 x 2 mixed factorial design, with the between-subject factor of order and a
      within-subject factor of eating condition (meal or grazing). Depending upon the eating
      condition, participants will be provided with a morning meal and an afternoon meal (meal) or
      two small meals and three snacks to be consumed every 2-3 hours (grazing).   The types of
      foods and amount of foods provided to participants will be identical in each condition; the
      only difference in the conditions is the time spacing during the day when the foods are
      consumed.  The primary dependent variable will be amount, both grams and energy, of food
      consumed during an ad libitum meal consumed in the evening at the completion of the meal
      condition, overall daily energy intake, and ratio of daily energy intake to energy
      expenditure. It is hypothesized that the grazing condition will produce lower consumption
      during an evening ad libitum meal, lower daily energy intake, and a lower ratio of energy
      intake to energy expenditure than the meal condition.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total grams of ad libitum meal consumed</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The foods that will be used in this investigation are Tyson Chicken Breast Tenders, Ore-Ida Tater Tots, Birds Eye Steamfresh Pure &amp; Simple green beans, and Sarah Lee Butter Pound Cake. Participants will be provided with ad libitum amounts of the foods, and the foods will be measured in grams to the tenth decimal point on an electronic food scale (Denver Instrument Co., Arvada, CO) before and after the meal. The weight of the container will also be measured. Total grams of each food consumed during the session will be determined by subtracting pre- and post-consumption weight of food.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Eating Frequency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EF condition</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EF condition</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>EF condition</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Grazing, Three meal</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age between 18 and 35 years

          -  body mass index (BMI) between 18.5 and 24.9 kg/m2

          -  no history of overweight or obesity

          -  unrestrained eater (&lt;12 on Three Factor Eating Questionnaire [TFEQ])

          -  regularly participate in at least 150 minutes of moderate-intense physical activity
             per week over the previous 4 weeks

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  currently taking medication that affects appetite or food intake

          -  have a medical condition affecting eating or currently following a therapeutic diet

          -  are currently participating in a weight loss program and/or taking weight loss
             medication

          -  have gained or lost &gt; 5% of body weight during the past 6 months

          -  diagnosed with type 1 or 2 diabetes

          -  have had bariatric surgery

          -  report disliking foods used in the investigation (scoring a 1 or 2 on a 5-point
             Likert scale)

          -  report having allergies to foods used in the investigation

          -  currently smoke

          -  report binge eating

          -  are graduate students in the Department of Nutrition

          -  are pregnant, lactating, &lt; 6 months post-partum.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Tennessee-Knoxville</name>
      <address>
        <city>Knoxville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37996-1920</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hollie A Raynor</last_name>
      <phone>865-974-6259</phone>
      <email>hraynor@utk.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 25, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 14, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
