<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="151400">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01974089</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DM-2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01974089</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dysphagia and Pneumonia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Dysphagia in Patients With Community Acquired Pneumonia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Vendsyssel Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Vendsyssel Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Denmark: The North Denmark Region Committee on Health Research Ethics</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine the prevalence of dysphagia among Danish patients hospitalized with pneumonia
      and to test whether it is possible to reduce the swallowing disorders by changing the
      consistence of food and drink. Patients hospitalized in the period from the 1st of September
      2013 to the 31st of March 2014 will be tested by an occupational therapist for dysphagia
      within the first 24 hours of their hospitalization. The endpoints will be number of
      hospitalization days, rehospitalisation and mortality. If the test is positive, the patient
      will get a diet of a manageable consistency to avoid dysphagia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hypothesis: Screening for and treating of dysphagia among patients with CAP can reduce
      rehospitalisation and mortality.

      The aims of the study are 1) to show the prevalence of dysphagia in patients with CAP and 2)
      to prevent rehospitalisation of patients with aspiration pneumonia and 3) to reduce
      mortality.

      The management of patients with dysphagia requires the coordinated expertise of a number of
      health-care professionals including doctors, nurses, dieticians and occupational therapists,
      as well as the primary caregivers. Occupational therapists will be responsible for the
      screening and the management of the dysphagia program. The nurses at the Lung Unit are all
      introduced to the importance of the diet and the postural changes to prevent dysphagia, and
      they will take over when the program has been implemented. In this project there will be
      focus on dietary adjustments and postural changes. There is weak evidence for the effect of
      preventing dysphagia by using thickened liquids and changing the posture, but even then
      there is consensus for this practice among experienced occupational therapists (22). When
      discharged the patients will receive a brochure about the importance of maintaining the
      diet, it will be noted what diet they have to follow, and primary caregivers will also be
      informed. Three weeks after discharge the patient will be visited by a primary occupational
      therapist and a dietrist. The occupational therapist will retest the patient and the
      dietrist will make sure the patient keep weight. Both will have a dialogue with the patient
      about the importance of maintaining the diet.

      There has not yet been made a calculation about how many patients to include, but according
      to experiences from study 1 we expect to include 200 patients.

      Outcome: number of hospitalization days, rehospitalisation within 30 days and within 180
      days and mortality during hospitalization, within 30 days and within 180 days.

      The study is a cross-sectional study. The collected data will be demographic data, level of
      pneuonia, comorbidity, BMI, tooth-status, number of hospitalization days, rehospitalisation
      and mortality. The study is registered by the Danish Data Protection Authority
      (2008-58-0028)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rehospitalization</measure>
    <time_frame>180 after discharge</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality rate</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days after discharge</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Dysphagia</condition>
  <condition>Pneumonia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Modified diet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Modified diet</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Modified diet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  have to be hospitalized due to pneumonia

          -  Admitted on a lung ward

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  if patient suffers from dementia

          -  if patient is palliative, e.g. cancer patients
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vendsyssel Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hjoerring</city>
        <zip>9800</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dorte M Kristiasen, Master of Rehabilitation</last_name>
      <phone>+ 45 97 64 10 48</phone>
      <email>dmk@rn.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dorte M Kristiasen, Master of Rehabilitation</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 31, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 25, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Vendsyssel Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dorte Melgaard Kristiansen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Developmental therapist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dysphagia</keyword>
  <keyword>Modified diet</keyword>
  <keyword>Community acquired pneumonia</keyword>
  <keyword>Mortality</keyword>
  <keyword>Rehospitalization</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Deglutition Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
