<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="50462">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02154529</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KD019-204</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02154529</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of the Combination of KD019 and Trastuzumab in Subjects With HER2-Positive Metastatic Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1b/2a Study of the Combination of KD019 and Trastuzumab in Subjects With HER2-Positive Metastatic Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kadmon Corporation, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kadmon Corporation, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Evaluate the safety and tolerability and determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of the
      combination of KD019 and trastuzumab in subjects with HER2-positive metastatic breast cancer
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Subjects Experiencing Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability and MTD</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the safety and tolerability and determine the MTD of the combination of KD019 and trastuzumab in subjects with HER2-positive metastatic breast cancer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the response rate (RR) using RECIST for non-CNS disease and by the Response Assessment in Neuro-Oncology (RANO) criteria for CNS disease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the following pharmacokinetic parameters (Cmax, Tmax, and AUC[0-24hr]) for the combination of KD019 and Trastuzumab.  Plasma concentrations of KD019 and serum concentrations of trastuzumab will be summarized by dose, sample collection day, and sample collection time for each drug.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median Progression-Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the median progression-free survival (PFS) and the percentage of subjects without disease progression after 2, 4, and 6 months of dosing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>30 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the median overall survival (OS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">38</enrollment>
  <condition>HER-2 Positive Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Malignant Neoplasm to Brain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1b, Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>KD019 in combination with Trastuzumab. KD019 will be orally administered to subjects at 150mg once daily in combination with Trastuzumab 8mg/kg every 3 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1b, Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>KD019 in combination with Trastuzumab. KD019 will be orally administered to subjects at 250mg once daily in combination with Trastuzumab 8mg/kg every 3 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1b, Arm 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>KD019 in combination with Trastuzumab. KD019 will be orally administered to subjects at 300mg once daily in combination with Trastuzumab 8mg/kg every 3 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2a</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>KD019 in combination with Trastuzumab. In the Phase 2a expansion group, KD019 will be orally administered to all subjects once daily at the MTD dose determined in Phase 1b in combination with Trastuzumab 8mg/kg every 3 weeks. Subjects will be limited to those with HER2-positive breast cancer and brain metastases that have progressed after radiation therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>KD019 in combination with Trastuzumab</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1b, Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1b, Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1b, Arm 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2a</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>XL647</other_name>
    <other_name>Herceptin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Females with histologically or cytologically confirmed HER2-positive breast cancer.
             HER2-positive is defined as 3+ staining by immunohistochemistry, or HER2 gene
             amplification by fluorescent in situ hybridization or silver in situ hybridization
             with HER2/CEP17 ratio ≥ 2.0 with average HER2 copy number ≥ 4.0 signals/cell

          -  Metastatic disease that has progressed on previous therapy

          -  Subjects may have received any number of prior therapies for breast cancer:

               -  Previous therapies must have included trastuzumab, pertuzumab, and trastuzumab
                  emtansine. However, subjects starting initial systemic therapy for HER2-positive
                  breast cancer prior to June 2012, when pertuzumab was approved for initial
                  treatment of patients with HER2-positive breast cancer, are not required to have
                  had pertuzumab

               -  If the subject has ER+ breast cancer, prior therapy must have included at least
                  1 hormonal therapy

               -  Subjects with brain metastases must have received radiation therapy prior to
                  study entry

          -  Subjects with disease progression in the brain after prior brain radiation therapy
             may have extra CNS metastases in any location or may have no extra CNS metastases

          -  Enrollment in the expansion Phase 2a portion of the study will be limited to subjects
             with HER2-positive metastatic breast cancer with brain metastases that have
             progressed after radiation therapy

          -  At least 1 measurable and new or progressing breast cancer lesion that is ≥ 10mm by
             spiral CT scan or by brain MRI

          -  No increase in corticosteroid dose during the week prior to screening brain MRI

          -  No history of another malignancy in the past 5 years, except treated non-melanoma
             skin cancer or superficial bladder cancer or carcinoma-in-situ of the cervix

          -  Adequate organ and bone marrow functions

          -  Serum potassium and magnesium levels within normal limits

          -  Cardiac injection fraction ranging from 55% or 70% as measure by echocardiogram

          -  No coexisting medical problems of sufficient severity to limit compliance with the
             study

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have negative urine pregnancy test.  They must
             agree to use highly effective method of birth control during the study and for 3
             months after the termination of the study.  Highly effective birth control methods
             include implants, injectables, combined oral contraceptives, some IUDs, sexual
             abstinence, or vasectomized partner

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any concurrent therapy for breast cancer other than the specified treatment in this
             study.  Concurrent treatment will biphosphonates is allowed

          -  Cerebrospinal fluid cytology positive for malignant cells or symptomatic
             leptomeningeal carcinomatosis

          -  Taking any medication known to inhibit the CYP3A4 isozyme or any drugs that are
             CYP3A4 inducers (including phenytoin), or any drugs associated with torsades de
             pointes or known to prolong the QTc(f) interval, including anti-arrhythmic
             medications within 2 weeks prior to Day 1 of treatment on study.  A stable regimen of
             antidepressants of the SSRI class is allowed

          -  Has evidence of active heart disease within the 3 months prior to study entry;
             symptomatic coronary insufficiency or heart block; congestive heart failure; moderate
             or severe pulmonary dysfunction

          -  History of torsades de pointes, ventricular tachycardia or fibrillation, pathologic
             sinus bradycardia, heart block, or congenital long QT syndrome. Subjects with a
             history of atrial arrhythmias should be discussed with the medical monitor

          -  Has an active infectious process

          -  Subject who is pregnant or lactating

          -  Known contraindications to MRI, such as cardiac pacemaker, shrapnel, or ocular
             foreign body

          -  Had had major surgery without fully recovery

          -  Has marked prolongation of QTc interval at screening or baseline using the Fridericia
             method of correction for heart rate

          -  Has gastrointestinal tract disease resulting in an inability to take or absorb oral
             medication
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>San Juan Oncology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Farmington</city>
        <state>New Mexico</state>
        <zip>87401</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rosemarie Mestas</last_name>
      <phone>505-564-6850</phone>
      <email>rosemarie@sjonc.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jeffrey Neidhart</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 30, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 28, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Second Primary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Trastuzumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
