<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="11598">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01907906</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CTS-0080</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>ERMS#12308001</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01907906</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Inactivation of Whole Blood With Mirasol</brief_title>
  <acronym>IMPROVEII</acronym>
  <official_title>Inactivation of Whole Blood With Mirasol : Performance in Red Blood Cells in Healthy Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Terumo BCTbio</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>U.S. Army Medical Research and Materiel Command</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Terumo BCTbio</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate radiolabeled recovery and survival of autologous
      red blood cells (RBC), derived from Mirasol-treated fresh whole blood (WB), stored as
      leukoreduced packed RBC (LR-pRBC), and re-infused in healthy adult subjects
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a feasibility level study conducted to assess the recovery and survival of
      autologous, radiolabeled leukoreduced packed red blood cells (LR-pRBC) derived from fresh
      whole blood (WB) units that have been treated with the Mirasol System for Whole Blood
      (Mirasol System) and stored for 21 days at 1-6°C.1
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Red Blood Cell Recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate, as per FDA criteria, the 24-hour post transfusion RBC recovery in healthy adult subjects of LR-pRBC that have been derived from Mirasol-treated fresh WB units and stored at 1 to 6°C for 21 days.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Other Data Collection</measure>
    <time_frame>168 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Data will be collected to: 1.) Evaluate RBC survival, half-life, and area under the curve (AUC); 2.) Determine incidence of neoantigenicity; 3.) Determine in vitro characteristics of test and control RBC; 4.) Determine incidence of adverse events (AEs); and 4.) Evaluate correlations identified in the initial IMPROVE Trial as predictive models (24-hour red blood cell (RBC) recovery and half-life with % hemolysis, adenosine triphosphate (ATP), and carbon dioxide partial pressure [pCO2]).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">29</enrollment>
  <condition>Focus of Study: Radiolabel Recovery and Survival of RBCs</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment Period 1: A unit of whole blood is donated and treated with the Mirasol System for Whole Blood; Treatment Period 2: a second unit of whole blood is donated and not treated.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment Period 1: A unit of whole blood is donated and not treated with the Mirasol System for Whole Blood; Treatment Period 2: a second unit of whole blood is donated and treated.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mirasol System for Whole Blood</intervention_name>
    <description>LR-pRBC units derived from WB will be treated with the Mirasol System.  Treatment with the Mirasol System requires riboflavin to be mixed into the whole blood unit, which is then exposed to UV light for a period of time; approximately an hour.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Pathogen Reduction Technology</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Eligible whole blood donor

          -  Age ≥ 18 years, of either sex

          -  Able to commit to the study follow-up schedule

          -  Subjects must have adequate bilateral antecubital venous access for WB collection and
             follow-up blood draws

          -  Negative screening test panel for infectious diseases

          -  Subjects of child-bearing potential (female or male) must agree to use effective
             contraceptive during the course of the study per site guidelines

          -  Subjects must agree to report adverse events (AEs) during the required reporting
             period

          -  Negative direct antiglobulin test (DAT) with subject's RBC

          -  Negative indirect antiglobulin test (IAT) with subject's serum

        Inclusion for radiolabeled reinfusion of LR-pRBC on Day 21 (evaluated the day of, prior
        to, reinfusion):

          -  Maintenance of healthy status

          -  Negative direct antiglobulin test (DAT) with subject's RBC (fresh)

          -  Negative indirect antiglobulin test (IAT) with subject's serum (fresh) versus
             autologous stored LR-pRBC

          -  Negative serum or urine pregnancy test in females

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any serious medical illness and/or therapy, including: abnormal bleeding episodes,
             clotting or bleeding disorder, evidence of anemia, myocardial infarction,
             uncontrolled hypertension, heart disease, surgery with bleeding complications,
             epilepsy or any major surgery (with general or spinal anesthesia) within the last 6
             months

          -  Pregnant or nursing females; For women of childbearing potential, negative serum or
             urine pregnancy tests at the time of WB donation and before the reinfusion are
             required

          -  Unable to give informed consent

          -  Participation currently, or within the last 12 months, in another investigational
             trial that would potentially interfere with the analysis of this investigation (e.g.,
             pharmaceutical)

          -  Have received an accumulated radiation dose that would exclude them from the study
             according to the local radiation safety limits established by each institution

          -  Inability to comply with the protocol in the opinion of the investigator
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Raymond P Goodrich, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>TerumoBCT Biotechnologies</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hoxworth Blood Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45267</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Puget Sound Blood Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 30, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 20, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pathogen reduction technology</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
