<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="82270">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01834248</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>I 227712</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-00565</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>I 227712</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016056</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01834248</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>DEC-205/NY-ESO-1 Fusion Protein CDX-1401and Decitabine in Treating Patients With Myelodysplastic Syndrome or Acute Myeloid Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of DEC205mAb-NY ESO 1 Fusion Protein (CDX-1401) Given With Adjuvant polyICLC in Conjunction With 5-Aza-2'Deoxycytidine (Decitabine) in Patients With MDS or Low Blast Count AML</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Celldex Therapeutics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial studies the side effects and immune response to DEC-205/NY-ESO-1 fusion
      protein CDX-1401 and decitabine in patients with myelodysplastic syndrome or acute myeloid
      leukemia. DEC-205-NY-ESO-1 fusion protein, called CDX-1401, is a full length NY-ESO-1
      protein sequence fused to a monoclonal antibody against DEC-205, a surface marker present on
      many immune stimulatory cells. This drug is given with another substance called PolyICLC,
      which acts to provoke any immune stimulatory cells which encounter the NY-ESO-1-DEC-205
      fusion protein to produce an immune response signal against NY-ESO-1. Immune cells which
      have thus been primed to react against NY-ESO-1 may then attack myelodysplastic or leukemic
      cells which express NY-ESO-1 after exposure to the drug decitabine. The chemotherapy drug
      decitabine is thought to act in several different ways, first, it may directly kill cancer
      cells, secondly, the drug can cause cancer cells to re-express genes that are turned off by
      the cancer, including the gene for NY-ESO-1. Giving DEC-205/NY-ESO-1 fusion protein
      (CDX-1401) and polyICLC together with decitabine may allow the immune system to more
      effectively recognize cancer cells and kill them.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Evaluate the safety of Anti-DEC-205-NY-ESOI (CDX-1401) fusion protein (DEC-205/NY-ESO-1
      fusion protein CDX-1401) given in combination with decitabine 20 mg/m^2 intravenously.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate NY-ESO-1 specific cellular and humoral immunity by determination of NY-ESO-1
      specific antibody, and T-cell clones following standard treatment with
      5-aza-2'-deoxycytidine (decitabine) in conjunction with immune sensitization with Anti-DEC
      205-NY-ESO-I fusion protein (CDX-1401).

      II. To determine the impact of decitabine treatment on peripheral blood cells from patients
      treated in this manner on NY-ESO-1 target gene expression, NY-ESO protein expression,
      NY-ESO-1 promoter methylation, and global deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) methylation.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To record the response rate (complete response, partial response and hematological
      improvement) in myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS) or low blast count acute myeloid leukemia
      (AML) patients treated with the combination in order to provide descriptive characteristics.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive DEC-205/NY-ESO-1 fusion protein CDX-1401 subcutaneously (SC) and
      intradermally (ID) and poly-ICLC subcutaneously (SC) on day -14 and day 15 of courses 1-4.
      Patients also receive decitabine intravenously (IV) over 1 hour on days 1-5. Treatment
      repeats every 28 days for up to 4 courses in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 30, 60, 90, and 180 days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Grade 3+ adverse event and serious adverse event (SAE) rate, graded according to the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE) v4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after last dose of study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Toxicity rates will be described using upper one-sided 95% Clopper Pearson binomial confidence intervals.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune and molecular epigenetic response</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and during treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Summarized by descriptive statistics (means, medians, quartiles, etc.) Confidence intervals will be constructed for the median and the mean. Exploratory graphical analysis will be used to discover associations among variables</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With 11q23 (MLL) Abnormalities</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With Del(5q)</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Myelomonocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>de Novo Myelodysplastic Syndromes</condition>
  <condition>Previously Treated Myelodysplastic Syndromes</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Anemia With Excess Blasts in Transformation</condition>
  <condition>Untreated Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (CDX-1401, decitabine)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive DEC-205/NY-ESO-1 fusion protein CDX-1401 SC and ID and poly-ICLC SC on day -14 and day 15 of courses 1-4. Patients also receive decitabine IV over 1 hour on days 1-5. Treatment repeats every 28 days for up to 4 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DEC-205/NY-ESO-1 fusion protein CDX-1401</intervention_name>
    <description>Given SC and ID</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (CDX-1401, decitabine)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CDX-1401</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>poly ICLC</intervention_name>
    <description>Given SC</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (CDX-1401, decitabine)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Hiltonol</other_name>
    <other_name>poly I:poly C with poly-1-lysine stabilizer</other_name>
    <other_name>Polyinosinic-Polycytidylic Acid Stabilized with Polylysine and Carboxymethylcellulose</other_name>
    <other_name>stabilized polyriboinosinic/polyribocytidylic acid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>decitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (CDX-1401, decitabine)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>5-aza-dCyd</other_name>
    <other_name>5AZA</other_name>
    <other_name>DAC</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (CDX-1401, decitabine)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with a confirmed diagnosis of:

               -  International Prognostic Scoring System (IPSS) intermediate-I, intermediate-2 or
                  high-risk MDS including chronic myelomonocytic leukemia (CMML) or

               -  Low blast count AML with =&lt; 30% blasts previously classified as refractory
                  anemia with excess blasts in transformation who have not been previously treated
                  with a hypomethylating agent

               -  Patients with IPSS intermediate-1 disease with an isolated deletion of
                  chromosome 5q must have previously failed treatment with lenalidomide

          -  Subjects with Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of =&lt; 2

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 2 X upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Aspartate transaminase (AST/serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase [SGOT]) and
             alanine transaminase (ALT/serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT]) =&lt; 2.5 X ULN

          -  Serum creatinine =&lt; 1.5 X ULN

          -  Any human leukocyte antigen (HLA) type

          -  Subjects of child-bearing potential must agree to use adequate contraceptive methods
             (e.g., hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry
             and for the duration of study participation; should a woman become pregnant or
             suspect she is pregnant while she or her partner is participating in this study, she
             should inform her treating physician immediately

          -  Subject or legal representative must understand the investigational nature of this
             study and sign an Independent Ethics Committee/Institutional Review Board approved
             written informed consent form prior to receiving any study related procedure

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with life-threatening illnesses other than MDS, uncontrolled medical
             conditions or organ system dysfunction which, in the investigator's opinion, could
             compromise the subject's safety, or put the study outcomes at risk

          -  AML associated with inv(16); t(I 6;16); t(8;21) or t(1 5;17)

          -  Subjects with uncontrolled or symptomatic arrhythmias, or any class 3 or 4 cardiac
             disease as defined by the New York Heart Association functional classification

          -  Subjects with symptomatic central nervous system (CNS) disease which is not
             adequately controlled

          -  Subjects who have received prior radiation therapy for extra-medullary disease within
             2 weeks of first dose

          -  Subjects with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or active infection with hepatitis C
             virus (HCV) or hepatitis B virus (HBV)

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements

          -  Subjects who are being treated with systemic corticosteroids

          -  Subjects who have hypersensitivity to decitabine

          -  History of auto-immune disease (eg. thyroiditis, lupus) except vitiligo

          -  Pregnant or nursing female subjects

          -  Unwilling or unable to follow protocol requirements

          -  Any condition which in the Investigator's opinion deems the subject an unsuitable
             candidate to receive study drug

          -  Received an investigational agent within 30 days prior to enrollment

          -  Subjects previously treated with an allogeneic stem cell transplant
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elizabeth Griffiths</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14263</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Roswell Park</last_name>
      <phone>877-275-7724</phone>
      <email>ASKRPCI@roswellpark.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elizabeth A. Griffiths</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Congenital Abnormalities</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Refractory</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Refractory, with Excess of Blasts</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelomonocytic, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelomonocytic, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Aplastic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carboxymethylcellulose Sodium</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Poly I-C</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Poly ICLC</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Decitabine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
