<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="50330">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01979029</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Left Colic Artery</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01979029</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of the Preservation of the Left Colic Artery on Rectum Cancer Surgery</brief_title>
  <acronym>POTLCAORCS</acronym>
  <official_title>Affection on Anastomotic Blood Flow and the Lymph Nodes Dissection Between Division at the Root of the Inferior Mesenteric Artery and Preserving the Left Colic Artery in Rectum Cancer Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jian Suo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>First Hospital of Jilin University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>China: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the influence to the blood supply of the anastomosis and the harvest of the No.
      253 lymph nodes in different surgical methods--- preserving the left colic artery (LCA) and
      resect the No. 253 lymph node specifically in the radical resection of rectal carcinoma or
      dividing at the root of the inferior mesenteric artery (IMA) in the radical resection of
      rectal carcinoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Methods: The patients who got rectal carcinoma are divided into two groups. Both groups will
      receive the radical resection of rectal carcinoma. We preserve the left colic artery and
      resect the No. 253 lymph node specifically in Group A and divide at the root of the inferior
      mesenteric artery in Group B, We insert a trocar into the arterial arcade at the proximal
      site of the anastomosis and measure the blood pressure of the arterial arcade in the
      operation, which can reflect the blood supply of the anastomosis. Besides, We will measure
      the length of the colon from the anastomosis to the level of the root of the IMA. Expecting
      Results：The blood pressure of the arterial arcade in Group A will be higher than that in
      Group B. And the patients in Group A will have less chance to get anastomotic fistula.
      Expecting Conclusions: Preserving the LCA and resecting the No. 253 lymph node specifically
      in the radical resection of rectal carcinoma can improve the blood supply of the anastomosis
      and decrease the incidence of anastomotic fistula, and won't affect the harvest of the No.
      253 lymph node.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The blood pressure of the arterial arcade</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Rectum Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>preserving the left colic artery</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patients who got rectal carcinoma are divided into two groups. Both groups will receive the radical resection of rectal carcinoma. We preserve the left colic artery and resect the No. 253 lymph node specifically in Group A and divide at the root of the inferior mesenteric artery in Group B, We insert a trocar into the arterial arcade at the proximal site of the anastomosis and measure the blood pressure of the arterial arcade in the operation, which can reflect the blood supply of the anastomosis. Besides, We will measure the length of the colon from the anastomosis to the level of the root of the IMA.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>preserving the left colic artery</intervention_name>
    <description>The patients who got rectal carcinoma are divided into two groups. Both groups will receive the radical resection of rectal carcinoma. We preserve the left colic artery and resect the No. 253 lymph node specifically in Group A and divide at the root of the inferior mesenteric artery in Group B, We insert a trocar into the arterial arcade at the proximal site of the anastomosis and measure the blood pressure of the arterial arcade in the operation, which can reflect the blood supply of the anastomosis. Besides, We will measure the length of the colon from the anastomosis to the level of the root of the IMA</description>
    <arm_group_label>preserving the left colic artery</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients coming to FirstJilinU diagnosed rectum cancer by endoscopy and pathology.

          -  The rectum cancer is the first malignant neoplasm the patient has got.

          -  The cancer is solitary, and is 5cm to 20cm to the anus.

          -  The surgical method is limited to Dixon.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Being in the acute phase of inflammation before operation and emergency surgery.

          -  Patients combined coronary heart disease，aortic stenosis，Arteritis。

          -  Discovering macrometastasis before or in the operation.

          -  The rectum cancer that can't be radical resected.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 7, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 25, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>First Hospital of Jilin University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jian Suo</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Headmaster, Dept.of General Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Rectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
