<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="166415">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01807598</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HEMMPD0016</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-00537</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01807598</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Brentuximab Vedotin in Treating Patients With Advanced Systemic Mastocytosis or Mast Cell Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study of Brentuximab Vedotin (SGN-35) in CD30-Positive Systemic Mastocytosis With or Without an Associated Hematological Clonal Non-Mast Cell Lineage Disease (AHNMD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This pilot clinical trial studies brentuximab vedotin in treating patients with advanced
      systemic mastocytosis or mast cell leukemia. Monoclonal antibodies, such as brentuximab
      vedotin, can block cancer growth in different ways. Some block the ability of cancer cells
      to grow and spread. Others find cancer cells and help kill them or carry cancer-killing
      substances to them
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the response rate to SGN-35 (brentuximab vedotin) in patients with tumor
      necrosis factor receptor superfamily, member 8 (CD30+) advanced systemic mastocytosis (SM)
      (ASM or mast cell leukemia [MCL] with or without an associated hematological clonal non-mast
      cell lineage disease [AHNMD]).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the tolerability and safety profile of SGN-35 in patients with SM.

      II. To evaluate expression of CD30 on neoplastic mast cells before and during therapy with
      SGN-35.

      III. To evaluate changes in mastocytosis related symptom scores and quality of life (QOL)
      using a modified Myeloproliferative Neoplasm Symptom Assessment Form (MPNSAF).

      IV. To evaluate the duration of response (DoR) and time to response (TTR). V. To evaluate
      progression-free survival (PFS).

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive brentuximab vedotin intravenously (IV) over 30 minutes on day 1. Treatment
      repeats every 21 days for 8 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable
      toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 6 weeks for 1 year and
      then every 12 weeks thereafter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate per consensus international response criteria (rate of complete or partial remissions or clinical improvement)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be estimated and its 95% confidence interval will be provided.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunohistochemical expression of CD30 on neoplastic mast cells in core biopsy samples by flow cytometry</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total symptom score using a modified Myeloproliferative Neoplasm Symptom Assessment Form (MPN-SAF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from first onset of confirmed response to the date of first documented and confirmed progression or death, assessed up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Kaplan-Meier product-limit method will be used to summarize.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to response</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from start of treatment until the date of onset of  a confirmed response, assessed up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Kaplan-Meier product-limit method will be used to summarize.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from start of treatment to the date of the first documented and confirmed progression or death or institution of new therapy, assessed up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Kaplan-Meier product-limit method will be used to summarize.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Type of adverse events measured by National Cancer Institute Common Toxicity Criteria  (NCI CTC) version 4.03</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life (QOL) score using a modified Myeloproliferative Neoplasm Symptom Assessment Form (MPN-SAF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events measured by National Cancer Institute Common Toxicity Criteria  (NCI CTC) version 4.03</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of adverse events measured by National Cancer Institute Common Toxicity Criteria  (NCI CTC) version 4.03</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Seriousness of adverse events measured by National Cancer Institute Common Toxicity Criteria  (NCI CTC) version 4.03</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relatedness of adverse events measured by National Cancer Institute Common Toxicity Criteria  (NCI CTC) version 4.03</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">26</enrollment>
  <condition>Aggressive Systemic Mastocytosis</condition>
  <condition>Mast Cell Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Systemic Mastocytosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (brentuximab vedotin)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive brentuximab vedotin IV over 30 minutes on day 1. Treatment repeats every 21 days for 8 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>brentuximab vedotin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (brentuximab vedotin)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Adcetris</other_name>
    <other_name>anti-CD30 ADC SGN-35</other_name>
    <other_name>anti-CD30 antibody-drug conjugate SGN-35</other_name>
    <other_name>antibody-drug conjugate SGN-35</other_name>
    <other_name>SGN-35</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (brentuximab vedotin)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>quality-of-life assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (brentuximab vedotin)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>quality of life assessment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>questionnaire administration</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (brentuximab vedotin)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient must give written informed consent

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0-3

          -  Life expectancy &gt; 12 weeks

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) =&lt; 2.5 x upper
             limit of normal (ULN), if caused by ASM/MCL =&lt; 5 x ULN

          -  Serum direct bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x ULN; if considered related to ASM/MCL =&lt; 3 x ULN

          -  Serum creatinine =&lt; 2.0 mg/dL

          -  A diagnosis of systemic mastocytosis (SM) per 2008 World Health Organization (WHO)
             Criteria

          -  Neoplastic mast cells must express CD30 by immunohistochemistry or flow cytometry

          -  Patients with ASM and MCL with or without an AHNMD are required to have at least one
             of the eligible organ damage findings as defined by the international consensus
             response criteria

          -  Both females of childbearing potential and males who have partners of childbearing
             potential must agree to use an effective contraceptive method during the study and
             for 30 days following the last dose of study drug

          -  Females of childbearing potential must have a negative serum or urine beta-human
             chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) pregnancy test result within 7 days prior to the first
             dose of SGN-35; females of non-childbearing potential are those who are
             postmenopausal greater than 1 year or who have had a bilateral tubal ligation or
             hysterectomy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients unwilling or unable to comply with the protocol

          -  Any other concurrent severe known disease (except carcinoma in-situ) or concurrent
             severe and/or uncontrolled medical condition (e.g. uncontrolled diabetes, or active
             uncontrolled infection) which could compromise participation in the study

          -  History of another primary malignancy that has not been in remission for at least 3
             years (the following are exempt from the 3-year limit: non-melanoma skin cancer,
             fully excised melanoma in situ [stage 0], curatively treated localized prostate
             cancer, and cervical carcinoma in situ on biopsy or a squamous intraepithelial lesion
             on Papanicolaou [PAP] smear)

          -  Patients with cardiovascular disease including congestive heart failure grade III or
             IV according to the New York Heart Association (NYHA) classification, left
             ventricular ejection fraction of &lt; 50%, myocardial infarction within previous 6
             months or poorly controlled hypertension

          -  Women who are pregnant or lactating

          -  Patients with &gt;= grade 2 neuropathy

          -  Patients with a known hypersensitivity to any excipient contained in the drug
             formulation

          -  Confirmed diagnosis of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection or active viral
             hepatitis

          -  Patients presenting with an AHNMD requiring immediate cytoreductive therapy or
             targeted drugs (e.g. AML)

          -  Patients who have received any investigational agent, chemotherapy, interferon-alfa,
             or 2-chlorodeoxyadenosine (2-CdA, cladribine) within 30 days prior to Day 1

          -  Patients who have received hematopoietic growth factor support within 14 days of Day
             1 of SGN-35

          -  Use of prednisone (or equivalent corticosteroid dose) for SM up to 10 mg/day or its
             equivalent is allowed, but it cannot have been started during screening; patients who
             are on prednisone up to 10 mg/day for medical problems unrelated to SM are also
             permitted on study

          -  Patients with the FIP1L1-PDGFRalpha fusion even with resistance to imatinib (such
             patients are no longer defined as systemic mastocytosis by the WHO)

          -  Patients who have received any treatment with SGN-35 prior to study entry

          -  Patients who have had any surgical procedure, excluding central venous catheter
             placement or other minor procedures (e.g. skin biopsy) within 14 days of Day 1
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jason Gotlib</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University Hospitals and Clinics</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Harshdeep Kaur</last_name>
    <phone>650-723-3589</phone>
    <email>hkaur@stanford.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jason R. Gotlib</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 17, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 5, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Aggression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Mast-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mastocytosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urticaria Pigmentosa</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mastocytosis, Systemic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoconjugates</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
