<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="95949">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02132156</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VAC 013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02132156</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety of P2-VP8 in South African Toddlers and Infants</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Descending Age, Double-blinded, Randomized, Placebo-controlled Dose Escalation Study to Examine the Safety, Reactogenicity, Tolerability and Immunogenicity of the P2-VP8 Subunit Parenteral Rotavirus Vaccine in Healthy Toddlers and Infants</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>PATH</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>PATH</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>South Africa: Medicines Control Council</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The trial is a double-blinded, randomized, placebo-controlled dose-escalation study in which
      three dose-levels (10 µg, 30 µg and 60 µg) of vaccine will be tested, first in toddlers and
      then in infants. Cohorts of 14 toddlers (12 vaccine recipients and 2 placebo recipients) per
      dose level will receive a single intramuscular injection. Cohorts of 16 infants (12 vaccine
      recipients and 4 placebo recipients) per dose level will receive three study injections at 4
      week intervals. The two highest dose levels tolerated in the infant cohort will be assessed
      in an expanded infant cohort of 114 infants (38 at each dose level and 38 placebo
      recipients). Study injections in the infant cohort will be administered concomitant with EPI
      vaccinations (with the exception of rotavirus vaccination). All infants will receive Rotarix
      at 4, 8 and 12 weeks after the third study injection, and fecal shedding of Rotarix will be
      assessed during the week after the first dose. The third dose of Rotarix is being provided
      to these infants to mitigate the theoretical risk that the P2-VP8 vaccine might interfere
      with the benefit of Rotarix vaccination.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety • Number of SAEs  • Number of AEs • Number of  vaccine induced local and systemic reactions Occurrence of Serious Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months following last vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of SAEs
Number of AEs
Number of vaccine induced local and systemic reactions
Local reactogenicity events (injection site pain/, tenderness, redness, swelling, itching, local lymphadenopathy) within 1 week (Day 0 to Day 7) after each injection and for the three combined injections
Systemic reactogenicity (fever, vomiting, decreasedpoor appetite, irritability, decreased activity) per cohort and product received, within 1 week (Day 0 to Day 7) after each injection and for the three combined injections</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>immunogenicity</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks post 3rd vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the immunogenicity of the P2-VP8 subunit + Al(OH)3 subunit rotavirus vaccine at different dose levels in healthy South African infants
Endpoints:
Proportion of infants with anti-P2-VP8 IgG and IgA seroresponses (four-fold increase in antibody titers between baseline and 4-weeks post-third injection)
Proportion of infants with neutralizing antibody responses against rotavirus (four-fold increases in antibody titers between baseline and 4-weeks post-third injection)
Anti-P2-VP8 IgG and IgA geometric mean titers (GMT)  4-weeks post-third injection
Neutralizing antibody GMT 4-weeks post-third injection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">168</enrollment>
  <condition>Rotavirus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Vaccine: The P2-VP8 subunit rotavirus vaccine produced in E. coli will be adsorbed onto aluminum hydroxide (0.6 mg/dose) within 6 hours of administration. Three different dose levels of vaccine will be tested: 10 µg, 30 µg and 60 µg, all to be administered in 0.5 mL volumes intramuscularly.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebe</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo: Normal Saline (NS)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>P2-VP8 subunit rotavirus vaccine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Vaccine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Normal Saline</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebe</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy infants/ toddlers as established by medical history and clinical examination
             before entering the study

          -  Age:

               1. Toddler cohort: &gt;2 and &lt;3 years old at the time of enrollment

               2. Infant cohort: &gt;6 and &lt;8 weeks at the time of enrollment

          -  Parental ability and willingness to provide informed consent

          -  Parental intention to remain in the area with the child during the study period

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of fever on the day of enrollment

          -  Acute disease at the time of enrollment

          -  Concurrent participation in another clinical trial throughout the entire timeframe
             for this study

          -  Presence of malnutrition or any systemic disorder as determined by medical history
             and/or physical examination that would compromise the participant's health or is
             likely to result in nonconformance to the protocol

          -  For infant cohort, history of premature birth (&lt;37 weeks gestation)

          -  History of congenital abdominal disorders, intussusception, or abdominal surgery

          -  Known or suspected impairment of immunological function based on medical history and
             physical examination

          -  For infant cohort only, prior receipt of rotavirus vaccine

          -  A known sensitivity or allergy to any components of the study vaccine

          -  History of anaphylactic reaction

          -  Major congenital or genetic defect

          -  Participant's parents not able, available or willing to accept active weekly
             follow-up by the study staff

          -  Has received any immunoglobulin therapy and/or blood products since birth or planned
             administration during the study period

          -  History of chronic administration (defined as more than 14 days) of immunosuppressant
             medications, including corticosteroids. Infants on inhaled or topical steroids may be
             permitted to participate in the study

          -  Any medical condition in the parents/infant that, in the judgment of the
             investigator, would interfere with or serves as a contraindication to protocol
             adherence or a participant's parents' ability to give informed consent

          -  HIV infection

               1. For toddlers, to be assessed by HIV ELISA

               2. For infants, to be assessed by PCR, if mother is not known to be negative
                  (negative test result between 24 weeks gestation and screening)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Weeks</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>3 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michelle Groome, MBBCh, DCH,</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Chris hani Baragwanath Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Respiratory and Menigeal pathogesn Research Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Soweto</city>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michelle Groome</last_name>
      <phone>27 11 983 4283</phone>
      <email>Micgroomem@rmpru.co.za</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Michelle Groome, MBBSCH</last_name>
      <phone>27 11 983 4283</phone>
      <email>Micgroomem@rmpru.co.za</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michelle Groome</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>South Africa</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 6, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 5, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>rotavirus vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>diarrheal disease</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
