<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="168031">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01688999</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>120205</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>12-C-0205</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01688999</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cabozantinib for Advanced Urothelial Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Cabozantinib (XL184) in Patients With Advanced/Metastatic Urothelial Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Cabozantinib is a drug that slows the growth of blood vessels that feed tumors. It has not
      been approved for cancer treatment. However, studies have shown that prostate and ovarian
      tumors respond to it. Researchers want see if cabozantinib can be a safe and effective
      treatment for urothelial cancer.

      Objectives:

      - To test the safety and effectiveness of cabozantinib for advanced urothelial cancer.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals at least 18 years of age who have advanced urothelial cancer that has not
      responded to standard treatments.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. Blood and urine
           samples will be collected. Tumor tissue samples will also be collected. Imaging studies
           will also be performed.

        -  Participants will take cabozantinib by mouth once per day on each day of a 28-day
           cycle.

        -  Treatment will be monitored with frequent blood tests and imaging studies.

        -  Participants will continue to take the study drug for as long as their cancer does not
           worsen and side effects are not too severe.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - In the United States, urothelial carcinoma (UC) of the bladder is the fourth most common

      malignancy in men and the ninth most common in women with an estimated 69,250 new

      cases and 14,990 deaths in the year 2011

        -  There is no FDA-approved second line drug for patients with metastatic UC

        -  Multiple lines of evidence support targeting angiogenesis in UC

        -  In human bladder cancer, overexpression of c-Met/Axl/PDGFR-alpha or c-Met alone showed

      significant correlation with poor survival

      - Cabozantinib is a new chemical entity that inhibits multiple receptor tyrosine kinases
      with

      growth-promoting and angiogenic properties.

      - The primary targets of cabozantinib are MET, VEGFR2, and RET

      Objectives:

      - To determine the response rate of cabozantinib in patients with progressive urothelial
      cancer who have received prior cytotoxic chemotherapy

      Eligibility:

      -Patients in cohort 1 must have a histologically confirmed diagnosis of metastatic,
      progressive

      urothelial carcinoma of the bladder, urethra, ureter, or renal pelvis .

      - Patients in cohort 2 must have a histologically confirmed diagnosis of bone only
      metastatic,

      urothelial carcinoma of the bladder, urethra, ureter, or renal pelvis.

      - Patients in cohort 3 must have a histologically confirmed diagnosis of non-transitional
      cell carcinoma cancer (including but not limited to squamous cell, neuroendocrine,

      adenocarcinoma including urachal and sarcomatoid) of the bladder, urethra, ureter, or renal
      pelvis.

      - Patients must have been previously treated, as defined by treatment with at least one
      prior

      cytotoxic chemotherapy regimen or agent. Patients may have received any number of prior

      cytotoxic agents.

      - 18 years of age or older.

      Design:

        -  A maximum of 55 subjects will be enrolled in this open label, non-randomized, phase II
           trial of 60 mg each day of cabozantinib. Up to 45 patients will be accrued to cohort 1
           (metastatic, progressive urothelial cancer. The remainder will be enrolled on
           exploratory cohorts 2 &amp;  3, bone only metastatic urothelial disease and non TCC bladder
           cancer respectively, during the time the study is accruing patients for cohort 1. Note:
           Patients who tolerate cabozantinib at 60 mg daily during the first 2 cycles (first
           restaging time period) without   (Bullet) grade 2 toxicity may undergo dose escalation
           to 80 mg daily at the discretion of the Principal Investigator.

        -  A Simon 2 stage design with alpha=0.05 and beta = 0.10 as acceptable error
           probabilities. Initially 21 subjects will be enrolled and followed for progression. If
           2 or more of cohort 1 subjects experiences a response, enrollment will continue until a
           total of 41 evaluable subjects with progressive urothelial cancer have been entered.
           2-3 patients per month may enroll on this trial; thus, 2 to 3 years is anticipated as
           the accrual period.

        -  Each patient will undergo response evaluation assessments with CAP CT (or MRI) with or
           without Na18F PET CT every 8 weeks while on active protocol therapy starting at
           baseline. Patients will undergo investigational FDG PET/CT and PET/MRI (optional) at
           baseline, week 4 and week 8.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>overall response rate</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>progression free survival, overall survival, tabulation of worst grade toxicity per patient</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">55</enrollment>
  <condition>Micropapillary Cancer of the Bladder</condition>
  <condition>Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Bladder</condition>
  <condition>Bladder Cancer With Bone Metastases</condition>
  <condition>Bladder Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Small Cell Cancer of the Bladder</condition>
  <condition>Urachal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Sarcomatoid Bladder Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cabozantinib</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FDG PET CT</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NaF PET CT</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Cohort 1 only (urothelial progressive disease)

          -  Patients must have a histologically confirmed diagnosis of urothelial carcinoma of
             the bladder, urethra, ureter, or renal pelvis. Confirmation may be obtained from any
             CLIA certified lab.

          -  Patients must have progressive metastatic disease. Progressive disease will be
             defined as new or progressive lesions on cross-sectional imaging.

          -  Patients must have at least one measurable site of disease

        Cohort 2 only (Bone-only)

          -  Patients must have a histologically confirmed diagnosis of urothelial carcinoma of
             the bladder, urethra, ureter, or renal pelvis. Confirmation may be obtained from any
             CLIA certified lab.

          -  Patients must not have measurable progressive disease

          -  Patient must have appearance of at least one new bone lesion.

        Cohort 3 (Rare histologies)

          -  Patient must have a histologically confirmed diagnosis of non-transitional cell
             carcinoma of the bladder, urethra, ureter, or renal pelvis including but not limited
             to squamous cell, neuroendocrine, adenocarcinoma including urachal and sarcomatoid.
             Confirmation may be obtained from any CLIA certified lab.

          -  Patients must have progressive metastatic disease. Progressive disease will be
             defined as new or progressive lesions on cross-sectional imaging.

          -  Patients must have at least one measurable site of disease

        All cohorts

          -  Patients must have been previously treated, as defined by treatment with at least one
             prior cytotoxic regimen or agent.

          -  Age greater than or equal to 18 years. Because no dosing or adverse event data are
             currently available on the use of cabozantinib in patients &lt; 18 years of age,
             children are excluded from this study, but may be eligible for future pediatric
             trials.

          -  ECOG performance status less than or equal to 2 (Karnofsky greater than or equal to
             60%

          -  Adequate organ function as defined by the following criteria:

          -  Hemoglobin greater than or equal to  9 g/dL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) greater than or equal to 1500/microL

          -  Platelets greater than or equal to 75,000/  L

          -  Serum aspartate transaminase (AST; serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase [SGOT])
             and serum alanine transaminase (ALT; serum glutamic pyruvic transaminase [SGPT]) less
             than or equal to 3.0 times upper limit of normal (ULN); less than or equal to  5.0
             times ULN in cases of liver metastases

          -  Total serum bilirubin less than or equal to 1.5 times the upper limit of normal
             (ULN). For subjects with known Gilbert   s disease or similar syndrome with slow
             conjugation of bilirubin, total bilirubin less than or equal to 3.0 mg/dL

          -  Serum creatinine less than or equal to 1.5 X institutional upper limits of normal or
             for patients with creatinine levels above 1.5 x institutional normal: creatinine
             clearance greater than or equal to 50 mL/min/1.73 m2 by 24 hour urine collection or
             estimated creatinine clearance of greater than or equal to 50 mL/min. For creatinine
             clearance estimation , the Cockcroft and Gault equation should be used:

          -  Male: CrCl (mL/min) = (140 - age) times wt (kg) / (serum creatinine times 72)

          -  Female: Multiply above result by 0.85

          -  Urine protein/creatinine ratio (UPCR) less than or equal to 2

          -  Patient must be able to provide either archival tumor samples (H&amp; E slides and one
             paraffin block or 10 unstained slides) or undergo tumor biopsy.

          -  Patient must be capable of understanding and complying with protocol requirements and
             is willing to give informed consent

          -  The effects of XL184 on the developing human fetus are unknown. For this reason and
             because tyrosine kinase inhibitors agents are known to be teratogenic, women of
             childbearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception  prior to
             study entry and for the duration of study participation. Should a woman become

        pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while she or her partner is participating in this
        study, she should inform her treating physician immediately. Men treated or enrolled on
        this protocol must also agree to use adequate contraception prior to the study, for the

        duration of study participation, and 4 months after completion of XL184 administration.

        Sexually active subjects (men and women) must agree to use medically accepted barrier
        methods of contraception (e.g., male or female condom) during the course of the study and
        for 4 months after the last dose of study drug(s), even if oral contraceptives are also
        used. All subjects of reproductive potential must agree to use both a barrier method and a
        second method of birth control during the course of the study and for 4 months after the
        last dose of study drug(s).

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test at screening.
             Women of childbearing potential include women who have experienced menarche and who
             have not undergone successful surgical sterilization (hysterectomy, bilateral tubal
             ligation, or bilateral oophorectomy) or are not postmenopausal. Postmenopause is
             defined as amenorrhea greater than or equal to 12 consecutive months. Note: women who
             have been amenorrheic for 12 or more months are still considered to be of
             childbearing potential if the amenorrhea is possibly due to prior chemotherapy,
             antiestrogens, ovarian suppression or any other reversible reason.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  The subject has received cytotoxic chemotherapy (including investigational cytotoxic
             chemotherapy) or biologic agents (eg, cytokines or antibodies) within 3 weeks, or
             nitrosoureas or mitomycin within 6 weeks before the first dose of study treatment.

          -  Prior treatment with cabozantinib

          -  Prior treatment with other small molecule inhibitors of VEGFR within less than or
             equal to 2 years of study enrollment.

          -  The subject has received radiation therapy:

          -  to the thoracic cavity or gastrointestinal tract within 3 months  before the first
             dose of study treatment

          -  to bone or brain metastasis within 14 days before the first dose of study treatment

          -  to any other site(s) within 28 days before the first dose of study treatment

          -  The subject has received radionuclide treatment within 6 weeks before the first dose
             of study treatment

          -  The subject has received prior treatment with a small molecule kinase inhibitor or a
             hormonal therapy (including investigational kinase inhibitors or hormones) within 14
             days or five half-lives of the compound or active metabolites, whichever is longer,
             before the first dose of study treatment.

          -  The subject has received any other type of investigational agent within 28 days
             before the first dose of study treatment.

          -  The subject has not recovered to baseline or CTCAE . Grade 1 from toxicity due to all
             prior therapies except alopecia and other non-clinically significant AEs.

          -  The subject has a primary brain tumor

          -  The subject has active brain metastases, leptomeningeal or epidural disease (Note:
             Subjects with brain metastases previously treated with whole brain radiation or
             radiosurgery or subjects with epidural disease previously treated with radiation or
             surgery who are asymptomatic and do not require steroid treatment for at least 2
             weeks before starting study treatment are eligible. Neurosurgical resection of brain
             metastases or brain biopsy is permitted if completed at least 3 months before
             starting study treatment. Baseline brain scans are not required to confirm
             eligibility.)

          -  The subject has prothrombin time (PT)/ International Normalized Ratio (INR) or
             partial thromboplastin time (PTT) test greater than or equal to 1.3 times the
             laboratory ULN within 7 days before the first

        dose of study treatment.

          -  The subject requires treatment, in therapeutic doses, with oral anticoagulants such
             as warfarin prior to initiation of protocol therapy. Low dose aspirin (less than or
             equal to 81 mg/day), lowdose warfarin (less than or equal to 1 mg/day), and low
             molecular weight heparin (LMWH) are permitted. Subjects will be permitted to use
             anticoagulation as described if treatment is required while they are enrolled on the
             protocol.

          -  The subject requires chronic concomitant treatment of strong CYP3A4 inducers (e.g.,
             dexamethasone, phenytoin, carbamazepine, rifampin, rifabutin, rifapentin,
             phenobarbital, and St. John's Wort).

        Because the lists of these agents are constantly changing, it is important to regularly
        consult a frequently-updated list such as http://medicine.iupui.edu/clinpharm/ddis/;
        medical reference texts such as the Physicians Desk Reference may also provide this

        information. As part of the enrollment/informed consent procedures, the patient will be
        counseled on the risk of interactions with other agents, and what to do if new medications
        need to be prescribed or if the patient is considering a new over-thecounter medicine or
        herbal product.

          -  The subject has experienced any of the following within 3 months before the first
             dose of study treatment:

          -  clinically-significant hematemesis or gastrointestinal bleeding

          -  hemoptysis of greater than or equal to 0.5 teaspoon (greater than or equal to 2.5 mL)
             of red blood

          -  any other signs indicative of pulmonary hemorrhage

          -  The subject has tumor invading (or concern for invasion) major blood vessels

          -  Other severe acute or chronic medical or psychiatric condition, or laboratory
             abnormality that may increase the risk associated with study participation or study
             drug administration, or may interfere with the interpretation of study results, and
             in the judgment of the Investigator would make the patient inappropriate for entry
             into this

        study.

          -  The subject has evidence of tumor invading the GI trac (esophagus, stomach, small or
             large bowel, rectum or anus), or any evidence of endotracheal or endobronchial tumor
             within 28 days before the first dose of cabozantinib.

          -  The subject has uncontrolled, significant intercurrent or recent illness including,
             but not limited to, the following conditions:

             a. Cardiovascular disorders including

             i. Congestive heart failure (CHF): New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class III
             (moderate) or Class IV (severe) at the time of screening

        ii. Concurrent uncontrolled hypertension defined as sustained BP &gt;  150 mm Hg systolic, or
        &gt;  90 mm Hg diastolic despite optimal antihypertensive treatment (BP must be controlled at
        screening)

        iii. Any history of congenital long QT syndrome

        iv. Any of the following within 6 months before the first dose of study treatment:

        - unstable angina pectoris

          -  clinically-significant cardiac arrhythmias

          -  stroke (including TIA, or other ischemic event)

          -  myocardial infarction

          -  thromboembolic event requiring therapeutic anticoagulation (Note:

        subjects with a venous filter (e.g. vena cava filter) are not eligible for this study)

        b. Gastrointestinal disorders particularly those associated with a high risk of
        perforation or fistula formation including:

        i. Any of the following within 28 days before the first dose of cabozantinib

          -  active peptic ulcer disease,

          -  active inflammatory bowel disease (including ulcerative colitis and

        Crohn   s disease), diverticulitis, cholecystitis, symptomatic cholangitis or appendicitis

          -  active malabsorption syndrome

        ii. Any of the following within 6 months before the first dose of study treatment:

          1. abdominal fistula

          2. gastrointestinal perforation

          3. bowel obstruction or gastric outlet obstruction

          4. intra-abdominal abscess. Note: Complete resolution of an intra-abdominal abscess must
             be confirmed prior to initiating treatment with cabozantinib even if the abscess
             occurred more than 6 months ago.

             c. Other disorders associated with a high risk of fistula formation including PEG
             tube placement within 3 months before the first dose of study therapy.

             d. Other clinically significant disorders such as:

             i. no active infection requiring parenteral antibiotics

        ii. serious non-healing wound/ulcer/bone fracture within 28 days before the first dose of
        study treatment

        iii. history of organ transplant

        iv. concurrent uncompensated hypothyroidism or thyroid dysfunction within 7 days before
        the first dose of study treatment

        v. history of major surgery as follows:

          1. Major surgery within 3 months of the first dose of cabozantinib if there were no
             wound healing complications or within 6 months of the first dose of cabozantinib if
             there were wound complications.

          2. Minor surgery within 1 months of the first dose of cabozantinib if there were no
             wound healing complications or within 3 months of the first dose of cabozantinib if
             there were wound complications

        In addition, complete wound healing from prior surgery must be confirmed at least 28 days
        before the first dose of cabozantinib irrespective of the time from surgery

          -  The subject is unable to swallow tablets

          -  The subject has a corrected QT interval calculated by the Fridericia formula (QTcF) &gt;
             500 ms within 28 days before treatment initiation.

          -  The subject has a previously identified allergy or hypersensitivity to components of
             the study treatment formulation.

          -  The subject is unable or unwilling to abide by the study protocol or cooperate fully
             with the investigator or designee.

          -  The subject has had within 2 years before the start of study treatment evidence of
             another malignancy which required systemic treatment

          -  HIV-positive patients on combination antiretroviral therapy are ineligible because of
             the potential for pharmacokinetic interactions with the study agents. In addition,
             these patients are at increased risk of lethal infections when treated with
             marrow-suppressive therapy. Appropriate studies will be undertaken in patients
             receiving combination antiretroviral therapy when indicated.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrea B Apolo, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kattie Khadar, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 435-4341</phone>
    <email>khadark@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Andrea B Apolo, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-1984</phone>
    <email>apoloab@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact National Cancer Institute Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>888-624-1937</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2012-C-0205.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://medicine.iupui.edu/clinpharm/ddis/</url>
    <description>http://medicine.iupui.edu/clinpharm/ddis/</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jemal A, Siegel R, Ward E, Hao Y, Xu J, Thun MJ. Cancer statistics, 2009. CA Cancer J Clin. 2009 Jul-Aug;59(4):225-49. Epub 2009 May 27.</citation>
    <PMID>19474385</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McCaffrey JA, Hilton S, Mazumdar M, Sadan S, Kelly WK, Scher HI, Bajorin DF. Phase II trial of docetaxel in patients with advanced or metastatic transitional-cell carcinoma. J Clin Oncol. 1997 May;15(5):1853-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9164195</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vaughn DJ, Broome CM, Hussain M, Gutheil JC, Markowitz AB. Phase II trial of weekly paclitaxel in patients with previously treated advanced urothelial cancer. J Clin Oncol. 2002 Feb 15;20(4):937-40.</citation>
    <PMID>11844814</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 14, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Bone Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Squamous Cell Carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Micropapillary Cancer of the Bladder</keyword>
  <keyword>Small Cell Cancer of the Bladder</keyword>
  <keyword>Urachal Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Sarcomatoid Bladder Cancer</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bone Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bone Marrow Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Small Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
