<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="141077">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01683383</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>22993</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01683383</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>California Transport Cooling Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>CTCT</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized Clinical Trial of Therapeutic Hypothermia During Transport for Hypoxic Ischemic Encephalopathy (HIE): Device-regulated Cooling Versus Standard Practice.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Inspiration Healthcare LTD UK</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hypoxic ischemic encephalopathy (HIE) remains a major cause of death and severe disability
      despite advances in neonatal and perinatal medicine. Therapeutic hypothermia is the single
      most promising intervention for HIE. Reduction of brain temperature by 2° to 5°C has shown
      to be neuroprotective in newborn and adult animal models of brain ischemia. Therapeutic
      hypothermia instituted within 6 hours of birth has been shown to significantly improve
      survival and neurodevelopmental outcome in term newborns with HIE. Hypothermia is most
      effective if begun during the latent period, before the secondary energy failure. It is not
      known whether cooling initiated after 6 hours of age is effective.

      The goal of this proposal is to test the efficacy of the cooling device in achieving the
      target temperatures in patients with moderate to severe HIE during transport when compared
      with current practices.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Statement of the Problem:

      Hypoxic ischemic encephalopathy (HIE) remains a major cause of death and severe disability
      despite advances in neonatal and perinatal medicine.  Therapeutic hypothermia is the single
      most promising intervention for HIE.  Reduction of brain temperature by 2° to 5°C has shown
      to be neuroprotective in newborn and adult animal models of brain ischemia.  Therapeutic
      hypothermia instituted within 6 hours of birth has been shown to significantly improve
      survival and neurodevelopmental outcome in term newborns with HIE.  Hypothermia is most
      effective if begun during the latent period, before secondary energy failure.  It is not
      known whether cooling initiated after 6 hours of age is effective.  Animal studies have
      shown that the sooner the initiation of cooling, the better the outcome.  They have also
      suggested that the latent period may be shorter with a more severe insult.  Cooling should
      be initiated as soon as possible, preferably within 2 hours and not later than 6 hours.
      There have been six large randomized clinical trials supporting the efficacy of therapeutic
      hypothermia for HIE and it is now the standard of care in the U.S.  and internationally.

      Once a patient qualifies for cooling, whole body cooling or selective head cooling is
      initiated.  However, most birth hospitals do not have the ability to provide therapeutic
      hypothermia; thus, patients must be transported to Level 3 NICUs specially equipped to
      provide this therapy.  As there is a limited therapeutic window for induction of
      hypothermia, it would be ideal to initiate therapeutic hypothermia as soon as the patient
      qualifies for cooling therapy.  If cooling is initiated at the birth hospital,
      neuroprotective temperatures can be achieved several hours prior to arrival in the cooling
      center.

      At this time patients cooled in transport receive passive cooling (turning off the active
      warming devices such as the transport isolette) or active cooling (ice packs placed around
      the baby).  These practices have been shown to present a significant risk for over-cooling
      and under-cooling.  The risks associated with excessive cooling include bradycardia, cardiac
      arrest, and coagulation disturbances.  Undercooling likely results in reduced efficacy of
      the neuroprotective effects provided by therapeutic hypothermia.

      Primary and secondary endpoints Primary end point: The percentage of temperatures in the
      target range (33°-34°C) both within and between enrolled infants after cooling initiation by
      the transport team.

      Secondary end point: Time to the target temperature range (33°-34°C), percentage of newborns
      in target temperature range one hour after cooling initiation by transport team, and
      temperature ranges.

      Study Design The proposed California Transport Cooling Trial (CTCT) is a prospective
      randomized multi-center clinical trial to be conducted by nine transport teams based at
      level III NICUs in California who perform therapeutic hypothermia for HIE.  The on-call
      neonatologist at the participating cooling center will determine if the infant qualifies for
      cooling.  Infants greater than or equal to 35 weeks and less than six hours of age who are
      being transported to a cooling center will be eligible.  The transport team will randomize
      the infant to either cooling as per center practice (Arm 1) or device-regulated cooling (Arm
      2).  Subjects in Arm 1 will receive passive or active cooling as per center practice with
      rectal temperatures being recorded every 15 minutes.  Subjects in Arm 2 will be placed on
      cooling blanket connected to the Tecotherm Neo.  Temperature will be monitored continuously
      and servo-regulated using a rectal temperature probe.  Pertinent clinical data will be
      collected using CPQCC/CPeTS data forms and CTCT data forms.  Temperatures from initiation of
      cooling until admission to the cooling center will be analyzed for percentage of
      temperatures in the target range after cooling initiation by the transport team, time to
      target temperature range, percentage of newborns in the target temperature range 1 hour
      after cooling initiation by the transport team, and temperature ranges.  ANOVA method will
      be used to compare the temperature ranges across arms.  Cox proportional hazard model will
      be used to compare time to target temperature.  Safety outcomes will be compared using
      standard logistic regression.

      Study Methods Subjects assigned to Arm 1 will be cooled as per the usual center practice
      with recording of rectal temperatures every 15 minutes.  Arm 2 subjects will be cooled using
      a portable servo-regulated cooling device using a rectal probe.  Temperatures will be stored
      on the memory card every minute.  No PHI will be stored in the cooling device.  Data will be
      downloaded from the device at the conclusion of the transport.

      Sample Size and Estimated Study Duration Power calculations for this study were based on
      anticipated 140 patients requiring initiation of therapeutic hypothermia by nine transport
      teams over a period of one year.  A 70% consent rate and 50 patients per arm will provide
      90% power to detect 30% absolute difference in the percentage of temperatures in the target
      range assuming a standard deviation for percentage of temperature in the target range of 45%
      based on the Kendall study, published in Archives of Diseases of Childhood in 2010.  All
      analyses will adjust for center and will be two-sided and conducted at the 0.05 level of
      significance.

      We estimate that patient enrollment will take approximately one year.  Data analysis,
      manuscript preparation, and submission will be completed within 6 months of completion of
      enrollment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of temperatures in target range</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of neonatal transport from the birth hospital to the cooling center, an expected average of 4 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The percentage of temperatures in the target range (33°-34°C) both within and between enrolled infants after cooling initiation by the transport team.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to target temperature</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of neonatal transport from the birth hospital to the cooling center, an expected average of 4 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Time to the target temperature range (33°-34°C) from initiation of cooling by the transport team</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of infants in the target range at 1 hour</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of neonatal transport from the birth hospital to the cooling center, an expected average of 4 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of infants in target range (33°-34°C) one hour after cooling initiation by the transport team</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Temperature ranges</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of neonatal transport from the birth hospital to the cooling center, an expected average of 4 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Range of temperatures during transport</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Safety outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of neonatal transport from the birth hospital to the cooling center, an expected average of 4 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The incidence, intervention and outcome  of cardiac arrhythmia, major bleeding, altered skin integrity, pulmonary hypertension, death and other serious adverse events from the time of initiation of transport cooling to the time of completion will be monitored</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypoxic Ischemic Encephalopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Practice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in Arm 1 will receive passive or active cooling as per center practice with rectal temperatures being recorded every 15 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Device regulated cooling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in Arm 2 will be placed on cooling blanket connected to the Tecotherm Neo (Inspiration Healthcare LTD UK). Temperature will be monitored continuously and servo-regulated using a rectal temperature probe.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Servo-regulated cooling device, Tecotherm Neo</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects in Arm 2 will be placed on a cooling blanket connected to the Tecotherm Neo. Temperatures will be monitored continuously and servo-regulated using a rectal temperature probe.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Device regulated cooling</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Practice</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects in Arm 1 will receive passive or active cooling as per center practice with rectal temperatures being recorded every 15 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Practice</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Term or near-term infants with gestational age ≥35 weeks who meet institutional
             criteria for use of therapeutic hypothermia and in whom the decision has been made to
             perform cooling during transport.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of a congenital or lethal chromosomal anomaly

          -  Decision to not provide full intensive care

          -  Refusal to consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>6 Hours</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Krisa Van Meurs, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Loma Linda University Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Loma Linda</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92354</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Central California</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madera</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>93636</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kaiser Permanente Oakland/Walnut Creek</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oakland</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital &amp; Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oakland</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94609</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sutter Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sacramento</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95819</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rady Childrens Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92123</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California San Francisco Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Santa Clara Valley Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Jose</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95128</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gunn AJ, Gunn TR, de Haan HH, Williams CE, Gluckman PD. Dramatic neuronal rescue with prolonged selective head cooling after ischemia in fetal lambs. J Clin Invest. 1997 Jan 15;99(2):248-56.</citation>
    <PMID>9005993</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vannucci RC, Perlman JM. Interventions for perinatal hypoxic-ischemic encephalopathy. Pediatrics. 1997 Dec;100(6):1004-14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9374573</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gluckman PD, Williams CE. When and why do brain cells die? Dev Med Child Neurol. 1992 Nov;34(11):1010-4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>1358734</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iwata O, Iwata S, Thornton JS, De Vita E, Bainbridge A, Herbert L, Scaravilli F, Peebles D, Wyatt JS, Cady EB, Robertson NJ. &quot;Therapeutic time window&quot; duration decreases with increasing severity of cerebral hypoxia-ischaemia under normothermia and delayed hypothermia in newborn piglets. Brain Res. 2007 Jun 18;1154:173-80. Epub 2007 Apr 1.</citation>
    <PMID>17475224</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gluckman PD, Wyatt JS, Azzopardi D, Ballard R, Edwards AD, Ferriero DM, Polin RA, Robertson CM, Thoresen M, Whitelaw A, Gunn AJ. Selective head cooling with mild systemic hypothermia after neonatal encephalopathy: multicentre randomised trial. Lancet. 2005 Feb 19-25;365(9460):663-70.</citation>
    <PMID>15721471</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eicher DJ, Wagner CL, Katikaneni LP, Hulsey TC, Bass WT, Kaufman DA, Horgan MJ, Languani S, Bhatia JJ, Givelichian LM, Sankaran K, Yager JY. Moderate hypothermia in neonatal encephalopathy: efficacy outcomes. Pediatr Neurol. 2005 Jan;32(1):11-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15607598</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shankaran S, Laptook AR, Ehrenkranz RA, Tyson JE, McDonald SA, Donovan EF, Fanaroff AA, Poole WK, Wright LL, Higgins RD, Finer NN, Carlo WA, Duara S, Oh W, Cotten CM, Stevenson DK, Stoll BJ, Lemons JA, Guillet R, Jobe AH; National Institute of Child Health and Human Development Neonatal Research Network. Whole-body hypothermia for neonates with hypoxic-ischemic encephalopathy. N Engl J Med. 2005 Oct 13;353(15):1574-84.</citation>
    <PMID>16221780</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Azzopardi DV, Strohm B, Edwards AD, Dyet L, Halliday HL, Juszczak E, Kapellou O, Levene M, Marlow N, Porter E, Thoresen M, Whitelaw A, Brocklehurst P; TOBY Study Group. Moderate hypothermia to treat perinatal asphyxial encephalopathy. N Engl J Med. 2009 Oct 1;361(14):1349-58. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2010 Mar 18;362(11):1056.</citation>
    <PMID>19797281</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simbruner G, Mittal RA, Rohlmann F, Muche R; neo.nEURO.network Trial Participants. Systemic hypothermia after neonatal encephalopathy: outcomes of neo.nEURO.network RCT. Pediatrics. 2010 Oct;126(4):e771-8. Epub 2010 Sep 20.</citation>
    <PMID>20855387</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jacobs SE, Morley CJ, Inder TE, Stewart MJ, Smith KR, McNamara PJ, Wright IM, Kirpalani HM, Darlow BA, Doyle LW; Infant Cooling Evaluation Collaboration. Whole-body hypothermia for term and near-term newborns with hypoxic-ischemic encephalopathy: a randomized controlled trial. Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med. 2011 Aug;165(8):692-700. doi: 10.1001/archpediatrics.2011.43. Epub 2011 Apr 4. PubMed PMID: 21464374.</citation>
    <PMID>21464374</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fairchild K, Sokora D, Scott J, Zanelli S. Therapeutic hypothermia on neonatal transport: 4-year experience in a single NICU. J Perinatol. 2010 May;30(5):324-9. Epub 2009 Oct 22.</citation>
    <PMID>19847186</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hallberg B, Olson L, Bartocci M, Edqvist I, Blennow M. Passive induction of hypothermia during transport of asphyxiated infants: a risk of excessive cooling. Acta Paediatr. 2009 Jun;98(6):942-6.</citation>
    <PMID>19484830</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Akula VP, Davis AS, Gould JB, Van Meurs K. Therapeutic hypothermia during neonatal transport: current practices in California. Am J Perinatol. 2012 May;29(5):319-26. doi: 10.1055/s-0031-1295661. Epub 2011 Dec 5.</citation>
    <PMID>22143969</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kendall GS, Kapetanakis A, Ratnavel N, Azzopardi D, Robertson NJ; Cooling on Retrieval Study Group. Passive cooling for initiation of therapeutic hypothermia in neonatal encephalopathy. Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed. 2010 Nov;95(6):F408-12. Epub 2010 Sep 24.</citation>
    <PMID>20870910</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 16, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 6, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Stanford University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Krisa P Van Meurs</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hypoxic ischemic encephalopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Therapeutic hypothermia</keyword>
  <keyword>Whole body cooling</keyword>
  <keyword>Transport cooling</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hypoxia-Ischemia, Brain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypoxia, Brain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Damage, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Delirium</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Encephalitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatic Encephalopathy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neurotoxicity Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
