<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="100821">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01890759</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MTA70</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1122-2171</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01890759</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immunogenicity and Safety of Menactra® Vaccine in Subjects Aged 9 to 23 Months in India and in the Russian Federation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Immunogenicity and Safety of a Meningococcal (Groups A, C, Y and W-135) Polysaccharide Diphtheria Toxoid Conjugate Vaccine (Menactra®) in Subjects Aged 9 to 23 Months in India and in the Russian Federation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sanofi Pasteur, a Sanofi Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sanofi</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>India: Drugs Controller General of India</authority>
    <authority>Russia: Ministry of Health of the Russian Federation</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess the immunogenicity and safety of Menactra® vaccine
      given as a two-dose series in infants and toddlers.

      Primary Objectives:

        -  To assess the seroprotection rate (percentage of subjects with a serum bactericidal
           assay using human complement [SBA-HC] titer ≥ 1:8) 28 days after the second of 2 doses
           of Menactra® administered 3 to 6 months apart.

      Secondary Objectives:

        -  To assess the immune responses to meningococcal antigens (serogroups A, C, Y, and
           W-135) 28 days following the second vaccination with Menactra® using SBA-HC and SBA-BR
           titers.

        -  To assess the safety profile of Menactra® after each and any vaccination.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study participants will receive 2 doses on Menactra® vaccine at 3 to 6 months apart and will
      be monitored for safety and immunogenicity.

      The planned duration of each subject's participation in the trial will be from 118 to 215
      days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with serum bactericidal assay using human complement [SBA-HC] titers ≥ 1:8  post vaccination with Menactra®</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28 post second vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Antibody titers measured by serum bactericidal assay using human complement (SBA-HC). Seroprotection defined as a post-vaccination titer of ≥ 1:8</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum Bovine Albumin Baby Rabbit and Human Complement Geometric Mean Titers Following Vaccination With Menactra® Vaccine</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28 post second vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Antibody titers measured by serum bactericidal assay using baby rabbit and human complement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with serum bactericidal assay using baby rabbits complement [SBA-BR] titers ≥ 1:8  post-vaccination with Menactra®</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28 post second vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Antibody titers measured by serum bactericidal assay using baby rabbit  complement (SBA-BR). Seroprotection defined as a post-vaccination titer of ≥ 1:8</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence and intensity of solicited injection site and systemic reactions and unsolicited adverse events occurring after each Menactra® vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 up to Month 6 post vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Solicited Injection site: Tenderness, Erythema and Swelling: Solicited Systemic: Fever (Temperature), Vomiting, Crying abnormal, Drowsiness, Appetite lost, and Irritability</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Meningitis</condition>
  <condition>Meningococcal Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants at age 9 to 17 months of enrollment will receive 2 doses on Menactra vaccine at 3 to 6 months apart</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Meningococcal (Groups A, C, Y and W-135) Polysaccharide Diphtheria Toxoid Conjugate Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>0.5 mL, Intramuscular</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Menactra®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and female subjects aged 9 to 17 months on the day of inclusion

          -  Informed consent form has been signed and dated by the parent(s) or other legally
             acceptable representative(s) (if applicable)

          -  Subject and parent/legally acceptable representative (if applicable) able to attend
             all scheduled visits and to comply with all trial procedures. Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participation in the 4 weeks preceding inclusion or planned participation during the
             present trial period in another clinical trial investigating a vaccine, drug, medical
             device, or medical procedure.

          -  Receipt of any vaccine in the 4 weeks preceding each trial vaccination or planned
             receipt of any vaccine in the 4 weeks following each trial vaccination, except for

          -  influenza vaccination, which may be received at least 2 weeks before study vaccines.

          -  measles (M) or measles, mumps, rubella (MMR) routine vaccination, which can be
             administered concomitantly with the first dose of study vaccine as per routine
             immunization schedule

          -  Previous vaccination against meningococcal disease with either the study vaccine or
             another meningococcal vaccine

          -  Receipt of immune globulins, blood or blood-derived products in the past 3 months

          -  Known or suspected congenital or acquired immunodeficiency; or receipt of
             immunosuppressive therapy, such as anti-cancer chemotherapy or radiation therapy,
             within the preceding 6 months; or long-term systemic corticosteroid therapy
             (prednisone or equivalent for more than 2 consecutive weeks within the past 3 months)

          -  History of meningococcal diseases, confirmed either clinically, serologically, or
             microbiologically

          -  At high risk, in the opinion of the Investigator, for meningococcal disease during
             the trial

          -  Known or suspected systemic hypersensitivity to any of the vaccine components, or
             history of a life-threatening reaction to the vaccine used in the trial or to a
             vaccine containing any of the same substances

          -  Known thrombocytopenia, contraindicating intramuscular vaccination

          -  Bleeding disorder, or receipt of anticoagulants in the 3 weeks preceding inclusion,
             contraindicating intramuscular vaccination

          -  In an emergency setting, or hospitalized involuntarily

          -  Chronic illness that, in the opinion of the investigator, is at a stage where it
             might interfere with trial conduct or completion

          -  For subjects enrolled at Indian sites: Moderate or severe acute illness/infection
             (according to investigator judgment) on the day of vaccination or febrile illness
             (temperature ≥ 38.0°C).

          -  For subjects enrolled at Russian sites: Acute disease of any severity on the day of
             vaccination or febrile illness (axillary temperature ≥ 37.0°C).

        A prospective subject should not be included in the study until the condition has resolved
        or the febrile event has subsided.

          -  Receipt of oral or injectable antibiotic therapy within 72 hours prior to the first
             blood draw

          -  Identified as a natural or adopted child of the Investigator or employee with direct
             involvement in the proposed study

          -  Personal history of Guillain-Barré Syndrome.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>9 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Sanofi Pasteur SA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Public Registry Sanofi Pasteur</last_name>
    <email>RegistryContactUs@sanofipasteur.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kolkata</city>
        <state>West Bengal</state>
        <zip>700017</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Lucknow</city>
        <zip>226003</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Ekaterinburg</city>
        <zip>620028</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Murmansk</city>
        <zip>183031</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Perm'</city>
        <zip>614066</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>St Pertersbourg</city>
        <zip>197022</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.sanofipasteur.com</url>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.sanofiaventis.com</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 27, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Meningitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Meningococcal Infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Menactra®</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Meningitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Meningococcal Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
