<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="38683">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02147522</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AD-1304-7364</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02147522</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Helping Hand Among Low-Income Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>AHH</acronym>
  <official_title>A Helping Hand (AHH) to Activate Patient-Centered Depression Care Among Low-Income Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Southern California</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Southern California</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Study Hypotheses (Ho) and Research Questions (RQ):

        -  Ho1. A Helping Hand (AHH) will significantly improve and sustain patient self-care
           management of depression and concurrent chronic illness management, Patient Assessment
           of Chronic Illness Care (PACIC) and Quality of Life vs UC at 6 and 12 months
           post-baseline.

        -  Ho2. AHH will significantly improve patient depression treatment acceptance/adherence
           and depression symptoms vs UC at 6 and 12 months post-baseline.

        -  RQ1. What is the association between depression symptoms and concurrent chronic illness
           status over time by group?

        -  RQ2. Will AHH reduce hospitalizations and Emergency Room visits and improve clinic
           appointment-keeping?

        -  RQ3. Will patient care satisfaction and reported barriers to self-care management vary
           by study group?

        -  RQ4. What factors are identified via qualitative assessments of patients, promotoras,
           Department of Health Services (DHS) medical and social work providers, and DHS
           clinic/organizational leadership regarding satisfaction with, sustainable uptake of,
           and suggested modifications of the AHH promotora delivery model?

        -  RQ5. What potential technology applications would enhance promotoras delivering
           patient-centered self-care training and resource navigation, communicating and
           integrating care with DHS, and disseminating AHH?
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Major depression, plus other chronic illness such as diabetes, coronary heart disease and
      heart failure is common among low-income, culturally diverse safety net care patients.
      Unfortunately, many of these patients are uncomfortable about either asking their doctor
      questions about their illness and treatment options and their illness self-care or informing
      their doctors about their treatment preferences. Lack of strong engagement with medical
      providers occurs because patients believe they lack the knowledge to ask questions or to
      understand and follow recommended self-care and their concern that their medical provider
      lacks understanding of their treatment preferences. These factors often result in patient
      worry, poor adherence to prescribed treatment, and worsening illness status and even early
      death. The study will be conducted by a university, the Los Angeles County Department of
      Health Services (DHS) and a community health worker organization research team. The study
      will be conducted within two DHS Patient-Centered Medical Home clinics, with each patient
      having a designated primary care team of physician, nurse, social worker and medical
      assistant. Study patients with major depression and other illnesses face numerous self-care
      management barriers: managing concurrent symptoms (depression, pain, anxiety etc.) and
      cultural influences (depression stigma, diet), difficulty in navigating primary and
      specialty doctor and treatment plans, while at the same time experiencing daily social and
      economic stress. The randomized comparative effectiveness study will recruit 350 patients
      with major depression and a concurrent chronic illness (i.e., diabetes, heart failure,
      coronary heart disease) from two DHS PCMH community health centers. To enhance
      patient-centered research community partnerships, patients will be provided A Helping Hand
      (AHH) in which a community organization- based promotora aims to activate patient-centered
      depression self-care training and practical assistance to: a) improve and personalize major
      depression self-care (e.g., medication or psychotherapy preference, treatment adherence,
      fatigue, pain, diet, activity, stress management, family/caregiver communication); b)
      activate patient-provider communication, clinic appointment keeping and treatment
      coordination; and c) and facilitate patient navigation and receipt of needed community
      resources. AHH aims to improve patient self-care management and patient-provider care
      management relationships among underserved low-income patients, who must simultaneously cope
      with major depression and chronic co-morbid physical illness. Study objectives aim to
      determine: 1) whether community health worker promotora care management training improves
      patient-centered outcomes, such as self-care need and management, treatment adherence,
      symptom improvement, and care satisfaction over the usual team care; 2) depression symptom
      improvement; and 3) patient hospitalizations and ER visits frequency.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PHQ-9</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12-month follow up.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The PHQ-9, which establishes provisional depressive disorder diagnosis as well as grades depressive symptom severity, will be obtained from all study subjects at recruitment and during the four waves of data collection (up to 12 months). The PHQ-9 scores each of the 9 DSM-IV criteria as &quot;0&quot; (not at all) to &quot;3&quot; (nearly every day), with possible scores ranging from 0 to 27, with cut points of 5,10,15, and 20 representing the thresholds for mild, moderate, moderately severe, and severe depression. A validated Spanish version of the PHQ-9 will be used.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MOS Short-Form Health Survey (SF-12)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 6- and 12-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Norm-based scores standardized to the general U.S. population with a mean of 50, and a SD of 10 will be administered at baseline and follow-up calls. The SF-12 includes one measure of pain impact that asks respondents to rate pain interference with normal work on a scale from none (1) to extremely (5).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Efficacy for Managing Chronic Disease 6-item Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 6- and 12-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Contains items that are common across chronic diseases: symptom control, role function, emotional functioning and communicating with physicians</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">350</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Heart Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A Helping Hand (AHH)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Self-care management to enhance chronic disease self-care management via telephone or home visits. AHH intervention: depression psycho-education,  behavior activation, medication management, resource navigation, communication with health care providers; healthy eating, physical activity, sleep health, pain and fatigue, managing conflicts with family/caregivers.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This UC has available DHS medical providers and social workers  for depression care and refer patients when indicated to community mental health clinics. Problem-Solving Therapy (PST) is available in some of participating clinics and PST have been shown to be effective and well-received by similar safety net patients in our previous studies of patients with cancer, diabetes or heart failure and coronary heart disease.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Self-care management</intervention_name>
    <description>The behavioral intervention is provided by promotoras</description>
    <arm_group_label>A Helping Hand (AHH)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age &gt;18 years, have a phone, meet PHQ-9 score of 10 or more, and have concurrent
             diabetes, CHD, or HF.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  current suicidal ideation,inability to speak either English or Spanish fluently, a
             score of 2 or greater on the CAGE 4M alcohol assessment,recent use of lithium or
             antipsychotic medication, and cognitive impairment precluding informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kathleen Ell, DSW</last_name>
    <phone>760-200-3961</phone>
    <email>ell@usc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Los Angeles County Department of Health Services</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jeffery Guterman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>818-364-3611</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jeffery Guterman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 23, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 19, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Southern California</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kathleen R. Ell</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>community health worker</keyword>
  <keyword>promotoras</keyword>
  <keyword>self-care behaviors activation</keyword>
  <keyword>depression</keyword>
  <keyword>low-income patients</keyword>
  <keyword>safety-net care</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
