<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="147852">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01702987</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>010-31415</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01702987</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Ubiquinol on Mitochondrial Oxidative Capacity in Statin Patients Using 31PMRS</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Ubiquinol on the Association of Statins and Mitochondrial Oxidative Capacity Using 31P Magnetic Resonance Imaging</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      It is our primary hypothesis that statin drugs impair skeletal muscle mitochondrial function
      and that ubiquinol (the reduced active form of CoQ10) supplementation will block impairment
      of PCr recovery kinetics in patients using statins. The investigators propose a pilot study
      to extend our research to examine PCr recovery kinetics in 20 statin users randomized in a
      parallel arm study to either ubiquinol or placebo over 4 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Synopsis: There are important gaps in our understanding of the pathogenesis and management
      of statin-associated myalgia. Data suggest that statins block the production of CoQ10, an
      essential component in electron transport during oxidative phosphorylation leading to
      mitochondrial dysfunction.  Preliminary data suggest that CoQ10 dietary supplements may
      improve statin-associated muscle symptoms; however, correlation with plasma CoQ10 and
      objective tests to assess statin-associated myalgia and response to treatment are lacking.

      Phosphorus-31 magnetic resonance spectroscopy (31P-MRS) is unique in its ability to study,
      continuously and non-invasively, the biochemical pathways for the supply and utilization of
      energy in muscle. The post-exercise recovery rate of skeletal muscle phosphocreatine (PCr)
      is a validated index of mitochondrial oxidative capacity in vivo. In a preliminary study, we
      measured PCr recovery kinetics following exercise, using 31P-MRS before and after initiating
      statin therapy and found that the return to metabolic equilibrium was longer after 4 weeks
      of statin therapy, suggesting mitochondrial impairment. i

      It is our primary hypothesis that statin drugs impair skeletal muscle mitochondrial function
      and that ubiquinol supplementation will block impairment of PCr recovery kinetics in
      patients using statins. We propose a pilot study to extend our research to examine PCr
      recovery kinetics in 20 statin users randomized in a parallel arm study to either ubiquinol
      or placebo over 4 weeks.

      This study will include 10 individuals with statin myalgia on confirmed statin rechallenge
      (5 assigned to each arm), to be recruited from an ongoing clinical trial in which statin
      users with suspected statin myalgia (based on clinical history) undergo an observed statin
      re-challenge to confirm statin myalgia. Confirmation by re-challenge is important, as only
      about one-third to one-half of those who report a clinical history of statin myalgia
      demonstrate statin myalgia, confirmed by improvement of symptoms when statin is discontinued
      and return of symptoms when undergoing an observed statin re-challenge. ii

      Our team is unique in 1) having demonstrated the feasibility to perform 31P-MRS studies in
      patients with hypercholesterolemia and 2) having access to individuals that have proven
      statin myalgia on standardized observed statin-rechallenge. We believe that the data
      obtained from this study will provide the critical data needed to support application to the
      NIH for a full-scale clinical trial exploring the relationship between statin use, PCr
      recovery rate, and ubiquinol therapy.

      Aims:

        1. o Aim: To compare the effects of ubiqunol on post exercise PCr recovery kinetics.

           We hypothesize that statin users randomized to 300 mg of ubiquinol twice daily will
           demonstrate shorter PCr recovery kinetics following exercise compared to statin users
           randomized to placebo.

        2. o Aims:  To assess the association between plasma CoQ10 and 1) post exercise PCr
           recovery kinetics and 2) inflammatory and vascular biomarkers We hypothesize that lower
           plasma CoQ10 concentrations will be associated with longer PCr recovery kinetics and
           lower inflammatory/vascular biomarkers.

      Exploratory Aims: In each arm we aim to include 5 individuals with previously confirmed
      statin myalgia on statin rechallenge and to explore differences among statin users with and
      without statin myalgia. We will evaluate for trends to assess whether statin users with
      previously confirmed statin myalgia show longer PCr recovery kinetics compared to statin
      users without statin myalgia.

      Study Design:  A pilot randomized placebo-controlled double-blinded study (pre-post statin
      use) comparing the effects of ubiquinol on post exercise PCr recovery kinetics over 4 weeks.

      Background and Rationale Statins, HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors are generally safe; however,
      myalgia (e.g., pain, cramping, muscle soreness and/or weakness) occurs in about 5% of users
      iii,iv and can seriously impact quality of life and adherence to statin medications.
      Furthermore, there are no objective, non-invasive method for assessing and tracking
      mild-moderate muscle symptoms, which are most common and often occur without significant
      muscle enzyme &quot;CK&quot; elevation. Muscle biopsy is used to assess severe myopathy and has been
      used to evaluate statin myalgia without CK elevation, but is invasive, painful, and provides
      only a single time point measurement.

      In contrast to invasive muscle biopsy, 31P-MRS is a non-invasive and validated technique
      that has been applied to study the metabolic processes in skeletal muscle in many muscle
      applications and diseases.v,vi  The rate of PCr recovery following exercise is an accepted
      gold standard for measuring mitochondrial function.

      We propose to apply 31P-MRS to the important problem of statin-associated myalgia to measure
      the rate of PCr recovery following exercise in statin users before and after statin therapy
      (with concurrent randomization to ubiquinol or placebo). Ultimately, we believe this work
      could have an important impact on the care and management of those with statin myalgia by 1)
      elucidating the relationship between muscle symptoms and mitochondrial function through a
      quantifiable, validated and non-invasive biochemical index and 2) by determining the effects
      of supplemental ubiquinol on mitochondrial function and muscle side effects in statin users.

      Methods We will measure the rate of PCr resynthesis (the time constant of PCr recovery)
      following a controlled exercise protocol that will recruit muscles in the lower leg.  We
      will evaluate muscle symptoms using a standardized questionnaire and measure muscle strength
      using an ergometer that was designed to apply a controlled variable pressure to a foot pedal
      through a pneumatic cylinder. We will perform baseline measurements after participants have
      been taken off statin medications and CoQ10 supplements (if applicable) for at least 2
      weeks. Additionally, those with statin myalgia will have improvement of symptoms before
      baseline measures are taken. Following baseline testing, statin therapy+ubiquinol or statin
      therapy+placebo will be given to participants for 4 weeks. Repeat measurements will be
      performed at 4 weeks to compare the effects of statins+placebo versus statin+ubiquinol on
      PCr resynthesis.  The primary outcome of this study will be the PCr recovery time constant.
      The post-exercise PCr recovery measurements will be performed in our MRI research facility
      using our dedicated 3T research MR scanner. Assessment of safety outcomes (CK, AST, ALT),
      and physiological parameters (BP, HR, height and weight measured), and blood measures of
      lipids and biomarkers (CRP, IL-6, TNF- α, E-selectin, VCAM-1, ICAM-1) will be collected on
      site and analyzed at the Harvard Catalyst Clinical Research Center (CRC) Core laboratory.
      Analysis of reduced and oxidized plasma CoQ10 will be performed at a qualified outside lab
      with a strong track record of using validated methods.

      Data Analysis Statistical Analysis: Each subject will have PCr concentration collected at
      the following 2 time points: pre-statin (t1), and after 4-weeks of statin therapy (with
      ubiquinol or placebo) (t2). At each of these time points, a series of measurements of PCr
      concentration are collected. For each subject, we will estimate this parameter using maximum
      likelihood estimation method. Thus we will obtain the point estimate and standard error for
      the time constant parameter for each subject at each of the time points. We will compute the
      relative percent change from baseline to post-statin (ubiquinol vs. placebo) time points and
      a linear mixed effects model to obtain the estimate of the relative change from baseline and
      the relative change between the post-statin time point. The linear mixed effects model, with
      the compound symmetry structure for the variance-covariance matrix of the within-subject PCr
      relative changes from baseline takes into account the within-subject correlation. The
      estimation of the linear mixed-effects model will be done via restricted maximum likelihood
      method. The PCr recovery time constant will be calculated using a monoexponential fit of PCr
      versus time, beginning at exercise completion and will be compared between the groups.

      Additional analyses will be performed to assess associations between plasma CoQ10 (adjusted
      for LDL) and PCr data, inflammatory and vascular biomarkers, measured muscle strength (in
      all), and reported symptoms (among those with statin myalgia).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>phosphocreatine recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Phosphocreatine recovery as measured by 31PMRS is the primary outcome measure is a representative of mitochondrial oxidative capacity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Myopathy</condition>
  <condition>HMG COA Reductase Inhibitor Adverse Reaction</condition>
  <condition>Hypercholesterolemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Statin + placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>10 patients taking statin medications and placebo.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Statin + ubiquinol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>10 patients on statins and ubiquinol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ubiquinol</intervention_name>
    <description>ubiquinol supplementation will be given for 1 month to 10 patients</description>
    <arm_group_label>Statin + ubiquinol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>coenzyme Q10</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>placebo (identical in appearance to ubiquinol)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Statin + placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>statin</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Statin + placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Statin + ubiquinol</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Persons age 18 years and older who have been advised to use a statin medication by
             their physician.

          2. Up to ten individuals will have a history of statin myalgia on observed statin
             rechallenge. All others will have a history (&gt;6 months) of tolerating a statin at a
             standard starting dose or higher.

          3. All persons will be able to cooperate for a period of 1-2 hours, able to provided
             informed consent and have no known adverse effects or contraindications to an MRI
             study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Having diabetes or known lower extremity peripheral vascular disease, as these
             conditions may interfere with interpretation of the MRI spectroscopy of the lower
             extremity (the only site we are examining in this study).

          2. Current users of a statin with a recent heart attack, stroke, or revascularization
             procedure (within the last 1 year) who could be at higher risk of stopping a statin.

          3. Creatine kinase (CK) &gt; 5 x ULN. If CK levels are greater than 3 x ULN, the
             participant will be given the option of returning for a repeat blood draw at their
             earliest convenience. Any elevation in CK will be treated per the safety guidelines
             outlined in section B5.

          4. Alanine transferase (ALT) or aspartate transferase (AST)  &gt; 3 x ULN. If ALT and/or
             AST levels are greater than 3 x ULN, the participant will return for a repeat blood
             draw at their earliest convenience. If the participant's ALT and/or AST is found
             elevated at this repeat analysis, they will be withdrawn from the study. Any
             elevation in ALT and/or AST will be treated per the safety guidelines outlined in
             section B5.

          5. Severe uncontrolled medical problems or medications that may influence measurements
             or impair ability to participate in the study exams (e.g. poorly controlled
             hypertension; (&gt;170/&gt;100); known creatinine &gt; 2.5 md/dl or GFR &lt; 30; anemia with Hgb
             &lt; 10, etc.).

          6. Pregnancy or breastfeeding (a contraindication for statin use)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jim S Wu, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Beth Israel Deaconess</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jim S Wu, MD</last_name>
    <phone>617-667-1283</phone>
    <email>jswu@bidmc.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Catherine Buettner, MD</last_name>
    <email>cbuettne@bidmc.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jim S Wu, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-667-1283</phone>
      <email>jswu@bidmc.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Allison Glasgow</last_name>
      <phone>617-66-70324</phone>
      <email>alglasgo@bidmc.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jim S Wu, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu JS, Buettner C, Smithline H, Ngo LH, Greenman RL. Evaluation of skeletal muscle during calf exercise by 31-phosphorus magnetic resonance spectroscopy in patients on statin medications. Muscle Nerve. 2011 Jan;43(1):76-81. doi: 10.1002/mus.21847.</citation>
    <PMID>21171098</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 13, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 5, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jim S Wu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor Department of Radiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ubiquinol (coenzyme Q10)</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hypercholesterolemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Muscular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Coenzyme Q10</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ubiquinone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydroxymethylglutaryl-CoA Reductase Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
