<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="33444">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01884519</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>200160</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-000855-42</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01884519</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immunogenicity and Safety Study of GlaxoSmithKline (GSK) Biologicals' Influenza Vaccine, Fluarix®/Influsplit SSW® (2013/2014 Season), in Adults 18 Years of Age and Older</brief_title>
  <official_title>Study for Evaluation of Immunogenicity and Reactogenicity of Fluarix/Influsplit SSW 2013/2014 in People 18 Years of Age and Above</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Paul-Ehrlich-Institut, Federal Institute for Vaccines and Biomedicines</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess, in adults 18 years of age and above, the
      immunogenicity and reactogenicity of the seasonal influenza vaccine, Fluarix/Influsplit SSW
      2013/2014, containing the three vaccine influenza strains (two A strains and one B strain)
      for the 2013/2014 season.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Humoral immune response in terms of anti-HA antibodies against each of the three vaccine influenza strains</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 0</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Humoral immune response in terms of anti-HA antibodies against each of the three vaccine influenza strains</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 21</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of solicited local and general symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>During a 4-day follow-up period after vaccination (Days 0-3) (i.e. day of vaccination and 3 subsequent days)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage, intensity and duration of solicited local symptoms during a 4-day follow-up period after vaccination. Percentage, intensity, duration and relationship to vaccination of solicited general symptoms during a 4-day follow-up period after vaccination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of unsolicited symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>During a 21-day follow-up period after vaccination (Days 0-20) (i.e. day of vaccination and 20 subsequent days)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage, intensity and relationship to vaccination of unsolicited symptoms during a 21-day follow-up period after vaccination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of serious adverse events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>During the entire study period (Day 0-Day 21)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Humoral immune response in terms of anti-HA antibodies against each of the 3 vaccine influenza strains, in subjects aged 18-60 years &amp; &gt;60 years who have &amp; who have not received an influenza vaccine during the 2 influenza seasons prior to season 2012/13</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 0</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Humoral immune response in terms of anti-HA antibodies against each of the 3 vaccine influenza strains,in subjects aged 18-60 years &amp; &gt;60 years who have &amp; who have not received an influenza vaccine during the 2 influenza seasons prior to season 2012/13</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 21</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Adult Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects 18-60 years of age receiving Fluarix/Influsplit SSW 2013-2014</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Elderly Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects aged &gt;60 years of age receiving Fluarix/Influsplit SSW 2013-2014</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluarix/Influsplit SSW® (2013-2014 season)</intervention_name>
    <description>Single dose administered intramuscularly in the deltoid region of the non-dominant arm</description>
    <arm_group_label>Elderly Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Adult Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who the investigator believes can and will comply with the requirements of
             the protocol.

          -  A male or female aged 18 years or above at the time of vaccination.

          -  Written informed consent obtained from the subject.

          -  Healthy subjects or subjects with well-controlled chronic diseases as established by
             medical history and clinical examination before entering the study.

          -  Female subjects of non-childbearing potential may be enrolled in the study.

               -  Non-childbearing potential is defined as pre-menarche, current tubal ligation,
                  hysterectomy, ovariectomy or post-menopause.

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential may be enrolled in the study, if the
             subject:

               -  has practiced adequate contraception for 30 days prior to vaccination, and

               -  has a negative pregnancy test on the day of vaccination, and

               -  has agreed to continue adequate contraception during the entire treatment period
                  and for 2 months after completion of vaccination.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participation in previous year's Fluarix registration study (116663).

          -  Use of any investigational or non-registered product (drug or vaccine) other than the
             study vaccine within 30 days preceding the dose of study vaccine, or planned use
             during the study period.

          -  Chronic administration of immunosuppressants or other immune-modifying drugs within
             the six months prior to vaccination. Inhaled and topical steroids are allowed.

          -  Any administration of a long-acting immune-modifying drug within 6 months before
             study start, or planned administration during the study period.

          -  Administration of immunoglobulins and/or any blood products within the three months
             preceding the administration of the study vaccine or planned administration during
             the study period.

          -  Administration of an influenza vaccine within the twelve months preceding the study
             vaccination.

          -  Receipt of a vaccine other than the study vaccine within 30 days before study
             vaccination and/or plan to receive any vaccine other than the study vaccine during
             the entire study period.

          -  Clinically or virologically confirmed influenza infection within the six months
             preceding the study vaccination.

          -  Acute disease and/or fever at the time of enrollment.

               -  Fever is defined as temperature ≥ 37.5°C/99.5°F on oral, axillary or tympanic
                  setting, or ≥ 38.0°C/100.4°F on rectal setting. The preferred route for
                  recording temperature in this study will be axillary.

               -  Subjects with a minor illness (such as mild diarrhoea, mild upper respiratory
                  infection) without fever may be enrolled at the discretion of the investigator.

          -  Acute, clinically significant pulmonary, cardiovascular, hepatic or renal functional
             abnormality, as determined by physical examination or laboratory screening tests.

          -  Chronic underlying disease (such as cancer, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease
             under oxygen therapy, insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus), not stabilized or
             clinically serious.

          -  History of chronic alcohol consumption and/or drug abuse.

          -  Any confirmed or suspected immunosuppressive or immunodeficient condition, based on
             medical history and physical examination (no laboratory testing required).

          -  History of Guillain-Barré syndrome.

          -  History of allergic disease or reactions likely to be exacerbated by any component of
             the vaccine including latex.

          -  Anaphylaxis following the administration of vaccine(s).

          -  Pregnant or lactating female.

          -  Female planning to become pregnant or planning to discontinue contraceptive
             precautions.

          -  Any condition which, in the opinion of the investigator, prevents the subject from
             participating in the study or would make intramuscular injection unsafe.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dresden</city>
        <state>Sachsen</state>
        <zip>01307</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Freiberg</city>
        <state>Sachsen</state>
        <zip>09599</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Freital</city>
        <state>Sachsen</state>
        <zip>01705</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Schmiedeberg</city>
        <state>Sachsen</state>
        <zip>01762</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 14, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 13, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Elderly</keyword>
  <keyword>Influenza</keyword>
  <keyword>Safety</keyword>
  <keyword>Adults</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunogenicity</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
