<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="159605">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01706094</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HeadPoST1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01706094</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Head Position in Stroke Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>HeadPoST-Pilot</acronym>
  <official_title>Head Position in Stroke Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Clinica Alemana de Santiago</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The George Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Clinica Alemana de Santiago</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Chile: Instituto de Salud Pública de Chile</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A simplest manner to augment cerebral blood flow to irrigate the ischemic penumbra in acute
      ischemic stroke could be to place the patient in a 'flat down' rather than upright head
      position.  Given uncertainty over the balance of potential modest benefits and risks, and
      variability regarding the ideal head position policy for patients with acute ischemic stroke
      around the world, reliable randomized evidence is required to standardize clinical practice.

      The main objectives of this pilot phase clinical trial are  to determine the feasibility,
      safety and potential efficacy of a large-scale cluster randomized clinical trial to assess
      whether a simple nursing care policy - 'flat down head position' - provides beneficial
      effects as compared to the standard upright head position in patients with acute ischemic
      stroke.  The main efficacy outcome of the pilot phase is demonstration of increased mean
      cerebral blood flow velocity in the flat down compared to the upright head position, as
      assessed by transcranial Doppler to the medial cerebral arteries of patients with anterior
      circulation infarction.  Secondary efficacy objectives are to demonstrate that the flat down
      head position improves neurological status at 7 days and disability at 90 days.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:  Several lines of investigation indicate there to be potential beneficial
      effects of interventions that augment cerebral blood flow (CBF) to irrigate the ischemic
      penumbra in acute ischemic stroke.  The simplest manner to do this is to place the patient
      in a 'flat down' rather than upright head position.  However, any potential benefits on the
      brain may be offset by an increased hazard of aspiration pneumonia or exacerbation of
      cardiac failure in vulnerable patients.  Given uncertainty over the balance of potential
      modest benefits and risks, and variability regarding the ideal head position policy for
      patients with acute ischemic stroke around the world, reliable randomized evidence is
      required to standardize clinical practice.

      Aims:  The main objectives of this pilot phase clinical trial are  to determine the
      feasibility, safety and potential efficacy of a large-scale cluster randomized clinical
      trial to assess whether a simple nursing care policy - 'flat down head position' - provides
      beneficial effects as compared to the standard upright head position in patients with acute
      ischemic stroke.  The main efficacy outcome of the pilot phase is demonstration of increased
      mean cerebral blood flow velocity (CBFV) in the flat down compared to the upright head
      position, as assessed by transcranial Doppler (TCD) to the medial cerebral arteries of
      patients with anterior circulation infarction.  Secondary efficacy objectives are to
      demonstrate that the flat down head position improves neurological status at 7 days and
      disability at 90 days.

      Methods:  Inclusion criteria include consecutive adult patients with acute ischemic stroke
      within 12 hours of onset admitted to participating centers.  A cluster (month) method of
      randomization to flat down or upright head position for 48 hours, stratified by site  The
      primary outcome is change in mean CBFV measured by TCD at 24 hours.  Secondary outcomes
      include proportion of adverse events at 7 days, distribution of NIHSS at 7 days, and
      distribution of mRS disability scale scores at 90 days.  Sample size is 16 clusters of 12
      patients totaling approximately 200 patients to detect an increase of 8.3 (±17) cm/sec in
      average CBFV from 30° to 0° head position.  This sample size will also allow detection of a
      30% increase in average CBFV from baseline with 80% power at a 5% significance level.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Increased mean cerebral blood flow velocity (CBFV) in the flat down compared to the upright head position</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The main efficacy outcome of the pilot phase is demonstration of increased mean cerebral blood flow velocity (CBFV) in the flat down compared to the upright head position, as assessed by transcranial Doppler (TCD) to the medial cerebral arteries of patients with anterior circulation infarction.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>proportion of Serious adverse events.</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessments of Serious adverse events at 7 days comparing between the two head positioning groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Functional outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days and 90 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Secondary efficacy outcome are to demonstrate that the flat down head position improves neurological status at 7 days and disability at 90 days, measured by modified Rankin Scale, in person or by telephone.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Ischemic Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>flat down head position</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>positioning the head of the bed at zero degrees during the first 48 hours from admission of patients with acute ischemic stroke Active Comparator: upright position of the head of the bed during 48 hours from admission of patients with acute ischemic stroke</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Head Position</intervention_name>
    <description>Head position during the first 48 hours from admission of patients with acute ischemic stroke.
This trial is organized as a cluster randomised trial to a policy of flat head position or upright head position. Clusters will be months, so that all patients admitted during a given month will be positioned either in the flat down head position (intervention) or upright head position (control).  This will allow health teams to follow a monthly protocol without changing position between patients.</description>
    <arm_group_label>flat down head position</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18 or more years old

          -  Patients with an acute stroke corresponding to anterior circulation, a CT scan ruling
             out intracranial hemorrhage, presenting within 12 hours from symptom onset

          -  NIHSS ≥1

          -  Susceptible to be tilted down to the flat position or to 30º of the head

          -  There is uncertainty about the benefit/harm of head position during a minimum of 24
             hours.

          -  Informed consent given

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Contraindications to a flat head position (active vomiting, pneumonia, uncontrolled
             heart failure)

          -  Concomitant medical illness that would interfere with outcome assessment and
             follow-up

          -  Planned decompressive craniectomy or carotid endarterectomy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Veronica V Olavarria, MD, Msc</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Clinica Alemana de Santiago, Chile.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Veronica V Olavarria, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>56 2 22101111</phone>
    <phone_ext>3557</phone_ext>
    <email>volavarria@alemana.cl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Pablo M Lavados, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>56 2 22101111</phone>
    <phone_ext>6158</phone_ext>
    <email>pablolavados@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinica Alemana de Santiago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santiago</city>
        <state>Region Metropolitana</state>
        <country>Chile</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Veronica V Olavarria, MD, Msc</last_name>
      <phone>56 2 22101111</phone>
      <phone_ext>3557</phone_ext>
      <email>veroolavarria@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Pablo M Lavados, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>56 2 22101111</phone>
      <phone_ext>6158</phone_ext>
      <email>pablolavados@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pablo M Lavados, MD, MPH, Stroke Unit Director</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Chile</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 15, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 11, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Clinica Alemana de Santiago</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Veronica V Olavarria</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, MSc</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>head position</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
