<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="112536">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01795066</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4-2012-0856</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01795066</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Endoscopic Ultrasound-guided Fine Needle Biopsy With 25-gauge Biopsy Needles for Solid Pancreatic Masses</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yonsei University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Yonsei University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Korea: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      For 12 months after approvement by the University of Yonsei institutional review board, of
      the 59 patients older than 20 years referred to our medical center for EUS-FNA or FNB, all
      consecutive pancreatic lesions were evaluated for inclusion in our prospective study. The
      inclusion criteria for this study were the following: diagnosed or suspected solid
      pancreatic masses according to clinical evaluation and imaging studies with need of
      histologic tissue confirmation by EUS-FNA or EUS-FNB. The exclusion criteria were the
      following: cystic pancreatic lesions, patients haemodynamically unstable or with severe
      coagulopathy (international normalized ratio [INR] &gt; 1.5 or platelet count &lt; 50,000
      cells/cubic millimeter [cmm3]), patients unable to suspend anticoagulant/anti-platelet
      therapy, pregnancy, inability or refusal to give informed consent, and refusal to
      participate in the study. Patients undergoing anticoagulant or anti- platelet therapy for
      non-critical problems discontinued treatment at least 5 days before the endoscopic
      procedure. Written informed consent was obtained from all patients for the procedures
      performed and participation in the study, and the study protocol was approved by the
      University of Yonsei institutional review board. All patients were underwent the procedure
      under conscious sedation with propofol and midazolam according to the current guidelines.8
      After procedure, the patients were monitored for at least six hours in order to immediately
      detect post-procedural complications and were followed for up to 7 days in order to detect
      late complications.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>accessing the rate for procurement of the histologic core</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 minuites after endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine needle biopsy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The tissue samples were immediately fixed in formalin. The histologic cassette was processed, embedded in paraffin, and then prepared in hematoxylin and eosin to be evaluated by one pathologist (K.H.K) for the presence of a histologic core. If the histologic core was present, the specimen was graded as optimal or suboptimal. Optimal specimens were those in which the procured material enabled satisfactory assessment of histologic architecture that either did not change the original diagnosis or yielded additional findings. Suboptimal specimens were those in which the quality of the histologic core was unsatisfactory for assessment of histologic architecture. When required, immunohistochemical or special staining was performed for differentiation of morphologically challenging lesions.10</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the percentage of cases in which pathologists classified the sample quality as optimal for histological evaluation of 25-gauge biopsy needle</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 minuites after after endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine needle biopsy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The tissue samples were immediately fixed in formalin. The histologic cassette was processed, embedded in paraffin, and then prepared in hematoxylin and eosin to be evaluated by one pathologist (K.H.K) for the presence of a histologic core. If the histologic core was present, the specimen was graded as optimal or suboptimal. Optimal specimens were those in which the procured material enabled satisfactory assessment of histologic architecture that either did not change the original diagnosis or yielded additional findings. Suboptimal specimens were those in which the quality of the histologic core was unsatisfactory for assessment of histologic architecture. When required, immunohistochemical or special staining was performed for differentiation of morphologically challenging lesions.10</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">59</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Pancreatic Masses</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EUS-FNB with 25-gauge</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EUS-FNB with 25-gauge (Echotip ProCore; Cook Endoscopy Inc, Limerick, Ireland)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>EUS-FNB with 25-gauge</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>EUS-FNA with the use of Wilson-Cook procore 25-gauge needles (Echotip, Wilson-Cook, Winston Salem, NC, USA)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients older than 20 years referred to our medical center for EUS-FNA or FNB with
             diagnosed or suspected solid pancreatic masses according to clinical evaluation and
             imaging studies

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  cystic pancreatic lesions, patients haemodynamically unstable or with severe
             coagulopathy (international normalized ratio [INR] &gt; 1.5 or platelet count &lt; 50,000
             cells/cubic millimeter [cmm3]), patients unable to suspend
             anticoagulant/anti-platelet therapy, pregnancy, inability or refusal to give informed
             consent, and refusal to participate in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Moon Jae Chung, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+82-2-2228-1981</phone>
    <email>mjchung@yuhs.ac</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Division of Gastroenterology, Department of Internal Medicine, Yonsei Institute of Gastroenterology, Yonsei University College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>120-752</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Moon Jae Chung, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+82-2-2228-1981</phone>
      <email>mjchung@yuhs.ac</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 26, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
