<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="58843">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02085434</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H00000948</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02085434</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pediatric Practice-based Obesity Intervention to Support Families: FITLINE</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Harvard School of Public Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The American Academy of Pediatrics (AAP) recommends a staged approach for pediatric
      practices to manage the growing problem of pediatric overweight and obesity, starting with
      Stage 1, Prevention Plus, which encourages families to improve basic lifestyle choices
      related to eating and activity in order to improve BMI status. This study will test the
      effectiveness of an innovative FITLINE telephone counseling program for overweight and obese
      8-12 year olds seen in pediatric practices where nutritionists coach parents in improving
      their child's diet and physical activity, to reduce BMI.  If found to be effective, the
      FITLINE program will provide a model for widespread implementation of Stage 1, Prevention
      Plus  of the AAP expert committee recommendations through pediatric practices nationwide.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The American Academy of Pediatrics (AAP) recommends a staged approach to the management of
      pediatric overweight and obesity, starting with Stage 1, Prevention Plus, which encourages
      families to improve lifestyle choices related to eating and activity in order to improve BMI
      status. Most pediatric practices, however, have difficulty implementing these guidelines due
      to limited time and access to weight loss experts to whom they can refer their patients and
      families, and burden to families in accessing in-person weight loss services. In response,
      The investigators team developed the FITLINE pediatric practice-based referral program that
      provides practices an easily accessible resource to help families make AAP-recommended Stage
      1 lifestyle changes.  The program includes two components.  The first, a pediatric
      practice-based component, consists of systems to identify overweight and obese children ages
      8-12, a brief pediatric provider-delivered intervention, referral to the FITLINE counseling
      program, and feedback from the FITLINE nutritionist.  The second, a parent support
      component, consists of eight weekly FITLINE counseling telephone calls delivered by
      centrally located nutritionists who provide tailored, personalized coaching, along with a
      parent booklet to guide parents in setting goals and working with their child to make Stage
      1 lifestyle changes.  Providers receive a summary from the nutritionist of the progress made
      by families so they may support maintenance of an improved lifestyle, or refer for
      additional intervention. The proposed five-year cluster randomized controlled pediatric
      practice-based trial will compare the effectiveness of two practice-based interventions on
      improving diet and physical activity and reducing BMI among  overweight and obese 8-12 year
      olds seen in pediatric practice.  The first consists of the pediatric practice-based
      component plus FITLINE counseling and booklet (PP-FITLINE); the second consists of the same
      practice-based component, but only the parent materials mailed over 8 weeks, with no
      referral to FITLINE counseling (PP-Mailings).  Sixteen pediatric primary care practices will
      be randomized to either the PP-FITLINE (N=8) or the PP-Mailings condition (N=8).  Five
      hundred and twelve parents of children ages 8-12 with a body mass index (BMI) of &gt; 85th
      percentile (overweight or obese) will be recruited from the practices (32/practice) to
      achieve N=400 at 12 month follow-up (25/practice).  Assessments will be completed at
      baseline and 6- and 12-months post-baseline.  The specific aims of this study are to
      determine the effectiveness of the PP-FITLINE program in reducing BMI in overweight and
      obese children and improving the child's diet and physical activity (PA) behaviors; explore
      possible mechanisms of the effect of the PP-FITLINE program on BMI, diet and PA; and conduct
      a cost-effectiveness analysis.  If found to be effective and cost-effective, the PP-FITLINE
      program will provide a model for widespread implementation of Stage 1, Prevention Plus of
      the AAP expert committee recommendations through pediatric practices nationwide,
      contributing significantly to the development of new standards for weight management care in
      pediatric practice.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Mass Index (BMI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months post-baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The child's weight and height were measure in the clinic using standard methodology.  BMI was calculated from weight (kg)/height squared (in meters) and BMI-z score for age/sex determined using Centers for Disease Control growth charts.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diet</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3-months post-baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Parents completed a survey assessing: (1) parent's feeding style using an 11-item questionnaire to assess interactions of the parent with the child during the dinner meal; (2) parent's perceived support and barriers to addressing their child's behavior changes using the Caregiver Attitudes and Beliefs Survey, created by the authors; (3) a 12-item survey regarding number of days their child engaged in key dietary behaviors (e.g., eat breakfast in the morning, eat fast food or restaurant meal, eat dinner with the family, (4) number of days in past week their child ate 5 fruit or vegetables, and drank water, fruit juice, and punch/sweet tea/soda/sports drinks; and (5) type of milk the child drinks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical activity behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months post-baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Parents completed a survey assessing: (1) parent's perceived support and barriers to addressing their child's behavior changes using the Caregiver Attitudes and Beliefs Survey, created by the authors; (2) a 12-item survey regarding number of days their child engaged in key physical activity behaviors (e.g., use computer or play video games, watch television, play sports).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">84</enrollment>
  <condition>Pediatric Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FITLINE practice-based referral program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Historical control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FITLINE practice-based referral program</intervention_name>
    <description>The FITLINE practice-based referral program provides pediatric practices an easily accessible resource to help families make AAP-recommended Stage 1 lifestyle changes.  The program includes a pediatric practice-based component (systems to identify overweight and obese children ages 8-12, a brief pediatric provider-delivered intervention, referral to the FITLINE counseling program, and feedback from the FITLINE nutritionist) and a parent support component(eight weekly FITLINE counseling telephone calls delivered by centrally located nutritionists).  Providers receive a summary from the nutritionist of the progress made by families so they may support maintenance of an improved lifestyle, or refer for additional intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>FITLINE practice-based referral program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  child ages 8-12

          -  child BMI &gt; 85th percentile for age/sex

          -  access to a telephone and parent available to participate in telephone counseling
             sessions,

          -  referred by the child's primary care provider (i.e., family deemed by the provider as
             able to participate in the study and interventions). If more than one child in a
             family is eligible, the oldest child will be invited to participate.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  planning to move out of the area during the period of study participation

          -  medical condition that precludes adherence to AAP dietary and physical activity
             recommendations

          -  prescribed medications associated with weight gain, or (4) morbidly obese (&gt; 300
             pounds).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Massachusetts Medical School</name>
      <address>
        <city>Worcester</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>01655</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 20, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lori Pbert</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
