<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="149554">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01754688</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1109M04335</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01754688</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Determining Prevalence of Acute Bilirubin Encephalopathy in Developing Countries</brief_title>
  <official_title>Determining Prevalence of Acute Bilirubin Encephalopathy in Developing Countries</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators hypothesize that a new BIND (Bilirubin Induced Neurologic Dysfunction)
      scoring method adapted for the developing world (BIND II, developed by our team for use by
      health care workers), with additional modifications for community use (the community BIND,
      C-BIND), will improve the ability to identify infants with ABE and to distinguish ABE from
      other common causes of neonatal morbidity and mortality compared to currently available
      survey tools.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Validate the Bilirubin Induced Neurologic Dysfunction II score (BIND II) instrument or scoring tool in a Nigerian hospital</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The orginal BIND was developed in the USA to score infants with Acute Bilirubin Encephalopathy using a focused physical exam (primarily) neuroligic and history to determine the degree of encephalopathy a infant with jaundice displayed.  The BIND has been adapted for Low-Middle-Income Countries. Our plan is to validate it by use a hearing test and physical exam and laboratory exams to rule out other causes of encephalopathy and rule in acute bilirubin encephalopathy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Develop the community Bilirubin Induced Neurologic Dysfunction Score or BIND (C-BIND) score in lay language and validate it in a Nigerian hospital/clinic setting</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will translate the BIND II into lay language and they have community workers administer it using pictures and/or short videos along with simple questions to the same infants that the doctors performed the BIND II and who have had a hearing test and compare the score of the community workers with those of the physicians and the results of the hearing test and other labs to validate this score.  The community workers will not exam the infants.  They will do everything through questions and pictures and/or videos.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Conduct a pilot study to determine prevalence of Acute Bilirubin Encephalopathy (ABE) in a Nigerian community using C-BIND.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will take the C-BIND into the community around Massey Street Children's Hospital in year 2 of the study to determine the prevalence of ABE in that community after the C-BIND has been validated as above</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">626</enrollment>
  <condition>Demonstrate BIND II Score of &gt;=5, is Valid for Detecting Moderate to Severe ABE in Neonates &lt;14 Days Old.</condition>
  <condition>Demonstrate Community-BIND Instrument, a Modified BIND II, is a Valid and Reliable Tool for Detecting ABE.</condition>
  <condition>Demonstrate That Community-BIND Can be Used for Acquiring Population-based Prevalence of ABE in the Community.</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Jaundice infants</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-jaundiced infants</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Neonates admitted to Massey Street Children's Hospital
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects will be eligible to participate in the study if all of the following
             conditions exist:

               1. At time of birth, neonates who are ≥ 35 weeks gestational age or

                  ≥ 2250 grams if gestational age unavailable.

               2. ≤ 14 days old

               3. Parent or guardian has given consent for the infant to participate

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Infants with a condition requiring urgent referral to another facility for treatment
             not available at the hospital study site.

          2. Infants being admitted for a surgical procedure only without an underlying medical
             illness.

          3. Infants who have a condition that requires no blood draws for treatment of their
             problem and only reason for blood draw would be study enrollment. -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>14 Days</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tina Slusher, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tina M Slusher, MD</last_name>
    <phone>612-840-8883</phone>
    <email>tslusher@umn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massey Street Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lagos</city>
        <country>Nigeria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bolajoka O Olusanya, MBBS</last_name>
      <phone>011-234-803-334-4300</phone>
      <email>boolusanya@aol.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bolajoko O Olusanya, MBBS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Nigeria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 18, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 21, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Kernicterus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Bilirubin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
