<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="60213">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01658735</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB_00052918</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>IRB_00052918</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01658735</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Electrotherapies for Chronic Low Back Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Electrical Stimulation for Chronic Non-specific Low Back Pain in a Working-Age Population: A 12-Week Double Blinded Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Utah</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Electronic Wave Form Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Utah</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The intent of this project is to execute a high-quality double-blinded randomized controlled
      clinical trial that compares the H-Wave® device with a commonly used TENS device with a
      sub-therapeutic electrocurrent device.  This study will provide a definable level of
      evidence for treatment efficacy, and provide a basis for evidence-based recommendation for
      or against utilization for these two modalities.  The results for H-Wave® device, if
      positive, could significantly impact morbidity by providing a non-invasive,
      non-pharmacologic treatment for symptomatic relief, and reduce overall disability and health
      care costs associated with chronic low back pain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      H-Wave® Device Stimulation (Intervention A) plus usual care, transcutaneous electrical nerve
      stimulation (TENS) (Intervention B) plus usual care, and sham electrotherapy plus usual care
      (control). Each treatment arm will have identical participants enrolled (n=38 per arm) of
      with the same number of visits and investigator contact time.

      Eligible participants will be allocated through computerized randomization utilizing a
      stratified permuted-block randomization employing random block sizes. Allocation is
      concealed.  Participants and assessors will be blinded.  Participants will not be told what
      types of electrotherapy devices are being studied, only that there are different types, and
      that they may be randomized to receive a sham device.

      Patients will be instructed on the use of the device they received to perform daily home
      therapy.  Subjects will be assessed at week 1, 4, 8 and 12 for the primary and secondary
      outcomes measures.  Compliance to treatment will be measured through an electronic meter on
      each of the devices, as well as by patient diary.  Patients will be allowed to receive usual
      care from their own health care provider, with the exception of invasive procedures or
      surgery.  Results will be analyzed by intention to treat methods.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Oswestry Disability Index at 1 week</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Oswestry Disability Index at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Oswestry Disability Index at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Oswestry Disability Index at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in VAS Pain Score at 1 week</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in VAS Pain Score at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in VAS Pain Score at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in VAS Pain Score at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">114</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-specific Chronic Low Back Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>H-Wave Device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>H-Wave Device with Usual Care</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TENS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation (TENS) Device with Usual Care</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Electrotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sham Device plus Usual Care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>H-Wave</intervention_name>
    <description>Proprietary electrotherapy device using electrical stimulation of unique wave form and energy level that is delivered through transcutaneous electrodes to nerves and soft tissue for analgesic effect.</description>
    <arm_group_label>H-Wave Device</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>H-Wave is the proprietary name of the device.  There is only one model currently.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Transcutaneous Electrical Nerve Stimulation (TENS)</intervention_name>
    <description>Electrotherapy device that delivers current at different frequency, amplitude, and wave form through cutaneous electrodes placed near body parts with pain for temporary analgesic effect.  The study device is installed inside the same housing as the H-Wave Device and Sham Device, so that all appear the same. There are no identifying marks on the case that participants will recognize in order to maintain blinding.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TENS</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Chattanooga Intellect TENS Device</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham</intervention_name>
    <description>The sham device is a TENS unit modified to have minimal electrical output.  The device is installed in the same housing as the two active arms with equal weight, so that each device in the study appears identical.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Electrotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Chronic Low Back Pain of at least 3 months duration

          -  ages 18-65

          -  Current VAS Pain Rating of 5 on 10 point scale

          -  No pain below the knee

          -  75% of pain located in low back or buttock pain rather than lower extremity pain

          -  Proficient in English

          -  Able to complete and tolerate treatment for the study period.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior home use of H-Wave Device or TENS.

          -  Prior history of spinal fusion or failed spinal surgery syndrome.

          -  Laminectomy, laminotomy or discectomy within 12 months of enrollment.

          -  Diagnostic or interventional injections or any low back surgeries not mentioned
             above, including     radiofrequency, neuroablation within 6 months of enrollment.

          -  Current implanted cardiac demand pacemakers, defibrillators, cardiac pumps, or other
             implanted electronic devices.

          -  Active psychiatric disorders will be excluded (e.g. use of antipsychotic medication,
             bipolar disorder, schizophrenia, uncontrolled depression or anxiety disorder).

          -  Patients currently or who become pregnant will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Matthew A Hughes</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>DFPM-ADMINISTRATION</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 30, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Utah</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Matt Hughes, MD, MPH</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor (clinical)</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chronic low back pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Electrotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>H-Wave</keyword>
  <keyword>H wave</keyword>
  <keyword>TENS</keyword>
  <keyword>Trial</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
