<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="97589">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02051257</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13277</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2014-00133</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>13277</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P50CA107399</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02051257</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Central Memory Enriched T Cells Following Stem Cell Transplant in Treating Patients With Recurrent B-Cell Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Study of Cellular Immunotherapy Using Central Memory-Enriched T Cells Lentivirally Transduced to Express a CD19-Specific, Hinge-Optimized, CD28-Costimulatory Chimeric Receptor and a Truncated EGFR Following Peripheral Blood Stem Cell Transplantation for Patients With High-Risk Intermediate Grade B-Lineage Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>City of Hope Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>City of Hope Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial studies the highest possible dose of central memory enriched T cells that
      can be given following standard stem cell transplant before unmanageable side effects are
      seen in patients with B-cell non-Hodgkin lymphoma that has returned after previous
      treatment. A T cell is a type of immune cell that can recognize and kill abnormal cells of
      the body. Central memory enriched T cells will be made from a patient's own T cells that are
      genetically modified in a laboratory. This means that the T cells are changed by inserting
      additional pieces of deoxyribonucleic acid (genetic material) into the cell to make it
      recognize and kill lymphoma cells. Central memory enriched T cells may kill the cells that
      are not killed by stem cell transplant and may lower the chances of the cancer recurring.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess the safety and describe the full toxicity profile of cellular immunotherapy
      utilizing ex vivo expanded autologous central memory T cell (Tcm)-enriched T cells that are
      genetically modified using a self-inactivating (SIN) lentiviral vector to express a cluster
      of differentiation (CD)19 specific-, hinge optimized, CD28-costimulatory chimeric antigen
      receptor (CAR) as well as a truncated human epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR)
      (CD19R[EQ]28zeta/EGFRt+ Tcm) (autologous CD19CAR-CD28-CD3zeta-EGFRt-expressing Tcm-enriched
      T cells) in conjunction with a standard myeloablative autologous hematopoietic stem cell
      transplant (HSCT) for patients with high-risk intermediate grade B-lineage non-Hodgkin
      lymphomas.

      II. To determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) based on dose limiting toxicities (DLTs).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the tempo, magnitude, and duration of engraftment of the transferred T cell
      product as it relates to the number of cells infused.

      II. To study the impact of this therapeutic intervention on the development of normal CD19+
      B-cell precursors in the bone marrow as a surrogate for the in vivo effector function of
      transferred autologous CD19R(EQ)28zeta/EGFRt+ Tcm.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study.

      Patients receive autologous CD19CAR-CD28-CD3zeta-EGFRt-expressing Tcm-enriched T cells
      intravenously (IV) over 15 minutes on day 2 or 3 following HSCT. Patients who experience
      disease progression and have not experienced serious treatment-related toxicities at greater
      than or equal to 100 days post T cell infusion will be allowed to receive an optional second
      T cell infusion.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 24 hours, weekly for 1
      month, monthly for 1 year, and then annually thereafter for a minimum of 15 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of DLTs defined as any grade 3 or higher toxicity, any toxicity requiring the use of steroids, any grade 3 or greater autoimmune toxicity, or failure for a research participant with documented T cell persistence to engraft by day 21 post HSCT</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Toxicity and adverse events will be assessed using Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0 (v4.0). Tables will be created to summarize all toxicities and side effects by dose, course, organ, severity and attribution. Rates and associated 95% confidence limits will be estimated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events attributable to Tcm adoptive transfer</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Toxicity and adverse events will be assessed using CTCAE v4.0. Tables will be created to summarize all toxicities and side effects by dose, course, organ, severity and attribution. Rates and associated 95% confidence limits will be estimated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MTD of autologous CD19CAR-CD28-CD3zeta-EGFRt-expressing Tcm-enriched T cells based on DLTs</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Toxicity and adverse events will be assessed using Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0 (v4.0). Tables will be created to summarize all toxicities and side effects by dose, course, organ, severity and attribution. Rates and associated 95% confidence limits will be estimated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Engraftment of the transferred T cell product</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Rates and associated 95% confidence limits will be estimated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of CD19+ B-cell precursors in the bone marrow, used as a surrogate for the in vivo effector function of transferred CD19-specific T-cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>CD19+ B cell levels will be reported over the study period using both descriptive statistics and graphical methods.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Adult Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia in Remission</condition>
  <condition>B-cell Adult Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>B-cell Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Cutaneous B-cell Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Extranodal Marginal Zone B-cell Lymphoma of Mucosa-associated Lymphoid Tissue</condition>
  <condition>Intraocular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Nodal Marginal Zone B-cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Burkitt Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Diffuse Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Diffuse Mixed Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Diffuse Small Cleaved Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Grade III Lymphomatoid Granulomatosis</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Immunoblastic Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Lymphoblastic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Grade 1 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Grade 2 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Grade 3 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Mantle Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Marginal Zone Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Hairy Cell Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Small Intestine Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Splenic Marginal Zone Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Testicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Waldenström Macroglobulinemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (autologous Tcm-enriched T cells)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive autologous CD19CAR-CD28-CD3zeta-EGFRt-expressing Tcm-enriched T cells IV over 15 minutes on day 2 or 3 following HSCT. Patients who experience disease progression and have not experienced serious treatment-related toxicities at greater than or equal to 100 days post T cell infusion will be allowed to receive an optional second T cell infusion.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>autologous CD19CAR-CD28-CD3zeta-EGFRt-expressing Tcm-enriched T cells</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (autologous Tcm-enriched T cells)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CD19-CAR-specific/truncated EGFR lentiviral vector-transduced autologous T cells</other_name>
    <other_name>CD19R:CD28:lentiviral/EGFRt+ T cells</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (autologous Tcm-enriched T cells)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Research participants enrolled are patients with an indication to be considered for
             HSCT, who are diagnosed with intermediate grade B-cell non-Hodgkin lymphoma (NHL)
             (e.g. diffuse large B-cell lymphoma [DLBCL], mantle cell lymphoma [MCL], or
             transformed NHL), and that have either (1) recurrence/progression following prior
             therapy, or (2) verification of high-risk disease in first remission

          -  Karnofsky performance status (KPS) of &gt;= 70% at time of enrollment

          -  Life expectancy &gt;= 16 weeks at time of enrollment

          -  Women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
             (hormonal or barrier method of birth control or abstinence) prior to study entry and
             for six months following duration of study participation; should a woman become
             pregnant or suspect that she is pregnant while participating on the trial, she should
             inform her treating physician immediately

          -  City of Hope (COH) pathology review confirms that research participant's diagnostic
             material is consistent with history of intermediate grade B-cell NHL (e.g., DLBCL,
             MCL, or transformed NHL)

          -  Negative serum pregnancy test for women of child-bearing potential

          -  Research participant has an indication to be considered for autologous stem cell
             transplantation

          -  All subjects must have the ability to understand and the willingness to sign a
             written informed consent

          -  ELIGIBILITY CRITERIA AT TIME OF INFUSION OF GENETICALLY MODIFIED AUTOLOGOUS T CELLS:

          -  Research participant has a released cryopreserved T cell product

          -  Research participant did not have evidence of disease progression after salvage
             therapy and therefore underwent an autologous myeloablative transplantation with
             hematopoietic progenitor cell autologous (HPC[A]) rescue procedure

          -  Not requiring supplemental oxygen or mechanical ventilation, oxygen saturation 90% or
             higher on room air

          -  Not requiring pressor support, not having symptomatic cardiac arrhythmias

          -  Lack of acute renal failure/requirement for dialysis, as evidenced by creatinine &lt;
             1.6

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 5.0

          -  Research participant without clinically significant encephalopathy/new focal deficits

          -  No evidence of uncontrolled active infectious process

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Research participants with any uncontrolled illness including ongoing or active
             infections; research participants with known active hepatitis B or C infection;
             research participants who are human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) seropositive based
             on testing performed within 4 weeks of enrollment; research participants with any
             signs or symptoms of active infection, positive blood cultures or radiological
             evidence of infections

          -  Research participants receiving any other investigational agents, or concurrent
             biological, chemotherapy, or radiation therapy; research participants who are to
             receive radioimmunotherapy-based (Zevalin-based) conditioning regimens

          -  Research participants with a history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of
             similar chemical or biological composition to rituximab, and/or cetuximab

          -  Research participants with known brain metastases (central nervous system [CNS]
             involvement either parenchymal or leptomeningeal involvement)

          -  Research participants with presence of other malignancy or history of prior
             malignancy within 5 years of study entry; although patients treated with curative
             intent within 5 years are eligible; this exclusion does not apply to non-melanoma
             skin tumors and in-situ cervical cancer

          -  Failure of research participant to understand the basic elements of the protocol
             and/or the risks/benefits of participating in this phase I/II study; a legal guardian
             may substitute for the research participant

          -  History of allogeneic HSCT or prior autologous HSCT

          -  Any standard contraindications to myeloablative HSCT per standard of care practices
             at COH

          -  Dependence on corticosteroids

          -  Currently enrolled in another investigational therapy protocol

          -  Active autoimmune disease requiring systemic immunosuppressive therapy

          -  Research participants will be excluded, who in the opinion of the investigator, may
             not be able to comply with the safety monitoring requirements of the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leslie Popplewell</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>City of Hope Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City of Hope Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Duarte</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Leslie L. Popplewell</last_name>
      <phone>800-826-4673</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Leslie L. Popplewell</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 29, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Burkitt Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Hairy Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Follicular</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphomatoid Granulomatosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Waldenstrom Macroglobulinemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large B-Cell, Diffuse</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large-Cell, Immunoblastic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell, Marginal Zone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Extranodal NK-T-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Mantle-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
