<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="25239">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02136914</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ADS-AMT-PD301</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02136914</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ADS-5102 for the Treatment of Levodopa Induced Dyskinesia (EASE LID Study)</brief_title>
  <acronym>EASE LID</acronym>
  <official_title>Efficacy and Safety of ADS-5102 (Amantadine HCl) Extended Release Capsules for the Treatment of Levodopa Induced Dyskinesia in Parkinson's Disease Patients (EASE LID Study)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Adamas Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Adamas Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, 2-arm, parallel group
      study to evaluate the efficacy and safety of ADS-5102 extended release (ER) capsules, an
      investigational formulation of amantadine, dosed once nightly at bedtime for the treatment
      of levodopa induced dyskinesia (LID) in subjects with Parkinson's disease (PD). The novel
      pharmacokinetic profile of ADS-5102 is expected to achieve i) maximal concentrations in the
      early morning through mid-day, when LID can be troublesome, and ii) lower concentrations in
      the evening, potentially reducing the negative impact of amantadine on sleep.  This
      pharmacokinetic profile could enable higher doses to be tolerated with a once-nightly ER
      formulation than can be tolerated with an immediate-release formulation.  The once-nightly
      dosing regimen may also provide enhanced convenience and compliance.

      In a previous clinical study, ADS-5102 met its primary endpoint; LID was significantly
      reduced as measured by the change in UDysRS score over 8 weeks vs. placebo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Unified Dyskinesia Rating Scale (UDysRS) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the standardized PD home diary (ON time without dyskinesia, ON time with troublesome dyskinesia, OFF time)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Movement Disorder Society Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale (MDS-UPDRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinician's Global Impression of Change in overall PD symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Dyskinesia</condition>
  <condition>Levodopa Induced Dyskinesia (LID)</condition>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ADS-5102</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ADS-5102 (amantadine HCl extended release)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ADS-5102</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral capsules to be administered once nightly at bedtime, for 13 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>ADS-5102</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ADS-5102</other_name>
    <other_name>amantadine HCl extended release</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Signed a current IRB/REB/IEC-approved informed consent form

          -  Parkinson's disease, per UK Parkinson's Disease Society (UKPDS) Brain Bank Clinical
             Diagnostic Criteria

          -  On a stable regimen of antiparkinson's medications for at least 30 days prior to
             screening, including a levodopa preparation administered not less than three times
             daily, and willing to continue the same doses and regimens during study participation

          -  Following diary training, the subject is willing and able to understand and complete
             the 24-hour PD home diary (caregiver/study partner assistance allowed)

          -  Any other current and allowed prescription/non-prescription medications and/or
             nutritional supplements taken regularly must have been at a stable dose and regimen
             for at least 30 days prior to screening, and subject must be willing to continue the
             same doses and regimens during study participation (this criterion does not apply to
             medications that are being taken pre-study only on an as-needed basis)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of neurosurgical intervention related to Parkinson's disease (e.g. deep brain
             stimulation)

          -  History of seizures within 2 years prior to screening

          -  History of stroke or transient ischemic attack (TIA) within 2 years prior to
             screening

          -  History of cancer within 5 years prior to screening, with the following exceptions:
             adequately treated non-melanomatous skin cancers, localized bladder cancer,
             non-metastatic prostate cancer or in situ cervical cancer

          -  Presence of cognitive impairment, as evidenced by a Mini-Mental Status Examination
             (MMSE) score of less than 24 during screening

          -  If female, is pregnant or lactating

          -  If a sexually active female, is not surgically sterile or at least 2 years
             post-menopausal, or does not agree to utilize an effective method of contraception
             from screening through at least 4 weeks after the completion of study treatment.

          -  Treatment with an investigational drug or device within 30 days prior to screening

          -  Treatment with an investigational biologic within 6 months prior to screening

          -  Current participation in another clinical trial
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Clinical Trials Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Adamas Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Clinical Trials Administrator</last_name>
    <phone>510-450-3500</phone>
    <email>clinicaltrials@adamaspharma.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 9, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 9, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Levodopa Induced Dyskinesia</keyword>
  <keyword>LID</keyword>
  <keyword>Parkinsonism</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dyskinesias</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Amantadine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levodopa</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
