<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="146288">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01880086</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Cornell-1301013472</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01880086</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clomiphene Citrate for the Treatment of Low Testosterone Associated With Chronic Opioid Pain Medication Administration</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clomiphene Citrate for the Treatment of Opioid-Induced Androgen Deficiency: Randomized Controlled Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Data and Safety Monitoring Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this randomized controlled clinical trial is to evaluate the effects of
      clomiphene citrate compared to placebo (substance without active medication) in men who are
      taking pain medication (opioids) for chronic pain conditions and who have low blood
      testosterone levels.

      The condition of men having low testosterone with long-term pain medication (opioid) usage
      is called opioid-induced androgen deficiency (OPIAD).  Low testosterone can be caused by
      pain medication effects on part of the brain (hypothalamic-pituitary axis) which ultimately
      result in decreased testosterone production by the testes.  Typical symptoms of low
      testosterone (hypogonadism) may include decreased muscle mass, increased fat, osteoporosis,
      anemia, erectile dysfunction, delayed ejaculation.  In addition, men with low testosterone
      may experience decreased attention, and decreased libido, fatigue, and depressed mood.  Few
      studies have looked at hormonal changes caused by long-term opioid usage in men.

      Clomiphene citrate, a selective estrogen receptor modulator (SERM) oral medication which
      inhibits estrogen effects (feedback) on the brain, has been identified by prior studies to
      raise testosterone in men with low testosterone (due to reasons other than chronic pain
      medication).  Clomiphene citrate is also known to lead to increased sperm production in men
      with low testosterone unlike testosterone topical or injection medications.  Although
      clomiphene citrate has been studied in hypogonadal men with beneficial outcomes and minimal
      side effects, no group has previously studied clomiphene citrate as treatment in patients
      with OPIAD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic nonmalignant pain is a widespread issue affecting 15-30% of the population.  Many
      patients with chronic pain are responsive to first-line combination of physical modalities
      and non-opioid analgesics.  Up to 20% of these patients, however, require opioid therapy for
      adequate pain relief.  The use of long-acting opioids, including morphine sulfate,
      oxycodone, fentanyl, and methadone, although effective for pain control, carries risks of
      addiction, tolerance, and systemic side effects including nausea, itching, constipation, and
      hypogonadotropic hypogonadism with consequent testosterone depletion (in up to 86% of
      patients taking chronic pain medication) leading to the multiple adverse effects.
      Opioid-induced androgen deficiency (OPIAD), occurs with high frequency and persistence, and
      commonly remains undiagnosed in the pain clinic.  Low testosterone may be treated using
      exogenous testosterone (topical or gel) or other medications such as selective estrogen
      receptor modulators (i.e. clomiphene citrate).  While both medication types increase serum
      testosterone levels, clomiphene citrate is known to benefit sperm parameters in hypogonadal
      men while exogenous testosterone is known to inhibit sperm production.  Few studies have
      examined the hormonal changes caused by long-term opioid usage in men, and no studies have
      formally studied clomiphene citrate for this patient population.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum total testosterone (change from baseline)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 weeks, 1 month, 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Morning venipuncture of serum total testosterone to assess change over time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Other hormonal profile (change from baseline)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 weeks, 1 month, 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Serum free testosterone, sex hormone-binding globulin (SHBG), luteinizing hormone  (LH), follicle stimulating hormone (FSH), dihydrotestosterone (DHT), estradiol, prolactin, adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH), cortisol, insulin like growth factor 1 (IGF-1), complete blood count  (CBC), cholesterol, B-endorphin, met-enkephalin.  Each lab test is intended to assess change over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine studies (change from baseline)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 weeks, 1 month, 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>24 hour urine aldosterone/cortisol to assess change over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Semen analysis (sperm count, concentration, motility, morphology: change from baseline)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 weeks, 1 month, 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This portion of the study will be completed with patient consent and may be omitted if desired by the patient.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Questionnaires- self-administered</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 weeks, 1 month, 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The following validated questionnaires will be used: Androgen Deficiency in the Aging Male (ADAM) questionnaire (with 10 yes/no questions assessing low testosterone symptoms), IIEF-5 (International Index of Erectile Function 5 question survey each with 1 to 5 answers, summed: score of 22-25 demonstrates no erectile dysfunction, score of 5-7 demonstrates severe erectile dysfunction), and Visual Analog Scale (VAS, scored 0=no pain to 10=worst possible pain).  Overall, study subjects will be assessed for possible change in hypogonadal, sexual function, and pain symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">134</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypogonadism</condition>
  <condition>Opioid-Related Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Male Infertility</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Clomiphene citrate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The initial dose of clomiphene citrate will be 25 mg (po, pill by mouth) every other day. This will be started at visit 2, week 0 of the study following diagnosis of low baseline testosterone (serum total testosterone &lt;350 ng/dl in men &lt;55 years, &lt;300 ng/dl in men 55-65 years).  Clomiphene citrate dose will be titrated up to a maximum of 50 mg daily according to serum total testosterone levels measured at follow-up visits during the 3 month duration of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo pill will be administered (po, pill by mouth) every other day starting at week 0 of the study in men diagnosed with low testosterone.  Treatment will be delayed in these men until the 3 month completion of the study, at which time this group may also receive testosterone replacement therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clomiphene citrate</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Clomiphene citrate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Clomid</other_name>
    <other_name>Milophene</other_name>
    <other_name>Serophene</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo pill that will have appearance identical to the treatment pill but will not contain active medication.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sugar pill</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male

          -  18 years to 65 years

          -  Low testosterone as defined by criteria (serum total testosterone &lt;350 ng/dl in men
             &lt;55 years, &lt;300 ng/dl in men 55-65 years)

          -  EITHER taking opioid pain medication (see A below) OR planning to start new pain
             medication regimen (see B below)

          -  A) EITHER continuous opioid treatment for chronic nonmalignant pain for &gt;=6 months
             receiving one of several specified opioid regimens for the past 1 month (including
             &gt;=20 mg/day of oral methadone, &gt;=30 mg/day of oral sustained release oxycodone, &gt;=30
             mg/day of oral morphine sulfate, &gt;=6 mg/day of oral dilaudid or &gt;= 8 mg/day of
             dilaudid ER, or &gt;=25 mcg/hr of transdermal fentanyl or buprenorphine, or intrathecal
             morphine pump)

          -  B) OR the pain management physician is planning to start pain medication (opioid or
             non-opioid pain therapy) but you have not received it yet.  If this is the case, your
             testosterone will be checked before starting and during 1 month of pain therapy to
             determine if you have low testosterone to qualify to begin medication (clomiphene or
             placebo) treatment in this study.

          -  BMI (20-35 kg/m2)

          -  Presence of clear secondary hypogonadism with hypogonadal symptoms and low total
             testosterone level (confirmed with morning testosterone level &lt;= 350 ng/dL for men
             age &gt;= 55 and &lt;= 300ng/dl for men age 55-65) or total testosterone &lt;=200 ng/dl
             (regardless of symptoms).  Additionally LH should be &lt;15 mIU (milli-International
             unit )/mL (at baseline only).  Symptoms of hypogonadism include fatigue, decreased
             energy level/endurance, depressed mood, decreased libido, erectile dysfunction.

          -  Chronic nonmalignant pain etiology includes rheumatoid arthritis, osteoarthritis,
             spinal stenosis, polymyalgia, complex region pain syndrome I and II, neurinoma,
             phantom limb pain, neuropathic pain of other origin, scoliosis, neck pain, failed
             back surgery, or chronic pancreatitis.

          -  All patients must have ability to complete the study in compliance with the protocol,
             and the ability to understand and provide written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Chronic pain of malignant etiology (cancer-related)

          -  Preexisting testosterone deficiency

          -  Concomitant use of medication that could interfere with testosterone levels including
             antidepressant medication, spironolactone, cimetidine, clomiphene (use in the past 1
             year), human chorionic gonadotropin  (hCG), androgen, estrogen, anabolic steroid,
             5-alpha-reductase inhibitors such as finasteride, dehydroepiandrosterone (DHEA),
             testosterone therapy (topical testosterone within 7 days of study, injectable
             testosterone within 6 months of study),

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension

          -  Clinically significant abnormal findings on screening examination based on the
             Investigator's assessment

          -  Known hypersensitivity to clomiphene

          -  Symptomatic cataracts

          -  Presence or history of known hyperprolactinemia with or without a tumor

          -  End-stage renal disease

          -  Any contraindication to testosterone supplementation therapy

          -  Absolute contraindications to hormone supplementation therapy which include active
             prostate cancer (or suspicion of prostate disease unless ruled out by biopsy),
             prostatic specific antigen (PSA)&gt;=3.6, breast cancer, hematocrit&gt;=51% (hemoglobin&gt;=17
             g/dL), uncontrolled congestive heart failure  (CHF), myocardial infarction, acute
             coronary event, unstable angina, coronary revascularization procedure in the
             preceding 6 months, untreated obstructive sleep apnea, high risk of prostate cancer
             (ethnicity or family history), or severe lower urinary tract symptoms (AUA symptom
             score&gt;19).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter N Schlegel, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Matthew Wosnitzer, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-746-5470</phone>
    <email>maw7011@med.cornell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Weill Cornell Medical College, Department of Urology</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Matthew Wosnitzer, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-746-5470</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter N Schlegel, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cornellurology.com</url>
    <description>Weill Cornell Medical College, Department of Urology</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 5, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 7, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chronic pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Low testosterone</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypogonadism</keyword>
  <keyword>Opioid analgesics</keyword>
  <keyword>Narcotics</keyword>
  <keyword>Opioid-induced androgen deficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>OPIAD</keyword>
  <keyword>Male infertility</keyword>
  <keyword>Clomiphene citrate</keyword>
  <keyword>Selective Estrogen Receptor Modulators</keyword>
  <keyword>Testosterone replacement therapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hypogonadism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infertility</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infertility, Male</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Opioid-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Testosterone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone enanthate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone undecanoate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone 17 beta-cypionate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Androgens</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methyltestosterone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Clomiphene</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Citric Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Selective Estrogen Receptor Modulators</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Estrogen Receptor Modulators</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Analgesics, Opioid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
