<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="164713">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01766297</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BRE007-12</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01766297</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase II Protocol of Proton Therapy for Partial Breast Irradiation in Early Stage Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Protocol of Proton Therapy for Partial Breast Irradiation in Early Stage Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Proton Collaborative Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Proton Collaborative Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research study is to compare the effects (good and bad) on women and
      their cancer using proton radiation therapy.

      This study is being done to see if proton radiation therapy will prove to be beneficial for
      women with early stage breast cancer. A clinical study is necessary to compare the results
      (good or bad) of proton radiation therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Current standard of care for early stage breast cancer is mastectomy or breast conserving
      therapy with whole breast irradiation following lumpectomy. However, studies of breast
      cancer recurrence have demonstrated the majority of tumors to recur in or adjacent to the
      original tumor site.  The question has thus been raised as to whether radiation to the whole
      breast is necessary or justified. Limiting radiation to the area of the original tumor may
      reduce acute and long-term skin and organ toxicities while making radiation therapy more
      convenient and less expensive. Several clinical trials are underway comparing partial breast
      irradiation (PBI) to whole breast irradiation. Numerous centers are offering partial breast
      irradiation outside of clinical trials as well, despite the lack of long-term safety and
      efficacy data on PBI.

      Available PBI methods include brachytherapy, in which catheters or balloons are surgically
      inserted to deliver radiation therapy to the lumpectomy cavity, and conventional external
      beam radiation therapy, or EBRT. External beam photon therapy is attractive for its
      non-invasive nature and ability to deliver a more homogenous dose distribution compared to
      brachytherapy, however it also delivers a greater radiation dose to surrounding normal
      breast tissue.Proton therapy has the capacity to provide the same advantages as photon EBRT
      while minimizing dose to normal surrounding tissue.  Clinical data on PBI with protons is
      minimal, however, leaving many questions unanswered. The impetus behind this protocol is to
      address these gaps by further investigating the feasibility, safety, and efficacy of proton
      therapy for partial breast irradiation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2030</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess events of freedom from ipsilateral breast recurrence occurrences in patients receiving partial breast proton radiation therapy limited to the region of the tumor.</measure>
    <time_frame>At 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Freedom from failure (FFF): The events for FFF will be the first ipsilateral breast cancer recurrence. It is expected that less than 3% of patients will experience an ipsilateral breast cancer recurrence (FFF ≥ 97%).   A recurrence rate of ≥ 15% (FFF ≤ 85%) is considered unacceptable.  Therefore, the null hypothesis is the FFF of ipsilateral breast cancer recurrence is 85% or lower and the alternative hypothesis is that FFF of ipsilateral breast cancer is 97% or higher.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess number and severity of acute and long-term toxicity of partial breast irradiation using proton therapy for the treatment of early stage breast cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>On average every 6 months for life</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess relationship between breast size and partial breast dosimetry.</measure>
    <time_frame>Average every 6 months for 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare freedom from failure, survival and dosimetry of post-operative vs. pre-operative partial breast irradiation.</measure>
    <time_frame>At 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine quality of life results</measure>
    <time_frame>Average every 6 months for 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine overall survival rate of patients with breast cancer treated with proton radiation</measure>
    <time_frame>at 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">42</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Breast Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Breast Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Cancer of the Breast</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Proton Radiotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Proton Radiotherapy 4.0 Gy (RBE) x10 fractions to 40 Gy (RBE) Total Dose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Proton Radiotherapy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Proton Radiotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must sign study-specific, IRB approved informed consent form prior to study entry.
             Note consent by legally authorized representative is not allowed for this trial.

          -  Must be female.

          -  Must be &gt; = 50 years of age.

          -  Must have a life expectancy of at least 5 years based on age and co-morbidities.

          -  Must have pathology proven invasive ductal carcinoma (lobular is not allowed) and/or
             ductal carcinoma in situ (DCIS).

          -  One of the following criteria must be met:  (a) Tumors that are microscopically
             multifocal must be 3.0 cm or less and encompassed within a single scar (b) Patient
             does not have microscopically multifocal tumor.

          -  In the presence of extensive intraductal component (EIC) the entire pathologic tumor
             size (including both the intraductal and invasive component) are 3.0 cm or less.

          -  Must be Stage 0, I, II (T1-2, N0, M0 per AJCC criteria 7th Ed.) If stage II, the
             tumor size must be &lt; = 3.0 cm. A patient with invasive histology must have nodal
             stage pN0 by H&amp;E stains on sentinel node biopsy or axillary lymph node dissection.

          -  Must have ER positive disease with ER/PR report available.

          -  HER2 performed and report available. (Positive or negative is acceptable).

          -  Must have Oncotype performed on core or lumpectomy and the results documented.

          -  Must have a lumpectomy performed, with documented negative surgical margins &gt; 0.2 cm.
             If re-excision results in negative surgical margins &gt; 0.2 cm, patient is eligible.

          -  Must be prepared to have 3 fiducial markers minimum, 4 preferred placed prior to
             treatment if not previously done.

               -  If markers or clips were placed at the time of surgery, must be able to start
                  treatment within 12 weeks after lumpectomy or re-excision for clean margins.

               -  If markers were not placed at the time of surgery, must have markers placed
                  within 6 weeks after surgery.

               -  If systemic chemotherapy was given patients must have had clips or markers
                  placed at the time of surgery and must have simulation scans within 6 weeks of
                  the completion of the chemotherapy.

          -  Must be able to start treatment within 12 weeks of surgery or 8 weeks of finalization
             of chemotherapy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous history of ipsilateral invasive breast cancer or DCIS.

          -  Any clinical or radiographically suspicious nodes, unless biopsy proven benign.

          -  Non-epithelial malignancies such as sarcoma or lymphoma.

          -  Suspicious microcalcifications of either breast, unless negative for malignancy on
             pathology.

          -  Multicentric or bilateral disease unless biopsy of the clinical abnormalities are
             performed and result is negative.

          -  Lymphovascular space invasion (LVSI) on pathology specimen.

          -  Any previously treated breast carcinoma or synchronous breast carcinoma in
             ipsilateral breast.

          -  Prior radiation therapy to the ipsilateral breast or thorax.

          -  Paget's disease of the nipple.

          -  Histologic examination showing invasive lobular histology.

          -  Skin involvement.

          -  Breasts technically unsatisfactory for radiation treatment upon the discretion of the
             treating physician.

          -  Ipsilateral breast implant unless removed prior to radiation treatment.

          -  Significant infection or other co-existing medical condition that would preclude
             protocol therapy such as pregnancy, HIV/AIDS or collagen vascular diseases
             specifically systemic lupus erythematosis, scleroderma, or dermatomysositis.

          -  Known BRCA 1 or BRCA 2 mutation.

          -  Pregnant or lactating
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrew Chang, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Proton Collaborative Group</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Megan Dunn, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>630-657-0092</phone>
    <email>megan.dunn@pcgresearch.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CDH Proton Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Warrenville</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60555</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Corey Woods, RN</last_name>
      <phone>630-821-6397</phone>
      <email>corey.woods@chi.procure.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paige Dorn, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Procure Proton Therapy Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73142</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tish Adams, MS CCRC</last_name>
      <phone>405-773-6775</phone>
      <email>tish.adams@okc.procure.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrew Chang, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 19, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 28, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Proton</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
