<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="36784">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01859221</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UFPTI 1301-OL01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01859221</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Radiotherapy for Oligometastatic Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Stereotactic Body Radiotherapy (SBRT) and Stereotactic Hypofractionated Radiotherapy (SHRT) for Oligometastatic Prostate Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this phase II study is to evaluate the outcomes of patients treated with an
      investigational radiation regimen using stereotactic radiotherapy for oligometastatic
      prostate cancer and to establish efficacy       (producing a desired result or effect) and
      safety in this setting.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will serve as a component of a larger program investigating the benefits of
      stereotactic radiotherapy in patients with metastatic disease.

      This particular study will serve as a benchmark analysis.

      All patients will receive stereotactic radiotherapy directed at metastatic tumors.

      If primary prostate cancer is active and has not previously been treated with radiation
      therapy, conventional radiation therapy (6-8 weeks of daily treatment) may be recommended.
      The metastatic tumor will be treated at the same time.

      Hormone therapy will be recommended for all patients.

      Patients will be asked to complete questionnaires at regular intervals.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in median progression-free survival in patients with metastatic prostate cancer over historic control rates in hormone receptive and castration resistant subgroups.</measure>
    <time_frame>78 months after radiation treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Over the 78 month period, any occurrence of toxicity and/or treatment failure will be monitored via regular patient follow-up interviews.  The cumulative rate at 78 months is analytic outcome of interest for each type of secondary outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in overall survival of patients with metastatic prostate cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>78 months after radiation treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Over the 78 month period, any occurrence of toxicity and/or treatment failure will be monitored via regular patient follow-up interviews.  The cumulative rate at 78 months is analytic outcome of interest for each type of secondary outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment failure rates in patients treated with stereotactic radiation for metastatic prostate cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>78 months after radiation treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Over the 78 month period, any occurrence of toxicity and/or treatment failure will be monitored via regular patient follow-up interviews.  The cumulative rate at 78 months is analytic outcome of interest for each type of secondary outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life in patients treated with stereotactic radiation for metastatic prostate cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>78 months after radiation treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Over the 78 month period, any occurrence of toxicity and/or treatment failure will be monitored via regular patient follow-up interviews.  The cumulative rate at 78 months is analytic outcome of interest for each type of secondary outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Oligometastatic Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Castration Resistant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>There are two different prognostic categories, hormones receptive and castration resistant, that have differing historical disease progression rates.  We have therefore stratified the trial so that we can independently monitor the hypothesized improvement provided by radiation therapy in these two groups. Both groups will receive the same radiation modality which is stereotactic radiation with two possible schedules of SBRT and SHRT.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hormone Receptive</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>There are two different prognostic categories, hormones receptive and castration resistant, that have differing historical disease progression rates.  We have therefore stratified the trial so that we can independently monitor the hypothesized improvement provided by radiation therapy in these two groups. Both groups will receive the same radiation modality which is stereotactic radiation with two possible schedules of SBRT and SHRT.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SBRT/SHRT</intervention_name>
    <description>SBRT/SHRT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Castration Resistant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Hormone Receptive</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with metastatic cancer of the prostate,

          -  Patients may have received prior surgery,

          -  Prior radiation therapy, androgen deprivation therapy (ADT), immunotherapy, bone
             metastasis directed therapy, or chemotherapy for prostate cancer.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  End-stage heart disease,

          -  End-stage liver disease,

          -  End-stage renal disease,

          -  End stage pulmonary disease

          -  Current brain or central nervous system metastasis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Roi Dagan, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Intake Coordinator</last_name>
    <phone>877-686-6009</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida Proton Therapy Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32206</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Intake Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>877-686-6009</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Roi Dagan, MD, MS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hsiao W, Moses KA, Goodman M, et al. Stage IV prostate cancer: survival differences in clinical T4, nodal and metastatic disease. J Urol 2010;184:512-518.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>James ND, Sydes MR, Mason MD, et al. Celecoxib plus hormone therapy versus hormone therapy alone for hormone-sensitive prostate cancer: first results from the STAMPEDE multiarm, multistage, randomised controlled trial. Lancet Oncol 2012;13:549-558.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Widmark A, Klepp O, Solberg A, Damber JE, Angelsen A, Fransson P, Lund JA, Tasdemir I, Hoyer M, Wiklund F, Fosså SD; Scandinavian Prostate Cancer Group Study 7; Swedish Association for Urological Oncology 3. Endocrine treatment, with or without radiotherapy, in locally advanced prostate cancer (SPCG-7/SFUO-3): an open randomised phase III trial. Lancet. 2009 Jan 24;373(9660):301-8. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(08)61815-2. Epub 2008 Dec 16. Erratum in: Lancet. 2009 Apr 4;373(9670):1174.</citation>
    <PMID>19091394</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Warde P, Mason M, Ding K, et al. Combined androgen deprivation therapy and radiation therapy for locally advanced prostate cancer: a randomised, phase 3 trial. Lancet 2011;378:2104-2111.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kantoff PW, Higano CS, Shore ND, et al. Sipuleucel-T immunotherapy for castration-resistant prostate cancer. N Engl J Med 2010;363:411-422.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saad F, Gleason DM, Murray R, Tchekmedyian S, Venner P, Lacombe L, Chin JL, Vinholes JJ, Goas JA, Chen B; Zoledronic Acid Prostate Cancer Study Group. A randomized, placebo-controlled trial of zoledronic acid in patients with hormone-refractory metastatic prostate carcinoma. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2002 Oct 2;94(19):1458-68.</citation>
    <PMID>12359855</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kelly WK, Halabi S, Carducci M, et al. Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Phase III Trial Comparing Docetaxel and Prednisone With or Without Bevacizumab in Men With Metastatic Castration-Resistant Prostate Cancer: CALGB 90401. J Clin Oncol 2012;30:1534-1540.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rana A, Chisholm GD, Khan M, Sekharjit SS, Merrick MV, Elton RA. Patterns of bone metastasis and their prognostic significance in patients with carcinoma of the prostate. Br J Urol. 1993 Dec;72(6):933-6.</citation>
    <PMID>8306158</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Noguchi M, Kikuchi H, Ishibashi M, Noda S. Percentage of the positive area of bone metastasis is an independent predictor of disease death in advanced prostate cancer. Br J Cancer. 2003 Jan 27;88(2):195-201. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12610502</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eisenhauer EA, Therasse P, Bogaerts J, Schwartz LH, Sargent D, Ford R, Dancey J, Arbuck S, Gwyther S, Mooney M, Rubinstein L, Shankar L, Dodd L, Kaplan R, Lacombe D, Verweij J. New response evaluation criteria in solid tumours: revised RECIST guideline (version 1.1). Eur J Cancer. 2009 Jan;45(2):228-47.</citation>
    <PMID>19097774</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Potters L, Steinberg M, Rose C, Timmerman R, Ryu S, Hevezi JM, Welsh J, Mehta M, Larson DA, Janjan NA; American Society for Therapeutic Radiology and Oncology; American College of Radiology. American Society for Therapeutic Radiology and Oncology and American College of Radiology practice guideline for the performance of stereotactic body radiation therapy. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2004 Nov 15;60(4):1026-32.</citation>
    <PMID>15519771</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Potters L, Kavanagh B, Galvin JM, Hevezi JM, Janjan NA, Larson DA, Mehta MP, Ryu S, Steinberg M, Timmerman R, Welsh JS, Rosenthal SA; American Society for Therapeutic Radiology and Oncology; American College of Radiology. American Society for Therapeutic Radiology and Oncology (ASTRO) and American College of Radiology (ACR) practice guideline for the performance of stereotactic body radiation therapy. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2010 Feb 1;76(2):326-32. doi: 10.1016/j.ijrobp.2009.09.042.</citation>
    <PMID>20117285</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hann DM, Jacobsen PB, Azzarello LM, Martin SC, Curran SL, Fields KK, Greenberg H, Lyman G. Measurement of fatigue in cancer patients: development and validation of the Fatigue Symptom Inventory. Qual Life Res. 1998 May;7(4):301-10.</citation>
    <PMID>9610214</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 20, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 13, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Prostate cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Oligometastatic prostate cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Proton radiation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
