<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="112636">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01921166</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Diminished Ovarian Reserve</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01921166</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Maximal Stimulation and Delayed Fertilization for Diminished Ovarian Reserve: a Randomized Pilot Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Maximal Stimulation and Delayed Fertilization for Diminished Ovarian Reserve: a Randomized Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Carolinas Healthcare System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Carolinas Healthcare System</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is (A) to determine if the following novel approach improves the
      live birth rate with In-Vitro Fertilization (IVF) for women with a poor prognosis due to
      diminished ovarian reserve:

        -  ovarian stimulation with medications that are effective in women with diminished
           ovarian reserve but adversely affect the endometrium

        -  oocyte retrieval and vitrification

        -  fertilization and embryo transfer in a subsequent cycle with controlled endometrial
           preparation B) To determine the optimal stimulation protocol for women with diminished
           ovarian reserve incorporating oocyte vitrification

      Women who are not eligible to participate in the Carolinas Medical Center (CMC) Assisted
      Reproductive Therapy program because of an extremely poor prognosis will be recruited for a
      prospective, randomized, open-label study to determine if a novel approach improves the live
      birth rate with traditional IVF &quot;poor prognosis&quot; stimulation protocols.  The novel approach
      will incorporate one of two protocols utilizing medications that provide maximal ovarian
      stimulation but have a temporary detrimental fertility-reducing effect on the endometrium.
      If ovarian stimulation is adequate, oocyte retrieval will be performed and viable oocytes
      vitrified (stored in a &quot;glass-like&quot; state in liquid nitrogen). At a later time, oocyte
      warming and fertilization will be performed in a subsequent cycle, in which the endometrium
      has been prepared.

      Key points include:

        -  Randomization to one of two ovarian stimulation protocols that have been shown to have
           a detrimental effect on the endometrium, and therefore are rarely used in a &quot;fresh&quot; IVF
           cycle

        -  Oocyte vitrification is considered to be an investigational procedure by the American
           Society of Reproductive Medicine (ASRM), and should only be performed under the
           supervision of an IRB.  With oocyte vitrification, ovarian stimulation and oocyte
           retrieval can &quot;unlinked&quot; from embryo transfer, allowing embryo transfer to occur in a
           more optimal environment

        -  Endometrial preparation is routine for frozen embryo transfer
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Women who are not eligible to participate in the CMC Assisted Reproductive Therapy (ART)
      program because of an extremely poor prognosis will be recruited for a prospective,
      randomized, open-label study to determine if a novel approach improves the live birth rate
      with traditional IVF &quot;poor prognosis&quot; stimulation protocols.  The novel approach will
      incorporate one of two protocols utilizing medications that provide maximal ovarian
      stimulation but have a temporary detrimental fertility-reducing effect on the endometrium.
      If ovarian stimulation is adequate, oocyte retrieval will be performed and viable oocytes
      vitrified (stored in a &quot;glass-like&quot; state in liquid nitrogen). At a later time, oocyte
      warming and fertilization will be performed in a subsequent cycle, in which the endometrium
      has been prepared.

      Key points include:

        -  Randomization to one of two ovarian stimulation protocols that have been shown to have
           a detrimental effect on the endometrium, and therefore are rarely used in a &quot;fresh&quot; IVF
           cycle

        -  Oocyte vitrification is considered to be an investigational procedure by the American
           Society of Reproductive Medicine (ASRM), and should only be performed under the
           supervision of an IRB.  With oocyte vitrification, ovarian stimulation and oocyte
           retrieval can be &quot;unlinked&quot; from embryo transfer, allowing embryo transfer to occur in
           a more optimal environment

        -  Endometrial preparation is routine for frozen embryo transfer Eligible patients will be
           randomized to one of two protocols:  clomiphene + HMG or leuprolide flare protocol.

      All subjects must undergo pre-cycle IVF testing as per routine for the CMC ART program.  In
      general, the study will be comprised of subjects not eligible for IVF due to extremely poor
      prognosis because of expected compromised ovarian stimulation (see inclusion criteria
      below).  Subjects are financially responsible for all treatments in this study.  Randomized
      will be performed by a random number generator after informed consent has been signed.
      Randomization at this point will allow time to order and obtain required medications.

      Cycle start requirements (performed cycle day 2 or 3):

        -  Basal Follicle Stimulating Hormone (FSH) 12 mIU/mL or less AND

        -  Basal estradiol 50 pg/mL or less AND

        -  Acceptable baseline ultrasound (no evidence of a condition for which IVF would be
           contraindicated) If patient does not meet start requirements, delay and repeat cycle
           start tests in the next IVF session.

      Group 1: clomiphene + human menopausal gonadotropin Menopur ® (HMG)

        -  Clomiphene 100 mg cycle days 3-7 plus

        -  HMG 300 units daily beginning cycle day 3 and continued until day of HCG (Ovidrel)
           administration

      Group 2: leuprolide flare + HMG

        -  leuprolide acetate 0.5 mg twice daily beginning cycle day 3 and continued until day of
           HCG (Ovidrel) administration

        -  HMG 300 units daily beginning cycle day 3 and continued until day of HCG (Ovidrel)
           administration

      Both groups:

        -  Follow-up ultrasound, estradiol cycle day 8.  Cancel cycle if estradiol is &lt; 200 pg/mL.
            If estradiol is 200 pg/mL or higher, make HMG dose adjustments and schedule follow-up
           estradiol and ultrasound visits as per routine IVF protocol.

        -  Administer Ovidrel 500 mg when 2nd largest follicle reaches a mean diameter of 18mm.
           Cancel cycle if &lt; 3 follicles 10mm or larger are recruited or if spontaneous ovulation
           occurs.

        -  Retrieval: per standard IVF routine

        -  Vitrification: all viable oocytes will be vitrified on the day of oocyte retrieval.

        -  Remainder of stimulation cycle: no additional medications

        -  Stimulation and retrieval cycle may be repeated at patient request if &lt; 5 oocytes are
           vitrified to store additional oocytes for transfer cycle.

      Transfer cycle:

        -  Programmed frozen embryo transfer protocol as per ART program routine: precycle
           treatment with oral contraceptives (OCP), leuprolide administration during OCP, OCP
           withdrawal bleeding, estrogen priming of endometrium, ultrasound assessment of
           endometrium after 12-14 days, addition of daily progesterone when endometrial thickness
           is 7mm or greater, oocyte warming/fertilization/transfer scheduled.

        -  Oocyte warming and intracytoplasmic sperm injection (ICSI): oocytes warmed on the 2nd
           day of progesterone administration (example, if progesterone is started on Monday,
           oocytes are warmed on Tuesday).  Semen sample collected on day of warming and prepared
           per IVF routine for ICSI.  Mature viable oocytes undergo ICSI.  Per ART laboratory
           routine, oocytes are assessed for fertilization the following day.  If embryos are
           available for transfer, the embryo transfer procedure is performed according to
           standard CMC ART program guidelines the 6-8 cell or blastocyst stage.  If available,
           excess embryos may be cryopreserved, at patients' request, as per CMC ART Program
           routine.  Follow-up hormonal therapy, pregnancy test(s), and ultrasound studies will be
           performed per CMC ART program protocol.

      Vitrified oocytes will be discarded or kept in storage according to the terms of our oocyte
      storage agreement.

      Crossover:

      If a patient fails to conceive after the above, she may elect to cross-over into the
      opposite treatment group
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of oocytes retrieved</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of oocytes vitrified</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>number of embryos from vitrified oocytes</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>per ovarian stimulation treatment protocol</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Infertility</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>clomiphene plus gonadotropins</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>clomiphene plus gonadotropins</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Leuprolide flare</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Leuprolide flare</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>clomiphene plus gonadotropins</intervention_name>
    <description>clomiphene plus gonadotropin ovulation induction</description>
    <arm_group_label>clomiphene plus gonadotropins</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Clomid. Serophene. Gonal f. Bravelle. Follistim. Menopur.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Leuprolide flare</intervention_name>
    <description>Leuprolide flare ovulation induction</description>
    <arm_group_label>Leuprolide flare</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lupron.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Basal FSH 17 IU/mL (highest ever)

          -  Basal FSH 15-17 (highest ever) and failed EFORT test

          -  Age &gt; 43 at the time of expected retrieval

          -  Failure to conceive with a prior &quot;poor prognosis&quot; IVF stimulation protocol (microdose
             leuprolide flare or GnRH antagonist cycle) if administered because of evidence of
             diminished ovarian reserve

          -  Failure to conceive with 3 or more IVF cycles at CMC

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Contraindications to IVF

          -  Contraindication to pregnancy

          -  Allergy or contraindication to medications used for IVF or embryo transfer

          -  Use for a gestational carrier

          -  Uncorrected or untreatable uterine infertility

          -  Smoking or substance abuse within 3 months of initiating stimulation for IVF
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bradley S Hurst, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Carolinas Healthcare System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 25, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Carolinas Healthcare System</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Brad Hurst</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Assisted Reproductive Therapies</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>infertility</keyword>
  <keyword>diminished ovarian reserve</keyword>
  <keyword>fertilization in vitro</keyword>
  <keyword>ovulation inducion</keyword>
  <keyword>vitrification</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Infertility</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Clomiphene</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leuprolide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
