<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="77333">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02035345</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-413</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02035345</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Slowed Carboplatin Infusion for Ovarian Cancer Patients Receiving Carboplatin Re-Treatment</brief_title>
  <official_title>Slowed Carboplatin Infusion for Ovarian Cancer Patients Receiving Carboplatin Re-Treatment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a research study to determine if administering carboplatin at a slower rate when
      re-treating recurrent ovarian cancer patients prior to the development of a hypersensitivity
      reaction will decrease the frequency and severity of future hypersensitivity reactions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      For women with recurrent ovarian cancer, re-treatment with carboplatin is frequently
      recommended.  However, carboplatin re-treatment can result in an allergic or allergic-like
      reaction called a hypersensitivity reaction.  Symptoms of a hypersensitivity reaction can
      include, but are not limited to itching, rash, swelling of the lips, tongue, or throat,
      chest pain, chest tightness, shortness of breath, wheezing, abdominal pain, nausea,
      vomiting, diarrhea, palpitations, dizziness, confusion, and low pressure.  Hypersensitivity
      reactions occur in 20-40% of women with recurrent ovarian cancer who are re-treated with
      carboplatin.  At least half of the hypersensitivity reactions are described as moderately
      severe with symptoms of generalized rash, wheezing, facial swelling, difficulty
      breathing/shortness of breath, and hypotension (low blood pressure).

      Patients who suffer from a hypersensitivity reaction while receiving carboplatin and require
      additional therapy may receive future carboplatin infusions utilizing a &quot;desensitization&quot;
      technique. A desensitization is when carboplatin is administered in slowly increasing
      amounts as an inpatient under the direction of the department of Allergy Immunology at
      Massachusetts General Hospital.  A desensitization allows patient to safely receive
      carboplatin, but requires an inpatient hospitalization, which may be of significant
      inconvenience to some patients.

      As part of this study, the participant will continue to receive carboplatin as part of their
      standard therapy.  The change would be instead of carboplatin being administered over a 30
      minute period, the carboplatin be administered intravenously according to the following
      schedule:

        -  First hour - Administer 1 percent of total dose

        -  Second hour - Administer 9 percent

        -  Third hour - Administer 90 percent

      Standard pre-medications will be administered immediately prior to the carboplatin infusion
      which will include of 20 mg of dexamethasone, 50mg of diphenhydramine, and famotidine 20 mg.

      The participant's medical record will also be reviewed to evaluate whether age, cancer
      stage/grade, number of previous carboplatin cycles, accompanying agents, and/or medical
      conditions have an effect on hypersensitivity reactions.  The participant will also be asked
      to fill out a short optional form regarding race and ethnicity to evaluate whether or not
      these factors contribute to hypersensitivity reactions.

      If the participant experiences a hypersensitivity reaction, the study protocol will be
      discontinued.  A standard blood draw for a tryptase (a blood test for an allergic reaction)
      will be obtained at the time of the reaction along with other discretionary laboratories
      recommended by your oncologist.  The participant will then be referred to the Allergy
      Immunology Department if carboplatin is determined to be necessary for future treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the frequency of carboplatin infusion reactions using a slowed carboplatin infusion program</measure>
    <time_frame>2 Years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the frequency of carboplatin infusion reactions using a slowed carboplatin infusion program</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To characterize the nature and symptoms of carboplatin reactions associated with the slowed infusion protocol.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 Years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To characterize the nature and symptoms of carboplatin reactions associated with the slowed infusion protocol.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Recurrent Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Platinum Sensitive Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Carboplatin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Carboplatin will be prepared as a single 500ml infusion. Potentially 6 cycles Carboplatin (Amount of total dose) will be administered intravenously by the treating nurse according to the following schedule:
First hour - Administer 1 percent of total dose (5ml with tubing primed)
Second hour - Administer 9 percent (45 mL)
Third hour - Administer 90 percent (450 mL)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Carboplatin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Paraplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>CBDCA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must have histologically or cytologically confirmed ovarian cancers for
             which carboplatin is an acceptable treatment option.  In addition, participants must
             be candidates for systemic chemotherapy as determined by their treating physician.

          -  Participants must have received a carboplatin-containing regimen at initial
             diagnosis.  Retreatment is permitted in second or greater line with carboplatin-based
             chemotherapy.

          -  Age ≥ 18 years of age

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status &lt;2 (see Appendix A).

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test within 72
             hours prior to initiating chemotherapy on trial and must agree to practice an
             effective method of birth control, such as an intrauterine device, tubal ligation, or
             oral contraceptives, during the study and for six months after their last treatment.
             Women should not breast-feed while on this study

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

          -  Patients must be willing to comply with study design and requirements for
             participating on the study.

          -  Laboratory Criteria for eligibility The following are laboratory criteria for
             baseline absolute neutrophil count, platelet count, and creatinine for inclusion on
             this study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants who exhibit any of the following conditions at screening will not be
             eligible for admission into the study.

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to carboplatin.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Aleena Banerji, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Aleena Banerji, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(617) 726-3850</phone>
    <email>tlax@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Timothy Lax, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(617) 726-3850</phone>
    <email>abanerji@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Aleena Banerji, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-726-3850</phone>
      <email>abanerji@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Timothy Lax, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(617) 726-3850</phone>
      <email>tlax@partners.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Aleena Banerji, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 12, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 21, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Aleena Banerji</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Recurrent Ovarian Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Platinum Sensitive Ovarian Cancer</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
