<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="158189">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02059993</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SF2009-2012</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02059993</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of Obstructive Sleep Apnea and Its Intervention on Coronary Heart Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effects of Obstructive Sleep Apnea and Its Intervention on Coronary Heart Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chinese Pulmonary Vascular Disease Research Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chinese Pulmonary Vascular Disease Research Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>China: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Obstructive sleep apnea(OSA) is an important identifiable cause of hypertension. Previous
      study has suggested that OSA significantly increases cardiovascular morbidity and mortality,
      especially in patients with pre-existing cardiovascular disease.The standardized treatment
      of moderate/severe OSA is continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP). Most of short-term
      trials indicated that CPAP treatment reduced BP in patients with OSA. But relevant studies
      have a relative short duration with only but few more than one year. In our opinion, they
      are not sufficient to detect the real effect of CPAP on reduction in BP. Besides, the impact
      of OSA on metabolic disorder is still unclear.We hypothesized that long-term CPAP treatment
      could reduce blood pressure and improve metabolic disorder in patients with coronary heart
      disease (CHD)and OSA.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is a common disorder characterized by repetitive partial
      (hypopnea) or complete (apnea) occlusion of the upper airway during sleep caused by collapse
      of the pharyngeal airway, resulting in sleep fragmentation and oxyhemoglobin desaturation.
      Kiely and colleague's study showed that over 20% of hypertensive patients exhibit OSA,
      whereas prevalence of hypertension in the setting of OSA exceeds 50%. One study confirmed
      that OSA is an important identifiable cause of hypertension. OSA is considered as one of the
      most common risk factors of resistant hypertension. Previous study has suggested that OSA
      significantly increases cardiovascular morbidity and mortality, especially in patients with
      pre-existing cardiovascular disease. Several studies confirmed that CPAP reduced systolic
      blood pressure (SBP) and diastolic blood pressure (DBP) in patients with OSA. Additionally,
      some papers reported that there was a protective effect of CPAP therapy against death from
      cardiovascular disease in patients with severe OSA. Other researches regarding the
      antihypertensive effect of CPAP therapy, however, showed that CPAP had no antihypertensive
      effect. But relevant studies have a relative short duration with only but few more than one
      year. In our opinion, they are not sufficient to detect the real effect of CPAP on reduction
      in BP. According to our knowledge, there is no report about long-term effect of CPAP on BP
      in hypertensive patients with  coronary revascularization (CRV)  and OSA under conventional
      antihypertensive medications. Therefore, we conducted a long-term, prospective controlled
      study to investigate the effects of CPAP on BP, metabolic disorder, clinical symptoms,
      cardiovascular and cerebrovascular events in patients with CHD and OSA on conventional
      treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Blood Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 month, 3 month, 6 month, 12 month, 18 month, 24 month, 30 month, 36 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Glucose and Lipid metabolism</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 month, 3 month, 6 month, 12 month, 18 month, 24 month, 30 month, 36 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in epworth sleepiness scale (ESS)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month，3 month，6 month，12 month，18 month，24 month，30 month，36 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>cardiovascular and cerebrovascular events</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 month, 3 month, 6 month, 12 month, 18 month, 24 month, 30 month, 36 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Metabolic Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>continuous positive airway pressure</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>mean continuous positive airway pressure use was at least 4 hours per night; continuous positive airway pressure group received fixed-level continuous positive airway pressure titration using an automated pressure</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>continuous positive airway pressure</intervention_name>
    <description>mean continuous positive airway pressure use was at least 4 hours per night;continuous positive airway pressure group received fixed-level continuous positive airway pressure titration using an automated pressure</description>
    <arm_group_label>continuous positive airway pressure</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  men and women, aged 45 to 75 years old

          -  verified diagnosis of hypertension by medical history or receiving antihypertensive
             drugs

          -  established diagnosis of CHD

          -  at least 3-month optimal treatment for  hypertension

          -  moderate or severe OSA

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  if they had secondary hypertension

          -  central sleep apneas

          -  history of significant chronic renal, or hepatic failure or severe pulmonary disease

          -  diagnosed with malignant cancer with a life expectancy of less than 2years

          -  regular use of medications that can affect BP(including corticosteroids or sedative
             drugs)

          -  severe psychiatric disease

          -  sustained excessive alcohol use

          -  current use of CPAP treatment for OSA or pharyngeal surgery for OSA

          -  New York Heart Association Class III-IV degree

          -  declined to participate or were unable to give informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zhihong Liu, MD，PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Fuwai Hospital, National Center for Cardiovascular Diseases</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 11, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 9, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>continuous positive airway pressure</keyword>
  <keyword>hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>coronary heart disease</keyword>
  <keyword>metabolic disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>obstructive sleep apnea</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Apnea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
