<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="79001">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01999946</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>S12-03724</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1U01DA033336-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01999946</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Extended-Release Naltrexone Opiod Treatment at Jail Re-Entry</brief_title>
  <acronym>XOR</acronym>
  <official_title>Extended-Release Naltrexone Opiod Treatment at Jail Re-Entry</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Friends Research Institute, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare the effectiveness of extended-release naltrexone
      (XR-NTX) vs. enhanced treatment-as-usual (TAU) among opioid dependent adults leaving NYC
      jails. In parallel, we propose to recruit a matched, quasi-experimental methadone cohort,
      which will result in a naturalistic comparison of XR-NTX vs. an established jail-based
      methadone treatment program standard-of-care. Our primary aim is to compare time-to-relapse
      among participants treated with XR-NTX vs. randomized TAU controls and time-to-relapse among
      XR-NTX arm vs. jail-based MTP participants, following release from jail. Secondary aims will
      compare related opioid treatment outcomes post-release across all arms.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a randomized control trial of XR-NTX (n=100) vs. enhanced TAU (n=100) among
      opioid dependent adults leaving NYC jails who explicitly reject agonist treatment.
      Initiating treatment the week prior to release and continuing for 25 weeks post-release, we
      hypothesize the XR-NTX arm will demonstrate significantly longer time-to-relapse vs. TAU. In
      parallel, we propose to recruit a matched, quasi-experimental methadone cohort (n=100),
      which will result in a naturalistic comparison of XR-NTX vs. an established jail-based MTP
      standard-of-care.

      Rationale: Immediate relapse to drug, alcohol, and tobacco use is a nearly universal and
      expected near-term outcome among adults with addiction disorders leaving U.S. jails.  Yet
      while opioid agonist therapies are proven and effective re-entry interventions, many US
      correctional facilities, including almost all large U.S. municipal jails, do not offer these
      treatments. However, in New York City (NYC), jail-to-community methadone treatment is, since
      1986, a well-studied standard-of-care, yet many inmates eligible to initiate the methadone
      treatment program (MTP) while incarcerated do not, possibly due to anti-methadone patient
      preferences. Rather, the vast majority of these jail detainees undergo a brief 6-day
      methadone taper following arrest, remain in jail for brief periods out-of-treatment while
      'drug free' and undergoing a decline in physiologic opioid tolerance, nearly universally
      relapse to heroin or other illicit opioid use following release,  and are re-arrested in the
      next 12 months at rates of 50-75%. Extended-release naltrexone (XR-NTX, Vivitrol), now
      FDA-approved for opioid dependence, produces a 30-day mu opioid receptor antagonist
      blockade, and offers an potentially promising modality for 'inoculating' persons leaving
      jails against immediate opioid relapse.  Persons injected with 380mg of XR-NTX are unable to
      effectively experience euphoria or respiratory depression when returning to average doses of
      illicit opioids for the ensuing 4-5 weeks. An injection prior to release would possibly give
      the individual a month or so to return home from jail, experience opioid abstinence, and
      then either continue XR-NTX, initiate agonist or behavioral treatments, or, resume a
      significantly postponed relapse to illicit use.  Our team recently established the
      feasibility of administering XR-NTX to opioid dependent adults within a week of release in
      NYC jails.  We now propose to conduct a large, definitive randomized controlled trial
      estimating the effectiveness of XR-NTX as opioid treatment at release from jail vs. a
      counseling- and referral-enhanced treatment-as-usual (TAU) condition.  We also propose to
      recruit a non-randomized, quasi-experimental cohort of participants in a jail-based
      methadone maintenance program (MTP), allowing an additional comparison of XR-NTX to a
      methadone standard-of-care.

      Specific Aim 1: Randomized Effectiveness Trial of XR-NTX vs. TAU for Jail-to-Community
      Re-Entry Opioid Relapse Prevention.  Our primary aim is to compare time-to-relapse among
      participants treated with XR-NTX vs. randomized TAU controls, following release from jail.

      Specific Aim 2: Quasi-Experimental Comparison of XR-NTX vs. a Methadone Treatment Program
      for Re-Entry Opioid Relapse Prevention. To compare time-to-relapse among the XR-NTX RCT arm
      vs. jail-based MTP participants using a quasi-experimental design.

      Specific Aim 3a-e: Related Opioid Treatment Outcomes.  To compare re-entry rates of 5
      treatment outcomes across all arms: 3a) community treatment initiation and retention, 3b)
      any opioid and other illicit drug or alcohol use, defined as continuous counts of both days,
      amount/day, and urine toxicologies, 3c) injection drug use and HIV sexual risk factors, 3d)
      accidental drug overdose and mortality, and, 3e) rates of re-incarceration and an
      exploratory analysis of cost-effectiveness.

      Implications: While there is growing interest in the newly approve use of XR-NTX for opioid
      treatment, its effectiveness has not been evaluated in any correctional facilities,
      including large municipal jails, vs. usual care, nor in the context of standard-of-care
      methadone treatment.  This study will allow providers, correctional and public health
      authorities, including our collaborators at the NYC Department of Health and Mental Hygiene,
      and payers and policy makers to assess the utility of XR-NTX as re-entry opioid treatment,
      with important implications for limiting the great public safety and societal costs of
      heroin and prescription opioid addictions.  Further, NYC jail inmates are predominantly
      African American and Hispanic, and represent communities disproportionately affected by
      unemployment, family poverty, HIV and hepatitis C, all downstream effects of opioid
      dependence.  As the majority of opioid addicted persons leave jail return to their
      neighborhoods untreated and prone to rapid relapse, we hypothesize adding XR-NTX to the
      re-entry 'toolbox' will save both money and lives in these underserved communities.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>DSM-5 Opioid Use Disorder Diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>DSM-5 Opioid Use Disorder Diagnosis measured at the 6-month follow-up visits (post-release). This will be measured using the CIDI DSM-V.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HIV risk behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3, 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>HIV risk behavior will be assessed using the HIV-GAIN assessment at 1, 3, 6 and 12 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of days incarcerated</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of days incarcerated at 1, 3, 6 and 12 months post-release will be measured by use of self-report, NYC DOC &quot;Inmate Locator&quot; source reports obtained online, and by using a modified Economic Form 90.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Non-opioid drug use (Cocaine, Alcohol, Benzodiazepines, IV Drug Use)</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Non-opioid drug use, including cocaine, alcohol, benzodiazepines, IV drug use will be assessed at 1, 3, 6 and 12 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Days in drug abuse treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Days in drug abuse treatment, including any inpatient, outpatient, substance abuse counseling, or 12-step recovery group meetings will be assessed at 1, 3, 6 and 12 months by self-report (Economic Form 90).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of arrests</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of arrests will be assessed at 1, 3, 6, and 12 months post-release using a combination of self-report, NYC DOC &quot;Inmate Locator&quot; information obtained online, and a modified Economic Form 90.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Craving</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1, 3, 6, 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Craving scale measurements (opiates, alcohol, nicotine, and other drugs) will be assessed using the Visual Analog Scale at baseline, 1, 3, 6, and 12 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overdose</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Any drug overdose will be assessed by a self-report measure at 1, 3, 6, and 12 months post-release.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Motivation for Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3, 6, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Motivation to discontinue drug use and to participate in substance abuse treatment will be assessed using an adapted motivation scale and assessed at baseline, 3, 6, and 12 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">255</enrollment>
  <condition>Heroin Dependence</condition>
  <condition>Opioid-Related Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Extended-Release Naltrexone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Extended-Release Naltrexone (Vivitrol®), 380mg administered 1x/month by intramuscular injection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Treatment As Usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Enhanced Treatment As Usual arm will not receive any study medication, but 2-session enhancement counseling centered on post-release treatment involvement and a patient-drug educational handout with direct referrals to re-entry community treatment, including agonist maintenance (methadone and buprenorphine programs), drug-free outpatient and 12-step resources, and residential treatment including supportive housing programs will be provided. These counseling and referral efforts are designed to exceed standard, out-of-treatment experiences, and will ensure both arms are offered tangible health benefits above and beyond that of the usual jail incarceration period in accordance with DHS prisoner research standards.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Extended-Release Naltrexone</intervention_name>
    <description>Extended-Release Naltrexone (Vivitrol®), 380mg administered 1x/month by intramuscular injection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Extended-Release Naltrexone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vivitrol</other_name>
    <other_name>XR-NTX</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults incarcerated in NYC jails with known release dates.

          -  DSM-IV criteria for current opioid dependence.

          -  Not currently in or planning to pursue agonist (methadone, buprenorphine)
               treatment at release.

          -  Currently opioid free by history ('detoxed') and with a negative urine for all
             opioids.

          -  General good health as determined by complete medical history and physical
             examination

          -  Age &gt;18 years.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of liver failure and/or liver function test levels greater than three times
             normal.

          -  Pregnancy, lactation, or planning conception.

          -  Active medical illness that might make participation hazardous.

          -  Untreated or poorly controlled psychiatric disorder precluding safe participation
             --History of allergic reaction to naltrexone.

          -  Current chronic pain condition treated with opioids.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joshua D Lee, MD MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NYU MEDICAL CENTER</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ryan D McDonald, MA</last_name>
    <phone>646-501-2541</phone>
    <email>ryan.mcdonald@nyumc.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Joshua D Lee, MD MS</last_name>
    <phone>212-263-4242</phone>
    <email>joshua.lee@nyumc.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NYC Department of Corrections: Rikers Island Jail Facilities</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11370</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bellevue Hospital Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nadina Santana-Correa</last_name>
      <email>nadina.santana-correa@nyumc.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 26, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 26, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Heroin Dependence</keyword>
  <keyword>Opioid-Related Disorders</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Heroin Dependence</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Opioid-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Naltrexone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
