<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="110834">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01755065</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRO12020593</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01755065</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Meaning of Visual Analog Scales(VAS) for Teenage Pediatric Patients Undergoing Laparoscopic Surgical Procedures</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Meaning of Visual Analog Scales (VAS) for Teenage Pediatric Patients Undergoing Laparoscopic Surgical Procedures</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to find a more accurate postoperative pain assessment for
      teenager patients. This is important because a patient should not have a very strong pain
      medication such as morphine if the pain is just mild.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pain is a sensory and emotional experience, modified by multiple factors, including meaning,
      context, previous pain experience, culture, gender, expectation, anxiety, depression, fear,
      family and social factors. Hospitalized teenager patients (11-18 years) admitted to surgical
      services experience high prevalence of moderate and severe pain.1 The VAS (Visual Analog
      Scale, 0 mm &quot;no pain&quot;, to 100 mm,&quot; the worst pain possible &quot;) is used to assess
      postoperative pain for teenager patients. The reliability and validity of this scale was
      proven but clinical significance of VAS pain score is not clear. 2 There is an increased
      focus on very good pain control and is a common practice that patients with moderate or
      severe pain scores (numeric rating score, more than 4) to receive opioid pain medication 3,
      regardless of pain behavior or health care providers'  input , and this can result in
      various side effects. Pediatric nurses administer more pain medications to the children who
      vocalize   their pain. 4  Numerous clinical trials of postoperative pain treatment in
      teenager use only VAS pain scores to assess the effectiveness of a studied pain medication.

      Although the treatment of pain may be a basic human right, that does not mean that all
      teenager patients require opioids administration if they report high pain scores. It is our
      observation that teenager's pain behavior does not always correlate with the magnitude of
      reported pain scores by the patient and different caregivers. Concomitant parental and nurse
      observation of teenager's pain behavior can provide additional information about pain
      severity. Minimal correlation between VAS pain scores reported by teenager and caregivers
      does not mean that pain severity is &quot;unreal&quot;. Perioperative teenager's pain catastrophizing
      thoughts about pain, anxiety, and mood level can influence teenager's postoperative pain
      scores.

      The authors aim is to develop a multi-modal assessment   of postoperative pain for the
      teenager patient, using VAS pain scores reported by the teenager, nurse, and parent in
      association with the teenager's postoperative pain behavior, pain catastrophizing thinking,
      anxiety, and mood level. The subjects included in this study will be 206 teenager patients
      (11-17 years old) undergoing any laparoscopic surgical procedures. On postoperative day 1,
      the teenager will complete the following questionnaires: Visual Analog Scale from teenager
      (VAS teen), State-Trait Anxiety Inventory for Children (STAIC S - Anxiety), Pain
      Catastrophizing Scale for Children (PCS-C) and Brief Mood Introspection Scale (BMIS). The
      nurse taking care of the patient and one parent, preferable the mother, will complete the
      following questionnaires: Visual Analog Scale from parent (VAS p), Visual Analog Scale from
      nurse (VAS n), and Adolescent Pain Behavior Questionnaire from parent (APBQ-p), Adolescent
      Pain Behavior Questionnaire from nurse (APBQ-n). The main goal is to determine if VAS score
      reported by the teenager correlates with VAS scores reported by the parent and nurse, and
      with pain behavior scores reported by the nurse and family. Expected correlation is minimal
      (0.23-0.29) to moderate (0.3-0.49). Our second goal is to determine whether postoperative
      pain is associated with psychosocial factors such as teenager catastrophizing attention to
      pain, anxiety, and mood level. Expected correlation between postoperative VAS teen and
      teenager catastrophizing attention to pain, anxiety, and mood level is moderate (0.3-0.49)
      to high (&gt;/=0.5).

      To our knowledge, this is the first study to investigate all these variables together to
      assess postoperative pain for a teenager patient. The findings  of this study may influence
      the medical decisions regarding administration of pain medication, allow for a safer and
      more effective use of opioids  in postoperative period and would be very helpful for
      clinical and research practice.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Cross-Sectional</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-op pain score</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day post-operation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">206</enrollment>
  <condition>Postoperative Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Teenager laparoscopic patients</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The participants will be selected based on medical records review and medical interview on
        the day of surgery:  we plan to enroll 206 teenager patients   (11-17 years old) with
        anticipated postoperative pain after any laparoscopic procedure and their parents and
        nurses.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  11-17 years old, both male and female

          -  the patient is having any laparoscopic surgeries, elective or emergent, including
             robotic surgeries

          -  the patient will be admitted in hospital for at least 23 hours

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient and family refusal

          -  Patient already enrolled in another study

          -  Non English-speaking patients and families

          -  Cognitive impairment

          -  Developmental delay

          -  Patients who experienced surgical, anesthesia or medical complications;

          -  Patients with chronic pain condition (pain more than 3 months)

          -  Patients medicated at home or in hospital with long acting opioid pain medication
             (methadone, oxycontin, oxymorphone ER, morphine slow release)

          -  Patients with psychiatric medical history (except attention deficit disorders such
             us: ADD and ADHD)

          -  Patients taking at home the following medication: clonidine, antipsychotic,
             antidepressant and anxiolytic medications.

          -  Patients taking drugs, including smoking marijuana and other recreational drugs

          -  Positive pregnancy test

          -  Laparoscopic surgical procedures converted to open procedures

          -  Patients will be discharged on the day of surgery.

          -  If none of the patient's parent will stay with the child during hospital stay, the
             patient will be not enrolled in the study. If all 8 questionnaires cannot be filled
             on the day after surgery, the patient will be discontinued from this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>11 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mihaela Visoiu, MD</last_name>
    <phone>412-692-5260</phone>
    <email>visoium@upmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mihaela Visoiu, MD</last_name>
      <phone>412-692-5260</phone>
      <email>visoium@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mihaela Visoiu, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 27, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 19, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mihaela Visoiu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Anesthesiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>laparoscopic surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>teenager</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
