<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="33389">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01814319</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Re-Prosper HF</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01814319</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Repurposing Probenecid as a Positive Inotrope for the Treatment of Heart Failure</brief_title>
  <acronym>ReProsperHF</acronym>
  <official_title>Initial Study on the Use of Probenecid as a Positive Inotrope for the Treatment of Systolic Heart Failure in Stable NYHA Class II to IV Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Cincinnati</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Cincinnati</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Probenecid is an FDA approved drug for the treatment gout and hyperuricemia. It has been
      used safely in humans for decades for this and other indications. The investigators have
      recently discovered that this drug can also stimulate other receptors in the heart and
      therefore improve its function. The hypothesis of this study is that probenecid can be used
      to improve the function of the heart and therefore the symptoms in patients with heart
      failure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators will test the hypothesis that oral administration of probenecid results in
      improved symptomatology and heart function in patients with systolic heart failure. There
      will be three cohorts.

      Cohort 1 will enroll up to 50 subjects in a double-blinded, randomized, placebo-control,
      cross-over study with each patient serving as his or her own control. The subjects will have
      stable HF, an ejection fraction of less than or equal to 40% and NYHA II to IV symptoms.
      Each subject will undergo 1 week of investigational product (IP), consisting of oral
      probenecid therapy 1 gram twice a day or placebo with weekly follow.

      The subjects will undergo EKGs, laboratory analysis, physical exams; dyspnea and quality of
      life questionnaires and a 6 minute walk test (MWT) at baseline. There will be 2 optional
      sub-studies one for echocardiographic data and the other biomarkers.

      Cohort 2 will enroll up to 50 subjects in a double-blinded, randomized, placebo-control
      study and will include patients admitted to the hospital with acute decompensated HF.  Each
      subject will also receive Investigational product consisting of either 1 gram orally twice
      daily of probenecid or placebo during their hospitalization. They will have daily follow-up
      with EKG and appropriate laboratory work. In addition to the EKG, laboratory analysis,
      physical exams, dyspnea and quality of life questionnaires and 6 MWT data will be collected;
      additional data such as length of hospital stay, biomarkers, use of inotropic therapy and
      diuretics, and rate of diuresis will also be collected.

      Cohort 3 will enroll up to 50 healthy subjects in a double-blinded, randomized,
      placebo-control study. Each subject will also receive Investigational product consisting of
      either 2 grams orally of probenecid or placebo. During a 6 hour course subjects will have
      laboratory analysis, physical exam, telemetry, EKG and echocardiographic studies performed
      as measures of both safety and effect of the compound.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>6 minute walk test</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measure for changes in the distance that the patient can walk over 6 minutes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>shortness of breath</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measure objectively if there are changes in perceived shortness of breath using a standardized scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ejection fraction</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will measure via echocardiography the systolic function of the heart</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>beta naturietic peptide</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will measure for changes in the beta natuiretic peptide as a marker of cardiac function and dilatation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>serum electrolytes</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>We will measure several important electrolytes such as Na, K and Ca.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Systolic Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Probenecid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Probenecid 1 gr oral twice daily or placebo will be given to the subject for 1 week (randomly assigned). A subsequent 1 week washout period will occur followed by the alternate therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Probenecid 1 gr oral twice daily</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Probenecid</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          1. 18 years of age or older

          2. EF &lt; 40% via echocardiogram within the past 12 months

          3. Stable dose of heart failure medications for &gt; past 1 month

          4. NYHA class II - IV

        Exclusion Criteria

          1. Pregnant or lactating female

          2. Receiving IV inotrope

          3. History of significant non-compliance

          4. Unwilling to adhere to the protocol

          5. Systemic systolic BP less than 90 mmHg at screening visit

          6. History of allergy to probenecid

          7. History of gout

          8. History of renal calculi

          9. Recent unstable coronary artery syndromes (USA, admission to hospital for AMI,
             revascularization procedure, or acute decompensated HF requiring hospitalization)
             within the past 3 months.

         10. Implant of CRT device within the past 3 months

         11. TIA, CVA or major surgery within the past 3 months

         12. Valvular heart disease (more than moderate stenosis or insufficiency)

         13. HOCM, myocarditis, constrictive pericarditis, congenital heart disease, 14 Active
             chemotherapy, significant malignancy or uncontrolled metabolic disease (untreated
             hyper or hypothyroidism, Cushing's disease etc.)What about uncontrolled DM??  HgA1C &gt;
             etc

        15. Elevated liver enzymes (&gt; 3 times ULN), 16. Current atrial fibrillation or frequent
        PVCs (should we define this now) 17. End stage renal disease (dialysis dependent) or
        worsening renal insufficiency should define now.

        18. History of gastric ulcerations, significant gastroesophageal reflux. 19. Other
        condition that in the opinion of the investigator, would make the subject a poor candidate
        for the study.

        20. Co-administration of any medication that in the opinion of the investigator places the
        subject at increased risks due to potential adverse drug interactions.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ginger Conway, MSN, RN, CNP</last_name>
    <phone>513 558-3476</phone>
    <email>conwaygg@ucmail.uc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Cincinnati</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45267</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 6, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 14, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Cincinnati</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jack Rubinstein</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Asst Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>heart failure</keyword>
  <keyword>ejection fraction equal or less than 40%</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure, Systolic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Probenecid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
