<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="77327">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02027545</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IIR 12-411</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02027545</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Promoting Veteran-Centered Colorectal Cancer Screening</brief_title>
  <acronym>PROM-IS</acronym>
  <official_title>Promoting Veteran-Centered Colorectal Cancer Screening</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Colon cancer is a common and serious cancer that is diagnosed in nearly 150,000 Americans
      each year. This cancer is thought to start as a benign (not serious) growth in the colon,
      called a polyp. Screening for polyps and colon cancer can reduce the chances of developing
      and dying from this condition. Experts therefore recommend that most adults get screened for
      colon cancer starting at age 50.

      In the past, many patients did not want to get screened for colon cancer, often because of
      fear or embarrassment. Patients and doctors who saw first-hand the effects of colon cancer
      have worked hard to change this, through education, media campaigns, and research. As a
      result, screening is now performed in most patients over age 50. These days, doctors are
      encouraged to screen through reminders, &quot;report cards&quot;, and even bonus payments.

      Colon cancer is a common and serious cancer that is diagnosed in nearly 150,000 Americans
      each year. This cancer is thought to start as a benign (not serious) growth in the colon,
      called a polyp. Screening for polyps and colon cancer can reduce the chances of developing
      and dying from this condition. Experts therefore recommend that most adults get screened for
      colon cancer starting at age 50.

      In the past, many patients did not want to get screened for colon cancer, often because of
      fear or embarrassment. Patients and doctors who saw first-hand the effects of colon cancer
      have worked hard to change this, through education, media campaigns, and research. As a
      result, screening is now performed in most patients over age 50. These days, doctors are
      encouraged to screen through reminders, &quot;report cards&quot;, and even bonus payments.

      So what is the problem? Well, some patients still are not getting screened when they should.
      This is especially a problem in high-risk patients, like those who have a family history,
      and in those who do not have access to health care. A lot of people are working on this
      important problem, and as a result, more people are getting screened than ever before.

      On the other hand, there are now patients who are getting screened even though they may not
      &quot;need&quot; to. This is mainly the case for people who are older and have other health problems
      that could make screening (and cancer treatment) more risky (or, for some, even harmful).
      This is happening because the efforts to get people screened are &quot;spilling over&quot; to some who
      might not benefit. Sometimes, these older individuals might not even realize that, for them,
      screening is not absolutely necessary. While doctors should continue to work to increase
      screening for those who might benefit, they also need to remember that one size does not fit
      all.

      The purpose of this study is to test a new, more patient-centered approach to colon cancer
      screening. In older individuals (ages 70 to 75) who have other health problems and are &quot;due&quot;
      for screening, the investigators will provide education on the benefits and harms of colon
      cancer screening. But instead of simply providing these patients with &quot;average&quot; information
      about these benefits, the investigators will give them information that takes their health
      and screening history into account and therefore applies to them more personally. The
      investigators will also work with health systems to create time and space for patient and
      doctor to discuss whether screening is the right choice for each individual. This way,
      patients can make an informed choice about what is right for them, with the help of their
      doctor. In the future, the results of this study will help patients make more informed
      screening decisions, especially when the benefits of screening may be uncertain for them
      personally.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Colorectal cancer (CRC) screening is a widely recommended, evidence-based preventive service
      that has traditionally been underused. Over the last decade, organized efforts by the
      Veterans Health Administration (VHA) to increase population screening for CRC among Veterans
      have been successful. But these population-centered efforts have increased screening
      utilization in a way that is not always concordant with screening benefit, particularly
      among older Veterans with comorbid illness. As patients get older and acquire health
      problems, the benefit of screening decreases and the potential harm of screening increases.
      Yet, existing population-centered efforts fail to adequately inform older, less healthy
      patients about this changing balance in benefit and harm, often yielding screening
      utilization that is discordant with benefit. In this study, the investigators will evaluate
      the impact of a 3-part Veteran-centered intervention (VC) versus population-centered control
      (PC) on the frequency of CRC screening orders in a cluster-randomized controlled trial.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>CRC screening ordered</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to six months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary dependent variable in the analysis will be whether screening was ordered at the clinic visit (dichotomous). The investigators will determine whether screening was ordered using CDW data, applying an algorithm similar to one that was previously developed for a QUERI-funded study on CRC screening overuse (RRP 12-184).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">440</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Decision Aid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>One half of the eligible patients will be randomly assigned the Veteran-centered intervention (VC) that includes an individualized decision aid, provider education, and modified performance measure/reminder).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No Decision Aid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>One half of the eligible patients will be randomly assigned to the pragmatic control (PC) (provider education and modified performance measure/reminder, but no decision aid).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Decision Aid</intervention_name>
    <description>The study entails a 3-part Veteran-centered intervention (VC) (individualized decision aid, provider education, and modified performance measure/reminder) versus pragmatic control (PC)
(provider education and modified performance  measure/ reminder, but no decision ai</description>
    <arm_group_label>Decision Aid</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Provider Education</intervention_name>
    <description>Providers of patients in both arms of the study will be given an educational module about recent data on the benefits and risks of screening in elderly patients and how these data fit in with existing (and highly influential) population-centered guidelines.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Decision Aid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>No Decision Aid</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Performance Measure Modification</intervention_name>
    <description>The clinical reminder system will be modified so to facilitate documentation of informed decision making about CRC screening, including specific reasons for not screening. Additionally, providers who indicate a specific exception for not screening (using the modified clinical reminder) will be considered as satisfying the requirements and will not be penalized in terms of performance pay, and will be removed from feedback reports that encourage population screening.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Decision Aid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>No Decision Aid</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Veterans who are 70-75 years of age

          -  Have a Charlson comorbidity index (CCI) greater than or equal to 1

          -  Are due for screening according to the 2008 USPSTF CRC screening guideline

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Veterans who are at increased risk for CRC due to a personal or family history of
             colon adenomas or cancer, or a personal history of inflammatory bowel disease

          -  Limited life expectancy (e.g., enrolled in hospice or diagnosed with metastatic
             cancer)

          -  Non-English speaking

          -  Legally blind

          -  Have severe cognitive impairments (e.g., dementia)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>70 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sameer D Saini, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Ann Arbor Healthcare System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Darcy Saffar, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>(734) 845-4395</phone>
    <phone_ext>54395</phone_ext>
    <email>darcy.saffar@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sameer D Saini, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(734) 769-7100</phone>
    <email>Sameer.Saini@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Ann Arbor Healthcare System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48113</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Darcy Saffar, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>734-845-4395</phone>
      <phone_ext>54395</phone_ext>
      <email>darcy.saffar@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sameer D Saini, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cancer screening</keyword>
  <keyword>decision making</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
