<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="116189">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02157168</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IHS-1306-04356</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02157168</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Connections for Healthy Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Connections for Healthy Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Arizona</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Arizona</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators propose to develop, deliver, and test a novel personalized education
      intervention that engages female Medicaid beneficiaries in making decisions about
      age-appropriate evidence-based utilization of women's preventive services.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators propose to test a community-developed and targeted intervention that
      employs community health workers (CHWs) as aides to newly Medicaid-insured women. These
      women face the challenges of engaging with their healthcare and health and of making highly
      personal and socioculturally embedded decisions about reproductive health-related preventive
      services (e.g., contraception, STI and cancer screening).

      All newly enrolled women in one of Arizona's state-wide Medicaid health plans (University
      Family Care) who are ambulatory and community-dwelling, and between the ages of 18-39, will
      be identified by the health plan on a monthly basis as eligible for this study. For at least
      the first month, these new health plan members will be randomized 2 to 1 (intervention to
      usual care control).  Each month the health plan will provide the study team with the number
      of new members. A study team member will then provide the health plan with a list of numbers
      (1's and 0's) generated using the biased coin design to apply to those new members. To avoid
      bias, health plan staff will not be aware of the study arm associated with each of those
      numbers at the time of assignment. Once assignments have been completed, the health plan
      will be notified as to which of the two groups will constitute the control arm. Members
      assigned to the control and intervention groups will be tracked separately by the health
      plan staff.

      All new health plan enrollees (as per current standard health plan practice) receive a
      series of welcome communications (by mail and electronically) from the health plan shortly
      after enrollment. These are designed to apprise new members of health plan policies and
      procedures related to covered benefits, facilitate the selection of a primary care provider,
      and provide general preventive health resources and information. This is followed by a
      second mailing at 3-months post enrollment, as well as a nurse follow-up call. The latter is
      designed to answer questions about covered services, finding a primary care provider, and/or
      otherwise provide support. Both intervention and control group member will receive identical
      communications from the health plan up to this point.

      Intervention group members will receive two additional mailings (at immediately after
      enrollment and randomization and again 2 months after enrollment) from the health plan (but
      paid for by the study) by post and electronically, briefly describing the intervention and
      inviting eligible women to participate. Potential participants will be given a confidential
      dedicated telephone number, email and website to contact for participation that they may use
      should they elect to participate in the study.

      When the potential participant contacts the research office she will be provided with a
      brief verbal overview of the intervention including time requirement and content to be
      covered. She will then be offered the opportunity to set up an individual confidential
      appointment with a community health worker (CHW) at her earliest convenience. At that time,
      basic contact and demographic information will be collected, language and location
      preference, date/time of proposed meeting, and the contact information for the research
      office for any questions. Additionally, a packet of information will be mailed to the
      participant explaining the nature and content of the intervention as well as a copy of the
      informed consent document. At 48 to 72 hours prior to the appointed time, the assigned CHW
      will call to introduce herself, to answer lingering questions about the proposed encounter,
      and to confirm the time and location of the intervention appointment.  The CHW will meet
      with the subject and complete the informed consent process. Also, the baseline informed
      patient choice survey will be performed using a touch tablet device (to ascertain baseline
      knowledge, patient preferences, informed decision making, and health literacy). The CHW will
      tailor the individual education session to meet the unique needs of the participant (e.g.,
      an individual who discloses a history of surgical sterilization will not receive information
      about contraception). The 45-minute intervention will be delivered as described above. The
      patient will be asked to personally assess her needs with regard to reproductive
      health-related issues. The CHW will work with the participant to develop a personalized plan
      to access the relevant targeted preventive services. This may involve assistance with
      contacting the Health Plan and assistance with identifying or making an appointment with a
      primary care provider. At the conclusion of the intervention, the patient will be encouraged
      to reach out to the CHW by telephone or electronically if she has any subsequent questions
      or concerns, and appointments for the two booster telephone calls will be scheduled.
      Finally, in consideration for her time and participation, the participant will be provided
      with a $50 gift card.

      Booster telephone support calls will occur at 2 and 4 months post intervention. A telephone
      call guide will be designed to reinforce and clarify key concepts from the initial
      intervention encounter as well as to help clients formulate relevant questions related to
      specific women's preventive services and other health concerns in anticipation of their next
      primary care provider (PCP) visit. Participants will also be queried specifically about any
      issues related to interactions with the health plan and/or contacting her primary care
      provider. The patient will be assisted with connecting to the health plan or her PCP's
      office for those issues that cannot be easily addressed by the CHW. Whenever possible, every
      effort will be made by the CHW to connect the patient to the appropriate outreach staff at
      that PCP's office (if such staff is available). Again the availability of the CHW by
      telephone or electronically for interval questions will be emphasized. At month 6, the
      participant will receive a call from the telephone interviewer to administer the 6-month
      informed patient choice survey identical to the survey that was completed at baseline. A $30
      gift card incentive will be offered to complete this survey.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case-Only, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <target_duration>6 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Identify and utilization of PCP</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Among participants how many have identified and sought care from a primary care physician.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The impact of the intervention on other healthcare utilization.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Utilization of women's preventive services, utilization of other preventive services, and utilization emergency department visits and preventable hospital stays.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Informed decision making making regarding the healthcare system and their health.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigators will start with existing measures (e.g.,Single Item Literacy Screener, International Patient Decision Aids Standards) and/or develop new items based on results of a series of participant focus groups.  The results will be used to finalize pre/post informed patient choice surveys and to choose our 10 allowed items for the health plan's twice annual Member Satisfaction Survey.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Contraception</condition>
  <condition>Sexually Transmitted Infections</condition>
  <condition>Cervical Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Each month all newly enrolled female health plan members will have an equal chance of being randomly picked by the health plan (according to a randomization scheme provided by the study team) to be invited to contact and work with a Community health worker. Those not invited will constitute the usual care control group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Each month all newly enrolled female health plan members will have an equal chance of being randomly picked by the health plan (according to a randomization scheme provided by the study team) to be invited to contact and work with a Community health worker in the intervention group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Community health worker</intervention_name>
    <description>Community health workers (CHWs) in Hispanic communities, often referred to as &quot;promotoras,&quot; are members of the community who use &quot;resource sharing, partnership development, education, outreach, health promotion, and disease prevention strategies to improve the health&quot; of their communities.
The intervention itself consists of a 45-minute one-on-one presentation and tailored planning session delivered by a CHW in a community setting of the new member's choosing. Presentations (in English or Spanish) will be delivered using a tablet computer or a hand held flipchart. Two booster telephone interactions will be performed at 2 and 6 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Promotoras</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All newly enrolled women in one of Arizona's state-wide Medicaid health plans (University
        Family Care) who are ambulatory and community-dwelling and between the ages of 18-39, will
        be identified by the health plan on a monthly basis as eligible for this study.

        The target population will be newly enrolled female health plan members between the ages
        of 18 and 39 who will be randomly selected to be invited to access a Community Health
        Worker (CHW) (the intervention arm). Those not selected will constitute the usual care
        control group.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women between the ages of 18 and 39

          -  Women newly enrolled in one of the state-wide Medicaid health plans (University
             Family Care)

          -  Women who are ambulatory

          -  Women who are community-dwelling

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women not between the ages of 18 and 39

          -  Women not newly enrolled in one of the state wide Medicaid health plans (University
             Family Care)

          -  Women who are not ambulatory

          -  Women who are not community dwelling
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>39 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Franciso AR Garcia, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Arizona</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Francisco Garcia, M.D., MPH</last_name>
    <phone>520-626-8539</phone>
    <email>fcisco@u.arizona.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Arizona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tucson</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85721-0477</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Francisco Garcia, M.D., MPH</last_name>
      <phone>520-626-8539</phone>
      <email>fcisco@u.arizona.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Francisco Garcia, M.D., MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 29, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Affordable Care Act</keyword>
  <keyword>Medically underserved minorities</keyword>
  <keyword>Community health workers</keyword>
  <keyword>Health disparities among Mexican origin</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Uterine Cervical Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sexually Transmitted Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
