<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="38360">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01727622</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>815471</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01727622</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Arterial Spin Labeling (ASL) MRI for Cognitive Decline</brief_title>
  <official_title>Optimized Arterial Spin Labeling MRI for Cognitive Decline</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the value of Arterial Spin Labeling (ASL) MRI, a
      measure of blood flow to the brain, in Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI) and compare it to
      existing measures.  In particular, the investigators will compare ASL MRI to Positron
      Emission Tomography (PET/CT), which measures brain metabolism reflecting how well cells in a
      patient's brain are functioning. In addition, the investigators will assess the relationship
      of these measures to specific protein levels associated with Alzheimer's Disease in the
      patient's cerebrospinal fluid (the fluid that surrounds the brain and spinal cord) obtained
      by lumbar puncture.  By comparing the information that is available from these procedures to
      the patient's performance on cognitive tests, the investigators hope to learn which
      procedures most accurately reflect and assist in determination of the potential causes of
      cognitive difficulties that arise with MCI, and thus, which are most useful in the clinical
      setting. In particular, PET scans have been found to be very useful in diagnosis of MCI and
      Alzheimer's Disease, but the investigators want to find out if they can get the same, or
      better, information from an ASL MRI scan, which is less expensive and easier to acquire.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite region of interest (ROI) measure of cerebral blood flow (CBF) measured by ASL MRI versus composite ROI measure of cerebral metabolism measured by FDG PET</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Our primary aim is to determine if the diagnostic accuracy of 'state-of-the art' Arterial Spin Labeling (ASL) MRI is as good as (i.e., noninferior to) the diagnostic accuracy of FDG-PET/CT in comparison of MCI patients to cognitively normal adults. To test if ASL in noninferior to FDG-PET, we will use an asymptotic z test statistic for equivalent studies described in an equation of Zhou et al. (2002). The test statistic compares the AUCs from ASL and FDG-PET/CT by appropriately accounting for the correlation between them.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prediction of longitudinal change in hippocampal volume</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigators will compare ASL MRI versus FDG PET in their ability to predict disease progression based on change in hippocampal volume.  Investigators will define patients as 'progressors' if they display an atrophy rate greater than one standard deviation above the mean rate for healthy controls. Investigators will again use the composite ROI for ASL sequences and FDG-PET data to determine the best single or combination of predictors of progression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prediction of longitudinal change in clinical status (i.e. progression to Alzheimer's Disease)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigators will compare ASL MRI versus FDG PET in their ability to predict disease progression based on conversion to clinical Alzheimer's Disease. Investigators will determine which measure best predicts conversion to clinical Alzheimer's Disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Mild Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <condition>Alzheimer's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Diagnostic Imaging</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>ASL-MRI and FDG-PET will be compared for ability to discriminate between Control subjects and adults with Mild Cognitive Impairment (prodromal AD).  A lumbar puncture will be obtained in a proportion of the participants.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FDG-PET</intervention_name>
    <description>Diagnostic: FDG-PET imaging to examine neuronal health</description>
    <arm_group_label>Diagnostic Imaging</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ASL-MRI</intervention_name>
    <description>Arterial-Spin Labeled MRI to examine cerebral blood flow</description>
    <arm_group_label>Diagnostic Imaging</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lumbar Puncture</intervention_name>
    <description>Lumbar puncture to acquire a small amount of cerebrospinal fluid for protein level analyses.  Note that this will not be required in all participants.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Diagnostic Imaging</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Spinal Tap</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Males and females between the ages of 55 and 89.

          -  Fluent in English

          -  Part of the longitudinal cohort of the PMC/ADCC  and have a study partner (for MCI
             patients only)

          -  Adequate visual and auditory acuity to allow for neuropsychological testing

          -  Women: post-menopausal or surgically sterile

          -  Willing and able to complete all required study procedures

          -  Completed 6 grades of education

          -  Geriatric Depression scale less than 6 (assessed within 3 months)

        PATIENTS ONLY:

          -  Diagnosis of MCI

          -  MMSE between 24 and 30

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any significant neurological disease other than MCI

          -  Presence of pacemakers, aneurysm clips, artificial heart valves, ear implants, metal
             fragments or foreign bodies in the eyes, skin, or body

          -  Occupational risks for ferrous metal in the eye

          -  Major depression, bipolar disorder, history of schizophrenia

          -  History of substance abuse or dependence within the past 2 years.

          -  Significant systemic illness or unstable medical condition that could lead to
             difficulty complying with the protocol

          -  Severe claustrophobia that would preclude subject from completing the MRI

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Clinically relevant abnormalities in prior blood or urine samples including a blood
             glucose of ≥ 180 mg/dl

          -  Currently receiving medical or drug treatment contraindicating protocol participation
              e.g. anticoagulants such as Coumadin/Warfarin
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>55 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>89 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David A Wolk, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Grace Stockbower, BA</last_name>
    <phone>215-746-3949</phone>
    <email>grace.stockbower@uphs.upenn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Lauren Mancuso, BA</last_name>
    <phone>215-349-5903</phone>
    <email>lauren.mancuso@uphs.upenn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Penn Memory Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dasha Kliot, BA</last_name>
      <phone>215-746-3949</phone>
      <email>daria.kliot@uphs.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David A Wolk, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 30, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 22, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Wolk</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Neurology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognition Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
