<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="60506">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02052635</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>D5130L00065</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02052635</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ticagrelor vs Clopidogrel in Non-ST Elevation Acute Coronary Syndrome Patients Undergoing PCI With Bivalirudin.</brief_title>
  <acronym>NSTE-ACS</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase IV, Open Label Study, Comparing Ticagrelor Versus Clopidogrel in Non-ST Elevation Acute Coronary Syndrome (NSTE-ACS) Patients Undergoing Percutaneous Coronary Intervention (PCI) With Bivalirudin</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AstraZeneca</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine if ticagrelor is as effective as clopidogrel in
      rate of onset and degree of platelet inhibition for patients with non-ST elevation of acute
      coronary syndrome  undergoing ad hoc PCI with bivalirudin.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Multi-center, open-label study that will compare the onset of the platelet inhibition with
      ticagrelor versus clopidogrel when administered with bivalirudin during PCI on a background
      therapy of aspirin in patients with NSTE-ACS.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacodynamics Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in inhibition of platelet aggregation and reactivity</measure>
    <time_frame>0.5 hour and 1 hour after single loading dose of ticagrelor or clopidogrel given at the time of the bivalirudin bolus</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>On day of PCI procedure, blood samples will be tested using VerifyNow™ which measures platelet aggregation of whole blood and reports results in P2Y12 Reaction Units (PRU). The blood samples will be collected and tested at each time point specified.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in inhibition of platelet aggregation and reactivity</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hrs, 3 hrs, and 4 hours after single loading dose of ticagrelor or clopidogrel given at the time of the bivalirudin bolus.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>On day of PCI procedure, blood samples will be tested using Verify Now™ which measures platelet aggregation of whole blood and reports results in P2Y12 Reaction Units (PRU). The blood samples will be collected and tested at Baseline and at each time point specified.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the activated clotting time (ACT) of blood</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose, 5 minutes after bivalirudin bolus, at time of bivalirudin discontinuation, 1 hr and 2 hrs post bivalirudin discontinuation.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>On day of PCI procedure, the degree of anticoagulation response will be measured using the Hemochron ACT clot detection module to measure the length of time required for blood clot formation. The blood samples will be tested at each time point specified.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of ticagrelor in terms of adverse events.</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 1 (Screening Day -7 to Day 1); Visit 2 (Randomization Day 1) and the Follow up telephone contact (4-7 days after randomization)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Adverse events of major bleeding</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-ST Elevation Acute Coronary Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ticagrelor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>90 mg oral tablet</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Clopidogrel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>300 mg oral tablet</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ticagrelor</intervention_name>
    <description>Single loading dose of 180mg of ticagrelor at time of bivalirudin administration. Beginning 12 hrs following study drug administration, all pts in the ticagrelor arm will receive ticagrelor 90 mg (maintenance dose) approximately every 12 hrs until Follow-up telephone contact.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ticagrelor</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Brilinta</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>clopidogrel</intervention_name>
    <description>Single loading oral dose of 600 mg of clopidogrel will be given at time of bivalirudin administration. Beginning 4 hrs following study drug administration, all pts in the clopidorgrel arm will receive ticagrelor 180mg for the loading dose, followed by 90 mg maintenance dose approximately every 12 hours until the Follow-up telephone contact.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Clopidogrel</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Plavix</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Hospitalised for chest pain and potential acute coronary syndrome.

          -  Onset of the most recent cardiac ischemic symptoms must occur within 7 days before
             randomisation and documented by cardiac ischemic symptoms of ≥ 10 min duration at
             rest and at least 2 of the following: ST segment changes on ECG indicative of
             ischemia, or Positive biomarker evdience of myocardial necrosis, or other risk
             factors such as: 60 yrs of age or older, previous myocardial infarction or coronary
             bypass surgery, multi-vessel coronary artery disease,  diabetes mellitus, peripheral
             arterial disease, chronic renal disfunction.

          -  Females must be either surgically sterile or post-menopausal.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participation in another clinical study with an investigational product during the
             last 30 days.

          -  Current acute complication of percutaneous coronary intervention or coronary bypass
             surgery.

          -  Any contraindication to ticagrelor, clopidogrel or bivalirudin.

          -  ST elevation myocardial infraction within 24 hours of study entry.

          -  Any indications for oral anticoagulation or aspirin dose other than 75 to 100 mg
             daily.

          -  Planned use of omeprazole or esomeprazole.

          -  Patients with known bleeding or coagulation disorders; patients requiring dialysis;
             patients who have an inability to swallow medication.

          -  Patients with known bleeding diathesis or coagulation disorder; history of
             intracranial bleed.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marc Cohen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Newark Beth Israel Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Daniel G. Dadourian, MD</last_name>
    <phone>302-885-5048</phone>
    <email>ClinicalTrialTransparency@astrazeneca.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Cynthia Ewel, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>240-271-1666</phone>
    <email>cynthia.ewel@ubc.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 31, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 14, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Percutaneous Coronary Intervention</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Acute Coronary Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Clopidogrel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ticlopidine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ticagrelor</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bivalirudin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
