<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="95981">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02152956</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CP-MGD006-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02152956</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety Study of MGD006 in Relapsed/Refractory AML</brief_title>
  <acronym>MGD006-01</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, First in Human, Dose Escalation Study of MGD006, a CD123 x CD3 Dual Affinity Re-Targeting (DART) Bi-Specific Antibody Based Molecule, in Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Acute Myeloid Leukemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>MacroGenics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>MacroGenics</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary goal of this Phase 1, dose-escalation study, is to determine the maximum
      tolerated dose level of MGD006 in patients with AML whose disease is not expected to benefit
      from cytotoxic chemotherapy. Studies will also be done to see how the drug acts in the body
      (pharmacokinetics, pharmacodynamics)  and to evaluate potential anti-tumor activity of
      MGD006.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Open-label, multi-dose, single-arm, multi-center, Phase 1, dose-escalation study to define a
      MTDS, describe preliminarily safety, and to assess PK, immunogenicity, immunomodulatory
      activity, and potential anti-tumor activity of MGD006 in patients with AML whose disease is
      not expected to benefit from cytotoxic chemotherapy.

      This study is designed in three segments: the Single Patient Dose Escalation Segment,
      followed by the Multi-Patient Dose Escalation Segment and the MTDS Expansion Cohort Segment.
      Transition to the Multi-Patient Dose Escalation Segment of the study will be based on review
      of the aggregate safety data on all patients participating in Cohort 0.

      The Multi-Patient Dose Escalation Segment will employ a classical 3+3 scheme to examine a
      series of increasing one-step dose escalations in sequential cohorts of patients.

      Once the MTDS is established, the cohort of patients treated at that dose/schedule will be
      expanded with the addition of 12 patients to increase the safety experience and more fully
      evaluate the PK and pharmacodynamics of MGD006.

      In all segments of the study, patients who benefit from MGD006 treatment, and continue to
      meet eligibility, may continue treatment in Cycles 2 and beyond.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Characterize dose limiting toxicity and to establish a Maximum Tolerated Dose and Schedule (MTDS).</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1 of a 28 day cycle.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety is based on evaluation of adverse events (AEs) and serious adverse events (SAEs) from the time of study drug administration through the End of Study Visit.  Safety review for the purposes of dose escalation and/or study segment transition will be based on AEs collected during the first cycle of treatment.
Maximum Tolerated Dose/Schedule: the MTDS will be defined as the highest dose/schedule administered during any Cohort in the study at which the incidence of DLT is &lt; 33% during the first cycle of MGD006 treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Describe the safety profile of MGD006</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1 through end of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluation of DLTs, treatment emergent adverse events (TEAEs), and the aggregate safety data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Characterize the PK and immunogenicity of MGD006</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1 through end of treatment (28 day cycles)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Serum concentrations of MGD006 will be monitored. Population PK modeling will be performed and an appropriate model will be selected to describe the data.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Describe any evidence of anti-leukemic activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Obtain bone marrow aspirate and/or biopsy specimen for local histopathological and immunohistochemical analysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">58</enrollment>
  <condition>AML</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MGD006</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MGD006, a CD123 x CD3 Dual Affinity Re-Targeting (DART) bi-specific antibody</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MGD006</intervention_name>
    <description>MGD006 is a CD123 x CD3 bi-specific antibody-based molecular construct referred to as a dual affinity re-targeting (DART) molecule. MGD006 will be administered as a single agent.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MGD006</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  confirmed diagnosis of primary or secondary AML [any subtype except acute
             promyelocytic leukemia (APL)] according to World Health Organization (WHO)
             classification.

          -  Patients must be unlikely to benefit from cytotoxic chemotherapy defined by any one
             of the following criteria:

               -  newly diagnosed leukemia refractory to ≥ 2 induction attempts,

               -  leukemia in 1st relapse with initial CR duration &lt; 6 months,

               -  leukemia in 1st relapse following ≥ 1 unsuccessful salvage attempts, or

               -  leukemia in 2nd or higher relapse.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status &lt;/= 1

          -  Life expectancy of at least 4 weeks

          -  Peripheral blast count &lt;/= 20,000/mm3 at the time of initiation of infusion on Cycle
             1 Day 1

          -  Acceptable laboratory parameters and adequate organ reserve

          -  Adult (≥ 18 years old)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior history of allogeneic stem cell transplantation

          -  Prior treatment with an anti-CD123-directed agent

          -  Need for concurrent other cytoreductive chemotherapy

          -  Any prior history of or suspected current autoimmune disorders (with the exception of
             vitiligo, resolved childhood atopic dermatitis, prior Grave's disease now euthyroid
             clinically and by laboratory testing)

          -  Second primary malignancy that has not been in remission for greater than 3 years.
             Treated non-melanoma skin cancer, cervical carcinoma in situ on biopsy, or squamous
             intraepithelial lesion on PAP smear, or resected melanoma in situ are exceptions and
             do not require a 3-year remission

          -  Previous treatment with radiotherapy or immunotherapeutic agents in the 4 weeks prior
             to study drug administration (Cycle 1 Day 1)

          -  Previous treatment with any other investigational agent in the 4 weeks prior to study
             drug administration (Cycle 1 Day 1)

          -  Requirement, at the time of study entry, for concurrent steroids &gt; 10 mg/day of oral
             prednisone or the equivalent, except steroid inhaler, nasal spray or ophthalmic
             solution

          -  Use of immunosuppressant medications in the 4 weeks prior to study drug
             administration (Cycle 1 Day 1)

          -  Use of granulocyte colony stimulating or granulocyte-macrophage colony stimulating
             factor in the 4 weeks prior to study drug administration (Cycle 1 Day 1)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John DiPersio, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stanford Stewart, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>MacroGenics</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lori Richards</last_name>
    <phone>650-624-2609</phone>
    <email>richardsl@macrogenics.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kathryn Maus</last_name>
      <phone>314-747-1849</phone>
      <email>kmaus@DOM.wustl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Geoff Uy, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 28, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 28, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>AML</keyword>
  <keyword>leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>myelogenous</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Bispecific</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
