<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="85646">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01873950</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-011D</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>SCR-002</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01873950</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of the Electrocardiographic Effects of Ranolazine, Dofetilide, Verapamil, and Quinidine in Healthy Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double-Blind, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Single-Dose, Five Period Crossover Study of the Electrocardiographic Effects of Ranolazine, Dofetilide, Verapamil, and Quinidine in Healthy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Food and Drug Administration (FDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Spaulding Clinical Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Food and Drug Administration (FDA)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study seeks to compare 4 known QT prolonging drugs versus placebo to determine their
      effects on electrophysiological and other clinical parameters. The underlying purpose is to
      determine if depolarization and repolarization effects caused by drugs with differing ionic
      channel mechanisms can be distinguished from one another, and to gauge the sensitivity and
      specificity of novel signal analyses for detection of depolarization and repolarization
      changes. Secondarily,  to evaluate the exposure response relationship and drug induced
      effects on the heart rate biomarker relationship.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This will be a randomized, double blind, 5 way crossover research study in healthy male and
      female subjects, 18 to 35 years of age, to compare 4 known QT prolonging drugs versus
      placebo to determine their effects on electrophysiological and other clinical parameters. To
      maintain the study blind, subjects will be blindfolded during study drug administration. The
      cardiologists at the central ECG laboratory (Spaulding Clinical Research, LLC) will be
      blinded to treatment, time, and study day/subject identifiers.

      Subjects who meet all of the following inclusion criteria will be eligible to participate in
      the study:

        1. Subject signs an Institutional Review Board (IRB) approved written informed consent and
           privacy language as per national regulations (e.g., Health Insurance Portability and
           Accountability Act [HIPAA] authorization for sites in the United States) before any
           study related procedures are performed.

        2. Subject is a healthy man or woman, 18 to 35 years of age, inclusive, who weighs at
           least 50 kg (110 pounds) and has a body mass index of 18 to 27 kg/m2, inclusive, at
           Screening.

        3. Subject has normal medical history findings, clinical laboratory results, vital sign
           measurements, 12 lead ECG results, and physical examination findings at Screening or,
           if abnormal, the abnormality is not considered clinically significant (as determined
           and documented by the investigator or designee).

        4. Female subjects must be at least 2 years postmenopausal, surgically sterile or
           practicing 2 highly effective methods of birth control (as determined by the
           investigator or designee; one of the methods must be a barrier technique), and not
           pregnant or lactating before enrollment in the study.

        5. Male or female subjects must agree to practice 2 highly effective methods of birth
           control (as determined by the investigator or designee; one of the methods must be a
           barrier technique) from Screening until 30 days after the last dose of study drug.

        6. Subject is highly likely (as determined by the investigator) to comply with the
           protocol-defined procedures and to complete the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Placebo, and baseline-adjusted changes in PR, QRS, J-Tpeak, Tpeak-Tend, QTc, spatial QRS-T angle and ventricular gradient</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Compute maximum mean placebo, and baseline-adjusted change for: PR (ms), QRS (ms), J-Tpeak (ms), Tpeak-Tend (ms), QTc (ms), spatial QRS-T angle (degrees) and ventricular gradient (mVms).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in relationship between heart rate and PR, QRS, J-Tpeak, Tpeak-Tend, QTc, spatial QRS-T angle and ventricular gradient</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Different post-dose timepoints employ different techniques for altering heart rate (leg raises and postural maneuvers). Using this data a model for different ECG parameters (same as for primary analysis) and heart rate will be developed. The model will either be a linear or non-linear model (as determined by visual inspection), but the model will be the same for all subjects and maneuvers. The model coefficients for different maneuvers and drugs will be compared.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in PR, QRS, J-Tpeak, Tpeak-Tend, QTc, spatial QRS-T angle and ventricular gradient using Exposure/Response</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The exposure response analysis will be performed for each treatment and will use a linear or nonlinear model (as determined by visual inspection) to quantify the relationship between exposure and Baseline and placebo adjusted change from Baseline for each ECG parameter (same as for primary analysis).
The magnitude of change (mean and 90% CI) in QTc for the observed mean Cmax for each drug, highest individual concentration observed with the dose, and other appropriate concentrations pertaining to drug may be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">27</enrollment>
  <condition>Drug-induced Surface ECG Changes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ranolazine 1500mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ranolazine</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dofetilide 500mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dofetilide</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Verapamil HCl 120 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Verapamil</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Quinidine sulfate 400mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Quinidine sulfate</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ranolazine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Ranolazine 1500mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dofetilide</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Dofetilide 500mcg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Verapamil</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Verapamil HCl 120 mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quinidine sulfate</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Quinidine sulfate 400mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria: Subjects who meet all of the following inclusion criteria will be
        eligible to participate in the study:

          1. Subject signs an IRB approved written informed consent and privacy language as per
             national regulations (e.g., Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act
             [HIPAA] authorization for sites in the United States) before any study related
             procedures are performed.

          2. Subject is a healthy man or woman, 18 to 35 years of age, inclusive, who weighs at
             least 50 kg (110 pounds) and has a body mass index of 18 to 27 kg/m2, inclusive, at
             Screening.

          3. Subject has normal medical history findings, clinical laboratory results, vital sign
             measurements, 12 lead electrocardiogram (ECG) results, and physical examination
             findings at Screening or, if abnormal, the abnormality is not considered clinically
             significant (as determined and documented by the investigator or designee).

          4. Female subjects must be at least 2 years postmenopausal, surgically sterile or
             practicing 2 highly effective methods of birth control (as determined by the
             investigator or designee; one of the methods must be a barrier technique), and not
             pregnant or lactating before enrollment in the study.

          5. Male or female subjects must agree to practice 2 highly effective methods of birth
             control (as determined by the investigator or designee; one of the methods must be a
             barrier technique) from Screening until 30 days after the last dose of study drug.

          6. Subject is highly likely (as determined by the investigator) to comply with the
             protocol defined procedures and to complete the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who meet any of the following exclusion criteria will not be eligible to
             participate in the study:

               1. Subject has a 12 lead safety ECG result at Screening or Check in of Period 1
                  with evidence of any of the following abnormalities:

                    -  QTc using Fridericia correction (QTcF) &gt;450 milliseconds (ms) for men and
                       &gt;470 ms for women

                    -  PR interval &gt;220 ms

                    -  QRS duration &gt;110 ms

                    -  Second- or third-degree atrioventricular block

                    -  Complete left or right bundle branch block or incomplete right bundle
                       branch block

                    -  Heart rate &lt;40 or &gt;90 beats per minute

                    -  Pathological Q-waves (defined as Q wave &gt;40 ms)

                    -  Ventricular pre-excitation

               2. Subject has more than 12 to 20 ectopic beats during the 3 hour Holter ECG at
                  Screening.

               3. Subject has a history of unexplained syncope, structural heart disease, long QT
                  syndrome, heart failure, myocardial infarction, angina, unexplained cardiac
                  arrhythmia, torsades de pointes, ventricular tachycardia, or placement of a
                  pacemaker or implantable defibrillator. Subjects will also be excluded if there
                  is a family history of long QT syndrome (genetically proven or suggested by
                  sudden death of a close relative due to cardiac causes at a young age) or
                  Brugada syndrome.

               4. Subject has a history or current evidence of any clinically significant (as
                  determined by the investigator) cardiovascular, dermatologic, endocrine,
                  gastrointestinal, hematologic, hepatic, immunologic, metabolic, neurologic,
                  psychiatric, pulmonary, renal, urologic, and/or other major disease or
                  malignancy (excluding nonmelanoma skin cancer). The investigator may allow
                  exceptions to these criteria (e.g., stable mild joint disease [that will not
                  interfere with or influence the leg raises/exercises required by the protocol,
                  in the opinion of the investigator], cholecystectomy, childhood asthma)
                  following discussion with the medical monitor.

               5. Subject has a history of thoracic surgery.

               6. Subject has any condition possibly affecting study drug absorption (e.g.,
                  gastrectomy, Crohn's disease, irritable bowel syndrome).

               7. Subject has a skin condition likely to compromise ECG electrode placement.

               8. Subject is a female with breast implants.

               9. Subject's laboratory test results at Screening or Check in of Period 1 are
                  outside the reference ranges provided by the clinical laboratory and considered
                  clinically significant (as determined and documented by the investigator or
                  designee).

              10. Subject's laboratory test results at Screening or Check in of Period 1 indicate
                  hypokalemia, hypocalcemia, or hypomagnesemia according to lower limits of the
                  reference ranges provided by the clinical laboratory.

              11. Subject's laboratory test results at Screening or Check in of Period 1 are &gt;2 ×
                  the upper limit of normal (ULN) for alanine aminotransferase or aspartate
                  aminotransferase, &gt;1.5 × ULN for bilirubin, or &gt;1.5 × ULN for creatinine.

              12. Subject has a positive test result at Screening for human immunodeficiency virus
                  antibody, hepatitis C antibodies, or hepatitis B surface antigen.

              13. Subject has a mean systolic blood pressure &lt;90 or &gt;140 mmHg or a mean diastolic
                  blood pressure &lt;50 or &gt;90 mmHg at either Screening or Check in of Period 1.
                  Blood pressure will be measured in triplicate after the subject has been resting
                  in a supine position for a minimum of 5 minutes.

              14. Subject has a known hypersensitivity to ranolazine, dofetilide, verapamil, or
                  quinidine or related compounds.

              15. Subject has consumed alcohol, xanthine containing products (e.g., tea, coffee,
                  chocolate, cola), caffeine, grapefruit, or grapefruit juice within 48 hours
                  before dosing or anticipates an inability to abstain from these products
                  throughout the duration of the study.

              16. Subject has used nicotine containing products (e.g., cigarettes, cigars, chewing
                  tobacco, snuff) within 6 weeks before Screening (self reported).

              17. Subject is unable to tolerate a controlled, quiet study conduct environment,
                  including avoidance of music, television, movies, games, and activities that may
                  cause excitement, emotional tension, or arousal during the prespecified time
                  points (e.g., before and during ECG extraction windows).

              18. Subject is unwilling to comply with study rules, including the study specific
                  diet, attempting to void at specified times (e.g., before ECG extraction
                  windows), remaining quiet, awake, undistracted, motionless, and supine during
                  specified times, and avoiding vigorous exercise as directed.

              19. Subject has a history of consuming more than 14 units of alcoholic beverages per
                  week within 6 months before Screening, has a history of alcoholism or
                  drug/chemical/substance abuse within 2 years before Screening (Note: 1 unit = 12
                  ounces of beer, 4 ounces of wine or 1 ounce of spirits/hard liquor), or has a
                  positive test result for alcohol or drugs of abuse (amphetamines, barbiturates,
                  benzodiazepines, cannabinoids, cocaine, and opiates) at Screening or Check in of
                  each period.

              20. Subject has used any prescription or nonprescription drugs within 14 days or 5
                  half lives (whichever is longer), or complementary and alternative medicines
                  within 28 days before the first dose of study drug (excluding oral
                  contraceptives, hormone replacement therapy, aspirin, ibuprofen, and
                  acetaminophen).

              21. Subject is currently participating in another clinical study of an
                  investigational drug or has been treated with any investigational drug within 30
                  days or 5 half lives (whichever is longer) of the compound.

              22. Subject has had any significant blood loss, donated 1 unit (450 mL) of blood or
                  more, or received a transfusion of any blood or blood products within 60 days,
                  or donated plasma within 7 days before Check in of Period 1.

              23. Subject has any other condition that precludes his or her participation in the
                  study (as determined by the investigator).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carlos Sanabria, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Spaulding Clinical Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 5, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 22, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Verapamil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dofetilide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Quinidine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Quinidine gluconate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ranolazine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
