<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="104127">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01817361</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R21DE017360-01A2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01817361</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Oral Health and People With Systemic Sclerosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Oral Health and People With Systemic Sclerosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alabama at Birmingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alabama at Birmingham</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The public health impact of this study will be the application of the greater understanding
      of the oral health status, oral health related behaviors, and quality of life of patients
      with systemic sclerosis (scleroderma or SSc). It is hoped that risks and protective factors
      can be identified to be associated with the oral health status of adults with systemic
      sclerosis,leading to the development of interventions for improved oral health in this
      population,and providing the basis for a larger study of oral health problems of adults with
      systemic sclerosis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The broad, long-term objective of our proposed research is to understand the oral health
      status, oral health-related behaviors, and quality of life in the US population of patients
      with systemic sclerosis (scleroderma or SSc). SSc is a rare, progressive connective tissue
      disease that affects predominately women (3.8:1) with a higher risk of the severe form among
      African-Americans. SSc adults experience manifestations of the systemic disease that include
      microstomia, xerostomia, and impaired manual dexterity. The two specific aims of this study
      are: 1) to characterize the oral health status of adults with SSc, and 2) to determine the
      SSc disease specific manifestations (microstomia, xerostomia, and manual dexterity
      impairments) that are associated with the severity of oral health problems and oral
      health-related quality of life among adults with SSc. This first study of US adults with SSc
      is a cross-sectional survey of 250 adults with SSc in South Carolina. This population is 25%
      African-American which is similar to the racial distribution of SSc in the US adult
      population. Data collection includes information on: oral health status (periodontal,
      dental, mucosal and microbial), oral manifestations of SSc (size of oral aperture, severity
      of oral dryness, and manual dexterity for oral hygiene), and oral health-related behaviors
      and quality of life. The oral health status of the South Carolina SSc population will be
      compared to that of the adult US population based on an analysis of corresponding measures
      using the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey 1999-2002 data. Multivariable
      regression modeling will be used to evaluate hypothesized risk and protective factors that
      are associated with oral health status in adults with SSc. Results of this study in South
      Carolina will be used in regional efforts for the development of interventions for improved
      oral health status of adults with SSc. Second, these results will provide the basis for a
      larger US study of oral health problems of adults with SSc.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case-Only, Time Perspective: Cross-Sectional</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>oral health status</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">210</enrollment>
  <condition>Systemic Sclerosis</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        adults with systemic sclerosis
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of SSc according to American College of Rheumatology criteria, and
             participants are 18 years of age or older at the time of invitation to the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  participants who require antibiotic medication before dental treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hon K Yuen, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical University of South Carolina</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29425</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 22, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>oral health</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Scleroderma, Systemic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Scleroderma, Diffuse</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
