<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="136321">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02105480</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MurmurDetect-AAAPN</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02105480</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Automated Algorithm Based Analysis of Phonocardiograms of Newborns</brief_title>
  <official_title>Automated Algorithm Based Analysis of Phonocardiograms of Newborns</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Murmur Detect</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Murmur Detect</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Austria: Austrian Agency for Health and Food Safety (AGES)</authority>
    <authority>Austria: Koordinierungszentrum für Klinische Studien der Med Uni Graz</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this double-blind pivotal clinical utility study is to determine on a large
      patient population whether heart murmurs can be reliably detected with high sensitivity and
      specificity using automated algorithm-based phonocardiogram analysis (also referred to as
      computer aided auscultation (CAA)).

      Each patient is auscultated and diagnosed independently by a medical specialist.
      Additionally, for each patient, an echocardiogram is performed as the gold-standard for
      determining heart pathologies. The CAA results are compared to the findings of the medical
      professionals as well as to the echocardiogram findings.

      Hypothesis: The specific CAA algorithms used in this study are able to automatically
      diagnose pathological heart murmurs in premature babies and newborns with at least the same
      accuracy as experienced medical specialists.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The following registry procedures and quality factors have been implemented:

        -  Quality assurance plan, including

             -  data validation

             -  proper registration procedures

             -  regular site monitoring

             -  regular auditing

        -  Data checks to compare data entered into the registry against predefined rules for
           range or consistency with other data fields in the registry.

        -  Source data verification to assess the accuracy, completeness, or representativeness of
           registry data by comparing the data to external data sources (medical records and paper
           case report forms).

        -  Standard Operating Procedures to address registry operations and analysis activities,
           such as patient recruitment, data collection, data management, data analysis, reporting
           for adverse events, and change management.

        -  Sample size assessment to specify the number of participants or participant years
           necessary to demonstrate an effect.

        -  Statistical analysis plan describing the analytical principles and statistical
           techniques to be employed in order to address the primary and secondary objectives, as
           specified in the study protocol or plan.

        -  Plan for missing data to address situations where variables are reported as missing,
           unavailable, &quot;non-reported,&quot; uninterpretable, or considered missing because of data
           inconsistency or out-of-range results.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Cross-Sectional</study_design>
  <target_duration>1 Day</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of correctly diagnosed heart murmurs through independent algorithm based auscultation and traditional stethoscope based auscultation by medical experts</measure>
    <time_frame>1.5 years (expected)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Each patient is screened and diagnosed regarding a potential heart murmur by a medical expert through standard stethoscope based auscultation. Heart sounds are recorded using an electronic stethoscope and analyzed and diagnosed independently (with no external input) by an algorithm. A final diagnoses for each patient is made by a medical expert by performing an echocardiogram, the gold standard method for heart murmur detection. The diagnoses of both the medical expert and the algorithm are finally compared to the echocardiogram based diagnosis (after completion of patient recruitment).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">220</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Murmurs</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Premature babies and newborns stationed at the department of neonatology
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  any premature baby or newborn

          -  parental approval for study participation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  none
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>5 Days</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gerhard Pichler, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical University of Graz</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gerhard Pichler, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+43 316 385</phone>
    <phone_ext>80520</phone_ext>
    <email>gerhard.pichler@medunigraz.at</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Graz</city>
        <state>Styria</state>
        <zip>8010</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 31, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Murmurs</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
