<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="132876">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01998178</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HPV IISP 38406</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01998178</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immune Response and Safety Study of Human Papillomavirus (HPV) Vaccine in HIV-infected Pre-adolescent in Kenya</brief_title>
  <official_title>Immunogenicity and Safety of Quadrivalent Human Papillomavirus Vaccine in HIV-infected Pre-adolescent Girls and Boys in Kenya</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kenyatta National Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kenyatta National Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Kenya: Pharmacy and Poisons Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine if the quadrivalent HPV vaccine 'Gardasil' is
      effective in eliciting a protective immune response among HIV-1 infected adolescents girls
      and boys age 9-14 years comparable to historical cohorts of HIV-1 uninfected women. The
      study will also determine if this response, differs by the degree of immunosuppression.

      The study will also determine the safety and tolerability of the 'Gardasil' vaccine among
      HIV-1 infected boys and girls age 9-14.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Human Papillomavirus (HPV) is a common sexually transmitted infection, with more than 50% of
      young women infected within  few years of initiatiing sexual activity. Persistent infection
      with high risk HPV types is known to cause cervical cancer among other tumors and genital
      warts. Cervical cancer and its precancerous lesions, genital warts are more common among
      HIV-1 infected individuals, among whom, cancer occurs at an earlier age and progresses more
      quickly.

      The HPV 'Gardasil'vaccine has been tested widely among HIV-1 negative persons demonstrating
      high efficacy and safety profiles, it is widely registered for use across continents.
      However, there is minimal data in HIV-1 infected persons.

      For many immunizations, HIV-1 infected persons experience lower immune responses compared to
      HIV-uninfected persons.

      The investigators therefore propose to conduct a prospective study of the quadrivalent HPV
      'Gardasil' vaccine among pre adolescent HIV infected girls and boys age 9-14 years in Kenya
      to extend current understanding f safety and immunogenicity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Antibody titre to HPV virus like particles as determined by the quadrivalent HPV competitive Luminex immunoassay (cLIA)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The purpose of the cLIA is to detect antibody to HPV virus like particles before and after vaccination and is specific to HPV types.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To correlate the immune response, as measured by antibody titers, with the degree of immunosuppression.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Most of the HIV-Infected boys and girls will be on HAART and thus have achieved partial immune reconstitution. However, nadir pre-HAART CD4 and WHO HIV disease stage as indicators of past immunosuppression, enrollment plasma HIV levels as an indicator of viral control on HAART, and enrollment CD4 compared to nadir CD4 as an indicator of immune reconstitution, may correlate with HPV vaccine immune response as measured by HPV antibody titers at months 7 and 12 post vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the safety and tolerability of the quadrivalent HPV vaccine (Gardasil) in boys and girls age 9-14 years in Kenya.</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The vaccine report card will be utilized to record immediate post vaccine events for a period of 14 days after each vaccine dose.
Adverse events reports will be gathered through out the study period and categorized as Severe adverse Events (SAEs) and Adverse Events (SAEs).
All SAEs will be reported to the regulatory authorities within a stipulated time limit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Genital Warts</condition>
  <condition>Cervical Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gardasil, Quadrivalent HPV Vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Injection of 0.5mls HPV Gardasil Quadrivalent Vaccine administered at enrollment, month 2 and month 6.
Gardasil, is a Quadrivalent HPV Vaccine which has been tested to have high efficacy against HPV 6,11,16 and 18.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quadrivalent HPV Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Intramuscular injections of 0.5 mls 'Gardasil' at enrollment, month 2 and month 6 visits the study has one study arm and the comparative data will be from historical cohorts</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gardasil, Quadrivalent HPV Vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Gardasil</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. laboratory confirmed HIV-1 infection,

          2. age range 9-14 years, and

          3. parental or guardian consent and participant assent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. are severely ill, as defined by Karnofsky score &lt;70,

          2. have a diagnosis of malignancy,

          3. on-going febrile illness (temperature ≥37.8°C), including active treatment for an
             opportunistic infection,

          4. have received systemic corticosteroids within prior one year,

          5. have received inactivated vaccine within prior 2 weeks, or live attenuated vaccine
             within prior 6 weeks,

          6. have history of allergy to any products included in the HPV vaccine,

          7. have received any of blood derivatives within prior 6 months,

          8. are pregnant

          9. lack parental consent and/or child declines to provide assent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>9 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>14 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nelly R. Mugo, MbCHB, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kenyatta National Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Partners in Prevention</name>
      <address>
        <city>Thika</city>
        <state>Kiambu</state>
        <country>Kenya</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Kenya</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 25, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 9, 2011</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Kenyatta National Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nelly R. Mugo</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HPV</keyword>
  <keyword>Cervical Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV-1</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Uterine Cervical Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Condylomata Acuminata</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
