<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="43660">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02059525</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SeTPAT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02059525</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treponema Pallidum-specific Proteomic Changes in Patients With Incident Syphilis Infection</brief_title>
  <acronym>SeTPAT</acronym>
  <official_title>Treponema Pallidum-specific Proteomic Changes in Patients With Incident Syphilis Infection: an Observational Study in Belgium</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institute of Tropical Medicine, Belgium</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital, Antwerp</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institute of Tropical Medicine, Belgium</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Belgium: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This  study is part of the Search for a Treponema pallidum Antigen Test (SeTPAT) project to
      study the proteomic, immunological, serological and clinical changes associated with pre-
      and post-treatment syphilis infection in a way that could ultimately lead to the development
      of a new ELISA and rapid diagnostic test of T. pallidum antigenaemia.

      The general aim of this prospecive observational cohort study is thus to quantify a set of
      target proteins with the highest diagnostic potential for the diagnosis of initial T.
      pallidum infection and T. pallidum persistence. A test which could directly detect the
      presence of T. pallidum antigens could represent a considerable advance over currently used
      tests in the diagnosis of initial syphilis infection, its response to therapy and in the
      diagnosis of syphilis reinfections. This prospective observational cohort study of
      HIV-positive patients with a new diagnosis of syphilis infection will be conducted at the
      HIV/Sexually Transmitted Infections (STI) Clinic at the Institute of Tropical Medicine,
      Antwerp.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This cohort study is part of the Search for a Treponema pallidum Antigen Test (SeTPAT)
      project to study the proteomic, immunological, serological and clinical changes associated
      with pre- and post-treatment syphilis infection in a way that will ultimately lead to the
      development of a new ELISA and rapid diagnostic test of T. pallidum antigenaemia. The
      general aim of this observational cohort study is thus to quantify a set of target proteins
      with the highest diagnostic potential for the diagnosis of initial T. pallidum infection and
      T. pallidum persistence. A test which could directly detect the presence of T. pallidum
      antigens could represent a considerable advance over currently used tests in the diagnosis
      of initial syphilis infection, its response to therapy and in the diagnosis of syphilis
      reinfections.

      This prospective observational cohort study of HIV-positive patients with a new diagnosis of
      syphilis infection will be conducted at the HIV/Sexually Transmitted Infections (STI) Clinic
      at the Institute of Tropical Medicine, Antwerp (ITM). 120 patients with a new diagnosis of
      syphilis infection who receive treatment for their syphilis at the ITM and give informed
      consent, will be recruited; based on the current rate of syphilis diagnosis this should take
      approximately 18 months. Participants will receive a detailed, standardized clinical
      assessment, fill out a brief behavioural questionnaire and then be treated with therapy for
      syphilis according to their stage of disease. In addition to the routine tests performed, if
      and after they consent to participate in this study, they will have their serum analyzed for
      a number of other immunological markers. A control group will be recruited, consisting of 30
      convenience selected patients who are HIV infected but have no evidence of syphilis (Rapid
      Plasma Reagin, T. pallidum antigenaemia , or clinical evidence that could be suggestive of
      syphilis infection) are attending the HIV clinic regularly, who were seen in the same month
      as one of the acute syphilis cases and who consent to take part in the study. The control
      group will only undergo the investigations planned for the baseline visit.

      Noteworthy, it is hoped that the results of the study will also allow to develop and
      evaluate the utility of a composite diagnostic rule for the diagnosis of syphilis
      reinfection.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case Control, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>T. Pallidum-specific antigens</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Presence/absence and concentration of the T. pallidum-specific antigens</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>T. pallidum persistence</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months pre-penicillin retreatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>T. pallidum-specific antigens</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>T. pallidum antigens variation</measure>
    <time_frame>Any point of suspected treatment failure/reinfection till 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in T. pallidum-specific antigens, Rapid Plasma Reagin (RPR), T. pallidum antigenaemia (TPA) and Syphilis- immunoglobulin M (IgM)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Accuracy of screening for Chlamydia trachomatis (CT) and Neisseria gonorrhoea (NG)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>CT-positives NG-positives</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Syphilis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>syphilis infected</arm_group_label>
    <description>all patients with a new diagnosis of syphilis, receiving treatment at the Institute of Tropical Medicine</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      serum, plasma, peripheral blood mononucleated cell (PBMC) and urine
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with a new diagnosis of syphilis infection who receive treatment for their
        syphilis at the Institute of Tropical Medicine (ITM), and a control group , consisting of
        patients who are HIV infected but have no evidence of syphilis
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Willingness to provide written consent

          -  Prepared to follow the study schedule

          -  EITHER a diagnosis of a new episode of syphilis - initial or repeat syphilis
             (Patients group), OR no evidence of past or present syphilis, defined as no clinical
             or serological evidence of syphilis (Control group).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Use of doxycycline, a macrolide antibiotic or a Beta-lactam antibiotic in the
             preceding 28 days

          -  Not willing to give informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chris Kenyon, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institute of Tropical Medicine, Belgium</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Chris Kenyon, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+3232470786</phone>
    <email>ckenyon@itg.be</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kara Osbak, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+3233455790</phone>
    <email>kosbak@itg.be</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute of Tropical Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Antwerp</city>
        <zip>2000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kara Osbak, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+323455790</phone>
      <email>kosbak@itg.be</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Chris Kenyon, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+3232470786</phone>
      <email>ckenyon@itg.be</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chris Kenyon, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kara Osbak, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 6, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>observational</keyword>
  <keyword>Belgium</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Syphilis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
