<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="40055">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01729923</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>7707</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-02137</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>7707</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA015704</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01729923</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Capecitabine and Celecoxib With or Without Radiation Therapy in Treating Patients With Colorectal Cancer Previously Treated With Fluorouracil</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Trial of Maintenance ADAPT Therapy With Capecitabine and Celecoxib in Patients With Metastatic Colorectal Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Washington</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well capecitabine and celecoxib with or without radiation
      therapy works in treating patients with metastatic colorectal cancer previously treated with
      fluorouracil. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as capecitabine, work in different ways to
      stop the growth of tumor cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from
      dividing. Celecoxib may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking some of the enzymes
      needed for cell growth. Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays to kill tumor cells.
      Giving capecitabine and celecoxib together with radiation therapy may kill more tumor cells.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the rate of complete response 2 years following the initiation of first line
      5-FU (fluorouracil) based chemotherapy in patients with initially unresected metastatic
      colorectal cancer who are then treated on the activating cancer stem cells (CSCs) from
      dormancy and priming them for subsequent targeting (ADAPT) protocol.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine progression free survival (PFS), overall survival (OS), relapse free
      survival (if complete response [CR]) from initiation of first line 5-FU based chemotherapy
      based on intent to treat (ITT) analysis.

      II. To determine the effects of v-Ki-ras2 Kirsten rat sarcoma viral oncogene homolog (K-ras)
      mutation status in response to ADAPT therapy.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients proceed to surgery, radiation therapy with ADAPT therapy followed by maintenance
      ADAPT therapy, or ADAPT therapy. Eligible patients undergo surgical resection at baseline or
      upon achievement of resectable disease after radiation therapy.

      RADIATION + ADAPT: Patients undergo radiation therapy 5 days per week and receive
      capecitabine orally (PO) twice daily (BID) and celecoxib PO BID 5 days per week during
      radiation.

      ADAPT: Patients receive capecitabine PO BID on days 1-14 and celecoxib PO BID on days 1-21.
      Courses repeat every 21 days for up to 3 years in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 3 months for 1 year,
      every 4 months for 2 years, and then every 6 months for 2 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of CR, assessed according to CEA and CA 19-9 measurements and Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relapse free survival in patients achieving CR</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method based on the ITT population starting from the time of induction chemotherapy initiation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PFS as defined by true disease progression (new sites of disease)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method based on the ITT population starting from the time of induction chemotherapy initiation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method based on the ITT population starting from the time of induction chemotherapy initiation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Best overall response rate, defined using RECIST 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The relationship between K-ras mutation, resection, and radiation and response to ADAPT therapy will be evaluated using Chi-squared analysis and Cox regression analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>K-ras mutation status</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The relationship between K-ras mutation, resection, and radiation and response to ADAPT therapy will be evaluated using Chi-squared analysis and Cox regression analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life (QOL), assessed using the M.D. Anderson Symptom Inventory (MDASI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Group differences in QOL will be estimated, with repeated measures used to improve precision of estimates.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events defined as any condition that appears or worsens after the subject is enrolled in an investigational study, graded by numerical score according to the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Toxicity Criteria (CTC) version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after completion of study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The number and percent of subjects reporting adverse events coded as grade 3 or greater will be summarized by treatment group and strata. Listings will be provided for all on-study deaths and adverse events that lead to withdrawal from study. Narratives of all serious adverse events and deaths on-study will be provided.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">43</enrollment>
  <condition>Recurrent Colon Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Rectal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Colon Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Rectal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Colon Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Rectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (capecitabine, celecoxib, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients proceed to surgery, radiation therapy with ADAPT therapy followed by maintenance ADAPT therapy, or ADAPT therapy. Eligible patients undergo surgical resection at baseline or upon achievement of resectable disease after radiation therapy.
RADIATION + ADAPT: Patients undergo radiation therapy 5 days per week and receive capecitabine PO BID and celecoxib PO BID 5 days per week during radiation.
ADAPT: Patients receive capecitabine PO BID on days 1-14 and celecoxib PO BID on days 1-21. Courses repeat every 21 days for up to 3 years in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>capecitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (capecitabine, celecoxib, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CAPE</other_name>
    <other_name>Ro 09-1978/000</other_name>
    <other_name>Xeloda</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>celecoxib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (capecitabine, celecoxib, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Celebrex</other_name>
    <other_name>SC-58635</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo radiation therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (capecitabine, celecoxib, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>irradiation</other_name>
    <other_name>radiotherapy</other_name>
    <other_name>therapy, radiation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>therapeutic conventional surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo surgical resection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (capecitabine, celecoxib, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (capecitabine, celecoxib, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>quality-of-life assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (capecitabine, celecoxib, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>quality of life assessment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>intensity-modulated radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo IMRT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (capecitabine, celecoxib, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IMRT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>stereotactic body radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo SBRT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (capecitabine, celecoxib, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SBRT</other_name>
    <other_name>stereotactic radiation therapy</other_name>
    <other_name>stereotactic radiotherapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed colorectal cancer

          -  Measurable radiographic evidence of colorectal cancer

          -  Patients with unresected metastases from colorectal cancer; patients may be either
             untreated with chemotherapy or currently receiving first-line 5-FU based chemotherapy
             (folinic acid-fluorouracil-irinotecan [FOLFIRI], capecitabine-irinotecan [CAPIRI],
             fluorouracil-leucovorin calcium-oxaliplatin [FOLFOX], or capecitabine-oxaliplatin
             [CAPOX] with or without bevacizumab) within 6 months of study entry date with at
             least stable disease radiographically; patients who received prior adjuvant
             chemotherapy with 5-FU, capecitabine, or FOLFOX are eligible if adjuvant therapy was
             completed greater than 6 months ago

          -  History of histological confirmation for recurrent disease, or if recurrent disease
             is not readily accessible to biopsy, must have two consecutive carcinoembryonic
             antigen (CEA) or cancer antigen (CA) 19-9 increases, or positron emission tomography
             (PET) avidity

          -  Men and women from all ethnic and racial groups

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status =&lt; 1

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x the institutional upper-normal limit (IUNL)

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase [SGOT])
             and/or alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamic pyruvate transaminase [SGPT])
             =&lt; 2.5 x IUNL

          -  Alkaline phosphatase =&lt; 2.5 x IUNL

          -  Leukocytes &gt;= 3,000/uL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1,000/uL

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100,000/uL

          -  Women of childbearing age and all men must agree to use adequate contraception
             (hormonal or barrier method of birth control) prior to study entry and for the
             duration of study participation

          -  Negative urine pregnancy test for women of childbearing age

          -  Must have the ability to understand and the willingness to provide a written informed
             consent to participate in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of allergies to sulfonamide, aspirin, any nonsteroidal anti inflammatory
             drugs (NSAIDS), 5-FU or celecoxib

          -  Prior 5-FU-based adjuvant chemotherapy less than 6 months prior to study entry and
             any residual neuropathy &gt; grade 2

          -  Any regular use of cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2) inhibitors as defined by 2-3 times per
             week

          -  Use of aspirin is NOT an exclusion criteria as long as the daily dose does not exceed
             325 mg daily; initiation of ADAPT therapy requires patient to discontinue aspirin for
             18 months

          -  Pregnant or lactating women

          -  History of significant neurologic or psychiatric disorders, including dementia or
             seizures that would impede consent, treatment, or follow up

          -  Any serious illness or medical condition that could affect participation on trial

          -  Any uncontrolled congestive heart failure New York Heart Association class III or IV

          -  Any uncontrolled hypertension, arrhythmia, or active angina pectoris

          -  Any history of major myocardial infarction, stroke or transient ischemic attack
             (TIA); minor acute myocardial infarction (AMI) and patients who have had cardiac
             bypass free of symptoms for at least 2 years may be eligible at the discretion of the
             study chair

          -  Serious uncontrolled active infection

          -  Patients with creatinine clearance: &lt; 50 mL/min are excluded from this protocol;
             capecitabine is contraindicated in severe renal impairment (clearance &lt; 40 mL/min)

          -  Inability to swallow oral medications or any medical conditions that may affect
             intestinal absorption of the study agent or inability to comply with oral medication

          -  History of active peptic ulcer disease or major upper gastrointestinal (GI) bleed &lt;
             12 months; history of GI bleeding from the colorectal cancer primary is not an
             exclusion criteria

          -  Use of warfarin is not allowed; patient is recommended to switch to low molecular
             weight heparin (LMWH) before participating in this study

          -  Patients with any history of brain or bone metastasis or who have develop progressive
             disease on first line 5-FU based therapy

          -  Current use of steroid medication

          -  Patients with an obstructive synchronous colorectal tumor requiring up-front surgery
             or chemoradiation

          -  Patients with partial or complete bowel obstruction due to abdominal carcinomatosis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Edward Lin</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Edward H. Lin</last_name>
      <phone>206-288-6678</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Edward H. Lin</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 15, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Colonic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Celecoxib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Capecitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluorouracil</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
