<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="159786">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01934894</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SCRI BRE 200</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01934894</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cabazitaxel Plus Lapatinib as Therapy for HER2-Positive Metastatic Breast Cancer Patients With Intracranial Metastases</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study With Lead-in Safety Cohort of Cabazitaxel Plus Lapatinib as Therapy for HER2-Positive Metastatic Breast Cancer Patients With Intracranial Metastases</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>SCRI Development Innovations, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sanofi</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>SCRI Development Innovations, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial will combine two agents, cabazitaxel and lapatinib, to treat patients
      with metastatic breast cancer (MBC) which has metastasized to the brain.  The first portion
      of the study will determine the optimal dose of the cabazitaxel/lapatinib combination to
      administer to patients.  After determining the optimal dose, patients will continue
      treatment with cabazitaxel and lapatinib to assess response to treatment with these agents.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-label, non-randomized, Phase II study with a lead-in safety cohort.
      Through the safety lead-in portion of this trial we will define the optimal dose of
      cabazitaxel when given in combination with lapatinib for patients with HER2-positive MBC and
      CNS metastases.  The Phase II portion will further assess intracranial response rate in
      patients with HER2-positive MBC and CNS metastases.  Toxicity and progression free survival
      (PFS)  will be obtained and evaluated.  The trial will be conducted at multiple study sites
      by SCRI Development Innovations.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Central Nervous System (CNS) response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Determine the CNS response rate of the combination of cabazitaxel and lapatinib when administered as treatment for CNS metastases in HER2-positive MBC patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with grade 3/4 adverse events as a measure of safety.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluate the safety of cabazitaxel and lapatinib when administered as treatment for CNS metastases in HER2-positive MBC patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical benefit rate (CNS metastases)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluate the clinical benefit rate of the combination in the treatment of CNS metastases (CR+PR +SD &gt;= 6 months).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CNS progression free survival rate</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluate the 3- and 6- month CNS progression free survival rate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Extra-cranial response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluate the extra-cranial response rate of the combination (CR+PR+SD &gt;= 6 months).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical benefit rate (extracranial disease)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluate the clinical benefit rate of the combination for extracranial disease (CR+PR+SD &gt;= 6 months)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Breast Cancer With Intracranial Metastases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>cabazitaxel and lapatinib combination</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cabazitaxel  1-hour IV infusion on Day 1 of each 3 week cycle (dose to be determined)
Lapatinib PO once daily (dose to be determined)
Treatment cycles will be repeated every 3 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cabazitaxel</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>cabazitaxel and lapatinib combination</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Jevtana</other_name>
    <other_name>XRP6258</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>lapatinib</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>cabazitaxel and lapatinib combination</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tykerb</other_name>
    <other_name>GW572016</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with HER2-positive MBC and unequivocal evidence of brain metastases.

          2. Documented HER2-positive tumor status at study entry defined as:

               -  Immunohistochemical (IHC) score 3+ or

               -  IHC score 1-2+ and confirmed as FISH (Fluorescence in situ  hybridization)
                  positive (defined by ratio &gt;2.2) or

               -  FISH or SISH (Silver in situ hybridization) positive (ratio &gt;2.2)

          3. Patient must have at least one measurable brain lesion (defined as any lesion ≥ 1.0
             cm in the longest dimension), on T1 weighted, gadolinium enhanced MRI.  Patients may
             have had surgical excisions of brain metastases provided at least one lesions meets
             the following criteria:

               -  Patients with brain metastases previously untreated with any intra-cranial
                  radiation (i.e. no WBRT or SRS) must have at least one intra-cranial tumor
                  lesion that is = 1.0 cm.

               -  Patients with brain metastases previously treated with WBRT only must have at
                  least one intra-cranial tumor lesion ≥1.0 cm and must have evidence of
                  intra-cranial progressive disease.

               -  Patients previously treated with WBRT and SRS must have at least one
                  intracranial tumor lesion ≥1.0 cm that was not treated with SRS and must have
                  evidence of intra-cranial progressive disease

               -  Patients previously treated with SRS must either demonstrate disease progression
                  ≥12 weeks after completing stereotactic radiosurgery (SRS) with a lesion
                  measuring ≥ 1.0 cm or must have at least one intra-cranial tumor lesion ≥1.0 cm
                  that was not treated with SRS.

          4. Patients who have received WBRT for intra-cranial metastases are eligible if
             treatment was completed ≥28 days prior to the first dose of study drug.

          5. Estrogen receptor (ER) and progesterone receptor (PR) status in the primary or most
             recent tumor assessment must be known or pending at the time of study registration.
             Patient's ER/PR status (i.e., positive or negative) does not influence enrollment but
             is a requirement.

          6. Patient must have received prior treatment with HER2-directed therapy such as
             trastuzumab, either in the adjuvant or metastatic setting.

          7. Patients without prior chemotherapy for MBC are eligible provided the patients
             relapsed during adjuvant therapy with trastuzumab or ≤6 months following completion
             of adjuvant therapy.  Otherwise, there is no specific minimum or maximum number of
             previous chemotherapy regimens for MBC.

          8. Patients must have completed cytotoxic chemotherapy ≥21 days (for an every 3-week
             regimen) or ≥14 days (for an every 2-week or weekly regimen) and   have  recovered
             from or come to a new chronic or stable baseline from all treatment-related
             toxicities in order to be eligible for study treatment.

               -  Patient must have completed biologic therapy ≥3 weeks or 5-half lives whichever
                  is shorter.

               -  Patient must be discontinued from hormonal therapy a minimum of 1 day prior to
                  the first dose of study treatment.

               -  Patients receiving palliative radiation to bone, soft tissue or any other
                  disease sites must have completed this ≥1 week prior to the first dose of study
                  treatment.

          9. Patients must have recovered (&gt;2 week recovery is mandated) from any   acute
             neurosurgical intervention for metastatic CNS disease (e.g., resection, shunt
             placement) and must be clinically stable.  These patients must have residual
             measurable CNS lesion(s) following the surgical procedure if this site is to serve as
             the target lesion.

         10. Patients must be neurologically stable, defined as being on stable low doses of
             corticosteroids (≤20 mg/day prednisone or its equivalent) and anticonvulsants
             (excluding enzyme-inducing anti-epileptic drugs [phenytoin, phenobarbitol,
             carbamazepine, fosphenytoin, primidone, oxcarbazepine]) for ≥5 days prior to
             obtaining baseline gadolinium enhanced MRI (Gd-MRI) of the brain and ≥5 days prior to
             the first dose of study treatment.

         11. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status (PS) score of 0 to 2.

         12. Adequate hematologic, renal, and hepatic function.

         13. Adequate coagulation parameters.

         14. Other laboratory testing:

               -  Serum magnesium ≥ the institutional lower limit of normal (LLN)

               -  Serum potassium ≥ the institutional LLN

         15. Male patients willing to use adequate contraceptive measures.

         16. Female patients who are not of child-bearing potential, and female patients of
             child-bearing potential who agree to use adequate contraceptive measures, who are not
             breastfeeding, and who have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test within 72 hours
             prior to start of treatment.

         17. Male or female patients.

         18. Life expectancy ≥12 weeks.

         19. Age ≥18 years of age.

         20. Ability to swallow oral medications.

         21. Willingness and ability to comply with trial and follow-up procedures.

         22. Ability to understand the nature of this trial and give written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Previous treatment with lapatinib for MBC (adjuvant/neoadjuvant lapatinib permitted).

          2. Previous treatment with cabazitaxel.

          3. CNS disease requiring immediate neurosurgical intervention (e.g., resection, shunt
             placement, etc.).

          4. Leptomeningeal metastases as the only site of CNS metastases.  Patients with
             parenchymal brain metastases and leptomeningeal metastases are eligible provided they
             meet all other eligibility criteria.

          5. Peripheral neuropathy ≥Grade 2 (CTCAE v4.0).

          6. Concurrent treatment with radiation therapy, hormonal therapy, biologic therapy or
             chemotherapy is not allowed.  Low dose corticosteroids (≤30 mg/day prednisone or its
             equivalent) are allowed.

          7. Concurrent treatment with drugs known to be moderate and strong inhibitors or
             inducers of isoenzyme CYP3A that cannot be discontinued or switched to different
             medication prior to starting study drug.

          8. Concurrent use of St. John's wort and grapefruit/grapefruit juice ≤7 days prior to
             starting study drug is not allowed.

          9. Presence of active gastrointestinal (GI) disease or other condition that in the
             opinion of the investigator will interfere significantly with the absorption,
             distribution, metabolism, or excretion of oral therapy (e.g. ulcerative disease,
             uncontrolled nausea, or vomiting).

         10. Known diagnosis of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), Hepatitis B (HBV) or Hepatitis
             C (HCV).

         11. Presence of other active cancers, or history of treatment for invasive cancer ≥3
             years.  Patients with stage I cancer who have received definitive local treatment
             with curative intent at least 3 years previously, and are considered unlikely to
             recur are eligible.  All patients with previously treated in situ carcinoma (i.e.
             non-invasive) are eligible, as are patients with history of non-melanoma skin cancer.

         12. Any severe and/or uncontrolled medical conditions or other conditions that could
             affect participation in the study such as:

               -  Symptomatic congestive heart failure (CHF) of New York Heart Association Class
                  III or IV.

               -  QTc &gt; 480 ms on screening ECG (using the Fredericia formula)

               -  Poorly controlled or clinically significant atherosclerotic vascular disease
                  including cerebrovascular accident (CVA), transient ischemic attack (TIA),
                  angioplasty, cardiac or vascular stenting in the past 6 months

               -  Active (acute or chronic) or uncontrolled severe infections.

               -  Active hepatic or biliary disease (except for patients with Gilbert's syndrome,
                  asymptomatic gallstones, liver metastases, or stable chronic liver disease per
                  investigator assessment).

         13. Known hypersensitivity to cabazitaxel or other drugs formulated with polysorbate 80.

         14. Psychological, familial, sociological, or geographical conditions that do not permit
             compliance with the protocol.

         15. Inability or unwillingness to comply with study and/or follow-up procedures outlined
             in the protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Denise A. Yardley, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>SCRI Development Innovations</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Denise A. Yardley, MD</last_name>
    <phone>877-691-7274</phone>
    <email>asksarah@scresearch.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Trials Info</last_name>
    <phone>877-691-7274</phone>
    <email>asksarah@scresearch.net</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Florida Cancer Specialists - South</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Myers</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33916</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Florida Cancer Specialists-North</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Petersburg</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oncology Hematology Care Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45242</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tennessee Oncology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Central Contact</last_name>
      <phone>877-691-7274</phone>
      <email>asksarah@scresearch.net</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Denise A. Yardley, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 9, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 27, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HER2-positive breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>intracranial metastases</keyword>
  <keyword>lapatinib</keyword>
  <keyword>cabazitaxel</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Second Primary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Lapatinib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
