<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="134493">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01914679</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NPT-201-UM</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01914679</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Prospective Evaluation of RINCE to Reduce Fibromyalgia Effects - University of Michigan</brief_title>
  <acronym>PERRFECT-UM</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase 2 Clinical Trial Evaluating Use of the NeuroPoint Medical Device as a Treatment for Fibromyalgia.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cerephex Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the mechanisms of noninvasive cortical
      electrostimulation therapy known as &quot;Reduced Impedance Noninvasive Cortical
      Electrostimulation&quot; RINCE)in the management of fibromyalgia. Patients who meet the 1990
      American College of Rheumatology criteria for fibromyalgia will receive up to 24 RINCE
      treatments delivered by a medical device called &quot;NeuroPoint&quot;. Approximately 20 patients will
      receive a combination of active and inactive (sham) therapy treatments over a 16-week period
      followed by a 4 week post-treatment evaluation. Patients will also undergo three (3)
      functional brain imaging scans while participating in the study: the first prior to the
      commencement of treatment, another mid-treatment; and the third at the completion of the
      treatment period.

      The study's primary outcome measure will be the change from baseline in self-reported
      24-hour average pain intensity. The study's hypothesis is that there will be a change in
      pain intensity as well brain functioning. We do not expect there to be a statistically
      significant improvement in pain intensity due to the small sample but do expect to see
      statistically significant changes in cortical function as measured by EEG and fMRI
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in patient 24-hour recall average pain intensity</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 4, 8 and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Although pain is our primary outcome this study is not powered to detect a change in pain or other clinical parameters, it is a mechanistic study powered to detects changes in EEG and fMRI measures of connectivity that occur with RINCE treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in network connectivity as measured by EEG</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (week 1), week 6, week 18 and week 21</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>EEGs will be measured at the baseline, week 4, week 18 and week 21 visits.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Investigate changes in neurocognitive functioning using the MASQ and MCS assessments.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to 21 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The MASQ and MCS questionnaires will be administered at Baseline (week 1), week 6, week 10, week 14, week 18 and week 21.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>fMRI measures of network connectivity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (week 1), week 6, and week 18</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Sujects will undergo a neuroimaging scan at Baseline (week 1), week 6, and week 18. The scan will meaure network connectivity during stimuli.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Fibromyalgia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham - no intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>4 weeks of  inactive (sham) RINCE therapy involveing no RINCE therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>12-week RINCE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>12 weeks of RINCE therapy involveing 24 total treatments</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RINCE</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention is repeat applications of RINCE therapy. The sham is created by not delivering the therapy stimulation signal.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham - no intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>12-week RINCE</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>RINCE therapy delivered by NeuroPoint Device</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient must provide written informed consent and privacy authorization prior to
             participation in the study. Patient must have the ability to read and/or follow
             written and oral instructions, abide by the study restrictions, and agree to return
             for the required assessments.

          -  Patient is female, 18-65 years of age (inclusive) at the time of consent.

          -  Patient must have a confirmed diagnosis of fibromyalgia meeting the ACR 1990
             diagnostic criteria for fibromyalgia.

          -  Patients must have a 24-hour recall pain intensity score at both the screening and
             baseline visits between 40 and 90 inclusive on a 100 mm VAS scale.

          -  Female patient of childbearing potential must be willing to use an acceptable method
             of birth control for the duration of their study participation.

          -  Patients must be willing to refrain from all excluded therapies for the duration of
             the study.

          -  In the opinion of the Investigator, the patient is willing and able to comply with
             all protocol-specified requirements.

          -  Participants undergoing fMRI and 1H-MRS must be predominantly right handed (i.e. the
             subject writes with their right hand).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        The patient will not be eligible for enrollment if there is any history of, or in the
        opinion of the investigator, any of the following criteria are met:

          -  Patient has a current significant psychological or psychiatric disorder (e.g.,
             severe,  unstable or poorly controlled depression, severe anxiety or
             obsessive-compulsive disorder; history of suicide attempt within preceding 5 years or
             suicidal ideation within preceding 6 months; or any history of bipolar disorder,
             schizophrenia, schizoaffective or other psychotic disorder).

          -  Patient has a total Hospital and Anxiety Depression score of 11-21 for either anxiety
             or depression, or, based on the investigator's judgment, the patient is at risk of
             suicidal ideation or behavior.

          -  Patient is currently using prohibited medications or treatments (see Prohibited
             Concomitant Therapy section of protocol) including stimulants, anesthetic patches,
             CPAP and/or TENS therapy.

          -  Patient has an active diagnosis and is being treated for chronic infection or chronic
             condition such as lupus, rheumatoid arthritis, Parkinson's disease, multiple
             sclerosis, hepatitis, polio, seizures, or cancer (other than basal or squamous cell
             skin cancer).

          -  Patient has any other chronic pain condition other than fibromyalgia that, in the
             Investigator's opinion, would interfere with the assessment of fibromyalgia (e.g.,
             rheumatoid arthritis, post herpetic neuralgia, pain associated with diabetic
             neuropathy, severe pain due to degenerative joint disease, etc.)

          -  Patient has history of seizure disorder, dementia or epilepsy anytime during his or
             her life except pediatric febrile seizures.

          -  Female patient who is pregnant, planning a pregnancy, or breastfeeding.

          -  Patient has any other disease or medical condition that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, would interfere with the evaluation of study device efficacy or safety,
             or would compromise the patient's ability to participate in or complete the study.

          -  Patient has a history of other cranial electrical stimulation device use, or
             electroconvulsive therapy.

          -  Patient has any metal implant, such as stents, aneurysm clips, shunts, pacemakers,
             defibrillators, neurostimulators or other contraindications with fMRI and 1H-MRS.
             Long-bone implants are not excluded.

          -  Any anticipated need for surgery that might confound results or interfere with
             patient's ability to comply with the protocol.

          -  Myocardial infarction during preceding 12 months, uncontrolled hypertension, active
             cardiac disease (American Heart Association Functional Class 2, 3 or 4 or Objective
             Class C or D), clinically significant cardiac rhythm or conduction abnormality, or
             anticipation of bypass or other cardiac surgery within the next 12 months.

          -  Current systemic infection (e.g., HIV, hepatitis).

          -  Patients receiving systemic corticosteroids (&gt; 5 mg prednisone or equivalent per
             day).

          -  Pending or current litigation or disability claim (including Workman's Compensation).
              Patients currently receiving disability benefits will require medical monitor
             approval on a case-by-case basis.

          -  Patient has history of alcohol and/or drug abuse.

          -  Patient has participated in any investigational study within 30 days prior to
             Screening visit or is currently participating in another clinical trial.

          -  Patient has received any prior experimental treatment or therapy that, in the opinion
             of the medical monitor, would compromise the patient's ability to participate in the
             study.

          -  Patient is a staff member or relative of a staff member at either the investigative
             site or the Cerephex Corporation.

          -  Body Mass Index (BMI) of greater than approximately 40 kg/m2.

          -  Claustrophobia or any other factor sufficiently significant that it is likely to
             prevent successful completion of fMRI and 1H-MRS procedures.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel J Clauw, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Megan Halvorson</last_name>
    <phone>1-886-288-0046</phone>
    <email>cpfrc-info@umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kathy Scott</last_name>
    <email>cpfrc-info@umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Megan Halvorson</last_name>
      <email>cpfrc-info@umich.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 30, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 23, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Daniel Clauw, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Anesthesiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Fibromyalgia</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain</keyword>
  <keyword>Stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Device</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fibromyalgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myofascial Pain Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
