<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="144522">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01791985</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C/23/2011</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2011-000454-32</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01791985</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Trial of AZD4547 for Breast Cancer That is Oestrogen Receptor Positive and Has Got Worse Despite Having Anastrozole or Letrozole</brief_title>
  <acronym>RADICAL</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomised PIIa Study (With Combination Safety run-in) to Assess the Safety and Efficacy of AZD4547 in Combination With Either Anastrozole or Letrozole Versus Exemestane Alone in ER Positive Breast Cancer Patients Who Are Progressing on Current Treatment With Anastrozole or Letrozole</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Imperial College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cancer Research UK</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Imperial College London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is looking at a new drug called AZD4547 which is being tested for the treatment
      of oestrogen receptor positive breast cancer. AZD4547 is a drug which specifically &quot;blocks&quot;
      proteins called fibroblast growth factor receptors (FGFR1) that are involved in the
      processes that help cancer cells to grow. These proteins may also be responsible for the
      development of resistance to hormonal therapies used to treat some breast cancers. AZD4547
      is not yet approved for use in breast cancer and is therefore being used in this study as a
      research drug.

      The investigators will also test the theory that it is not necessary for high levels of
      FGFR1 to be present in the body to see benefit from AZD4547.

      The study will be carried out in two stages. Stage 1 is to find a suitable dose of AZD4547
      which can be used together with a class of drugs called nonsteroidal aromatase inhibitors
      (e.g. anastrozole or letrozole) i.e. a dose which does not cause too many unacceptable side
      effects.

      Stage 2 will then compare this new treatment of AZD4547 and nonsteroidal aromatase inhibitor
      against the current standard treatment using a steroidal aromatase inhibitor (exemestane) to
      see if the new treatment can either stop the cancer from growing or cause a reduction in the
      size of the tumour. Patients will be randomly selected to receive either:

        1. Exemestane (control arm) or

        2. AZD4547+letrozole or anastrozole (experimental arm).

      In both stages, the study will look at how well the new treatment is tolerated. Each patient
      is only allowed to take part in either stage 1 or 2.

      Patients with hormone sensitive (oestrogen receptor positive) breast cancer, whose current
      treatment with anastrozole or letrozole has recently stopped working properly will be
      eligible for this study. The study will be run in 9 Hospitals across England and Scotland.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of AZD4547 to be used in combination with a standard dose of anastrozole or letrozole, as assessed by Dose limiting toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>DLT assessment window  - days 1 to 28 of cycle 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>This is the primary outcome measure in the Safety Run-In part of the study</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in tumour size at 12 weeks (or progression if prior to week 12)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This is the primary outcome measure in the Randomised Phase IIa part of the study</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">99</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: exemestane alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control Arm (Standard treatment)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>anastrozole or letrozole + AZD4547</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Experimental Arm</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AZD4547</intervention_name>
    <description>80mg twice daily, one week on / one week off</description>
    <arm_group_label>anastrozole or letrozole + AZD4547</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>exemestane</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: exemestane alone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>anastrozole or letrozole</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>anastrozole or letrozole + AZD4547</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Written (signed and dated) informed consent and be capable of co-operating with
             treatment and follow-up

          2. Aged ≥ 25 years of age (N.B. in line with other studies with AZD4574 and due to
             concerns of possible effects on the immature skeleton)

          3. Post menopausal women. Women will be considered postmenopausal if they have had a
             bilateral oophorectomy or the following specific requirements apply:

               -  Women under 50 years old would be considered post-menopausal if they have been
                  amenorrhoeic for 24 months and have follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) and
                  oestradiol levels in the post-menopausal range. Patients with prior exposure to
                  depot LHRH analogues must be 24 months or more following the last administration

               -  Women aged 50 years and older would be considered post-menopausal if they have
                  been amenorrhoeic for 12 months and patients with prior exposure to depot LHRH
                  analogues must be 12 months or more following the last administration

               -  Women rendered amenorrhoeic by adjuvant chemotherapy, who were premenopausal or
                  perimenopausal prior to chemotherapy, must have been amenorrhoeic for at least
                  24 months

          4. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0-1 with no
             deterioration over the previous 2 weeks and minimum life expectancy of 12 weeks

          5. Histological confirmation of breast cancer with documented positive oestrogen
             receptor status (ER+) of primary or metastatic tumour tissue according to local
             laboratory parameters

          6. Randomised phase IIa: Mandatory provision of tumour biopsy for AZ central laboratory
             confirmation of FGFR1 status by FISH

          7. Fulfils criteria for previous treatment of breast cancer:

               -  Relapse during a single regimen of adjuvant endocrine therapy with either
                  anastrozole or letrozole or

               -  Progression during first line endocrine therapy with a non-steroidal AI for
                  advanced breast cancer*. Co-administration of a targeted agent with the
                  non-steroidal AI is permitted providing all toxicities have recovered to CTCAE
                  Grade 1 or below Safety run-in: 1 prior regimen of chemotherapy in the advanced
                  setting is permitted. Chemotherapy administered in the adjuvant setting is
                  permitted Randomised phase IIa: Chemotherapy administered in the adjuvant
                  setting is permitted * Advanced breast cancer: metastatic disease or locally
                  advanced disease which is not amenable to treatment with curative intent

          8. Safety run-in: At least one lesion (measurable and/or non-measurable) that can be
             accurately assessed by CT/MRI/plain x-ray at baseline and follow up visits Randomised
             phase IIa: At least one lesion ≥ 10mm in the longest diameter at baseline that can be
             accurately measured with CT/MRI at baseline and is suitable for accurate repeated
             measurements

        Exclusion Criteria

          1. Treatment with any of the following:

               1. more than 1 regimen of endocrine therapy for advanced breast cancer

               2. previous exposure to any FGFR inhibitor

               3. Safety run in: more than 1 prior regimen of chemotherapy for advanced breast
                  cancer.

                  Randomised phase IIa: any prior chemotherapy for advanced breast cancer

               4. potent inhibitors or inducers of CYP3A4 or CYP2D6, or substrates of CYP3A4
                  within 2 weeks prior to first dose of study treatment  (3 weeks for St John's
                  Wort)

               5. major surgery within 4 weeks prior to first dose of study treatment

               6. radiotherapy with a wide field of radiation within 4 weeks prior to first dose
                  of study treatment; or radiotherapy with a limited field of radiation for
                  palliation within 2 weeks before the first dose of study treatment

          2. With the exception of alopecia, any unresolved toxicities from prior therapy greater
             than CTCAE grade 1 at time of starting study

          3. Spinal cord compression or brain metastases unless asymptomatic, treated and stable
             and not requiring steroids for at least 4 weeks prior to start of study treatment

          4. Any evidence of severe or uncontrolled systemic diseases or active infection

          5. Any of the following cardiac criteria:

               1. Mean resting corrected QT interval (QTc) &gt;470 ms obtained from 3
                  electrocardiograms (ECGs)

               2. Any clinically important abnormalities in rhythm, conduction or morphology of
                  resting ECG e.g. complete left bundle branch block, third degree heart block

               3. Any factors that increase the risk of QTc prolongation or risk of arrhythmic
                  events such as heart failure, hypokalaemia, congenital long QT syndrome, family
                  history of long QT syndrome or unexplained sudden death under 40 years of age or
                  any concomitant medication known to prolong the QT interval

          6. Inadequate bone marrow reserve or organ function as defined by any one of the
             following parameters:

             Haemoglobin &lt; 9.0 g/dL

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &lt; 1.5 x 109 /L

               -  Platelet count &gt; 100 x 109 /L

               -  Alanine aminotransferase &gt; 2.5 x ULN if no demonstrable liver metastases or &gt; 5
                  x ULN in the presence of liver metastases

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase 2.5 x ULN if no demonstrable liver metastases or &gt; 5
                  x ULN in the presence of liver metastases

               -  Total bilirubin &gt; 1.5 x ULN if no demonstrable liver metastases or &gt; 3 x ULN in
                  the presence of liver metastases

               -  Creatinine &gt; 1.5 times ULN or creatinine clearance &lt;50ml/min

               -  Corrected calcium &gt; ULN

               -  Phosphate &gt; ULN

          7. Refractory nausea and vomiting, chronic gastrointestinal diseases, inability to
             swallow the formulated IMP or previous significant bowel resection that would
             preclude absorption of AZD4547 or exemestane or anastrozole or letrozole

          8. History of hypersensitivity to AZD4547 or exemestane or  anastrozole or letrozole

          9. History of another malignancy within 5 yrs prior to starting study treatment, except
             adequately treated basal or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin, carcinoma of the
             cervix and the disease under study

         10. Any of the following ophthalmological criteria:

               -  Current evidence or previous history of retinal pigmented epithelium detachment
                  (RPED)

               -  Previous laser treatment or intra-ocular injection for treatment of macular
                  degeneration

               -  Current evidence or previous history of dry or wet age-related macular
                  degeneration

               -  Current evidence or previous history of retinal vein occlusion (RVO)

               -  Current evidence or previous history of retinal degenerative diseases (e.g.
                  hereditary)

               -  Current evidence or previous history of any other clinically relevant
                  chorioretinal defect

         11. Concurrent treatment with another investigational agent or use of another
             investigational agent within 30 days or 5 half lives, whichever is longer, preceding
             the first dose of study treatment

         12. Patients taking prohibited medications who will not have completed the stated washout
             period for that drug before starting the study medication
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Seckl</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Imperial College Healthcare NHS Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ruth Plummer</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Newcastle-upon-Tyne Hospitals NHS Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard Baird</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cambridge University Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Iain MacPherson</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Greater Glasgow Health Board</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Philip Badman</last_name>
    <phone>02033115203</phone>
    <email>p.badman@imperial.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cambridge University Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust, Addenbrooke's Hospital, Breast Cancer Research Unit, PO Box 97, Hills Road,</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cambridge</city>
        <zip>CB2 0QQ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard Baird</last_name>
      <email>richard.baird@addenbrookes.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Richard Baird</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Greater Glasgow Health Board, Beatson West of Scotland Cancer Centre, 1053 Great Western Road,</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glasgow</city>
        <zip>G12 0YN</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Iain MacPherson</last_name>
      <email>Iain.MacPherson@glasgow.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Iain MacPherson</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Imperial College Healthcare NHS Trust, Charing Cross Hospital,1st Floor, Department of Medical Oncology, Fulham Palace Road</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>W6 8RF</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laura Woodley</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 203 3115314</phone>
      <email>Laura.Woodley@imperial.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Seckl</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Newcastle upon Tyne Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust, Sir Bobby Robson Cancer Trials Research Centre, Freeman Hospital, High Heaton</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newcastle upon Tyne</city>
        <zip>NE7 7DN</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stephenson Stephenson</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0)191 2138433</phone>
      <email>rachel.stephenson@newcastle.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ruth Plummer</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 15, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 13, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>AZD4547</keyword>
  <keyword>Randomised Phase IIa</keyword>
  <keyword>Safety Run-In</keyword>
  <keyword>FGFR1</keyword>
  <keyword>ER positive breast cancer</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Exemestane</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Letrozole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anastrozole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
