<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="154725">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01924091</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FAME-02B</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>DAIDS-ES# 11939</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01924091</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PK/PD of Single Dose Dapivirine Vaginal Film</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of the Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of Single Dose Dapivirine Vaginal Gel and Film Formulation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>International Partnership for Microbicides, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>International Partnership for Microbicides, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To compare drug concentrations in vaginal fluid, genital tissue, and blood
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dapivirine concentrations in plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <condition>Pharmaokinetics</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dapivirine Gel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dapivirine Film</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dapivirine gel</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Dapivirine Gel</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dapivirine film</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Dapivirine Film</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. 18 years of age or older with a history of receptive vaginal intercourse.

          2. HIV negative by EIA within 28 days of enrollment.

          3. Understand and agree to local STI reporting requirements.

          4. Able and willing to provide written informed consent to take part in the study.

          5. Able and willing to provide adequate information for locator purposes.

          6. Availability to return for all study visits, barring unforeseen circumstances.

          7. Availability to return for the second formulation dosing at the same time in the
             subject's menstrual cycle as when the first formulation was administered, at least 10
             days before menses.

          8. Willing to abstain from vaginal intercourse and insertion of anything (e.g., drug,
             vaginal douche, or sex toy) in vagina for 72 hours before each study product
             exposure, and 7 days following each vaginal sampling procedure.

          9. Willingness to have partner(s) use condoms (must not contain Nonoxynol-9) for the
             duration of the study.

         10. Agree not to participate in other research studies involving drugs and/or medical
             devices.

         11. Negative qualitative urine pregnancy test.

         12. Per participant report, using an effective method of contraception at enrollment;
             hormonal method (except vaginal ring) used continuously for the past 30 days;
             intrauterine device (IUD [copper or hormonal] inserted at least 30 days prior to
             enrollment); female sterilization; abstinent from sexual activity with male partner
             for the past 30 days; or sexual activity with vasectomized partner; and willingness
             to use effective method of contraception until the completion of final scheduled
             study visit if enrolled.

         13. Willingness to remain in the research unit for up to 24 hours on each of two dosing
             days, -

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Current sexual partner known by participant to be HIV seropositive.

          2. Individuals who, by history, engage in condom-less intercourse with HIV-infected
             partners, or partners that have unknown HIV serostatus, or women who exchange sex for
             money, shelter, or gifts.

          3. Active sexually transmitted infection or documented treatment of sexually transmitted
             infections including, but not limited to: chlamydia, gonorrhea, syphilis,
             trichomonas, cervicitis or PID within 6 months prior to enrollment.

          4. Known history of genital HSV (diagnosed by either clinical or laboratory test).

          5. Symptomatic vaginal candidiasis or bacterial vaginosis.

          6. Undiagnosed irregular uterine bleeding

          7. Pathology of the female genital tract, which in the judgment of the investigator
             might increase the risk of the study to the research participant.

          8. Individuals who are status post hysterectomy.

          9. History of any cervicovaginal procedure (i.e. colposcopy with cervical biopsy) within
             the past 2 months.  Individuals who have a history of cone biopsy or extensive loop
             electrosurgical excision procedure (LEEP), which in the judgment of the investigator
             may affect permeability assessment.

         10. Any known primary or secondary uro-genital malformations, which in the assessment of
             the investigator may interfere with the intended urine collection for PK studies.

         11. Use of vaginally administered medications within 4 week of enrollment

         12. Any active urinary tract infection

         13. By history, subjects with irregular menstrual cycles.

         14. At screening:

               -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) greater than
                  1.5 X the site laboratory ULN (upper limit of normal)

               -  Hemoglobin less than 10.0 g/dL

               -  Platelet count less than 100,000/mm3

               -  Other safety tests outside of the normal range that in the judgment of the
                  investigator may interfere with conduct of the study.

               -  Positive findings on urinalysis that are clinically significant in the opinion
                  of the investigator

         15. Estimated creatinine clearance &lt; 60 ml/min based on established nomograms

         16. Recent history (past 6 months) of injection drug use or, a level of alcohol use that,
             in the judgement of the Investigator of Record, may interfere with the conduct of
             this study.

         17. Unwillingness to refrain from aspirin and NSAIDs product use for one week prior to
             and one week post study procedures.

         18. Use of warfarin or heparin.

         19. Use of systemic immunomodulatory medications within 4 weeks of enrollment.

         20. Use of product containing nonoxynol-9 within 4 weeks of enrollment.

         21. Use of any investigational products within 4 weeks of enrollment.

         22. Any other medical conditions deemed not safe for participation by the investigator.

         23. Any individual that is actively breast feeding.

         24. Post-menopausal defined as 12 months of amenorrhea.

             -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Craig Hendrix, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>John's Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christine Radebaugh, BS, RN</last_name>
    <phone>443-287-3060</phone>
    <email>cradeba1@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 13, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 13, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
