<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="40056">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01740323</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00055328</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>Winship2139-11</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01740323</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase II Study of Curcumin vs Placebo for Chemotherapy-Treated Breast Cancer Patients Undergoing Radiotherapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Phase II Study of Curcumin Versus Placebo for Inhibition of NF-kB DNA Binding in Peripheral Blood Mononuclear Cells of Chemotherapy-Treated Breast Cancer Patients Undergoing Radiotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Andrew H Miller</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main purpose of the investigation is to determine if curcumin reduces NF-kB DNA binding
      in patients receiving XRT for their breast cancer after having completed chemotherapy.
      Patients who have received prior chemotherapy will be eligible, because we have found that
      this enriched population is at particular risk for exhibiting increased NF-kB DNA binding
      following XRT.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      As many as 60% of breast cancer (BrCA) patients receiving radiation are known to develop
      fatigue with about 30% suffering persistent fatigue several months to years after treatment
      completion (12-23).  The physical, psychological, and molecular mechanisms by which patients
      develop fatigue are poorly understood and most likely multi-factorial.  One pathway that has
      received considerable attention is nuclear factor-kappa B (NF-kB)(24). The NF-kB pathway has
      emerged as having an important role not only in cancer treatment resistance but in the
      development of fatigue.  NF-kB activation leads to over expression of interleukin
      (IL)-1beta, IL-6, and tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-alpha, all factors related to inflammation
      and factors that have been found to be upregulated in patients receiving radiation as well
      as BrCA survivors with fatigue (25-29).  A recently published study looking at TNF-alpha,
      fatigue and cachexia in cancer patients receiving docetaxol showed that NF-kB is upregulated
      in fatigued patients and that agents which inhibit TNF-alpha lead to better tolerance of
      chemotherapy dose escalation (30).  Work by our group and others has shown that ionizing
      radiation increases NF-kB pathway activity in circulating immune cells (as well as within
      breast cancer cells) and that this effect is most pronounced in women previously treated
      with chemotherapy (31, 32). Our work has shown that the NF-kB pathway activity in
      circulating immune cells is also related to fatigue development in BrCA patients treated
      with radiation and that patients most at risk for persistent fatigue and NF-kB pathway
      activity are those who have received chemotherapy for their breast cancer (31).

      Curcumin, a known inhibitor of NF-kB, has been shown to decrease NF-kB activation in human
      participants.  In a recent study, 8 grams of curcumin by mouth daily for 8 weeks was well
      tolerated in patients with pancreatic cancer and other pre-malignant conditions with no
      associated toxicities (6, 8). Although there is concern over the body's absorption of
      curcumin, the bioavailability of curcumin in the study of pancreatic cancer patients was
      shown, with peak drug levels at 22 to 41ng/mL that remained relatively constant over the
      first 4 weeks of treatment with 8 grams of curcumin daily (8).  Clinical trials with daily
      dosages of 1,125 to 2,500mg have also confirmed the safety of curcumin and also shown its
      ability to decrease inflammation in patients with rheumatoid arthritis and in post-operative
      patients (6, 33, 34).  In vivo murine models of chronic fatigue syndrome have also shown
      that curcumin may also alleviate symptoms of fatigue (35).  While these studies are
      promising, very little is known about the capacity of Meriva to inhibit NF-kB in women
      treated for BrCA.  We hypothesize that oral Meriva, a known inhibitor of NF-kB, may be used
      to decrease levels of NF-kB activity in BrCA patients previously treated with chemotherapy
      who go on to receive radiotherapy (XRT), a carefully chosen group of patients at particular
      risk for high levels of NF-kB DNA binding (a direct measure of NF-kB pathway activity).

      We have chosen to administer oral Meriva, 500mg BID, in our patient population based on the
      above data. Meriva-500 is a curcumin formulation that also contains phosphatidylcholine,
      derived from soy that has been shown to aid in absorption of curcumin (9), permitting a
      lower overall dose of curcumin. Of note, 1000 mg Meriva contains 200 mg curcuminoids (&gt;90%
      curcumin).

      By decreasing activity of NF-kB, fatigue may improve in BrCA patients taking Meriva.
      Results from this study will contribute to the limited research available on the capacity of
      curcumin treatment, including Meriva, to inhibit NF-kB in vivo as well as symptoms of
      fatigue associated with excessive NF-kB pathway activity in BRCA patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>NF-kB DNA binding as measured by ELISA six weeks following treatment with daily placebo or curcumin</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks following completion of XRT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Curcumin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>500 mg BID</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>daily placebo for 6 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Curcumin</intervention_name>
    <description>500 mg BID</description>
    <arm_group_label>Curcumin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female breast cancer patients over the age of 18 will be recruited for this study.
             Patients enrolled in the study will meet standard criteria for whole breast XRT.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects will be excluded for a number of medical conditions that are
             contraindications to XRT and/or might confound the relationship among fatigue, and
             inflammation, including pregnancy, major psychiatric disorders, autoimmune or
             inflammatory disorders, chronic infectious diseases (e.g. HIV, hepatitis B or C),
             neurologic disorders and uncontrolled cardiovascular, metabolic, pulmonary or renal
             disease (as determined by medical history, physical examination and laboratory
             testing).  Subjects with a history of a major psychiatric disorder including
             Schizophrenia or Bipolar Disorder or a diagnosis of Substance Abuse or Dependence
             within the past 1 year (as determined by standardized psychiatric interview) will be
             excluded.  Subjects taking drugs known to affect the immune system (e.g.
             glucocorticoids, methotrexate) will also be excluded. Subjects using supplements or
             other natural products with one week of starting medications, excluding vitamins and
             calcium supplementation or at the discretion of the attending physician, will be
             excluded. Patients who have evidence of infection as determined by history, physical
             exam or laboratory testing (complete blood count and urinalysis) at baseline will be
             excluded.  In addition, patients who develop evidence of infection (as determined by
             history, physical exam or laboratory testing) during the study will be discontinued
             from the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrew H Miller, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory Winship Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bobbi Woolwine</last_name>
    <phone>404-712-9620</phone>
    <email>bwoolwi@emory.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 22, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 30, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Emory University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Andrew H Miller</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Sponsor Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Chemotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>NF-kB</keyword>
  <keyword>DNA Binding</keyword>
  <keyword>Curcumin</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Curcumin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
