<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="94040">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01838655</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130124</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-EI-0124</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01838655</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nitisinone for Type 1B Oculocutaneous Albinism</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study of Nitisinone in the Treatment of Oculocutaneous Albinism, Type 1B</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Oculocutaneous albinism, type 1B (OCA1B) is a genetic disease caused by problems in the
      gene that makes tyrosine. Tyrosine is an amino acid needed to produce pigment in the skin,
      hair, and eyes. People with OCA1B have pale skin, white hair, and light-colored eyes.
      Pigment in the back of the eye helps vision, so people with OCA-1B often have visual
      problems. Researchers want to see if a drug called nitisinone can help improve eye
      pigmentation and vision in people with OCA1B. Nitisinone is approved for treating a related
      genetic disease that causes problems with tyrosine, so it may help people with OCA1B.

      Objectives:

      - To see if nitisinone can help improve eye pigmentation and vision in people with OCA1B.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals at least 18 years of age who have OCA1B.

      Design:

        -  This study will last about 18 months. It requires eight outpatient visits, each about 3
           months apart. Each visit will require 1 to 2 days of testing.

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam, eye exam, and medical history. They
           will have additional vision and neurological tests. They will be tested to see how
           their brain and retinas respond to light. They will also take hair and blood samples,
           and answer questions about diet.

        -  Participants will receive the study drug. They will take one pill a day for 1 year.
           They will keep track of the dose in a study diary.

        -  At the outpatient visits, participants will have the following tests:

        -  Medical history and physical exam

        -  Neurological and eye exams

        -  Retina function tests

        -  Tests of the skin and brain's response to light

        -  Blood and urine tests

        -  Dietary consultation

        -  Visual function questionnaire.

        -  After the end of the study, participants will return to the care of their regular eye
           doctor.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective: The primary objective of this study is to evaluate oral nitisinone as a treatment
      that improves ocular pigmentation in adult participants with oculocutaneous albinism, type
      1B (OCA1B). Secondary objectives of this study are to determine whether the selected outcome
      measures are robust enough to use in a larger trial and to assess whether oral nitisinone
      improves visual function, skin pigmentation, and hair pigmentation in participants with
      OCA1B.

      Study Population: Five participants with OCA1B will be enrolled initially. However, up to an
      additional three participants may be enrolled to account for participants who withdraw from
      the study for any reason before the Month 12 visit.

      Design: In this pilot, phase 1/2, single-site, prospective, open label trial, participants
      will receive 2 mg of oral nitisinone daily for at least one year, and they will be followed
      for at least

      18 months. Ocular and non-ocular data will be collected at least every three months, with
      the first follow-up visit occurring three months after the final baseline visit.
      Participants will be required to have at least 8 outpatient visits at the NEI clinic over a
      period of 18 months. This study has a common termination date and therefore may continue for
      up to four years.

      Outcome Measures: The primary outcome for the study is the absolute change in iris
      pigmentation on an 8-point scale at 12 months as compared to baseline. Participants    left
      and right eyes will be analyzed. The absolute change in iris pigmentation for each eye on an
      8-point scale at 3, 6 and 9 months compared to baseline will be assessed as secondary
      outcomes. Other secondary outcomes for each eye include the absolute and percent change in
      semi-quantitative iris pigmentation on image analysis; the absolute change in electronic
      visual acuity (EVA); the absolute change in contrast sensitivity without glare, with medium
      glare, and with high glare; the absolute change in full-field ERG measures; the absolute and
      percent change in melanin content in skin using skin reflectometry; and qualitative changes
      in hair, skin, and fundus pigmentation at 3, 6, 9 and 12 months as compared to baseline. The
      absolute and percent change in hair melanin will also be assessed at 12 months as compared
      to baseline. The number and severity of adverse events and the number of withdrawals will be
      assessed as safety outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary outcome for the study is the absolute change in iris pigmentation on an 8-point scale at 12 months as compared to baseline. Participants    left and right eyes will be analyzed.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in hair, skin, and fundus pigmentation</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in hair melanin</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in melanin content in skin</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in full-field ERG measures</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in contrast sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in iris pigmentation</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">8</enrollment>
  <condition>Albinism</condition>
  <condition>Vision Loss</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nitisinone (NTBC)</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        To be eligible, the following inclusion criteria must be met, when applicable.

          1. Participant must be 18 years of age or older.

          2. Participant must understand and sign the protocol   s informed consent document.

          3. Participant must have normal renal function, liver function, and platelet counts or
             have mild abnormalities no greater than grade 1 as defined by the Common Terminology
             Criteria for Adverse Events v4.0 (CTCAE).

          4. Any female participant of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test
             at screening and must be willing to undergo pregnancy testing immediately prior to
             the start of the investigational product and while on the investigational product.

          5. Any female participant of childbearing potential and any male participant able to
             father children must have (or have a partner who has) had a hysterectomy or
             vasectomy, be completely abstinent from intercourse, or must agree to practice two
             effective methods of contraception while taking the investigational product and for
             at least two months following the last dose of investigational product. Acceptable
             methods of contraception include:

               -  Hormonal contraception (i.e., birth control pills, injected hormones, dermal
                  patch, or vaginal ring),

               -  Intrauterine device,

               -  Barrier methods (diaphragm, condom) with spermicide, or

               -  Surgical sterilization (tubal ligation).

          6. Participant must have OCA1B, as defined by ALL (a-d) of the following criteria:

               1. Participant has ophthalmic signs or symptoms of albinism, including:

                    -  Bilateral visual acuity E-ETDRS EVA letter score of     83 (i.e., Snellen
                       equivalent of 20/25 or worse) that is not attributable to any other
                       pathology.

                    -  Bilateral iris transillumination that can be seen in clinical photographs.

               2. Predominant contralateral decussation of ganglion cell axons, as determined by
                  pattern visual evoked potential (VEP).

               3. Participant has at least one definitive mutation in the OCA1 gene (tyrosinase).

               4. Participant has no definitive mutations in the other known albinism genes (OCA2,
                  OCA3, OCA4, OA1).

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Participant is pregnant or breast-feeding.

          -  Participant has any of the following abnormal laboratory test results:

               1. Serum potassium &lt;  3.0 mEq/L,

               2. Serum creatinine &gt;  2.0 mg/dL,

               3. Serum CK &gt;  500 U/L,

               4. Serum SGPT &gt;  41 U/L or serum SGOT &gt;  34 U/L,

               5. Hemoglobin &lt;  10.0 g/dL,

               6. Platelets &lt;  100 k/mm(3),

               7. White blood cell (WBC) count &lt;  3.0 k/microL,

               8. Plasma tyrosine &gt;  150 microM,

               9. ESR &gt;  100 mm/h, and/or

              10. Serum T4 &gt;  15 microg/dL OR Serum T4 &lt;  4 microg/dL.

          -  Participant has keratopathy.

          -  Participant has a current malignancy.

          -  Participant has open skin lesions.

          -  Participant is on a diet that deliberately increases protein intake to
             disproportionate levels (e.g., Atkins diet). The diet must be reasonably balanced, as
             determined by a dietician.

          -  Participant has uncontrolled hypertension, defined as systolic blood pressure above
             180 mmHg or diastolic blood pressure above 95 mmHg.

          -  Participant has another chronic ocular disease that may confound the results of
             visual tests, such as age-related macular degeneration, cataract of possible visual
             significance, or uncontrolled glaucoma.

          -  Participant drinks more than the equivalent of two glasses of wine per day on
             average, has a history of alcohol abuse, or has a severe liver illness.

          -  Participant   s liver is &gt;  3 cm below the right costal margin.

          -  Participant has a muscle disease.

          -  Participant is currently taking a medication known to cause elevated liver function
             tests including statins/HMG-Co-A reductase inhibitors (e.g., lovastatin,
             simvastatin); anti-epileptic medications (e.g., carbamazepine, phenytoin,
             phenobarbital); tetracycline or its derivatives, if used chronically; acetaminophen,
             if  used daily/chronically; amiodarone; and any other medications with known
             significant liver toxicity.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brian P Brooks, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Eye Institute (NEI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Allison T Bamji, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-3437</phone>
    <email>bamjia@nei.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Brian P Brooks, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-3577</phone>
    <email>brooksb@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-EI-0124.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hertle RW, Anninger W, Yang D, Shatnawi R, Hill VM. Effects of extraocular muscle surgery on 15 patients with oculo-cutaneous albinism (OCA) and infantile nystagmus syndrome (INS). Am J Ophthalmol. 2004 Dec;138(6):978-87.</citation>
    <PMID>15629289</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Giebel LB, Tripathi RK, King RA, Spritz RA. A tyrosinase gene missense mutation in temperature-sensitive type I oculocutaneous albinism. A human homologue to the Siamese cat and the Himalayan mouse. J Clin Invest. 1991 Mar;87(3):1119-22.</citation>
    <PMID>1900309</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Giebel LB, Tripathi RK, Strunk KM, Hanifin JM, Jackson CE, King RA, Spritz RA. Tyrosinase gene mutations associated with type IB (&quot;yellow&quot;) oculocutaneous albinism. Am J Hum Genet. 1991 Jun;48(6):1159-67. Erratum in: Am J Hum Genet 1991 Sep;49(3):696.</citation>
    <PMID>1903591</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 20, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Albinism</keyword>
  <keyword>Nitisinone</keyword>
  <keyword>Melanin</keyword>
  <keyword>Vision Loss</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Albinism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Albinism, Oculocutaneous</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Blindness</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Nitisinone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
