<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="134362">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01746979</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EMR 200592-001</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-002957-42</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01746979</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Trial Testing TH-302 in Combination With Gemcitabine in Previously Untreated Subjects With Metastatic or Locally Advanced Unresectable Pancreatic Adenocarcinoma</brief_title>
  <acronym>MAESTRO</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Phase III Study of the Efficacy and Safety of Gemcitabine in Combination With TH-302 Compared With Gemcitabine in Combination With Placebo in Previously Untreated Subjects With Metastatic or Locally Advanced Unresectable Pancreatic Adenocarcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>EMD Serono</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Threshold Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>EMD Serono</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>European Union: European Medicines Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This Phase 3 trial is a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of gemcitabine in
      combination with TH-302 compared to gemcitabine in combination with placebo in subjects with
      locally advanced unresectable or metastatic pancreatic adenocarcinoma. Randomized subjects
      will receive TH-302 plus gemcitabine or gemcitabine plus placebo in 4-week cycles until
      there is evidence of progressive disease, intolerable toxicity, or the subject discontinues
      from the trial for other reasons (for example, withdrawal of consent). The primary efficacy
      endpoint is overall survival (OS) time. The data cut-off for statistical analyses of the
      primary and secondary endpoints will be reached when 508 events (deaths) will be reported.
      No planned interim analyses will be conducted. An Independent Safety Monitoring Board (ISMB)
      will provide periodic evaluations of the unblinded safety data to ensure subject safety and
      the validity and scientific merit of the study. A total of 660 subjects will be enrolled.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival Time</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall survival time is defined as time from randomization to death or last day known to be alive.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival Time</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Progression Free Survival time is defined as the time from randomization to either first observation of progressive disease or occurrence of death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with best overall response according to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors Version 1.1 (RECIST v.1.1)</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of subjects with objective response is based on assessment of complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) according to RECIST v.1.1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with disease control according to RECIST v.1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of subjects with disease control is based on assessment of complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) or stable disease (SD) according to RECIST v.1.1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life (QOL) EuroQuol-5D (EQ-5D) Health Outcome questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The EuroQuol-5D (EQ-5D) questionnaire is a measure of health status that provides a simple descriptive profile and a single index value. The EQ-5D defines health in terms of mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort and anxiety/depression. The 5 items are combined to generate health profiles. These profiles are converted to a continuous single index score using a one to one matching. The lowest possible score is -0.59 and the highest is 1.00, wherein higher scores on the EQ-5D represent a better QOL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life (QOL) Assessment European Organization for the Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Quality of Life Questionnaire-Core 30 (QLQ-C30) (Version 3.0)</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The EORTC QLQ-C30 scores were derived from mutually exclusive sets of items, with scale scores ranging from 0 to 100 after a linear transformation. Higher scores indicate a higher level of functioning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain intensity using a Numerical Rating Scale (NRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The 11-point NRS will be used to assess pain intensity. The score can vary between &quot;0&quot; and &quot;10&quot; wherein, 0 = no pain and 10 = the worst possible pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum Carcinoma Antigen  19-9 response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Serum Carcinoma antigen 19-9 is a serum marker for pancreatic cancer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with treatment-emergent adverse events (TEAEs) according to National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE v.4.03)</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>An Adverse Event (AE) is defined as any new untoward medical occurrences/worsening of pre-existing medical condition without regard to possibility of causal relationship.  Treatment-emergent adverse events are events from first dose of study drug that were absent before treatment or that worsened relative to pretreatment state.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">660</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic or Locally Advanced Unresectable Pancreatic Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gemcitabine plus TH-302</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gemcitabine plus placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TH-302</intervention_name>
    <description>TH-302 will be administered at a dose of 340 milligrams per square meter (mg/m^2) as intravenous infusion over 30 minutes on Day 1, 8 and 15 of every 28-day cycle.  Doses will be administered until evidence of progressive disease, intolerable toxicity or subject withdrawal.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gemcitabine plus TH-302</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gemcitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Gemcitabine will be administered at a dose of 1000 (mg/m^2) as intravenous infusion over 30 minutes on Day 1, 8 and 15 of every 28-day cycle. Doses will be administered until evidence of progressive disease, intolerable toxicity or subject withdrawal.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gemcitabine plus TH-302</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Gemcitabine plus placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo (5 percent dextrose - D5W)</intervention_name>
    <description>TH-302 placebo (5 percent dextrose - D5W) will be administered as intravenous infusion over 30 minutes on Day 1, 8 and 15 of every 28-day cycle. Doses will be administered until evidence of progressive disease, intolerable toxicity or subject withdrawal.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gemcitabine plus placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  At least 18 years of age

          -  Locally advanced unresectable or metastatic pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma proven
             by histology or cytology and previously untreated with chemotherapy or systemic
             therapy other than:

               -  Radiosensitizing doses of 5-fluorouracil;

               -  Radiosensitizing doses of gemcitabine if relapse occurred at least 6 months
                  after completion of gemcitabine;

               -  Neoadjuvant chemotherapy if relapse occurred at least 6 months after surgical
                  resection;

               -  Adjuvant chemotherapy if relapse occurred at least 6 months after completion of
                  adjuvant chemotherapy

          -  Measurable disease (at least one target lesion outside of previous radiation fields)
             or non-measurable disease by RECIST v.1.1 criteria

          -  Documentation of disease progression since any prior therapy

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1.

          -  Life expectancy of at least 3 month

          -  Acceptable liver, renal function and acceptable hematological status

          -  Other protocol defined inclusion criteria may apply

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class III or IV congestive heart failure,
             myocardial infarction within 6 months prior to the date of randomization, unstable
             arrhythmia or symptomatic peripheral arterial vascular disease

          -  Symptomatic ischemic heart disease

          -  Known brain, leptomeningeal or epidural metastases (unless treated and well
             controlled for at least 3 months)

          -  Previous malignancy other than pancreatic cancer in the last 5 years, except for
             adequately treated non-melanoma skin cancer or pre-invasive cancer of the cervix

          -  Severe chronic obstructive or other pulmonary disease with hypoxemia

          -  Major surgery, other than diagnostic surgery, less than or equal to 28 days prior to
             the date of randomization. Subject must have completely recovered from surgery

          -  Active, uncontrolled bacterial, viral, or fungal infections, requiring systemic
             therapy

          -  Treatment of pancreatic cancer with radiation therapy or surgery less than or equal
             to 28 days prior to the date of randomization

          -  Prior therapy with a hypoxic cytotoxin

          -  Subjects who participated in an investigational drug or device trial less than or
             equal to 28 days prior to Day 1 of the first cycle

          -  Known infection with Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV), or an active infection with
             Hepatitis B or Hepatitis C

          -  Subjects who have exhibited allergic reactions to a structural compound similar to
             TH-302 or the drug product excipients or to gemcitabine or its excipients

          -  Other protocol defined exclusion criteria may apply
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert J. Fram, MD, FACP</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>EMD Serono Inc., a subsidiary of Merck KGaA, Darmstadt, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Please Contact U.S. Medical Information Located in</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rockland</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>for US Recruiting Sites</last_name>
      <phone>888-275-7376</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Please Contact Merck Communication Services Located in</name>
      <address>
        <city>Darmstadt</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>for EU Recruiting Sites</last_name>
      <phone>+49 6151 72 5200</phone>
      <email>service@merckgroup.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://maestrostudy.com</url>
    <description>Website including further information about the MAESTRO study</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://maestrostudy.com/AreYouEligible/StudySiteFinder.aspx</url>
    <description>Study site finder for recruiting sites in the US</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 17, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 7, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>TH-302; Pancreatic Cancer; EMR200592-001</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Gemcitabine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
