<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="104044">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01704261</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3102-022</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-002612-10</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01704261</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Addition of MK-3102 to Participants With Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus Who Have Inadequate Glycemic Control on Combination Therapy With Glimepiride and Metformin (MK-3102-022 AM4)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase III, Multicenter, Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled Clinical Trial to Study the Safety and Efficacy of the Addition of MK-3102 to Subjects With Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus Who Have Inadequate Glycemic Control on Combination Therapy With Glimepiride and Metformin</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine the safety and efficacy of the addition of MK-3102 in participants
      with type 2 diabetes mellitus with inadequate glycemic control on metformin and
      sulfonylurea. The primary hypothesis is that after 24 weeks, the addition of treatment with
      MK-3102 provides a greater reduction in hemoglobin A1c (A1C) compared with the addition of
      placebo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in hemoglobin A1c (A1C)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants Who Experienced at Least One Adverse Event</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 27</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants Who Discontinued from the Study Due to an Adverse Event</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in fasting plasma glucose (FPG)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants attaining A1C glycemic goals of &lt;7% and &lt;6.5%</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3102</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MK-3102 25 mg capsule administered orally once a week for 24 weeks.  Participants continue pre-study concomitant therapy of open-label glimepiride tablet(s) orally once daily (total daily dose &gt;=4 mg per day) and metformin tablet(s) orally once or twice daily (total daily dose &gt;=1500 mg per day).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Matching placebo to MK-3102 capsule administered orally once a week for 24 weeks.  Participants continue pre-study concomitant therapy of open-label glimepiride tablet(s) orally once daily (total daily dose &gt;=4 mg per day) and metformin tablet(s) orally once or twice daily (total daily dose &gt;=1500 mg per day).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MK-3102</intervention_name>
    <description>MK-3102 25 mg capsule administered orally once a week</description>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3102</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Matching placebo to MK-3012</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo to MK-3102 capsule administered orally once a week</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Glimepiride</intervention_name>
    <description>Open-label glimepiride tablet(s) administered orally once daily for a total daily dose &gt;=4 mg. In the event of hypoglycemia, the glimepiride dose may be down-titrated to a minimum dose of 1 mg daily.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3102</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Amaryl®</other_name>
    <other_name>Glimy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metformin</intervention_name>
    <description>Open-label metformin tablet(s) administered orally once or twice daily for a total daily dose &gt;=1500 mg</description>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3102</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fortamet®</other_name>
    <other_name>Glucophage®</other_name>
    <other_name>Glucophage® XR</other_name>
    <other_name>Glumetza®</other_name>
    <other_name>Riomet®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosed with type 2 diabetes mellitus

          -  Currently taking stable doses of metformin (&gt;=1500 mg/day) and sulfonylurea

          -  Male, or female not of reproductive potential or female of reproductive potential who
             agrees to remain abstinent or use (or have their partner use) 2 methods of acceptable
             contraception to prevent pregnancy during the study and for 21 days after the last
             dose of study drug

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of type 1 diabetes mellitus or a history of ketoacidosis

          -  Treated with any antihyperglycemic agent therapies other than the protocol-required
             sulfonylurea and metformin within 12 weeks prior to study participation or with
             MK-3102 at any time prior to study participation.

          -  History of hypersensitivity to a dipeptidyl peptidase IV (DPP-4) inhibitor

          -  On a weight loss program and is not in the maintenance phase; or has been on a weight
             loss medication in the past 6 months; or has undergone bariatric surgery within 12
             months prior to study participation.

          -  Is on or likely to require treatment for &gt;=2 consecutive weeks or repeated courses of
             corticosteroids (inhaled, nasal or topical corticosteroids are permitted)

          -  Currently being treated for hyperthyroidism or is on thyroid replacement therapy and
             has not been on a stable dose for at least 6 weeks

          -  Medical history of active liver disease (other than non-alcoholic hepatic steatosis),
             including chronic active hepatitis B or C, primary biliary cirrhosis, or symptomatic
             gallbladder disease

          -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)

          -  New or worsening coronary heart disease, congestive heart failure, myocardial
             infarction, unstable angina, coronary artery intervention, stroke, or transient
             ischemic neurological disorder within the past 3 months

          -  Poorly controlled hypertension

          -  History of malignancy &lt;=5 years prior to study participation, except for adequately
             treated basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer, or in situ cervical cancer

          -  Clinically important hematological disorder (such as aplastic anemia,
             myeloproliferative or myelodysplastic syndromes, thrombocytopenia)

          -  Pregnant or breast feeding, or is expecting to conceive or donate eggs during the
             trial, including 21 days following the last dose of study drug

          -  Current user of recreational or illicit drugs or has had a recent history of drug
             abuse or routinely consumes &gt;2 alcoholic drinks per day or &gt;14 drinks per week, or
             engages in binge drinking

          -  Donated blood products within 8 weeks of study participation, or intends to donate
             blood products during the study or has received or anticipates receiving blood
             products within 12 weeks prior to study participation or during the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
    <country>South Africa</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>Romania</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 28, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 8, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Glimepiride</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
