<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="121062">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01961271</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BUP12-AP-401</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01961271</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation Of Efficacy And Safety Of Norspan In Moderate To Severe Pain Due To Osteoarthritis, Rheumatoid Arthritis, Joint/Muscle Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Multicentre Study To Evaluate Efficacy And Safety Of Buprenorphine Transdermal Patch (Norspan) In Chronic Non-Malignant Pain Of Moderate To Severe Intensity Due To Osteoarthritis, Rheumatoid Arthritis, Lower Back Pain And Joint / Muscle Pain, When Opioid Is Needed For Analgesia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mundipharma Pte Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mundipharma Korea Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mundipharma (Hong Kong) Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mundipharma Distribution GmBH (Philippine Branch)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mundipharma (China) Pharmaceutical Co. Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mundipharma Pte Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Philippines : Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>South Korea: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>Hong Kong: Department of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess the efficacy of the buprenorphine transdermal patch
      (Norspan® or Sovenor® transdermal patch) in patients with chronic non-malignant pain of
      moderate to severe intensity due to osteoarthritis, rheumatoid arthritis, lower back pain
      and joint/muscle pain, who are not adequately responding to non-opioid painkillers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Baseline assessment (Visit 1) includes medical history, physical examination, vital signs.

      At Visit 2 [7 days ( ± 3 days) after Visit 1] and subsequent optional titration visits up to
      (Visit 1 + 42 days) , patients will be titrated up to an effective and tolerated dose of
      Norspan® or Sovenor® transdermal patch and continue rescue analgesic, if necessary.

      Titration period is dependent on time to achieving optimal pain control as determined by the
      investigator. The up-titration regime is planned on a weekly basis. Earlier dose titration
      (i.e. minimum 3 days after the patch application) is permitted at the investigator's
      discretion if the pain is uncontrolled. Effective and tolerated dose is assessed by data
      recorded in the case report form and patient diary.

      According to country label, all patients will begin treatment with Norspan® or Sovenor®
      transdermal patch 5mg and will then be up-titrated, if necessary, to a maximum of Norspan®
      or Sovenor® transdermal patch 40mg or according to country label to achieve stable pain
      control. Patients that require oral opioid at any time during the study should be
      discontinued from the trial.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy according to BS-11 pain score</measure>
    <time_frame>Maximum 17 weeks starting from enrolment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary efficacy outcome analysis is the pre- and post-intervention change in BS-11 pain score.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary efficacy outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>approximately 17 weeks starting from enrolment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Pre- and post-intervention EQ5D-3L quality of life score change and 8-items global sleep quality assessment (GSQA) score change.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>From time of enrolment up to 7 days after completion / discontinuation visit</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Side effects of the transdermal patch treatment will also be analysed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary efficacy outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 17 weeks starting from enrolment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Daily use of breakthrough pain medication from visits 1-6, assessed from patient diaries.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary efficacy outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>At visit 6</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Physicians' and patients' treatment satisfaction assessed using Physician's Global Impression of Change scale and Patient's Global Impression of Change scale respectively</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary efficacy outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Incidence of early treatment discontinuation due to lack of efficacy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">230</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <condition>Rheumatoid Arthritis</condition>
  <condition>Lower Back Pain</condition>
  <condition>Joint Pain</condition>
  <condition>Muscle Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Buprenorphine transdermal patch</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be on either 5mg, 10mg, 15mg, 20mg, 25mg, 30mg or 40mg doses for 17 weeks. Dose titration will occur every week for the first 6 weeks, and will be maintained for the next 11 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Buprenorphine transdermal patch</intervention_name>
    <description>Please see Arm Description.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Buprenorphine transdermal patch</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Norspan transdermal patch</other_name>
    <other_name>Sovenor transdermal patch</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Males and females aged 18-80 years (both inclusive) at the time of recruitment.

          2. Clinical diagnosis of osteoarthritis, rheumatoid arthritis, lower back pain or joint
             / muscle pain.

          3. Having non-malignant pain of moderate or severe intensity requiring an opioid for
             adequate analgesia (according to local label of Norspan® or Sovenor®). This is to be
             determined using BS-11 scores, where the cut-off point is ≥4.

          4. Patients with chronic uncontrolled pain and is assessed to require opioid treatment
             but have not been treated with opioids (including tramadol, morphine etc.) within 4
             weeks or more before study entry.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant and lactating females.

          2. Patients with chronic condition(s), in addition to osteoarthritis, that require(s)
             frequent analgesic treatment (e.g. frequent headaches, frequent migraine, and gout).

          3. Patients who are awaiting a scheduled operation or other surgical procedure during
             study period or 3 months or less post-operative.

          4. Prior history of being on opioids in the preceding 1 month prior to the study for the
             management of chronic non-malignant pain.

          5. Prior history of buprenorphine transdermal system use.

          6. Patients with history of allergic reactions against paracetamol/ acetaminophen,
             NSAIDs and/or opioids.

          7. Patients with allergies or other contraindications to transdermal systems or patch
             adhesives.

          8. Patients with dermatological disorders who may have problems applying patch or
             rotating patch placement area.

          9. Patients with cancer (except for basal cell carcinoma) or history of cancer who have
             been diagnosed within five years prior to the first study  visit (except for treated
             basal cell carcinoma).

         10. Patients with conditions such as brain tumour, brain injury or raised intracranial
             pressure.

         11. Patients with history of psychiatric disorder, uncontrollable epilepsy, untreated
             depression or other psychiatric disorders of a type that would make participation in
             the study an unacceptable risk to the patient.

         12. Patients with any conditions causing poor cognitive function as assessed by the
             participating physician.

         13. Patients with history of alcohol and drug abuse or patients who have demonstrated
             behaviour that suggests a dependency or drug abuse.

         14. Patients currently taking hypnotics or other central nervous system depressants that
             may pose a risk of additional central nervous system depression with study
             medication.

         15. Patients who are currently being administered monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOIs) or
             have taken MAOIs within 2 weeks before screening.

         16. Patients requiring dose titration of adjuvant analgesics i.e. antidepressants (e.g.
             amitriptyline, amoxapine, clomipremine, selective serotonin re-uptake inhibitors
             (SSRIs)) and anticonvulsants (e.g. gabapentin, pregabalin). Patients will be allowed
             to enter the study as long as they are on the stable doses of adjuvant analgesics at
             screening and do not have dose adjustments during the study.

         17. Patients who have received steroid treatment (intra-articular, intramuscular, oral,
             intravenous, epidural or other corticosteroid injections) within 6 weeks prior to
             clinical study or planned steroid treatment during the clinical study period.

         18. Patients who have to use heating facility (examples: heating lamp, electric blanket,
             sauna, warm compresses, heated saline baths, etc.).

         19. Patients who cannot or do not wish to remove hair growing at body surface where the
             patch can be placed.

         20. Patients who are currently on disability claims or in the process of applying for
             disability claims.

         21. Patients at child-bearing age who are planning to conceive a child during the study
             period and are not practicing adequate contraception.

         22. Patients with known severe hepatic impairment as determined by liver function test
             within the past one year.

         23. Patients who are currently in or have participated in other clinical trials within
             the last 30 days prior to study recruitment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Abhishek Bhagat</last_name>
    <phone>+65 6511 1167</phone>
    <email>info.rma@mundipharma.com.sg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Valerie A Leck</last_name>
    <phone>+65 6511 3681</phone>
    <email>info.rma@mundipharma.com.sg</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Samsung Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gangnam-Gu</city>
        <state>Seoul</state>
        <zip>135710</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seoul National University Hospital (Dept of Neurology)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jongno-gu</city>
        <state>Seoul</state>
        <zip>110744</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seoul National University Hospital (Dept of Orthopedics)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jongno-gu</city>
        <state>Seoul</state>
        <zip>110744</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seoul St. Mary's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seocho-gu</city>
        <state>Seoul</state>
        <zip>137701</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Severance Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seodaemun-gu</city>
        <state>Seoul</state>
        <zip>120752</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Asan Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Songpa-Gu</city>
        <state>Seoul</state>
        <zip>138736</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 30, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 7, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Norspan</keyword>
  <keyword>buprenorphine</keyword>
  <keyword>transdermal</keyword>
  <keyword>patch</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic pain</keyword>
  <keyword>non-malignant</keyword>
  <keyword>osteoarthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>rheumatoid arthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>lower back pain</keyword>
  <keyword>joint pain</keyword>
  <keyword>muscle pain</keyword>
  <keyword>opioid</keyword>
  <keyword>analgesic</keyword>
  <keyword>painkiller</keyword>
  <keyword>Mundipharma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Arthralgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Buprenorphine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
