<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="94226">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02089555</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00066145</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R21AG043885</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02089555</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>African American Alzheimer's Progression Markers - CSF and Neuro-Imaging</brief_title>
  <acronym>A3PM</acronym>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      African Americans are twice as likely to develop Alzheimer's disease as white Americans, but
      few African Americans are enrolled in large Alzheimer's biomarker studies.  The current
      proposal aims to determine the influence of Alzheimer's disease and vascular disease on
      memory and aging in African Americans through modern biomarkers (spinal fluid, MRI, and
      amyloid imaging), and how these may differ between African Americans and white Americans in
      preparation for a large multi-center study of aging in African American.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      African Americans represent about 10% of the population in the US, but are under-represented
      in biomarker-related aging studies such as the Alzheimer's Disease Neuro-imaging Initiative
      (ADNI) and World Wide ADNI.  Epidemiologic studies show that, compared to non-Hispanic white
      (NHW) Americans, African Americans (AA) are more likely to develop mild cognitive impairment
      (MCI) and Alzheimer's disease (AD), have different genetic risks of developing AD, and
      experience different rates of cognitive decline after cognitive symptoms develop.  All these
      point to the existence of an MCI/AD endophenotype for AA, although few of these
      epidemiological studies involve modern chemical or imaging biomarkers associated with AD
      pathology and progression.  Preliminary studies using AA subjects who have undergone CSF
      analysis (n=36) show that AA MCI subjects are more likely to have normal CSF AD biomarkers
      than NHW MCI subjects, yet at the same time greater hippocampal atrophy on MRI.  The
      investigators hypothesize that endothelial dysfunction is an alternate mechanism which
      independently contributes to cognitive impairment in AA subjects with sub-threshold AD
      pathology in a race-independent fashion, and endothelia dysfunction further enhances the
      neurotoxicity of AD-associated brain changes in a race-dependent fashion.  The investigators
      propose to build on their success in recruiting AA volunteers into memory and aging studies
      at the Emory's Registry for Remembrance to recruit a cross-sectional cohort of 75 AA
      subjects along with 75 NHW subjects with normal cognition, MCI, or mild AD.  They will test
      this hypothesis through two aims.  In Aim 1, they will determine whether endothelial
      dysfunctions independently contribute to cognitive decline in AA and NHW subjects by
      measuring cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) levels of AD, endothelial, and inflammatory markers.
      Each subject will also undergo MRI analysis for total area of white matter hyperintensities
      as an imaging marker of endothelial dysfunction.  Based on the hypothesis, they predict that
      AA MCI/AD subjects are more likely than NHW MCI subjects to have normal CSF AD biomarkers,
      abnormal CSF endothelial markers, and greater number and area of white matter
      hyperintensities on MRI.  In Aim 2, the investigators will determine if an endothelial
      marker - intercellular adhesion molecule 1 or ICAM-1 - gene variant unique to AA enhances AD
      neurotoxicity to explain the greater hippocampal atrophy among AA MCI subjects.  The
      Lys56Met ICAM1 gene variant associated with low ICAM-1 levels is uniquely found in 16-20% of
      AA, and these subjects may have impaired downstream activation of neprilysin, an
      Abeta-degrading enzyme.  If the hypothesis is true, AA subjects with the Lys56Met gene
      variant will be more likely to have hippocampal atrophy, temporal-parietal cerebral
      hypoperfusion, and cerebral amyloid deposition than AA subjects and NHW subjects without the
      gene variant.  This may occur in the setting of CSF Abeta2 pseudo-normalization if low
      neprilysin levels lead to increased Abeta42 levels.  Successful completion of the current
      proposal will confirm the preliminary finding of a unique AA endophenotype within the
      broader AD-spectrum disorders, directly examine whether endothelial dysfunctions additively
      and synergistically lead to cognitive decline in AD among AA in a cross-sectional cohort,
      and help power and design a future a multi-center, multi-racial longitudinal biomarker study
      to validate these cross-sectional findings.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case Control, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>CSF endothelial marker levels</measure>
    <time_frame>one time only</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>CSF Alzheimer's biomarker levels</measure>
    <time_frame>one time only</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MRI evidence of small vessel disease</measure>
    <time_frame>one time only</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MRI evidence of brain atrophy</measure>
    <time_frame>one time only</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Mild Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <condition>Alzheimer's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>African Americans</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Hispanic Whites</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Cerebrospinal fluid, plasma, and DNA will be saved.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        African American and non-Hispanic white seniors with normal cognition, mild cognitive
        impairment (MCI), or mild Alzheimer's disease.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ages 60-85.

          -  Has normal cognition, a diagnosis of mild cognitive impairment, or a diagnosis of
             Alzheimer's disease or mild cognitive impairment.

          -  Self-reported race of African American or non-Hispanic white.

          -  Able to undergo neuropsychological testing, lumbar puncture, and MRI.

          -  English speaking.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of stroke.

          -  Diagnosis of Parkinson's disease, amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, or another
             progressive neurological disorder which may spare cognition.

          -  MMSE &lt; 17
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>William Hu, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>404-727-4174</phone>
    <email>wthu@emory.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Christina Howell, BS</last_name>
    <phone>404-727-4174</phone>
    <email>jhowel4@emory.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.med.emory.edu/ADRC/</url>
    <description>Emory Alzheimer's Disease Research Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 17, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 14, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Emory University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>William Hu MD/PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Neurology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognition Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
