<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="99271">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02075658</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012-9088</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02075658</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Comparative Study Between AirSeal, an Integrated Insufflation System, and Conventional Insufflation</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Comparative Study of the Physiological Response, Between AirSeal, an Integrated Insufflation and Access System, and Conventional Insufflation and Trocars</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Irvine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Irvine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Renal cancer has traditionally been treated by surgical removal of the tumor, as the tumors
      are resistant to chemotherapy and radiation. The traditional treatment, where the entire
      kidney and tumor were removed through an abdominal incision, may now have more long term
      problems than the actual cancer. As a result, less invasive techniques have been developed
      such as laparoscopic surgery where the abdomen is inflated with carbon dioxide (i.e. via an
      insufflation system) and the surgery performed with special instruments through small ports,
      known as trocars. Rapid advances in minimally invasive surgical techniques demand ongoing
      technological improvement.

      Conventional insufflators and trocars allow for laparoscopic surgery to occur, however the
      system does not account for pressure changes within the abdomen when instruments are
      inserted or removed. The AirSeal® System consisting of an insufflation, filtration, and
      recirculation system (AirSeal® IFS), a triple lumen filtered tube set, and a valve free
      trocar (AirSeal® Access Port) has been designed to create and maintain the pressure barrier
      throughout the procedure. The objective of this study is to collect comparative
      physiological, pulmonary compliance and surgical utility data for both the AirSeal® System
      and conventional insufflators and trocars in a controlled population undergoing
      laparoscopic/robotic renal or peri-renal procedures. Subjects enrolled in this study will
      have their procedure performed using either the AirSeal® System or a conventional
      insufflator and trocars. Both systems have been cleared for use by the FDA's 510(k) process
      and are currently employed in clinical practice, including at University of California,
      Irvine Medical Center. We hypothesize that with the use of the AirSeal® System, laparoscopic
      efficiencies and outcomes will be significantly greater than with the conventional
      insufflator and trocars system.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rapid advances in minimally invasive surgical techniques demand ongoing technological
      improvement.

      The benefits of laparoscopic surgery to patient comfort and recovery have been made with
      procedures such as the cholecystectomy and gastric bypass. The AirSeal® System consists of
      an insufflation, filtration, and recirculation system (AirSeal® IFS), a triple lumen
      filtered tube set, and a valve free trocar (AirSeal® Access Port). The device enables
      peritoneal access with a novel mechanism to maintain pneumoperitoneum without a mechanical
      seal. Specifically, the AirSeal® System creates a pressure barrier within the proximal
      housing of the cannula which acts as an invisible seal to maintain pneumoperitoneum during
      the course of surgery. It utilizes a re-circulation and filtration control unit (AirSeal®
      IFS) designed specifically for the AirSeal® Access Port to create and maintain the pressure
      barrier. The AirSeal® System has applications in abdominal minimally invasive surgical
      procedures to establish a path of entry for laparoscopic instruments. The insufflation and
      recirculation system (AirSeal® IFS) is reusable and the AirSeal® Access Port and triple
      lumen filtered tube set are designed as single patient use devices. The 1st generation
      AirSeal® System received FDA 510(k) clearance in 2007 and the current system received FDA
      510(k) Clearance in May 2011. Since that time, the AirSeal™ system has been used routinely
      in centers throughout the United States and has been observed by surgeons and anesthesia
      teams to provide a more gentle, stable, and consistent pneumoperitoneum. Initial evidence of
      this has reported in the literature1. Kavoussi and colleagues state; &quot;We have found that
      patients had blunted end-tidal carbon dioxide (CO2) levels and CO2 elimination rates
      compared with the CO2 elimination rates observed in studies evaluating transperitoneal
      laparoscopy using the conventional trocar. To determine if a difference truly exists, CO2
      elimination rates must be prospectively analyzed in a head to head comparison between
      valve-less and conventional trocars.&quot; This study is designed to compare the physiological
      impact and pulmonary compliance of patients undergoing laparoscopic/robotic renal or
      peri-renal surgery with and without the AirSeal® System.

      1 A new Valve-Less Trocar for Urology Laparoscopy: Initial Evaluation. Journal of
      Endourology 2009;23: 1535-39
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AirSeal reduction in the variance of intra-abdominal pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 (Day of Procedure)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Our primary aim is to show reduction in the variance of intra-abdominal pressure throughout the operative procedure when using the AirSeal device compared to a conventional insufflator. Based on preliminary data, we assume pressures maintained at a mean of 15 through out surgery for both devices and a variance of 3.6 with the conventional insufflator.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in cardiac output with the AirSeal device.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 (Day of Procedure)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assuming cardiac output of approximately 5.0 l/min with the conventional device, we will have 96% power to detect as significant an improvement in cardiac output to 5.5 l/min using a two-group Satterwaite t-test and assuming variance of 0.25.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Renal Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Insufflation and Trocars</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects enrolled in this study arm will have their procedure performed using either the  conventional insufflator and trocars. This system have been cleared for use by the FDA's 510 (k)process and are currently employed in clinical practice, including at UC Irvine Medical Center.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AirSeal® System-Interventional</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The AirSeal® System consists of an insufflation, filtration, and recirculation system (AirSeal® IFS), a triple lumen filtered tube set, and a valve free trocar (AirSeal® Access Port).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AirSeal® System-Interventional</intervention_name>
    <description>The AirSeal® System consists of an insufflation, filtration, and recirculation system (AirSeal® IFS), a triple lumen filtered tube set, and a valve free trocar (AirSeal® Access Port). The device enables peritoneal access with a novel mechanism to maintain pneumoperitoneum without a mechanical seal.</description>
    <arm_group_label>AirSeal® System-Interventional</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional Insufflator and Trocar</intervention_name>
    <description>Conventional insufflator and trocars are used in standard procedures and will serve as the base for comparison of the study device (AirSeal® System).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Insufflation and Trocars</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Competent adult (18 years of age and older) males and females.

          2. Persons undergoing laparoscopic/robotic renal or peri-renal procedures.

        Exclusion criteria:

          1. Under age 18

          2. Unable to provide informed consent

          3. Have a history of ascites

          4. History of transplant kidney

          5. Solitary kidney (one kidney)

          6. Uncontrolled Diabetes (HbA1c &gt; 8)

          7. Pregnancy (as noted by standard of care history and physical)

          8. Women who are breast-feeding

          9. History of narcotic abuse or chronic pain

         10. Emergency Surgery

         11. Person's participating in any other research
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jaime Landman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Irvine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jamie Landman, MD</last_name>
    <phone>7144563330</phone>
    <email>landmanj@uci.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Victor Huynh, BS</last_name>
    <phone>7144568176</phone>
    <email>vbhuynh@uci.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, Irvine Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orange</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92868</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Victor Huynh</last_name>
      <phone>714-456-8176</phone>
      <email>vbhuynh@uci.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jaime Landman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 27, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 1, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Irvine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jaime Landman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Urology and Radiology Chairman, Department of Urology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>renal cell carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>minimally invasive procedures</keyword>
  <keyword>robotic nephrectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>laparoscopic nephrectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>pneumoperitoneum</keyword>
  <keyword>trocars</keyword>
  <keyword>AirSeal® IFS</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
