<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="53597">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01847131</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R015532021</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01847131</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of Oxymetazoline Added on Nasal Steroid in Rhinitis With Persistent Nasal Obstruction</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of Oxymetazoline Added on Intranasal Steroid in the Treatment of Allergic and Nonallergic Rhinitis With Persistent Nasal Obstruction</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mahidol University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mahidol University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Thailand: Ethical Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background Allergic rhinitis is a common health problem with a worldwide prevalence is
      10-25%, and poses significant impact on the quality of life of the patients. In Thailand,
      the prevalence of allergic rhinitis in the general population is 13.5%, of  which the
      frequency of allergic rhinitis increased from 23% to 38% in the children, and 61.9% in the
      graduate students. Despite intranasal steroid being the current first-line treatment of
      patients with allergic rhinitis, only 60% of patients achieve excellent control. Persistent
      nasal congestion is the major symptom which is difficult to control in these patients. Data
      are limited about efficacy and safety of the additional use of 0.05% intranasal
      oxymetazoline hydrochloride (OXY) for persistent nasal congestion that does not adequately
      respond to recommended doses of intranasal steroid (INS) and oral antihistamine(OAH).

      Objective To determine the efficacy and safety of the additional use of OXY for persistent
      nasal congestion in allergic rhinitis or non-allergic rhinitis patients inadequately
      controlled by combination treatment with INS and OAH.

      Methods The investigators performed a 4-week, randomized, double blind, placebo controlled,
      clinical trial in 50 patients with allergic rhinitis or non-allergic rhinitis whom
      inadequately controlled by combination treatment with INS and oral antihistamine (OAH).
      After an initial screening, qualified individuals were randomized into 2 groups including
      the treatment group and the control group. The treatment group received the INS (2 puffs in
      each nostril twice daily) and OAH (1 tablet once daily) plus OXY (2 puffs in each nostril
      twice daily) The control group received INS (2 puffs in each nostril twice daily) and OAH (1
      tablet once daily) plus placebo (2 puffs in each nostril twice daily).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      All participants will continue medications for 4 weeks, then stop using interventional
      medication. Two weeks afterward, all participants will come for the last visit to see
      whether rebound nasal symptoms occur. Participants will be asked to record nasal symptom
      diary card, and nasal peak inspiratory flow. Qol questionnaire will be recorded during
      visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effectiveness and safety of oxymetazoline in the treatment of rhinitis with persistent nasal obstruction</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Primary outcome measure is the percentage of rhinitis patients who have improved nasal congestion score measuring by visual analog scale (VAS)compared between treatment group and controlled group. We also give patients Incheck peak inspiratory peak flow meter to measure and record nasal peak inspiratory flow (NPIF) daily which is an objective parameter for nasal congestion. Furthermore the quality of life questionnaire (RCQ36), a validated questionnaire, will be used to measure Qol score prior to start the study and every follow-up visit. During follow-up visits, patients will be asked for any possible adverse effects and events of the study medication and thorough physical examination including blood pressure measurement will be performed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of rhinitis medicamentosa after using oxymetazoline</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Rhinitis medicamentosa is the rebound nasal congestion after prolonged use (&gt;7 days) of topical nasal decongestant (eg. oxymetazoline). However, a previous study by Baroody FM et al (J Allergy Clin Immunol 2011;127:927-34) showed that using oxymetazoline together with intranasal steroid for 1 month did not increase rhinitis medicamentosa compared to placebo. So we give rhinitis patients in the treatment group with oxymetazoline and intranasal steroid for 1 month, then stop using oxymetazoline and come back for the last visit 2 weeks later to see whether patients develop rebound nasal congestion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Nasal Obstruction Present Finding</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>oxymetazoline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>0.05% oxymetazoline nasal sprays 2 sprays in each nostril twice daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>placebo nasal spray 2 sprays in each nostril twice daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>oxymetazoline</intervention_name>
    <description>0.05% Oxymetazoline nasal sprays were commercially available.</description>
    <arm_group_label>oxymetazoline</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Iliadin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo nasal spray</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo nasal spray has made by the local pharmaceutical company in thailand who commercially manufacture and sell 0.05% oxymetazoline nasal spray. The placebo contains the same ingredients as the drug except the active ingredient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient 18 years of age or greater

          -  Diagnosis with allergic or nonallergic rhinitis with persistent nasal obstruction

          -  Being treated with intranasal steroid and oral antihistamine

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Underlying disease of hypertension

          -  Use oral or nasal decongestant 7 days prior to entering the study

          -  Nasal polyp or significant deviated nasal septum

          -  Respiratory tract infection 14 days prior to entering the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Torpong Thongngarm, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mahidol University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Panitan Pradubpongsa, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Mahidol University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paraya Assanasen, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Mahidol University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Faculty of Medicine Siriraj Hospital, Mahidol University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangkok</city>
        <zip>10700</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Thailand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 1, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 14, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Rhinitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Oxymetazoline</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Nasal Obstruction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rhinitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Oxymetazoline</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Phenylephrine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
