<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="84123">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02096549</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>YUH-14-0319-O10</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02096549</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Validity of Bispectral Index Monitoring During Deep Sedation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Validity of Bispectral Index Monitoring During Deep Sedation for Botulinum Toxin Injection in Children With Cerebral Palsy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yeungnam University College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Yeungnam University College of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Korea: Ministry of Food and Drug Safety</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      During Intramuscular botulinum toxin injections for children with cerebral palsy, immobility
      is essential to inject botulinum toxin to the right muscle. Because children with cerebral
      palsy are generally unable to control their movement, deep sedation is required during this
      painful procedure.

      Short-acting drugs such as propofol and remifentanil are widely used for pediatric
      anesthesia and sedation but still have possibility of over-sedation and associated
      complications due to their rather narrow therapeutic window. Therefore, objective scoring
      system to assess the level of sedation to provide an effective and safe sedation in
      children. Bispectral index (BIS) monitoring,an objective guidance of sedation might be
      helpful.

      The present study is to investigate the validity of the BIS monitoring during deep sedation
      of children with cerebral palsy for injection of botulinum toxin.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Intramuscular botulinum toxin injections for children with cerebral palsy have been
      extensively performed to relive spasticity and improve rehabilitation. During procedure
      immobility is essential to inject botulinum toxin to the right muscle for optimal effect.
      Because children with cerebral palsy are generally unable to control their movement, deep
      sedation is required during this painful procedure.

      Short-acting drugs with rapid, predictable onset and offset of action, such as propofol and
      remifentanil, facilitate infusion rate adjustments and rapid recovery. However, there is
      always the possibility of over-sedation, hypotension and respiratory depression due to their
      rather narrow therapeutic window.

      Several clinical sedation scales have been used to provide an effective and safe sedation in
      children. Because clinical scoring depends on patient response to verbal or physical
      stimulation, it is difficult to assess the level of sedatin in patients with deep sedation
      during delicate phase of the procedure. Bispectral index (BIS) monitoring,an objective
      guidance of sedation might be helpful. Although BIS scores in children with conscious and
      deep sedation were reported to correlate with clinical sedation scales, the validity during
      painful procedure in children with cerebral palsy was not investigated yet.

      The present study is to investigate the validity of the BIS monitoring and its correlation
      to University of Michigan sedation scale  during deep sedation of children with cerebral
      palsy for injection of botulinum toxin.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>bispectral index score at deep sedation after injection of propofol</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline(on arrival in operating room), 15 seconds after achivement of deep sedation ( University of Michigan sedation scale (UMSS) 4) after injection of propofol(</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>deep sedation is defined by a depression of consciousness during which patients cannot be easily aroused but respond purposefully after repeated verbal or painful stimulation (e.g., purposefully pushing away the noxious stimuli).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>purposeful withdrawal in response to significant physical stimulation (Trapezius squeeze)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 10 min after injection of propofol</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>deep sedation is defined by a depression of consciousness during which patients cannot be easily aroused but respond purposefully after repeated verbal or painful stimulation (e.g., purposefully pushing away the noxious stimuli).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oxygen saturation (sPO2(%))</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 10 min after injection of propofol</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>1deep sedation is defined by a depression of consciousness during which patients cannot be easily aroused but respond purposefully after repeated verbal or painful stimulation (e.g., purposefully pushing away the noxious stimuli).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebral Palsy</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        primary care clinic (rehabilitation)
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) physical status I-II healthy children
             Ages Eligible for study: 3 to 18 years scheduled for injection of botulinum toxin
             under deep sedation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unstable cardiac disease Recent (&lt; 8 week) pneumonia, bronchitis, asthma attack,
             respiratory infection Craniofacial defect History of a difficult airway management
             Hypotonia and lack of head control Tremors
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sung Mee Jung, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+82-53-620-3368</phone>
    <email>applejsm@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Hyo Eun Kang, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+82-53-620-3166</phone>
    <email>fhssm12@naver.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yeungnam University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Daegu</city>
        <zip>705-717</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jong Won Park, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+82-53-620-8001</phone>
      <email>1203204@edms.yu.ac.kr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>McDermott NB, VanSickle T, Motas D, Friesen RH. Validation of the bispectral index monitor during conscious and deep sedation in children. Anesth Analg. 2003 Jul;97(1):39-43, table of contents.</citation>
    <PMID>12818940</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Soudant DL, Staal HM, Witlox AM, Vles JS. Conscious sedation or general anaesthetic for intramuscular botulinum toxin injections in children - a two centre cross-sectional prospective audit. Eur J Paediatr Neurol. 2013 Mar;17(2):219-20. doi: 10.1016/j.ejpn.2012.06.012. Epub 2012 Aug 4.</citation>
    <PMID>22871256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>American Academy of Pediatrics; American Academy of Pediatric Dentistry, Coté CJ, Wilson S; Work Group on Sedation. Guidelines for monitoring and management of pediatric patients during and after sedation for diagnostic and therapeutic procedures: an update. Paediatr Anaesth. 2008 Jan;18(1):9-10.</citation>
    <PMID>18095958</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 28, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 17, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Yeungnam University College of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sung Mee Jung</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate professor in Anesthesiology and Pain Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cerebral palsy</keyword>
  <keyword>Botulinum toxin</keyword>
  <keyword>Propofol</keyword>
  <keyword>Deep sedation</keyword>
  <keyword>Bispectral index monitor</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Palsy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paralysis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Botulinum Toxins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
