<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="6674">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02063503</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>B300201215600</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02063503</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Development of Clinical Prediction Rules for Rehabilitation in Chronic Nonspecific Low Back Pain Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Development of Clinical Prediction Rules for Rehabilitation in Chronic Nonspecific Low Back Pain Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universiteit Antwerpen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Universitair Ziekenhuis Antwerpen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universiteit Antwerpen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Belgium: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project concerns the rehabilitation of nonspecific chronic low back pain patients
      (CLBP), in particular conservative rehabilitation by means of exercise therapy. Exercise
      therapy covers a broad spectrum of different kind of therapy approaches in daily practice.
      For example stabilization therapy, isometric muscle training, general exercises to improve
      general fitness... In the European guidelines  and the Belgian report on chronic low back
      pain of the &quot;Federaal Kenniscentrum voor de gezondheidszorg (KCE)&quot; supervised exercise
      therapy and multidisciplinary rehabilitation (bio-psycho-social) are recommended, due to the
      high level of evidence. The content or type of exercises are not specified. An important
      recommendation of the European guideline is the need for development of tools to improve the
      classification and identification of specific clinical sub-groups of low back pain patients
      to determine the effectiveness of specific exercise interventions.

      Consequently, we will investigate three active rehabilitation approaches for back pain:
      stabilization therapy, general active exercise therapy and isometric training devices, well
      known in Flanders and described in international peer reviewed journals. For each type of
      exercise therapy a clinical prediction rule (CPR) will be determined. Recent systematic
      reviews show the lack of CPR for exercise therapy in low back pain patients. The methodology
      to develop a validated and applicable CPR contains 3 different phases: 1. derivation phase,
      2. validation phase, 3. impact phase.

      Phase 2: validation phase. The CPR will be applied in a new but comparable test group to
      confirm findings of phase. The RCT design with 3 treatment groups (stabilization therapy/
      general active exercise therapy/ isometric training devices) that was accomplished in phase
      1 will be repeated. The prediction rule will be applied after at random assignment of the
      patients to an intervention group. Within each intervention group treatment success will be
      compared between &quot;matched treatment subgroup&quot; and &quot;unmatched treatment subgroup&quot; according
      to the phase 1 prediction rules for each of the three intervention types.

      Phase 3: Impact analysis. Patient satisfaction will be analyzed (SF36, patient satisfaction
      questionnaire, return to work). Work field will be informed on completed CPR and changes in
      therapists behavior will be evaluated.

      Our scientific goal is to:  Develop a validated CPR that is applicable in nonspecific CLBP
      resulting in a better choice of active rehabilitation  therapy, tailor fit for each
      individual patient.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      State of the art:

        1. Efficacy of active rehabilitation  in chronic low back pain (CLBP): Conclusion: There
           is strong evidence that active rehabilitation  is more effective than general
           practitioner care for the reduction of pain and disability and return to work in at
           least the mid-term (3-6 months) (level A of evidence). Little consensus has been
           reached on the type of exercises. The conclusion in most RCT's is that there is need
           for identifying specific subgroups of patients to determine effectiveness of specific
           exercise interventions.

        2. Existing clinical prediction rule (CPR) for active rehabilitation  in LBP patients: A
           systematic review of Haskins et al, published in 2012 describes 23 studies on clinical
           prediction rules in low back pain patients. Of those 23 studies only two handled the
           development of clinical prediction rules for active rehabilitation in low back pain
           patients. One of those two was on a McKenzie approach, which is not our point of
           interest. Secondly Hicks et al developed two preliminary clinical prediction rules in
           recurrent LBP patients, one for success of stabilization therapy and a second for the
           absence of success (no success) of stabilization therapy. In the study of Hicks a
           Multivariate regression analysis resulted in 4 prediction factors for success with
           therapy. Presence of 3 or more of the predicting factors leads to a positive LR of 4,0
           (95CI: 1,6 - 10,0) and increases the chance of success with stabilization therapy from
           33% pre-test to 67% post-test. Secondly 4 predicting factors for no success with
           stabilization therapy were detected. Presence of 2 or more predicting factors leads to
           a negative LR of 0,18 (95%CI: 0,08 - 0,38). These existing CPR are only useful when
           they lead to better therapy outcome. Brennan et al. investigated the application of the
           Hicks prediction rule in 123 acute and sub acute nonspecific LBP patients. The
           conclusion of the study was that patients who were assigned to the correct therapy
           group showed significant larger improvement on the Oswestry Disability Questionnaire
           compared to the control patients. This difference was measured 4 weeks after finishing
           the therapy as well as in a one year follow up.

      Added value to the current knowledge/state-of-the-art:

      Up till this moment the CPR for stabilization therapy is developed by a single arm
      intervention study. It should be repeated in an RCT design to confirm and reinforce
      findings. Besides stabilization therapy, general exercise therapy and/or isometric training
      devices are used in back rehabilitation in Flanders. RCT's that compare these different kind
      of interventions using a between group analysis don't find a difference in effectiveness.
      They conclude that the heterogeneity of the population is responsible for this &quot;wash out
      effect&quot;. Therefore it is important to create a CPR not only for the stabilization group but
      also for other commonly used exercise therapies.

      Primary objectives:

      Our scientific objectives to be reached within the 42-month period are to obtain clear and
      reliable answers on the following questions:

        -  Can we determine prognostic indicators for &quot;success&quot; and for &quot;no success&quot; for applying
           a specific form of active rehabilitation  (stabilization therapy or general exercise
           therapy or isometric training devices)?

        -  Can we validate our findings by repeating the intervention trial and applying the
           drafted CPR?

        -  Does the use of the CPR lead to increased patient satisfactory?

        -  Will the instruction of the new CPR lead to changes in clinician behavior of (a sample)
           therapists in Flanders?

      Secondary objectives:

        -  Are the CPR for the 3 types of active rehabilitation  diverse?

        -  Is there a domain within the ICF framework that is more relevant in predicting therapy
           outcome?

        -  Can we determine with a baseline measurement which patients are therapy resistant for
           an intervention program containing an active rehabilitation ?

        -  Can we determine prognostic factors for recurrence of low back pain within one year
           after entering the revalidation program?

      Utilisation of the project:

      Number of patients with chronic low back pain:

      Low Back Pain (LBP) can be considered as epidemic. The European Guidelines mention a
      lifetime prevalence of low back pain of 84%. About 5 to 10% of LBP patients develop chronic
      low back pain (CLBP), 85% of these patients have non-specific low back pain. According to
      the latest  report on chronic low back pain of the &quot;Federaal Kenniscentrum voor de
      gezondheidszorg (KCE)&quot; 5% of all consultations of a general practitioner are low back pain
      patients. One out of four people between 18 and 75 years old has consulted the general
      practitioner the last 10 years.

      Overview of different scientific steps of the project:

      I.Preparation:

      First 3 months will be spend at operationalising working processes. For example training the
      testers and treaters of the patients. This will be coordinated by the project leader. We
      already have performed a pilot study and know the organizational pitfalls, most frequently
      asked questions by patients and referring doctors. These have to be approached in order to
      have an optimal work environment for this project.

      II. Phase 1:

        1. In and exclusion criteria subjects:

           Patients are recruited by the doctors at the service of physical medicine UZA.

           Inclusion criteria:

           &gt; 3 months low back pain LRP, consulted a medical doctor because of the persistent low
           back pain the last month, age between 18 and 60.

           Exclusion criteria :

           Vestibulare dysfunction, spine fractures, spondylolysis and spondylolisthesis,
           radiating pain below the knee, muscle-, nerve-, skin-, or joint diseases, pregnancy

        2. Power analysis:

           A pilot study shows that the standard deviation of our primary outcome measure, the
           Oswestry score, is comparable to the results of Brennan et al. Given these estimates,
           120 patients should suffice to detect a minimum clinically important difference of 6
           points on the Oswestry (effect size _ 0.43) with 80% power using a two-tailed
           hypothesis.

           This means that in total 3 X 40 patients should complete the whole trial. Based on Van
           der wouden et al. we know that we can expect a drop out of 54% of the patients during
           the whole process. This means that initially 260 patients should be included.

           Each year 300 patients enter the multidisciplinary back revalidation program
           (containing amongst other 30 physiotherapy sessions) at the University hospital of
           Antwerp. About 220 patients enter the polyclinic because of low back pain receiving
           between 1 and 18 sessions of physiotherapy.

        3. Information form and informed consent After evaluation of in- and exclusion criteria we
           will inform the patient about the trial. Information form and informed consent are made
           and have been approved by the ethics committee of the UZA.

        4. Baseline testing:

           As primary outcome measure (dependant variable) the Oswestry Disability Questionnaire
           is used. This variable is reliable, valid and responsive.

           As secondary outcome measures (independent variables) the following tests are used:

           - Measurement of impairments: Duration of the LBP, prone instability test, Straight Leg
           Raise, Beighton scale, Active Straight Leg Raise, sitting knee extension test, waiters
           bow, pelvic tilt, side support test, extensor endurance test, active sit-up, active ROM
           (3D motion analysis), isometric strength (Tergumed), visual analogue scale for pain,
           evaluation of postural control

           - Measurement of limitations in activities and participation: SF36, hours of physical
           activity/week.

           - Measurement of contextual factors: Tampa scale for kinesiophobia, Fear avoidance
           belief questionnaire, age, weight, smoking, comorbidity

        5. Randomisation After baseline testing patients will be assigned to one of the three
           treatment groups ad random. Randomization will be done by a computer. The tester will
           be aware of the treatment group of the patient. The practitioners who give treatments
           are blinded for the baseline and follow-up measurements.

        6. Intervention

             -  Specific stabilization therapy: The participants in this group follow specific
                stabilization training based on the work by Richardson et al. The treatment will
                be given by two trained physiotherapists. To make sure all therapists will give
                the same exercises a protocol is set up and a treatment diary will be filled in
                during each session. Patients will receive 2 treatment every week during 9
                following weeks.

             -  General active exercise therapy: These participants receive a global form of
                exercise therapy existing of all kinds of active exercises that do not have the
                direct purpose of contracting the m. multifidii or m. transversus abdominis. In
                general the active therapy consists of:1.warming up (home trainer) 2.aerobe
                conditioning exercises for lower and upper limbs, strength training of the back-
                and abdominal muscles and advice in relation to their complaints. 3. Cooling down
                (hometrainer + stretching). To make sure all therapists will give the same
                exercises a protocol is set up and a treatment diary will be filled in during each
                session. Patients will receive 2 treatment every week during 9 following weeks.

             -  Isometric training devices: Tergumed protocol is followed. It contains progressive
                resistance isometric training of trunk muscles on devices  in following
                directions: flexion, extension, rotation and lateral flexion.

        7. Retesting and follow-up:

           Retesting will take place after finishing the treatment program at 9 weeks. All
           independent and dependent variables of the baseline testing will be measured.

           Follow-up: at 6 months and 1 year after entering the study the dependent variable will
           be measured. The patients will be contacted by mail initially and by phone if they
           don't respond to the mail within 2 weeks.

        8. Data analysis:  We will search for predictors for &quot;success&quot; and &quot;no success&quot; for the
           three types of active rehabilitation exercises (stabilization therapy/ general active
           exercise therapy/ isometric training devices). First an univariate regression analysis
           will select potential predictors. Secondly these predictors will be entered in a
           multivariate regression analysis.Since the dependant variable is continuous (the
           Oswestry Disability Index), a linear regression analysis will be used. First the
           predictors determined in the study of Hicks et al. are entered in the analysis. When
           discrete variables are entered in the multivariate analysis the Oswestry score will be
           dichotomized (responders/ non responders) and a logistic regression analysis will be
           used. A mediator analysis as described by Baron and Kenny and Preacher and Hayes will
           be used to examine why the dependant variable is influenced by one or more independent
           variables. Consecutive regression analysis are performed, this calculates the effect of
           a variable (mediator) on the relation between two other variables. When more than one
           mediator is determined a multiple mediator model can be calculated.

      III.Phase 2:

      In Phase 2 we will investigate validation of the prediction rules determined in phase 1.
      Again we will work according to procedure of phase 1 (see steps 1- 7 above).

      Step 8: data analysis will be different: Using the baseline measurements the CPR determined
      in phase 1 of our research will be applied to divide each treatment group into 2 subgroups:
      &quot;matched therapy&quot; vs &quot;unmatched therapy&quot;. The patients that are assigned to an intervention
      group that according to the CPR is not the best suitable therapy (unmatched) are considered
      as control patients. The patients that are assigned to an intervention group that according
      to the CPR is indeed the best suitable therapy are considered as test patients (matched).
      Baseline variables will be compared between groups using an anova, Kruskall Wallis, or chi2
      tests of independence based on the nature of the data. To examine the principle hypothesis
      of phase 2 development op the CPR, a three-way repeated- measures analysis of variance will
      be performed with treatment group (stabilization vs. general exercise vs. isometric
      training) and classification subgroup (stabilization vs. general exercise vs. isometric
      training) as between-subject variables and time (baseline, 9 weeks, 6 months and 1 year) as
      the within-subject variable. The dependent variable is disability (Oswestry score). The
      hypothesis of interest is the three-way interaction, and the two-way interactions between
      time and treatment group, and between time and classification subgroup. We hypothesize that
      outcome over time will not differ based on the randomized treatment group, or the
      classification subgroup, but will depend on the interaction between the treatment group and
      classification subgroup, such that patients randomized to treatment matched to the subgroup
      will have better outcomes than patients randomized to an unmatched treatment. This
      hypothesis will be supported if the three-way interaction is significant, but the two-way
      interactions are not. Pairwise post hoc comparisons will be performed at each follow-up
      period to further explore any significant interaction terms.

      IV.Phase 3:

      The goals of phase 3 of this project are: Analyze patient satisfactory, inform work field on
      completed CPR, evaluate change in therapists behavior.

        1. Patient satisfaction: During phase 1 and 2 we will evaluate patient satisfactory
           concerning the applied treatment at the retest moment at 9 weeks. Patient satisfaction
           will be based on 3 outcome measures: 1. the SF36 and 2. Return to work and 3. A patient
           satisfaction questionnaire. An ordinal 5 point Likert scale for following items will be
           used: 1 Overall quality, 2 Humanness, 3 Competence, 4 Outcome, 5 Facilities, 6
           Continuity of care, 7 Access, 8 Informativeness, 9 Cost, 10 Bureaucracy, 11 Attention
           to psychosocial problems (based on Verbeek et al). A comparison will be made between
           matched subgroup (patients that are assigned to a treatment group that according to the
           CPR is the best suitable therapy) and unmatched subgroup (patients that are assigned to
           a treatment group that according to the CPR is not the best suitable therapy).

        2. Inform work field on prediction rules and changes evaluate therapists behavior: We will
           organize courses at the end of phase 2 of this project to inform clinicians about the
           CPR. This will be done at the University of Antwerp, at the University Hospital of
           Antwerp and we will candidate to give lectures at local physiotherapy associations. At
           the end of these courses (T0) we will inform the participants on the survey on changes
           in therapists behavior after introduction of the CPR. We will hand out information form
           and informed consent. Volunteers will leave their contact information (mail, telephone
           number) on the informed consent. After 3 (T3) and 6 (T6) months we will contact the
           clinicians who volunteered and evaluate changes in therapists behavior between T0 and
           T3 and T6 using an online survey. Following items will be inventoried: baseline testing
           according to CPR, change in choice of exercise program based on CPR, usability, change
           in number of consultations of the nonspecific CLBP due to CPR.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of functional disability</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Oswestry Low Back Pain Disability Questionnaire: the patient questionnaire contains topics concerning intensity of pain, lifting, ability to care for oneself, ability to walk, ability to sit, sexual function, ability to stand, social life, sleep quality, and ability to travel. Each topic category is followed by 6 statements describing different potential scenarios in the patient's life relating to the topic. Zero is equated with no disability and 100 being maximum disability.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of impairments</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Duration of the LBP, prone instability test, Straight Leg Raise, Beighton scale, Active Straight Leg Raise, sitting knee extension test, waiters bow, pelvic tilt, side support test, extensor endurance test, active sit-up, active ROM (3D motion analysis), isometric strength (Tergumed), visual analogue scale for pain, evaluation of postural control.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of limitations in activities and participation</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>SF36, hours of physical activity/week</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of contextual factors</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Tampa scale for kinesiophobia, Fear avoidance belief questionnaire, age, weight, smoking, comorbidity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Low Back Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Specific stabilization therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>2 treatments every week during 9 consecutive weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>General active exercise therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>2 treatments every week during 9 consecutive weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Isometric training devices</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>2 treatments every week during 9 consecutive weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>physiotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>every group receives 2 treatments every week during 9 consecutive weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Specific stabilization therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>General active exercise therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Isometric training devices</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>- Specific stabilization therapy</other_name>
    <other_name>- general active exercise therapy</other_name>
    <other_name>- isometric training devices</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  at least 3 months low back pain

          -  consulted a medical doctor during last month because of persistent low back pain

          -  age between 18 - 60

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  vestibular dysfunction

          -  a history of known spinal fractures

          -  spondylolysis and spondylolisthesis

          -  radiating pain below the knee

          -  muscle, nerve, skin, joint diseases

          -  pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ulrike Van Daele, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Universiteit Antwerpen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gaetane Stassijns, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Universiteit Antwerpen, Universitair Ziekenhuis Antwerpen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lenie Denteneer, Principal investigator</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universiteit Antwerpen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lenie Denteneer, Principal investigator</last_name>
    <phone>0032494884189</phone>
    <email>lenie.denteneer@uantwerpen.be</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ulrike Van Daele, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>003236418265</phone>
    <email>ulrike.vandaele@uantwerpen.be</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitair Ziekenhuis Antwerpen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edegem</city>
        <state>Antwerpen</state>
        <zip>2650</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lenie Denteneer, Dra, Pt</last_name>
      <phone>0032494884189</phone>
      <email>lenie.denteneer@uantwerpen.be</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ulrike Van Daele, Professor, Dr, Pt, Mt</last_name>
      <phone>003236418265</phone>
      <email>ulrike.vandaele@uantwerpen.be</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lenie Denteneer, Dra, Pt</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.uantwerp.be</url>
    <description>official website of the University of Antwerp</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 12, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 10, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universiteit Antwerpen</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Denteneer Lenie</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dra. Denteneer Lenie</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>clinical prediction rule</keyword>
  <keyword>nonspecific</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic</keyword>
  <keyword>low back pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Non specific chronic low back pain</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
