<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="45349">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02060526</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HGT-SAN-093</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-003450-24</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02060526</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Randomized, Controlled, Open-label, Multicenter, Safety and Efficacy Study of rhHNS Administration Via an IDDD in Pediatric Patients With Early Stage MPS IIIA Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Controlled, Open-label, Multicenter, Phase IIb Safety and Efficacy Study of rhHNS (Recombinant Human Heparan N Sulfatase) Administration Via an Intrathecal Drug Delivery Device in Pediatric Patients With Early Stage Mucopolysaccharidosis Type IIIA Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shire</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>PPD</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shire</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>France: Agence Nationale de Sécurité du Médicament et des produits de santé</authority>
    <authority>Netherlands: Medicines Evaluation Board (MEB)</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Agencia Española de Medicamentos y Productos Sanitarios</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Sanfilippo syndrome Type A, or Mucopolysaccharidosis (MPS) IIIA, is a rare lysosomal storage
      disease caused by deficiency of the enzyme heparan N-sulfatase (sulfamidase). In the absence
      of this enzyme, there is an accumulation of the glycosaminoglycan, heparan sulfate,
      resulting in progressive neurodegeneration. Symptoms are usually first noted in the 1st or
      2nd year of life, although definitive diagnosis is often delayed, with an average age of
      diagnosis of 4.5 years. The disease is characterized by developmental delays initially,
      followed by neurological developmental arrest, then regression. These developmental deficits
      are typically associated with severe behavioral disturbances. Patients have a significantly
      reduced lifespan, with few surviving beyond the 2nd or 3rd decade.

      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety and efficacy of recombinant human
      heparan-N-sulfatase (rhHNS) in pediatric patients with Early Stage Mucopolysaccharidosis
      Type III A Disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      No effective, disease-modifying therapies are currently approved as treatments for this
      devastating and disabling disease.

      Shire Human Genetic Therapies (Shire HGT) is developing an enzyme replacement therapy (ERT)
      recombinant human heparan-N-sulfatase (rhHNS) for patients with MPS IIIA. rhHNS is being
      administered into the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) via an surgically implanted intrathecal drug
      delivery device (IDDD), because when administered intravenously (IV) it does not cross the
      blood brain barrier (BBB).

      This study will evaluate the effect of 48 weeks of rhHNS treatment on the clinical course of
      MPS IIIA, using cognitive function as the primary outcome measure. The trial will evaluate 2
      dosing regimens of rhHNS administered via an IDDD in comparison with a no treatment control
      group. Patients will be randomized 1:1:1 to either of the treatment groups or the no
      treatment group. Treatment will be administered in an open-label manner. The safety and
      tolerability profile of rhHNS will continue to be evaluated in this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>A maximum decline in DQ (Developmental Quotient) of 10 points over 48 weeks, assessed by neurocognitive testing</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 48</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of serious adverse events (SAE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 48</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of treatment emergent adverse events (TEAE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 48</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-rhHNS Antibody Status in serum</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 48</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The change from baseline in adaptive behavioral function, assessed by  neurocognitive tests</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 48</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The change from baseline in the DQ assessed by neurocognitive tests</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 48</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The change from baseline in total cortical grey matter volume</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 48</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The change from baseline in concentration of GAG in CSF</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 48</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The change from baseline in concentration of GAG in urine</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 48</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The concentration of rhHNS in CSF</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 48</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The concentration of rhHNS in serum</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 48</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Mps III A</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>45 mg Q2W</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>rhHNS 45 mg administered intrathecally Q2W (once every 2 weeks ie, every 14 days), for 48 weeks via the surgically implanted IDDD (or LP)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>45 mg Q4W</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>rhHNS 45 mg administered intrathecally Q4W (once every 4 weeks ie, every 28 days), for 48 weeks via the surgically implanted IDDD (or LP)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Comparator group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The comparator group will receive no treatment with rhHNS.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Recombinant human heparan N-sulfatase [rhHNS]</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>45 mg Q2W</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>45 mg Q4W</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Each patient must meet the following criteria to be enrolled in this study.

          1. Documented MPS IIIA diagnosis

          2. Age ≥12 months and ≤48 months

          3. The patient has a DQ score ≥60%

          4. The patient is medically stable, in the opinion of the Investigator, and able to
             accommodate the protocol requirements, including travel, assessments, and IDDD
             surgery, without placing an undue burden on the patient/patient's family

          5. The patient's parent(s) or legally authorized representative(s) must have voluntarily
             signed and dated an Independent Ethics Committee-approved informed consent form after
             all relevant aspects of the study have been explained and discussed with the
             patient's parent(s), or legally authorized representative(s). Consent of the
             patient's parent(s) or legally authorized representative(s) must be obtained prior to
             the start of any study procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patients who meet any of the following criteria will be excluded from the study.

          1. The presence of significant non-MPS IIIA related CNS impairment or behavioral
             disturbances that would confound the scientific integrity or interpretation of study
             assessments, as determined by the Investigator.

          2. The presence of at least one S298P mutation in SGSH, associated with attenuated
             disease OR there is documentation of the S298P mutation in a sibling affected by MPS
             IIIA, provided parental consent is obtained to use this information.

          3. The presence of relatively attenuated MPS IIIA disease in an older sibling, defined
             as preservation of any speech beyond the age of 10 years.

          4. Visual or hearing impairment sufficient, in the clinical judgment of the
             investigator, to preclude cooperation with neurodevelopmental testing. Use of hearing
             aids is permitted.

          5. In the opinion of the Investigator, the patient is assessed as having an unacceptably
             high risk for anesthesia due to airway compromise, drug hypersensitivity, or other
             conditions (such as neuroleptic malignant syndrome, malignant hyperthermia, or other
             anesthesia-related concerns).

          6. The patient has a history of poorly controlled seizure disorder.

          7. The patient is currently receiving psychotropic or other medications, which in the
             Investigator's opinion would be likely to substantially confound test results.

          8. The patient has a history of bleeding disorder or is unable to abstain from
             medications that, in the opinion of the investigator, place them at risk of bleeding
             following surgery or LP.

          9. The patient participated in a clinical trial of another investigational medicinal
             product, within the 30 days prior to the study (or within 5 elimination half lives of
             the investigational product), or is currently enrolled in another study that involves
             an investigational drug or device. NOTE: Nutritional supplements, including genistein
             are permitted if they are taken or administered outside the context of a formal
             investigation.

         10. The patient has received a hematopoietic stem cell or bone marrow transplant, or gene
             therapy.

         11. The patient has a condition that is contraindicated as described in the SOPH-A-PORT
             Mini S-IDDD

         12. The patient's parent(s) or patient's legally authorized representative(s) is/are
             unable to understand the nature, scope, and possible consequences of the study, or
             do/does not agree to comply with the protocol defined schedule of assessments.

         13. The patient is unable to comply with the protocol (eg, has a clinically relevant
             medical condition making implementation of the protocol difficult, unstable social
             situation, or otherwise unlikely to complete the study) or is, in the opinion of the
             Investigator, otherwise unsuited for the study.

         14. The patient has any item (braces, tattoos, etc.) which would exclude the patient from
             being able to undergo MRI according to local Institutional Policy, or the patient has
             any other situation that would exclude the patient from undergoing any other
             procedure required in this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>48 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patrick Haslett, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Shire Human Genetic Therapies, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>MedInfo UK</last_name>
    <phone>+44 (0) 800 055 6614</phone>
    <email>HGTmedcomm@shire.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>MedInfo US &amp; Canada</last_name>
    <phone>1-866-888-0660</phone>
    <email>US_ShireHGT_Medicalinformation@shire.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Bicêtre-Paris Sud</name>
      <address>
        <city>Le Kremlin-Bicêtre</city>
        <state>Paris</state>
        <zip>94270</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Hamburg Eppendorf</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>20246</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pediatrician for Metabolic Diseases, Academic Medical Center (AMC)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <zip>22660</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Servei de Neurologia Pediàtrica</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08035</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Great Ormond Street Hospital for Children</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>WC1N 3JH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 17, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 10, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sanfilippo Syndrome Type A (Sanfilippo A)</keyword>
  <keyword>Hunter's Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>recombinant human heparan N-sulfatase (rhHNS)</keyword>
  <keyword>Lysosomal Storage Disease (LSD)</keyword>
  <keyword>enzyme replacement therapy (ERT)</keyword>
  <keyword>sulfoglucosamine sulfohydrolase (SGSH)</keyword>
  <keyword>Shire HGT</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Mucopolysaccharidoses</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mucopolysaccharidosis III</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
