<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="82120">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01671748</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-SUR-5323</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01671748</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MIST Ultrasound Therapy Compared to UK Standard Care for the Treatment of Non-healing Venous Leg Ulcers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pragmatic Randomised Controlled Trial of MIST Ultrasound Therapy Compared to UK Standard Care for the Treatment of Non-healing Venous Leg Ulcers.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cardiff and Vale University Health Board</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Celleration, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cardiff and Vale University Health Board</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: National Health Service</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chronic venous leg ulcers (VLUs) impact negatively on patients' quality of life. Standard
      treatment in the UK for patients with VLUs is compression bandaging or stockings. The MIST
      ultrasound system is a noncontact device which delivers low frequency ultrasound through a
      gentle saline mist directed at a patient's wound. This study aims to determine whether the
      use of the MIST device used in combination with standard treatments can improve healing of
      VLUs compared to UK standard practice. This will be assessed by measuring any reduction in
      wound size in the two groups after receiving 8 weeks of either Standard Care once a week or
      MIST combined with Standard Care three times a week.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Venous leg ulcers (VLUs) are wounds which are often chronic and difficult to heal. VLUs
      affect between 1 and 3.2 people per 1000; they cause pain, reduced mobility and impact
      negatively on patients' quality of life (QoL). Standard treatment for patients with VLUs is
      the application of strong, sustained compression with bandages or stockings. This
      pragmatically-designed study aims to determine whether the use of a device called MIST used
      in combination with standard treatments can improve healing of VLUs compared to UK standard
      practice. It will also show whether the MIST regimen improves participants' QoL and reduces
      the incidence of infection.

      The MIST ultrasound system is a non-contact device which delivers low-frequency ultrasound
      through a gentle saline mist directed at a patient's wound. Patients (over 18 years old)
      will be invited to take part in this study if they have had a VLU for 6 weeks or more, which
      measures between 5 and 100 cm2, and is not infected. Participants with diabetes must show
      good blood glucose control, and those with underlying chronic disorders which may affect
      wound healing will be excluded.

      All study participants will receive four weeks of standard treatment once a week at a single
      clinic at the Wound Healing Research Unit (WHRU), University Hospital of Wales. Patients
      whose wounds reduce by more than 40% during this time will be withdrawn from the study.
      Remaining patients will be randomly allocated to either the active group or the control
      group to receive a further eight weeks of treatment. Participants in the active group will
      receive treatment with the MIST device three times a week, as well as standard care (change
      of compression bandage and dressings) three times a week. The control group will receive UK
      standard care (which is dressing and compression bandage change at least once a week). The
      participants' ulcers will be measured and photographed once a week, and the wound
      characteristics will be assessed. Changes in participants' health related QoL will be
      assessed using a questionnaire at the beginning and end of the trial. Wound recurrence rates
      90 days after the end of the treatment will be assessed by telephoning patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Wound area</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 to 13 (weekly)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Wound area is measured weekly using a digital wound imaging device. The wound boundary is digitally traced by a blinded assessor. Percentage and actual change in wound area between start of treatment (week 5) and end of treatment (week 13) is evaluated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1 (start) and week 13 (exit)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in health related quality of life between start and end of the study is assessed using a validated questionnaire, the Cardiff Wound Impact Schedule (CWIS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of wound infection</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 to 13 (weekly)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of wound infections (as demonstrated by clinical symptoms) from beginning of treatment (week 5) and end of treatment (week 13)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Wound characteristics</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 to 13 (weekly)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Wound characteristics including wound condition, exudate, pain frequency, pain severity, and odour will be assessed weekly.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Wound recurrence rate</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days after time of healing</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients whose wound has healed (defined as 100% epithelialisation with no scab present) before or at the end of treatment will be asked 90 days after date of healing if their wound has remained closed.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Varicose Ulcer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard treatment for VLUs is administered once a week, i.e. compression bandaging and non-adherent dressing, with debridement if required.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MIST and Standard Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MIST ultrasound therapy is applied for between 3 and 12 minutes (depending on wound size) 3 times a week in combination with standard treatment for VLUs of compression bandaging and non-adherent dressing change 3 times a week, with debridement as required.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MIST ultrasound therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Low frequency, non-contact ultrasound system delivering therapeutic ultrasound via a fine saline mist to the wound bed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MIST and Standard Care</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MIST non-contact low-frequecy ultrasound device</other_name>
    <other_name>MIST</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Compression bandaging, non-adherent dressing, and debridement if required.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MIST and Standard Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Venous leg ulcers (as diagnosed by the clinician)

          -  Ankle Brachial Pressure Index (ABPI) &gt;0.8

          -  If multiple ulcers are present treat largest ulcer only (index ulcer) with minimum
             distance of 1 cm between index ulcer and any other ulcer

          -  18 years or older

          -  Ulcer size of 5 cm2 - 100 cm2 (with no longest length being greater than 10 cm) at
             randomisation point (week 5)

          -  Mobile enough to attend clinic

          -  Index ulcer between 6 weeks and 5 years duration prior to screening date

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Uncontrolled diabetes (Hba1c ≥12%) as tested within the past 3 months

          -  Index ulcer has active infection on day of inclusion requiring use or oral or IV
             antibiotics

          -  Renal failure

          -  Index ulcer has exposed tendons, ligaments, muscle, or bone

          -  Osteomyelitis or cellulitis or gangrene in study limb

          -  Subjects with amputation above a trans metatarsal amputation (TMA) in the study limb

          -  Subjects with active malignancy on the study limb

          -  Index ulcer that is of arterial disease aetiology

          -  Females of child bearing potential who are not willing to use a method of highly
             effective contraception during the entire study

          -  Planned vascular surgery, angioplasty, or thrombolysis procedures within the study
             period, or 6 weeks post-operatively

          -  Planned surgical procedure during the study period for the index wound

          -  Prior skin replacement, negative pressure therapy, ultrasound therapy applied to the
             index wound 2 weeks before screening

          -  Oral or IV antibiotics within 48 hours of baseline measurements

          -  Growth factor therapy within previous 14 days of screening date

          -  Currently receiving or has received radiation or chemotherapy within 3 months of
             randomisation

          -  Pregnant or breast feeding women

          -  Subject is currently enrolled or has been enrolled in the last 30 days in another
             investigational device or drug trial

          -  Subject's wound would require ultrasound near an electronic implant or prosthesis

          -  Subjects lacking capacity to provide informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Keith G Harding, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wound Healing Research Unit, Cardiff University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wound Healing Research Unit, Cardiff University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cardiff</city>
        <zip>CF14 4XN</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 27, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 21, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cardiff University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Professor Keith G Harding</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director - Institute for Translation, Innovation, Methodology and Engagement (TIME)</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Venous Leg Ulcer</keyword>
  <keyword>Varicose Ulcer</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic ulcer</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic wound</keyword>
  <keyword>Ultrasound therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>MIST device</keyword>
  <keyword>Wound healing</keyword>
  <keyword>Low frequency non contact ultrasound</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Leg Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Varicose Ulcer</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
