<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="35151">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01919320</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RA-409</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>Data Collection via INTERMACS</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01919320</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>SynCardia Companion 2 Driver System Post Approval Study Protocol With INTERMACS™-Based Data Collection</brief_title>
  <acronym>C2 PAS</acronym>
  <official_title>SynCardia Companion 2 Driver System Post Approval Study Protocol With INTERMACS™-Based Data Collection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>SynCardia Systems. Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>SynCardia Systems. Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Study Purpose

      The purpose of this PAS is to confirm that patients implanted with the temporary Total
      Artificial Heart (TAH-t) and supported with the Companion 2 Driver System have outcomes
      similar to those patients implanted with the TAH-t and supported with the CSS Console. The
      data collection mechanism for this study is the INTERMACS Registry.

      Study Objectives

      Primary Objectives:

        -  To confirm that patients implanted with the TAH-t and supported by the Companion 2
           Driver System have outcomes similar to those patients implanted with the TAH-t and
           supported by the CSS Console.

        -  To review additional data (patient survival, adverse event rates and bridge to
           transplant rates) to support the conclusion that the use of an artificial heart is
           reasonable and necessary for the treatment of irreversible biventricular failure in
           Medicare/Medicaid patients.

      Secondary Objective:

        -  To evaluate the incidence of adverse events (AEs). The AEs will follow the definitions
           in the INTERMACS Registry.

      Study Hypothesis

      The primary hypothesis is that the survival rate (defined as transplant prior to three
      months, transfer to the Freedom Driver System support prior to three months, or continuing
      on implant driver support at three months, whichever occurs first) for patients supported
      with the Companion 2 Driver System is not worse than the survival rate for patients
      supported with the Circulatory Support System (CSS) Console.

      Data Collection

      The data will be collected as defined in the INTERMACS Protocol and the patients will be
      followed at one week, one month and three months or until their study endpoint is reached.

      Data Analysis

      Data analysis will provide descriptive statistics on enrollment, adverse events, and
      outcomes for TAH-t patients who were implanted while supported with the Companion 2 Driver
      System compared to TAH-t patients who were implanted while supported with the CSS Console.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case Control, Time Perspective: Cross-Sectional</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival outcome at Day 90 Post TAH-t Implant</measure>
    <time_frame>Post TAH-t Implant Day 90</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The survival rate, defined as transplant prior to three months, transfer to the Freedom Driver System support prior to three months, or continuing on implant driver support at three months (whichever occurs first) for patients supported with the Companion 2 Driver System will be compared to the survival rate for patients supported with the Circulatory Support System (CSS) Console.
The analysis will include a lower one-sided 95% confidence bound on the observed survival rate for patients supported with the Companion 2 Driver system which will be compared to the CSS Console survival rate to evaluate non-inferiority.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sub-population Comparison for Generalizability</measure>
    <time_frame>Post TAH-t Implant Day 90</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To review additional data (patient survival, adverse event rates and bridge to transplant rates) to support the conclusion that the use of an artificial heart is reasonable and necessary for the treatment of irreversible biventricular failure in Medicare/Medicaid patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of Adverse Event Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study endpoint or Post TAH-t Implant Day 90</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the incidence of adverse events (AEs). The AEs will follow the definitions in the INTERMACS Registry.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">302</enrollment>
  <condition>Bi-ventricular Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CSS Console TAH-t Patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Last 151 records from TAH-t patients implanted while supported with the CSS Console who were enrolled in the INTERMACS Registry as of March 31, 2013.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>C2 Driver System TAH-t Patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>151 TAH-t patients implanted while supported by the Companion 2 (C2) Driver System and who were or will be enrolled in the INTERMACS Registry.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>C2 Driver System TAH-t Patients</intervention_name>
    <description>Comparison of two pneumatic drivers supporting the SynCardia TAH-t</description>
    <arm_group_label>C2 Driver System TAH-t Patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SynCardia</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CSS Console TAH-t Patients</intervention_name>
    <description>Comparison of two pneumatic drivers supporting the SynCardia TAH-t.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CSS Console TAH-t Patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SynCardia</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with bi-ventricular failure at risk of imminent death who are implanted with the
        SynCardia temporary Total Artificial Heart (TAH-t) AND who have enrolled in the INTERMACS
        Registry
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Implanted with the TAH-t

          -  Patient or their legal representative has signed an informed consent (ICF) form for
             INTERMACS Registry participation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient or legal guardian has not signed an ICF for INTERMACS Registry participation.

          -  Patient is incarcerated.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Francisco Arabia, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 24, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 6, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>SynCardia</keyword>
  <keyword>Total Artificial Heart</keyword>
  <keyword>TAH-t</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
