<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="162958">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01678196</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CRE 12-024</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01678196</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Helping Families Help Veterans With PTSD and Alcohol Abuse: An RCT of VA-CRAFT</brief_title>
  <official_title>Helping Families Help Veterans With PTSD and Alcohol Abuse: An RCT of VA-CRAFT</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project begins to evaluate the effectiveness of a web-based family outreach tool that
      is designed to promote treatment engagement among Veterans with posttraumatic stress
      disorder (PTSD) or alcohol use disorders (AUDs) but who have not yet engaged in mental
      health care. The National Center for PTSD has developed an on-line, Veteran-tailored,
      interactive web tool called VA - Community Reinforcement and Family Training (VA-CRAFT) that
      trains family members to effectively help their Veterans to engage in treatment for PTSD
      and/or AUDs. This project will provide preliminary information about VA-CRAFT's
      effectiveness.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background PTSD and AUDs are highly prevalent psychiatric disorders among combat Veterans
      that can lead to substantial impairments and disability. Although empirically supported
      treatments are available, the majority of Veterans suffering PTSD or AUDs do not engage in
      any mental health care. Data show that encouragement and support by family members play a
      key role in Veterans' willingness to engage in mental health care. However, many family
      members may not know how best to help their Veterans engage in mental health care. VA-CRAFT
      is an innovative adaptation of an empirically supported family training intervention (CRAFT)
      that has been shown to dramatically increase treatment engagement among substance abusing
      civilian samples.  VA-CRAFT includes Veteran-specific content, a focus on PTSD, SUDs, or
      both, and also make use of interactive web-technology to increase its efficiency and reach.
      Pilot research is needed to begin to evaluate the effectiveness of this adaptation of an
      existing, efficacious intervention, to provide feedback to VA-CRAFT developers for possible
      modifications to content and delivery, and to inform future studies.

      Objectives Specific aims are to: 1) provide pilot data on the effectiveness of VA-CRAFT on
      Veterans' mental health service utilization; 2) provide pilot data on the effectiveness of
      VA-CRAFT on family members' wellbeing, personal quality of life, perceived relationship
      quality with Veteran, and communication about treatment seeking; 3) obtain pilot data to
      explore possible differences in intervention response between Veterans with AUDs only, PTSD
      only, or both; and 4) provide information regarding potential changes in content and
      delivery as well as mediators and moderators of outcome for VA-CRAFT.

      Methods This is a randomized controlled trial of VA-CRAFT that will obtain preliminary
      information on its effectiveness and pilot information to inform future studies.
      Participants will be drawn from a cohort of Veterans and family members enrolled in the
      Readiness and Resilience in National Guard Soldiers studies (RINGS; Polusny &amp; Erbes, PIs).
      Using Veterans' responses to post-deployment RINGS surveys and administrative data, family
      members of Veterans who screen positive for PTSD or AUDs will be recruited and divided into
      1 of 3 subsamples:  1) family of Veterans with AUDs only (anticipated n = 38), 2) family of
      Veterans with PTSD only (anticipated n = 72), and 3) family of Veterans with both PTSD and
      AUDs (anticipated n = 74; total anticipated N =184 across the 3 subsamples). Family member
      participants will complete baseline questionnaires of perceived Veteran PTSD and AUD
      symptoms, family functioning and communication, and well-being and will be randomly assigned
      to VA-CRAFT or Control (no treatment) conditions. Those assigned to the VA-CRAFT condition
      will complete the online VA-CRAFT course.  Progress through VA-CRAFT will be monitored and
      stepped outreach efforts (emails, phone contacts) will be systematically used, as necessary,
      to promote completion of the intervention. Three months after the baseline assessment,
      family members and Veterans will complete follow-up questionnaires. Primary outcomes will
      include: 1) Veteran's mental health service utilization during the 3 months following
      initiation of VA-CRAFT as assessed by VA administrative data and 2) family member
      self-reports of wellbeing and quality of life and 3) family and Veteran reports of perceived
      relationship quality and communication about treatment seeking. Effect sizes will be
      estimated for each outcome within each subsample of participants (AUD only, PTSD only, and
      comorbid) and, if patterns are similar within subsamples, for the sample overall.  Following
      the post-intervention questionnaires, qualitative interviews will be conducted with up to 40
      family participants to examine possible moderators and mediators of treatment responses and
      to elicit participant feedback on VA-CRAFT modules and development to inform future VA-CRAFT
      development.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Veteran engagement in VA Mental Health services</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after initiation of the intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administrative data on mental health service utilization for Veterans will be compared for those whose family members receive the intervention (VA-CRAFT) and those who do not.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Family member psychosocial wellbeing</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after initiation of the intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Self-report questionnaires assessing family member reports of psychiatric symptoms (Brief Symptom Inventory) and quality of life (World Health Organization Quality of Life Scale - Brief)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Family functioning</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after the initiation of the intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Family and Veteran self-reports of family functioning including:  Family conflict and cohesion (Family Environment Scale), Overall family happiness (Relationship Happiness Scale), and satisfaction (Dyadic Adjustment Scale - Brief)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">336</enrollment>
  <condition>PTSD</condition>
  <condition>Alcohol Abuse</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VA-CRAFT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Family participants complete an on-line training course (VA-CRAFT) over a 3 month period</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will have the opportunity to complete the VA-CRAFT training program after 3 months; otherwise no intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>VA-CRAFT</intervention_name>
    <description>VA-CRAFT is an on-line training program that teaches family members how to communicate and interact with Veterans to promote their engagement in needed mental health services for PTSD or Alcohol Use Disorders.  12 on-line sessions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>VA-CRAFT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will have the opportunity to complete the VA-CRAFT training program after 3 months; otherwise no intervention</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Family participants:

               -  must have participated in a Readiness and Resilience in National Guards Soldiers
                  - (RINGS) study and be a spouse, partner, or family member of a Veteran who has
                  also participated in a RINGS study

               -  report frequent contact with the Veteran

               -  be paired with a Veteran who has not received mental health services at VA or in
                  the community for the past 3 months and who has screened positive for PTSD or
                  AUDs

               -  and have regular access to the internet.

          -  Veteran participants:

               -  must have participated in a RINGS study

               -  be in significant contact with a spouse/partner/family member who has enrolled
                  in this protocol

               -  screened positive for PTSD and/or AUD through their responses to a RINGS survey

               -  and have not received mental health care (based on VA administrative data) or in
                  the community for the past 3 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Family members (and thus Veterans) will not be eligible for the study if they or
             their Veteran have reported severe levels of interpersonal violence in their
             relationship in the past 3 months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christopher R. Erbes, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Minneapolis VA Health Care System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Minneapolis VA Health Care System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55417</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Reger GM, Hoffman J, Riggs D, Rothbaum BO, Ruzek J, Holloway KM, Kuhn E. The &quot;PE coach&quot; smartphone application: an innovative approach to improving implementation, fidelity, and homework adherence during prolonged exposure. Psychol Serv. 2013 Aug;10(3):342-9. doi: 10.1037/a0032774.</citation>
    <PMID>23937084</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Polusny MA, Kumpula MJ, Meis LA, Erbes CR, Arbisi PA, Murdoch M, Thuras P, Kehle-Forbes SM, Johnson AK. Gender differences in the effects of deployment-related stressors and pre-deployment risk factors on the development of PTSD symptoms in National Guard Soldiers deployed to Iraq and Afghanistan. J Psychiatr Res. 2014 Feb;49:1-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jpsychires.2013.09.016. Epub 2013 Oct 5.</citation>
    <PMID>24290487</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 18, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 29, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Family Members</keyword>
  <keyword>Community Outreach</keyword>
  <keyword>Internet</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alcoholism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
