<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="35218">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02003820</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pedidentalautism</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02003820</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Using Video Modeled Social Stories to Improve Oral Hygiene in Children With Autism Spectrum Disorder</brief_title>
  <official_title>Using Video Modeled Social Stories to Improve Oral Hygiene in Children With Autism</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yale University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Yale University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      We hypothesize that oral hygiene habits in children 8-14 years of age can be improved using
      video format Social Story intervention techniques. The purpose of this study is to
      investigate the effectiveness of video format social stories used to inform and educate
      children and parents about proper dental hygiene technique over a 6 week intervention
      period. We will measure the success of intervention using data collected from clinical exams
      and caregiver/participant surveys. Evaluation of data collected will be used to determine
      the effectiveness of the intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this pilot study improvement of tooth brushing practices in children with Autism Spectrum
      Disorder between the ages of  eight and twelve years old will be evaluated. Participants
      placed in two randomized groups will watch a Youtube format instructional video twice each
      day immediately before each brushing during the three-week intervention period.

      The video intervention will teach participants to use the usual and customary hygiene
      skills. Participants will view a child in their age range demonstrating proper brushing
      using the Bass brushing technique. The video will also have written narration at the bottom
      of the screen delivering printed information using Social Story style prompts. The Social
      Story prompts will also be read aloud for auditory delivery of information. The video will
      be two to three minutes long.

      Success of intervention will be determined using data collected at multiple times during the
      pilot. First, clinical exams will be completed before the intervention, half way through the
      intervention, and at the end of three weeks to evaluate how clean the patients oral cavity
      appears. Exams should take no more than twenty minutes in the dental chair. Second,
      Qualtrics emails will be sent to the patient's caregiver at 5:30 AM and 4:30 PM each day
      during intervention providing access to the instructional video. After opening the email and
      watching the video, there will be a simple &quot;yes or no&quot; survey question asking the caregiver
      if the video was watching before that brushing session. Finally, more in depth caregiver
      surveys will be completed at the end of each week during the intervention consisting of no
      more than fifteen questions. The surveys will evaluate the caregiver's perception of
      intervention success. At completion of the intervention the video will be made available to
      all participants via Youtube.com. One final survey will be sent to caregivers three weeks
      post intervention to determine if the video is still being used for hygiene reinforcement.

      Multiple efforts for study control will be implemented. To control for the impact the
      initial exam may have on hygiene Group 2 will wait two weeks from the time of clinical exam
      before starting video intervention. Group 1 will start the intervention immediately after
      clinical exam. Clinical evaluators will also be blinded to prevent bias when evaluating the
      two groups clinically. One examiner will conduct initial exams. A second examiner will
      conduct all subsequent exams with no knowledge of what group each patient is assigned.
      Evaluators will be calibrated pre-study evaluating hygiene patients at the dental clinic.

      All participants in this study will also be enrolled at Yale Child Study Center to measure
      the participants IQ using autism specific IQ testing methods.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of video intervention use</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Video intervention will be emailed to participants twice daily during intervention period. After watching video the patient will be given a one question survey asking if they watched the video before that brushing period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plaque index</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients will be given a usual and customary dental exam in the clinic before intervention is introduced to evaluate level of oral hygiene by a blinded evaluator. Plaque index will also be measured in the usual and customary manor half way through intervention and at the end of intervention period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Caregiver survey</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Caregivers will be given 10-15 question surveys at beginning of intervention, at the end of each week during the intervention, and 3 weeks post intervention measuring their perception of the intervention's effect on the study subject. Questions will measure ease of completing brushing, perceived brushing effectiveness, amount of help patient requires to brush effectively, interest in video...</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Autism Spectrum Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Dental Caries</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group 1 will receive plaque index exam and immediately start their three week intervention of watching video modeled social story immediately before brushing twice per day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group 2 will receive their initial plaque index and wait two weeks before starting their intervention of watching the video modeled social story immediately before brushing. This will control for any improvement in oral hygiene the plaque index visit itself may cause.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>video modeled social story</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient will watch a Youtube compatible video of a child in the same age range as the study participants demonstrating proper brushing technique. The video will be paired with written subtitles created using the Social Story format. The subtitles will be read to the participant as the video plays. The patient will watch the video immediately before each brushing session morning and night for the three week intervention. After the intervention period the video will be made available on Youtube.com for the participants to use as they wish.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosed with Autism Spectrum Disorder

          -  Access to internet and email at home

          -  Patient of record at Yale New Haven Hospital Pediatric Dental Clinic

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Outside of specified age range

          -  Multiple diagnosis

          -  No home access to email and internet
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Keri Discepolo, DDS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Yale Pediatric Dentistry</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Keri Discepolo, DDS</last_name>
    <phone>203-688-3000</phone>
    <email>keri.discepolo@ynhh.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ben Popple, DMD</last_name>
    <phone>203-688-3000</phone>
    <email>ben.popple@ynhh.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale Pediatric Dental Center Suite 403</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06511</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Enrolling by invitation</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Friedlander AH, Yagiela JA, Paterno VI, Mahler ME. The neuropathology, medical management and dental implications of autism. J Am Dent Assoc. 2006 Nov;137(11):1517-27. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17082277</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rice C, Schendel D, Cunniff C, Doernberg N. Public health monitoring of developmental disabilities with a focus on the autism spectrum disorders. Am J Med Genet C Semin Med Genet. 2004 Feb 15;125C(1):22-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14755430</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marshall J, Sheller B, Mancl L. Caries-risk assessment and caries status of children with autism. Pediatr Dent. 2010 Jan-Feb;32(1):69-75.</citation>
    <PMID>20298657</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jaber MA. Dental caries experience, oral health status and treatment needs of dental patients with autism. J Appl Oral Sci. 2011 May-Jun;19(3):212-7.</citation>
    <PMID>21625735</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klein U, Nowak AJ. Characteristics of patients with autistic disorder (AD) presenting for dental treatment: a survey and chart review. Spec Care Dentist. 1999 Sep-Oct;19(5):200-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10765886</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Capozza LE, Bimstein E. Preferences of parents of children with autism spectrum disorders concerning oral health and dental treatment. Pediatr Dent. 2012 Nov-Dec;34(7):480-4.</citation>
    <PMID>23265165</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DeMattei R, Cuvo A, Maurizio S. Oral assessment of children with an autism spectrum disorder. J Dent Hyg. 2007 Summer;81(3):65. Epub 2007 Jul 1.</citation>
    <PMID>17908421</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rada RE. Controversial issues in treating the dental patient with autism. J Am Dent Assoc. 2010 Aug;141(8):947-53. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20675420</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loo CY, Graham RM, Hughes CV. The caries experience and behavior of dental patients with autism spectrum disorder. J Am Dent Assoc. 2008 Nov;139(11):1518-24.</citation>
    <PMID>18978390</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marshall J, Sheller B, Mancl L, Williams BJ. Parental attitudes regarding behavior guidance of dental patients with autism. Pediatr Dent. 2008 Sep-Oct;30(5):400-7.</citation>
    <PMID>18942599</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stein LI, Polido JC, Najera SO, Cermak SA. Oral care experiences and challenges in children with autism spectrum disorders. Pediatr Dent. 2012 Sep-Oct;34(5):387-91.</citation>
    <PMID>23211914</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weil TN, Inglehart MR. Three- to 21-year-old patients with autism spectrum disorders: parents' perceptions of severity of symptoms, oral health, and oral health-related behavior. Pediatr Dent. 2012 Nov-Dec;34(7):473-9.</citation>
    <PMID>23265164</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Orellana LM, Martínez-Sanchis S, Silvestre FJ. Training Adults and Children with an Autism Spectrum Disorder to be Compliant with a Clinical Dental Assessment Using a TEACCH-Based Approach. J Autism Dev Disord. 2013 Sep 4. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>24002415</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cardon TA, Wilcox MJ. Promoting imitation in young children with autism: a comparison of reciprocal imitation training and video modeling. J Autism Dev Disord. 2011 May;41(5):654-66. doi: 10.1007/s10803-010-1086-8.</citation>
    <PMID>20697791</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Charlop MH, Milstein JP. Teaching autistic children conversational speech using video modeling. J Appl Behav Anal. 1989 Fall;22(3):275-85.</citation>
    <PMID>2793634</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bohlander AJ, Orlich F, Varley CK. Social skills training for children with autism. Pediatr Clin North Am. 2012 Feb;59(1):165-74, xii. doi: 10.1016/j.pcl.2011.10.001. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22284800</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Litras S, Moore DW, Anderson A. Using video self-modelled social stories to teach social skills to a young child with autism. Autism Res Treat. 2010;2010:834979. doi: 10.1155/2010/834979. Epub 2010 Jun 9.</citation>
    <PMID>22937239</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Karkhaneh M, Clark B, Ospina MB, Seida JC, Smith V, Hartling L. Social Stories ™ to improve social skills in children with autism spectrum disorder: a systematic review. Autism. 2010 Nov;14(6):641-62. doi: 10.1177/1362361310373057. Epub 2010 Oct 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20923896</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kokina A, Kern L. Social Story interventions for students with autism spectrum disorders: a meta-analysis. J Autism Dev Disord. 2010 Jul;40(7):812-26. doi: 10.1007/s10803-009-0931-0.</citation>
    <PMID>20054628</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 2, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 2, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Yale University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Keri Discepolo</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Attending</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Autism</keyword>
  <keyword>Dental Caries</keyword>
  <keyword>Prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Oral Hygiene</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Autistic Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dental Caries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Child Development Disorders, Pervasive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
