<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="121177">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02117271</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0068</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02117271</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Treatment of Obstructive Sleep Apnea With Continuous Positive Airway Pressure on Appearance and Age</brief_title>
  <official_title>&quot;BEAUTY CPAP&quot;: The Impact of the Treatment of Obstructive Sleep Apnea With Continuous Positive Airway Pressure on Appearance and Age: a Randomized Crossover Placebo-controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nucleo Interdisciplinar da Ciencia do Sono</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nucleo Interdisciplinar da Ciencia do Sono</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Brazil: National Committee of Ethics in Research</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators hypothesized that the treatment of obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) with
      continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) will positively affect the appearance of the
      patient. The purpose of this study is to compare effects of one month of treatment of CPAP
      and placebo on appearance of patient with OSA in a randomized and crossover study.

      The investigators will include 30 consecutive patients (both genders, aged 30 to 60 years)
      referred to a sleep clinic, with history of snoring, excessive sleepiness, and severe OSA.
      Patients will be excluded if presenting previous treatment for sleep-disordered breathing,
      previous diagnosis of chronic diseases that interfere with sleep patterns and history the
      chronic use of alcohol, sedatives or drugs of abuse, in the last month.

      Patients will be randomized into two treatment arms: 1) Placebo - use of nasal dilator
      strip; and 2) CPAP - use of CPAP. After one month of treatment in the first randomized arm,
      patients will be submitted to two weeks without treatment (washout period). After washout
      period, patients will be assigned to the treatment crossover, i.e., patients in arm 1) will
      receive CPAP therapy and patients in arm 2) will receive placebo treatment, during a period
      of one additional month. Excessive sleepiness (Epworth Sleepiness Scale) and quality of life
      (Functional Outcomes of Sleep Questionnaire - FOSQ) will be evaluated in the three
      experimental times: baseline (immediately before treatment), one month (after one month of
      treatment defined at baseline), and 2 months (after one month of treatment crossover).

      All patients will be photographed in the three experimental times. The photographs will be
      displayed in a randomized order for 100 observers (general population, both genders, similar
      socioeconomic status and education), who will be unaware of the conditions of the study. The
      observers will rate the faces for attractiveness (very unattractive to very attractive),
      health (very sick to very healthy), and tiredness (not at all tired to very tired) on a 100
      mm visual analogue scale. Age perceived will be rated by the observers' evaluation.

      Presence of porphyrins, coloration/evenness, vascular features, porosity, wrinkles and skin
      texture of the patient's face will be analyzed using the VISIA TM system. Skin hydration and
      skin elasticity will be measured out from forearm. Collection of dermatological assessments
      will be conducted in three experimental sampling times.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction: A previous study showed that sleep deprived people were perceived as less
      healthy, less attractive, and more tired than after a normal night's sleep (Axelsson et al.,
      Beauty sleep: experimental study on the perceived health and attractiveness of sleep
      deprived people. BMJ 2010;341:c6614). The investigators believe that likewise sleep
      deprivation, patients with OSA also are perceived as less attractive, tired, healthy and
      look older than your age. the investigators therefore hypothesized that the treatment of OSA
      with continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) will positively affect the appearance of the
      patient. The purpose of this study is to compare effects of one month of treatment of CPAP
      and placebo on appearance of patient with OSA in a randomized and crossover study.

      Methods:The investigators will include 30 consecutive patients of both genders, aged between
      30 and 60 years, referred to the sleep clinic of the Heart Institute (InCor) of University
      of Sao Paulo, with a history of snoring, excessive sleepiness, and with severe OSA confirmed
      by polysomnography. Patients will be excluded if presenting previous treatment for
      sleep-disordered breathing, previous diagnosis of chronic diseases that interfere with sleep
      patterns and history the chronic use of alcohol, sedatives or drugs of abuse, in the last
      month.

      Patients will be randomized into two treatment groups: 1) Placebo arm - use of nasal dilator
      strip; and 2) CPAP arm - use of CPAP. At the first night of each treatment the patients will
      be submitted to a polysomnography with nasal strip (placebo arm) or to CPAP titration (CPAP
      arm). After one month of treatment in the first randomized arm, patients will be submitted
      to two weeks without treatment (washout period). After washout period, patients will be
      assigned to the treatment crossover, i.e., patients in group 1) will receive CPAP therapy
      and patients in Group 2) will receive placebo treatment, during a period of one additional
      month. Excessive sleepiness (Epworth Sleepiness Scale) and quality of life (Functional
      Outcomes of Sleep Questionnaire - FOSQ) will be evaluated in the three experimental times:
      baseline (immediately before treatment), one month (after one month of treatment defined at
      baseline), and 2 months (after one month of treatment crossover).

      During the study period, the patients will be followed by trained professionals and will
      receive all the necessary information about the use of each treatment. After three days of
      treatment, patients will be contacted by phone to ensure the adherence treatment and to
      solve potential doubts. After each week of treatment, patients should return to the sleep
      clinic to management of the adherence data from the memory card (CPAP group) and data from
      the full filled sleep log (Placebo group), and also to have reinforced the information about
      the study protocol. Any issues or concerns about the treatment will be also solved by phone
      calls.

      All patients will be photographed in the three experimental times: baseline (immediately
      before treatment), one month (after one month of treatment defined at baseline) and 2 months
      (after one month of treatment crossover). Photographs will be taken by a trained
      photographer in a standardized manner. The photographer will be blind to the experimental
      condition of patients. The photographs will be displayed at a fixed interval of six seconds
      in a randomized order for 100 observers (general population, both genders, similar
      socioeconomic status and education), who will be unaware of the conditions of the study. The
      observers will rate the faces for attractiveness (very unattractive to very attractive),
      health (very sick to very healthy), and tiredness (not at all tired to very tired) on a 100
      mm visual analogue scale. Age perceived will be rated by the observers' evaluation.

      The high-resolution analyzing system VISIA TM (Canfield Scientific Inc. Fairfield USA) will
      be used for computer analysis to precisely measure presence of porphyrins (P. acnes),
      coloration/evenness, vascular features, porosity, wrinkles and skin texture of the patient's
      face. The photographs from VISIA TM will be taken after standard skin preparation and will
      be analyzed by a specific analysis algorithm. Additionally, skin hydration will be measure
      by the Corneometer CM 820 CM825-OR-MPA 5 (Courage-Khazaka, GmHB) and the skin elasticity
      will be evaluated by the CUTOMETER SEM 575 or MPA580 (Courage-Khazaka, GmHB). Measures will
      be carried out in a 10 cm2 area from forearm, with a distance of 10 cm from the top of the
      handle. Collection of dermatological assessments will be conducted in three experimental
      sampling times.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>appearance</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients will be rated for attractiveness (very unattractive to very attractive), health (very sick to very healthy), and tiredness (not at all tired to very tired)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>skin quality</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Computer analysis of face image to measure presence of porphyrins (P. acnes), coloration/evenness, vascular features, porosity, wrinkles and skin texture.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Obstructive Sleep Apnea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>nasal dilator strip</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Breathe Right ® nasal dilator strip used during sleep</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>continuous positive airway pressure</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>nasal continuous positive airway pressure used during sleep</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>continuous positive airway pressure</intervention_name>
    <description>device to treat obstructive sleep apnea using positive airway pressure with a nasal mask</description>
    <arm_group_label>continuous positive airway pressure</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Philips Respironics, System One, REMstar Pro</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Breathe Right ®</intervention_name>
    <description>Nasal dilator strip treatment used during sleep to open the nasal airway</description>
    <arm_group_label>nasal dilator strip</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>GlaxoSmithKline Brasil Ltda.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  severe sleep apnea (apnea-hypopnea index &gt; 30)

          -  Epworth Sleepiness Scale score &gt; 10

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  previous treatment for sleep-disordered breathing

          -  previous diagnosis of chronic diseases that interfere with sleep patterns

          -  history the chronic use of alcohol, sedatives or drugs of abuse, in the last month.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GERALDO L FILHO, MD, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Sao Paulo</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>GERALDO L FILHO, MD, PHD</last_name>
    <phone>55 11 30871240</phone>
    <email>GERALDO.LORENZI@GMAIL.COM</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>FABIANA T YAGIHARA, MsD</last_name>
    <phone>55 11 963699200</phone>
    <email>YAGIHARA@GMAIL.COM</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nucleo Interdisciplinar Da Ciencia Do Sono</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sao Paulo</city>
        <state>SP</state>
        <zip>05401-000</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>ROGERIO S SILVA, PHD</last_name>
      <phone>55 11 991778965</phone>
      <email>ROGER.SS@UOL.COM.BR</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>FABIANA T YAGIHARA, MsD</last_name>
      <phone>55 11 963699200</phone>
      <email>YAGIHARA@GMAIL.COM</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>GERALDO L FILHO, MD, PHD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 15, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 10, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Nucleo Interdisciplinar da Ciencia do Sono</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Geraldo Lorenzi Filho</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>obstructive sleep apnea</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>placebo</keyword>
  <keyword>appearance</keyword>
  <keyword>skin quality</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Apnea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
