<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="163214">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02000596</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HP-00054959</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>GCC1303</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02000596</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trastuzmab &amp; Pertuzumab Alone or in Combination With Hormonal Therapy or Chemotherapy With Eribulin in Women Aged 60 and Over With HER2/Neu Overexpressed Locally Advanced or MBC</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of Trastuzumab and Pertuzumab Alone and in Combination With Hormonal Therapy or Chemotherapy With Eribulin in Women Aged 60 and Over With HER2/Neu Overexpressed Locally Advanced and/or Metastatic Breast Carcinoma (GCC 1303)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Katherine Tkaczuk</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genentech</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Maryland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Currently available standard therapies for HER2 overexpressed metastatic breast cancers
      (MBC) include treatments with chemotherapy or hormonal therapy, alone or in combination with
      medications that target HER2 gene, such as Trastuzumab or Pertuzumab. This study will
      examine the effect of treating HER2 overexpressed MBC with the combination of Trastuzumab
      plus Pertuzumab, without hormonal or chemotherapy, as a first line treatment. If patients
      progress on this treatment, they will receive hormonal or chemotherapy in addition to the
      Trastuzumab plus Pertuzumab treatment. The objective is to see how the overall response rate
      for this treatment compares to other first line treatments in the same patient population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>ORR in T+P only</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall response rate (ORR) in patients with HER2+ MBC treated with Trastuzumab and Pertuzumab (T+P) alone (cohort 1).  Defined as the total of complete response (CR) + partial response (PR) + stable disease (SD) &gt;= 24 weeks over the total number of participants (ORR=[CR+PR+SD]/n) as defined by the Response Evaluation in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1 response criteria.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>ORR in T+P plus hormonal therapy (HT)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall response rate (ORR) in patients with HER2+ ER and/or PR &gt; 1% positive MBC with T+P+ Hormonal therapy ( Anastrozole+ Fulvestrant) after progression on T+P alone (Cohort 2-ArmA).  Defined as the total of complete response (CR) + partial response (PR) + stable disease (SD) &gt;= 24 weeks over the total number of participants (ORR=[CR+PR+SD]/n) as defined by the RECIST 1.1 response criteria.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>ORR in T+P plus chemotherapy with Eribulin</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall response rate (ORR) in patients with HER2+, ER/PR negative MBC with T+P+ Eribulin (Cohort 2 - arm-B) after progression on T+P alone.  ORR defined as the total of complete response (CR) + partial response (PR) + stable disease (SD) &gt;= 24 weeks over the total number of participants (ORR=[CR+PR+SD]/n) as defined by the RECIST 1.1 response criteria.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: T+P</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Trastuzumab plus Pertuzumab as first line treatment for HER2 overexpressed Metastatic Breast Cancer (without hormonal therapy or chemotherapy)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 - Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Hormonal Therapy with Anastrozole and Fulvestrant in addition Trastuzumab plus Pertuzumab for women who progressed on T+P alone, and who are ER/PR +</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 - Arm B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Chemotherapy with Eribulin in addition to Trastuzumab plus Pertuzumab for women who progressed on T+P alone and who are ER/PR -</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trastuzumab plus Pertuzumab</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: T+P</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 - Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 - Arm B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hormonal Therapy with Anastrozole and Fulvestrant</intervention_name>
    <description>Anastrozole 1mg by mouth daily FULVESTRANT 500mg i.m. D1, D15, D28 then every 28-30 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 - Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Anastrozole (Arimidex)</other_name>
    <other_name>Fulvestrant (Faslodex)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chemotherapy with Eribulin</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 - Arm B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Women ≥60 Years of Age.

          2. Histologically confirmed, locally advanced (T4 primary tumor and stage IIIB or IIIC
             disease) or metastatic breast cancer that progressed after treatment with standard
             treatment regimens in the adjuvant or neoadjuvant setting.

          3. Prior treatment with trastuzumab and/or lapatinib in the neo-adjuvant or adjuvant
             setting is allowed but not required. Lapatininb has to be discontinued &gt; 21 days
             before the initiation of the T+P study treatments.

          4. Prior chemotherapy is allowed in the neo-adjuvant, adjuvant, or metastatic setting
             with the exception of Eribulin; up to 3 prior chemotherapy regimens for treatment of
             metastatic disease are acceptable. All chemotherapy has to be discontinued &gt;=21 days
             before starting the study treatments with T+P.

          5. Patients may have had prior hormonal therapy with any hormonal agents with the
             exception of Fulvestrant or anastrozole in the neo-adjuvant, adjuvant, or metastatic
             setting and with subsequent documented progression of disease after completion of, or
             while on treatment with hormonal therapy and as long as other study eligibility
             criteria are met.

          6. Prior Lapatinib in combination with chemotherapy or hormonal therapy for treatment of
             MBC is allowed but not required as long as the other eligibility criteria are met.

          7. Human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2) positive, as defined in Section 3.3
             of this protocol

          8. Must have measurable or evaluable disease according to RECIST 1.1 criteria.

          9. The following laboratory values obtained ≤7 days prior to registration.

               -  Hemoglobin &gt;9.0g/dL

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥1000/mL

               -  Platelet count ≥100,000/mL

               -  Total bilirubin ≤1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  Serum Glutamic-Oxaloacetic Transaminase (SGOT)/aspartate transaminase (AST) and
                  Serum Glutamic Pyruvic Transaminase (SGPT)/ alanine aminotransferase (ALT) ≤2.5
                  x ULN or SGOT (AST) and SGPT (ALT) ≤5 x ULN if elevations are due to liver
                  metastases

               -  Serum creatinine ≤1.5 x ULN

               -  Serum potassium and magnesium- within normal limits (WNL)

               -  Fasting glucose &lt;250 mg/dL. Patients with diabetes are allowed to participate,
                  provided that their blood glucose is &lt;250 mg/dL upon enrollment

         10. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status (PS) of 0, 1 or 2.

         11. Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) of at least 50% as determined by Multi
             Gated Acquisition Scan (MUGA) or echocardiogram.

         12. Life expectancy &gt;3 months.

         13. Written informed consent.

         14. Willingness to return to the University of Maryland Greenebaum Cancer Center (UMGCC)
             or other participating institutions for treatment and follow-up.

         15. Normal QTc interval defined on EKG as QTc ≤ 440 msec. Note: patients who are assigned
             to Arm B must have QTc ≤ 440 msec  on D1 and D8 of cycle 1 of Eribulin treatments for
             continued eligibility.

         16. Postmenopausal women defined as women with:

               -  Prior bilateral surgical oophorectomy, or

               -  Medically confirmed post-menopausal status defined as spontaneous cessation of
                  regular menses for at least 12 consecutive months with no alternative
                  pathological or physiological cause.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Stage III or IV cancer, other than breast cancer, in ≤5 years prior to registration.

          2. Actively being treated for other malignancy. If there is a history of prior
             malignancy, patient must not be receiving other specific treatment for their cancer.

          3. New York Heart Association Class III or IV cardiovascular disease.

          4. History of coronary heart failure (CHF)

          5. Current use of drugs known to prolong the QTc interval including Class Ia and III
             antiarrhythmics or history of congenital long QTc syndrome. (Appendix C)

          6. Evidence of active brain metastasis including leptomeningeal involvement. Central
             nervous system (CNS) metastasis controlled by prior surgery and/or radiotherapy is
             allowed. NOTE: To be considered controlled, there must be at least 4 weeks of no
             clinical symptoms or evidence of progression prior to study entry and corticosteroid
             therapy must have been discontinued.

          7. Major surgery, chemotherapy, hormonal or immunologic therapy ≤3 weeks prior to
             registration.

          8. Radiotherapy ≤3 weeks prior to registration, except if to a non-target lesion only.

             Note: Prior radiation to a target lesion is permitted only if there has been clear
             progression of the lesion since radiation was completed. If patient receives single
             dose radiation for palliation or radiation to non-target lesion, they may immediately
             proceed to registration without waiting. Acute adverse events from radiation must
             have resolved to ≤ Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) v3.0 Grade
             1.

          9. Prior treatment with Pertuzumab, Eribulin, Fulvestrant or Anastrozole.

         10. Uncontrolled illness including, but not limited to:

               -  Ongoing or active infection

               -  Symptomatic congestive heart failure

               -  Unstable angina pectoris

               -  Cardiac arrhythmia

               -  Psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study
                  requirements.

         11. Co-morbid systemic illnesses or other severe concurrent disease which, in the
             judgment of the investigator, would make the patient inappropriate for entry into
             this study or interfere significantly with the proper assessment of the safety of the
             prescribed regimens.

         12. Currently receiving treatment in a different clinical study in which investigational
             procedures are performed or investigational therapies are administered.

         13. Immunocompromised patients (other than that related to the use of corticosteroids)
             including patients known to be HIV positive.

         14. International normalized ratio (INR), activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) or
             partial thromboplastin time (PTT) &gt;1.5 × ULN (unless on anticoagulation medication)

         15. Receipt of intravenous (IV) antibiotics for infection within 7 days prior to
             enrollment into the study.

         16. Current chronic daily treatment (continuous for &gt;3 months) with corticosteroids (dose
             equivalent to or greater than 10 mg/day methylprednisolone), excluding inhaled
             steroids.

         17. Known hypersensitivity to any of the study treatments or to excipients of recombinant
             human or humanized antibodies.

         18. History of receiving any investigational treatment within 28 days prior to enrollment
             into the study.

         19. Assessed by the investigator to be unable or unwilling to comply with the
             requirements of the protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Katherine Tkaczuk, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Maryland Greenebaum Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nancy Tait, RN</last_name>
    <phone>410-328-3546</phone>
    <email>ntait@umm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jane Lewis, RN</last_name>
    <phone>410-328-7856</phone>
    <email>jlewis@umm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Maryland Marlene &amp; Stewart Greenebaum Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nancy Tait, RN</last_name>
      <phone>410-328-3546</phone>
      <email>ntait@umm.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Katherine Tkaczuk, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 26, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 21, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Maryland</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Katherine Tkaczuk</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HER2 overexpressed</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Elderly</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fulvestrant</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anastrozole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Trastuzumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
