<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="111077">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02065765</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14945</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>I4T-MC-JVCP</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02065765</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>International Expanded Access Program to Provide Ramucirumab for the Treatment of Metastatic Gastric Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>An International Single-Arm Protocol to Provide Expanded Access to Ramucirumab for the Treatment of Metastatic Gastric or Gastroesophageal Junction Adenocarcinoma Following Disease Progression After Prior Fluoropyrimidine and/or Platinum-Containing Chemotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eli Lilly and Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eli Lilly and Company</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Netherlands: Medicines Evaluation Board (MEB)</authority>
    <authority>Austria: Austrian Medicines and Medical Devices Agency</authority>
    <authority>Belgium: Federal Agency for Medicinal Products and Health Products</authority>
    <authority>Czech Republic: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>Finland: Finnish Medicines Agency</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Paul-Ehrlich-Institut</authority>
    <authority>Greece: National Organization of Medicines</authority>
    <authority>Italy: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>Norway: Norwegian Medicines Agency</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Spanish Agency of Medicines</authority>
    <authority>Sweden: Swedish National Council on Medical Ethics</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The treating physician/investigator contacts Lilly when, based on their medical opinion, a
      patient meets the criteria for inclusion in the compassionate use program.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Available</overall_status>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Expanded Access</study_type>
  <study_design>N/A</study_design>
  <condition>Metastatic Gastric Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Adenocarcinoma of the Gastroesophageal Junction</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ramucirumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Administered intravenously (IV)</description>
    <other_name>LY3009806</other_name>
    <other_name>IMC-1121B</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The participant has histologically or cytologically confirmed gastric carcinoma,
             including gastric adenocarcinoma or gastroesophageal junction (GEJ) adenocarcinoma.
             (Participants with adenocarcinoma of the distal esophagus are eligible if the primary
             tumor involves the GEJ)

          -  The participant has metastatic disease or locally recurrent, unresectable disease

          -  The participant has measureable or evaluable disease as determined by standard
             computed tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) imaging. Examples of
             evaluable, nonmeasurable disease include gastric, peritoneal, or mesenteric
             thickening in areas of known disease, or peritoneal nodules that are too small to be
             considered measurable by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST version
             1.1)

          -  The participant has experienced disease progression during treatment or within 4
             months after the last dose of first-line therapy for metastatic disease, or during
             treatment, or within 6 months after the last dose of adjuvant therapy

             o Acceptable prior chemotherapy regimens for this protocol are combination
             chemotherapy regimens that include platinum and/or fluoropyrimidine components.
             Regimens including a third agent, such as an anthracycline or a taxane, are
             acceptable provided a fluoropyrimidine and/or a platinum were used.

          -  The participant has resolution to Grade ≤1 (or to Grade ≤2 in the case of neuropathy)
             by the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events
             (NCI-CTCAE), Version 4.03, of all clinically significant toxic effects of prior
             chemotherapy, surgery, radiotherapy, or hormonal therapy (with the exception of
             alopecia)

          -  The participant has an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status (ECOG
             PS) score of 0 or 1

          -  The participant has adequate hepatic function

          -  The participant does not have:

               -  cirrhosis at a level of Child-Pugh B (or worse) or

               -  cirrhosis (any degree) and a history of hepatic encephalopathy or clinically
                  meaningful ascites resulting from cirrhosis. Clinically meaningful ascites is
                  defined as ascites from cirrhosis requiring diuretics or paracentesis

          -  The participant has adequate renal function as defined by a serum creatinine ≤1.5
             times the upper limit of normal (ULN), or creatinine clearance (measured via 24-hour
             urine collection) ≥40 milliliter per minute (mL/minute)

          -  The participant's urinary protein is ≤1+ on dipstick or routine urinalysis (UA)

          -  The participant has adequate hematologic function

          -  The participant must have adequate coagulation function

          -  If the participant has received prior anthracycline therapy as part of his or her
             first-line regimen, the participant is able to engage in ordinary physical activity
             without significant fatigue or dyspnea (equivalent to New York Heart Association
             Class I function)

          -  Because the teratogenicity of ramucirumab is not known, the participant, if sexually
             active, must be postmenopausal, surgically sterile, or using effective contraception
             (hormonal or barrier methods)

          -  Female participants of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy
             test within 7 days prior to enrollment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The participant has documented and/or symptomatic brain or leptomeningeal metastases

          -  The participant has experienced any Grade 3 to 4 gastrointestinal (GI) bleeding
             within 3 months prior to enrollment

          -  The participant has experienced any arterial thromboembolic events, including but not
             limited to myocardial infarction, transient ischemic attack, cerebrovascular
             accident, or unstable angina, within 6 months prior to enrollment

          -  The participant has an ongoing or active infection, symptomatic congestive heart
             failure, unstable angina pectoris, symptomatic or poorly controlled cardiac
             arrhythmia, uncontrolled thrombotic or hemorrhagic disorder, or any other serious
             uncontrolled medical disorders in the opinion of the treating physician

          -  The participant has ongoing or active psychiatric illness or social situation that
             would limit compliance with treatment

          -  The participant has uncontrolled or poorly controlled hypertension [&gt;160 milliliter
             of mercury (mmHg) systolic or &gt;100 mmHg diastolic for &gt;4 weeks] despite standard
             medical management

          -  The participant has a serious or nonhealing wound, ulcer, or bone fracture within 28
             days prior to enrollment

          -  The participant has received chemotherapy, radiotherapy, immunotherapy, or targeted
             therapy for gastric cancer within 2 weeks prior to enrollment

          -  The participant has received any investigational therapy within 30 days prior to
             enrollment

          -  The participant has undergone major surgery within 28 days prior to enrollment, or
             subcutaneous venous access device placement within 7 days prior to enrollment

          -  The participant has received prior therapy with an agent that directly inhibits
             vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) (including bevacizumab), or vascular
             endothelial growth factor receptor-2 (VEGFR-2) activity, or any antiangiogenic agent

          -  The participant is receiving chronic antiplatelet therapy, including aspirin,
             nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs; including ibuprofen, naproxen, and
             others), dipyridamole or clopidogrel, or similar agents. Once-daily aspirin use
             (maximum dose 325 mg/day) is permitted

          -  The participant has elective or planned major surgery to be performed during the
             course of the clinical trial

          -  The participant has a known allergy to any of the treatment components

          -  The participant is pregnant or breastfeeding

          -  The participant is known to be positive for infection with the human immunodeficiency
             virus (HIV)

          -  The participant has known alcohol or drug dependency

          -  The participant has a concurrent active malignancy other than adequately treated
             nonmelanomatous skin cancer, other noninvasive carcinoma, or in situ neoplasm

          -  The participant has a known hypersensitivity to ramucirumab or any of the excipients

          -  The patient may not have received more than 1 prior therapy in the metastatic
             setting.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>There may be multiple sites in this clinical trial. 1-877-CTLILLY (1-877-285-4559) or</last_name>
    <phone>1-317-615-4559</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>For additional information regarding investigative sites for this trial, contact 1-877-CTLILLY (1-877-285-4559, 1-317-615-4559) Mon - Fri from 9 AM to 5 PM Eastern Time (UTC/GMT - 5 hours, EST), or speak with your personal physician.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Metairie</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70006</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eli Lilly</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>For additional information regarding investigative sites for this trial, contact 1-877-CTLILLY (1-877-285-4559, 1-317-615-4559) Mon - Fri from 9 AM to 5 PM Eastern Time (UTC/GMT - 5 hours, EST), or speak with your personal physician.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mineola</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11501</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eli Lilly</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>For additional information regarding investigative sites for this trial, contact 1-877-CTLILLY (1-877-285-4559, 1-317-615-4559) Mon - Fri from 9 AM to 5 PM Eastern Time (UTC/GMT - 5 hours, EST), or speak with your personal physician.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>20245</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eli Lilly</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>For additional information regarding investigative sites for this trial, contact 1-877-CTLILLY (1-877-285-4559, 1-317-615-4559) Mon - Fri from 9 AM to 5 PM Eastern Time (UTC/GMT - 5 hours, EST), or speak with your personal physician.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <zip>1105 AZ</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eli Lilly</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 20, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 17, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stomach Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
