<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="154700">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01879891</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>5R01DK049779-14</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01879891</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Exercise Intensity, Metabolic Rate and Insulin Sensitivity</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alabama at Birmingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alabama at Birmingham</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: National Institute of Health</authority>
    <authority>United States: DHHS</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary goal is to test the hypothesis high interval exercise increases energy
      expenditure and Insulin sensitivity more than 2 days of rest or moderate intensity exercise
      cumulatively over 23 hours during and following the exercise. Secondary goals are to
      evaluate exercise difficulty during moderate intensity exercise and high interval exercise
      as well as difficulty of activities of daily living and free living physical activity
      following rest, moderate intensity exercise and high interval exercise.

      A secondary study is designed to evaluate potential mechanism.  Hypotheses are that changes
      in muscle lipid metabolism, mitochondrial function, fat and cellular insulin signals will be
      increased following the high intensity interval exercise. In addition, these changes will be
      related to changes in insulin sensitivity and increases in protein metabolism and muscle
      damage.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 1995</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Exercise Intensity</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To test the hypothesis that high interval exercise increases energy expenditure and Insulin sensitivity more than 2 days of rest or moderate intensity exercise cumulatively over 23 hours during and following the exercise</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exercise Difficulty</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate exercise difficulty during moderate intensity exercise and high interval exercise as well as difficulty of activities of daily living and free living physical activity following rest, moderate intensity exercise and high interval exercise</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Women Between the Ages of 21 - 40.</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Aerobic</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Both groups will complete a VO2 maximum test, are provided food 2 days prior to assessments, exercise in the metabolic chamber, have a Resting Energy Expenditure test, complete a DEXA and have blood drawn. Both groups will remain, overnight in the metabolic chamber and have the clamp procedure. Exercise training is exactly the same for both groups.
Those who select the muscle biopsies will complete this test a week following the metabolic room calorimeter visit.
Those who select the Non-Biopsy group, in lieu of the biopsy test, will complete an Activities of Daily Living (ADL) test that involves sub-maximal VO2 assessment. The participants will also be asked to where an accelerometer home for 4 consecutive days after the ADL test.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aerobic</intervention_name>
    <description>Exercise training will consist of bicycle ergometer riding starting at 67% of heart rate max for 20 minutes. Exercise Intensity will be progressively increased every week until 80% of heart rate max for 40 minute sessions is reached.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Aerobic</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  healthy premenopausal African-American or Caucasian women ages 21-40

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  subjects cannot be smoking,

          -  taking medications which alter energy expenditure or fuel utilization,

          -  be diabetic or have a body mass index (BMI) less than 18 or more than 35.

          -  Also subjects cannot be pregnant or have cardiopulmonary disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UAB</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gary R Hunter, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>205-934-8338</phone>
      <email>ghunter@uab.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Brandon L Kane, MA</last_name>
      <phone>205-975-3806</phone>
      <email>kane003@uab.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gary R. Hunter, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 13, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Exercise Intensity</keyword>
  <keyword>Metabolism</keyword>
  <keyword>Insulin</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Insulin Resistance</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
