<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="88970">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01812252</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2661.00</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-00538</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA015704</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01812252</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Chemotherapy in Treating Patients With Myelodysplastic Syndrome Before Donor Stem Cell Transplant</brief_title>
  <acronym>ICT-HCT</acronym>
  <official_title>Initial Cytoreductive Therapy for Myelodysplastic Syndrome Prior to Allogeneic Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation (the ICT-HCT Study)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This clinical trial studies different chemotherapies in treating patients with
      myelodysplastic syndrome before donor stem cell transplant. Giving chemotherapy before a
      donor hematopoietic stem cell transplant helps stop the growth of cancer cells before, and
      may prevent the myelodysplastic syndrome from coming back after the transplant. When the
      healthy stem cells from a donor are infused into the patient they may help the patient's
      bone marrow make stem cells, red blood cells, white blood cells, and platelets.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the effect of induction chemotherapy (IC) (intensive acute myeloid leukemia
      [AML]-like therapy), versus less intensive hypomethylation agent (HMA) as initial therapy,
      on failure-free survival.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Determine if IC (intensive AML-like therapy) in comparison to HMA as initial therapy,
      will affect transplantation frequency, quality of life, pre-hematopoietic cell
      transplantation (HCT) toxicity, and transplant candidacy.

      II. Conduct exploratory analysis of post-HCT outcomes (overall survival, non relapse
      mortality, incidence of graft rejection, graft-versus-host disease [GVHD], relapse, and
      relapse-free survival).

      OUTLINE: Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 treatment arms.

      ARM A: Patients receive decitabine or azacitidine intravenously (IV) or subcutaneously (SC)
      for 7 days. Treatment repeats every 28 days for 4 courses of decitabine or 6 courses of
      azacitidine in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      ARM B: Patients receive cytarabine IV continuously over 24 hours for 7 days and idarubicin
      IV or daunorubicin hydrochloride IV on days 1-3 at the discretion of the treating physician.
      Treatment repeats every 28 days for up to 2 courses in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for 18 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Failure-free survival (failure defined as death, lack of response to initial therapy, relapse after response to initial therapy)</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency at which the patients undergo transplantation</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Factors present at enrollment that predict transplant frequency</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reasons for which patients were not transplanted</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in quality of life scores using European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Quality of Life Questionnaire-Core 30 (QLQ-C30)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to 18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in comorbidities</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and time of transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relapse-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of acute and chronic GVHD assessed using National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 3.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Myelomonocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>de Novo Myelodysplastic Syndromes</condition>
  <condition>Secondary Myelodysplastic Syndromes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (decitabine or azacitidine)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive decitabine or azacitidine IV or SC for 7 days. Treatment repeats every 28 days for 4 courses of decitabine or 6 courses of azacitidine in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (cytarabine, idarubicin or daunorubicin hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive cytarabine IV continuously over 24 hours for 7 days and idarubicin IV or daunorubicin hydrochloride IV on days 1-3 at the discretion of the treating physician. Treatment repeats every 28 days for up to 2 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>decitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV or SC</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (decitabine or azacitidine)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>5-aza-dCyd</other_name>
    <other_name>5AZA</other_name>
    <other_name>DAC</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>azacitidine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV or SC</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (decitabine or azacitidine)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>5-AC</other_name>
    <other_name>5-azacytidine</other_name>
    <other_name>azacytidine</other_name>
    <other_name>Vidaza</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cytarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (cytarabine, idarubicin or daunorubicin hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ARA-C</other_name>
    <other_name>arabinofuranosylcytosine</other_name>
    <other_name>arabinosylcytosine</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytosar-U</other_name>
    <other_name>cytosine arabinoside</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>idarubicin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (cytarabine, idarubicin or daunorubicin hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>4-demethoxydaunorubicin</other_name>
    <other_name>4-DMDR</other_name>
    <other_name>DMDR</other_name>
    <other_name>IDA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>daunorubicin hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (cytarabine, idarubicin or daunorubicin hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cerubidin</other_name>
    <other_name>Cerubidine</other_name>
    <other_name>daunomycin hydrochloride</other_name>
    <other_name>daunorubicin</other_name>
    <other_name>RP-13057</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>quality-of-life assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (decitabine or azacitidine)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (cytarabine, idarubicin or daunorubicin hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>quality of life assessment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of de novo or secondary myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS), including chronic
             myelomonocytic leukemia, as defined by the 2008 World Health Organization
             classification system

          -  Patients must have measurable disease requiring cytoreduction, defined as a bone
             marrow myeloblast count &gt;= 5% and &lt; 20% on morphologic examination

          -  Patients in which adequate marrow/biopsy specimens cannot be obtained to determine
             disease burden by morphologic assessment, but have fulfilled criteria (abnormal
             myeloblast count &gt;= 5% and &lt; 20%) by flow cytometry are still be eligible; reasonable
             attempts must be made to obtain an adequate specimen for morphologic assessment,
             including possible repeat procedures

          -  Patients must be considered to have an acceptable risk of early mortality with
             intensive chemotherapy as determined by the attending physician at the time of the
             initial visit; since the specific therapy within each arm will be determined after
             randomization, there is no threshold of organ dysfunction or performance status for
             inclusion; the attending may use metrics such as Treatment Related Mortality Score
             (TRM) or Karnofsky performance status, in addition to clinical values (age, platelet
             count, serum albumin, secondary or de novo disease, white blood cell count,
             peripheral blood blast percentage, and serum creatinine) to determine if a patient
             should be included

          -  Considered a potential transplant candidate; the attending physician will determine
             transplant candidacy at the time of initial visit

          -  Human leukocyte antigen (HLA)-typing must be requested by the time of enrollment, but
             does not need to be resulted to enroll

          -  Males should be willing to use an effective contraceptive method during the study and
             for a minimum of 6 months after study treatment

          -  Women must be postmenopausal or must be willing to use an acceptable method of
             contraception to avoid pregnancy for the entire period of the study and for at least
             3 months after the study; a postmenopausal woman is defined as a woman who has
             experienced amenorrhea &gt; 12 consecutive months or a woman on hormone replacement
             therapy with documented follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) level &gt; 35 mIU/mL; for
             patients in whom menopausal state is in question, a negative pregnancy test will be
             required prior to enrollment

          -  Capable of understanding the investigational nature, potential risks and benefits of
             the study, and able to provide valid informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A diagnosis of acute promyelocytic leukemia as defined by the 2008 World Health
             Organization classification system

          -  Previous treatment for MDS or AML with intensive chemotherapy regimen (induction
             chemotherapy) or hypomethylating agent; previous treatment with iron chelation,
             growth factors (filgrastim [GCSF], erythropoiesis stimulating agent, or
             thrombopoietin mimetics), small molecule inhibitors, or immune modulatory drugs
             (thalidomide, lenalidomide) is acceptable

          -  Use of any anticancer therapy within 2 weeks before study entry with the exception of
             hydroxyurea

          -  Have any other severe concurrent disease, or have a history of serious organ
             dysfunction or disease involving the heart, kidney, liver, or other organ system that
             may place the patient at undue risk to undergo treatment

          -  Patients with a systemic fungal, bacterial, viral, or other infection not controlled
             (defined as exhibiting ongoing signs/symptoms related to the infection and without
             improvement, despite appropriate antibiotics or other treatment)

          -  Pregnant or lactating patients

          -  Any uncontrolled or significant concurrent disease, illness, or psychiatric disorder
             that would compromise patient safety or compliance, interfere with consent, study
             participation, follow up, or interpretation of study results

          -  Clinical evidence suggestive of central nervous system (CNS) involvement with
             leukemia unless a lumbar puncture confirms the absence of leukemic blasts in the
             cerebrospinal fluid (CSF)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bart Scott</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bart L. Scott</last_name>
      <phone>800-422-6237</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bart L. Scott</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 14, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>myelodysplastic syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic myelomonocytic leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>bone marrow transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>hypomethylating agent</keyword>
  <keyword>induction chemotherapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelomonocytic, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelomonocytic, Acute</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Azacitidine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cytarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Decitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Daunorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Idarubicin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
