<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="79015">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02015546</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00036210</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02015546</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Switching From Generic Selective Serotonin Reuptake Inhibitors (SSRIs) and Selective Serotonin and Norepinephrine Reuptake Inhibitors (SNRIs) to Three Different Dose Initiation Strategies With Vilazodone</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, 8-week Comparing Safety and Tolerability of Switching From Generic Selective Serotonin Reuptake Inhibitors (SSRIs) and Selective Serotonin and Norepinephrine Reuptake Inhibitors (SNRIs) to Three Different Dose Initiation Strategies With Vilazodone</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Vilazodone HCl under the trade name Viibryd™ is approved by the U.S. FDA for the treatment
      of major depressive disorder in adults.  The purpose of this study is to evaluate the
      efficacy (how well the drug works), safety (the side effects), and tolerability (how well
      tolerated) of Vilazodone in preventing relapse or recurrence of depression. As vilazodone is
      not approved by the United States Food and Drug Administration (FDA) to prevent the
      recurrence of depression, for the purposes of this study it is considered investigational.
      The word &quot;investigational&quot; means that the study drug is still being tested in research
      studies and has not been approved for this use by the FDA.  During the course of this study,
      there are times where you will receive vilazodone and other times where you may receive
      vilazodone.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Discontinuation Emergent Signs and Symptoms Check List (DESS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Weeks 1, 2, 3, 4, 6,8, and 9</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary tolerability measure for discontinuation symptoms will be The Discontinuation Emergent Signs and Symptoms Check List (DESS). Discontinuation symptoms that do not respond to education and supportive psychotherapy will be managed by reinstituting the last dose of Vilazodone at which patients did not experience discontinuation symptoms and slowly tapering the dose over 1 week or longer, if necessary.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Safety as assessed by spontaneously reported adverse events.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Weeks 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 9</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety and tolerability will be assessed by spontaneously reported adverse events, Arizona Sexual Experience Scale (ASEX) scores, vital signs, physical examination findings, weight and BMI measurements, ECG and clinical laboratory assessments and evaluating reasons for dropout from the trial.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in MADRS scores from Baseline to Week 9</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline &amp; Week 9</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The efficacy of switching to three different doses of vilazodone (10 mg/d, 20 mg/d, 40 mg/d) from equivalent dose range of generic SSRIs or SSNRIs in patients with MDD measured by the MADRS..</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Rate and intensity of discontinuation symptoms (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Weeks 1, 2, 3, 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Intensity of AEs will be measured by rating the severity and duration of AEs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the rate of in severity of discontinuation symptoms (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Weeks 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8 and 9.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Compare the rate and severity of discontinuation symptoms following abrupt discontinuation versus a 1-week taper of vilazodone at the end of the 8-week trial.
Intensity of AEs will be measured by rating the severity and duration of AEs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder (MDD)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vilazodone 10mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Vilazodone 10 mg/d arm (10mg/d initiation dose, titrated to 40 mg/d in 2 weeks, continued for 8 week trial)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vilazodone 20mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>vilazodone 20 mg arm (20mg/d initiation dose, titrated to 40 mg/d in 1 week, continued for 8-week trial)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vilazodone 40mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>vilazodone 40 mg/d arm (40 mg/d initiation and continuation dose for 8-week trial.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vilazodone</intervention_name>
    <description>All subjects will receive Vilazodone at 10, 20 or 40mg.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vilazodone 10mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Vilazodone 20mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Vilazodone 40mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Viibryd</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 18-65 years inclusive

          2. DSM-IV Diagnosis of major depressive disorder

          3. If female, nonpregnant/nonlactating

          4. If a sexually active female of reproductive potential, must be using adequate
             contraception (i.e., oral contraceptives, barrier protection, or prior tubal
             ligation)

          5. Inadequate response to  antidepressants: having a score of ≥14 on the 17-item HAMD or
              a CGI-S score of ≥ 3 after  a retrospective confirmation of an adequate trial of a
             single antidepressant (defined as an 6-week trial of acceptable therapeutic dose [40
             mg of fluoxetine, paroxetine  30 mg of citalopram, 20 mg of escitalopram, 37.5 mg of
             paroxetine CR, 150 mg of sertraline, 100 mg of fluvoxamine, 225 mg of venlafaxine XR)

          6. Lack of tolerability of antidepressants:  Patient reports of side effects  that are
             judged to be clinically meaningful by the investigator

          7. HAMD item 2 score ≥ 2 at screening

          8. Duration of current MDD ≥ 4 weeks and &lt; 24 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any Axis I disorder within previous six months of screening except Generalized
             Anxiety Disorder, Social Anxiety Disorder, Panic Disorder and Simple Phobias

          2. MDD with postpartum onset, psychotic features or seasonal features

          3. DSM-IV substance abuse or dependence in the previous  6 months

          4. Medically unstable as judged by study investigators on clinical and/or laboratory
             findings

          5. Lack of capacity to provide informed, written, consent to investigators

          6. Previous intolerance to vilazodone or current use of vilazodone at  screening or
             within 3 months of study entry

          7. Significant suicide risk as judged by the investigator based on information collected
             on the Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale (CSSRS)

          8. History of augmentation with atypical antipsychotics, lithium, T3 or another
             antidepressant within 3 months of screening

          9. Failure of ≥ 3 adequate trials of different antidepressants for the current episode
             of MDD

         10. Concomitant medications: All medications for pre existing medical conditions will be
             permitted to continue unchanged provided subjects are on a stable dose of at least 12
             weeks.  Subjects on concomitant mood stabilizers or atypical antipsychotics will
             require a 2-week washout prior to screening visit. Subjects on a minimum of 3 month
             of stable dose of hypnotics (e.g. zolpidem 10 mg per day or benzodiazepine dose of ≤
             2 mg per day of lorazepam or trazodone ≤ 100 mg per day or quetiapine ≤ 100 mg per
             day) will be allowed to continue their hypnotic medication at the same dose.
             Quetiapine at doses ≤ 100 mg per day is appropriate only for hypnotic effects. Over
             the counter medications will be permitted if in the opinion of the investigator, they
             are not considered to have any significant impact on the study. Any medication that
             has the potential to cause a clinical significant drug interaction with vilazodone in
             the judgment of the investigator will require a washout.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ashwin A Patkar, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University Health Systems</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Medical Center / Civitan Building</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 13, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 8, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Major Depressive Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Vilazodone</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Norepinephrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Serotonin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Serotonin Uptake Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
