<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="53508">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01722331</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3222-010</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-002255-42</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P07770</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01722331</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Subcutaneous MK-3222, Followed by an Optional Long-Term Safety Extension Study, in Participants With Moderate-to-Severe Chronic Plaque Psoriasis (MK-3222-010)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A 64-Week, Phase 3, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled, Parallel Design Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety/Tolerability of Subcutaneous Tildrakizumab (SCH 900222/MK-3222), Followed by an Optional Long-Term Safety Extension Study, in Subjects With Moderate-to-Severe Chronic Plaque Psoriasis (Protocol No. MK-3222-010)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is being conducted to evaluate the efficacy and safety/tolerability of
      subcutaneous MK-3222, followed by an optional long-term safety

      extension study, in participants with moderate-to-severe chronic plaque psoriasis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Participants With Psoriasis Area Sensitivity Index 75 (PASI-75) Response at Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Participants With a Physician's Global Assessment (PGA) Score of Clear or Minimal With at Least a 2 Grade Reduction From Baseline at Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Experiencing Adverse Events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 276</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Discontinuing Due to Drug-Related AEs</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 276</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Experiencing an AE Up to Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Discontinuing Study Treatment Due to an AE Up to Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Participants With PASI-90 Response At Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Participants With PASI-100 Response at Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in the Participant Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI) at Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Participants With DLQI Score of 0 or 1 at Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">885</enrollment>
  <condition>Plaque Psoriasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3222 200 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MK-3222 administered subcutaneously (SC) at a dose of 200 mg at Week 0 and Week 4, and then every 12 weeks until study end or participant discontinuation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3222 100 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MK-3222 administered SC at a dose of 100 mg at Week 0 and Week 4, and then every 12 weeks until study end or participant discontinuation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Matching placebo administered SC at Week 0 and Week 4.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MK-3222 200 mg</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3222 200 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SCH 900222</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MK-3222 100 mg</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3222 100 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SCH 900222</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Matching Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical diagnosis of moderate-to-severe plaque psoriasis for at least 6 months prior
             to study enrollment

          -  A candidate for phototherapy or systemic therapy

          -  For the extension study: must have completed Part 3 of the base study

          -  For the extension study: must have achieved at least a PASI-50 response by the end of
             Part 3 of the base study

          -  For the extension study: must have received active MK-3222 treatment within 12 weeks
             prior to the end of Part 3 of the base study

          -  Premenopausal female participants must agree to abstain from heterosexual activity or
             use a medically accepted method of contraception or use appropriate effective
             contraception as per local regulations or guidelines

          -  If enrolled at a Japanese site, participants with psoriatic arthritis using
             non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) must be on a stable dose for at least
             4 weeks prior to the first dose of study drug and must not be expected to require an
             increase in dose over the course of the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has erythrodermic psoriasis, predominantly pustular psoriasis, medication-induced or
             medication-exacerbated psoriasis, or new onset guttate psoriasis

          -  Current or history of severe psoriatic arthritis and is well-controlled on current
             treatment

          -  Women of child-bearing potential that are pregnant, intend to become pregnant within
             6 months of completing the trial, or that are breast feeding

          -  Expected to require topical treatment, phototherapy, or systemic treatment during the
             trial

          -  Presence of any infection

          -  History of recurrent infection requiring treatment with systemic antibiotics within 2
             weeks of screening

          -  Previous use of MK-3222 or other IL-23/Th-17 pathway inhibitors including P40, p19,
             and IL-17 antagonists

          -  Evidence of active or untreated latent tuberculosis (TB)

          -  Positive test for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis B surface antigen
             (HBs Ag) or hepatitis C virus (HCV)

          -  At Japanese sites, positive test for HBs antibody and hepatitis B virus (HBV)
             deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA)

          -  At Japanese sites, positive test for the Hepatitis B core (HBc) antibody and HBV DNA

          -  For the extension study: women of child-bearing potential that are pregnant, intend
             to become pregnant within 6 months of completing the trial, or that are breast
             feeding

          -  For the extension study: active or uncontrolled significant organ dysfunction or
             clinically significant laboratory abnormalities

          -  For the extension study: expected to require topical treatment, phototherapy, or
             systemic treatment during the extension study

          -  At Japanese sites, abnormal for Beta D Glucan and/or KL-6 test result(s) at the
             screening visit.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>Japan</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
    <country>Australia</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 2, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Psoriasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
