<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="6711">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02115503</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DSA 3242014</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02115503</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Prospective, Global, Multi-center, Treatment Registry Study of Intravenous Immunoglobulin Maintenance Therapy in Alloantibody Positive Renal Allograft Recipients</brief_title>
  <acronym>DSA</acronym>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Global, Multi-center, Treatment Registry Study of Intravenous Immunoglobulin Maintenance Therapy in Alloantibody Positive Renal Allograft Recipients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Databean</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Octapharma</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Databean</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Data and Safety Monitoring Board</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this treatment registry study is to determine if monthly infusions of
      Intravenous Immunoglobulin (IVIg) for 6 months will neutralize donor specific antibodies
      that are thought to be responsible for chronic rejection episodes in renal transplant
      subjects. 162 renal transplant subjects will receive IVIg 5% at 2gm/kg/month for 6 months
      and be followed for 3 years.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <target_duration>3 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>This trial with evaluate the treatment effect of maintenance intravenous immunoglobulin therapy on graft survival and glomerular filtration rates in renal transplant recipients who present with anti-human leukocyte antigen (HLA) antibodies (DSA).</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>This trial will provide an estimate of the kinetics of the change in anti-HLA antibodies Class I and/or Class II, as it relates to IVIg therapy response rates.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>This trial will provide an estimate of the kinetics of the change in anti-HLA antibodies Class I and/or Class II, as it relates to allograft function by estimated GFR.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>This trial will provide an estimate of the kinetics of the change in anti-HLA antibodies Class I and/or Class II, as it relates to allograft damage as determined by serum creatinine and proteinuria measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>This trial will provide an estimate of the kinetics of the change in anti-HLA antibodies Class I and/or Class II, as it relates to allograft damage as determined by renal biopsy (in a subset of 50 subjects)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">162</enrollment>
  <condition>Renal Transplant Recipients With Anti-HLA Antibody (DSA) Positivity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DSA positive</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Primary care clinic
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject is 18 years of age or older

          -  Able to provide voluntary written informed consent

          -  Renal transplant recipient at least 6 months post-transplant

          -  On stable doses of maintenance immunosuppression for at least 14 days prior to study
             entry and remains on stable maintenance doses for the duration of the study

          -  Presence of DSA above 2999 but equal to, or below, 15,000 mean fluorescence intensity
             (MFI) single    antigen bead assay via Luminex (normalized 3,000 - 15,000 MFI,
             inclusive) measured within 6 months prior to consent

          -  Female subjects must be post-menopausal for at least 1 year, or surgically
             sterilized, or must agree to use two effective methods of birth control from the time
             of consent through 30 days after the last dose of IVIg.

          -  Male subjects must be surgically sterilized, or must agree to use two effective
             methods of birth control from the time of consent through 30 days after the last dose
             of IVIg

          -  Subject is compliant and intends to be available for follow-up study period of 3
             years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Re-transplant or multi-organ transplant

          -  History of anaphylactic or severe systemic reactions to human immunoglobulin

          -  IgA deficient subjects with antibodies against IgA and a history of hypersensitivity

          -  Serum creatinine &gt; 3.0 mg/dL within 90 days prior to consent

          -  Recipients of ABO incompatible kidney transplants

          -  Biopsy-proven acute rejection within 6 months prior to consent defined as Acute
             Cellular Rejection [Banff grade I (including IA and IB), grade II (including IIA and
             IIB) or grade III], an antibody-mediated rejection with C4d positivity, or chronic
             rejection with C4d positivity (C4d positivity is defined as staining diffuse in
             peritubular capillary area. Isolated C4d glomerular staining or C4d staining of &lt; 50%
             of the peritubular capillaries will not be exclusion criteria). Borderline cellular
             rejection will not be excluded (Banff 2005)

          -  Biopsy proven transplant glomerulopathy (TG) (Banff 2007 - cg score ≥2) within 6
             months prior to consent

          -  Evidence of proteinuria (&gt; 3 grams) within the 6 months prior to consent

          -  History of CMV+ or EBV+ viremia since transplantation

          -  History of HCV positivity (by PCR).

          -  History of post-transplant lymphoproliferative disease.

          -  History of polyoma virus nephropathy, or BK nephritis, or BK serum PCR &gt;10,000
             copies/mL.

          -  HIV-positive

          -  HBsAg-positive.

          -  Recipients of a kidney from a donor who tests positive for HIV, HBsAg or anti-HCV.

          -  History of malignancy within the past 5 years that is not considered to be cured,
             with the exception of complete resection of localized basal cell carcinoma of the
             skin (excised ≥ 2 years prior to enrollment).

          -  Subjects who are receiving everolimus, sirolimus or azathioprine as immunosuppressive
             agents and who are unwilling, or unable, to change to mycophenolate mofetil or
             mycophenolic acid within 30 days prior to consent

          -  Subjects receiving cyclosporine as an immunosuppressive agent and who is unwilling,
             or unable, to change to tacrolimus (Prograf) within 30 days prior to consent

          -  Absolute neutrophil count of &lt;1,000/mm3 within 90 days prior to consent

          -  Platelet count &lt;60,000/mm3 within 90 days prior to consent

          -  Evidence of severe liver disease with abnormal liver profile (aspartate
             aminotransferase [AST] or alanine aminotransferase [ALT] &gt; 3 times upper limit of
             normal [ULN]) within 90 days prior to consent

          -  Total bilirubin &gt; 1.5 times ULN within 90 days prior to consent

          -  Post-transplant history of cardiovascular disease including:

               1. Myocardial infarction (MI) within 6 months prior to consent

               2. New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class II - IV heart failure symptoms with LVEF
                  of ≤40% within 6 months prior to consent

               3. Electrocardiographic evidence of acute ischemia or severe conduction system
                  abnormalities within 6 months prior to consent, any ECG abnormality at screening
                  must be documented by the investigator as not medically relevant.

          -  Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women

          -  Enrolled in any other treatment study within 30 days of consent

          -  Serious medical illness (other than renal disease), or psychiatric illness likely to
             interfere with study participation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 4, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Isoantibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins, Intravenous</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rho(D) Immune Globulin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
