<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="40108">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01793623</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRO12050391</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01793623</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of Atrial Tissue Obtained From Patients Undergoing Heart Surgery and Tissue Banking</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessment of Atrial Tissue Obtained From Patients Undergoing Heart Surgery and Tissue Banking</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pittsburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Over the past decade, techniques have been refined which permit an enormous amount of
      information relevant to disease mechanisms to be gained from the examination of heart
      tissue. The Cardiovascular Institute has extensive experience with these techniques, and has
      utilized them to examine other heart disease substrates. In this study, the investigators
      propose to obtain heart tissue at the time of cardiac surgery which would otherwise be
      discarded. Their plan is to examine this tissue and correlate their findings with clinical
      data. Their hope is that the proposed study will provide insight into atrial physiology,
      including the molecular mechanisms underlying atrial disease and the potential development
      of atrial fibrillation (AF).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Atrial fibrillation (AF), a disorder of heart rhythm, is epidemic in the United States,
      affecting nearly 3 million people. AF arises in a variety of settings, often in association
      with other cardiac disease. Demographic and clinical factors can be utilized to profile
      &quot;at-risk&quot; patients, but the predictive value of such algorithms is low. The reasons for this
      presumably relate to the fact that these factors are interacting with the tissue substrate
      in a variable way. In addition, correlations such as these provide no insight into
      mechanisms associated with the development of AF in patients without other known heart
      disease, which is commonplace. Over the past decade, techniques have been refined which
      permit an enormous amount of information relevant to disease mechanisms to be gained from
      examination of heart tissue. The Cardiovascular Institute has extensive experience with
      these techniques, and has utilized them to examine other heart disease substrates. In this
      study, we propose to obtain heart tissue at the time of cardiac surgery which would
      otherwise be discarded.

      Our plan is to examine this tissue and correlate our findings with clinical data. Our hope
      is that the proposed study will provide insight into atrial physiology, including the
      molecular mechanisms underlying atrial disease and the potential development of AF.

      This will be a prospective tissue bank for atrial tissue. We propose an enrollment of 300
      subjects, to take place at UPMC Presbyterian over a 5 year period. Subjects will be
      recruited from among those patients referred for non-emergent surgery on the heart for
      standard indications. The patient's medical record will be reviewed and health information
      recorded that includes but is not limited to demographics, heart disease history, other past
      medical history, lab work,drug therapy,and all cardiac testing the patient has undergone
      prior to surgery. Patients undergoing surgery will have residual atrial tissue which would
      otherwise be discarded (related to cannulation and/or appendectomy). Thus, obtaining this
      tissue will have no effect on the flow, duration, or outcome of the operative procedure.

      Tissue assessment will include:

        -  Microscopic histology using standard tissue stains; and

        -  Characterization of gene expression.

      Characterization of gene expression will be performed using a multiplicity of techniques
      which focus on DNA, RNA and proteins produced by the various cells comprising atrial tissue.
      Expression of a variety of genes known to be important in other cardiac diseases will be
      analyzed. In addition, expression of novel genes previously not known to be relevant to
      heart disease may be examined.

      Tissue assessment data will be correlated with clinical data including preoperative AF
      history, demographic information, features of the medical history, details of cardiac
      structure/function(obtained by examining preoperative tests performed for standard
      indications), and the incidence of postoperative AF as a first arrhythmia diagnosis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case-Only, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evidence of atrial physiology</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 1, Atrial tissue sample obtained at the time of surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Normally discarded atrial tissue samples will be collected at the time of cardiac surgery and microscopic histology will be performed using standard tissue stains</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evidence of underlying molecular mechanisms of atrial disease</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 1, Atrial tissue samples obtained at the time of surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Normally discarded atrial tissue samples will be collected at the time of cardiac surgery and the samples will be assayed for gene expression</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>nonemergent heart surgery, atrial tissue</arm_group_label>
    <description>patients undergoing non-emergent heart surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>atrial tissue</intervention_name>
    <description>retrieval of discarded atrial tissue</description>
    <arm_group_label>nonemergent heart surgery, atrial tissue</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      (1) myocardial tissue (2) DNA
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects are patients of UPMC Cardiothoracic Surgery who are having standard of care open
        heart surgery
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years or over

          -  Referred for heart surgery for standard indication

          -  Competent to give informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to give informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David S Schwartzman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David S Schwartzman, MD</last_name>
    <phone>412-802-3372</phone>
    <email>schwartzmand@upmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kimberly A Veltre, MSN</last_name>
    <phone>412-864-1420</phone>
    <email>veltrek@upmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Pittsburgh Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kimberly Veltre, MSN</last_name>
      <phone>412-864-1420</phone>
      <email>veltrek@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Dina Poole, RN</last_name>
      <phone>412-647-2931</phone>
      <email>pooledr@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vinay Badhwar, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Li YY, Feldman AM, Sun Y, McTiernan CF. Differential expression of tissue inhibitors of metalloproteinases in the failing human heart. Circulation. 1998 Oct 27;98(17):1728-34.</citation>
    <PMID>9788826</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 24, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 17, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Schwartzman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine, University of Pittsburgh</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>atrial fibrillation</keyword>
  <keyword>genetics</keyword>
  <keyword>cardiac arrhythmias</keyword>
  <keyword>heart disease</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
