<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="36958">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02086721</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Toxicity L19-IL2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02086721</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of Toxicity of the Immunocytokine L19-IL2 Administered Directly After the Course of Stereotactic Ablative Body Radiotherapy in Patients Suffering From Oligometastatic Non-small Cell Lung Cancer.</brief_title>
  <acronym>L19--IL2</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase I Clinical Study Combining L19-IL2 With Stereotactic Ablative Body Radiotherapy in Patients With Oligometastatic Non-small Cell Lung Cancer.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Maastricht Radiation Oncology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Maastricht Radiation Oncology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Netherlands: The Central Committee on Research Involving Human Subjects (CCMO)</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The formation of metastasis is responsible for as much as 90% of cancer-associated
      mortality. In spite of recent advances in oncologic therapy, approximately 50 % of the lung
      cancer patients have already overt disseminated cancer at diagnosis. Additionally, numerous
      patients with locoregional disease initially treated with curative intent develop
      (oligo)metastases during the course of disease. In both instances, these stage IV patients
      are generally considered to be incurable and mostly treated palliatively.

      Oligometastases, defined as 1-5 sites of active disease on whole body imaging, was coined to
      refer to isolated sites of metastasis resembling limited tumor metastatic capacity. The
      implication of this concept is that local cancer treatments are curative in a proportion of
      patients with metastases and that incorporating local therapy is a conceptually attractive
      approach. In several, but not all, academic centers the standard treatment of patients with
      oligometastases in good general health is standard chemotherapy followed by surgery or by
      Stereotactic Ablative Body Radiotherapy (SABR) with radical dose on the macroscopic visible
      tumors.

      The widespread introduction of SABR and of minimally invasive surgery has fuelled research
      in treating patients with oligometastases. Indeed, local control of metastases can be
      obtained in virtually all parts of the body with a low proportion of patients experiencing
      severe side effects. In the few prospective studies published to date, approximately 20% of
      patients remained free of recurrence several years after treatment when all sites of disease
      were targeted by radiation.

      Along with standard anti-cancer therapeutic modalities like chemotherapy and radiotherapy
      (RT), immunotherapy has recently gained a lot of attention.

      Angiogenesis is one of the hallmarks of cancer, and therefore, considerable efforts have
      been made to exploit this unique target for selective drug delivery. One of the appealing
      targets for both approaches is the splice variant of fibronectin containing extra domain B
      (EDB), which is abundantly expressed in vascular endothelial cells of a variety of primary
      tumors as well as metastases , but virtually absent in normal tissues. Recently, a human
      recombinant scFv fragment directed against EDB, designated L19, was developed and
      subsequently combined with the pro-inflammatory interleukin-2 (IL2), resulting in the
      immunocytokine L19-IL2. L19-IL2 delivers high doses of IL2 to the (metastatic) tumor site(s)
      exploiting the selective expression of EDB on newly formed blood vessels. Interleukin-2
      (IL2) plays an essential role in the activation phases of both specific and natural immune
      responses. Even though it has no direct cytotoxic effects on cancer cells, it can induce
      tumor regression by stimulating a potent cell-mediated response. In summary, L19-IL2 is an
      immunocytokine which will stimulate immune response specifically in tumors with angiogenesis
      and tissue remodeling.

      Radiotherapy is a particularly interesting partner for immunotherapy, since it can be
      harnessed to specifically modify the immunogenicity of the primary tumors and their
      microenvironment, in the attempt to generate an in situ immunization of the host against a
      patient's own cancer. Our hypothesis is that three independent therapeutic approaches will
      synergize to improve dramatically survival in patients with oligometastases of solid tumors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. Tumor vasculature Profound differences exist between vascular endothelium and
           surrounding stroma of normal tissues and tumors. Tumor vasculature is extremely
           disorganized and tortuous. Vascular shunts are frequent, and distinguishing arterioles
           from venules can be challenging. Apart from the architecture, the blood flow itself is
           strikingly altered: it can be sluggish, sometimes stationary or even reverse. The
           endothelium in tumors proliferates rapidly and contributes to active angiogenesis. The
           direct contact of the tumor endothelium with the host's blood pool makes this site a
           unique target for selective drug delivery.

        2. L19 Fibronectin (FN) is a broadly present soluble constituent of plasma and other body
           fluids. FN usually exists as a dimer formed by two nearly identical (approximately 250
           kDa) subunits covalently linked near their C-terminus by a pair of disulfide bonds.
           Even though FN molecules are the product of a single gene, the resulting protein can
           exist in multiple forms that arise from alternative spicing of pre-mRNA that can
           generate up to 20 variants in humans. Splicing occurs in 3 regions of the FN gene,
           leading to inclusion or exclusion of either one of the two type III repeats, named EDB
           and EDA. The 91 amino acid sequence of EDB is identical in mice, rats, rabbits, dogs
           and humans. EDB-containing FN is dispensable during embryogenesis, but is thought to
           play a modulating role in the growth of connective tissues. In adults, EDB-FN is highly
           expressed in normal tissues during angiogenesis, but not in mature vessels.
           Furthermore, EDB-containing FN is abundantly found in solid tumors. It is mainly
           produced by tumor cells and deposited in the subendothelial extracellular matrix of
           solid tumors and hematological malignancies.

           L19 is the single chain (scFv) human antibody that specifically targets EDB-FN.
           Antibody fragments in small scFv formats are useful and versatile tools with various
           advantages including rapid blood clearance and easy manipulation for antibody
           engineering. The L19 antibody has been shown to recognize and target EDB-FN in vivo
           both in animal models and patients. In past years, the L19 antibody has been conjugated
           with numerous agents, including therapeutic radionuclides, and cytokines.

        3. Interleukin-2 Cytokines are a heterogeneous group of soluble small polypeptides or
           glycoproteins exerting pleiotropic or redundant effects promoting growth,
           differentiation, and activation of normal cells. Cytokines produced by immune cells may
           have pro- or anti-inflammatory and immune-modulatory activities. In malignant diseases,
           cytokine production and release can be affected by the tumor itself and/or therapeutic
           interventions. Cytokines may also display potent anticancer activities, but are
           frequently hampered by treatment-related toxicities prohibiting dose-escalation to
           therapeutically effective concentrations.

           Interleukin-2 (IL2) plays an essential role in the activation phases of both specific
           and natural immune responses. Even though it has no direct cytotoxic effects on cancer
           cells, it can induce tumor regression by stimulating a potent cell-mediated response.
           As such, IL2 is one of the treatment options in metastatic renal cell carcinoma
           patients.

        4. L19-IL2 In order to overcome toxicity while simultaneously delivering therapeutic doses
           of IL2 to the tumor issue, the elegant option of combining the anti-EDB scFv L19
           antibody with IL2 was pursued. It has been shown that the L19-IL2 conjugate mediates
           the selective delivery and accumulation of IL2 at tumor endothelial cells, where the
           EDB antigen is expressed during angiogenesis, leading to a dramatic increase of the
           therapeutic efficacy of IL2. In the first preclinical study, 80% of the xenograft
           tumors (including teratocarcinoma and small cell lung cancer) tackled with L19-IL2 were
           subsequently composed of connective and necrotic tissue. At the same time an increase
           in the levels of interferon-gamma and of cytotoxic lymphocytes, macrophages and natural
           killer cells was found. These histological and therapeutic effects were underlined in a
           orthotopic pancreatic cancer model treated with the antibody-cytokine conjugate. One
           year later, this response percentage was repeated in Ramos lymphoma xenografts treated
           with L19-IL2 and the anti-CD20 antibody rituximab whereby a complete remission lasting
           for more than one year was found in 4 of the 5 mice treated.

      In a recent phase I/II clinical trial, the use of L19-IL2 was proven safe in a variety of
      stage IV malignancies with a recommended dose of 22.5 Mio IU. Furthermore, it was safely
      combined with dacarbazine in stage IV melanoma patients maintaining the same recommended
      dose level. In the first study, the overall objective response rate was reported to be 51%
      after two cycles, and in the second this rate was 28% with one complete response still
      ongoing 21 months after treatment initiation.

      At present, three phase I/II clinical trials on L19-IL2 alone or in combination with
      chemotherapy for patients with metastatic melanoma (ClinicalTrials.gov numbers: NCT01055522
      and NCT01253096) and pancreatic cancer (ClinicalTrials.gov number: NCT01198522) are ongoing.

      Summary Study Design

      Details on SABR:

      Prescribed dose is risk adapted to the metastatic localization and closeness to organs at
      risk (in accordance with local protocol of MAASTRO clinic). Patients will receive a dose
      schedule of 1 x 30 Gy, 3 x 15-20 Gy; 5 x 12 Gy; 8 x 7.5 Gy; to the 80 % or 100 % isodose
      which should encompass the periphery of the PTV as closely as possible. Maximum dose is not
      restricted but volumes with a dose higher than 105% must be located within the gross tumor.
      The minimum dose allowed is EQD2α/ẞ10 =60 Gy, an ablative dose with EQD2iso=≥ 87.5Gy10
      should always be the objective. Treatment will be delivered with intensity modulated arcs
      treatments.

      Step -1:  Assessment of the toxicity of 10 Mio IU of L19-IL2 (n=3-6); this step is only
      chosen when dose-limiting toxicity occurs in Step 1.

      Administration of 10 Mio IU of L19-IL2 given on day 1, 3 and 5 of each 21-day cycle (max. 6
      cycles) via i.v. bolus injection starting within one week after completion of SABR.

      Toxicity will be scored at every intravenous (i.v.) drug administration and on day 7, 14 and
      21 of the cycle, according to the CTCAE4.0 scoring system. Hematology, liver and kidney
      function will be controlled on day 1, 3, and 5 prior to L19-IL2 administration, and on day
      7, 14 and 21.

      When in 0/3 patients a toxicity of grade 2 or more has occurred step 1 is considered safe.
      If in 1/3 or more patients a grade 2 or more toxicity has occurred, 3 more patients will be
      included in this step. If another grade 2 or more toxicity occurs in 1/3 or more patients,
      the study will be stopped. When at maximum 1/6 patients experience grade 2 toxicity, this
      step will be considered safe. When step 1 is considered safe, step 2 will be initiated.

      Step 1:  Assessment of the toxicity of 15 Mio IU of L19-IL2 (n=3-6) Administration of 15 Mio
      IU of L19-IL2 given on day 1, 3 and 5 of each 21-day cycle (max. 6 cycles) via i.v. bolus
      injection starting within one week after completion of SABR.

      Toxicity will be scored at every i.v. drug administration and on day 7, 14 and 21 of the
      cycle, according to the CTCAE4.0 scoring system. Hematology, liver and kidney function will
      be controlled on day 1, 3, and 5 prior to L19-IL2 administration, and on day 7, 14 and 21.

      When in 0/3 patients a toxicity of grade 2 or more has occurred step 1 is considered safe.
      If in 1/3 or more patients a grade 2 or more toxicity has occurred, 3 more patients will be
      included in this step. If another grade 2 or more toxicity occurs in 1/3 or more patients,
      the study will be stopped. When at maximum 1/6 patients experience grade 2 toxicity, this
      step will be considered safe. When step 1 is considered safe, step 2 will be initiated.

      Step 2:  Assessment of the toxicity of 22.5 Mio IU of L19-IL2 (n=3-6) Administration of 22.5
      Mio IU of L19-IL2 given on day 1, 3 and 5 of each 21-day cycle (max. 6 cycles) via i.v.
      bolus injection starting within one week after completion of SABR.

      Toxicity will be scored at every i.v. drug administration and on day 7, 14 and 21 of the
      cycle, according to the CTCAE4.0 scoring system. Hematology, liver and kidney function will
      be controlled on day 1, 3, and 5 prior to L19-IL2 administration, and on day 7, 14 and 21.

      When in 0/3 patients a toxicity of grade 2 or more has occurred step 1 is considered safe.
      If in 1/3 or more patients a grade 2 or more toxicity has occurred, 3 more patients will be
      included in this step. If another grade 2 or more toxicity occurs in 1/3 or more patients,
      the study will be stopped. When at maximum 1/6 patients experience grade 2 toxicity, this
      step will be considered safe. When step 1 is considered safe, step 2 will be initiated.

      Step 3:  Expansion cohort of the maximally tolerable dose (n=10) Administration of the
      maximally tolerable dose of L19-IL2 given on day 1, 3 and 5 of each 21-day cycle (max. 6
      cycles) via i.v. bolus injection starting within one week after completion of SABR.

      Toxicity will be scored at every i.v. drug administration and on day 7, 14 and 21 of the
      cycle, according to the CTCAE4.0 scoring system. Hematology, liver and kidney function will
      be controlled on day 1, 3, and 5 prior to L19-IL2 administration, and on day 7, 14 and 21.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity (CTCAE 4.0)</measure>
    <time_frame>three months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Local control rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>non-invasive response evaluation using PET</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of outcome measures with PET-imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>correlation of outcome measures with immunological markers in tumor tissue.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oligometastatic non-small cell lung cancer patients; N=19-28</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>L19-IL2</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients receive a schedule of 1 x 30 Gy, 3 x 15-20 Gy; 5 x 12 Gy; 8 x 7.5 Gy; to the 80 % or 100 % isodose.
Step -1:  Toxicity of 10 Mio IU of L19-IL2 (n=3-6)10 Mio IU of L19-IL2 (max. 6 cycles) via i.v. bolus injection.
Toxicity scored at every i.v. drug administration and on day 7, 14 and 21. Step 1:  Toxicity of 15 Mio IU of L19-IL2 (n=3-6)(max. 6 cycles) via i.v. bolus injection.
Step 2:  Toxicity of 22.5 Mio IU of L19-IL2 (n=3-6)(max. 6 cycles) via i.v. bolus injection.
Toxicity scored at every i.v. drug administration and on day 7, 14 and 21 of the cycle.
Step 3:  Expansion cohort of the maximally tolerable dose (n=10) Administration of the maximally tolerable dose of L19-IL2(max. 6 cycles) via i.v. bolus injection.
Toxicity scored at every i.v. drug administration and on day 7, 14 and 21 of the cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oligometastatic non-small cell lung cancer patients; N=19-28</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria

          -  Histological or cytological confirmed oligometastatic non-small cell lung
             canceroccurring synchronous (at time of diagnosis) or metachronous (&gt; 6 months after
             radical treatment for primary tumor; i.e., surgically);

          -  ≤ 5 metastases, or 4 if the primary tumor is to be treated concomitantly;

          -  Maximal 3 metastatic lesions confined to one organ;

          -  Maximal 2 organ systems affected with metastases;

          -  Centrally located lung tumors should have a maximum diameter of 5 cm to facilitate
             SABR;

          -  WHO performance status 0 to 2;

          -  Patients with EGFR-mutations can be included in the study, but treatment with TK
             inhibitors is not allowed;

          -  Adequate lung function: FEV1 &gt; 1l; DLCO &gt; 30% of predicted;

          -  Adequate bone marrow: Normal white blood cell count and formula, normal platelet
             count, no anemia requiring blood transfusion or erythropoietin;

          -  Adequate hepatic function: total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) for
             the institution; ALT, AST, and alkaline phosphatase ≤ 2.5 x ULN for the institution);

          -  Adequate renal function: calculated creatinine clearance at least 60 ml/min;

          -  The patient is capable of complying with study procedures;

          -  Oral and written informed consent;

          -  Life expectancy of at least 12 weeks;

          -  18 years or older.

        Exclusion criteria

          -  Patients with brain metastases;

          -  T4 tumors that invade main bronchi, trachea or carina, adjacent vertebral body,
             esophagus, mediastinum, heart, or great vessels;

          -  Previous thoracic radiotherapy;

          -  Previous chemotherapy to treat recurrent NSCLC;

          -  Patients with malignant pleural nodules (pleural carcinosis), malignant pleural
             effusion, malignant pericardial effusion;

          -  Other active malignancy or malignancy within the last 5 years (with exception of
             localized skin basal/squamous cell carcinoma, bladder in situ carcinoma);

          -  Other histological/cytological forms of lung cancer;

          -  HIV infection, active infection, or active hepatitis;

          -  Acute or sub-acute coronary syndromes within the last year, heart insufficiency or
             irreversible cardiac arrhythmias;

          -  Pregnancy or breast-feeding.

        Stratification criteria:

          -  Synchronous versus metachronous oligometastatatic disease;

          -  number of oligometastases (1-2 versus 3-5);

          -  EGFR and ALK status;

          -  Squamous versus non-squamous pathology;

          -  Presence of liver metastasis;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Esther Troost, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+31 88 44 55 666</phone>
    <email>esther.troost@maastro.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Philippe Lambin, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+31 88 44 55 666</phone>
    <email>philippe.lambin@maastro.nl</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MAASTRO clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maastricht</city>
        <state>Limburg</state>
        <zip>6229 ET</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Esther Troost, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+31 88 44 55 666</phone>
      <email>esther.troost@maastro.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Chantal Overhof</last_name>
      <phone>+31 88 44 55 686</phone>
      <email>chantal.overhof@maastro.nl</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Philippe Lambin, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Esther Troost, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 11, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 3, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Interleukin-2</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
