<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="28287">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01735916</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MIRACLE EF</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01735916</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MIRACLE EF Clinical Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>MIRACLE EF</acronym>
  <official_title>MIRACLE EF Clinical Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medtronic Cardiac Rhythm Disease Management</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medtronic Cardiac Rhythm Disease Management</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is looking at whether the electrical treatment provided by a special type of
      pacemaker called a Cardiac Resynchronization Therapy (CRT) pacemaker may keep a patient's
      heart failure from getting worse. When the lower heart chambers (i.e. ventricles) are
      electrically paced to beat together by the CRT pacemaker, blood may be pumped to the body
      more efficiently.

      The CRT pacemaker being studied in this clinical trial is approved by the US Food and Drug
      Administration (FDA) for patients with moderate to severe heart failure, whose hearts pump
      blood inefficiently. In the MIRACLE EF study, patients who have heart failure with slightly
      less inefficient hearts will be observed to see if the electrical pacing treatment is better
      than not getting the treatment. This study is being conducted to support FDA approval of
      this type of pacemaker for people whose heart failure is less inefficient.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Medtronic, Inc. is sponsoring the MIRACLE EF study, a prospective, randomized, controlled,
      double-blinded, global multi-center, Cardiac Resynchronization Therapy (CRT) in Heart
      Failure (HF) clinical study. The purpose of this study is to evaluate market released CRT
      pacemaker (CRT-P) devices in symptomatic HF patients with less severe left ventricular
      systolic dysfunction, specifically patients with reduced left ventricular ejection fraction
      (LVEF) in the range of 36% to 50%. This study will support expansion of indications for CRT
      worldwide. The outcome of this study is expected to support modification of existing U.S.
      and Japanese labeling for Medtronic's implantable CRT-P devices and to provide further
      evidence to support changes to cardiology practice guidelines (ACC/AHA, ESC guidelines)
      regarding the use of CRT in patients with mild to moderate HF.

      Following enrollment and the baseline assessment, eligible subjects will be implanted with a
      CRT-P system and randomized in a 2:1 fashion to either treatment (CRT-P ON) or control
      (CRT-P OFF) groups. Study subjects will be followed for a minimum of 24 months or until
      study closure, and will remain in their randomized groups until their 60 month visit or
      until the study is stopped, whichever comes first. The effectiveness of CRT-P in this
      population will be assessed using a composite endpoint of time to first event, with event
      defined as All-cause mortality or HF Event. To assess the safety of CRT-P in this
      population, the primary safety endpoint will measure freedom from system-related
      complications at 6 months post-implant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to mortality or heart failure morbidity</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization to date of event, assessed for a minimum of 24 months and up to 60 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Primary Efficacy Endpoint: The time to first event, with event defined as:
All-cause mortality, or
HF Event, defined as either:
Inpatient hospitalization for HF, or
Outpatient event requiring invasive clinical intervention and management for HF (i.e. IV diuretics, ultrafiltration, or equivalent) and overnight stay</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to system-related complication</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of implant to the date of 6 month follow-up visit</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Primary Safety Endpoint: Time to first system-related complication in subjects with a successful implant</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization to date of death, for a minimum of 24 months and up to 60 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Time to death between the study groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to mortality or heart failure morbidity or worsening systolic function</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization to date of event, assessed for a minimum of 24 months and up to 60 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Secondary Composite Efficacy Endpoint: The time to first event, with event defined as:
All-cause mortality
HF Event, defined as either:
Inpatient hospitalization for HF, or
Outpatient event requiring invasive clinical intervention and management for HF (i.e. IV diuretics, ultrafiltration, or equivalent) and overnight stay, or
Worsening systolic function meeting an ICD/CRT-D indication, defined as:
A drop in LVEF to 35% or below, with an absolute decrease of greater than or equal to 10%, after maximum tolerated doses of guideline HF medications have been established</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recurrent HF Events</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization to date of event, assessed for a minimum of 24 months and up to 60 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The frequency of HF events between the study groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life (QoL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed from baseline visit to 24-month follow-up visit</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The quality of life between study groups and the change in quality of life over time between study groups using clinically accepted quality of life measures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reverse Remodeling by Echocardiography</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed from baseline visit to 24-month follow-up visit</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The change in LVEF between study groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2900</enrollment>
  <condition>Congestive Heart Failure</condition>
  <condition>Left Bundle Branch Block</condition>
  <condition>Systolic Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CRT-P ON</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>CRT-P Implant CRT-P ON</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CRT-P OFF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>CRT-P Implant CRT-P OFF</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CRT-P Implant</intervention_name>
    <description>The Medtronic Consulta CRT-P (models C3TR01, C4TR011) dual chamber implantable pacemaker with cardiac resynchronization therapy (CRT-P) is a multi-programmable cardiac device that monitors and regulates the patient's heart rate by providing single or dual chamber rate-responsive bradycardia pacing, and sequential biventricular pacing.
The device senses the electrical activity of the patient's heart using the electrodes of the implanted atrial and right ventricular leads. It then analyzes the heart rhythm based on selectable detection parameters. The device responds to bradyarrhythmias by providing bradycardia pacing therapy.
Simultaneous or sequential biventricular pacing is used to provide patients with cardiac resynchronization therapy. The device also provides diagnostic and monitoring information that assists with system evaluation and patient care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CRT-P ON</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>CRT-P OFF</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cardiac Resynchronization Therapy Pacemaker (CRT-P)</other_name>
    <other_name>Consulta CRT-P</other_name>
    <other_name>C4TR01</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CRT-P OFF</intervention_name>
    <description>Device programmed to minimal pacing at 40 beats/minute. Device and arrhythmia diagnostics may remain enabled.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CRT-P OFF</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient has diagnosis of chronic heart failure &gt; 90 days in duration

          -  Has left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) between 36% and 50%, inclusive, as
             documented at baseline or within 30 days prior to enrollment

          -  Is either: (a) NYHA Class III at enrollment or at baseline OR (b) NYHA Class II at
             enrollment or at baseline, with a documented hospitalization for HF in the 12 months
             prior to enrollment OR (c) NYHA Class II at enrollment or at baseline, without a
             documented hospitalization for HF in the prior 12 months, but with BNP ≥250 pg/ml or
             NT-proBNP ≥1000 pg/ml

          -  Has documented left bundle branch block (LBBB) with QRS ≥130ms at baseline or within
             30 days prior to enrollment.

          -  Is in sinus rhythm at time of enrollment or at the baseline visit.

          -  Has had no additions to or subtractions from non-diuretic heart failure medical
             therapy within 30 days prior to enrollment

          -  Is on maximum tolerated (guideline) dosages of medications in ACC/AHA guidelines for
             HF, Ischemic Heart Disease, Hypertension and AF as appropriate.

          -  Has signed and dated the study informed consent.

          -  Is able to receive a pectoral CRT-P implant.

          -  Is expected to remain available for follow-up visits.

          -  Is willing and able to comply with the Clinical Investigation Plan.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Requires permanent cardiac pacing.

          -  Indicated for implantable cardioverter defibrillator (ICD), such as for secondary
             prevention of prior sudden cardiac arrest, related to prior history of ventricular
             tachycardia and/or ventricular fibrillation.

          -  Less than 18 years of age, or under a higher minimum age requirement as defined by
             local law.

          -  Unstable angina or an acute MI within 40 days prior to enrollment.

          -  Coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) or percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI)
             within the 90 days prior to enrollment.

          -  Chronic (permanent) atrial arrhythmias. Chronic (permanent) atrial arrhythmias are
             defined as cases of long-standing atrial fibrillation (e.g., greater than 1 year) in
             which cardioversion has not been indicated or attempted.

          -  Cardioversion for atrial fibrillation within 30 days prior to enrollment.

          -  Treatable pericardial constraint within 30 days prior to enrollment.

          -  Restrictive (infiltrative) cardiomyopathies, such as amyloidosis, sarcoidosis, or
             hemochromatosis.

          -  Enrolled in a concurrent study, with the exception of a study-manager approved study
             that is strictly observational in nature and does not confound the results of this
             study (e.g. registries).

          -  Life expectancy of less than 24 months due to non-cardiac conditions.

          -  Pregnant, or of childbearing potential and not on a reliable form of birth control.

          -  CRT-P, pacemaker, ICD or CRT-D device implanted previously, or currently.

          -  Restrictive, hypertrophic, or reversible cardiomyopathy.

          -  Mechanical right heart valve.

          -  Primary valvular disease and is indicated for valve repair or replacement.

          -  Heart transplant, or is currently on a heart transplant list.

          -  Significant renal dysfunction, as manifested by serum creatinine level &gt;2.5 mg/dl or
             ≥275 μmol/L or estimated glomerular filtration rate (GFR) ≤30 mL/min/1.73 m2, which
             is documented within the 30 days prior to enrollment or at baseline.

          -  Significant hepatic dysfunction, as evidenced by a hepatic function panel (serum) &gt; 3
             times upper limit of normal, which is documented within the 30 days prior to
             enrollment or at baseline.

          -  Chronic or treatment-resistant severe anemia (hemoglobin &lt;10.0 g/dL), which is
             documented within the 30 days prior to enrollment or at baseline.

          -  On intravenous inotropic drug therapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cecilia Linde, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Karolinska Hospital, Stockholm, Sweden</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>John Muir Medical Center, Cor Cardiovascular Specialists, John Muir Medical Center (Concord), John Muir Cardiovascular Institute, Contra Costa Cardiology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Concord</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94520</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Scripps Clinic Torrey Pines, Scripps Green Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Jolla</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92037</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Greater Los Angeles Healthcare System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90073</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Eisenhower Desert Cardiology Center, Eisenhower Medical Center Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rancho Mirage</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92270</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Los Robles Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Thousand Oaks</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91360</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Colorado Health Medical Group, Memorial Hospital Colorado Springs</name>
      <address>
        <city>Colorado Springs</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80909</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hartford Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hartford</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bradenton Cardiology, Manatee Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bradenton</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>34205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Melbourne Internal Medicine Associates / Century Research Associates, Holmes Regional Medical Center Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32901</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aventura Hospital and Medical Center, Hospital Corporation of America (Aventura), Hospital Corporation of America (Miami)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33137</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University Hospital Midtown</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30308</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>WellStar Cobb Hospital, WellStar Kennestone Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marietta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30060</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Advocate Medical Group, Midwest Heart Specialists (Elmhurst), Elmhurst Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Elmhurst</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60126</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Prairie Education and Research Cooperative (Springfield IL), Prairie Education Research Consultants, St. John's Hospital (Springfield IL)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Springfield</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>62701</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>McFarland Clinic PC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ames</city>
        <state>Iowa</state>
        <zip>50010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cardiovascular Medicine PC (Davenport IA), Trinity (Rock Island), Midwest Cardiovascular Research Foundation, Trinity Bettendorf Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Davenport</city>
        <state>Iowa</state>
        <zip>52803</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Midwest Cardiology Associates PA, Menorah Medical Center, Centerpoint Medical Center, Overland Park Regional Medical Center Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Overland Park</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66209</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sparrow Clinical Research Institute, McLaren Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lansing</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48910</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>HealthEast HeartCare Clinic at Saint John's</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maplewood</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Minneapolis Heart Institute Foundation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55407</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Cardiovascular Center, University of Minnesota Medical Center Fairview</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>North Memorial Heart and Vascular Institute, North Memorial Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Robbinsdale</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55422</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Minneapolis Heart Institute Foundation, Mercy Hospital (Coon Rapids MN), Unity Hospital, United Hospital, Abbott Northwestern Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Paul</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55102</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Missouri Cardiovascular Specialists, Boone Hospital Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbia</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>65201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cardiovascular Consultants, P.C., Saint Luke's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kansas</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>64111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mercy Heart and Vascular Clinic, Mercy Hospital St. Louis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63141</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Glacier View Research Institute Cardiology, Duplicate Glacier View Research Institute Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kalispell</city>
        <state>Montana</state>
        <zip>59901</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Buffalo Heart Group LLP, Buffalo Heart Group LLC-Cheektowaga, Mercy Hospital of Buffalo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stony Brook Islandia Clinic, Stony Brook Hauppauge, Stony Brook University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stony Brook</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11794</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Durham VA Medical Center, Duke University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>FirstHealth Cardiology Services, FirstHealth Moore Regional Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pinehurst</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28374</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Forsyth Medical Center, Novant Clinical Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sanford Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fargo</city>
        <state>North Dakota</state>
        <zip>58102</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lindner Research Center, The Christ Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45219</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University, Ohio State University Medical Center The Richard M Ross Heart Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mercy Hospital Fairfield, Mercy Hospital Anderson, The Jewish Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fairfield</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45014</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lehigh Valley Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Allentown</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>18103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mercer Bucks Cardiology, Saint Mary Medical Center, Arrhythmia Institute Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newtown</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>18940</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cardiac Diagnostic Associates, York Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>York</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>17405</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pee Dee Cardiology, McLeod Regional Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Florence</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29506</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Arrhythmia Consultants (Greenville SC), Greenville Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Greenville</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29605</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cardiology Consultants PA, Spartanburg Regional Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Spartanburg</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29303</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wellmont CVA Heart Institute, Wellmont Holston Valley Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kingsport</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37660</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centennial Heart Cardiovascular Consultants LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Saint Thomas Research Institute LLC, Baptist Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Amarillo Heart Group, Northwest Texas Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amarillo</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>79106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cardiology Center of Amarillo, Northwest Texas Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amarillo</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>79106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>HeartPlace Cardiology Research, Baylor Heart &amp; Vascular Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Methodist DeBakey Cardiology Associates, The Methodist Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor Research Institute (Plano TX), Legacy Heart Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Plano</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75204</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Scott &amp; White Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Temple</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>76508</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fletcher Allen Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Burlington</city>
        <state>Vermont</state>
        <zip>05405</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Virginia (UVA) Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlottesville</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22908</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centra Medical Group Stroobants Cardiovascular Center, Centra Lynchburg General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lynchburg</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>24501</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Richmond Cardiology Associates, Bon Secours Memorial Regional Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mechanicsville</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23116</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sentara Cardiovascular Specialist, Sentara Williamsburg Regional Medical Center, Sentara Norfolk General Hospital, Sentara Virginia Beach General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Norfolk</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23507</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Harborview Medical Center, University of Washington (UW) Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aurora Cardiovascular Services, Aurora Sinai Medical Center, Aurora Saint Luke's Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medanta-The Medicity</name>
      <address>
        <city>Haryana</city>
        <zip>122041</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tyumen Cardiology Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tyumen</city>
        <zip>625026</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Karolinska University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stockholm</city>
        <zip>17176</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>India</country>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 9, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 15, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Bundle-Branch Block</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Block</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure, Systolic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
