<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="162955">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01676896</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01NR007770</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01NR007770</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01676896</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Asthma in Central Texas Project</brief_title>
  <official_title>Enhancing Children's and Parents' Asthma Management</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas at Austin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Nursing Research (NINR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas at Austin</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Asthma is the most common chronic childhood illness and disproportionately affects children
      who are ethnic minorities and poor. Few studies of childhood asthma have been conducted with
      children who live in rural areas or have included Mexican American children in their
      samples. This study builds on the original R01NR007770 with findings that demonstrated the
      intervention could improve children's asthma self-management, asthma knowledge, metered dose
      inhaler skill, asthma severity, and parents' asthma management and access to care. In this
      competing continuation, the investigators added a third arm to the current research design
      with schools randomized into either an in-school asthma intervention, an in-school
      attention-control intervention, or an alternate intervention-delivery format of a single
      5.5-hour asthma day camp. The tri-ethnic sample will be composed of 320 Mexican-American,
      African-American, and White rural school-aged children (grades 2-5) who have asthma and
      their parents. In addition, the investigators propose adding a non-invasive measure of
      chronic airway inflammation (exhaled nitric oxide) to assess the impact of changes in asthma
      management on airway inflammation. Families will be followed for a full year with data
      collection at baseline and at 1-month, 4-months, and 7-months after the intervention to
      assess improvement in children's asthma morbidity, asthma severity, airway inflammation,
      family asthma management and quality of life. Hypotheses (H): Children in the Camp-Workshop
      group and the School-Home group will demonstrate equivalent improvements, but greater
      improvements than the Attention-Control group in:(H1.1) their asthma severity and airway
      inflammation from the Time 1 assessment when compared to Time 4 assessment; (H1.2) office
      visits, ED visits, and hospitalizations for asthma, and absenteeism for the study year (Time
      4) when compared to the pre-study year (Time 1); and (H1.4) Parents in the intervention arms
      will demonstrate sustained improvements in asthma caregiver's quality of life (QOL0 from the
      pre-study year (Time 1) to the end of the study year (Time 4) measurement, when compared to
      the Attention-Control group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Families are recruited at the beginning of the school year (Time 1, October-November);
      parents consent and child assent obtained and baseline data collected in fall. The
      intervention is provided in December-January. Follow-up data are collected at February (Time
      2), April (Time 3), and August (Time 4).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor)</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Absenteeism</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>(Days absent/days enrolled)x100 = absenteeism. Using data from pre-enrollment school year for first 12 months and the data from the enrolled study year as months 13-24.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Self reported asthma-related quality of life. Data is collected at baseline (Time 1) and at end of study (Time 4)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospitalization</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of times hospitalized for asthma, how many days hospitalized. Data is obtained for the pre-study year for first 12 months and over the study year for months 13-24.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Emergency Department Visits</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of visits to Emergency Department for asthma. Data is obtained for the pre-study year for first 12 months and over the study year for months 13-24.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Asthma self-management</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Child self-report of asthma preventive and management activities. Data is collected at each time point, Time 1, 2, 3, and 4.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Home Asthma Management</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Parent report of asthma preventive and treatment activities. Data are collected at each time point (Time 1, 2, 3, 4).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Metered dose inhaler skill</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Observation score of child's skill in using a placebo metered dose inhaler (a teaching inhaler). Data are collected at each time point (Time 1, 2, 3, 4).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medication Adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Parent report of their child remembering/forgetting to take medications. Data are collected at each time point (Time 1, 2, 3, 4).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>lung inflammation</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Exhaled breath condensation collected and sent for lab analysis of NO3. Data are collected at each time point (Time 1, 2, 3, 4).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">320</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Asthma in-school class</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Provided in 16 15-minute sessions (4 hours total didactic time); scheduled 3 sessions/week. The content is provided by trained asthma educators. The Asthma Plan for Kids (AP-K) is a 7-step curriculum for children to use when responding to asthma symptoms. Skills practice with placebo metered dose inhaler (MDI) and peak expiratory flow (PEF) meters with PEF score interpretation. Topics include (a) identifying lung function, asthma warning signs, symptoms, and triggers; (b) learning skills to manage symptoms, including PEF meter score interpretation, communication with adults (e.g. teachers, coaches, family members), medication use and MDI technique; (c) evaluating asthma symptoms and the effectiveness of management; and (d) discussing how to stay active in a safe manner.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Asthma Day Camp</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The asthma day camp is provided in a single day session (5.5 hours total) by trained camp staff. The same skills (i.e., placebo metered dose inhaler (MDI) and peak expiratory flow (PEF) meters) and topics [a) identifying lung function, asthma warning signs, symptoms, and triggers; (b) learning skills to manage symptoms, including PEF meter score interpretation, communication with adults (e.g. teachers, coaches, family members), medication use and MDI technique; (c) evaluating asthma symptoms and the effectiveness of management; and (d) discussing how to stay active in a safe manner] are covered as those in the asthma in-school classes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Health Promotion in-school class</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The mock comparison follows the in-school format of 16 15-minute sessions; scheduled 3 sessions/week. The content is provided by trained health educators and includes skills practice (i.e., handwashing and brushing teeth) and health promotion topics of nutrition, healthy snacks, preventing colds, and safe exercise.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Asthma in-school class</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Asthma in-school class</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Asthma Plan for Kids</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Asthma Day Camp</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Asthma Day Camp</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Health Promotion in-school class</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Health Promotion in-school class</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  parent reports the child has a diagnosis of asthma made by a medical provider;

          -  has had asthma symptoms in the previous 12 months;

          -  speaks either English or Spanish.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  has a significant co-morbidity that would preclude participation in classes (e.g.,
             severe cerebral palsy, oxygen dependent conditions)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>13 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Texas at Austin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Austin</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78712</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 5, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 24, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>children</keyword>
  <keyword>asthma</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>self-management</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
