<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="25025">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01863914</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>101-2314-B-006-045</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01863914</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Vascular Protective Effect of Rosuvastatin in Arteriovenous Fistula</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Rosuvastatin in the Mobilization of Endothelial Progenitor Cells and Graft Vascular Function Following Creation of Arteriovenous Fistula in Diabetic Patients With Chronic Renal Failure</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cheng-Kung University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cheng-Kung University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Taiwan: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background Arteriovenous (AV) fistula is the most common vascular access for long-term
      hemodialysis in the end-stage renal disease (ESRD) patients. About 25% of these patients are
      diabetes mellitus. However, the effects of hyperglycemia on the vascular function of
      arteriovenous fistula are still remained unclear. Studies have shown that blood flow in the
      AV fistula is significantly reduced in patients with diabetes mellitus. Diabetic patients
      also require a longer period of time for the maturation of AV fistula, and have slightly
      higher complication rate than non-diabetic patients. Statins have been widely shown to
      mediate several important pleiotropic effects in the improvement of vascular endothelial
      dysfunction, attenuation of inflammatory responses, stabilization of atherosclerotic
      plaques, inhibition of vascular smooth muscle proliferation, and modulation of procoagulant
      activity and platelet function.Our experimental studies in diabetic animals demonstrate that
      administration of a water-soluble statin rosuvastatin significantly improves the fistula
      flow, vascular function and luminal dilatation of AV fistula in diabetic rats by suppression
      of vascular oxidative stress and inflammatory load.

      Study hypothesis The central hypothesis of this research project is rosuvastatin mediates
      pleiotropic protective effect on vascular endothelial function and suppresses the regional
      pro-inflammatory reaction in the vasculature, therefore administration of rosuvastatin
      during the perioperative period of creation of native AV fistulas in diabetic patients with
      ESRD may potentiate the vascular function and reduce the primary failure rate of AV
      fistulae.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary patent rate of AV fistula</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after operation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The definition of primary patency of an AV fistula is defined as successful cannulation of the fistula for first hemodialysis treatment (first dialysis session)(reference: BMC Nephrol 2013;14:79). Administration of rosuvastatin protects the endothelial function in the AV fistula and restores the blood flow rate in the shunt of diabetic patients with ESRD, thereby improves the primary patent rate and early maturation of these fistulas</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite outcome measurement of the overall shunt-related complication rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after operation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The most commonly shunt-related complications are formation of aneurysms, failure of shunt to mature, and development of thrombosis in AV fistula (Ann Vasc Surg 2012;26:680). The occurrence of shunt-related complications usually require surgical reintervention. Administration of rosuvastatin improves the vascular function of AV fistulas in diabetic patients with ESRD, therefore reduces the overall shunt-related complication rate and the requirement for surgical re-interventions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Composite outcome measurement of systemic pro-inflammatory response</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after operation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Systemic proinflammatory response is determined by measuring blood concentrations of MCP-1, IL-1 beta, IL-6 and TNF-alpha, and the numbers of circulating endothelial progenitor cells (EPCs). Administration of rosuvastatin is associated with reduction of the systemic pro-inflammatory response and oxidative stress (levels of proinflammatory cytokines and other mediators in the circulation) in diabetic patients with ESRD. On the other hand, administration of rosuvastatin may mobilize the bone marrow-derived EPCs into systemic circulation, and the number of these circulating endothelial progenitors may provide prognostic value to the outcomes of AV fistula.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>End-stage Kidney Disease</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <condition>Arteriovenous Fistula</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo tablet contains only inactive ingredient. The placebo tablets will be taken once daily for 4 weeks (1 week before operation and 3 weeks after creation of AV fistula)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rosuvastatin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Rosuvastatin (CrestorÒ, Astrazeneca) 5mg once daily for 4 weeks (1 week before operation and 3 weeks after creation of AV fistula)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rosuvastatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Rosuvastatin tablet (CrestorÒ, Astrazeneca) 5 mg/d PO for 4 weeks (1 week before and 3 weeks after creation of AV fistula)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rosuvastatin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with diabetes mellitus (postprandial blood sugar &gt;140 mg/dl)

          2. Patients with end-stage kidney disease and is proposed to undertake chronic
             hemodialysis

          3. Patients of age 18-60 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Preoperative blood sugar level &gt;250 mg/dl or most recent HbA1c &gt;10%

          2. Hyperlipidemia (serum LDL &gt;100mg/dl)

          3. Recent treatment with statins

          4. Advanced liver disease

          5. Chronic alcoholism

          6. Congestive heart failure

          7. Malignancy or hematologic disorder

          8. Pregnancy or breastfeeding

          9. Past history of creation of AV fistula

         10. Scheduled for general anesthesia

         11. Emergent operation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cheng Kung University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tainan</city>
        <zip>704</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chen-Fuh Lam, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>8866-2353535</phone>
      <phone_ext>5348</phone_ext>
      <email>lamcf@mail.ncku.edu.tw</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chen-Fuh Lam, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jun-Neng Roan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 23, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 14, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National Cheng-Kung University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lam Chen Fuh</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ESRD</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes mellitus</keyword>
  <keyword>Endothelial progenitor cells</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood flow</keyword>
  <keyword>Hemodialysis</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Arteriovenous Fistula</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fistula</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Rosuvastatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
