<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="164639">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01679197</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MCRU 2834</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01DK088114-02</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01679197</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Protocol to Investigate the Efficacy of Recombinant Human Leptin (Metreleptin) in Nonalcoholic Steatohepatitis (NASH) or Nonalcoholic Fatty Liver Disease (NAFLD) Associated With Lipodystrophy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Protocol to Investigate the Efficacy of Recombinant Human Leptin (Metreleptin) in Nonalcoholic Steatohepatitis (NASH) or Nonalcoholic Fatty Liver Disease (NAFLD) Associated With Lipodystrophy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study involves research about an investigational medicine called metreleptin. The
      reason for this study is to find out how metreleptin can improve non-alcoholic
      steatohepatitis or nonalcoholic fatty liver disease associated with lipodystrophy, a rare
      disorder associated with abnormal loss of the body's fat tissue. In this study, metreleptin
      is considered to be investigational for the treatment of lipodystrophy. Metreleptin will be
      given via injections under the skin. We plan to continue therapy for a period of one year
      and evaluate the change in liver disease by a liver biopsy. We will also follow the
      metabolic parameters (e.g. blood cholesterol, liver function, insulin resistance) and body
      composition characteristics (e.g. the pattern of fat distribution in the body).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The goal is to test the efficacy of restorative leptin therapy on the degree of hepatic
      steatosis and on amelioration of pathological features of NASH/NAFLD. In addition, the study
      will evaluate the impact of leptin therapy on total body insulin sensitivity and lipid
      levels as well as energy expenditure. In order to accomplish this aim, we now propose an
      efficacy study with recombinant human leptin therapy in patients with all forms of
      lipodystrophy who also have NASH/NAFLD.

        1. AIM 1: To determine the efficacy of leptin in promoting amelioration of body
           composition, hepatic steatosis and histopathological scores in patients with all forms
           of lipodystrophy and NAFLD/NASH. We will conduct a 1 year, open-label study, to assess
           the metabolic effects of recombinant human leptin (METRELEPTIN, Amylin Pharmaceuticals,
           San Diego, CA). The primary outcome measure will be NASH scores. We will also explore
           body weight, insulin sensitivity, glucose and lipid control, body composition, and free
           fatty acid levels.

        2. AIM 2: To Investigate molecular effects of leptin therapy. In parallel to our
           preliminary studies, gene expression will be performed on individuals participating in
           Aim 1 at baseline and following 1 year of leptin. We will combine this with measures of
           liver metabolite levels to provide novel insights into alterations in metabolism that
           occur secondary to leptin therapy. We will also measure plasma metabolites at baseline
           and after 2 (optional), 24 and 48 weeks of therapy to assess the dynamic changes
           induced by leptin and correlate these changes with phenotypic measures.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Liver histopathology</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Primary outcome will be the Total NASH score read histopathologically from the liver biopsy samples, as determined by the NIH NASH Clinical Network criteria. At baseline and at the end of the year, patients will undergo a transcutaneous liver biopsy and the specimen will be graded for the severity of NAFLD/NASH pathology.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Liver fat by MRI and MR spectroscopy</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>All enrolled patients will have a baseline MRI of the liver to evaluate liver volume and liver fat. For determination of hepatic fat content by MRI and MR spectroscopy in patients, a series of out-phase and in-phase MRI at multiple flip angles are used. By combination of out-phase and in-phase MRI at multiple flip-angles and TE times, relaxation-time effects can be removed to yield quantitative intra-hepatic (and other organs') fractional fat content throughout the liver in a few breath-hold intervals.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Liver function tests</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fasting lipids</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fasting glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body weight</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Fatty Liver Disease, Nonalcoholic</condition>
  <condition>Nonalcoholic Steatohepatitis</condition>
  <condition>Lipodystrophy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Metreleptin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metreleptin</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>(originally A100, recombinant-human-methionyl-leptin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Is male or female ≥ 5 years old at baseline.

          -  Is male, female not of childbearing potential, or meets all the following criteria if
             female of childbearing potential (including perimenopausal women who have had a
             menstrual period within one year):

               -  Not breastfeeding

               -  Negative pregnancy test result (human chorionic gonadotropin, beta subunit
                  [βhCG]) at baseline (not applicable to hysterectomized females).

               -  Must practice and be willing to continue to practice appropriate birth control
                  (defined as a method which results in a low failure rate when use consistently
                  and correctly, such as implants, injectables, oral contraceptives, some
                  intrauterine contraceptive devices, sexual abstinence, tubal ligation, or a
                  vasectomized partner) during the entire duration of metreleptin treatment.

          -  Has physician-confirmed lipodystrophy as defined by evidence of generalized (whole
             body) or partial (limbs) loss of body fat outside the range of normal variation.

          -  Alcohol consumption of less than 40 grams/week.

          -  A liver ultrasound confirming non-alcoholic fatty liver disease, or previous liver
             biopsy confirming NASH status.

          -  If ≥ 18 years of age, is able to read, understand and sign the U of M IRBMED approved
             informed consent form (ICF), communicate with study physician and study team,
             understand and comply with protocol requirements.

          -  If &lt; 18 and ≥ 7 years of age, is able to read, understand and sign the appropriate U
             of M IRBMED approved assent form and has a parent or legal guardian that is able to
             read, understand and sign the ICF.

          -  If &lt; 7 and ≥ 5 years of age or unable to read, the appropriate assent form must be
             explained to the child.

          -  If previously treated with thiazolidinediones or Vitamin E, stable dose of these
             medications for at least 3 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of advanced liver disease (as evidenced by abnormal synthetic function,
             abnormal PT or albumin).

          -  Evidence of other etiologies of viral hepatitis.

          -  Presence of clinically significant hematologic abnormalities (such as neutropenia
             and/or lymphadenopathy).

          -  Presence of HIV infection.

          -  Very poorly controlled diabetes; HbA1c &gt;10%

          -  Inability to give informed consent.

          -  Presence of ESRD, any type of active cancer, or &gt;class 2 congestive heart failure
             ((New York Heart Association Functional Classification System), based on medical
             history and physical examination.

          -  Active infection (may be transient).

          -  Has known allergies to E. coli-derived proteins or hypersensitivity to any component
             of metreleptin treatment.

          -  Any other condition in the opinion of the investigators that may impede successful
             data collection.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elif A Oral, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Adam Neidert, MS</last_name>
    <phone>734-615-0539</phone>
    <email>aneidert@med.umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Elif A Oral, MD, MS</last_name>
    <phone>734-615-7271</phone>
    <email>eliforal@med.umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Adam Neidert, MS</last_name>
      <phone>734-615-0539</phone>
      <email>aneidert@med.umich.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elif A Oral, MD, MS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Charles Burant, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Barbara McKenna, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hari Conjeevaram, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Thomas Chenevert, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hero Hussain, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nevin Ajluni, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 24, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 31, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Elif Oral</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease</keyword>
  <keyword>NAFLD</keyword>
  <keyword>Nonalcoholic steatohepatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>NASH</keyword>
  <keyword>Lipodystrophy</keyword>
  <keyword>Leptin</keyword>
  <keyword>Metreleptin</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypertriglyceridemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes mellitus</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fatty Liver</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lipodystrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
