<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="111044">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02021565</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>D7873-R</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>D7873R</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02021565</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluating the CG ASSIST Program for Caregiving Dyads</brief_title>
  <acronym>CG ASSIST</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluating the CG ASSIST Program for Caregiving Dyads</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The CG ASSIST Project is a four-year study for older Veterans with transfer impairments and
      informal caregivers. CG ASSIST is an  in-home training program for dyads designed to teach
      Veterans how to safely, skillfully, and (when possible) independently perform Activities of
      Daily Living involving transfers.  Experts (OTs) who provide this training will also
      recommend, provide, and install assistive technology devices such as grab bars, bed rails,
      and toileting aids as needed.  Research assistants conduct home visits with the dyads pre
      and post intervention to determine the effects of the program on Veteran and caregiver
      quality of life measures (burden, depression, task efficacy, lifespace).

      Half of the couples in this study will receive the training from the expert remotely through
      a tele-video conferencing device.  Research assistants will bring the device to
      participants' homes and assist in the training session.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction and Objective: The primary objective of the proposed four-year randomized,
      controlled trial is to document that providing a hands-on skills training and assistive
      technology (AT)/environmental modification program for older Veterans who are dependent in
      activities of daily living (ADLs) and their informal caregivers will result in improvements
      in caregiving processes (i.e., caregiving skills) and outcomes (i.e., safety during tasks)
      compared to the current standard of care and have beneficial direct and indirect effects for
      both members of the dyad. Secondary objectives are to determine the effects of the program
      on Veteran and caregiver subjective well-being (depression, quality of life) and to compare
      the relative effectiveness of two validated implementation modalities the traditional
      in-person approach and real-time interactive tele-video conferencing.

      Research Plan. The study will be conducted with older Veterans (&gt;60yrs) with mobility
      impairments who live in the community and are dependent on an informal caregiver for ADL
      assistance involving mobility, transfer or positional change.  The study will utilize a
      modified randomized controlled cross-over design with four study arms and three or four
      outcome assessment periods. Prior to the first home visit, participants will be randomized
      to an intervention modality (in-person vs. tele-video) then randomized within those groups
      to an immediate intervention (IIG) or delayed intervention/control group (DICG).

      Methods. In-home interviews will be completed with 180 Veteran caregiving dyads to obtain
      baseline, self-reported measures of caregiving needs, processes and outcomes using
      standardized, validated instruments. In-home visits by an Assistive Technology Specialist
      (ATS) will mirror the interview visits (within 1 week) to independently and objectively
      assess needs through observation of functional tasks. Dyads will be re-evaluated one (T2),
      two (T3), and four to five (T4) months later to ascertain change. Following T1 assessments,
      those in the IIG will receive 2 additional home visits from the ATS to (1) deliver the
      intervention and (2) reinforce the intervention. A 2nd blinded ATS will conduct the T2
      outcome assessments. At T2 an ATS will conduct observation-based assessments which will also
      serve as a repeat baseline for the DICG. The intervention schedule will then be repeated for
      dyads in the DICG during T3.  The final assessments for both groups will be collected 3
      months after the intervention during T4.

      Intervention. The Caregiver Assessment of Skill Sets &amp; Individualized Support Thru Training
      or CG ASSIST program has recently undergone feasibility testing in a VA RR&amp;D pilot study.

      The intervention consists of (a) provision of assistive technology (AT) and simple home
      modifications to facilitate ADLs and (b) dyad training on the appropriate use of the devices
      and proper task execution using standardized protocols individualized to the needs and
      preferences of the dyad and environmental features of the home.

      Clinical Relevance. Supporting and assisting caregivers in providing care for Veterans to
      help them age in place  has important implications for the VHA system and the safety,
      dignity and quality of life of the Veterans we serve.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assistance Provided - Subjective - Caregiver</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline in Assistance Provided reported by Caregiver at post-intervention, 1 month, and 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This outcome is a self-report from the Caregiver of the level of assistance provided to the Veteran to complete three tasks (transferring in and out of bed, toileting, and bathing) using a modified version for the Functional Independence Measure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assistance Provided - Subjective - Veteran</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1, 6, 10 and either 19 or 23</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This outcome is a self-report from the Veteran of the level of assistance provided by the Caregiver using a modified version for the Functional Independence Measure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assistance Provided - Objective</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2, 5, 9, and either 18 or 22</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This outcome is an objective report from the Assistive Technology Specialist (expert who conducts training) of the level of assistance provided to the Veteran using a modified version of the Functional Independence Measure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assistance Needed - Subjective - Caregiver</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1, 6, 10, and either 19 or 23</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This outcome is a self-report from the Caregiver of the level of assistance the Veteran needs to complete three tasks (transferring in and out of bed, toileting, and bathing) using a modified version of the Functional Independence Measure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assistance Needed - Subjective - Veteran</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1, 6, 10, and either 19 or 23</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This outcome is a self-report from the Veteran of the level of assistance needed from the Caregiver to complete three tasks (transferring in and out of bed, toileting, and bathing) using a modified version of the Functional Independence Measure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assistance Needed - Objective</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2, 5, 9, and either 18 or 22</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This outcome is an objective report from the Assistive Technology Specialist (expert who conducts training) of the level of assistance needed by the Veteran to complete three tasks (transferring in and out of bed, toileting, and bathing) using a modified version of the Functional Independence Measure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Transfer Impairment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Receives the in-home training intervention immediately after completing the baseline assessment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Delayed Intervention Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Receives the in-home training intervention six weeks after completing the initial baseline assessment.  This allows for a control comparison group while still providing the intervention to all participants.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>In-person Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Receives the in-home training intervention in a traditional face-to-face format.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tele Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Receives the in-home training intervention via a tele-video communication device brought to the home by a research assistant. The expert conducts the training remotely observing and training the participants through a tele-rehabilitation device.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>In-home Training and Provision of Assistive Technology (prn)</intervention_name>
    <description>Assistive Technology Specialists (ATSs), experts on assistive technology devices and how to performing transfer tasks, train Veteran and caregiver dyads to safely, skillfully, and (when appropriate) independently perform four activities of daily living (ADLs): transferring in and out of bed, toileting, and bathing. During the baseline assessments, ATSs also recommend assistive technology equipment (grab bars, bed rails, raised toilet seats, etc.), environmental modifications, adaptive methods, and energy conservation techniques. On the first day of the intervention, ATSs provide and install recommended equipment and train the dyad to complete the three ADLs using the recommended the modified methods.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Delayed Intervention Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>In-person Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Tele Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Veterans 60 who require assistance from the identified caregiver with more than one
             Activity of Daily Living or three or more Instrumental Activity of Daily Living,

          -  have a life expectancy of greater than or equal to six (6) months,

          -  have no plans for transitioning out of home or into hospice in the next six months,

          -  and have approval from the primary care provider to participate in the research.

          -  Caregivers must live with the Veteran, provide care four (4) or more days out of the
             week for at least 6 months,

          -  and obtain a negative mini-cog assessment.  Caregivers can be any relation (spouse,
             child, sibling, friend, etc.) to the Veteran so long as the two are co-habitating.

          -  Caregiver can be any age.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Caregivers who have a positive screen with the Mini-Cog fail to demonstrate cognitive
        capacity to provide informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patricia C Griffiths, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Atlanta VA Medical and Rehab Center, Decatur, GA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Patricia C Griffiths, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(404) 321-6111</phone>
    <phone_ext>7138</phone_ext>
    <email>pcgriff@emory.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ashley Harrill</last_name>
    <phone>(404) 321-6111</phone>
    <phone_ext>1191</phone_ext>
    <email>Ashley.Harrill@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Atlanta VA Medical and Rehab Center, Decatur, GA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Decatur</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Patricia C Griffiths, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>404-321-6111</phone>
      <phone_ext>7138</phone_ext>
      <email>pcgriff@emory.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ashley Harrill</last_name>
      <phone>(404) 321-6111</phone>
      <phone_ext>1191</phone_ext>
      <email>Ashley.Harrill@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Patricia C Griffiths, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 24, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Caregivers</keyword>
  <keyword>Activities of Daily Living</keyword>
  <keyword>Dementia</keyword>
  <keyword>Veterans</keyword>
  <keyword>Self-Help Devices</keyword>
  <keyword>Telemedicine</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
