<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="60516">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02059135</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RB AT PPE 01-13</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02059135</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pharmacokinetics, Safety and Efficacy Study of Recombinant Antithrombin Versus Placebo in Preterm Preeclampsia</brief_title>
  <acronym>PRESERVE-1</acronym>
  <official_title>Prospective Randomized Double-Blind, Placebo Controlled Evaluation of the Pharmacokinetics, Safety and Efficacy of Recombinant Antithrombin Versus Placebo in Preterm Preeclampsia (PRESERVE-1)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>rEVO Biologics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>rEVO Biologics</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to  assess the efficacy, safety and pharmacokinetics (PK) of
      recombinant human antithrombin (ATryn) in addition to expectant management for the treatment
      of preterm preeclampsia (PPE). Efficacy will be assessed by comparing the difference in
      extension of gestational age from the time of randomization into the study until delivery
      between ATryn and placebo treated subjects. In addition, the effect of ATryn on fetal and
      neonatal clinical outcomes will be assessed. The PK characteristics of ATryn in the subjects
      will be investigated by measuring AT activity levels in the mother during treatment and in
      cord blood.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hospitalized PPE patients who are being expectantly managed, after initial assessment and
      stabilization period, will be considered for the study. After informed consent has been
      obtained subjects will be screened for eligibility. Screening includes obtaining the
      subject's medical/obstetric history and a physical examination which includes an assessment
      of maternal and fetal status. Blood samples for hematology, clinical chemistries,
      biomarkers, coagulation, immunogenicity and AT activity levels will be drawn. A 12/24-hour
      urine collection for protein or protein/creatinine ratio will be collected if not available
      at the time of screening. Eligible subjects who meet inclusion/exclusion criteria will be
      randomized in a 1:1 ratio to receive a continuous infusion of either ATryn or placebo.

      Sampling for AT activity will be performed immediately prior to the first dose of study drug
      and at specified times thereafter.

      Subjects will continue on study drug until maternal and/or fetal indications for delivery
      necessitate cessation of expectant management or until 34 0/7 weeks of gestation. The
      average extension of pregnancy with standard of care expectant management in this patient
      population is approximately 7 days. It is assumed that treatment with ATryn will provide an
      additional increase in gestational age of 5-7 days as compared to this standard of care.
      Total duration on study drug is therefore estimated to be approximately 7 to 14 days on
      average.

      Post treatment assessments of the mother will be performed approximately 4-6 weeks after
      delivery of the neonate. Information on the neonates will be collected until they reach a
      post-menstrual age of 36 weeks (and a minimum of 28 days post delivery).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary outcome measure is the increase in gestational age.</measure>
    <time_frame>Subjects will continue on study drug until maternal and/or fetal indications for delivery necessitate cessation of expectant management or until 34 0/7 weeks of gestation.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Increase in gestational age is defined as the gestational age at delivery minus the gestational age at randomization.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The secondary outcome measure is a composite measure of specific fetal and neonatal outcomes.</measure>
    <time_frame>Subjects will continue on study drug until maternal and/or fetal indications for delivery necessitate cessation of expectant management or until 34 0/7 weeks of gestation and for the neonate until 36 weeks post menstrual age.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The specific fetal and neonatal outcomes include bronchopulmonary dysplasia, intraventricular hemorrhage, cystic periventricular leucomalacia, retinopathy of prematurity, late Sepsis, necrotizing enterocolitis and mortality (fetal and neonatal).  The outcome is measured on a 5 point scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Other outcomes include individual maternal, perinatal and neonatal outcomes.In addition, a second neonatal composite outcome score, the avoidance of all morbidity and mortality will be examined</measure>
    <time_frame>Subjects will continue on study drug until maternal and/or fetal indications for delivery necessitate cessation of expectant management or until 34 0/7 weeks of gestation and for the neonate until 36 post menstrual age.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>These  outcomes will be summarized using counts and percentages, and exact (Clopper-Pearson) 95% confidence intervals for the true proportions will be calculated for each treatment.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Preeclampsia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Recombinant Human Antithrombin (ATryn)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>ATryn 250 mg loading dose over 15 minutes, immediately followed by continuous infusion of 2000 mg per 24 hours. Total daily dose is 2250 mg for the first day and 2000 mg on subsequent days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Saline 0.9%</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo (Normal Saline 0.9%, matched for volume of active treatment) consisting of a loading dose over 15 minutes followed by continuous infusion.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Recombinant human antithrombin (ATryn)</intervention_name>
    <description>Atryn 250 mg loading dose over 15 minutes, immediately followed by continuous infusion of 2000 mg per 24 hours. Total daily dose is 2250 mg for the first day and 2000 mg on subsequent days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Recombinant Human Antithrombin (ATryn)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Recombinant human antithrombin (rhAT)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Hospitalized female pregnant patients of gestational age of ≥24 0/7 weeks to &lt;28 0/7
             weeks (based on an ultrasound performed prior to study enrollment)

          2. At least 18 years of age

          3. Recent diagnosis of Preeclampsia or Superimposed Preeclampsia in current
             hospitalization as defined by:

               -  For Preeclampsia

                    -  Gestational hypertension defined as a recorded systolic blood pressure (BP)
                       of

                       ≥140 mm Hg or diastolic BP of ≥90 mm Hg on 2 occasions at least 4 hours
                       apart (since the commencement of medical intervention in any facility) OR

                    -  Severe gestational hypertension defined as systolic blood pressure of ≥ 160
                       mm Hg or diastolic blood pressure ≥ 110 mm Hg, confirmed with second
                       assessment within a short interval (minutes) AND

               -  New onset of any of the following:

                    -  proteinuria defined as  ≥0.3 g protein per 24 hours in a 12-24 hour urine
                       collection or protein/creatinine ratio (PCR) of  ≥0.3 mg/g (on a random
                       sample or any collection period)

                    -  Platelet count less than 100,000/µL

                    -  Serum creatinine concentrations greater than 1.1 mg/dL or a doubling of the
                       serum creatinine concentration in the absence of other renal disease

                    -  Elevated liver transaminases to ≥ twice upper limit of normal

                    -  Cerebral or visual symptoms

               -  For Superimposed preeclampsia:

                    -  The start of antihypertensive medication or adding a second
                       antihypertensive medication after 20 weeks of pregnancy for systolic BP ≥
                       160 or diastolic BP ≥ 105 in a patient that had a previous history of
                       controlled hypertension before 20 weeks of pregnancy.

             AND

               -  New onset of any of the following:

                    -  proteinuria defined as  ≥0.3 g protein per 24 hours in a 12-24 hour urine
                       collection or protein/creatinine ratio (PCR) of  ≥0.3 mg/g (on a random
                       sample or any collection period)

                    -  Platelet count less than 100,000/µL

                    -  Serum creatinine concentrations greater than 1.1 mg/dL or a doubling of the
                       serum creatinine concentration in the absence of other renal disease

                    -  Elevated liver transaminases to ≥ twice upper limit of normal

                    -  Cerebral or visual symptoms

          4. In the opinion of the investigator the patient has demonstrated sufficient clinical
             stability to be eligible for expectant management

          5. The patient is expected to be managed as an inpatient until delivery

          6. Signed informed consent for both subject and neonate

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Criteria (assessed just prior to decision to screen patient) that would likely
             require immediate delivery of the fetus:

               -  Refractory hypertension despite maximal medical intervention of  systolic BP
                  ≥160 mm Hg or diastolic BP of ≥110 mm Hg

               -  Thrombocytopenia (platelets ˂ 100/mm3) with or without Hemolysis elevated liver
                  enzymes low platelets (HELLP) syndrome defined as defined as Aspartate amino
                  transferase (AST) ≥70 units/L, and platelets ˂100/mm3, and evidence of hemolysis
                  on blood film plus either Lactic dehydrogenase (LDH) ≥600 IU/mL or total
                  bilirubin ≥1.2 mg/dL)

               -  Oliguria (≤500 mL/24 hours) or evidence of progressive renal insufficiency

               -  Serum creatinine concentration greater than 1.1 mg/dL or a doubling of the serum
                  creatinine concentration in the absence of other renal disease

               -  Persistent visual disturbances

               -  Placental abruption

               -  Pulmonary edema

               -  Nonreassuring fetal heart rate tracing

               -  Intractable headache unrelieved with analgesia

               -  Intractable right upper quadrant abdominal pain or vomiting

               -  If umbilical doppler ultrasound has been performed, the presence of an abnormal
                  umbilical artery doppler as defined by absent or reverse end diastolic flow

               -  History of biophysical score ≤ 4/10 on 2 occasions

               -  Oligohydramnios (index &lt;5 cm)

               -  Intra uterine growth restriction (IUGR) &lt; 5th percentile

               -  Other maternal or fetal conditions that would preclude expectant management

          2. Known lethal or major fetal anomaly

          3. Recent (within 12 months) history of maternal alcoholism or drug dependence

          4. Diagnosis of epilepsy

          5. Received within last 7 days or has need for therapy with nonsteroidal
             anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), selective cyclooxygenase (Cox)-2 inhibitors (low
             dose aspirin of 81 mg/day or less allowable)

          6. Received within 72 hours or has requirement for heparin; low molecular weight
             heparins such as enoxaparin or dalteparin; fondaparinux; antiplatelet agents such as
             clopidogrel, prasugrel, or high dose aspirin (&gt;81 mg/day); Direct Thrombin Inhibitors
             (DTI) such as dabigatran

          7. Pre-existing renal disease, documented pre-pregnancy or in pregnancy prior to 20
             weeks gestation (prior to the diagnosis of preeclampsia) or 24 hr urine of ≥0.3 gm/24
             hours, documented in pregnancy, prior to 20 weeks gestation or ≥2+ dipstick or ≥ 0.3
             PCR, documented in pregnancy at the last available test  prior to 20 weeks gestation

          8. Multi-fetal pregnancy

          9. History of Antiphospholipid antibody syndrome

         10. Known hypersensitivity to goat and goat milk proteins

         11. Participation in another interventional clinical trial within 30 days of consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Paidas, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Yale New Haven Health System Center for Healthcare Solutions</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Laura Massey, BS</last_name>
    <phone>508-370-5157</phone>
    <email>laura.massey@revobiologics.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Denise Tilton, RN, MHA</last_name>
    <phone>508-370-5257</phone>
    <email>denise.tilton@revobiologics.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale New Haven Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06519</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Erlanger Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chattanooga</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>347403</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 6, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Preeclampsia</keyword>
  <keyword>Preterm preeclampsia</keyword>
  <keyword>Pregnancy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Pre-Eclampsia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antithrombins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antithrombin III</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antithrombin Proteins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
