<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="136199">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01933880</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR016078</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CONCERTAATT4099</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01933880</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Long Term Post-Marketing Study on the EffIcacy and Safety of Osmotic Release Oral System (OROS) Methylphenidate on the Cognitive Functions of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) Participants</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open, Self-Controlled, Prospective Study of Concerta on Cognitive Functions, Efficacy and Tolerance in the Pediatric Patients With Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Xian-Janssen Pharmaceutical Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Xian-Janssen Pharmaceutical Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>China: China Food and Drug Administration (CFDA)</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this long term post-marketing study is to evaluate the effectiveness and
      safety of osmotic release oral system methylphenidate hydrochloride (OROS-MPH) in
      participants with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-label (all people know the identity of the intervention), prospective (study
      following participants forward in time), self-controlled, long-term post-marketing study in
      participants with ADHD. The study consists of 3 periods: screening period, wash-out
      period/run-in period (3 days), and open-label treatment period (12 weeks) which is divided
      into 2 periods that is dosage adjustment period and dose-optimization period. The total
      duration of the study is 12 weeks. During the dosage adjustment period, the dose of
      methylphenidate hydrochloride was adjusted to the optimal dose within 1-3 weeks starting
      with initial dosage of 18 milligram per day (mg/d) which can be increased to 36 mg/d up to a
      maximum dosage of 54 mg/d according to the therapeutic effect and tolerance or maintained at
      36 mg or re-adjusted to 18 mg due to intolerance.  Participants will receive the optimal
      dose determined during dose adjustment period for 9 weeks during the dose-optimization
      period. In the study, 2 types of participants will be enrolled in 2 groups (according to
      condition): OROS-MPH group (participants with ADHD) and the normal children group (healthy
      participants). The efficacy will be assessed primarily by Digit Span Test and Inattention
      /Over activity With Aggression (IOWA) Conners evaluation scale. Participants' safety will be
      monitored throughout the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Digit Span Test Total Score at Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The digit span test is mainly used to measure the ability of short-term memory and attention. The participant will be given a string of digits and asked to repeat them forward, and then a second string of digits to repeat backward. The score is the number of correct responses, where the digits were repeated correctly. One point will be given for each correctly repeated string of digits. The maximum subscore in the Digits Forward is 16, and the maximum subscore in the Digits Backward is 14, for a total score of 30. A higher score is indicative of better recall and attention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Inattention /Overactivity With Aggression (IOWA) Conners Behavior Rating Scale - I/O Score at Week 1</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>IOWA Conners Behavior Rating Scale evaluated by parents provides accurate measurement standards for behavioral change and therapeutic response. It includes 2 sub-scales: Inattention/Overactivity (I/O) subscale and Attacks (A), also known as Opposition/Defiant (O/D) sub-scale. IO (primary measurement ) will be assessed using 5-items and all Items will be scored on a 4-point scale (from 0=not at all to 3=very much). Total score range is from 0 to 15. Higher scores indicate worsening.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in IOWA Conners Behavior Rating Scale - I/O Score at Week 2</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>IOWA Conners Behavior Rating Scale evaluated by parents provides accurate measurement standards for behavioral change and therapeutic response. It includes 2 sub-scales: Inattention/Overactivity (I/O) subscale and Attacks (A), also known as Opposition/Defiant (O/D) sub-scale. IO (primary measurement ) will be assessed using 5-items and all Items will be scored on a 4-point scale (from 0=not at all to 3=very much). Total score range is from 0 to 15. Higher scores indicate worsening.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in IOWA Conners Behavior Rating Scale - I/O Score at Week 3</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 3</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>IOWA Conners Behavior Rating Scale evaluated by parents provides accurate measurement standards for behavioral change and therapeutic response. It includes 2 sub-scales: Inattention/Overactivity (I/O) subscale and Attacks (A), also known as Opposition/Defiant (O/D) sub-scale. IO (primary measurement ) will be assessed using 5-items and all Items will be scored on a 4-point scale (from 0=not at all to 3=very much). Total score range is from 0 to 15. Higher scores indicate worsening.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in IOWA Conners Behavior Rating Scale - I/O Score at Week 7</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 7</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>IOWA Conners Behavior Rating Scale evaluated by parents provides accurate measurement standards for behavioral change and therapeutic response. It includes 2 sub-scales: Inattention/Overactivity (I/O) subscale and Attacks (A), also known as Opposition/Defiant (O/D) sub-scale. IO (primary measurement ) will be assessed using 5-items and all Items will be scored on a 4-point scale (from 0=not at all to 3=very much). Total score range is from 0 to 15. Higher scores indicate worsening.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in IOWA Conners Behavior Rating Scale - I/O Score at Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>IOWA Conners Behavior Rating Scale evaluated by parents provides accurate measurement standards for behavioral change and therapeutic response. It includes 2 sub-scales: Inattention/Overactivity (I/O) subscale and Attacks (A), also known as Opposition/Defiant (O/D) sub-scale. IO (primary measurement ) will be assessed using 5-items and all Items will be scored on a 4-point scale (from 0=not at all to 3=very much). Total score range is from 0 to 15. Higher scores indicate worsening.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants with total score of IO sub-scale less than or equal to 5 in IOWA Conners measurement scale.</measure>
    <time_frame>End of Week 1, 2, 3, 7 and 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Remission rate is the percentage of participants with total score of IO sub-scale less than or equal to 5 in IOWA Conners measurement scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroop Color Word Naming Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This is a psychological test to observe the interference in which disparity between the meaning and color affects reading speed. A participant will be given 3 tasks of recognition: reading the printed colored ink (Color Test), reading color words in black ink (Word Test), and interference, reading color words printed in different colored ink (Word-Color Test). The test is scored on the number of correct answers. There are 100 items for each of the three categories and if they made it through the 100 words with time remaining, they would repeat the list. Median naming time in the Stroop color word naming test will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Wisconsin Card Sorting Test (WCST)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This test is used to evaluate participants' abilities of abstract generalization, working memory, and distraction-cognitive clinically, which responses participants' cognitive function objectively and comprehensively. This test consists of 13 test indicators and all indicators will be analyzed separately. The 13 indicators are as follows: Number of trials administered; Number of Categories Completed; Response corrects; Percent corrects; Total Number of Errors; Trials to Complete First Category; Percent Conceptual Level Responses; Perseverative Responses; Perseverative Errors; Percent Perseverative Errors; Nonperseverative Errors; Failure to Maintain Set; Learning to Learn.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Coding Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The coding Test is a common test indicator for perceptual speed. The test presents a series of corresponding relationship between graphics and symbols to the participant, and then participants will be required to fill out the appropriate symbol following single symbol in the test part. The test is limited within 150 seconds and evaluated the number of symbols been replaced correctly by the participants.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Academic Achievement</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Mathematics and language scores will be obtained from their corresponding examinations at school. Scores ranges from 0-100 respectively. Mathematics and language would be summarized separately.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Clinical Global Impression - CGI Scale Score</measure>
    <time_frame>End of Week 1, 2, 3, 7 and 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>CGI is an overall rating scale. Clinical Global Impression (Improvement of Diseases) is divided into seven grades: 1=very significant improvement, 2=significant improvement, 3=improvement, 4=no change, 5=slight aggravation, 6=significant aggravation, and 7=very significant aggravation. Number of participants in each category of grade will be accessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in I/O Score of IOWA Conners Behavior Rating Scale at Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>IOWA conners behavior rating scale score in different dosage groups will be accessed to evaluate relationship between therapeutic effect and dosage. IOWA Conners Behavior Rating Scale evaluated by parents provides accurate measurement standards for behavioral change and therapeutic response. It includes 2 sub-scales: Inattention/Overactivity (I/O) subscale and Attacks (A), also known as Opposition/Defiant (O/D) sub-scale. IO (primary measurement ) will be assessed using 5-items and all Items will be scored on a 4-point scale (from 0=not at all to 3=very much). Total score range is from 0 to 15. Higher scores indicate worsening.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Total Scores of Digit Span Test at Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The digit span test total score will be accessed in different dosage groups to evaluate the relationship between therapeutic effect and dosage. The digit span test is mainly used to measure the ability of short-term memory and attention. The participant will be given a string of digits and asked to repeat them forward, and then a second string of digits to repeat backward. The score is the number of correct responses, where the digits were repeated correctly. One point will be given for each correctly repeated string of digits. The maximum subscore in the Digits Forward is16, and the maximum subscore in the Digits Backward is 14, for a total score of 30. A higher score was indicative of better recall and attention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Completion Time of Stroop Color-word Test at Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Completion time of stroop color-word test in different dosage groups will be accessed to evaluate the relationship between therapeutic effect and dosage. This is a psychological test to observe the interference in which disparity between the meaning and color affects reading speed. A participant will be given 3 tasks of recognition: reading the printed colored ink (Color Test), reading color words in black ink (Word Test), and interference, reading color words printed in different colored ink (Word-Color Test). The test will be scored on the number of correct answers. There are 100 items for each of the three categories and if they made it through the 100 words with time remaining, they would repeat the list. Median time of the naming time in the Stroop color word naming test will be accessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants With Total Score of IO sub-scale Less Than or Equal to 5 in IOWA Conners Measurement Scale at Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Remission rate in different dosage groups will be accessed to evaluate the relationship between therapeutic effect and dosage. Remission rate is the percentage of participants with total score of IO sub-scale less than or equal to 5 in IOWA Conners measurement scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Compliant with Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>End of Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of Participants Who are Compliant with Treatment will be accessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">194</enrollment>
  <condition>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>OROS-MPH Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with ADHD will receive OROS -MPH starting at initial dosage of 18 milligram per day (mg/d) which can be increased to 36mg/d up to a maximum dosage of 54mg/d according to the therapeutic effect and tolerance or maintained at 36 mg or re-adjusted to 18mg due to intolerance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Healthy Participants will receive OROS-MPH starting at initial dosage of 18 mg/d which can be increased to 36mg/d up to a maximum dosage of 54mg/d according to the therapeutic effect and tolerance or maintained at 36 mg or re-adjusted to 18mg due to intolerance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Osmotic Release Oral System Methylphenidate Hydrochloride (OROS-MPH)</intervention_name>
    <description>Osmotic release oral system methylphenidate hydrochloride (OROS-MPH) starting at initial dosage of 18 milligram per day (mg/d) which can be increased to 36mg/d up to a maximum dosage of 54mg/d according to the therapeutic effect and tolerance or maintained at 36 mg or re-adjusted to 18mg due to intolerance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>OROS-MPH Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ADHD children must sign the consent form in person, and their parents or guardian
             must endorse, in the consent form,  participation of the child in the designated
             research program

          -  Through personal interaction and assessment questionnaire, examine to determine
             compliance of DSM-IV ADHD diagnostic criteria

          -  According to the judgment of researchers, the ADHD children should have normal
             intelligence. Normal intelligence is defined as no obvious evidence of mental
             retardation in general (specific learning disabilities will not be considered mental
             retardation in general), formal IQ test to be conducted and 85 marks or above ought
             to be scored

          -  ADHD children should not have been subjected to psychotropic drug treatment within 6
             months. Those ADHD children on whom methylphenidate immediate-release tablets
             treatment is  effective (with maximum daily dosage of 60 mg), may be admitted

          -  Normal children with IQ greater than or equal to 85

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to fully comply with the cognitive function test in the laboratory

          -  Known to be allergic to methylphenidate

          -  Consumption of psychoactive drugs currently or in the past 30 days, including use of
             monoamine oxidase inhibitors, clonidine, other alpha 2 adrenergic receptor agonists,
             tricyclic antidepressants, theophylline, bishydroxycoumarin etc

          -  History of alcohol, drugs or substances abuse

          -  Have medical history of type I or II bipolar affective disorder, anxiety disorder,
             schizophrenia or pervasive developmental disorder
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janssen Pharmaceutica Clinical trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Janssen Pharmaceutica</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 5, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 28, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Methylphenidate Hydrochloride</keyword>
  <keyword>CONCERTA</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Attention Deficit Disorder with Hyperactivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperkinesis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Methylphenidate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
