<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="137964">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02034981</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UC-0105/1303</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-000885-13</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02034981</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 2 Study Assessing Efficacy and Safety of Crizotinib in Patients Harboring an Alteration on ALK, MET or ROS1</brief_title>
  <acronym>AcSé</acronym>
  <official_title>AcSé CRIZOTINIB : Secured Access to Crizotinib for Patients With Tumors Harboring a Genomic Alteration on One of the Biological Targets of the Drug.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>UNICANCER</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fondation ARC</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>UNICANCER</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>France: Agence Nationale de Sécurité du Médicament et des produits de santé</authority>
    <authority>France: Committee for the Protection of Personnes</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a biology driven, trans-tumoral, multicentric phase II trial assessing the efficacy
      and the safety of the targeted agent crizotinib as a monotherapy in 23 cohorts of patients
      with identified activating molecular alterations in the crizotinib target genes. A cohort is
      defined by a pathology and a crizotinib-target alteration (eg gastric cancer with MET
      amplification).

      For each cohort a two-stage design will be implemented. In the situation where expected
      accrual allows for a sufficient number of patients to be accrued, the alpha and beta errors
      will be fixed at 10%. However, in very rare diseases, such as inflammatory myofibroblastic
      tumor (IMT), neuroblastoma, glioblastoma, and rhabdomyosarcoma (RMS), it is anticipated that
      the target number may not be achievable in a reasonable timeframe; for these cohorts, the
      alpha and beta errors will be fixed at 15%. Consequently three different statistical designs
      will be a priori considered according to the expected response rate and incidence.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Twenty cohorts are identified, a cohort being defined as [one pathology, one target
      alteration] such as [gastric cancer with MET amplification (6%)].

      One cohort will be dedicated to miscellaneous, very rare pediatric diseases identified
      through INCa platforms or pan-genome programs (e.g. MOSKIDO, IGR) and will recruit up to 10
      patients.

      Two cohorts will be dedicated to a couple of diseases harbouring at least one specific
      alteration in one crizotinib target, same or different from those listed above, e.g. in AXL
      gene, arising from pan-genome trials.

        1. ALCL, adults and children, ALK-translocated

        2. Colorectal cancer, adults, ALK-translocated

        3. Colorectal cancer, adults, MET amplified

        4. Colorectal cancer, adults, MET mutated

        5. NSCLC, adults, MET amplified

        6. NSCLC, adults, ROS1-translocated

        7. Breast cancer, adults, ALK-translocated

        8. Gastric cancer, adults, MET amplified

        9. Cholangiocarcinoma, adults, ROS1-translocated

       10. Ovarian cancer, adults, MET amplified

       11. Clear cell renal cell carcinoma, adults, ALK-translocated

       12. Clear cell renal cell carcinoma, adults, ALK-amplified

       13. Papillary renal cell carcinoma, adults, MET mutated (+ MET amplified)

       14. Hepatocarcinoma, adults, MET amplified

       15. Neuroblastoma, adults and children, ALK-amplified + ALK mutated

       16. IMT, adults and children, ALK-translocated

       17. Rhabdomyosarcoma (alveolar and embryonal), adults and children, ALK-amplified

       18. Glioblastoma, adults, MET amplified.  This cohort will only be open after amendment

       19. Anaplastic thyroid cancer, adults, ALK mutated

       20. Thyroid cancer (follicular + medullary + papillary), adults, MET mutated

       21. Miscellaneous rare pediatric diseases associated to at least one specific alteration in
           one crizotinib target, same or different from those listed above

       22. One another pathology associated to at least one specific alteration in one crizotinib
           target, same or different from those listed above.

       23. One another pathology associated to at least one specific alteration in one crizotinib
           target, same or different from those listed above.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The efficacy of crizotinib as a single agent across diverse type of tumors guided by the presence of identified activating molecular alterations in the crizotinib target genes, per cohort, per pathology, and per target.</measure>
    <time_frame>Determined after 8 weeks (2 cycles) of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Anti-tumor activity of crizotinib, as the primary objective of the trial, will be carried out by the determination of the objective response assessed in each cohort defined by a pathology associated with a crizotinib target alteration.
The objective response is defined as either a complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) according to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1 criteria.
The objective response after 2 cycles (8 weeks) will be reported to define a success in the 2-stage design.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The safety profile of crizotinib.</measure>
    <time_frame>Safety profile will be assessed during the whole treatment period (6 months expected in average) followed by a 2-year post-treatment follow-up period, and reported during the visits scheduled by the study flow chart</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Toxicities will be assessed by clinical and paraclinical examinations at every scheduled visit during the whole treatment period and the post-treatment follow-up period (around 2.5 years) This study will use the International Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE), version 4.0, for adverse event reporting.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease control rate</measure>
    <time_frame>After 8 weeks (2 cycles) and 16 weeks (4 cycles) of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Disease Control Rate will be the percentage of patients with a CR, PR or Stable Disease (SD) according to RECIST at the end of cycle 2 (8 weeks) and at the end of cycle 4 (16 weeks) in the group of patients evaluable for response</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>response duration</measure>
    <time_frame>interval beetween the objective response (CR or PR) and time of progression, reccurrence or death</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Response duration will be the time interval between the date that the criteria of CR/PR (whichever is first recorded) are met for the first time and the first date of documented re-appearance of the disease (recurrence, progression or death). If neither event has been observed, then the patient is censored at the date of the last follow up examination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>from registration until time of disease progression or death</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Progression-free survival will be the time interval between the date of registration and the day of first documented sign of disease progression (first day when RECIST criteria of progression are met) or day of death whatever the cause (events). If neither event has been observed, then the patient is censored at the date of the last follow up examination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>from registration until date of death</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall survival will be the time interval between the date of registration and the date of death, whatever the cause of death. Patients still alive at follow-up are censored at the date of last follow up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">470</enrollment>
  <condition>Hematologic Cancers</condition>
  <condition>Solid Tumors</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CRIZOTINIB</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All eligible patients entering the study will receive oral crizotinib as monotherapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Crizotinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive oral crizotinib, daily continuously, until progression or unacceptable toxicity develops.
-250 mg twice daily for adults ≥ 18 years of age
280 mg/m2 twice daily for children and adolescents aged from  1 to 17 (except ALCL).
165 mg/m² twice daily for ALCL patients aged from 1 to 17.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CRIZOTINIB</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>XALKORI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and female ≥ 1 year of age

          -  unresectable locally advanced or metastatic malignant tumor (solid or hematological)
             of any histological type (but Non Small Cell Lung Cancer with an ALK derived
             translocation) and not amenable to any other validated therapeutic option

          -  At least one proven specific alterations among ALK, MET, RON and ROS1 genes
             determined on the primary and/or the metastatic lesion

          -  Measurable disease according to RECIST 1.1 guidelines

          -  Adequate hematologic function (ANC ≥ 1.0x109/L, platelets ≥ 75x109/L,  platelets ≥
             50x109/L for ALCL with bone marrow involved ; Hb ≥ 8g/L), renal function (creatinine
             clearance ≥ 60 mL/min using Cockcroft and Gault formula) and hepatic function (serum
             bilirubin ≤ 1.5x upper limit of normal (ULN) unless due to Gilbert's syndrome ; ASAT
             and ALAT ≤ 5x ULN if documented liver metastasis or ≤ 3x ULN if documented liver
             metastasis associated with advanced fibrosis (FibroTest&gt;0.48) or ≤ 3x ULN without
             liver metastasis)

          -  Patients presenting strictly normal values for calcium, magnesium and  potassium
             levels

          -  able to swallow and retain oral medication

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status of 0 to 2, or Karnofsky
             scale &gt; 50 % or Lansky Play scale (&lt; 12 years) &gt; 50%

          -  Life expectancy ≥ 3 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non Small Cell Lung Cancer patients harbouring ALK derived translocations

          -  Patient eligible for a clinical trial with an anticancer drug (including crizotinib)
             targeting the same molecular alteration in the patient's pathology open to accrual in
             France.

          -  Genomic alteration limited to an overexpression of ALK, MET, RON, ROS1 or any other
             crizotinib-target (i.e. without increased copy number or structural gene alteration)
             . Only patients with ALCL are eligible if their tumor is ALK positive as evidenced by
             immunohistochemistry

          -  Patients with primary or secondary central nervous system (CNS) disease

          -  Previous treatment with crizotinib

          -  Major surgery or tumor embolization within 4 weeks and minor surgery within 2 weeks
             prior to the initiation of the study drug

          -  Patients with other concurrent severe and/or uncontrolled medical disease which could
             compromise participation in the study, such as, but not limited to :

               1. Any of the following within the 3 months prior to starting study treatment:
                  myocardial infarction, severe/unstable angina, coronary/peripheral artery bypass
                  graft, or cerebrovascular accident including transient ischemic attack

               2. Ongoing congestive heart failure

               3. Congenital long QT syndrome

               4. Heart rate ≤ 45 beats/minute

               5. Ongoing cardiac dysrhythmias of NCI CTCAE Grade ≥2, uncontrolled atrial
                  fibrillation of any grade, or machine-read ECG with QTcF interval &gt;470 msec

               6. History of extensive disseminated/bilateral or known presence of Grade 3 or 4
                  interstitial fibrosis or interstitial lung disease, including a history of
                  pneumonitis, hypersensitivity pneumonitis, interstitial pneumonia, interstitial
                  lung disease, obliterative bronchiolitis, and pulmonary fibrosis, but not
                  history of prior radiation pneumonitis

               7. Spinal cord compression unless treated with the patient attaining good pain
                  control and stable or recovered neurologic function

               8. Carcinomatous meningitis or leptomeningeal disease

               9. Known HIV-positive, known active hepatitis A, B or C, or latent hepatitis B or
                  C, or any other uncontrolled infection

              10. Other severe acute or chronic medical or psychiatric conditions, or end stage
                  renal disease on hemodialysis or laboratory abnormalities

          -  Patients using non-substitutable drugs that are potent cytochrome P450 isoenzyme 3A4
             (CYP3A4) inhibitors, or potent CYP3A4 inducers

          -  Patients using non-substitutable drugs that are CYP3A4 substrates with narrow
             therapeutic indices
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gilles VASSAL</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Gustave Roussy, Villejuif</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Céline MAHIER</last_name>
    <phone>+ 33 (0)1 44 23 55 84</phone>
    <email>c-mahier@unicancer.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gustave Roussy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Villejuif</city>
        <state>Ile de France</state>
        <zip>94805</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gilles VASSAL</last_name>
      <phone>+ 33 (0) 1 42 11 49 47</phone>
      <email>Gilles.vassal@gustaveroussy.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gilles VASSAL</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.unicancer.fr/sites/default/files/Liste_centres_ouverts_recrutement_acse_crizotinib_04_10_2013.pdf</url>
    <description>List of the centers opened to the recruitment.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 16, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>metastatic or unresectable locally advanced malignancies.</keyword>
  <keyword>genomic alterations.</keyword>
  <keyword>biological crizotinib targets (ALK, MET, ROS1, RON, AXL).</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Second Primary</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hematologic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
