<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="14835">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01725308</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>6949-CL-0021</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01725308</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Efficacy of FK949E in Bipolar Disorder Patients With Major Depressive Episodes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II/III Study of FK949E — Placebo-controlled, Double-blind, Parallel-group Comparative Study and Open-label, Non-controlled Extension Study in Bipolar Disorder Patients With Major Depressive Episodes —</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Astellas Pharma Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Astellas Pharma Inc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Japan: Pharmaceuticals and Medical Devices Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In period I, the treatment effect of FK949E will be compared with that of placebo in a blind
      manner in bipolar disorder patients with major depressive episodes.  In period II, long-term
      safety and efficacy of FK949E will be evaluated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study consists of two part.  In Treatment Period I, FK949E or placebo will be
      administered orally in a blind manner to bipolar disorder patients with major depressive
      episodes, with the aim of evaluating the superiority of FK949 over placebo and the dose
      response of two doses of FK949E based on changes in Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating
      Scale (MADRS) total score. In Treatment Period II, the long-term safety, efficacy and
      parmacokinetics of FK949E will be evaluated in patients who have participated in the study
      and completed the Treatment Period I.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) total score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at 8 weeks after dosing</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MADRS</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at 8 weeks after dosing</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (HAM-D17)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at 8 weeks after dosing</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impression-Bipolar-Severity (CGI-BP-S)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at 8 weeks after dosing</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>(Mania, Depression and Overall)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety assessed by the incidence of adverse events, vital signs, 12-lead ECGs and Labo-tests</measure>
    <time_frame>for 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">340</enrollment>
  <condition>Bipolar Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Period I FK949E</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Period I placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Period II FK949E</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients who completed the treatment Period I</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FK949E</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral</description>
    <arm_group_label>Period I FK949E</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Period II FK949E</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>quetiapine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral</description>
    <arm_group_label>Period I placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of bipolar I or II disorder as specified in the DSM-IV-TR, with a major
             depressive episode

          -  The Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (HAM-D17) total score of 20 points or more and
             HAM-D17 depressed mood score of 2 points or more

          -  Able to participate in the study with understanding of and compliance with subject
             requirements during the study in the investigator's or subinvestigator's opinion

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Concurrent or previous history of DSM-IV-TR Axis I disorders, except bipolar
             disorder, within the last 6 months before informed consent

          -  Concurrence of DSM-IV-TR Axis II disorder that is considered to greatly affect
             patient's current mental status

          -  The Young Mania Rating Scale (YMRS) total score of 13 points or more

          -  Nine or more mood episodes within the last 12 months before informed consent

          -  Lack of response to at least 6-week treatment with at least 2 antidepressants for the
             current major depressive episode in the investigator's or subinvestigator's opinion

          -  History of abuse or dependence of alcohol or substances other than caffeine and
             nicotine

          -  Treatment with a depot antipsychotic within the last 42 days before primary
             registration

          -  Unable to suspend mood stabilizers (lithium carbonate and/or sodium valproate),
             lamotrigine, antipsychotics, or antidepressants from 7 days before secondary
             registration

          -  Unable to suspend antiepileptics (except lamotrigine and sodium valproate),
             antianxiety agents, hypnotics, sedatives, psychostimulants, antiparkinsonian agents,
             cerebral ameliorators, antidementia agents, or anorectics, except those specified as
             conditionally-allowed concomitant drugs, after primary registration

          -  Electroconvulsive therapy within the last 76 days before primary registration

          -  The current major depressive episode persisting for more than 12 months or less than
             4 weeks before informed consent

          -  A possible need of psychotherapy during the study period (unless the therapy has been
             commenced at least 76 days before primary registration and been maintained on a fixed
             level at fixed frequency)

          -  Documented or suspected conditions such as renal failure, hepatic failure, serious
             cardiac disease, hepatitis B, hepatitis C, or acquired immunodeficiency syndrome
             (AIDS) (or to be a carrier of hepatitis B, hepatitis C, or AIDS)

          -  Concurrence of malignancy or history of cured malignancy within 5 years

          -  Concurrence of uncontrolled hypertension (defined as a systolic blood pressure of 180
             mmHg or more, or a diastolic blood pressure of 110 mmHg or more at primary
             registration) or unstable angina that may worsen with the study or may affect the
             study results based on the clinical judgment of the investigator or sub-investigator

          -  Concurrence of hypotension (defined as a systolic blood pressure of less than 100
             mmHg at primary registration) or orthostatic hypotension

          -  History of transient, idiopathic orthostatic hypotension, with or without pre-syncope
             symptoms or syncope, or a current condition susceptible to transient hypotension,
             such as dehydration and decreased blood volume

          -  Concurrent or previous history of cerebrovascular disease or transient ischemic
             attack (TIA)

          -  Abnormal laboratory or electrocardiographic findings considered clinically
             significant in the investigator's or subinvestigator's opinion (in reference to grade
             3 of the Adverse Drug Reactions Severity Grading Criteria [Notification No. 80 of the
             Safety Division, Pharmaceutical Affairs Bureau, Ministry of Health and Welfare dated
             29 June 1992])

          -  Participation in another clinical study or post-marketing study within the last 12
             weeks before informed consent

          -  History of quetiapine therapy during the current major depressive episode

          -  Pregnant or lactating women
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Astellas Pharma Inc</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Clinical Development Administration Dept.</last_name>
    <email>clinicaltrials_info@jp.astellas.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Chubu</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Chugoku</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Hokkaido</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kansai</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kanto</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kyushu</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Shikoku</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Touhoku</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 22, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 8, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>FK949E</keyword>
  <keyword>Major depressive episode</keyword>
  <keyword>patients</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Bipolar Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
