<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="95768">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01894256</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>D0816C00006</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-002225-30</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01894256</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Assess the Blood Levels and Safety of Olaparib in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumours and Normal or Impaired Kidney Function</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label, Non-randomised, Multicentre, Comparative, Phase I Study of the Pharmacokinetics, Safety and Tolerability of Olaparib Following a Single Oral 300 mg Dose to Patients With Advanced Solid Tumours and Normal Renal Function or Renal Impairment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AstraZeneca</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Belgium: Federal Agency for Medicinal Products and Health Products</authority>
    <authority>Belgium: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>Netherlands: The Central Committee on Research Involving Human Subjects (CCMO)</authority>
    <authority>Netherlands: Medical Ethics Review Committee (METC)</authority>
    <authority>Denmark: Danish Dataprotection Agency</authority>
    <authority>Denmark: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>France: Institutional Ethical Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a 2-part study in patients with advanced solid tumours. Part A will investigate the
      PK of olaparib in patients with mild or moderate renal impairment compared to patients with
      normal renal function; Part B will allow eligible study patients continued access to
      olaparib after the PK phase and will provide additional safety data.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of olaparib: maximum olaparib concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood samples will be collected on Day 1 of Part A at these time points: pre-dose, 0.25,0.5,1,1.5,2,3,4,6,8,12,24,48,72 and 96 hours post-dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In Part A, the following variable will be calculated for olaparib where the data allow: maximum plasma concentration (Cmax). Pharmacokinetics will not be measured in Part B</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of olaparib : time to maximum concentration (tmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood samples will be collected on Day 1 of Part A at these time points: pre-dose, 0.25,0.5,1,1.5,2,3,4,6,8,12,24,48,72 and 96 hours post-dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In Part A, the following variable will be calculated for olaparib where the data allow: time to reach maximum plasma concentration (tmax). Pharmacokinetics will not be measured in Part B</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of olaparib: area under the plasma concentration-time curve from zero to the last measurable time point (AUC0-t)</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood samples will be collected on Day 1 of Part A at these time points: pre-dose, 0.25,0.5,1,1.5,2,3,4,6,8,12,24,48,72 and 96 hours post-dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In Part A, the following variable will be calculated for olaparib where the data allow: area under the plasma concentration-time curve from zero to the last measurable time point (AUC0-t). Pharmacokinetics will not be measured in Part B</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of olaparib : area under the plasma concentration-time curve from zero to infinity (AUC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood samples will be collected on Day 1 of Part A at these time points: pre-dose, 0.25,0.5,1,1.5,2,3,4,6,8,12,24,48,72 and 96 hours post-dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In Part A, the following variable will be calculated for olaparib where the data allow: area under the plasma concentration-time curve from zero to infinity (AUC). Pharmacokinetics will not be measured in Part B</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of olaparib : apparent plasma clearance following oral administration  (CL/F)</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood samples will be collected on Day 1 of Part A at these time points: pre-dose, 0.25,0.5,1,1.5,2,3,4,6,8,12,24,48,72 and 96 hours post-dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In Part A, the following variable will be calculated for olaparib where the data allow: apparent plasma clearance following oral administration (CL/F). Pharmacokinetics will not be measured in Part B</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of olaparib : terminal half-life (t½)</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood samples will be collected on Day 1 of Part A at these time points: pre-dose, 0.25,0.5,1,1.5,2,3,4,6,8,12,24,48,72 and 96 hours post-dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In Part A, the following variable will be calculated for olaparib where the data allow: terminal half-life (t½). Pharmacokinetics will not be measured in Part B</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of olaparib : apparent volume of distribution  (Vz/F)</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood samples will be collected on Day 1 of Part A at these time points: pre-dose, 0.25,0.5,1,1.5,2,3,4,6,8,12,24,48,72 and 96 hours post-dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In Part A, the following variable will be calculated for olaparib where the data allow: apparent volume of distribution (Vz/F). Pharmacokinetics will not be measured in Part B</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of olaparib : terminal rate constant (λz)</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood samples will be collected on Day 1 of Part A at these time points: pre-dose, 0.25,0.5,1,1.5,2,3,4,6,8,12,24,48,72 and 96 hours post-dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In Part A, the following variable will be calculated for olaparib where the data allow: terminal rate constant (λz). Pharmacokinetics will not be measured in Part B</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of olaparib : renal clearance (CLR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood samples will be collected on Day 1 of Part A at these time points: pre-dose, 0.25,0.5,1,1.5,2,3,4,6,8,12,24,48,72 and 96 hours post-dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In Part A, the following variable will be calculated for olaparib where the data allow: renal clearance (CLR). Pharmacokinetics will not be measured in Part B</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of the safety and tolerability of olaparib by collection of adverse event reports</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline, every visit until 30 days after last dose, assessed up to 20 months.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessment of adverse events (AEs) graded by Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) v4.0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine safety and tolerability of olaparib by assessment of 12 lead Electrocardiograms</measure>
    <time_frame>Part A: baseline, days 1 and 3. Part B: Day 1 then every 4 weeks. Final assessment within 30 days after last dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessment of standard 12 lead electrocardiograms (ECGs)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine safety and tolerability of olaparib by physical examination</measure>
    <time_frame>Part A: baseline, day -1 and within 30 days after last dose. Part B: Day 1.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessment of physical examination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine safety and tolerability of olaparib by assessment of vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>Part A: baseline, days 1,2 and 3. Part B: Days 1,8,15,22,29  then every 4 weeks. Final assessment within 30 days after last dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessment of standard vital signs (including blood pressure, pulse)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine safety and tolerability of olaparib by assessment of body temperature</measure>
    <time_frame>Part A: baseline, day 1. Part B: Days 1,8,15,22,29  then every 4 weeks. Final assessment within 30 days after last dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessment of standard vital signs (body temperature)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine safety and tolerability of olaparib by assessment of clinical chemistry results</measure>
    <time_frame>Part A: baseline, days -1 and 3. Part B: Days 1,8,15,22,29 then every 4 weeks. Final assessment within 30 days after last dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessment of laboratory parameters (clinical chemistry)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine safety and tolerability of olaparib by assessment of haematology results</measure>
    <time_frame>Part A: baseline, days -1 and 3. Part B: Days 1,8,15,22,29  then every 4 weeks. Final assessment within 30 days after last dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessment of laboratory parameters (haematology)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine safety and tolerability of olaparib by assessment of urinalysis results</measure>
    <time_frame>Part A: baseline, days -1 and 3. Part B: Days 1,8,15,22,29  then every 4 weeks. Final assessment within 30 days after last dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessment of laboratory parameters (urinalysis)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in plasma protein binding of olaparib and subsequent effects on pharmacokinetics: free maximum plasma concentration of unbound olaparib (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood sample taken at 1 hour post first olaparib dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In Part A, plasma protein binding at 1 hour after dosing, used to calculate free Cmax (Cmax of unbound olaparib)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in plasma protein binding of olaparib and subsequent effects on pharmacokinetics: free area under the plasma concentration-time curve from zero to infinity of unbound olaparib (AUC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood sample taken at 1 hour post first olaparib dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In Part A, plasma protein binding at 1 hour after dosing, used to calculate free AUC (AUC of unbound olaparib)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in plasma protein binding of olaparib and subsequent effects on pharmacokinetics: free apparent plasma clearance of unbound olaparib (CL/F)</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood sample taken at 1 hour post first olaparib dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In Part A, plasma protein binding at 1 hour after dosing, used to calculate unbound CL/F (CL/F of unbound olaparib)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">42</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumours</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal renal function</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with calculated serum creatinine clearance ≥81 mL/min (using Cockcroft-Gault equation).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mild renal impairment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with calculated serum creatinine clearance 51-80 mL/min (using Cockcroft-Gault equation).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Moderate renal impairment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with calculated serum creatinine clearance 31-50 mL/min (using Cockcroft-Gault equation).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Olaparib tablet dosing</intervention_name>
    <description>Part A - single 300mg oral dose olaparib (administered as 2x150mg tablets) Part B - 300mg oral dose olaparib (administered as 2x150mg tablets) bd</description>
    <arm_group_label>Normal renal function</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Mild renal impairment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Moderate renal impairment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:-

        For inclusion in the study as a patient with renal impairment, the following criterion
        must be met:

          1. Patients must have stable renal impairment (moderate or mild), depending on
             creatinine clearance estimated using the Cockcroft-Gault equation (moderate 31 to 50
             mL/min; mild 51 to 80 mL/min), for at least 2 months prior to the start of the study.
              For inclusion in the study as a patient with normal renal function, the following
             criterion must be met:

          2. Calculated serum creatinine clearance greater than or equal to 81 mL/min (using
             Cockcroft-Gault equation).  All patients must fulfil the following criteria:

          3. Provision of written informed consent prior to any study specific procedures .

          4. Patients must be  greater than or equal to 18 and less than or equal to 75 years of
             age.

          5. Histologically or, where appropriate, cytologically confirmed malignant solid tumour
             refractory or resistant to standard therapy or for which no suitable effective
             standard therapy exists.

          6. BMI between 18-30 kg/m2.

          7. Normal liver and bone marrow function measured within 28 days prior to administration
             of IP as defined below:  Haemoglobin (Hb)  greater than or equal to 10.0 g/dL, with
             no blood transfusions in the previous 28 days.

             Absolute neutrophil count (ANC)  greater than or equal to 1.5 x 109/L. White blood
             cells (WBC) greater than 3 x 109/L. Platelet count greater than or equal to 100 x
             109/L. Total bilirubin  less than or equal to 1.5 x institutional upper limit of
             normal (ULN) (except in the case of Gilbert's disease).

             Aspartate aminotransferase or serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase (AST), alanine
             aminotransferase or serum glutamic pyruvic transaminase (ALT) less than or equal to
             2.5 x institutional ULN unless liver metastases are present in which case it must be
             less than or equal to 5x ULN.

          8. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status  less than or equal to
             2.

          9. Patients must have a life expectancy  greater than or equal to 12 weeks.

         10. Evidence of non childbearing status for women of childbearing potential, or
             postmenopausal status:  negative urine or serum pregnancy test within 28 days of
             study treatment, confirmed prior to treatment on Day 1 of the first treatment period
             in Part A.  Postmenopausal is defined as:

             Amenorrheic for 1 year or more following cessation of exogenous hormonal treatments.

             Luteinising hormone and follicle-stimulating hormone levels in the postmenopausal
             range for women under 50 years of age.

             Radiation-induced oophorectomy with last menses greater than 1 year ago.
             Chemotherapy-induced menopause with greater than 1 year interval since last menses
             Surgical sterilisation (bilateral oophorectomy or hysterectomy).

         11. Patients are willing and able to comply with the protocol for the duration of the
             study including undergoing treatment and scheduled visits and examinations.

         12. Patients must be on a stable concomitant medication regimen (with the exception of
             electrolyte supplements), defined as no changes in medication or in dose within 2
             weeks prior to start of olaparib dosing, except for bisphosphonates, denosumab and
             corticosteroids, which should be stable for at least 4 weeks prior to start of
             olaparib dosing.

        Exclusion criteria:-

        Patients must not enter the study if any of the following exclusion criteria are
        fulfilled:

          1. Involvement in the planning and/or conduct of the study (applies to both AstraZeneca
             staff, its agents and/or staff at the study site).

          2. Previous enrolment in the present study.

          3. Participation in another clinical study with an investigational medicinal product
             (IP) during the last 14 days (or a longer period depending on the defined
             characteristics of the agent used).

          4. Renal transplant and end stage renal disease (ESRD) patients.

          5. Patients receiving any systemic chemotherapy or radiotherapy (except for palliative
             reasons) within 2 weeks prior to study treatment (or a longer period depending on the
             defined characteristics of the agents used).  The patient can receive a stable dose
             of bisphosphonates or denosumab for bone metastases before and during the study as
             long as these were started at least 4 weeks prior to treatment.

          6. Patients who have received or are receiving inhibitors or inducers of CYP3A4 within
             the washout period.

          7. For Part A only, drugs which affect creatinine clearance such as cephalosporin
             antibiotics, ascorbic acid, trimethoprim, cimetidine and quinine should not be used
             within the 7 days prior to dosing with olaparib.

          8. Treatment in the previous 3 months with any drug known to have a well-defined
             potential for hepatotoxicity (eg, halothane).

          9. Persistent toxicities (greater than or equal to CTCAE Grade 2) caused by previous
             cancer therapy, excluding alopecia.

         10. Patients with myelodysplastic syndrome/acute myeloid leukaemia.

         11. Patients with symptomatic uncontrolled brain metastases.  A scan to confirm the
             absence of brain metastases is not required.  Patients with asymptomatic brain
             metastases or with symptomatic but stable brain metastases can receive a stable dose
             of corticosteroids before and during the study as long as these were started at least
             4 weeks prior to treatment.

         12. Major surgery within 2 weeks of starting study treatment and patients must have
             recovered from any effects of major surgery.

         13. Patients considered a poor medical risk due to a serious uncontrolled medical
             disorder, non malignant systemic disease, uncontrolled seizures, or active
             uncontrolled infection.  Examples include, but are not limited to, uncontrolled
             ventricular arrhythmia, recent (within 3 months) myocardial infarction, uncontrolled
             major seizure disorder, unstable spinal cord compression, superior vena cava
             syndrome, extensive bilateral interstitial lung disease on high resolution computer
             tomography (HRCT) scan, or any psychiatric disorder that prohibits obtaining informed
             consent.

         14. Patients with a history of heart failure or left ventricular dysfunction.

         15. Patients who have gastric, gastro-oesophageal or oesophageal cancer.

         16. Patients unable to swallow orally administered medication and patients with
             gastrointestinal disorders or significant gastrointestinal resection likely to
             interfere with the absorption of olaparib.

         17. Breastfeeding women.

         18. Immunocompromised patients eg, patients who are known to be serologically positive
             for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).

         19. Patients with known active hepatic disease (eg, hepatitis B or C).

         20. Patients with a known hypersensitivity to olaparib or any of the excipients of the
             product.

         21. Resting ECG at screening with measurable QTc  greater than 470 msec at 2 or more time
             points within a 24 hour period or family history of long QT syndrome.

         22. Clinical judgment by the investigator that the patient should not participate in the
             study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anitra Fielding</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>AstraZeneca Senior Research Physician</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christian Rolfo</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UZ Antwerpen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Clinical Trials Transparency</last_name>
    <email>ClinicalTrialTransparency@astrazeneca.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jan Van Riet</last_name>
    <phone>+ 32 2 755 08 27</phone>
    <email>jan.van.riet@quintiles.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brussels (Jette)</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edegem</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liege</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wilrijk</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Herlev</city>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>København Ø</city>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bordeaux</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dijon</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maastricht</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newcastle Upon Tyne</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Surrey</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Denmark</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 16, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 4, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>oncology,</keyword>
  <keyword>cancer,</keyword>
  <keyword>neoplasm,</keyword>
  <keyword>anticancer drug,</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacokinetics,</keyword>
  <keyword>area under curve,</keyword>
  <keyword>olaparib,</keyword>
  <keyword>solid tumour,</keyword>
  <keyword>mild renal impairment,</keyword>
  <keyword>moderate renal impairment</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
