<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="55294">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01854632</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LAIV-SEN-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01854632</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Efficacy of Trivalent Live-Attenuated Influenza Vaccine (LAIV) Among Children in Senegal</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial of the Clinical Efficacy of Trivalent Live-Attenuated Influenza Vaccine (LAIV) Among Children in Senegal</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>PATH</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institut de Recherche pour le Developpement</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institut Pasteur de Dakar</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>PATH</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Senegal: National Ethics Commitee for Health Research, Ministry of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will provide the Senegal Ministry of Health with data on the clinical efficacy of
      the Live-Attenuated Influenza Vaccine (LAIV). This data will inform future policy
      considerations for influenza vaccine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a double-blind, individual-randomized, placebo-controlled, clinical efficacy
      trial among healthy children aged 24 through 71 months in the Niakhar area of Senegal. A
      total of 1,761 healthy children will be randomized in a 2:1 ratio of LAIV to placebo.

      For evaluation of efficacy, passive and active surveillance will be conducted weekly
      throughout the study to identify outcomes among vaccinated subjects. Children meeting the
      protocol-defined clinical case definition will have a nasal swab and throat swab specimen
      collected for testing by rRT-PCR for evidence of influenza virus infection.

      A subset of 100 children will be additionally included in a substudy designed to evaluate
      virologic evidence of LAIV replication. As such, nasal and throat swab specimens will be
      collected on day 0 (prior to vaccination), as well as on post-vaccination days 2, and 4 from
      all subjects included in the substudy. These specimens will be tested for presence of
      wild-type and vaccine virus. Additionally, a more detailed assessment of vaccine
      reactogenicity will be made among these children by actively collecting solicited and
      unsolicited reactions at each study visit for the week post vaccination (days 2 and 4).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of LAIV in reducing rates of symptomatic, laboratory-confirmed influenza virus infection (regardless of vaccine match)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 7 to 8 months post vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety profile of LAIV: immediate reactions occurring within 30 minutes of administration of study vaccine.</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 30 minutes post vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety profile of LAIV: solicited and unsolicited local and systemic reactions</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 7 days post vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety profile of LAIV: serious adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 1 month post vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety profile of LAIV: other non-serious adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 1 month post vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety profile of LAIV: Protocol Defined Wheezing Illness</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 7 to 8 months post vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of LAIV in reducing rates of symptomatic, laboratory-confirmed influenza virus infection (vaccine-matched strains)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 7 to 8 months post vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of LAIV in reducing rates of symptomatic, laboratory-confirmed influenza virus infection by influenza type/subtype (influenza A/H1N1, influenza A/H3N2, and influenza B)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 7 to 8 months post vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical characteristics of influenza in the study population</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 7 to 8 months post vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Etiologies of influenza-like illness in the study population</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 7 to 8 months post vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Bacterial and viral etiologies of acute respiratory and febrile illness will be parameterized as the percentage of those with each particular laboratory-confirmed infection categorized by vaccine allocation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of vaccine-take as shedding of vaccine virus post-vaccination, including viral load and duration of virus detection</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 4 days post vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Vaccine take will be parameterized as the percentage of participants with detectable vaccine-virus in nasal or throat swab on each day pre- (day 0) and post vaccination (i.e., 2 and 4 days post vaccination), and the quantity of detected virus.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1761</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SIIL Live Attenuated Influenza Vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single 0.5 mL dose of trivalent live-attenuated influenza vaccine 2012/2013 Northern Hemisphere vaccine containing A/California/7/2009 (H1N1), A/Victoria/361/2011 (H3N2), B/Wisconsin/1/2010</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Matched placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single 0.5mL inactive placebo will be identical to reconstituted SIIL LAIV in ingredients and concentrations except A/California/7/2009 (H1N1), A/Victoria/361/2011 (H3N2), B/Wisconsin/1/2010 will be replaced with egg allantoic fluid.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SIIL Live Attenuated Influenza Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Trivalent live-attenuated influenza vaccine 2012/2013 Northern Hemisphere vaccine containing A/California/7/2009 (H1N1), A/Victoria/361/2011 (H3N2), B/Wisconsin/1/2010</description>
    <arm_group_label>SIIL Live Attenuated Influenza Vaccine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Matched placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Matched placebo will be identical to reconstituted SIIL LAIV in ingredients and concentrations except A/California/7/2009 (H1N1), A/Victoria/361/2011 (H3N2), B/Wisconsin/1/2010 will be replaced with egg allantoic fluid.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Matched placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy male or female child at least 24 months of age and no older than 71 months of
             age at the time of study vaccination.

          -  A child whose parent or guardian's primary residence, at the time of study
             vaccinations, is within the Niakhar DSS and who intends to be present in the area for
             the duration of the trial.

          -  A child whose parent or legal guardian is willing to provide written informed consent
             prior to the participant's study vaccination

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Serious, active, medical condition, including: chronic disease of any body
             system,chronic infections such as tuberculosis, genetic disorders, such as Down's
             syndrome or other cytogenetic disorder, known or suspected disease of the immune
             system of any kind.

          -  History of documented hypersensitivity to eggs or other components of the vaccine
             (including gelatin, sorbitol, lactalbumin and chicken protein), or with
             life-threatening reactions to previous influenza vaccinations.

          -  History of Guillain-Barré syndrome.

          -  Receipt of immunosuppressive agents, including systemic corticosteroids, during the
             month before planned study vaccination.

          -  Receipt of aspirin therapy or aspirin-containing therapy within the two weeks before
             planned study vaccination.

          -  History of any severe allergic reaction with generalized urticarial, angioedema, or
             anaphylaxis.

          -  Receipt of an influenza vaccine within the past 12 months.

          -  Has any condition determined by investigator as likely to interfere with evaluation
             of the vaccine or be a significant potential health risk to the child or make it
             unlikely that the child would complete the study.

        Temporary Contraindications:

          -  Acute illness accompanied by a body temperature of 37.5°C or above (axillary
             measurement) within 14 days of enrollment visit.

          -  Any acute respiratory infection within 14 days of enrollment visit.

          -  Any illness accompanied by active wheezing within 14 days of enrollment visit.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>24 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>71 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Aldiouma Diallo, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institut de Recherche pour le Développement (IRD)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut de Recherche pour le Développement (IRD), Niakhar station</name>
      <address>
        <city>Niakhar</city>
        <country>Senegal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Senegal</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 6, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 13, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>influenza vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>trivalent live-attenuated influenza vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>efficacy</keyword>
  <keyword>Africa</keyword>
  <keyword>Senegal</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
