<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="146404">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02036086</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ML28606</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02036086</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Neoadjuvant Vemurafenib for BRAF Mutant Melanoma and Palpable Lymph Node Metastasis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study of the Neo-adjuvant Use of Vemurafenib in Patients With BRAF Mutant Melanoma With Palpable Lymph Node Metastasis.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the clinical and pathological response to vemurafenib in the
      neoadjuvant treatment of patients with histologically confirmed, BRAF V600 mutation-positive
      Stage IIIB and C melanoma.  Approximately 20 patients will take vemurafenib 960 mg by mouth
      twice a day for 2 months and then assessed for resectability. Patients will then undergo
      surgical resection (lymphadenectomy) and subsequently resume taking vemurafenib after
      recovery from surgery. Patients will undergo adjuvant radiation therapy if appropriate then
      continue vemurafenib for another 10 months, for total of 12 months or until disease
      recurrence, death, unacceptable toxicity, or withdrawal of consent. Doses of study treatment
      may be modified and/or interrupted for management of toxicities associated with study
      treatment. Patients will be followed for disease recurrence and survival during and after
      the treatment period for a total of 5 years.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi centre pilot study for neoadjuvant treatment of patients with histologically
      confirmed, BRAF V600 mutation-positive Stage IIIB and C melanoma. 20 patients will be
      enrolled. During Screening: They will undergo protocol assessments within 28 days of
      randomization or unless otherwise indicated as per protocol. Physical exam will be done
      within 7 days of study treatment initiation. Core biopsy will be done within 14 days of
      study entry. During treatment, they will take vemurafenib 960 mg by mouth twice a day for 2
      months &amp; then be assessed for respectability. They then undergo surgical resection
      (lymphadenectomy) &amp; resume taking vemurafenib after recovery from surgery. They will undergo
      adjuvant radiation therapy if appropriate, then continue vemurafenib for another 10 months,
      for total of 12 months or until disease recurrence, death, unacceptable toxicity, or
      withdrawal of consent.  If a patient receives 2 months of neoadjuvant vemurafenib then they
      will receive 10 months post surgery.  Or, if they receive 4 months then 8 months will be
      post surgery for a total of 12 months.  They will be assessed every 28 days while on drug
      therapy.  After Treatment, they are followed for disease recurrence/survival every 4 months
      for the 1st year post treatment, then they are seen every 6 months to year 5 or as
      clinically indicated.  Imaging scans will be performed every 6 months for first 3 years and
      yearly to 5 years or as clinically indicated.  Dermatological exams are scheduled before
      drug therapy, before surgery and then as clinically indicated during follow-up.  Head and
      neck exams take place every 26 weeks on treatment until 26 weeks after treatment to assess
      for Squamous Cell Carcinoma (SCC). Suspicious SCC lesions will be biopsied.  Anal and pelvic
      exams take place on treatment Cycle 6 Day 1 and at end of treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The feasibility of treating patients with unresectable melanoma and palpable lymph node metastases that harbor the BRAF mutation with neoadjuvant vemurafenib.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Resectability rates post vemurafenib therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Local-regional recurrence rates after treatment with neo-adjuvant vemurafenib.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to distant metastases and Distant Metastatic Free Survival (DMFS).</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Free Survival (DFS) and Overall Survival (OS).e</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunohistochemical correlates of tumor response.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of vemurafenib in the neoadjuvant setting</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vemurafenib, pill, twice daily</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Vemurafenib, 960 mg, oral, twice daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vemurafenib</intervention_name>
    <description>Drug</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vemurafenib, pill, twice daily</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vemurafenib</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  male or female ≥ 18 years

          -  melanoma with palpable regional lymph node metastases, stage IIIB or C or with
             recurrent regional lymphadenopathy that are not suitable or not preferred for
             surgical intervention

          -  BRAF V600 mutation positive

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0 or 1

          -  Ability to participate and willingness to give written informed consent prior to
             performance of any study-related procedure and to comply with study protocol

          -  Adequate hematologic, renal and liver function as defined by the following laboratory
             values performed within 7 days prior to the first dose of vemurafenib:

               1. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 x 109/L

               2. Platelet count ≥ 100 ×109/L

               3. Hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dL

               4. Bilirubin ≤ 1.5 × the upper limit of normal (ULN)

               5. Aspartate aminotransferase (AST), Alanine aminotransferase (ALT), and alkaline
                  phosphatase (ALP) ≤ 2.5 × the ULN Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 × the ULN or creatinine
                  clearance ≥ 50 mL/min on the basis of the Cockroft−Gault glomerular filtration
                  rate estimation: [(140−age) × (weight in kg × (0.85 if female)]/[72 × (serum
                  creatinine in mg/dL)]

               6. Prothrombin time (PT), international normalized ratio (INR), partial
                  thromboplastin time (PTT) ≤ 1.5 × the ULN

          -  Female patients of childbearing potential and male patients with partners of
             childbearing potential must agree to always use an effective form(s) of contraception
             beginning from the informed consent signature date until at least 6 months after
             completion of study therapy

          -  Negative serum pregnancy test within 14 days prior to randomization in women of
             childbearing potential

          -  Women of non-child bearing potential need not undergo pregnancy testing.

          -  Absence of any psychological, familial, sociological, or geographical condition
             potentially hampering compliance with the study protocol and follow-up schedule

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of clinically significant cardiac or pulmonary dysfunction, including the
             following:

               1. Current uncontrolled, Grade ≥ 2 hypertension (treated or untreated) or unstable
                  angina

               2. Current Grade ≥ 2 dyspnea or hypoxia or need for supplemental oxygen

               3. History of symptomatic congestive heart failure of Grade II−IV New York Heart
                  Association Class

               4. Serious cardiac arrhythmia requiring treatment, with the exceptions of atrial
                  fibrillation and paroxysmal supraventricular tachycardia

               5. History of myocardial infarction within 6 months prior to randomization

               6. History of congenital long QT syndrome or corrected QT interval (QTc interval)
                  &gt;450 ms at baseline

               7. History of an uncorrectable electrolyte disorder affecting serum levels of
                  potassium, calcium, or magnesium

          -  Evidence of distant metastatic disease.

          -  History of clinically significant liver disease (including cirrhosis), current
             alcohol abuse, or known infection with Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV), hepatitis
             B virus, or hepatitis C virus.

          -  Active infection or chronic infection requiring chronic suppressive antibiotics

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding at the time of randomization

          -  Active autoimmune disease (e.g., systemic lupus erythematosus, autoimmune vasculitis,
             inflammatory bowel disease [Crohn's disease and ulcerative colitis])

          -  Acromegaly
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Teresa Petrella, MD, BSc, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Teresa Petrella, MD, BSc, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>416 480 5248</phone>
    <email>teresa.petrella@sunnybrook.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Frances Wright, MD, MEd</last_name>
    <phone>416 480 4210</phone>
    <email>frances.wright@sunnybrook.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M4N 3M5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Teresa Petrella, MD, BSc, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>416 480 5248</phone>
      <email>teresa.petrella@sunnybrook.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Teresa Petrella, MD, BSc, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Victoria Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H3A 1A1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Catalin Mihalcioiu, MD</last_name>
      <phone>514 934 1934</phone>
      <phone_ext>35800</phone_ext>
      <email>catalin.mihalcioiu@muhc.mcgill.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Catalin Mihalcioiu, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Balch CM, Soong SJ, Gershenwald JE, Thompson JF, Reintgen DS, Cascinelli N, Urist M, McMasters KM, Ross MI, Kirkwood JM, Atkins MB, Thompson JA, Coit DG, Byrd D, Desmond R, Zhang Y, Liu PY, Lyman GH, Morabito A. Prognostic factors analysis of 17,600 melanoma patients: validation of the American Joint Committee on Cancer melanoma staging system. J Clin Oncol. 2001 Aug 15;19(16):3622-34.</citation>
    <PMID>11504744</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bevilacqua RG, Coit DG, Rogatko A, Younes RN, Brennan MF. Axillary dissection in melanoma. Prognostic variables in node-positive patients. Ann Surg. 1990 Aug;212(2):125-31.</citation>
    <PMID>2375645</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mocellin S, Pasquali S, Rossi CR, Nitti D. Interferon alpha adjuvant therapy in patients with high-risk melanoma: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2010 Apr 7;102(7):493-501. doi: 10.1093/jnci/djq009. Epub 2010 Feb 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20179267</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hauschild A, Gogas H, Tarhini A, Middleton MR, Testori A, Dréno B, Kirkwood JM. Practical guidelines for the management of interferon-alpha-2b side effects in patients receiving adjuvant treatment for melanoma: expert opinion. Cancer. 2008 Mar 1;112(5):982-94. doi: 10.1002/cncr.23251. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18236459</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Balch CM, Gershenwald JE, Soong SJ, Thompson JF, Atkins MB, Byrd DR, Buzaid AC, Cochran AJ, Coit DG, Ding S, Eggermont AM, Flaherty KT, Gimotty PA, Kirkwood JM, McMasters KM, Mihm MC Jr, Morton DL, Ross MI, Sober AJ, Sondak VK. Final version of 2009 AJCC melanoma staging and classification. J Clin Oncol. 2009 Dec 20;27(36):6199-206. Epub 2009 Nov 16.</citation>
    <PMID>19917835</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shah GD, Socci ND, Gold JS, Wolchok JD, Carvajal RD, Panageas KS, Viale A, Brady MS, Coit DG, Chapman PB. Phase II trial of neoadjuvant temozolomide in resectable melanoma patients. Ann Oncol. 2010 Aug;21(8):1718-22. doi: 10.1093/annonc/mdp593. Epub 2010 Jan 15.</citation>
    <PMID>20080829</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moschos SJ, Edington HD, Land SR, Rao UN, Jukic D, Shipe-Spotloe J, Kirkwood JM. Neoadjuvant treatment of regional stage IIIB melanoma with high-dose interferon alfa-2b induces objective tumor regression in association with modulation of tumor infiltrating host cellular immune responses. J Clin Oncol. 2006 Jul 1;24(19):3164-71.</citation>
    <PMID>16809739</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gibbs P, Anderson C, Pearlman N, LaClaire S, Becker M, Gatlin K, O'Driscoll M, Stephens J, Gonzalez R. A phase II study of neoadjuvant biochemotherapy for stage III melanoma. Cancer. 2002 Jan 15;94(2):470-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11900232</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Young K, Minchom A, Larkin J. BRIM-1, -2 and -3 trials: improved survival with vemurafenib in metastatic melanoma patients with a BRAF(V600E) mutation. Future Oncol. 2012 May;8(5):499-507. doi: 10.2217/fon.12.43.</citation>
    <PMID>22646765</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Long GV, Menzies AM, Nagrial AM, Haydu LE, Hamilton AL, Mann GJ, Hughes TM, Thompson JF, Scolyer RA, Kefford RF. Prognostic and clinicopathologic associations of oncogenic BRAF in metastatic melanoma. J Clin Oncol. 2011 Apr 1;29(10):1239-46. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2010.32.4327. Epub 2011 Feb 22.</citation>
    <PMID>21343559</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sosman JA, Kim KB, Schuchter L, Gonzalez R, Pavlick AC, Weber JS, McArthur GA, Hutson TE, Moschos SJ, Flaherty KT, Hersey P, Kefford R, Lawrence D, Puzanov I, Lewis KD, Amaravadi RK, Chmielowski B, Lawrence HJ, Shyr Y, Ye F, Li J, Nolop KB, Lee RJ, Joe AK, Ribas A. Survival in BRAF V600-mutant advanced melanoma treated with vemurafenib. N Engl J Med. 2012 Feb 23;366(8):707-14. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1112302.</citation>
    <PMID>22356324</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chapman PB, Hauschild A, Robert C, Haanen JB, Ascierto P, Larkin J, Dummer R, Garbe C, Testori A, Maio M, Hogg D, Lorigan P, Lebbe C, Jouary T, Schadendorf D, Ribas A, O'Day SJ, Sosman JA, Kirkwood JM, Eggermont AM, Dreno B, Nolop K, Li J, Nelson B, Hou J, Lee RJ, Flaherty KT, McArthur GA; BRIM-3 Study Group. Improved survival with vemurafenib in melanoma with BRAF V600E mutation. N Engl J Med. 2011 Jun 30;364(26):2507-16. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1103782. Epub 2011 Jun 5. PubMed PMID: 21639808; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3549296.</citation>
    <PMID>21639808</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 28, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Melanoma stage IIIB or C with BRAF mutation</keyword>
  <keyword>Recurrent regional lymphadenopathy not suitable for surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Eligible for neoadjuvant vemurafenib</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
