<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="87268">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01802151</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>177-2012</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01802151</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Bacillus Subtilis R0179 in Healthy Young Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Bacillus Subtilis R0179 in Capsules on Gastrointestinal Survival, Transit Time, Gastrointestinal Symptoms, and General Wellness in Healthy Young Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Lallemand Human Nutrition</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the effect of three doses of the probiotic B.
      subtilis (Bacillus subtilis R0179) delivered in capsules on gastrointestinal and general
      wellness in healthy young adults, survival through the gastrointestinal tract and impact on
      intestinal microbes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A 6 week randomized, double blind placebo controlled trial in healthy young adults aged 18
      to 50. Participants will be administered an oral dose of B. subtilis or placebo (1
      capsule/day) for a period of 4 weeks. Viable counts will be measured from stool samples to
      assess transit survival, daily questionnaires will be administered to assess general
      wellness and gastrointestinal (GI) symptoms will be evaluated three times with a validated
      GI symptom questionnaire.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of the effect of B. subtilis R0179 on General  Wellness  and Gastrointestinal Symptoms using Questionnaires</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Questionnaires administered to participants nightly evaluated a broad range of general wellness symptoms on a scale of 0 (no symptom present) to 6 (very severe).
Gastrointestinal Symptom Questionaires were administered at baseline (week 1), end of treatment (week 5), and washout (post week 6) to evaluate the presence or absence of gastrointestinal symptoms.  Scale ranged from 1 (no discomfort at all) to 7 (very severe).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of the Survival of B. Subtilis R0179 and Analyzing the Microbial Diversity in Stool Samples by Participants (Microbiota Study)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Microbial diversity measured by denaturing gradient gel electrophoresis (DGGE) profiling
Quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) to quantify treatment effects on specific bacteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">81</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo (starch, magnesium stearate, citric acid) capsules once daily for 4 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B. subtilis R0179 (10 billion CFU)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>B. subtilis R0179 (approximately 10 billion CFU/capsule) once daily for 4 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B. subtilis R0179 (1 billion CFU)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>B. subtilis R0179 (approximately 1 billion CFU/capsule) once daily for 4 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B. subtilis R0179 (0.1 billion CFU)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>B. subtilis R0179 (approximately 0.1 billion CFU/capsule) once daily for 4 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>B. subtilis R0179</intervention_name>
    <description>B. subtilis R0179 for a period of 4 weeks. One capsule per day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>B. subtilis R0179 (10 billion CFU)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>B. subtilis R0179 (1 billion CFU)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>B. subtilis R0179 (0.1 billion CFU)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>B. subtilis R0179</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo (starch, magnesium stearate, citric acid) capsules for a period of 4 weeks. One capsule per day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria: Participants

          -  Are 18-50 years of age

          -  Are willing and able to complete the Informed Consent Form in English

          -  Are willing to complete the GPAQ (Global Physical Activity Questionnaire) at baseline
             and during the last week of the study as well as completing the GSRS
             (Gastrointestinal Symptom Response Survey) questionnaire at baseline, during
             treatment and post treatment

          -  Are currently &quot;moderately active&quot; as determined by the GPAQ (Global Physical Activity
             Questionnaire)

          -  Are willing to have height and weight measured and to provide demographic information
             (age, race, sex)

          -  Are willing to consume B. subtilis R0179 (approximate doses of 1, 10, or 0.1 billion
             CFU per day) or placebo for a 28 day period by capsule (1 per day)

          -  Are willing to complete daily questionnaires regarding general and gastrointestinal
             wellness for the duration of the study

          -  Are willing to provide 1 stool at baseline, 1 stool during week 4 of the treatment
             and 1 stool after 7 days of washout

          -  Are willing to provide a social security number to receive study payment. Note: the
             subject can still participate if unwilling to provide social security number, but no
             financial reimbursement can be provided

          -  Are willing to have internet access for the duration of the study

        Exclusion Criteria: Potential Participants will be excluded if they

          -  Do not meet the inclusion criteria

          -  Are currently taking medications for constipation or diarrhea

          -  Have taken antibiotics within the past four weeks prior to randomization

          -  Are currently taking probiotics supplements and do not want to discontinue a minimum
             of two weeks prior to the study

          -  Known to have or are currently being treated for any diseases or illnesses such as
             gastrointestinal disease (gastric ulcers, Crohn's, ulcerative colitis, etc.), other
             chronic diseases (diabetes, kidney disease, etc.) or immune-compromising diseases or
             conditions (HIV, AIDS, autoimmune, hepatitis, cancer, transplant patient etc.)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wendy J Dahl, PhD, RD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bobbi Henken-Langkamp, PhD, RD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Volker Mai, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hong HA, Duc le H, Cutting SM. The use of bacterial spore formers as probiotics. FEMS Microbiol Rev. 2005 Sep;29(4):813-35. Epub 2004 Dec 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16102604</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oelschlaeger TA. Mechanisms of probiotic actions - A review. Int J Med Microbiol. 2010 Jan;300(1):57-62. doi: 10.1016/j.ijmm.2009.08.005. Epub 2009 Sep 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19783474</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tompkins TA, Hagen KE, Wallace TD, Fillion-Forté V. Safety evaluation of two bacterial strains used in Asian probiotic products. Can J Microbiol. 2008 May;54(5):391-400. doi: 10.1139/w08-022.</citation>
    <PMID>18449224</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tompkins TA, Xu X, Ahmarani J. A comprehensive review of post-market clinical studies performed in adults with an Asian probiotic formulation. Benef Microbes. 2010 Mar;1(1):93-106. doi: 10.3920/BM2008.1005. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21840798</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 27, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 20, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>probiotics</keyword>
  <keyword>microbiota</keyword>
  <keyword>survival</keyword>
  <keyword>gastrointestinal</keyword>
  <keyword>wellness</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
