<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="104249">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01962961</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IU SRI 1306011647</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01962961</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>N-acetylcysteine to Reduce Oxidative Stress and Improve Endothelial Function in HIV-infected Older Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Pilot Trial Assessing Two Doses of N-Acetylcysteine on Changes in Oxidative Stress and Endothelial Function in HIV-infected Older Adults Receiving Stable Antiretroviral Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Indiana University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>BioAdvantex Pharma</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Indiana University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to determine if n-acetylcysteine, given as PharmaNAC, reduces
      oxidative stress and improves vascular function in HIV-infected older adults already on HIV
      treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to compare 8-week changes in circulating levels of
      malondialdehyde (MDA), circulating levels of F2-isoprostanes, and flow-mediated dilation
      (FMD) of the brachial artery in older HIV-infected adults already receiving virologically
      suppressive antiretroviral therapy (ART) who are then randomized to either NAC 900 mg twice
      daily, NAC 1800 mg twice daily, or placebo. The relative efficacy and safety of these two
      doses of NAC will be assessed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating malondialdehyde levels</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measure of oxidative stress</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating F2-isoprostane levels</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Oxidative stress measure</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Flow-mediated dilation (FMD) of the brachial artery</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measure of endothelial function</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>4 week and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety measures of PharmaNAC given at two different doses</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <condition>Endothelial Dysfunction</condition>
  <condition>Oxidative Stress</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PharmaNAC 1800 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PharmaNAC 900 mg orally twice daily for 8 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PharmaNAC 3600 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PharmaNAC 1800 mg orally twice daily for 8 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Matching placebo pills given twice daily for 8 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PharmaNAC (N-acetylcysteine)</intervention_name>
    <description>PharmaNAC is considered a nutritional supplement and can be obtained without a prescription. All participants will be asked to ingest two tablets twice per day during this trial. For those randomized to PharmaNAC 1800 mg twice daily, this will be two active tablets twice per day. For those randomized to PharmaNAC 900 mg twice daily, this will be one active tablet twice per day and one matching placebo tablet twice per day. For those randomized to placebo, this will be two matching placebo tablets twice per day.
PharmaNAC can be taken with or without food. The effervescent tablets should be dissolved in 8 oz. of water or juice prior to oral intake. Each participant will take study drug and/or matching placebo for 8 weeks (up to 60 days).</description>
    <arm_group_label>PharmaNAC 1800 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>PharmaNAC 3600 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>N-acetylcysteine</other_name>
    <other_name>NAC</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Matching placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>PharmaNAC 1800 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV-1 infection, documented by (1) any licensed rapid HIV test or HIV enzyme or
             chemiluminescence immunoassay (E/CIA) test kit at any time prior to study entry and
             confirmed by a licensed Western blot or a second antibody test by a method other than
             the initial rapid HIV and/or E/CIA, or (2) by two detectable HIV-1 antigens, or (3)
             two detectable plasma HIV-1 RNA viral loads.

          -  Age equal to or greater than 50 years.

          -  Receipt of antiretroviral therapy of any kind for at least 6 months prior to
             screening.

          -  HIV-1 RNA level &lt; 75 copies/mL at screening.

          -  For women who are still of reproductive potential, a negative urine pregnancy test at
             screening and willingness to use two forms of birth control during the course of the
             study. Acceptable forms of birth control include condoms (with or without a gel that
             can kill sperm), a diaphragm or cervical cap (with or without a gel that can kill
             sperm), an intrauterine device (IUD), or hormonal-based birth control (&quot;the pill&quot;).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to complete written, informed consent.

          -  Incarceration at the time of any study visit.

          -  Known allergy or intolerance to n-acetylcysteine.

          -  Use of n-acetylcysteine within 180 days of screening.

          -  Diagnosed vascular disease (history of angina pectoris, coronary disease, peripheral
             vascular disease, cerebrovascular disease, aortic aneurysm, or otherwise known
             atherosclerotic disease).

          -  History of congestive heart failure even if currently compensated.

          -  History of portal hypertension or hepatic cirrhosis (either clinically diagnosed or
             histologically diagnosed).

          -  Diagnosed disease or process, besides HIV infection, associated with increased
             systemic inflammation (including, but not limited to, systemic lupus erythematosis,
             inflammatory bowel diseases, other collagen vascular diseases).

          -  Known or suspected malignancy requiring systemic treatment within six months of
             screening.

          -  History of ADA-defined diabetes mellitus (115)

          -  History of migraine headaches.

          -  History of Raynaud's phenomenon.

          -  History of cardiac arrhythmias or cardiomyopathy.

          -  Uncontrolled hyperthyroidism or hypothyroidism, defined as TSH values outside of the
             local reference range on most recent clinical assessment.

          -  Asthma or COPD requiring daily use of beta-2-agonist therapy (e.g. albuterol)

          -  History of carotid bruits.

          -  Creatinine clearance &lt; 50 mL/min (using the Cockcroft-Gault equation) using a serum
             creatinine level measured at screening.

          -  Hemoglobin &lt; 9.0 g/dL at screening.

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) level or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &gt; 3 times
             ULN at screening.

          -  Total bilirubin &gt; 2.5 times ULN at screening; if the participant is receiving
             atazanavir, then s/he would be excluded if total bilirubin is &gt; 3.5 times ULN at
             screening.

          -  Therapy for serious medical illnesses within 14 days prior to screening.

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding during the course of the study.

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension, defined as systolic blood pressure &gt; 160 mmHg or diastolic
             blood pressure &gt; 100 mmHg at screening.

          -  Receipt of investigational agents, cytotoxic chemotherapy, systemic glucocorticoids
             (of any dose), or anabolic steroids at screening.

          -  Previous receipt of stavudine or didanosine for more than 7 cumulative days.

          -  Receipt of daily Vitamin C or Vitamin E supplements at screening.

          -  Alcohol intake more than the equivalent of one 8 oz. of wine daily for the 7 days
             prior to screening.

          -  Active drug use or dependence that, in the opinion of the investigator, would
             interfere with adherence to study requirements.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Samir K Gupta, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Indiana University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paula Johnson, NP</last_name>
    <phone>317-278-2945</phone>
    <email>johnpaul@iu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University Health University Hospital, Indiana Clinical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 28, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 11, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Indiana University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Samir K Gupta, MD, MS</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>Endothelial function</keyword>
  <keyword>Oxidative stress</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiovascular disease</keyword>
  <keyword>N-acetylcysteine</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Acetylcysteine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>N-monoacetylcystine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
