<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="147997">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01908387</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CC-486-MDS-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01908387</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 1 Study of CC-486 in Japanese Subjects With Myelodysplastic Syndromes</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Multicenter, Open-label, Dose-escalation Study of Oral Azacitidine (CC-486) in Japanese Subjects With Myelodysplastic Syndromes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Celgene Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Celgene Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Japan: Pharmaceuticals and Medical Devices Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To identify the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of oral azacitidine in Japanese subjects with
      myelodysplastic syndromes
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Protocol to be amended.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose limiting toxicities</measure>
    <time_frame>For 28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of subjects experiencing dose limiting toxicity during the first 28-day cycle</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of participants with adverse events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>On day 1 and day 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Maximum observed concentration in plasma</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>On day 1 and day 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Observed time to first maximum plasma concentration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - AUCt</measure>
    <time_frame>On day 1 and day 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero to the last quantifiable time point, calculated by the linear trapezoidal rule</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - AUC∞</measure>
    <time_frame>On day 1 and day 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero to infinity, calculated by the linear trapezoidal rule and extrapolated to infinity will be calculated according to the following equation:
AUC∞ = AUCt + (Ct/λz), where Ct is the last quantifiable concentration If the percentage of AUC extrapolated is ≥ 25%, AUC∞ will not be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - AUCext%</measure>
    <time_frame>On day 1 and day 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of AUC∞ due to extrapolation from the time from the last quantifiable concentration to infinity, calculated as (AUC∞ - AUCt) / AUC∞ ×100</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - λz</measure>
    <time_frame>On day 1 and day 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Terminal phase rate constant, determined by linear regression of the terminal points of the log-linear plasma concentration-time curve Visual assessment may be used to identify the terminal linear phase of the concentration versus time profile. A minimum of three data points will be used for calculation. λz will not be estimated if the terminal phase of the log-concentration versus time profile does not exhibit a linear decline phase, or if the regression coefficient &lt; 0.8.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - t1/2</measure>
    <time_frame>On day 1 and day 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Terminal phase half-life, will be calculated according to the following equation:
t1/2 = 0.693/λz</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - CL/F</measure>
    <time_frame>On day 1 and day 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Apparent total clearance, calculated as Dose/AUC∞</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - Vz/F</measure>
    <time_frame>On day 1 and day 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Apparent volume of distribution will be calculated according to the equation:
Vz/F = (CL/F)/λz</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - Aet</measure>
    <time_frame>On day 1 and day 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Cumulative amount excreted from time zero to time t (ng), calculated as the summation of the amounts (Aet, product of urine volume and urine concentration) excreted in subsequent collection intervals</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - fet</measure>
    <time_frame>On day 1 and day 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Cumulative fraction of dose excreted in the urine from time zero to time t (%), calculated as Ae t divided by dose</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - CLr</measure>
    <time_frame>On day 1 and day 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Renal clearance (mL/min), calculated as Aet divided by AUCt</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hematologic response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of participants with hematologic improvement using International Working Group (IWG 2006) criteria for Myelodysplastic Syndrome (MDS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hematologic improvement</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of participants with hematologic improvement using International Working Group (IWG 2006) criteria for Myelodysplastic Syndrome (MDS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Red blood cell (RBC) transfusion independence</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>RBC transfusion independence is defined as the absence of any RBC transfusion during any consecutive 84 days during study treatment. For subjects who are RBC transfusion dependent at baseline, the percentage of subjects who achieved RBC transfusion independence on treatment will be provided.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Platelet transfusion independence</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Platelet transfusion independence is defined as the absence of any platelet transfusion during any consecutive 56 days during study treatment. For subjects who are platelet transfusion dependent at baseline, the percentage of subjects who achieved platelet transfusion independence on treatment will be provided.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oral azacitidine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oral azacitidine</intervention_name>
    <description>100 mg to 300 mg oral azacitidine once daily for the first 21 days of the initial 28-day cycle</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oral azacitidine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CC-486</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Twenty years of age to 80 years of age at the time of signing the informed consent
             document 2. Understand and voluntarily sign an informed consent document prior to any
             study related assessments and/or procedures being conducted 3. Able to adhere to the
             study visit schedule and other protocol requirements 4. Have a documented diagnosis
             of myelodysplastic syndromes according to World Health Organization 2008
             classification.

             5. Have at least one of the following:

               -  Hemoglobin level ≤ 9.0 g/dL

               -  Platelet count ≤ 50,000 /μL

               -  Red blood cell transfusion-dependent as defined by:

          -  Average red blood cell transfusion requirement of ≥ 4 units per 28 days confirmed for
             a minimum of 84 days prior to starting study treatment. Hemoglobin levels within 7
             days prior to administration of an red blood cell transfusion must be ≤ 9.0 g/dL in
             order for the transfusion to be counted towards red blood cell transfusion-dependent
             status. Red blood cell transfusions administered when hemoglobin levels were &gt; 9.0
             g/dL and/or red blood cell transfusions administered for elective surgery will not
             qualify as a required transfusion for the purpose of providing evidence of red blood
             cell transfusion-dependent status. Note that 4 units of red blood cell in Japan is
             equivalent to 2 units of red blood cell outside of Japan.

          -  No consecutive 42 days that are red blood cell-transfusion-free during the 84 days
             prior to starting study treatment

             • Platelet transfusion-dependent as defined by:

          -  Have at least two separate platelet transfusion episodes during 56 days prior to
             starting study treatment. Platelet transfusions administered for elective surgery
             will not qualify as a required transfusion for the purpose of providing evidence of
             platelet transfusion-dependent status.

          -  No consecutive 28 days that are platelet-transfusion-free during the 56 days prior to
             starting study treatment 6. ECOG performance status of 0, or 1 7. Females of
             childbearing potential (FCBP: a sexually mature woman who: 1) has not undergone a
             hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy or 2) has not been naturally postmenopausal
             [ie, amenorrhea following cancer therapy does not rule out childbearing potential]
             for at least 24 consecutive months [ie, has had menses at any time in the preceding
             24 consecutive months]) must:

               -  Agree to use at least two effective contraceptive methods (oral, injectable, or
                  implantable hormonal contraceptive; tubal ligation; intra-uterine device;
                  barrier contraceptive with spermicide; or vasectomized partner; injectable and
                  implantable hormonal contraceptive have not been approved in Japan as of March
                  2013) throughout the study, and for 3 months following the last dose of oral
                  azacitidine; and

               -  Have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test (sensitivity of at least 25
                  mIU/mL) at screening; and

               -  Have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test (investigator's discretion) within
                  72 hours prior to starting study treatment (note that the screening serum
                  pregnancy test can be used as the test prior to starting study treatment if it
                  is performed within the 72-hour timeframe).

                  8. Male subjects with a female partner of childbearing potential must agree to
                  use at least 2 physician-approved contraceptive methods throughout the course of
                  the study and should avoid fathering a child during the course of the study and
                  for 3 months following the last dose of study drug.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Hypoplastic myelodysplastic syndromes defined as bone marrow cellularity of &lt; 20%
             2. Chronic myelomonocytic leukemia, atypical chronic myeloid leukemia and
             unclassifiable myeloproliferative disease. Subjects with white blood cell counts &gt;
             12,000/μL must be excluded.

             3. Dry tap bone marrow aspirate due to myelofibrosis, and/or myelofibrosis
             accompanied by splenomegaly 4. Prior treatment with azacitidine or other
             hypomethylating agent 5. Prior allogeneic or autologous stem cell transplant 6.
             History of inflammatory bowel disease (eg, Crohn's disease, ulcerative colitis),
             celiac disease (ie, sprue), prior gastrectomy or upper bowel removal, or any other
             gastrointestinal disorder or defect that would interfere with the absorption,
             distribution, metabolism or excretion of the study drug and/or predispose the subject
             to an increased risk of gastrointestinal toxicity 7. Thrombocytopenia secondary to
             other possible causes, including medication(s), congenital disorder(s), immune
             disorder(s) (eg, idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura), or microvascular disorder(s)
             (eg, disseminated intravascular coagulation, hemolytic uremic syndrome, thrombotic
             thrombocytopenic purpura) 8. Use of any of the following within 28 days prior to
             starting study treatment:

               -  Cytotoxic, chemotherapeutic, investigational or targeted agents/therapies

               -  Thrombopoiesis stimulating agents (eg, romiplostim, eltrombopag, interleukin-11)

               -  Erythropoiesis stimulating agents or other red blood cell hematopoietic growth
                  factors (eg, interleukin-3)

               -  Hydroxyurea

               -  Lenalidomide

               -  Cyclosporine or antithymocyte globulin 9. Concurrent use of any of the
                  following:

               -  Corticosteroids, except for subjects on a stable or decreasing dose for at least
                  1 week prior to starting study treatment for medical conditions other than
                  myelodysplastic syndromes. Topical use of corticosteroids is permitted
                  regardless of dose

               -  Iron-chelating agents, except for subjects on a stable dose for at least 4 weeks
                  prior to starting study treatment 10. Prior history of malignancies, other than
                  myelodysplastic syndromes, unless the subject has been free of the disease for &gt;
                  3 years. Exceptions include the following:

               -  Basal or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin

               -  Carcinoma in situ of the cervix or breast

               -  Incidental histological finding of prostate cancer (Tumor nodes metastasis stage
                  of T1a N0M0 or T1b N0M0)

               -  Early-stage gastric cancer suitable for endoscopic mucosal resection or
                  endoscopic submucosal dissection 11. Significant active cardiac disease within
                  the previous 6 months, including:

               -  New York Heart Association class III-IV congestive heart failure

               -  Unstable angina or angina requiring surgical or medical intervention

               -  Myocardial infarction 12. Uncontrolled systemic fungal, bacterial, or viral
                  infection (defined as ongoing signs/symptoms related to the infection without
                  improvement despite appropriate antibiotics, antiviral therapy, and/or other
                  treatment) 13. Known human immunodeficiency virus positivity (eg, subjects who
                  are receiving antiretroviral therapy for human immunodeficiency virus disease)
                  14. Hepatitis B surface antigen-positive, or hepatitis C virus
                  antibody-positive. In case hepatitis B core antibody and/or hepatitis B surface
                  antibody is positive even if hepatitis B surface antigen-negative, a hepatitis B
                  virus deoxyribonucleic acid test should be performed and if positive the subject
                  will be excluded 15. Any of the following laboratory abnormalities:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count &lt; 1,000/μL

               -  Serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase/aspartate transaminase or serum glutamic
                  pyruvate transaminase/alanine transaminase &gt; 2.5 × upper limit of normal

               -  Serum bilirubin &gt; 1.5 × upper limit of normal. High levels are acceptable if
                  these can be attributed to active red blood cell precursor destruction within
                  the bone marrow (ie, ineffective erythropoiesis). Subjects are excluded if there
                  is evidence of autoimmune hemolytic anemia manifested as a corrected
                  reticulocyte count of &gt; 2% with either a positive Coomb's test or over 50% of
                  indirect bilirubin

               -  Serum creatinine &gt; 1.5 × upper limit of normal

               -  Serum bicarbonate (venous blood) &lt; 22 mEq/L

               -  Abnormal coagulation parameters (Prothrombin time-international normalized ratio
                  &gt; 1.5 or activated partial thromboplastin time &gt; 40 seconds) 16. Known
                  clinically significant anemia due to iron, vitamin B12, or folate deficiencies,
                  or autoimmune or hereditary hemolytic anemia, or gastrointestinal bleeding 17.
                  History of cerebrovascular accident or transient cerebral ischemic attack within
                  6 months prior to starting study treatment 18. Interstitial lung disease,
                  pulmonary fibrosis, or other severe respiratory disease 19. Hepatic cirrhosis,
                  or other moderate to severe hepatic disease 20. Known or suspected
                  hypersensitivity to azacitidine or mannitol 21. Pregnant or lactating females
                  22. Any significant medical condition, laboratory abnormality, or psychiatric
                  illness that would prevent the subject from participating in the study 23. Any
                  condition including the presence of laboratory abnormalities, which places the
                  subject at unacceptable risk if he/she were to participate in the study 24. Any
                  condition that confounds the ability to interpret data from the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Toru Sasaki, Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Celgene K.K.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cancer Center Hospital East</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kashiwa</city>
        <state>Chiba</state>
        <zip>277-8577</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cancer Center Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tokyo</city>
        <zip>104-0045</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Cancer Institute Hospital of JFCR</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tokyo</city>
        <zip>135-8550</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 23, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Oral azacitidine, CC-486, MDS, phase 1</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Azacitidine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
