<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="16745">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02048709</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NLG9191</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02048709</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>IDO Inhibitor Study for Advanced Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of NLG-919 for Adult Patients With Recurrent Advanced Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NewLink Genetics Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NewLink Genetics Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the safety and appropriate dose for future studies
      of NLG919 an investigational agent intended to inhibit the IDO enzyme and help the human
      immune system attack solid tumor cells more effectively.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cancer continues to be a major global health burden. In the United States of America (USA),
      it is the second most common cause of death after heart disease, accounting for nearly 1 in
      every 4 deaths (American Cancer Society, 2011). The 5-year survival rate for all cancers
      diagnosed between 1999 and 2006 is 68%, which is 18% higher than the rate reported between
      1975 and 1977, likely reflecting progress in diagnosing certain cancers earlier and
      improvements in treatment (American Cancer Society, 2011). Unfortunately, despite
      indisputable progress in the treatment of cancer, there continues to be an unmet medical
      need for more effective and less toxic therapies, especially for those patients with
      advanced disease that do not respond or have become resistant to existing therapies. One
      aspect of the growth and spread of cancer cells is overcoming the immune response from the
      affected individual. The mechanisms for this are multiple. One aspect is the existence of a
      preexisting state of functional tolerance towards tumor antigens. Another is the ability of
      tumors to avoid or suppress immune responses directed towards them. One immune regulatory
      pathway, the IDO pathway, has emerged as an important part of the immune evasion by cancers.
      IDO plays a predominant role in regulation of the acquired local and systemic immune
      tolerance towards the tumor. Therefore, IDO is an attractive target in therapeutic
      interventions aimed at restoring the immune response towards the tumor, and drugs that
      inhibit the enzymatic activity of IDO, like NLG919 are expected to bring a significant
      benefit to an active immunotherapy regimen.

      This protocol provides a first in human study to evaluate the safety and toxicity of NLG919
      in advanced solid tumors for which no standard therapy exists.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluate the safety (adverse events - type, incidence, severity, duration, causality and treatment intervention) and toxicity of NLG919 in advanced solid tumors for which no standard therapy exists.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dose</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To define the Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD), Maximally Biologically Effective Dose (MBED) and/or Recommended Phase 2 Dose (RP2D) of NLG919</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess the pharmacokinetics of NLG919. A thorough pharmacokinetic (PK) profile will be performed for each patient entered into the study through  analysis of blood samples collected at protocol-defined time points.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlative studies</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluation of serum for biomarkers of IDO activity (kynurenine and tryptophan), before and after initiation of therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the overall response rates (CR+PR+SD) to NLG919 in advanced solid tumors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Characterize overall survival by Kaplan-Meier analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumors</condition>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NLG919 Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>NLG919 to be given on an outpatient basis as a single agent. Starting dose of NLG919 will be 50 mg PO Q 12 hr. Patients will receive the study drug daily for 21 days followed by 7 days off for a cycle length of 28 days.
Patients will be monitored during administration of their first dose (Cycle 1, Day 1) by clinical research nursing staff for 12 hours while PK tests are performed over the initial 24 hours.
All doses will be recorded by the research staff and patient using the pill diary form and confirmed using pill counts by the research staff at each biweekly visit. The pill diary forms will be turned into the research staff at the end of each treatment cycle.
Doses will be escalated from 50mg PO Q 12 hr to 800mg PO Q 12 hr following dose escalation guidelines in response to any dose-limiting toxicities experienced on study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NLG919</intervention_name>
    <description>Supplied in 50mg and 200 mg capsules. To be taken every 12 hours with water by mouth on an empty stomach (no food or drink other than water for 2 hours prior to dose). Taken BID for 21 days each cycle, followed by 7 days off.</description>
    <arm_group_label>NLG919 Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NLG-919</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically or cytologically confirmed solid tumor cancer that is
             relapsed/refractory to standard therapies or for which no approved or curative
             therapy exists.

          -  Age between 18 and 70

          -  ECOG performance status &lt; 2

          -  Bone marrow function as defined by the following laboratory values:

          -  1. Absolute Neutrophil Count (ANC) ≥ 1000/mm3

          -  2. Platelets ≥ 100,000/mm3

          -  3 Hemoglobin ≥ 10.0 gm/dL

          -  Adequate renal function (creatinine level within normal institutional limit, or
             creatinine clearance &gt;60 mL/min/1.73 m2 for patients with creatinine levels above
             institutional normal)

          -  Liver function (AST/ALT &lt;3 X institutional upper limit of normal, Total bilirubin ≤
             1.5 times ULN, (INR) within 1.5 times ULN (or if receiving anticoagulant therapy an
             INR of ≤ 3.0 is allowed with concomitant increase in PT or an aPTT ≤ 2.5 × control

          -  The effects of NLG919 on the developing human fetus are unknown. For this reason and
             because NLG919 may affect maternal immune tolerance of the fetus, sexually active
             women of child-bearing potential must agree to use two forms of contraception
             (hormonal and barrier method of birth control or abstinence) prior to study entry and
             for the duration of study participation. Use of contraception or abstinence should
             continue for a minimum of 1 month after completion of the study. Should a woman
             become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while participating in this study, she
             should discontinue the study drug and inform her treating physician immediately. Also
             men should be discouraged from fathering children while on treatment.

          -  Must be 28 days from the administration of any investigational agent or prior
             cytotoxic

          -  Must be fully recovered from all prior surgeries and/or adjuvant treatments

          -  Life expectancy greater than or equal to 4 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Active or history of autoimmune disease

          -  Serious uncontrolled medical or psychiatric disorder or active infection that would
             impede treatment

          -  Previous therapy with ipilimumab or tremelimumab

          -  Prior malignancy except non-melanomatous skin cancer or carcinoma in situ of the
             cervix unless the patient has been disease free and off therapy for that disease for
             a minimum of 3 years

          -  Infection with HIV, Hepatitis B or Hepatitis C

          -  Concomitant therapy with IL-2, interferon, other non-study immunotherapy, or
             cytotoxic chemotherapy; immune-suppressive agents within 30 days of
             registration;other investigational therapies; chronic use of systemic corticosteroids
             (topical and inhaled standard dose corticosteroids are allowed but not to exceed 2 mg
             of dexamethasone or equivalent)

          -  Dementia or significantly altered mental status that would prohibit understanding or
             rendering of informed consent and compliance with protocol requirements

          -  Prisoners or subjects who are compulsorily detained (involuntarily incarcerated) for
             treatment of either a psychiatric or physical (e.g. infectious) illness

          -  Untreated brain metastases

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding

          -  Patients with QTc interval &gt; 470 msec at baseline ECG

          -  Patients who currently take drugs that are generally considered to have a high risk
             of causing Torsades de Pointes. It will be at the determination of the treating
             physician to discontinue or substitute as appropriate. If discontinued, the washout
             period needs to be at least 5-7 half-lives of the drug.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicholas Vahanian, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>NewLink Genetics Corporation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Georgia Regents University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Augusta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30912</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robbin Dobbins, RN</last_name>
      <phone>706-721-2154</phone>
      <email>rdobbins@gru.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Khleif Samir, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 10, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Solid Tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Lung Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Pancreatic Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>relapsed</keyword>
  <keyword>refractory</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
