<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="122687">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01894672</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-053</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01894672</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>BRAF Inhibitor, LGX818, Utilizing a Pulsatile Schedule in Patients With Stage IV or Unresectable Stage III Melanoma Characterized by a BRAFV600 Mutation</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2 Trial of the BRAF Inhibitor, LGX818, Utilizing a Pulsatile Schedule in Patients With Stage IV or Unresectable Stage III Melanoma Characterized by a BRAFV600 Mutation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this phase II study is to find out if an investigational drug called LGX818
      can stop the melanoma from growing.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>1.5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Efficacy for all patients will be evaluated by the study sites using RECIST v1.1 and response criteria based on contrast-enhanced CT</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>1.5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall survival will be calculated for the start of treatment to the date of last death or follow-up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>1.5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Response rate (defined as complete + partial response) and 95% confidence interval will be estimated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>safety</measure>
    <time_frame>1.5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Frequencies of toxicities will be tabulated according to the CTCAE (version 4.03).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics</measure>
    <time_frame>1.5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PK parameters will be determined on PK profiles after the first dose and at steady-state using non-compartmental method(s) using WinNonlin (Pharsight, Mountain View, CA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">26</enrollment>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LGX818</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>LGX818 capsules will be administered orally on a once -daily schedule (QD) dosing for the first 6 weeks. This will be followed by a 2 week break. Thereafter, patients will resume LGX818 on a once daily schedule at a dose of  300 mg/day for 2 weeks followed again by a 2 week break. This schedule of 2 weeks on, followed by 2 weeks off, will continue for the duration of time the patients remains on the clinical trial.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LGX818</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>LGX818</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Stage IV, or unresectable stage III melanoma that harbors a BRAFV600 mutation

          -  Any prior therapy allowed except a BRAF or MEK inhibitor,.

          -  Patients must provide written informed consent prior to any screening procedures.

          -  Age 18 years or older.

          -  Willing and able to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plan and laboratory tests

          -  Patient is able to swallow and retain oral medication

          -  Measurable disease according to RECIST v1.1

          -  ECOG performance status ≤ 1

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Brain metastasis or leptomeningeal disease

          -  Known acute or chronic pancreatitis

          -  Prior colectomy

          -  Clinically significant cardiac disease including any of the following:

          -  CHF requiring treatment (NYHA Classification ≥ 2) in which patients have a history of
             LVEF &lt; 45% as determined by MUGA scan or ECHO, or uncontrolled hypertension (please
             refer to WHO-ISH guidelines)

          -  History or presence of clinically significant ventricular arrhythmias or atrial
             fibrillation

          -  Clinically significant resting bradycardia

          -  Unstable angina pectoris ≤ 3 months prior to starting study drug

          -  Acute Myocardial Infarction (AMI) ≤ 3 months prior to starting study drug

          -  QTcF&gt; 480 msec

          -  Patients with any of the following laboratory values at Screening/baseline:

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &lt;1,500/mm3 [1.5 x 109/L]

          -  Platelets &lt;100,000/mm3 [100 x 109/L]

          -  Hemoglobin &lt; 9.0 g/dL

          -  Serum creatinine&gt;1.5 x ULN

          -  Serum total bilirubin &gt;1.5 x ULN

          -  AST/SGOT and/or ALT/SGPT &gt; 2.5 x ULN

          -  Impairment of gastrointestinal (GI) function or GI disease that may significantly
             alter the absorption of oral LGX818 (e.g., ulcerative diseases, uncontrolled nausea,
             vomiting, diarrhea, malabsorption syndrome, small bowel resection).

          -  Previous or concurrent malignancy. Exceptions: adequately treated basal cell or
             squamous cell skin cancer; in situ carcinoma of the cervix, treated curatively and
             without evidence of recurrence for at least 3 years prior to study entry; or other
             solid tumor treated curatively, and without evidence of recurrence for at least 3
             years prior to study entry.

          -  Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women, where pregnancy is defined as the state of a
             female after conception and until the termination of gestation, confirmed by a
             positive hCG laboratory test (&gt; 5 mIU/mL).

        Women of child-bearing potential, defined as all women physiologically capable of becoming
        pregnant, are not allowed to participate in this study UNLESS they are using highly
        effective methods of contraception throughout the study and for 3 months after study drug
        discontinuation. Highly effective contraception methods include:

        Total abstinence or

          -  Male or female sterilization

          -  Combination of any two of the following (a+b or a+c or b+c)

               1. Use of oral, injected, or implanted hormonal methods of contraception

               2. Placement of an intrauterine device (IUD) or intrauterine system (IUS)

               3. Barrier methods of contraception: condom or occlusive cap (diaphragm or
                  cervical/vault caps) with spermicidal foam/gel/film/cream/vaginal suppository

                    -  Post-menopausal women are allowed to participate in this study. Women are
                       considered post-menopausal and not of child bearing potential if they have
                       had 12 months of natural (spontaneous) amenorrhea with an appropriate
                       clinical profile (e.g. age appropriate, history of vasomotor symptoms) or
                       six months of spontaneous amenorrhea with serum Follicle-Stimulating
                       Hormone (FSH) levels &gt; 40 mIU/mL or have had surgical bilateral
                       oophorectomy (with or without hysterectomy) or tubal ligation at least six
                       weeks prior to screening. In the case of oophorectomy alone, only when the
                       reproductive status of the woman has been confirmed by follow up hormone
                       level assessment is she considered not of child bearing potential.

        Sexually active males must use a condom during intercourse while taking the drug and for 5
        T1/2 after stopping treatment and should not father a child in this period. A condom is
        required to be used also by vasectomized men in order to prevent delivery of the drug via
        seminal fluid.

        History of thromboembolic or cerebrovascular events within the last 6 months, including
        transient ischemic attack, cerebrovascular accident, deep vein thrombosis, or pulmonary
        embolism.

          -  Patients who have undergone any major surgery within the last 2 weeks prior to
             starting study drug or who would not have fully recovered from previous surgery.

          -  Known Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) infection

          -  Other severe, acute, or chronic medical or psychiatric condition or laboratory
             abnormality that may increase the risk associated with study participation or study
             drug administration or that may interfere with the interpretation of study results
             and, in the judgment of the investigator, would make the patient inappropriate for
             the study.

          -  Treatment with a prior BRAF or MEK inhibitor
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul Chapman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paul Chapman, MD</last_name>
    <phone>646-888-4162</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Michael Postow, MD</last_name>
    <phone>646-888-4589</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center at Basking Ridge</name>
      <address>
        <city>Basking Ridge</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paul Chapman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-888-4162</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center at Commack</name>
      <address>
        <city>Commack</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11725</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paul Chapman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-888-4162</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paul Chapman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-888-4162</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Michael Postow, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-888-4589</phone>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paul Chapman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center at Mercy Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rockville Centre</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11570</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paul Chapman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-888-4162</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center at Phelps Memorial Hospital Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sleepy Hollow</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10591</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paul Chapman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-888-4162</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mskcc.org/</url>
    <description>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 9, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 3, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>LGX818</keyword>
  <keyword>BRAF Inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Stage IV melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>unresectable stage III melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>BRAFV600 mutation</keyword>
  <keyword>13-053</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
