<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="95660">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01760356</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3PIGREF- 2009 -1165</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01760356</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Study of the Pharmacogenetic / Pharmacokinetic / Pharmacodynamic Relationships of Calcineurin Inhibitors Cyclosporine and Tacrolimus in Liver Transplant Recipients</brief_title>
  <acronym>3PIGREF</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase IV - Study of PK,PD,PG Relationships of Anticalcineurin Drugs: Cyclosporin and Tacrolimus in Liver Transplant Recipients.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>UDA Centro Nacional Hepato-Bilio-Pancreático</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>INSERM UMR-S850, Limoges, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital, Limoges</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>PEDECIBA Química,University of the Republic,Uruguay</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Facultad de Química,University of the Republic, Uruguay</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>ANII (Agencia Nacional de Investigación e Innovación), Uruguay</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Servicio de Cooperación Científica y Técnica de la Embajada de Francia, Uruguay</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital Central de las Fuerzas Armadas, Uruguay</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>UDA Centro Nacional Hepato-Bilio-Pancreático</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Uruguay: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study aims to contribute to the safety and efficacy of individual
      immunosuppressive treatment.

      Its principal objective is to investigate biochemical and physiological effects of
      calcineurin inhibitors on the body, go in depth of their mechanisms of action and to see if
      there is a correlation between drug concentration, outcomes and genetics. This will be able
      to explain the variability of the response observed, and correlated with rejection episodes
      or drug adverse effects.

      As an approach to pharmacodynamic monitoring of calcineurin it has been proposed to measure
      indirectly calcineurin activity in peripheral blood lymphocytes, through the measure of the
      Nuclear Factor of activated T Cells nuclear translocation inhibition, the intracytosolic
      expression of interleukin 2, and the expression of activation markers as CD25 in T
      lymphocytes.

      Once the biomarkers selected can be validated, it is expected to contribute to a better
      understanding of the steps associated with lymphocyte activation and response resulting from
      exposure of calcineurin, fine-tune the levels of these immunosuppressants, and alert in
      prematurely about a possible episode of rejection and / or occurrence of side effects -
      immediate or delayed - as a result of immunosuppressive therapy.

      The study on healthy volunteers, would help to determine the baseline for these patients.

      Tracking patients from inclusion on the transplant waiting list, will reveal the profile of
      the patient prior to initiating chronic treatment and closely monitor the evolution of the
      changes that occur at the molecular level, so as to warn clinicians on the basis of the
      evidence, to act accordingly.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The research will be conducted under the rules of Good Clinical Practice, Good Laboratory
      Practice of the International Conference on Harmonisation (ICH)and the Principles of
      Declaration of Helsinki.

      The cohorts are formed by its own nature:healthy volunteers, transplant patients and
      patients on the liver waiting list for transplantation. Each member, shall belong to them
      once consented to participate in the study and has been found to meet the inclusion criteria
      of the study.

      Once the information stage was completed, and after obtaining signed informed consent, each
      volunteer was evaluated to ensure that he meets all inclusion criteria and none of the
      exclusion ones. From this instance proceed the sampling plan.

      Considering potential dropouts or withdrawals during the study, the intention is to recruit
      an additional 10% to compensate for the cohorts, as they allow.

      The study design does not suppose applying masking methods, since it is an open study.

      All data required in the registration forms will be recorded, however in case of persistent
      failure, will be properly documented the reasons for the absence. Each instance will merit a
      particular analysis, dated and signed.

      Models will be used to estimate the impact of bias due to potential missing data, and if
      applicable will be complemented with a sensibility analysis.SPSS and ACCESS are the proposed
      softwares to carry out this type of analysis.

      The loading of data will be conducted electronically. The data will be validated according
      to the data management plan, jointly defined by the principal investigator and the
      methodologist, in charge of the data managing and the statistics. The software to be used to
      test consistency will be: ACCESS ®.

      The freezing and thawing process data will be held in accordance with the procedure
      established in the methodology and data management.

      The pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic modeling will be done using the program NONMEM
      version 6.

      Data back ups will be run everyday, and will be archived on tape and a USB storage drive.

      Besides self monitoring procedures, the study may be audited by the health authority (during
      the course of the study or even when it is completed), to assess compliance with the
      standards of Good Clinical Practice.

      Atypical results if any, will be handled according to the criteria of results outside of
      specification.If re-analysis of samples eill occur,those will be documented and the reasons
      for it.

      The calculation of sample size includes the percentage of occurrence of rejection and side
      effects to consider, as reported by the National Liver Transplant Program and the possible
      rates of abandonment or premature retirement of the in study volunteers.

      Under national rates, will be studied at least 30 healthy volunteers, 50 patients and 10
      patients transplanted from the instance of pretransplant liver  waiting list, with serial
      follow-up during the first year.

      Statistical analysis will be performed according to the principle of &quot;intention to treat&quot;,
      and will be the responsible for at least one specialist in biostatistics and research
      methodology independent.

      It will be developed a descriptive analysis of all variables collected. Categorical
      variables will be expressed in percentages and number of observations. Continuous variables
      will be expressed as mean and standard deviation or median and 25th and 75th percentiles,
      minimum and maximum. Variables developed over time will be presented by Kaplan-Meier curves.

      The variables will be compared between groups according to the patient's original listing
      (intention to treat). They will be calculated and presented the estimated relative risks and
      their effect with 95% confidence intervals.

      For comparison of categorical variables, it will be used the Chi-square test or Fisher's
      exact test as appropriate.

      For comparison of continuous variables, it will be used the test &quot;t&quot; of Student.

      For variables that develop with time, they will be represented by Kaplan-Meier curves and
      compared using the &quot;log-rank&quot; test. Their relative risk with 95% confidence interval will be
      calculated.

      To identify variables associated with different responses multivariate linear analysis,
      logistic or Cox proportional will be used.

      All analyzes will be performed with hypothesis testing and a 2-tailed significance level of
      5%.

      The program used will be R.

      We have established standard operating procedures to describe blood collection instances,
      biological fluids sampling circuit, evaluation of the candidates to include in the study,
      verification of the inclusion criteria, monitoring of patients during the study, record of
      undesirable events and report of adverse drug reactions, terminating tracking.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2011</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <target_duration>12 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Percentage of CD25 (IL2RA) in CD3 Lymphocytes. Flow Cytometry Measurement.</measure>
    <time_frame>All the cohorts at the inclusion. Afterwards, Transplant patients: if there is acute rejection, infection or toxicity episodes related to anticalcineurin drugs; Patients in the liver waiting list: at 30, 90, 180 and 360 days post transplantation.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Related to the activation of T lymphocytes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>SNP genotyping. Taqman Technique.</measure>
    <time_frame>At the moment of the inclusion for all cohorts.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood through levels of anticalcineurin drug Concentration. Chemiluminescent microparticle immunoassay.</measure>
    <time_frame>At the moment of the inclusion and at each office visit during regular check up.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Related to blood target concentration ranges</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Mean Fluorescence Intensity of NFAT Nuclear Translocation Inhibition in PMBC nuclei. Flow Cytometry Measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>All the cohorts at the inclusion. Afterwards, Transplant patients: if there is acute rejection, infection or toxicity episodes related to anticalcineurin drugs; Patients in the liver waiting list: at 30, 90, 180 and 360 days post transplantation.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Related to Calcineruin activity (enzyme target of this group of drugs).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Percentage of IL-2 in CD4 and CD8 subsets of T lymphocytes. Flow Cytometry Measurement.</measure>
    <time_frame>All the cohorts at the inclusion. Afterwards, Transplant patients: if there is acute rejection, infection or toxicity episodes related to anticalcineurin drugs; Patients in the liver waiting list: at 30, 90, 180 and 360 days post transplantation.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Related to the maintenance of the immune response.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute and Chronic Cellular Rejection. Percutaneous biopsy.</measure>
    <time_frame>Within the year of follow up.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Infection events. Clinical, biochemical, microbiological, endoscopic, radiological, echocardiographic, serological, imaging, evolution criteria.</measure>
    <time_frame>Within the year of follow up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity: renal, hematological, neurological. clinical, biochemical, imaging, nerve conduction, electromyography, CBC criteria.</measure>
    <time_frame>Within the year of follow up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular disease. Blood pressure measurements, biochemical tests, BMI and waist circumference, myocardial revascularization, angioplastic, CTP, ischemia testing, echocardiographic imaging, ultrasound, bone densitometry, radiology.</measure>
    <time_frame>Within the year of follow up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Malignancies. Tissue or lymph biopsy.</measure>
    <time_frame>Within the year of follow up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Re transplantation - Loss of the graft. Biopsy and functional tests.</measure>
    <time_frame>Within the year of follow up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rehospitalization. Hospital admission.</measure>
    <time_frame>Within the year of follow up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Death. Absence of vital signs.</measure>
    <time_frame>Within the year of follow up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">46</enrollment>
  <condition>Liver Transplantation</condition>
  <condition>Graft Versus Host Disease</condition>
  <condition>Infection</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Malignancy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No treatment</arm_group_label>
    <description>Healthy Volunteers. In the design of the trial is set as reference a cohort of untreated healthy volunteers, over which will be measured the biomarkers to determine the baseline. Implies PBMC ex-vivo drug contact prior all cell incubations.
Number proposed 30.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Liver Transplant Patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>About the cohort treated with immunosuppressive calcineurin drugs, it will be studied the behavior of pharmacodynamic markers ruled, their drug plasma concentration achieved before next dose and the clinical response.
The number proposed is 50.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Waiting LiverTransplantation List</arm_group_label>
    <description>Biomarkers determination, plasma concentrations of calcineurin and monitoring of the clinical response, will be done before transplantation (time 0), and then at 30, 60, 90, 180 and 365 days after transplantation.
The number proposed is 12.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Genetic analysis is carried out from whole blood samples,from which DNA is extracted for the
      study of relevant polymorphisms.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Transplant Patients on anticalcineurin drugs and Transplant Waiting List Patients
        comprising the National Program of Liver Transplantation in Uruguay.

        Healthy Volunteers belonging to the Hospital payroll.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Healthy volunteers:

          -  Age: 18 to 70 years.

          -  Ethnicity: Hispanic, African American.

          -  Gender: male and female.

          -  Condition: healthy.

          -  Informed consent: granted and signed informed consent at the time of inclusion and
             agree to comply with all the procedures included in the protocol.

        Waiting List Patients:

          -  Age: 18 to 70 years.

          -  Ethnicity: Hispanic, African American.

          -  Gender: male and female.

          -  Being active on the waiting list for liver transplantation

          -  Informed consent: granted and signed at the time of inclusion and agree to comply
             with all the procedures included in the protocol.

        Transplant Patients:

          -  Age: 18 to 70 years.

          -  Ethnicity: Hispanic, African American.

          -  Gender: male and female.

          -  Drug therapy: cyclosporine or tacrolimus, with or without mycophenolic acid
             derivatives and/or corticosteroids.

          -  Informed consent: granted and signed at the time of inclusion and agree to comply
             with all the procedures included in the protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Healthy volunteers:

          -  pregnancy

          -  breastfeeding

          -  chronic drug treatment

          -  non healthy

        Waiting List Patients:

          -  Patients with previous transplant.

          -  Patients with more of one transplanted organ.

          -  Patients on anticalcineurin drugs.

          -  Patients with impaired renal function - creatinine clearance ≤ 20 ml/min.

        Transplant Patients:

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding.

          -  Patients with prior retransplantation.

          -  Patients with more of one transplanted organ.

          -  Patients with impaired renal function - creatinine clearance ≤ 20 ml/min.

          -  Everolimus indication at any time during treatment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ofelia M Noceti</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UDA Centro Nacional Hepato-Bilio-Pancreático</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Solange Gerona, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>National Liver Transplantation Program</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Central de las Fuerzas Armadas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montevideo</city>
        <zip>11300</zip>
        <country>Uruguay</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Uruguay</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 16, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 1, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Liver organ transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>Anticalcineurin drugs</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacodynamic biomarkers</keyword>
  <keyword>Calcineurin pathway</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Graft vs Host Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclosporins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclosporine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tacrolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
