<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="48453">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01686828</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>43007-B</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01686828</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>T-IR- Study to Understand the Effects of Testosterone and Estrogen on the Body's Response to the Hormone Insulin, Which Regulates Blood Sugar Levels</brief_title>
  <acronym>T-IR</acronym>
  <official_title>Androgen-mediated Pathways in the Regulation of Insulin Sensitivity in Men</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Washington</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research study is to understand the effects of testosterone and estrogen
      on the body's response to the hormone insulin.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators will examine the effects of testosterone on insulin sensitivity and body
      composition in men.  This study may lend greater insight into the increased risk of diabetes
      evident in men with low circulating levels of testosterone. Three drugs will be used in this
      study: acyline, given by injection; testosterone (T) gel that is applied to the skin; and
      letrozole, which is an oral drug that blocks the conversion of androgens (male hormones) to
      estrogens (female hormones).  Acyline inhibits the production of luteinizing hormone (LH)
      and follicle stimulating hormone (FSH).  When acyline stops the production of these
      hormones, it blocks the signal from the brain that stimulates the testicles to make
      testosterone.  Adding testosterone to acyline will restore physiologic levels of
      testosterone in some study participants.  One group of men will receive T gel with
      letrozole, an aromatase inhibitor; these men will have normal levels of testosterone but low
      levels of estrogen in the blood.  This design will enable determination of the respective
      metabolic effects of testosterone and estrogen.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics/Dynamics Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Insulin sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Glucose disposal assessed by frequently sampled oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in body composition</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in adipose tissue gene expression</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Insulin Resistance</condition>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Androgen Deficiency</condition>
  <condition>Metabolic Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Acyline &amp; placebo gel &amp; placebo pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Acyline (300mcg/kg at Day 0 &amp; week 2, by injections) + placebo transdermal gel + placebo aromatase inhibitor daily for 4 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Acyline &amp; Testosterone Gel 1.25g/d &amp; placebo pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Acyline (300mcg/kg at Day 0 &amp; week 2, by injections) + Testosterone 1.62% gel (1.25g) daily + placebo aromatase inhibitor pill daily for 4 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Acyline &amp; Testosterone Gel 5g/d &amp; placebo pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Acyline (300mcg/kg every 2 weeks, by injections) + Testosterone 1.62% gel (5g) daily + placebo aromatase inhibitor pill daily for 4 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Acyline &amp; Testosterone gel &amp; Letrozole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Acyline (300mcg/kg at Day 0 &amp; week 2, by injections) + Testosterone transdermal 1.62% gel (5g) daily + letrozole (5mg) aromatase inhibitor pill daily for 4 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Acyline</intervention_name>
    <description>300 mcg/mL administered subcutaneously (at Day 0, Week 2)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Acyline &amp; placebo gel &amp; placebo pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Acyline &amp; Testosterone Gel 1.25g/d &amp; placebo pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Acyline &amp; Testosterone Gel 5g/d &amp; placebo pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Acyline &amp; Testosterone gel &amp; Letrozole</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Testosterone 1.62% gel</intervention_name>
    <description>Transdermal Testosterone Gel (either 3.75g or 5g/d) for 4 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Acyline &amp; Testosterone Gel 1.25g/d &amp; placebo pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Acyline &amp; Testosterone Gel 5g/d &amp; placebo pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Acyline &amp; Testosterone gel &amp; Letrozole</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Androgel</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Letrozole</intervention_name>
    <description>Letrozole oral aromatase inhibitor 5mg daily for 4 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Acyline &amp; Testosterone gel &amp; Letrozole</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Femara</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo gel (for Testosterone 1.62% gel)</intervention_name>
    <description>placebo gel manufactured to mimic Testosterone 1.62% gel</description>
    <arm_group_label>Acyline &amp; placebo gel &amp; placebo pill</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo pill (for Letrozole)</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral placebo aromatase inhibitor to mimic Letrozole 5mg/d</description>
    <arm_group_label>Acyline &amp; placebo gel &amp; placebo pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Acyline &amp; Testosterone Gel 1.25g/d &amp; placebo pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Acyline &amp; Testosterone Gel 5g/d &amp; placebo pill</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  PSA ≤ 3 ng/mL

          -  Age 25-55 years

          -  Ability to understand the study, study procedures and provide informed consent

          -  Serum total T &gt; 300 ng/dL

          -  Normal reproductive history and exam

          -  International Prostate Symptom Score (IPSS) &lt; 11

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A history of prostate cancer including suspicious DRE or history of highgrade PIN on
             prostate biopsy

          -  Invasive therapy for BPH in the past

          -  History of acute urinary retention in the previous 3 months

          -  Current or recent past use of androgenic or anti-androgenic drugs, steroids or drugs
             which interfere with steroid metabolism (within the last 3 months)

          -  Current use of statins or glucocorticoids

          -  Severe systemic illness (renal, liver, cardiac, lung disease, cancer, diabetes
             mellitus) or skin disease

          -  A history of or current breast cancer

          -  Known, untreated obstructive sleep apnea

          -  Hematocrit &gt; 50 or &lt; 34

          -  Hypersensitivity to any of the drugs used in the study

          -  History of a bleeding disorder or anticoagulation

          -  Participation in any other drug study within past 90 days

          -  History of drug or alcohol abuse within the last 12 months

          -  Weight &gt; 280 lbs. or BMI ≥ 33

          -  Desire for fertility in the next 6 months or current pregnant partner

          -  Sperm concentration &lt;14 million/ml

          -  Significant, uncontrolled hypertension (BP &gt;160/100 mmHg); subjects with
             well-controlled BP on medical therapy will be eligible to participate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William J Bremner, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Washington</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephanie T Page, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Washington</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Katya Rubinow, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Washington</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Katya Rubinow, MD</last_name>
    <phone>206-616-1818</phone>
    <email>rubinow@uw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Genecelle Delossantos</last_name>
    <phone>206 779-9496</phone>
    <email>gen7@uw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Washington</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Genecelle Delossantos</last_name>
      <phone>206-221-3490</phone>
      <email>gen7@uw.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kathy Winter</last_name>
      <phone>206-616-0484</phone>
      <email>klwinter@uw.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Katya Rubinow, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://depts.washington.edu/popctr/</url>
    <description>Dedicated to basic and clinical research focused primarily on the male reproductive system.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Flegal KM. Excess deaths associated with obesity: cause and effect. Int J Obes (Lond). 2006 Aug;30(8):1171-2.</citation>
    <PMID>16871273</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Araujo AB, O'Donnell AB, Brambilla DJ, Simpson WB, Longcope C, Matsumoto AM, McKinlay JB. Prevalence and incidence of androgen deficiency in middle-aged and older men: estimates from the Massachusetts Male Aging Study. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2004 Dec;89(12):5920-6.</citation>
    <PMID>15579737</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yeap BB, Chubb SA, Hyde Z, Jamrozik K, Hankey GJ, Flicker L, Norman PE. Lower serum testosterone is independently associated with insulin resistance in non-diabetic older men: the Health In Men Study. Eur J Endocrinol. 2009 Oct;161(4):591-8. Epub 2009 Aug 6.</citation>
    <PMID>19661128</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muller M, Grobbee DE, den Tonkelaar I, Lamberts SW, van der Schouw YT. Endogenous sex hormones and metabolic syndrome in aging men. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2005 May;90(5):2618-23. Epub 2005 Feb 1.</citation>
    <PMID>15687322</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Li C, Ford ES, Li B, Giles WH, Liu S. Association of testosterone and sex hormone-binding globulin with metabolic syndrome and insulin resistance in men. Diabetes Care. 2010 Jul;33(7):1618-24. doi: 10.2337/dc09-1788. Epub 2010 Apr 5.</citation>
    <PMID>20368409</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith MR, Lee H, Fallon MA, Nathan DM. Adipocytokines, obesity, and insulin resistance during combined androgen blockade for prostate cancer. Urology. 2008 Feb;71(2):318-22.</citation>
    <PMID>18308111</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith MR, Lee H, Nathan DM. Insulin sensitivity during combined androgen blockade for prostate cancer. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2006 Apr;91(4):1305-8. Epub 2006 Jan 24.</citation>
    <PMID>16434464</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mauras N, Hayes V, Welch S, Rini A, Helgeson K, Dokler M, Veldhuis JD, Urban RJ. Testosterone deficiency in young men: marked alterations in whole body protein kinetics, strength, and adiposity. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 1998 Jun;83(6):1886-92.</citation>
    <PMID>9626114</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yialamas MA, Dwyer AA, Hanley E, Lee H, Pitteloud N, Hayes FJ. Acute sex steroid withdrawal reduces insulin sensitivity in healthy men with idiopathic hypogonadotropic hypogonadism. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2007 Nov;92(11):4254-9. Epub 2007 Aug 28.</citation>
    <PMID>17726076</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klimcakova E, Roussel B, Kovacova Z, Kovacikova M, Siklova-Vitkova M, Combes M, Hejnova J, Decaunes P, Maoret JJ, Vedral T, Viguerie N, Bourlier V, Bouloumié A, Stich V, Langin D. Macrophage gene expression is related to obesity and the metabolic syndrome in human subcutaneous fat as well as in visceral fat. Diabetologia. 2011 Apr;54(4):876-87. doi: 10.1007/s00125-010-2014-3. Epub 2011 Jan 26.</citation>
    <PMID>21267541</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Odegaard JI, Chawla A. Mechanisms of macrophage activation in obesity-induced insulin resistance. Nat Clin Pract Endocrinol Metab. 2008 Nov;4(11):619-26. Epub 2008 Oct 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18838972</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rubinow KB, Snyder CN, Amory JK, Hoofnagle AN, Page ST. Acute testosterone deprivation reduces insulin sensitivity in men. Clin Endocrinol (Oxf). 2012 Feb;76(2):281-8. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2265.2011.04189.x.</citation>
    <PMID>21797916</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ortega Martinez de Victoria E, Xu X, Koska J, Francisco AM, Scalise M, Ferrante AW Jr, Krakoff J. Macrophage content in subcutaneous adipose tissue: associations with adiposity, age, inflammatory markers, and whole-body insulin action in healthy Pima Indians. Diabetes. 2009 Feb;58(2):385-93. Epub 2008 Nov 13.</citation>
    <PMID>19008342</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weisberg SP, McCann D, Desai M, Rosenbaum M, Leibel RL, Ferrante AW Jr. Obesity is associated with macrophage accumulation in adipose tissue. J Clin Invest. 2003 Dec;112(12):1796-808.</citation>
    <PMID>14679176</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Xu HZ, Li Y, Zhao YF. [Diagnosis and treatment of osteopathic parathyroid adenoma]. Zhongguo Xiu Fu Chong Jian Wai Ke Za Zhi. 2003 Nov;17(6):446-9. Chinese.</citation>
    <PMID>14663938</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lumeng CN, DelProposto JB, Westcott DJ, Saltiel AR. Phenotypic switching of adipose tissue macrophages with obesity is generated by spatiotemporal differences in macrophage subtypes. Diabetes. 2008 Dec;57(12):3239-46. Epub 2008 Oct 1.</citation>
    <PMID>18829989</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rull A, Camps J, Alonso-Villaverde C, Joven J. Insulin resistance, inflammation, and obesity: role of monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 (or CCL2) in the regulation of metabolism. Mediators Inflamm. 2010;2010. pii: 326580. Epub 2010 Sep 23.</citation>
    <PMID>20936118</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bastard JP, Maachi M, Lagathu C, Kim MJ, Caron M, Vidal H, Capeau J, Feve B. Recent advances in the relationship between obesity, inflammation, and insulin resistance. Eur Cytokine Netw. 2006 Mar;17(1):4-12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16613757</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chazenbalk G, Bertolotto C, Heneidi S, Jumabay M, Trivax B, Aronowitz J, Yoshimura K, Simmons CF, Dumesic DA, Azziz R. Novel pathway of adipogenesis through cross-talk between adipose tissue macrophages, adipose stem cells and adipocytes: evidence of cell plasticity. PLoS One. 2011 Mar 31;6(3):e17834. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0017834.</citation>
    <PMID>21483855</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gilliver SC. Sex steroids as inflammatory regulators. J Steroid Biochem Mol Biol. 2010 May 31;120(2-3):105-15. doi: 10.1016/j.jsbmb.2009.12.015. Epub 2010 Jan 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20045727</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cunningham M, Gilkeson G. Estrogen receptors in immunity and autoimmunity. Clin Rev Allergy Immunol. 2011 Feb;40(1):66-73. doi: 10.1007/s12016-010-8203-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20352526</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bouman A, Moes H, Heineman MJ, de Leij LF, Faas MM. The immune response during the luteal phase of the ovarian cycle: increasing sensitivity of human monocytes to endotoxin. Fertil Steril. 2001 Sep;76(3):555-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11532481</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lai JJ, Lai KP, Chuang KH, Chang P, Yu IC, Lin WJ, Chang C. Monocyte/macrophage androgen receptor suppresses cutaneous wound healing in mice by enhancing local TNF-alpha expression. J Clin Invest. 2009 Dec;119(12):3739-51. doi: 10.1172/JCI39335. Epub 2009 Nov 9.</citation>
    <PMID>19907077</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hildebrand F, Thobe BM, Hubbard WJ, Choudhry MA, Pape HC, Chaudry IH. Effects of 17beta-estradiol and flutamide on splenic macrophages and splenocytes after trauma-hemorrhage. Cytokine. 2006 Nov;36(3-4):107-14. Epub 2007 Jan 4.</citation>
    <PMID>17207634</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Qiu Y, Yanase T, Hu H, Tanaka T, Nishi Y, Liu M, Sueishi K, Sawamura T, Nawata H. Dihydrotestosterone suppresses foam cell formation and attenuates atherosclerosis development. Endocrinology. 2010 Jul;151(7):3307-16. doi: 10.1210/en.2009-1268. Epub 2010 Apr 28.</citation>
    <PMID>20427482</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rettew JA, Huet-Hudson YM, Marriott I. Testosterone reduces macrophage expression in the mouse of toll-like receptor 4, a trigger for inflammation and innate immunity. Biol Reprod. 2008 Mar;78(3):432-7. Epub 2007 Nov 14.</citation>
    <PMID>18003947</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ribas V, Drew BG, Le JA, Soleymani T, Daraei P, Sitz D, Mohammad L, Henstridge DC, Febbraio MA, Hewitt SC, Korach KS, Bensinger SJ, Hevener AL. Myeloid-specific estrogen receptor alpha deficiency impairs metabolic homeostasis and accelerates atherosclerotic lesion development. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2011 Sep 27;108(39):16457-62. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1104533108. Epub 2011 Sep 7. Erratum in: Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2012 Jan 10;109(2):645.</citation>
    <PMID>21900603</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kratz M, Purnell JQ, Breen PA, Thomas KK, Utzschneider KM, Carr DB, Kahn SE, Hughes JP, Rutledge EA, Van Yserloo B, Yukawa M, Weigle DS. Reduced adipogenic gene expression in thigh adipose tissue precedes human immunodeficiency virus-associated lipoatrophy. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2008 Mar;93(3):959-66. Epub 2007 Dec 18.</citation>
    <PMID>18089690</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herbst KL, Anawalt BD, Amory JK, Bremner WJ. Acyline: the first study in humans of a potent, new gonadotropin-releasing hormone antagonist. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2002 Jul;87(7):3215-20.</citation>
    <PMID>12107227</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herbst KL, Coviello AD, Page S, Amory JK, Anawalt BD, Bremner WJ. A single dose of the potent gonadotropin-releasing hormone antagonist acyline suppresses gonadotropins and testosterone for 2 weeks in healthy young men. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2004 Dec;89(12):5959-65.</citation>
    <PMID>15579744</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Page ST, Herbst KL, Amory JK, Coviello AD, Anawalt BD, Matsumoto AM, Bremner WJ. Testosterone administration suppresses adiponectin levels in men. J Androl. 2005 Jan-Feb;26(1):85-92.</citation>
    <PMID>15611571</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bhasin S, Storer TW, Berman N, Callegari C, Clevenger B, Phillips J, Bunnell TJ, Tricker R, Shirazi A, Casaburi R. The effects of supraphysiologic doses of testosterone on muscle size and strength in normal men. N Engl J Med. 1996 Jul 4;335(1):1-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8637535</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tricker R, Casaburi R, Storer TW, Clevenger B, Berman N, Shirazi A, Bhasin S. The effects of supraphysiological doses of testosterone on angry behavior in healthy eugonadal men--a clinical research center study. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 1996 Oct;81(10):3754-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8855834</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bhasin S, Woodhouse L, Casaburi R, Singh AB, Mac RP, Lee M, Yarasheski KE, Sinha-Hikim I, Dzekov C, Dzekov J, Magliano L, Storer TW. Older men are as responsive as young men to the anabolic effects of graded doses of testosterone on the skeletal muscle. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2005 Feb;90(2):678-88. Epub 2004 Nov 23.</citation>
    <PMID>15562020</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cuzick J, DeCensi A, Arun B, Brown PH, Castiglione M, Dunn B, Forbes JF, Glaus A, Howell A, von Minckwitz G, Vogel V, Zwierzina H. Preventive therapy for breast cancer: a consensus statement. Lancet Oncol. 2011 May;12(5):496-503. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(11)70030-4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21441069</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leder BZ, LeBlanc KM, Schoenfeld DA, Eastell R, Finkelstein JS. Differential effects of androgens and estrogens on bone turnover in normal men. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2003 Jan;88(1):204-10.</citation>
    <PMID>12519853</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Belgorosky A, Guercio G, Pepe C, Saraco N, Rivarola MA. Genetic and clinical spectrum of aromatase deficiency in infancy, childhood and adolescence. Horm Res. 2009;72(6):321-30. Epub 2009 Oct 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19844120</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Campbell KL, Makar KW, Kratz M, Foster-Schubert KE, McTiernan A, Ulrich CM. A pilot study of sampling subcutaneous adipose tissue to examine biomarkers of cancer risk. Cancer Prev Res (Phila). 2009 Jan;2(1):37-42.</citation>
    <PMID>19139016</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muniyappa R, Lee S, Chen H, Quon MJ. Current approaches for assessing insulin sensitivity and resistance in vivo: advantages, limitations, and appropriate usage. Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab. 2008 Jan;294(1):E15-26. Epub 2007 Oct 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17957034</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Olefsky JM, Glass CK. Macrophages, inflammation, and insulin resistance. Annu Rev Physiol. 2010;72:219-46. doi: 10.1146/annurev-physiol-021909-135846. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20148674</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 12, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Washington</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Katya Rubinow</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>insulin</keyword>
  <keyword>androgens</keyword>
  <keyword>insulin resistance</keyword>
  <keyword>testosterone</keyword>
  <keyword>estradiol</keyword>
  <keyword>obesity</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insulin Resistance</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Testosterone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone enanthate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone undecanoate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone 17 beta-cypionate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Androgens</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methyltestosterone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Letrozole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insulin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aromatase Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
