<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="18129">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01661010</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>120181</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>12-HG-0181</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01661010</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Study of Y Chromosome Variants and Infertility</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Clinical Study of Patients With Y Chromosome Variants</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - 10% of couples has difficulty having children. The term    infertility    is used when a
      couple tries to have a child and is unable to get pregnant within 1 year, or is unable to
      carry a pregnancy to 20 weeks for three or more pregnancies. The causes of infertility
      include issues involving both men and women. Some of the known causes are endometriosis;
      decreases in fertility due to aging; problems with the ovaries, fallopian tubes, or uterus;
      and problems with the men   s sperm. However, the genetic causes of infertility are not well
      understood. Sometimes, infertility is related to chromosome differences in both men and
      women. Chromosomes are the structures inside of each cell that carry our genetic material
      (genes). Certain differences in the Y chromosome are known to cause infertility. However, it
      is not known whether people with Y chromosome differences (missing or extra Y chromosome
      material) have medical conditions other than infertility. This study is seeking to learn
      whether persons with Y chromosome differences have other health issues in addition to
      infertility.

      Objectives:

      - To study related medical conditions in people with a known genetic cause of infertility
      related to the Y chromosome.

      Eligibility:

      -In the event that a patient with a Y-chromosome variant self-refers to the protocol,
      medical records will be reviewed by a committee to include Dr. David Page, Dr. Maximilian
      Muenke, and others to decide whether the patient is appropriate for enrollment in the
      protocol.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. Blood and urine
           samples will be collected.

        -  This study will last about 4 to 5 days. Participants will have a variety of endocrine
           and other tests. They will provide blood, urine, and semen samples for these tests. No
           genetic tests will be done as a part of this study; however, DNA from participants will
           be stored and may be used in future studies.

        -  Imaging studies of the heart and abdomen will be performed. These tests may include
           ultrasounds and magnetic resonance imaging.

        -  Participants will also have their vision and hearing checked.

        -  Treatment will not be provided as part of this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Infertility is a disease that affects approximately 10% of couples world-wide. Causes of
      infertility are varied and include age-related decline in fecundity, other causes of
      ovulatory dysfunction, tubal and pelvic pathology, male causes, idiopathic, and
      multifactorial. The underlying genetic causes of infertility are incompletely understood.
      The purpose of this study is to increase our understanding of the genetic and clinical
      manifestations of infertility related to Ychromosome differences through detailed physical,
      radiologic, and laboratory studies. We will concentrate on a group of patients (both male
      and female) with known Y-chromosome variations and infertility previously identified by our
      collaborator, Dr. David Page   s lab. Patients recruited and consenting to this study will
      be evaluated at the NIH Clinical Center.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>N/A</study_design>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Male Factor Infertility</condition>
  <condition>Female Factor Infertility</condition>
  <condition>Turner Syndrome</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. Patients previously identified through the Page lab as having Y-chromosome
                  variants causing deletion/duplication of Y-linked genes, male and female, with
                  infertility.

               2. In the event that a patient with a Y-chromosome variant self-refers to the
                  protocol, medical records will be reviewed by a committee to include Dr. David
                  Page, Dr. Maximilian Muenke, and others to decide whether the patient is
                  appropriate for enrollment in the protocol.

               3. Willing family members of subjects enrolled may be enrolled as control subjects.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Anyone unwilling to provide informed consent or assent.

          2. We reserve the right to exclude patients with medical conditions that would place a
             potential participant at high risk of complications if managed at the NIH clinical
             center (ex. dialysis dependency, unstable cardiac conditions, unstable severe
             depression/suicidality).

          3. We reserve the right to exclude cases that are clearly not related to Ychromosome
             variants, infertility or our direct research interests (e.g. infertility with clearly
             non-genetic etiology). This almost never happens, and we would attempt to make
             referrals to a more appropriate investigator.

        It is our intention to try to remove as many economic, cultural, geographic, racial, and
        gender barriers as we reasonably can to promote a diverse participation of infertility
        cases for research purposes.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maximilian Muenke, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Maximilian Muenke, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-8167</phone>
    <email>mamuenke@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2012-HG-0181.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brandell RA, Mielnik A, Liotta D, Ye Z, Veeck LL, Palermo GD, Schlegel PN. AZFb deletions predict the absence of spermatozoa with testicular sperm extraction: preliminary report of a prognostic genetic test. Hum Reprod. 1998 Oct;13(1O):2812-5.</citation>
    <PMID>9804236</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bondy CA; Turner Syndrome Study Group. Care of girls and women with Turner syndrome: a guideline of the Turner Syndrome Study Group. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2007 Jan;92(1):10-25. Epub 2006 Oct 17.</citation>
    <PMID>17047017</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berta P, Hawkins JR, Sinclair AH, Taylor A, Griffiths BL, Goodfellow PN, Fellous M. Genetic evidence equating SRY and the testis-determining factor. Nature. 1990 Nov 29;348(6300):448-50.</citation>
    <PMID>2247149</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 7, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <keyword>Infertility</keyword>
  <keyword>Male Factor Infertility</keyword>
  <keyword>Female Factor Infertility</keyword>
  <keyword>Unexplained Infertility</keyword>
  <keyword>Sex Chromosome</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Infertility</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Turner Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gonadal Dysgenesis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Primary Ovarian Insufficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
