<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="58719">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01922934</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GM3469</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01922934</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Toolbox Approach to Obesity Treatment in Primary Care</brief_title>
  <acronym>Toolbox</acronym>
  <official_title>A Toolbox Approach to Obesity Treatment in Primary Care</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Denver Health and Hospital Authority</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Denver Health and Hospital Authority</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Obesity is common and it causes many medical problems in adults such as
      diabetes, high blood pressure, high cholesterol, sleep apnea, heart attack, and stroke.  A
      range of treatments have been shown to be effective to treat obesity.  These treatments
      include intensive lifestyle modification, meal replacements, and weight loss medication.
      However, most primary care settings do not provide very much obesity treatment.  This is
      because primary care providers (PCPs) are not well trained and because reimbursement for the
      treatments is not consistent.

      Hypothesis: If PCPs have training in weight management and if most of the cost of treatment
      is reimbursed, we believe that a &quot;toolbox&quot; of treatments can produce a clinically important
      amount of weight loss in a large group of patients.

      Design:  We are proposing to establish a registry of patients who have obesity and at least
      one common medical condition related to their weight.  From the registry, we will randomly
      select 350 people who will be offered treatments to assist with weight loss.  The remainder
      of the patients in the registry can still receive treatment for obesity but will not have
      reimbursement for the treatments.  We will conduct the study at Denver Health, which is a
      large public health care system that treats a low income, ethnically diverse population. All
      350 patients will be offered some self-monitoring tools for weight management and the chance
      to take a computer assessment to select the right treatment for weight loss.  Patients who
      complete this and who record their food intake and physical activity for 1 week will be
      offered a &quot;Level 2&quot; treatment to help with weight loss.  The Level 2 treatments will
      include: a voucher for a commercial weight loss program; an intensive group behavioral
      weight loss program; meal replacements; fitness center membership; or weight loss
      medication.  Patients will be able to choose which treatment they want, with the approval of
      their PCP.  A Patient Navigator at Denver Health will help with the computer assessment and
      with accessing the treatments.  Each patient who completes the self-monitoring will be
      offered the Level 2 treatment for one year.  We are interested to see what percentage of
      patients lose at least 5% of their starting weight.  We will also look at changes in blood
      sugar, blood pressure, and cholesterol, and we will look at how much it costs to do this
      intervention and whether patients need less medication for their weight-related conditions
      at the end of the study.

      Impact: If the study is successful, we plan to take the results to the leaders at Denver
      Health to see if they will make obesity treatment more broadly available for all patients
      there.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: Obesity is prevalent and is a root cause of many common medical conditions
      affecting U.S. adults.  A range of treatment options have demonstrated efficacy in producing
      weight loss and reducing health risks in randomized controlled trials.  However, very little
      obesity treatment is currently delivered in most primary care settings.  Inadequate
      reimbursement for treatment modalities and a lack of systematic training of primary care
      providers (PCPs) are two of the major barriers to more widespread treatment.

      Hypothesis:  If PCPs are given training and support for weight management, and if treatment
      options with proven efficacy are offered to obese adults with weight related co-morbidities
      with the majority of the treatment cost reimbursed, then clinically meaningful weight loss
      will be produced in a significant number of these individuals at a reasonable cost.

      Design:  This application proposes a 12 month intervention trial among obese adults cared
      for at 4 primary care clinics affiliated with Denver Health (DH), an integrated health care
      system serving an ethnically diverse medically underserved population.  From among a large
      population of patients (~8,000) with obesity and at least one co-morbid condition, 350
      individuals will be randomly selected to be offered a &quot;toolbox&quot; of treatment options.  The
      remainder will be assigned to a control condition.  The &quot;toolbox&quot; will include: 1) meal
      replacements; 2) group weight loss counseling; 3) membership at recreation centers; 4)
      pharmacotherapy with phentermine; and 5) other options.  Patients in the intervention arm
      will undergo an initial evaluation using an &quot;expert systems&quot; computer program.  They will
      then be required to self-monitor diet and physical activity before gaining access to the
      higher cost weight management services in the toolbox.  Primary care providers will help
      patients choose treatment approaches, encourage adherence, and monitor success.  Patient
      Navigators will assist patients in accessing prescribed treatments.  The primary outcome
      will be the fraction of patients in each group who achieve a 5% weight loss after 12 months
      of intervention.  Secondary outcomes will include uptake and utilization of treatment
      options, changes in cardiovascular disease risk factors, and other health care utilization,
      in particular outpatient medications for diabetes, hypertension, and lipids.  While the
      treatment modalities to be used in this trial are not new, an intervention delivering a
      toolbox of weight management services in a safety net clinical setting and examining the
      effect on health care utilization is innovative.  The submitted letters of support attest to
      the need for more data so that health care providers and payers can make evidence-based
      decisions regarding the provision of obesity treatment to large patient populations.

      Impact:  A positive result would encourage the broader adoption of a toolbox approach to
      weight management in primary care settings.  A negative result would strongly suggest that
      even with a &quot;best case scenario&quot; of training and support for obesity treatment, the primary
      care clinic is not an effective route of delivery for weight management.  Either result
      would be important in shaping future policy decisions about obesity treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight change</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Weight loss as a percentage of starting weight</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health care utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in utilization of utilization of health care resources (prescription drugs, labs, outpatient visits, procedures, urgent care visits, ER visits and hospitalizations)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Documentation of obesity</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Fraction of patients with a ICD-9 code for obesity; evidence that the PCP discussed weight loss with the patient; evidence of a specific intervention for weight management (e.g., Weight Watchers, medication).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular risk factors</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in blood pressure, glycemic control, and lipids</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">350</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity With Co-morbid Conditions</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>350 patients at one of 4 intervention clinics will be randomly selected to be offered a &quot;toolbox&quot; of weight management interventions. The toolbox will include: self-monitoring tools; educational materials; physical activity resources; a commercial weight loss program; an intensive group behavior modification program; a meal replacement approach; and weight loss medication. The initial assessment will use a computer program to take a diet and physical activity history and help patients choose personal treatment goals. Interested patients will be given a &quot;starter kit&quot; including self-monitoring tools and samples of meal replacement products. Subjects will be required to demonstrate self-monitoring of diet and physical activity to be eligible for the more intensive therapies. Patients will pay a 25% &quot;co-pay&quot; for the higher cost therapies. Patients will select a primary intensive therapy, but will be able to add or change depending on results, adherence and budget availability.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Registry patients not selected to be offered the toolbox will receive usual care for weight management.  Usual care for obesity at DH includes brief weight loss advice provided by PCPs or prescribing of weight loss medication, for which patients pay out of pocket.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Commercial weight loss program</intervention_name>
    <description>vouchers for Weight Watchers</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Colorado Weigh</intervention_name>
    <description>Group behavioral weight loss program</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Meal replacements</intervention_name>
    <description>Slim-Fast</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pharmacotherapy for obesity</intervention_name>
    <description>Phentermine or phentermine-topiramate (Qsymia)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Recrecation center passes</intervention_name>
    <description>1 year pass to a Denver recreation center</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. BMI &gt; 30 kg/m2 and &lt; 45 kg/m2

          2. Any one of the following (weight-related) diagnoses: type 2 diabetes or pre-diabetes,
             including those treated with glucose lowering medications; hypertension, including
             patients treated with anti-hypertensive medications; hyperlipidemia, including those
             treated with lipid lowering agents; atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease, including
             coronary heart disease, cerebrovascular disease, or peripheral vascular disease;
             obstructive sleep apnea

          3. Visited their primary care provider (PCP) at least twice during the past 12 months,
             including once in the last 6 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Heart attack or stroke within the past 6 months; cancer treated within the past 5 years,
        except for non-melanoma skin cancer or localized prostate cancer; other medical
        contraindications to weight loss (e.g., end-stage renal disease, cirrhosis); active
        substance abuse; current treatment for bipolar disorder or schizophrenia; discretion of
        PCP (see below)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Denver Health and Hospital Authority</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80204</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Daniel H Bessesen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Adam G Tsai, MD, MSCE</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 13, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Denver Health and Hospital Authority</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Daniel Bessesen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
