<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="141330">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01990183</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ICT-2011.5.1-287932</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01990183</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CareToy - A Modular Smart System for Infants' Rehabilitation at Home Based on Mechatronic Toys</brief_title>
  <acronym>CareToy</acronym>
  <official_title>CareToy - A Modular Smart System for Infants' Rehabilitation at Home Based on Mechatronic Toys</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>IRCCS Fondazione Stella Maris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>BioRobotics Institute - Scuola Superiore Sant'Anna, Italy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>STMicroelectronics SRL, Italy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Ljubljana</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Hamburg, Germany</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fonden for Helen Elsass Center, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Marketing Research &amp; Development SPA, Italy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>IRCCS Fondazione Stella Maris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Italy: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>Italy: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>Denmark: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Stroke and other neurological conditions affect the population of infants in percentages
      that cannot be considered marginal. Preterm infants are the highest infants at risk for
      neurological damage. Currently, infants have rehabilitation sessions few times a week in
      rehabilitation centres but according to basic neuroscience it would be necessary to provide
      them with an early, intensive and multiaxial intervention. One option to reduce the cost of
      the entire European Healthcare System while increasing the practice of rehabilitation is to
      devise therapies and technologies that can be administered at home by caregivers and
      telemonitored by rehabilitation staff. The aim of this proposal is to promote early
      intervention in the first year of life and to reinforce therapy by &quot;CareToy&quot;: a portable low
      cost smart system telemonitored thus augmenting the clinical effectiveness of the therapy
      while reducing the cost. The smart system is based on a common baby gym, composed of
      different modules: a) an instrumented baby gym with mechatronic hanging toys, so that the
      infants' actions on the gym can be measured and stimulated, b) a vision module, for
      measuring and promoting infants' attention and gaze movements and c) a sensorized mat for
      measuring and promoting postural control. Each module will also incorporate built-in signal
      processor, memory and wireless communication. A fourth telerehabilitation module completes
      the system that allows the system to remotely communicate with the rehabilitation staff for
      monitoring and assessing the rehabilitation techniques. CareToy and the effectiveness of
      home rehabilitation based on this system will be validated by clinical trials on at least 50
      preterm infants. The result of this project could have a large impact. CareToy may become a
      commercial product, manufactured on a large scale and distributed not only in rehabilitation
      centres but also at homes, sold or rented by the Health Care System to families as a
      therapeutic tool for care intensity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study population will be made up of premature infants recruited at the local Department of
      Neonatology. The eligibility of infants, i.e. children who meet the criteria for inclusion
      and exclusion, will be evaluated by the Neonatology team. Recruitment should take place
      after discharge from Neonatal Intensive Care Unit (NICU) until the age stated by inclusion
      criteria and will begin with the signing of the participation agreement by the parents.
      During the recruitment extensive perinatal data will be collected from medical records. Each
      clinical centre will maintain these data in an internal database storing. Every child will
      be evaluated on the basis of a standard neurological examination supplemented by movement
      analysis on video recording using Prechtl's Method Qualitative Assessment of General
      Movements.

      The sample will be randomized in two groups in order to compare the effectiveness of the
      CareToy intervention program vs standard care on cognitive, motor ed visual development. We
      designed the study as randomized clinical trial with cross-over in order to guarantee the
      same opportunities to all infants recruited. The sample size was calculated on the basis of
      the primary outcome measure (Bayley III Cognitive Subtest [BSID], see Outcome measures).

      Before the starting of the RCT we have planned a short pilot phase where few infants will be
      assigned to the experimental arm without randomization. These cases will follow the same
      steps planned for the RCT. This phase aims to optimize the functioning of the CareToy system
      and of its rehabilitation packages.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes on Bayley III - Cognitive subscale</measure>
    <time_frame>T0 (baseline, 1week before beginning of Study period);T1 (within 1 week after the end of the first training/control period; before the cross-over); T2 (within 1 week after the end of the second training/control 2nd period, after cross‐over)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This scale is sensitive in detecting differences between normative sample and children at risk for delayed development, such as premature infants. It has normative value referenced assessments, with means of 100 and Standard Deviation [SD] of 15 points. Children whose  scores are 2 SDs below the normative value in a domain are considered as having a significant delay in that domain. Bayley--‐III is appropriate for administration to children between the ages of 1 month and 42 months (although norms extend downward to age 16 days). The Bayley III revision includes Cognitive, Language, Motor, Social-Emotional, and Adaptive Behaviour scales. Items on the cognitive subscale assess sensor‐motor development, exploration, manipulation, object relatedness, concept  formation, problem-solving and memory, all functions promoted during the CareToy sessions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes on Infant Motor Profile (IMP)</measure>
    <time_frame>T0(baseline, 1week before beginning of Study period);T1 (within 1 week after the end of the first training/control period; before the cross-over); T2 (within 1 week after the end of the second training/control 2nd period, after cross‐over)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>IMP is a reliable video-based assessment of motor behaviour in infancy from 3 to 18 months. It addresses to the child's motor abilities and evaluates motor behaviour in five domains: (1) variation, (2) variability (ability to select motor strategies), (3) movement fluency, (4) movement symmetry, and (5) motor performance. It has been validated in preterm and full term infants.  This tool is intended to detect and quantify changes after intervention and it is reported as having a satisfactory intra and inter observer reliability and a very good concurrent validity with Alberta Infant Motor Scale and Touwen Infant Neurological Examination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes on Alberta Infant Motor Scale (AIMS)</measure>
    <time_frame>T0 (baseline, 1week before beginning of Study period);T1 (within 1 week after the end of the first training/control period; before the cross-over); T2 (within 1 week after the end of the second training/control 2nd period, after cross‐over)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This scale examines delayed and abnormal motor development in infants overtime and is valid for assessment from term until 18 months of age. It has a good psychometric properties, it is quick to administer with limited handling and focuses on achievement of  motor milestones, quality of  posture and movement outcomes. Sensitivity of AIMS items has been demonstrated in differentiate preterm's infant motor development, that typically results in lower scores, and full term infants motor development.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CareToy Evaluation Packages</measure>
    <time_frame>T0 (baseline, 1week before beginning of Study period);T1 (within 1 week after the end of the first training/control period; before the cross-over); T2 (within 1 week after the end of the second training/control 2nd period, after cross‐over)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>CareToy Evaluation Packages will be carried out using a highly equipped system, called Caretoy C in a subgroup of the enrolled infants. This evaluation is composed by: visual and grasping packages. Visual package has design to evaluate some different infants visual abilities i.e. attention, audio-visual, fixation shift and novelty. Grasping package has design to evaluate grasping force and eye-head coordination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes on Teller Acuity Cards</measure>
    <time_frame>T0 (baseline, 1week before beginning of Study period);T1 (within 1 week after the end of the first training/control period; before the cross-over); T2 (within 1 week after the end of the second training/control 2nd period, after cross‐over)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Teller Acuity Cards II is a paediatric test used to evaluate visual acuity. It is based on behavioural response by judging infant's attention to a series of cards showing stripes of different widths.  This tool allows rapid assessment  of  resolution (grating) visual acuity in infants, young children, and other populations where verbal response to recognition (letter) visual acuity charts is difficult or impossible. It evaluates infants' acuity development and it has been used in several studies for diagnostic purposes and to measure results of early intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Ages &amp; Stages Questionnaire (ASQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>T0(baseline, 1week before beginning of Study period);T3 (18 months of corrected age)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>It has been developed as a screening tool for developmental delay in infants in numerous paediatric populations with reported sensitivity, a  measure of true positives, and specificity, a measure of true negatives, varying, with most studies reporting higher accuracy in at - risk populations.
This questionnaire will be given to parents after enrolment in order to define the most appropriate starting time for each infant.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Social - Emotional Scale of BSID-III</measure>
    <time_frame>T0 (baseline, 1week before beginning of Study period);T3 (18 months of corrected age)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The survey uses this observational rating scale that  provides a general indication of the infant's level of social- emotional development and information about whether or not  sensory processing difficulties are present.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Parenting Stress Index (PSI)</measure>
    <time_frame>T0 (baseline,1wk before beginning of Study period);T1(within 1 wk after end of 1st training/control period; before cross-over);T2 (within 1wk after end of 2nd training/control 2nd period, after cross‐over) T3 (18 mths of corrected age)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This is a self-report questionnaire designed to identify specific parental, child, and situational characteristics most commonly associated with dysfunctional parenting. Currently, the PSI is mostly used as a screening instrument  for early identification of parent- child systems, which are under stress and at risk of developing dysfunctional parenting behaviour.  Validity of PSI is good and has been established in numerous studies on children with developmental problems, behaviour problems, disabilities and illnesses, as well as studies of  at- risk families, and cross - cultural studies</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">54</enrollment>
  <condition>Preterms at Risk for Developmental Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CareToy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CareToy intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard Care</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CareToy</intervention_name>
    <description>Infants randomized in the Intervention Group will begin the habilitation intervention immediately after evaluation at baseline. Rehabilitation staff, in accordance with each infant's needs and clinical characteristics, will set up the CareToy System to perform individualized intervention packages and its user's manual. So a personalized CareToy System will be delivered at infant's home. Moreover parents will attend a training course to use it. During each daily home ‐ session (about 30 - 40 minutes overall) it will be proposed to the child various interactive activities in supine, prone and sitting position. The intervention phase lasts 4 weeks and each session will be remotely monitored by the rehabilitation staff.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CareToy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Care performed by caregiver to promote the infant development</description>
    <arm_group_label>CareToy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  gestational age ≥ 28+0 weeks  and 32+6 weeks

          -  corrected age at baseline: between 2 and 9 months;

          -  achievement of fixed cut off score in gross motor ability derived from Ages &amp; Stages
             Questionnaire, in relation to corrected age. In detail: 2 months (from 1 months to 2
             month 30 days) score ≥ 25; 4 months (from 3 months to 4 months 30 days) score ≥ 10;
             6 months  (from 5 months to 6 months 30 days) score ≥  5; 8 months (from 7 months to
             8 months 30 days)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  infants with gestational age &lt; 28 weeks or ≥ 33 weeks

          -  infants &quot;small for gestational age&quot; (SGA) i.e. weight below the 10th

          -  presence of brain damage (i.e. malformation, IntraVentricular Hemorrhage [IVH] &gt; ;
             any degree of periventricular leukomalacia

          -  known epilepsy or other form of seizure

          -  severe sensory deficits (blindness, deafness)

          -  other severe non neurological malformations

          -  simultaneous participation in other experimental study having rehabilitation aims

          -  withdrawal of informed concent

          -  onset of certain epilepsy or photosensitive form

          -  worsening of clinical conditions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>9 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Giovanni Cioni, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+39 050 886230</phone>
    <email>g.cioni@inpe.unipi.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Helene Elsass Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Holmegaardsvej 28</city>
        <state>Charlottenlund</state>
        <zip>2920</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jens Bo Nielsen, Dr.Med.Sci.</last_name>
      <phone>+ 45 35 32 74 50</phone>
      <email>jbnielsen@sund.ku.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jens Bo Nielsen, Dr.Med.Sci.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IRCCS Stella Maris Foundation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calambrone</city>
        <state>Pisa</state>
        <zip>56128</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Giovanni Cioni, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+39 050 886230</phone>
      <email>g.cioni@inpe.unipi.it</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Giovanni Cioni, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.caretoy.eu</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 24, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 7, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>preterm infants</keyword>
  <keyword>early intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>enrichment</keyword>
  <keyword>cognitive, motor, visual development</keyword>
  <keyword>tele-rehabilitation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Developmental Disabilities</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
