<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="65359">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01789138</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SARTH12115T</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>3.2.1001.11-0020</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01789138</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Adherence Support Intervention for Persons Living With HIV/AIDS (PLWHA) on Antiretroviral Therapy (ART) in Estonia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Controlled Trial of Situated Optimal Adherence Intervention Estonia (sOAI Estonia) Among Persons Living With HIV/AIDS (PLWHA) on Antiretroviral Therapy (ART) in Estonia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Tartu</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute for Health Development, Estonia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Tartu</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Estonia: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The specific aim of the study is to assess antiretroviral therapy adherence and evaluate the
      impact of a situated treatment adherence intervention program among persons living with
      HIV/AIDS on antiretroviral therapy in Estonia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Specific antiretroviral therapy (ART) can suppress HIV replication and consequently preserve
      the functioning of immune system. ART is a lifelong treatment with several different
      concomitantly administered oral medications. According to studies, low adherence to
      treatment is directly related to knowledge and beliefs about ART.

      Studies have shown the success of different interventions increasing adherence to ART, but
      additional studies need to be carried out in order to determine the most effective
      components of the interventions and the methods most suitable considering the local context,
      that could be easily incorporated into the working routine of an medical institution
      (clinic) with limited extra resources.

      Primary locations to implement activities directed at improving treatment adherence are
      medical institutions, i.e. the departments of infectious diseases where persons living with
      HIV/AIDS receive their ART.

      The aim of the study is to conduct a small-scale intervention (randomised controlled) study
      implementing a brief adherence counseling targeting persons receiving ART.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Antiretroviral therapy (ART) adherence (self-reported 3-day recall measure)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of study subjects with undetectable HIV-1 RNA count</measure>
    <time_frame>At study baseline and on months 6 and 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">600</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <condition>AIDS</condition>
  <condition>Medication Adherence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Situated Optimal Adherence Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Situated Optimal Adherence Intervention: see 'Interventions' for more details.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Adherence counseling, standard of care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard of care: Antiretroviral therapy adherence is discussed with patient (study participant) according to usual practice in the medical institution no special protocol followed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Situated Optimal Adherence Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Situated Optimal Adherence Intervention consists of 3 individual sessions (during consecutive medication pick-up visits to the clinic) -- patient-centered, non-judgmental, Motivational Interviewing- and theory-based, semi-structured, brief, candid conversations with a trained clinical care nurse using the Next Step Counseling approach. The intervention targets: accurate information about ART (mechanisms of HIV and antiretrovirals) and the development of mental imagery around it; promotion of perceived sense of ease and efficacy in working the ART regimen into the context of one's daily life and circumstances that may challenge drug use persistence; identification and refinement of skills that promote ease of adhering to one's ART regimen across the diverse and challenging contexts.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Situated Optimal Adherence Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV infected

          -  aware of the HIV-positive status for at least 3 months

          -  ≥ 18 years of age

          -  speak and read either Estonian or Russian

          -  receive or start (on recruitment date) antiretroviral therapy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  pregnant

          -  under the influence of alcohol or (illicit)drugs
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anneli Uusküla, MD, MSc, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Tartu</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Anneli Uusküla, MD, MSc, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+3727374195</phone>
    <email>anneli.uuskula@ut.ee</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kaja-Triin Laisaar, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>+3727374201</phone>
    <email>kaja-triin.laisaar@ut.ee</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>West-Tallinn Central Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tallinn</city>
        <state>Harju County</state>
        <zip>10617</zip>
        <country>Estonia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kristi Rüütel, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>East-Viru Central Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kohtla-Järve</city>
        <state>Ida-Viru County</state>
        <zip>31025</zip>
        <country>Estonia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kaja-Triin Laisaar, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Estonia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chesney MA, Ickovics JR, Chambers DB, Gifford AL, Neidig J, Zwickl B, Wu AW. Self-reported adherence to antiretroviral medications among participants in HIV clinical trials: the AACTG adherence instruments. Patient Care Committee &amp; Adherence Working Group of the Outcomes Committee of the Adult AIDS Clinical Trials Group (AACTG). AIDS Care. 2000 Jun;12(3):255-66.</citation>
    <PMID>10928201</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>R Amico K, McMahan V, Goicochea P, Vargas L, Marcus JL, Grant RM, Liu A. Supporting study product use and accuracy in self-report in the iPrEx study: next step counseling and neutral assessment. AIDS Behav. 2012 Jul;16(5):1243-59. doi: 10.1007/s10461-012-0182-5.</citation>
    <PMID>22460228</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fisher JD, Amico KR, Fisher WA, Harman JJ. The information-motivation-behavioral skills model of antiretroviral adherence and its applications. Curr HIV/AIDS Rep. 2008 Nov;5(4):193-203. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18838059</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fisher JD, Fisher WA, Amico KR, Harman JJ. An information-motivation-behavioral skills model of adherence to antiretroviral therapy. Health Psychol. 2006 Jul;25(4):462-73.</citation>
    <PMID>16846321</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uusküla A, Laisaar KT, Raag M, Šmidt J, Semjonova S, Kogan J, Amico KR, Sharma A, Dehovitz J. Antiretroviral therapy (ART) adherence and correlates to nonadherence among people on ART in Estonia. AIDS Care. 2012;24(12):1470-9. doi: 10.1080/09540121.2012.672724. Epub 2012 Apr 25.</citation>
    <PMID>22533736</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laisaar KT, Avi R, DeHovitz J, Uusküla A. Estonia at the threshold of the fourth decade of the AIDS era in Europe. AIDS Res Hum Retroviruses. 2011 Aug;27(8):841-51. doi: 10.1089/AID.2010.0223. Epub 2011 Jan 11.</citation>
    <PMID>21142588</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 8, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 8, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Tartu</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Anneli Uusküla</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Epidemiology, Department of Public Health</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Antiretroviral Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Adherence</keyword>
  <keyword>Intervention</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
