<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="75439">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01765244</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CAH/Ulc/2010</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2010-024290-40</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01765244</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Allogeneic Tissue Engineering (Nanostructured Artificial Human Cornea) in Patients With Corneal Trophic Ulcers in Advanced Stages, Refractory to Conventional (Ophthalmic) Treatment</brief_title>
  <official_title>Multicenter Clinical Trial to Evaluate the Safety and Feasibility of an Allogeneic Tissue Engineered Drug (Nanostructured Artificial Human Cornea) in Patients With Corneal Trophic Ulcers Refractory to Conventional Treatment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fundación Pública Andaluza Progreso y Salud</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Iniciativa Andaluza en Terapias Avanzadas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fundación Pública Andaluza Progreso y Salud</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Spain: Agencia Española de Medicamentos y Productos Sanitarios</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Phase I- II clinical trial to evaluate the feasibility of the method and the absence of
      relevant side effects derived from product implant.

      HYPOTHESIS: Once designed the nanostructured artificial human corneas by the Tissue
      Engineering Group of the University of Granada, and after evaluating their suitable
      properties ex vivo and their in vivo utility by means of anterior lamellar keratoplasty in
      laboratory animals, it is necessary to proceed to clinical evaluation in human patients
      suffering from severe corneal pathology. The results obtained during pre-clinical study,
      both in laboratory and in experimental animals, suggest that nanostructured artificial human
      corneas could help to treat various corneal diseases that occur with any substance loss or
      serious structural alteration, with no relevant side effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Phase I-II, controlled, randomized, multicenter clinical trial. The total number of patients
      to be included is 20. In an initial phase, will be included 5 patients sequentially (be
      subjected to the experimental treatment), with a month and a half safety period between
      patients.

      At random, 5 of these patients will be implanted cornea and 10 control patients will receive
      conventional treatment of corneal trophic ulcers in advanced stages.

      The study population consists of patients with corneal trophic ulcers refractory to
      conventional treatment attending the ophthalmology departments involved in this research
      project.

      It is estimated that the inclusion period is approximately 24 months, and a follow-up period
      of 24 months for each patient. Thus the total duration of the study will be about 48 months
      from the inclusion of the first patient until the end of the follow-up period of the last
      patient included.

      To all patients enrolled in the trial, assigned to the experimental group will proceed to be
      implanted an anterior lamellar nanostructured artificial cornea with allogeneic cells from
      dead donors and biomaterials.

      The implant of this Advanced Therapy drug will cover defects or structural alterations
      existing in the affected cornea. In this phase of the study, it is aimed to assess the
      feasibility of the procedure and the biosafety of the implant once grafted in the patient's
      cornea.

      Patients who are randomized to the control group will be subjected to the usual treatment of
      their condition, consisting of amniotic membrane transplantation

      Once the artificial corneal graft or amniotic membrane transplantation in the affected eye
      is completed, will proceed with the monitoring and continuous assessment of each subject.
      For this, it will be used the usual revision methods used for the anterior pole of the
      eyeball in all hospitals involved in the study.

      Main objective: To evaluate the safety, feasibility and evidence of clinical efficacy of an
      anterior lamellar nanostructured artificial human cornea model, in a group of patients with
      severe corneal disease, for whom there are currently no effective therapeutic alternative.

      Secondary objectives:

        -  To generate lamellar nanostructured artificial human corneas of allogeneic origin of
           dead donor, from sclerocorneal limbus and agarose-fibrin biomaterials.

        -  To implant the nanostructured artificial human corneas of allogeneic origin of dead
           donor in a group of patients randomized to the experimental group, suffering from
           severe corneal pathology as a graft in the wound bed.

        -  To assess Biosecurity the nanostructured artificial human corneas of allogeneic origin
           of dead donor implanted in patients to rule out relevant adverse reactions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Appearance of adverse events and serious adverse events related to treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Persistence of the ulcer or regeneration / repair of the corneal stroma.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual acuity.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Corneal transparency</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Corneal Ulcer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Anterior lamellar nanostructured artificial human cornea</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Anterior lamellar nanostructured artificial human cornea  with  allogenic from dead donor  and cultured in its inside and allogeneic corneal epithelium cultured in its surface</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Amniotic membrane transplantation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Amniotic membrane transplantation as conventional treatment of corneal trophic ulcers.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anterior lamellar nanostructured artificial human cornea.</intervention_name>
    <description>Implantation of an anterior lamellar nanostructured artificial human cornea with allogeneic cells from dead donors and biomaterials</description>
    <arm_group_label>Anterior lamellar nanostructured artificial human cornea</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who give informed consent to participate in the study.

          -  Presence of corneal ulcers Mackie stage 3 not responding to conventional medical
             treatment, besides being secondary to any of the specified causes : Riley-Day
             syndrome, Goldenhar-Gorlin syndrome, Mobius Syndrome, Corneal hypoesthesia family,
             Diabetes, Multiple Sclerosis, Leprosy, Hypovitaminosis A, Acoustic neuroma,
             Meningioma, Neuralgia, Aneurysm, Ictus, Neoplasia, Simple herpes, Zoster herpes,
             Caustic burns, Injury, inflammation, or wear contact lenses, Cataract surgery or
             keratoplasty, Topical anesthetics abuse, Toxicity of timolol, betaxolol, diclofenac
             sodium or sulfacetamide, Lattice or granular, Orbital neoplasia.

          -  Stromal involvement should exist, but with a depth not reaching the Descemet's
             membrane. The location may be central and / or peripheral.

          -  No active ocular infection.

          -  Patients of both sexes over 18 years; no upper age limit exist

          -  Duration of the disease causing the corneal ulcer equal or superior to six weeks.

          -  Patients with normal laboratory parameters, defined by:

               1. Leukocytes ≥ 3000

               2. Neutrophils ≥ 1500

               3. Platelets ≥ 100,000

               4. Aspartate Aminotransferase (AST) / Alanine Aminotransferase (ALT) ≤ 1.5 standard
                  range institution

               5. Creatinine ≤ 1.5 mg / dl

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Absence of stromal involvement (eg persistent epithelial defects).

          -  Corneal Pathology responding properly to standard medical treatments in a shorter
             period of 3-5 weeks.

          -  Active ocular infection.

          -  Positive serology for Hepatitis B virus (HBV), Hepatitis B virus (HCV),
             Immunodeficiency human virus (HIV) or other coexisting pathology that, in the opinion
             of the investigator, would prevent from monitoring patients in the trial.

          -  Pregnant or lactating women or women of childbearing potential not using a proven
             efficacy contraceptive method. It is described as highly effective contraceptive
             method that oral contraceptive one (combining estrogen with progestin) or any other
             such as, for example, an injectable hormonal contraceptive, implantable or patch,
             intrauterine device (IUD) or surgical sterilization (provided that hormonal
             contraceptives do not interact with the drug in research

          -  History of neoplasia except for orbital neoplasia.

          -  Patients who participated in the last 3 months prior to study inclusion in a clinical
             trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Miguel González, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital San Cecilio</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Miguel Alaminos, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Universidad de Granada</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ana Cardesa</last_name>
    <phone>0034 955019040</phone>
    <email>ana.cardesa@juntadeandalucia.es</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Puerta del Mar</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cádiz</city>
        <zip>11009</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Belén Hoyos, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>660409473</phone>
      <email>belenhoyossanabria@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Belén Hoyos, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>María Jesús Cruz, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Leticia Royo, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Iratze Zabalza, Zabalza</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital San Cecilio</name>
      <address>
        <city>Granada</city>
        <zip>18012</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Miguel González, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>636362952</phone>
      <email>mgandrades@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Miguel González, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Daniel Serrano, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Inmaculada Domínguez, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carmen González, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>José Ignacio Muñoz, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>José Luis García, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alberto Villarrubia, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Virgen de las Nieves</name>
      <address>
        <city>Granada</city>
        <zip>18014</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Santiago Medialdea, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>619271254</phone>
      <email>santiago.medialdea.sspa@juntadeandalucia.es</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Santiago Medialdea, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Daniel Martínez, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>José Lucena, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Virgen de Rocío</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <zip>41013</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Juan Ramón del Trigo, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>630926841</phone>
      <email>deltrigo@telefonica.net</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Juan Ramón del Trigo, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ana María Muñoz, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carmen Vázquez, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Virgen Macarena</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <zip>41009</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ignacio Montero, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>955008696</phone>
      <email>l_morillo@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>María Dolores Morillo, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.juntadeandalucia.es/terapiasavanzadas/</url>
    <description>Andalusian Initiative for Advanced Therapies</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cabimer.es</url>
    <description>Andalusian Molecular Biology and Regenerative Medicine Centre</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 9, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 9, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Corneal trophic ulcers</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Corneal Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
