<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="36663">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01688921</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PJ-501-12-2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01688921</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Jet Injection for Influenza</brief_title>
  <acronym>JIFI</acronym>
  <official_title>Jet Injection for Influenza: A Randomized Controlled Clinical Trial to Demonstrate Non Inferiority of Jet Injection vs. Needle and Syringe for Administration of Trivalent Inactivated Influenza Vaccine</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>PharmaJet, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>PharmaJet, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine if the administration of a seasonal flu vaccine
      using a PharmaJet's needle-free injection device (STRATIS) is equivalent to needle and
      syringe administration, as measured by laboratory tests of immune response.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti influenza type A/H1N1 Hemagglutination Inhibition (HAI) antibody Geometric Mean Titer (GMT)</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti influenza type A/H3N2 HAI antibody GMT</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti influenza type B HAI antibody GMT</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti influenza type A/H1N1 seroconversion</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Seroconversion is defined as a 4-fold rise in HAI titer in post-immunization serum relative to pre-immunization serum, or if pre-immunization serum had an undetectable titer (&lt;1:10), attainment of a post-immunization titer of ≥1:40.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti influenza type A/H3N2 seroconversion</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Seroconversion is defined as a 4-fold rise in HAI titer in post-immunization serum relative to pre-immunization serum, or if pre-immunization serum had an undetectable titer (&lt;1:10), attainment of a post-immunization titer of ≥1:40.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti influenza type B seroconversion</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Seroconversion is defined as a 4-fold rise in HAI titer in post-immunization serum relative to pre-immunization serum, or if pre-immunization serum had an undetectable titer (&lt;1:10), attainment of a post-immunization titer of ≥1:40.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with immediate complaints</measure>
    <time_frame>30 minutes</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The following possible immediate complaints will be solicited following the 30 minute safety observation period post-vaccination:  pain at injection site, tenderness at injection site, redness, induration/swelling (lump), bruising, itching where the injection is given. The data will be reported as &quot;immediate complaints&quot; and presumed to be related to the test article. Any other symptom experienced at 30 minutes is to be recorded as an adverse event.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with vaccine reactogenicity events</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Vaccine reactogenicity will be collected on a patient-completed diary card during checkout from Day 0 and on the next six evenings post-vaccination.  The following adverse events will be solicited on the diary card: pain at injection site, tenderness at injection site, redness where the injection is given; induration/swelling (lump) where the injection is given; bruising where the injection is given; itching where the injection is given; headache; tiredness/fatigue (asthenia, lethargy, malaise); general muscle ache (myalgia); chills; nausea; vomiting. Subjects will also record their oral temperature on the diary card each evening.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with spontaneously reported adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Subjects will be asked to report any other symptoms experienced in addition to the solicited &quot;immediate&quot; and &quot;vaccine reactogenicity&quot; events.  Any other events reported will be tabulated as spontaneously reported adverse events.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1252</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza, Human</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>STRATIS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients assigned to this arm will receive AFLURIA vaccine administered using the STRATIS needle-free injection device.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Needle-Syringe</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients assigned to this arm will receive AFLURIA vaccine administered using a needle and syringe.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AFLURIA vaccine (2012-2013 formulation)</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive a single 0.5 mL injection of AFLURIA vaccine in the deltoid region.</description>
    <arm_group_label>STRATIS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Needle-Syringe</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>trivalent inactivated influenza vaccine (TIV)</other_name>
    <other_name>influenza virus vaccine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Needle-Syringe</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Needle-Syringe</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>STRATIS needle-free injection device</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>STRATIS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults aged ≥18 and ≤64 years of age at the time of enrollment

          -  Willing and able to give informed consent after reading the consent form and adequate
             opportunity to discuss the study with the investigator or qualified designee

          -  Willing and able to adhere to all protocol required study procedures and to attend
             scheduled visits.

          -  Able to receive the TIV influenza vaccine, based on UCH employee health flu screening
             guidelines.

          -  Stable health status with no exclusionary medical or neuropsychiatric conditions as
             determined during the screening evaluation and based on the clinical judgment of the
             investigator or qualified designee.

          -  Access to a consistent means of telephone contact

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of any febrile illness (oral temperature &gt;38°C) on the day of immunization.
             Such subjects will be reevaluated for enrollment after resolution of illness.

          -  Presence of significant acute or chronic uncontrolled medical or neuropsychiatric
             illness and /or presence of any significant condition that may prohibit inclusion as
             determined by the investigator or his qualified designee. Uncontrolled is defined as:
             requiring institution of a new treatment within 1 month prior to study enrollment or
             change in medication dosage in the month prior to study enrollment.

          -  Any immunosuppressive condition including: history of HIV infection, cancer or cancer
             treatment within 3 years of study enrollment, systemic glucocorticoids (in a dose ≥10
             mg prednisone daily or equivalent for more than 7 consecutive days or for 10 or more
             days in total) within 1 month of study enrollment, or any other cytotoxic or
             immunosuppressive drug within 3 months of study enrollment. Any significant disorder
             of coagulation that would increase the risk of intramuscular injections or treatment
             with Coumadin derivatives or heparin.

          -  Known or suspected to be allergic to eggs, chicken protein, gentamicin or influenza
             vaccine.

          -  History of severe or previous serious adverse reaction after an influenza
             vaccination.

          -  Receipt of any immunoglobulin and/or blood products within 3 months of immunization
             or planned administration of any of these products during the study period.

          -  Prior history of any demyelinating disease including Guillain-Barre syndrome.

          -  Presence of an active neurological disorder.

          -  History of significant alcohol or drug abuse within one year prior to study
             enrollment.

          -  Influenza vaccination or laboratory confirmed influenza infection within the previous
             six months before study vaccination or planned influenza vaccination during the study
             period.

          -  Planned administration of any non-influenza vaccines 30 days prior to the study or
             during the study period.

          -  Pregnant or plans to become pregnant during the study period.

          -  Currently enrolled in another vaccine or drug study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David K Cobb, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Rocky Mountain Infectious Disease Consultants</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Linda McAllister, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>PharmaJet, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Poudre Valley Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ft. Collins</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80524</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Health Harmony Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ft. Collins</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80528</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical Center of the Rockies</name>
      <address>
        <city>Loveland</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80538</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 17, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Injections, Jet</keyword>
  <keyword>Influenza Vaccines</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
