<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="41752">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01758224</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>W81XWH-11-1-0707</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01758224</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Expiratory Muscle Conditioning in Multiple Sclerosis Using Magnetic Stimulation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cleveland Clinic Research Program: Expiratory Muscle Conditioning Using Functional Magnetic Stimulation for Patients With Multiple Sclerosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Cleveland Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Department of Defense</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Cleveland Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Multiple sclerosis (MS) is a primary disorder of the central nervous system that may affect
      motor pathways and cause muscle weakness. Respiratory complications due to respiratory
      muscle weakness are common in the terminal stages of MS and contribute to mortality in these
      patients. Respiratory muscle weakness may also impair the performance of coughing and
      aspiration, pneumonia, or even acute ventilatory failure may ensue. Functional magnetic
      stimulation (FMS) is a non-invasive method that promotes the contraction of muscles through
      nerve activation. Over the last few years, the study investigators have demonstrated
      efficacy of FMS technology for stimulating respiratory muscles in animal models, able-bodied
      subjects [3] and spinal cord injured (SCI) patients [4]. In this study, the researchers will
      investigate the efficacy of using FMS technique for respiratory muscle conditioning in
      patients with MS. Furthermore, the investigators will also compare expiration related
      outcomes of FMS technique with resistive expiratory muscle training (REMT) methodology.

      Hypotheses

        1. FMS conditioning of the expiratory muscles can generate significant expiratory flows
           and pressures in patients with MS.

        2. FMS conditioning of expiratory muscles is more effective compared to resistive
           expiratory muscle training (REMT) in patients with MS.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Optimal respiratory function depends on intact neural circuitry which orchestrates the
      interplay between respiratory muscles and intrinsic pulmonary function to maintain adequate
      ventilation. In the absence of respiratory muscle activation, pressure gradients cannot be
      developed and air exchange at the alveolar surface cannot occur. Thus, any impairment in
      respiratory muscle performance can lead to pulmonary dysfunction, respiratory distress and
      even death. Multiple sclerosis (MS) is a primary disorder of the central nervous system that
      often affects motor pathways, causing diminished muscle strength and endurance throughout
      the body including the ventilatory muscles. Respiratory complications are recognized as the
      major cause of morbidity and mortality in individuals with advanced MS. The investigators'
      research team has over 15 years of experience using Functional Magnetic Stimulation (FMS)
      for stimulating nerves and muscles below the level of injury in patients with chronic SCI;
      and has also demonstrated significant benefit for improving respiratory muscles, bladder and
      bowel functions. In this study, the investigators will investigate the efficacy of using FMS
      technique for respiratory muscle conditioning in patients with multiple sclerosis; and will
      compare the results of the expired functions (volume, pressure, and flow) generated by using
      the FMS technique with data obtained from using the resistive expiratory muscle training
      (REMT) methodology.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulmonary Function Testing (PFT)</measure>
    <time_frame>At study initiation and every two weeks over a 14 week period (8 PFTs)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in participant's pulmonary (lung) function will be assessed using a non-invasive pulmonary function test (PFT).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">8</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Functional Magnetic Stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive magnetic stimulation of the respiratory (breathing) muscles that may improve the breathing function in subjects with MS.  The magnetic stimulation protocol (plan of study) consists of a daily expiratory (breathing out) muscle conditioning program (20 minutes).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Resistive Expiratory Muscle Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this group will perform breathing exercises using a resistive breathing device. The training will take place in the FMS lab. After training, participants will perform the exercise for 20 minutes daily (5days each week for 6 weeks) in their home.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Functional Magnetic Stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>The magnetic stimulation protocol (plan of study) consists of a daily expiratory (breathing out) muscle conditioning program (20 minutes). A magnetic coil will be placed on participant's back to stimulate the nerves related to the breathing function.  Each stimulation will last two seconds and the time between each stimulation is about half a minute.  The training session will begin with low intensity FMS for 20 minutes daily. The FMS stimulation intensity will gradually increase during the 6-week training period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Functional Magnetic Stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>FMS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Resistive Expiratory Muscle Training</intervention_name>
    <description>The REMT training will take place in the FMS lab using a standard resistive breathing device. After training, participants will perform the exercise for 20 minutes daily (5days each week for 6 weeks) in their home. Participants will wear a nose clip when performing the breathing exercise. The exercise protocol will begin with a low resistance level for 20 minutes a day. The resistance level will gradually increase during the 6-week training period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Resistive Expiratory Muscle Training</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>REMT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Multiple Sclerosis diagnosis

          -  Baseline maximal expiratory pressure (MEP) values between 50% and 70% of predicted
             values

          -  Patients must also be in stable condition and free of active brain disease or
             cardiovascular disorders (history of myocardial infarction, congestive heart disease,
             or uncontrolled hypertension).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Cardiac pacemakers, ferromagnetic metal implants, uncontrolled high blood pressure,
             active pulmonary conditions such as chronic obstructive pulmonary disease,
             bronchiectasis, asthma, and diaphragmatic paralysis.

          -  Patients who are ventilator dependent, with significant scoliosis, other chest wall
             deformity, obesity, severe diabetes mellitus, as well as pregnant women will be
             excluded from participating in the study.

          -  Patients with substance abuse or mental incompetence will also be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vernon W Lin, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Cleveland Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Vernon W Lin, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>216 445-7350</phone>
    <email>linv@ccf.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Xiaoming Zhang, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>216 445-7647</phone>
    <email>zhangx6@ccf.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Vernon W Lin, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>216-445-7350</phone>
      <email>linv@ccf.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Xiaoming Zhang, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>216 445-7647</phone>
      <email>zhangx6@ccf.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vernon W Lin, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Xiaoming Zhang, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lin VW, Hsiao IN, Zhu E, Perkash I. Functional magnetic stimulation for conditioning of expiratory muscles in patients with spinal cord injury. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2001 Feb;82(2):162-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11239305</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Singh H, Magruder M, Bushnik T, Lin VW. Expiratory muscle activation by functional magnetic stimulation of thoracic and lumbar spinal nerves. Crit Care Med. 1999 Oct;27(10):2201-5.</citation>
    <PMID>10548207</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 26, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 19, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Multiple Sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Functional Magnetic Stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary Function</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
