<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="119452">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02046070</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C16020</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-003113-17</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02046070</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 2 Study to Evaluate the Oral Combination of MLN9708 With Cyclophosphamide and Dexamethasone in Patients With Newly Diagnosed Multiple Myeloma (NDMM)</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label, Phase 2 Study to Evaluate the Oral Combination of MLN9708 With Cyclophosphamide and Dexamethasone in Patients With Newly Diagnosed Multiple Myeloma Requiring Systemic Treatment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase 2, multicenter, open-label study in patients with NDMM who have not received
      prior systemic treatment for multiple myeloma (MM) and who are ineligible for high-dose
      therapy (HDT)-SCT due to age (ie, ≥ 65 years) or comorbid disease(s).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Combined response rate of CR (including sCR) + VGPR in patients treated with MLN9708 when added to a standard care regimen of Cyclophosphamide and Dexamethasone (Cd) during the induction phase</measure>
    <time_frame>28-day cycles of treatment of MLN9708 + Cyclophosphamide on days 1, 8, 15 and Dexamethasone on days 1, 8, 15, 22 for approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All AEs, Grade 3 or higher AEs, AEs resulting in discontinuation, AEs resulting in dose reduction, serious adverse events (SAEs), and assessments of clinical laboratory values</measure>
    <time_frame>Recorded from the first dose of drug in the study drug regimen through 30 days after last dose of drug in the study drug regimen</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1-3, 5, 8, 15-17, 19 and 22 during cycle 1 and day 1 of cycle 2 (safety lead-in patients) or days 1, 8, 15, and 22 during cycles 1-3 (excluding safety lead-in)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Includes single-dose maximum (peak) concentration (Cmax), single-dose first time of occurrence of maximum (peak) concentration (Tmax), and area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ORR (Overall response rate, CR + VGPR + PR), CR, VGPR, and PR during the induction phase and throughout the entire study</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from the start of treatment to the occurrence of disease progression, unacceptable toxicities, discontinuation of study due to any other reasons, or end of study (EOS) up to 60 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Response (TTR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from the date of enrollment to the date of first documented response during induction phase up to 36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Response (DOR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Time interval from the date of first response to the date of disease progression up to 60 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Progression (TTP)</measure>
    <time_frame>Time interval from the date of enrollment to the date of first documented disease progression up to 60 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Time interval from the date of enrollment to the date of first documented disease progression or death up to 60 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AEs, SAEs, AEs resulting in discontinuation, AEs resulting in dose reduction in patients remaining on treatment after 13 cycles.</measure>
    <time_frame>From signing of the informed consent form through 30 days after the last dose of drug in the study drug regimen</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of change in global health status between baseline and each post-baseline assessment, as measured by the global health scale, functioning, and symptoms of the EORTC QLQ-C30 and MY-20</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 of each 28-day cycle</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ORR, CR, VGPR, and PR of single agent MLN9708 as maintenance therapy in patients remaining on treatment after 13 cycles</measure>
    <time_frame>From signing of the informed consent form through 30 days after the last dose of drug in the study drug regimen</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MLN9708 + 300mg/m^2 Cyclophosphamide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Induction: MLN9708 + Cyclophosphamide (300mg/m^2) + Dexamethasone. Maintenance: MLN9708.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MLN9708 + 400mg/m^2 Cyclophosphamide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Induction: MLN9708 + Cyclophosphamide (400mg/m^2) + Dexamethasone. Maintenance: MLN9708.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide (300mg/m^2)</intervention_name>
    <description>Induction. Days 1, 8, 15 and dexamethasone on days 1, 8, 15, 22. Repeat every 28 days for 13 cycles in the absence of progressive disease (PD)/death or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MLN9708 + 300mg/m^2 Cyclophosphamide</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide (400mg/m^2)</intervention_name>
    <description>Induction. Days 1, 8, 15 and dexamethasone on days 1, 8, 15, 22. Repeat every 28 days for 13 cycles in the absence of progressive disease (PD)/death or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MLN9708 + 400mg/m^2 Cyclophosphamide</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MLN9708</intervention_name>
    <description>Days 1, 8, 15 during 28-day cycles until PD/death or unacceptable toxicity</description>
    <arm_group_label>MLN9708 + 300mg/m^2 Cyclophosphamide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MLN9708 + 400mg/m^2 Cyclophosphamide</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>Days 1, 8, 15, 22. Repeat every 28 days for 13 cycles in the absence of progressive disease (PD)/death or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MLN9708 + 300mg/m^2 Cyclophosphamide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MLN9708 + 400mg/m^2 Cyclophosphamide</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult male or female patients 18 years of age or older with a confirmed diagnosis of
             symptomatic multiple myeloma (MM) according to standard criteria who have not
             received prior treatment for MM.

          2. Patients for whom cyclophosphamide and dexamethasone treatment is appropriate and who
             are considered not eligible for HDT-SCT for 1 or more of the following reasons:

               -  Patient is ≥ 65 years of age.

               -  Patient is ≤ 65 years of age but has significant comorbid condition(s) that are,
                  in the opinion of the investigator, likely to have a negative impact on
                  tolerability of HDT-SCT.

          3. Measurable disease as defined in the protocol.

          4. Meets clinical laboratory values as defined in the protocol.

          5. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status of 0, 1, or 2.

          6. Female patients who are post menopausal, surgically sterile, or agree to practice 2
             effective methods of contraception or agree to practice true abstinence.

             Male patients who agree to practice effective barrier contraception or agree to
             practice true abstinence.

          7. Voluntary written consent.

          8. Suitable venous access for the study-required blood sampling.

          9. Patient is willing and able to adhere to the study visit schedule and other protocol
             requirements.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patients meeting any of the following exclusion criteria are not to be randomized to
        treatment:

          1. Prior treatment for multiple myeloma with either standard of care treatment or
             investigational regimen.

          2. Diagnosis of smoldering MM, Waldenstrom's macroglobulinemia, POEMS (polyneuropathy,
             organomegaly, endocrinopathy, monoclonal gammopathy, and skin changes) syndrome,
             plasma cell leukemia, primary amyloidosis, myelodysplastic syndrome, or
             myeloproliferative syndrome.

          3. Central nervous system involvement.

          4. Diagnosed or treated for another malignancy within 2 years before the first dose or
             previously diagnosed with another malignancy and have any evidence of residual
             disease. Patients with nonmelanoma skin cancer or carcinoma in situ of any type are
             not excluded if they have undergone complete resection.

          5. Peripheral neuropathy Grade 1 with pain or ≥ Grade 2 of any cause.

          6. Known GI disease or GI procedure that could interfere with the oral absorption or
             tolerance of study drug, including difficulty swallowing.

          7. Infection requiring IV antibiotic therapy or other serious infection within 14 days
             before the first dose of study drug.

          8. Ongoing or active infection, known HIV positive, active hepatitis B or C infection

          9. Systemic treatment with strong inhibitors of CYP1A2 or CYP3A, or strong CYP3A
             inducers, or use of Ginkgo biloba or St. John's wort within 14 days before the first
             dose of study treatment.

         10. Known allergy to any of the study medications, their analogues, or excipients in the
             various formulations.

         11. Major surgery within 14 days before the first dose of study drug.

         12. Female patients who are lactating and breastfeeding or pregnant.

         13. Serious medical or psychiatric illness that could, in the investigator's opinion,
             potentially interfere with the completion of treatment according to the protocol.

         14. Comorbid systemic illnesses or other severe concurrent disease which, in the judgment
             of the investigator, would make the patient inappropriate for entry into this study
             or interfere significantly with the proper assessment of safety and toxicity of the
             prescribed regimens.

         15. Treatment with any investigational products for reasons other than MM within 30 days
             before the first dose of study drug.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Monitor</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>For an updated listing of recruitment sites contact: Millennium Medical and Drug Information Center</last_name>
    <phone>1-877-674-3784</phone>
    <email>medical@mlnm.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <state>Attiki</state>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Stockholm</city>
        <state>Sodermanlands lan</state>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Lund</city>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Greece</country>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 9, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>MLN9708</keyword>
  <keyword>Newly diagnosed</keyword>
  <keyword>NDMM</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone 21-phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
