<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="84182">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02145949</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12272013.024</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01AG046401</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02145949</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mechanistic Approach to Preventing Atrophy and Restoring Function in Older Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>Mechanistic Approach to Preventing Atrophy and Restoring Function in Older Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oregon</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Slocum Center for Orthopedics and Sports Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Slocum Research and Education Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oregon Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oregon Health and Science University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Arkansas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oregon</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      As a function of the investigators growing population of older adults, an estimated 3.48
      million total knee arthroplasty (TKA) procedures will be performed annually in the U.S. by
      2030. Despite the near-universal success of this surgery in mitigating chronic knee pain,
      TKA is not successful in restoring long-term physical function in older adults, primarily
      because of quadriceps muscle atrophy, which explains 77% of the strength deficits. Overall,
      strength and functional mobility in TKA patients is 30-50% below age-matched healthy
      controls. Functional tasks such as stair-climbing, which is considered a high fall-risk
      activity, remain a clinical problem for 75% of patients following TKA. Muscle atrophy occurs
      in both operative and non-operative legs, and is essentially permanent for older patients
      because their ability to increase muscle mass is significantly impaired. Thus, safe and
      effective treatments to prevent muscle loss and preserve strength are urgently needed and
      clinically meaningful, as they have the potential to significantly impact the quality of
      life for millions of older adults. The purpose of the proposed clinical research is to
      determine the effects of essential amino acid (EAA) supplementation on muscle mass,
      strength, and functional mobility following TKA in older adults. The investigators
      hypothesis, based on strong preliminary data, is that twice-daily ingestion of 20 g of EAA
      for 1 wk before through 6 wk after TKA will increase basal rates of muscle protein synthesis
      via inactivation of catabolic signaling, and up-regulation of anabolic and cyto-protective
      proteins. The investigators  further hypothesize that short-term atrophy prevention and
      accelerated return of functional mobility will lead to longer-term structural and functional
      adaptations, and improved quality of life in older TKA patients vs. Placebo. The rationale
      for the proposed research is that effective treatments to prevent muscle atrophy after
      increasingly common TKA surgery will result in short- and longer-term muscle cell
      adaptations that boost functional mobility and quality of life. Identifying the mechanisms
      up-regulated by EAA treatment that preserve muscle volume and mobility will have a major
      impact on rehabilitation science. The proposed research will empirically test the
      investigators hypotheses by accomplishing two specific aims: (1) determine if EAA elevates
      basal rates of muscle protein synthesis by up-regulating anabolic pathways and
      cyto-protective proteins, and inactivating catabolic pathways in the short term vs. Placebo
      and (2) determine if short-term prevention of atrophy, weakness, and functional mobility
      leads to positive changes in muscle cell structure and function, and improved quality of
      life (WOMAC &amp; SF-36) in the longer term vs. Placebo. The proposed work is significant
      because it advances knowledge of the molecular and cellular changes occurring during muscle
      atrophy (Placebo) and atrophy prevention (EAA) in a clinical setting using a treatment that
      is broadly applicable, is well tolerated, and can be implemented immediately.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Lower Extremity Muscle Volume</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 6 months, and 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will measure volumetric muscle volume using MRI</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Functional Mobility</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 6 months, and 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will measure the change in timed up and go (TUG)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Functional Mobility</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 6 months, and 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will measure the change in timed stair ascent</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Functional Mobility</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 6 months, and 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will measure the change in timed stair descent</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Functional Mobility</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 6 months, and 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will measure the change in the distance covered in 6 minutes (6 minute walk test)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Short Physical Performance Battery (SPPB)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 6 months, and 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will measure the change in SPPB</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Muscle Atrophy</condition>
  <condition>Functional Mobility</condition>
  <condition>Quality of Life</condition>
  <condition>Patient Activation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EAA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Twice-daily ingestion of 20 g of EAA for 1 wk before through 6 wk after TKA. Supplement composition for the EAAs: histidine, 2.2 g (11% of total); isoleucine, 2.0 g (10%); leucine, 3.6 g (18%); lysine, 3.2 g (16%); methionine, 0.6 g (3%); phenylalanine, 3.2 g (16%); threonine, 2.8 g (14%); and valine, 2.4 g (12%).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Twice-daily ingestion of 20 g of Alanine (Non-essential amino acid)  for 1 wk before through 6 wk after TKA.
The placebo supplement consists of 20 g (100%) alanine.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EAA</intervention_name>
    <description>Twice daily ingestion of 20 grams of EAA for 7 days leading up to surgery and continuing for 6 weeks after surgery [surgery = primary total knee arthroplasty]</description>
    <arm_group_label>EAA</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>L-Histidine, H3911</other_name>
    <other_name>L-Isoleucine, I5281</other_name>
    <other_name>L-Leucine, L6914</other_name>
    <other_name>L-Lysine monohydrochloride, L7039</other_name>
    <other_name>L-Methionine, M8349</other_name>
    <other_name>L-Phenylalanine, P8740</other_name>
    <other_name>L-Threonine, T4071</other_name>
    <other_name>L-Valine, V4638</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Twice daily ingestion of 20 grams Placebo (alanine) for 7 days leading up to surgery and continuing for 6 weeks after surgery [surgery = primary total knee arthroplasty]</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>L-Alanine, A4349 (Non-essential amino acid)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age: between 60-80 years.

          -  Primary TKA surgery.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Previous TKA and/or total hip arthroplasty surgery (older subjects).

          2. Dementia or related mental issues that may potentially put the subject at risk as
             determined by the surgeon.

          3. Untreated endocrine disease (Hypo/Hyperthyroidism, Addison's or Cushing's syndrome,
             etc.).

          4. Significant heart, liver, kidney, blood, or respiratory disease.

          5. Peripheral vascular disease.

          6. Active cancer.

          7. Recent (within 6 months) treatment with anabolic steroids.

          8. Alcohol or drug abuse.

          9. Inability to have MRI
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Erin Owen, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>541-868-3232</phone>
    <email>erin.owen@slocumfoundation.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <link>
    <url>http://muscle.uoregon.edu</url>
    <description>Muscle Physiology Lab at the University of Oregon</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dreyer HC, Strycker LA, Senesac HA, Hocker AD, Smolkowski K, Shah SN, Jewett BA. Essential amino acid supplementation in patients following total knee arthroplasty. J Clin Invest. 2013 Nov 1;123(11):4654-66. doi: 10.1172/JCI70160. Epub 2013 Oct 25.</citation>
    <PMID>24135139</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 28, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 19, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Oregon</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hans Dreyer</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Muscular Atrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atrophy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
