<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="82356">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01975948</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDHA-RS/2014-150</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01975948</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of a Mental Health Physician Support Program in Nova Scotia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of a Mental Health Physician Support Program in Nova Scotia: Impact on Patient Outcomes and Stigmatization</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Capital District Health Authority, Canada</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Capital District Health Authority, Canada</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Ethics Review Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Department of Health and Wellness (DHW), along with key stakeholders, are ready to
      launch a demonstration project for another deliverable of the province's mental health and
      addictions strategy, &quot;Together We Can&quot;. The demonstration project is for the Adult Mental
      Health Module of the Practice Support Program (PSP), a training program for family
      physicians developed by family physicians.

      The investigators will be completing a randomized control trial to determine the
      program/tools effectiveness, its power to reduce stigma and its ability to increase the
      comfort level of physicians in providing treatment to those living with mental illness in a
      primary care setting.

      110 Nova Scotia family physicians along with their medical office assistants administrative
      assistants/secretaries will participate to evaluate this program before deciding on whether
      or not it will be implemented on a more permanent basis in Nova Scotia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>• Change from Baseline to study end-point of the Patient Health Questionnaire-9(PHQ-9)score in patients</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 2, 3, and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The PHQ-9, developed by Drs. Robert L. Spitzer, Janet B.W. Williams specifically for primary care settings is a self-report instrument which takes only a few minutes to complete. The tool is highly sensitive and specific for the diagnosis of depression, and covers the nine symptom-based DSM-IV (Diagnostic and Statistical Manual) and DSM-5 criteria for major depression. It can also produce dimensional symptom severity ratings. The scale covers a two week time frame, essentially covering current rather than past episodes. The PHQ-9 has been extensively validated and is widely used in primary care as a screening instrument and for monitoring treatment outcomes. A PHQ-9 score &gt;10 has a sensitivity for major depression of 88%, and a specificity of 88%, and a positive likelihood ratio of 7.1.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lam's Employment Absence and Productivity Scale (LEAPS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2,3, and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>As a measure of occupational functioning, Lam's Employment Absence and Productivity Scale (LEAPS) will be used  . This scale was developed in Canada to assess the workplace impact of major depression.  LEAPS displayed excellent internal consistency as assessed by Cronbach's alpha:  0.89. During scale development, validity was assessed by comparing the LEAPS to the other clinical and work functioning scales, where it showed excellent concordant validity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Health Care Costs Comparison</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and at 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>For the purposes of quantifying economic impacts, the Client Service Receipt Inventory will be used  . This is a well-used and extensively validated inventory.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Primary Care Physician Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Primary Care Treatment as Usual</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Adult Mental Health Training practice support program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Primary Care  Mental Health Training and Support Program</intervention_name>
    <description>The principal components of the program include: (1) training and (2) practice support.
Training is delivered in three half day workshop-style sessions conducted over a 24 week period.
Practice support is two-fold
Through 3 tools which provide an Assessment tool and 3 different evidence based Supported Self Management tools : 1.  The Cognitive Behavioral Interpersonal Skills Manual  2. The Bounceback program led by the Canadian Mental Health Association, British Columbia Division, which consists of a telephone delivered evidence-based skills program designed to help adults experiencing symptoms of mild to moderate depression 3. The Antidepressant Skills Workbook for patients with mild and moderate depression.
Through a practice support coordinator to ensure participants receive as much benefit as possible throughout the training period and have the guidance they need to incorporate newly acquired tools, skills, and processes into their every-day practice workflow</description>
    <arm_group_label>Primary Care Physician Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Adult Mental Health Training practice support program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:To be eligible, patients must

        have been identified as depressed by a physician-participant in the trial and must have a
        PHQ-9 score of &gt; 10 at the time of enrollment.

        be over the age of 18

        be able to read and speak in English

        have sufficiently intact cognitive functioning, according to the judgment of the physician

        be free of urgent or emergent medical or psychiatric issues such as unstable
        cardiovascular disease or suicidal ideation potentially requiring hospitalization.

        -

        Exclusion Criteria:

        not currently under treatment for depression either with an antidepressant medication or
        psychotherapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bianca A Lauria-Horner, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Associate Professor Dalhousie University Department of Psychiatry</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bianca A Lauria-Horner, MD</last_name>
    <phone>902-473-5633</phone>
    <email>hornerb@dal.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dalhousie University Department of Psychiatry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Halifax</city>
        <state>Nova Scotia</state>
        <zip>B3H2E2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 29, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 21, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mental Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Education and practice Support Program</keyword>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Primary Care</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
