<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="73714">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01690143</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CTO 101669</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>Onyx IST-CAR-536</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01690143</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Carfilzomib + High Dose Melphalan as Preparative Regimen for Autologous Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 1/2A Study Carfilzomib + High Dose Melphalan as Preparative Regimen for Autologous Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation in Multiple Myeloma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical University of South Carolina</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Onyx Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of South Carolina</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is for patients that have multiple myeloma that has come back or relapsed and
      their condition indicates a procedure called an Autologous Hematopoietic Stem Cell
      Transplantation (AHSCT). AHSCT is a procedure when stem cells from bone marrow or blood are
      removed before high-dose chemotherapy. Afterwards, the removed stem cells are put back into
      the patient's body to form a new population of blood cells.

      The high-dose chemotherapy administered before the AHSCT is called &quot;Conditioning Therapy.&quot;
      The FDA has approved the use of the drug melphalan as a conditioning therapy. This research
      study will look at whether adding the study drug called carfilzomib will improve participant
      outcomes. Carfilzomib is considered investigational and is not approved by the FDA for the
      treatment of relapsed multiple myeloma.

      This study is divided into two phases.

      Phase I: Dose Escalation Phase:

      The main purpose of Part I of this study is to examine the safety of the study drug,
      carfilzomib, and determine the safest amount of the study drug that can be given to subjects
      who have multiple myeloma. Subjects on this study will receive different dose levels of the
      study drug. If you are one of the first three subjects to receive the study drug, it will be
      at what is called the 'starting dose' for the study which is the lowest dose that is
      expected to be tolerated based on prior research. After the first set of participants
      receive the study drug, the study doctor will review their health to see how they are
      tolerating the treatment. This will decide if the study drug dosage will be increased or
      decreased for the next set of subjects who join the study.  It is anticipated that 12- 18
      participants will enroll in the Phase I portion of this study.

      Phase II: Safety Confirmation Phase:

      Once the study doctor has discovered the highest possible dose of study drug that subjects
      can tolerate, up to 28 more subjects may be enrolled at that dose level. The main purpose of
      the Phase II portion of the study is look at how effective the combination of carfilzomib
      and melphalan when given before your stem cell transplantation is in treating multiple
      myeloma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase 1/2a trial. Since this is an AHSCT conditioning regimen trial, only one
      cycle of therapy will be administered for each subject.

      PHASE 1 The phase 1 component has a typical 3+3 design.

        -  Initially up to three subjects will be enrolled in each cohort starting at cohort 0 in
           the table below.

        -  If no dose limiting toxicity (DLT) is noted among the 3 initial subjects, 3 additional
           patients will be accrued at the subsequent cohort.

        -  If 1/3 subjects experience DLT, 3 additional subjects will be accrued at the cohort. If
           no additional DLT occur, accrual will continue at the subsequent cohort.

        -  If 2 or more subjects experience DLT in a given cohort, the dose will be considered
           higher than the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) and the immediately lower dose will be
           considered the MTD.

        -  If accrual is completed in cohort 4 with 0/3 or 1/6 DLT, the MTD will be considered
           &quot;not reached&quot; and cohort 4 will be expanded in the phase 2 of the trial.

        -  If 2 subjects experience DLTs in cohort 0, patients will be accrued in cohort -1, one
           subject at a time, with the subsequent subject only being accrued once the current
           subject has completed the DLT period (transplant day 30). The doses in cohort -1 will
           be considered the MTD if 0/3 or 1/6 subjects experience DLT.

        -  If ≥ 2 subjects experience DLT in cohort -1 the study will be interrupted without
           proceeding to phase 2a and the combination of carfilzomib and high dose melphalan will
           be considered too toxic.

      PHASE 2 Once the MTD for the combination of carfilzomib and high dose melphalan with AHSCT
      is found, there will be expansion of the MTD cohort so that 28 individuals will be treated
      at the MTD of carfilzomib and high dose melphalan.

      Screening - Subjects likely to meet eligibility criteria will be offered participation in
      the study after the investigator verifies with the registration system that there is a
      current available slot (phase 1).  Subjects will sign informed consent prior to any protocol
      associated procedure. Screening procedures are outlined in Table 3 and will 1) ensure that
      subject meets all the eligibility criteria, 2) obtain disease assessment to allow efficacy
      measurements, 3) assess baseline toxicity and 4) provide initial biological samples for
      pharmacodynamic and correlative studies.

      Treatment- Subjects will receive the appropriate dose of carfilzomib (according to assigned
      cohort in phase 1 and at the determined MTD in phase 2) on days -3 and -2. Carfilzomib will
      be infused over 30 minutes. On day -2, with 60 to 120 minutes of the end of infusion of
      carfilzomib, subjects will receive 200 mg/m2 of intravenous melphalan as an intravenous push
      or a fast infusion, according to institutional standard operating procedure (SOP).
      Prophylaxis of chemotherapy induced nausea and vomiting will follow institutional guidelines
      and SOPs.

      Infusion of autologous cells- Infusion of autologous hematopoietic stem cells will occur on
      day 0 and follow institutional SOP.

      Follow up phase - On day 1 following HSCT patients will receive pegfilgrastim 6 mg
      subcutaneously as per institutional standard of care aiming at faster engraftment. The
      follow up phase will last 100 days and will consist of standard post transplantation
      supportive care and monitoring of AEs. For the phase 1 component of the study, dose-limiting
      toxicities will be captured during the first 30 days after transplantation (DLT period).

      Disease assessment- Disease assessment will occur at day 100 (+/- 7 days) and will consist
      of serum protein electrophoresis, serum and urine immunofixation, 24h urine protein
      electrophoresis, serum free light chains, bone marrow aspiration and biopsy, complete blood
      counts and metabolic panel.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the  Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD) of carfilzomib plus melphalans conditioning for AHSCT in patients with relapsed Multiple Myeloma(MM) [Phase I portion of study]</measure>
    <time_frame>4 1/2 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate efficacy of carfilzomib plus melphalan conditioning in patients with relapsed MM</measure>
    <time_frame>4 1/2 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate toxicity and tolerability of carfilzomib plus melphalan conditioning in patients with relapsed MM.</measure>
    <time_frame>4 1/2 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To investigate the pharmacodynamic effects of carfilzomib + high dose melphalan in terms of changes in expression of fanconi anemia/BRCA DNA repair genes and DNA fragmentation</measure>
    <time_frame>4 1/2 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">58</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Carfilzomib + high dose melphalan</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single arm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carfilzomib</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will receive the appropriate dose of carfilzomib (according to assigned cohort in phase 1 and at the determined MTD in phase 2) on days -3 and -2. Carfilzomib will be infused over 30 minutes. On day -2, with 60 to 120 minutes of the end of infusion of carfilzomib, subjects will receive 200 mg/m2 of intravenous melphalan as an intravenous push or a fast infusion, according to institutional standard operating procedure (SOP). Prophylaxis of chemotherapy induced nausea and vomiting will follow institutional guidelines and SOPs.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Carfilzomib + high dose melphalan</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≥ 18 years and ≤ 70 years

          2. Life expectancy ≥ 12 months

          3. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0-2

          4. Diagnosis of symptomatic multiple myeloma38, relapsed after initial therapy.

          5. At least minimal response (defined as 25% decrease in the M protein in serum or
             urine) to the most recent treatment regimen.

          6. Evaluable disease prior to most recent treatment regimen as defined by at least one
             of the following:

               -  Serum monoclonal (M) protein ≥0.5 g/dl by protein electrophoresis

                    -  200 mg of M protein in the urine on 24 hour electrophoresis

               -  Serum immunoglobulin free light chain ≥10 mg/dL AND abnormal serum
                  immunoglobulin kappa to lambda free light chain ratio

               -  Monoclonal bone marrow plasmacytosis ≥30%

          7. Adequate hepatic function, with serum ALT ≤ 3.5 times the upper limit of normal and
             serum direct bilirubin ≤ 2 mg/dL (34 µmol/L) within 14 days prior to start of therapy

          8. Hemoglobin ≥ 8 g/dL (80 g/L) within 14 days prior to start of therapy (subjects may
             be receiving red blood cell [RBC] transfusions in accordance with institutional
             guidelines)

          9. Creatinine clearance (CrCl) ≥ 40 mL/minute within 14 days prior to start of therapy,
             either measured or calculated using a standard formula (eg, Cockcroft and Gault).

         10. Prior storage of at least 2 x 106 CD34+ cells/kg available for autologous
             transplantation. During the phase 1 component of the study, at least the same amount
             of cells is required as &quot;back up&quot; in the unlikely event of non-engraftment.

         11. Subjects may have had a prior AHSCT for the treatment of MM as long as it was
             performed greater than 12 months from study registration.

         12. Subjects must meet institutional general eligibility criteria for autologous
             transplantation.

         13. Written informed consent in accordance with federal, local, and institutional
             guidelines.

         14. Female of childbearing potential (FCBP) must agree to ongoing pregnancy testing and
             to practice contraception.

         15. Male subjects must agree to practice contraception.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant or lactating females.

          2. Major surgery within 30 days prior to start of treatment.

          3. Acute active infection requiring treatment (systemic antibiotics, antivirals, or
             antifungals) within 14 days prior to randomization.

          4. Known human immunodeficiency virus infection.

          5. Active hepatitis B or C infection.

          6. Unstable angina or myocardial infarction within 4 months prior to randomization, NYHA
             Class III or IV heart failure, uncontrolled angina, history of severe coronary artery
             disease, severe uncontrolled ventricular arrhythmias, sick sinus syndrome, or
             electrocardiographic evidence of acute ischemia or Grade 3 conduction system
             abnormalities unless subject has a pacemaker.

          7. Uncontrolled hypertension or uncontrolled diabetes within 14 days prior to
             randomization.

          8. Nonhematologic malignancy within the past 3 years with the exception of a) adequately
             treated basal cell carcinoma, squamous cell skin cancer, or thyroid cancer; b)
             carcinoma in situ of the cervix or breast; c) prostate cancer of Gleason Grade 6 or
             less with stable prostate-specific antigen levels; or d) cancer considered cured by
             surgical resection or unlikely to impact survival during the duration of the study,
             such as localized transitional cell carcinoma of the bladder or benign tumors of the
             adrenal or pancreas.

          9. Significant neuropathy (Grades 3-4, or Grade 2 with pain) within 14 days prior to
             randomization.

         10. Known history of allergy to Captisol® (a cyclodextrin derivative used to solubilize
             carfilzomib).

         11. Subjects with pleural effusions requiring thoracentesis or ascites requiring
             paracentesis within 14 days prior to randomization.

         12. Any other clinically significant medical disease or condition that, in the
             Investigator's opinion, may interfere with protocol adherence or a subject's ability
             to give informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Luciano Costa, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical University of South Carolina</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jessica Simons</last_name>
    <phone>843-792-8856</phone>
    <email>simonsjl@musc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tricia Bentz, CCRP</last_name>
    <phone>843-792-1753</phone>
    <email>adraleta@musc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloane Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sergio Giralt, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-6009</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical University of South Carolina Hollings Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29425</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jessica Simons</last_name>
      <phone>843-792-8856</phone>
      <email>simonsjl@musc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Tricia Bentz, CCRP</last_name>
      <phone>843-792-1753</phone>
      <email>adraleta@musc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Luciano Costa, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert Stuart, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yubin Kang, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 30, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 17, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical University of South Carolina</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Luciano J. Costa</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melphalan</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
