<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="129470">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01942876</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DESPR DA022445</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01942876</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Preventing Drug Use in Low Income Clinic Populations</brief_title>
  <acronym>QUIT</acronym>
  <official_title>Preventing Drug Use in Low Income Clinic Populations</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Los Angeles</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study will address the critical need to reduce illegal drug use, in particular
      drug use, and the occurrence of drug-related harm in low-income racially diverse patient
      populations at urban primary care safety-net clinics.  Since they are at risk for
      accelerated trajectories to drug dependence once drug use begins, low-income racially
      diverse populations pose particular concern for public health policy makers and drug-use
      prevention efforts.  The study will be the first to standardize drug screening and
      primary-care clinician delivered brief intervention among racially diverse &quot;at risk&quot; drug
      users, that is users with casual or frequent use without the physiological or psychological
      manifestations of dependence, to reduce their 'at risk' use of drugs, and it may effectively
      interrupt their pathway to dependence.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Quit Using Drugs Intervention Trial (QUIT) will be the first randomized controlled trial
      in the U.S. that is powered to detect the effect of a primary care clinician delivered brief
      intervention protocol for reducing 'at risk' drug use and drug-related harm among low-income
      adult patients (ages 18 and older) at 2 safety net clinics in Los Angeles County.  For this
      small trial, we will sample patients with 'at risk' use of drugs (marijuana, crack/cocaine,
      amphetamines/methamphetamines, inhalants, sedatives or sleeping pills, hallucinogens, and
      opiates), the most commonly used serious drugs among patients at our clinic sites.  &quot;At
      risk&quot; drug use is defined in this study as current use (past 90 days) of drug measured as a
      self-reported total score of 4 to 26 on the WHO Alcohol Substance Involvement Screening Test
      (ASSIST).  A total of 8,000 patients will be approached for screening to yield a 12-month
      effective sample size of 200 eligible patients per condition (1) an intervention condition
      or (2) a control condition involving care as usual. In the intervention condition, very
      brief (less than 5 minutes) clinician advice regarding quitting drug use will be followed by
      two 2 and 6 week post-visit drug health education sessions on quitting drug use and
      cautioning against use of other 'at risk' substance use such as alcohol and tobacco.
      Patients assigned to the control condition will receive standard care for drug use at the
      baseline visit with their clinician, which will be followed by two post-visit telephone
      health education sessions that will be of equal duration as the intervention sessions but
      will address healthy eating, physical activity, and seat belt use. Follow-up assessments
      will be conducted at 3 month post-randomization. The framework for the QUIT project is the
      Social Action Theory, and the brief intervention protocol is based on NIDA's principles on
      prevention research and the utility of the 5 A's approach for assisting behavioral changes
      among patients (Ask, Advise, Assess, Assist, Arrange) in the clinic setting. If found to be
      effective in the community health center setting, this clinician and telephone drug-use
      health education program could become a model for health promotion activities. that would be
      expanded to all 'at risk' substance use and shared between community health centers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline of Self-reported number of drug-free days at 3 month</measure>
    <time_frame>past 30 and 90 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease in drug-related harm (e.g., unemployment and job absenteeism, poor social support, poor health-related quality of life, HIV risk behaviors, motor vehicle accidents, and inpatient health services utilization).</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months post randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">411</enrollment>
  <condition>Drugs; Harmful Use</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Quit Using Drugs Intervention Trial (QUIT) experimental arm includes: screening, very brief clinician advice, and telephone drug-use health education to reduce 'at risk' drug use and thus interrupt progression from casual or episodic abuse to dependence.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will receive a sham telephone intervention of equivalent duration on health behavior maintenance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quit Using Drugs Intervention Trial</intervention_name>
    <description>The goal of the Quit Using Drugs Intervention Trial (QUIT) is to conduct a small RCT of a primary care clinic-based very brief intervention protocol for reducing the use of illegal drugs and the occurrences of drug-related harm in low-income, racially-diverse patient populations at two 'safety-net' clinics in Los Angeles.  The design will emphasize screening, very brief clinician advice, and telephone drug-use health education to reduce 'at risk' drug use and thus interrupt progression from casual or episodic abuse to dependence.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>QUIT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Health behavior maintenance</intervention_name>
    <description>This attention-control arm will receive a sham telephone intervention of equivalent duration on health behavior maintenance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Attention-Control condition</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ages 18 and older

          -  report of drug use in the previous 90 days (i.e., (marijuana, crack/cocaine,
             amphetamines/methamphetamines, inhalants, sedatives or sleeping pills, hallucinogens,
             and opiates)

          -  an ASSIST score between 4 and 26 indicating 'at risk' drug use

          -  English or Spanish speaking

          -  able (not cognitively impaired) and willing to cooperate with data collection and
             research procedures, including 2 telephone counseling sessions and 3 month follow-up
             assessments

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant

          -  Drug or alcohol dependence
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lillian Gelberg, MD, MSPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UCLA Department of Family Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90024</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 10, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 6, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lillian Gelberg</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Drugs</keyword>
  <keyword>at risk</keyword>
  <keyword>community health center patients</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
