<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="56929">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01790633</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IMEA 38B</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-A01681-42</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01790633</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Study Evaluating the Use of Simultaneous HBV, HCV, and HIV Rapid Tests</brief_title>
  <acronym>OPTISCREEN-III</acronym>
  <official_title>Pilot Study Evaluating the Use of Simultaneous HBV, HCV, and HIV Rapid Tests As a Tool for Screening and Access to Care Among At-Risk Populations</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institut de Médecine et d'Epidémiologie Appliquée - Fondation Internationale Léon M'Ba</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>French National Institute for Health and Medical Research-French National Agency for Research on AIDS and Viral Hepatitis (Inserm-ANRS)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Gilead Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Roche Pharma AG</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mairie de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Biomerieux</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institut de Médecine et d'Epidémiologie Appliquée - Fondation Internationale Léon M'Ba</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>France: Committee for the Protection of Personnes</authority>
    <authority>France: Afssaps - Agence française de sécurité sanitaire des produits de santé (Saint-Denis)</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a pilot, monocentric, prospective, randomized control trial looking at the use of
      rapid tests as a part of normal care.  The investigators will be testing for hepatitis B
      virus (HBV), hepatitis C virus (HCV), and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).  Testing will
      be proposed to all persons seeking care at the Centre d'Accueil, de Soins et d'Orientation
      from the organization Médecin du Monde (CASO, MDM).

      Infection status of participants will be determined by either the standard test (ELISA) or
      rapid test.  The choice between tests will be determined randomly.

      The overall goal is to determine the general acceptability and feasibility of rapid tests
      and to see if they can help individuals increase their awareness of infection status when
      compared to longer, routine methods of testing.  In addition, results from these tests will
      allow the medical doctor to guide participants to appropriate care.  All positive tests will
      be confirmed at a specialized hospital (Hôptial Saint-Antoine, Paris, France) and
      health-specific information will be obtained four months after testing.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Screening</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Accessibility of testing results</measure>
    <time_frame>Evaluated once, up to 4 months after testing</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of individuals who obtained test results for HBV, HCV, and/or HIV divided by the total number of tested individuals.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Access to care</measure>
    <time_frame>Evaluated once, up to 4 months after testing</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of individuals seeking specialized care with a complete evaluation of disease severity divided by the total number of seropositive individuals.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion participating</measure>
    <time_frame>At testing</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of individuals accepting to participate in the study divided by the total number of individuals proposed.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion accepting to test</measure>
    <time_frame>At testing</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The number individuals accepting to test divided by the total number of individuals accepting to participate in the study.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of rapid test failures</measure>
    <time_frame>At testing</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of rapid tests giving inconclusive results divided by the total number of rapid tests (only available in the rapid test arm).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <condition>Hepatitis B</condition>
  <condition>Hepatitis C</condition>
  <condition>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</condition>
  <condition>AIDS</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard testing with ELISA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>HBV, HCV, and HIV infection status determined by enzyme-linked immuno-assay (ELISA).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rapid testing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>HBV, HCV, and HIV infection status determined by a rapid test</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ELISA</intervention_name>
    <description>Enzyme-linked immuno-assay (ELISA) will be used to determine hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), anti-HBsAg antibody (anti-HBs Ab), anti-HCV antibody, and anti-HIV antibody status. Results will be given after test results are available (8-10 days).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard testing with ELISA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rapid Test</intervention_name>
    <description>A rapid test will be performed to determine the subjects' hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg, using VIKIA®), anti-HCV antibody (HCV, using OraQuick®), and anti-HIV antibody (HIV, using VIKIA®) status. Results will be given the same day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rapid testing</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>VIKIA®, Biomerieux, Marcy-l'Étoile, France</other_name>
    <other_name>OraQuick® HCV Rapid Antibody Test, OraSure Technologies, Inc., Bethlehem, PA, USA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  At least 18 years of age

          -  Seeking care at the CASO MDM health care center

          -  Accept to be followed at Saint-Antoine Hospital in the event of a positive test.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Currently under physician's care for viral hepatitis (HBV/HCV-specific) or HIV

          -  Already has been tested (must give any of the following as evidence):

               -  results from HBV and HCV and HIV tests dating at least 3 months back

               -  results from HCV and HIV tests dating at least 3 months back and HBV serology
                  indicating that the participant is immunized against HBV.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Julie Bottero, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hôpital Saint-Antoine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Consultation d'Accueil, de Soins et d'Orientation (CASO) de Médecins du Monde (MDM)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75011</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.optiscreenb.fr/</url>
    <description>OPTISCREEN B study website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bottero J, Boyd A, Gozlan J, Lemoine M, Carrat F, Collignon A, Boo N, Dhotte P, Varsat B, Muller G, Cha O, Picard O, Nau J, Campa P, Silbermann B, Bary M, Girard PM, Lacombe K. Performance of rapid tests for detection of HBsAg and anti-HBsAb in a large cohort, France. J Hepatol. 2012 Nov 23. doi:pii: S0168-8278(12)00885-9. 10.1016/j.jhep.2012.11.016. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>23183527</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cazein F, Barin F, Le Strat Y, Pillonel J, Le Vu S, Lot F, Thierry D, Meffre C, Semaille C. Prevalence and characteristics of individuals with undiagnosed HIV infection in France: evidence from a survey on hepatitis B and C seroprevalence. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2012 Aug 1;60(4):e114-7. doi: 10.1097/QAI.0b013e318256b3fd.</citation>
    <PMID>22772350</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hutchinson AB, Branson BM, Kim A, Farnham PG. A meta-analysis of the effectiveness of alternative HIV counseling and testing methods to increase knowledge of HIV status. AIDS. 2006 Aug 1;20(12):1597-604. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16868440</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weinbaum CM, Williams I, Mast EE, Wang SA, Finelli L, Wasley A, Neitzel SM, Ward JW; Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Recommendations for identification and public health management of persons with chronic hepatitis B virus infection. MMWR Recomm Rep. 2008 Sep 19;57(RR-8):1-20.</citation>
    <PMID>18802412</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>European Association For The Study Of The Liver. EASL clinical practice guidelines: Management of chronic hepatitis B virus infection. J Hepatol. 2012 Jul;57(1):167-85. doi: 10.1016/j.jhep.2012.02.010. Epub 2012 Mar 20. Erratum in: J Hepatol. 2013 Jan;58(1):201. Janssen, Harry [corrected to Janssen, Harry L A].</citation>
    <PMID>22436845</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>European Association for the Study of the Liver. EASL Clinical Practice Guidelines: management of hepatitis C virus infection. J Hepatol. 2011 Aug;55(2):245-64. doi: 10.1016/j.jhep.2011.02.023. Epub 2011 Mar 1.</citation>
    <PMID>21371579</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 22, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 7, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>rapid test</keyword>
  <keyword>screening</keyword>
  <keyword>ELISA</keyword>
  <keyword>hepatitis B virus</keyword>
  <keyword>hepatitis C virus</keyword>
  <keyword>human immunodeficiency virus</keyword>
  <keyword>access to care</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis B</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
