<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="55276">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01835132</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130102</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-EI-0102</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01835132</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Gevokizumab for Active Scleritis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Gevokizumab Treatment for Active Scleritis By IL-1 Inhibition (GATSBY)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Scleritis is the inflammation of the white outer coating of the eye, known as the sclera.
      In severe cases, it can cause blindness. It is commonly associated with autoimmune disorders
      such as rheumatoid arthritis. Mild scleritis can be treated with drugs such as ibuprofen.
      More severe scleritis may need oral steroids or immunosuppressive treatments; however, these
      treatments can cause side effects in the whole body. Gevokizumab is a newer
      anti-inflammatory drug that is under investigation to treat other inflammatory diseases. It
      may not have as severe side effects as some other drugs. However, it has not yet been used
      to treat scleritis. Researchers want to see if it can be given as a safe and effective
      treatment for scleritis.

      Objectives:

      - To see if gevokizumab is a safe and effective treatment for scleritis.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals at least 18 years of age who have active scleritis.

      Design:

        -  There are two parts in this study, the initial phase and the extension phase. The
           extension phase is optional. The initial phase of the study requires seven visits to
           the National Eye Institute.

        -  Participants will be screened with a medical history, physical exam, and eye exam.
           Blood and urine samples will be collected.

        -  Participants will receive an injection of gevokizumab. The injections will be given at
           the first study visit and at Weeks 4, 8, and 12. They will be given under the skin by
           the stomach, or in the upper arm or thigh.

        -  Participants will have additional visits at 2, 16, and 28 weeks after the first study
           visit. These visits will monitor the treatment. Eye exams will be given, and blood and
           tear samples will be collected.

        -  If the scleritis improves by Week 16, participants may choose to continue the study.
           They will have a visit every 4 weeks until Week 36 and then two additional monitoring
           visits at Weeks 40 and 52 for a total of 13 study visits.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective: Scleritis is a chronic, painful and potentially blinding inflammatory disease
      characterized by edema of the episcleral and sclera tissues and is commonly associated with
      systemic autoimmune disorders. Gevokizumab is an interleukin-1Beta (IL-1B) inhibitor, thus
      possibly preventing the IL-1B that may be responsible for scleral breakdown in patients with
      anterior scleritis. The study objective is to evaluate the safety and potential efficacy of
      gevokizumab as a possible treatment of non-infectious, active, anterior scleritis.

      Study Population: Ten participants with non-infectious, active, anterior scleritis with a
      scleral inflammatory grade of greater than or equal to plus 1 in at least one eye will be
      initially enrolled. However, up to an additional two participants may be enrolled to account
      for participants who withdraw from the study prior to Week 16. Participants may be on less
      than or equal to 20 mg/day of prednisone or the equivalent at the time of enrollment but all
      other immunosuppressive drugs will be stopped with the initiation of study drug.

      Design: This is a Phase 1/2, open label, non-randomized, prospective, single-arm, pilot
      trial to evaluate the safety and potential efficacy of gevokizumab in non-infectious,
      active, anterior scleritis. The study consists of an initial phase followed by an extension
      phase. For the initial phase, all participants will receive one subcutaneous injection of 60
      mg gevokizumab at Baseline and Weeks 4, 8 and 12. At Week 16, participants will be assessed
      for eligibility in the extension phase of the study. Participants who do not continue in the
      extension phase of the study will discontinue the study drug and may receive salvage therapy
      using standard-of-care treatment at the investigator   s discretion. Participants who do not
      continue in the extension phase will return for a final safety visit at Week 28.
      Participants who are determined eligible for the extension phase may continue in the
      extension phase and receive one gevokizumab injection (60 mg) every four weeks until the
      Week 36 visit. Participants in the extension phase will have safety visits at Weeks 40 and
      52.

      Outcome Measures: The primary outcome is the number of participants with at least a 2-step
      reduction or reduction to grade 0 in scleral inflammation in the study eye (or eyes, if both
      eyes meet study eye criteria), according to a standardized photographic scleritis grading
      system developed at NEI, on or before the Week 16 visit as compared to Baseline. Secondary
      outcomes include changes in visual acuity, changes in intraocular pressure and changes in
      scleral grading. Safety outcomes include the number and severity of systemic and ocular
      toxicities and adverse events (AEs), and the proportion of participants with loss of greater
      than or equal to 15 ETDRS letters at any follow-up visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with &amp; gt; =2-step reduction or reduction to 0 in scleral inflammation in the study eye (or eyes, if both eyes meet study eye criteria), on or before the Week 16 visit as compared to Baseline.</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in visual acuity, intraocular pressure, and in scleral grading.</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Scleritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gevokizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gevokizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gevokizumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Participant must be 18 years of age or older.

          2. Participant must have a diagnosis of non-infectious anterior scleritis requiring
             treatment.

          3. Participant must agree not to undergo elective major surgery for the first 16 weeks
             of the study.

          4. Participant must not have received any the following:

               -  Another systemic biologic immunosuppressive agent within the last three months
                  prior to enrollment (e.g., infliximab, daclizumab, etanercept, adalimumab,
                  anakinra);

               -  Rituximab or alklyating agent (e.g., cyclophosphamide) within the last 12 months
                  prior to enrollment.

          5. Participants on systemic anti-inflammatory therapy (including corticosteroids) must
             not have had a dose escalation in any of their immunosuppressive treatments within
             the last four weeks prior to enrollment.

          6. Participant must stop all immunosuppressives upon enrollment in the study, with the
             exception of less than or equal to 20 mg/day of prednisone or equivalent.

          7. Participant must have chest X-ray results (frontal and lateral) within the last 12
             weeks prior to enrollment with no evidence of active pulmonary infection, active
             tuberculosis (TB) or malignancy.

          8. Participant must be cleared by internal medicine for enrollment.

          9. Female participants of childbearing potential must not be pregnant or breast-feeding,
             must have a negative pregnancy test at screening and must be willing to undergo
             pregnancy tests throughout the study.

         10. Both female participants of childbearing potential and male participants able to
             father a child must have (or have a partner who has) had a hysterectomy or vasectomy,
             be completely abstinent from intercourse or must agree to practice two acceptable
             methods of contraception throughout the course of the study and for four months after
             the last investigational product injection. Acceptable methods of contraception
             include:

               -  hormonal contraception (i.e., birth control pills, injected hormones, dermal
                  patch or vaginal ring),

               -  intrauterine device,

               -  barrier methods (diaphragm, condom) with spermicide, or

               -  surgical sterilization (tubal ligation).

         11. Participant must be able to undergo slit lamp biomicroscopy on both eyes.

         12. Participant must understand and sign the protocol   s informed consent document.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Participant has a significant active infection that requires treatment or has a
             history of recurrent systemic infections.

          2. Participant has a history of TB and s/he has not received a full course of TB
             treatment, OR participant has a history of latent TB infection (or a positive IGRA)
             and has not received prophylactic treatment with isoniazid [also known as
             isonicotinylhydrazine (INH)] or rifampicin within the last six months prior to
             enrollment.

          3. Participant is seropositive for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or Hepatitis C.

          4. Participant has Hepatitis B. Positivity for Hepatitis B without evidence of active
             disease (per investigator judgment) is not exclusionary.

          5. Participant has a history of cancer (other than a non-melanoma skin cancer or
             carcinoma in situ of the cervix) diagnosed within the last five years.

          6. Participant has a history of severe allergic or anaphylactic reaction to monoclonal
             antibodies.

          7. Participant has a history of previous treatment with gevokizumab.

          8. Participant received live (attenuated) vaccine within the last three months prior to
             enrollment. Live seasonal flu and H1N1 vaccines are permitted greater than or equal
             to two weeks prior to enrollment. Recombinant or killed vaccines are permitted at any
             time.

          9. Participant has received an investigational drug or device within the last three
             months.

         10. articipant has active joint or systemic inflammation requiring immediate addition or
             increase in systemic anti-inflammatory medications.

         11. Participant has a condition (e.g., psychiatric illness, severe alcoholism or drug
             abuse) or situation that may put the participant at significant risk, may confound
             the study results or may interfere significantly with his/her participation or
             cooperation in the study.

        STUDY EYE ELIGIBILITY CRITERIA:

        The participant must have at least one eye meeting all inclusion criteria and none of the
        exclusion criteria listed below.

        STUDY EYE INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Participant must have scleritis with a grade of greater than or equal to plus 1 in
             the study eye.

          2. Participant must have visual acuity of 20/640 or better in the study eye.

          3. Participant must agree not to undergo elective ocular surgery (e.g., cataract
             extraction) in the study eye for the first 16 weeks of the study.

        STUDY EYE EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Participant has had any of the following in the study eye:

               -  periocular, intravitreal steroid injection within the last six weeks prior to
                  enrollment,

               -  Ozurdex within the last six months prior to enrollment, or

               -  Retisert within the last three years prior to enrollment.

          2. Participant has had intraocular surgery in the study eye in the last four weeks prior
             to enrollment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hatice N Sen, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Eye Institute (NEI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dominic Obiyor, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 435-4556</phone>
    <email>dobiyor@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Hatice N Sen, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 435-5139</phone>
    <email>senh@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-EI-0102.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rothova A, Suttorp-van Schulten MS, Frits Treffers W, Kijlstra A. Causes and frequency of blindness in patients with intraocular inflammatory disease. Br J Ophthalmol. 1996 Apr;80(4):332-6.</citation>
    <PMID>8703885</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jabs DA, Mudun A, Dunn JP, Marsh MJ. Episcleritis and scleritis: clinical features and treatment results. Am J Ophthalmol. 2000 Oct;130(4):469-76.</citation>
    <PMID>11024419</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Watson PG, Hayreh SS. Scleritis and episcleritis. Br J Ophthalmol. 1976 Mar;60(3):163-91.</citation>
    <PMID>1268179</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 16, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Scleritis</keyword>
  <keyword>IL-1</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Scleritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
