<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="132770">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01844778</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CTBM100C2403</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-001565-33</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01844778</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ease of Use and Microbial Contamination of TIP vs Nebulised TIS and Nebulised Colistimethate</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label, Crossover, Interventional Phase IV Study to Compare the Ease of Use of TIP With TIS and Nebulized Colistimethate for the Treatment of Pulmonary Pseudomonas Aeruginosa in Patients With Cystic Fibrosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Novartis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this interventional Phase IV study is to explore the ease of use of TIP and
      prevalence of microbial contamination of the T-326 Inhaler compared with TIS and
      colistimethate administered via nebulizer for the treatment of Cystic Fibrosis (CF) patients
      chronically infected with P. aeruginosa.

      It is anticipated that the data from this study will provide clinicians with further
      guidance on the relative differences between the speed and ease of use of these treatments
      as well as useful information on the prevalence of microbial contamination of the inhalation
      devices in &quot;real world&quot; use.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this interventional Phase IV study is to explore the ease of use of TIP and
      prevalence of microbial contamination of the T-326 Inhaler compared with TIS and
      colistimethate administered via nebulizer for the treatment of CF patients chronically
      infected with P. aeruginosa.

      Patients who're currently on colistimethate, Tobramycin Inhalation Powder (TIP) or
      Tobramycin Inhalation Solution (TIS) will be recruited for the study. They will go through
      one treatment cycle on their current treatment, and will all transfer to TIP for the second
      treatment cycle. The primary endpoint is the total administration time of TIP vs TIS vs
      colistimethate, defined as the total time taken to prepare the delivery device and drug,
      administer the drug, and clean and disinfect the delivery device.

      It is anticipated that the data from this study will provide clinicians with further
      guidance on the relative differences between the speed and ease of use of these treatments
      as well as useful information on the prevalence of microbial contamination of the inhalation
      devices in &quot;real world&quot; use.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total time for administration of TIP with the Podhaler compared to the total time for administration of TIS or colistimethate with nebulisers</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The total time for administration of Tobramycin Inhalation Powder (TIP) via Podhaler vs the total time for administration of colistimethate or Tobramycin Inhalation Solution (TIS) will be assessed from information entered by participants  into an ediary, with a built in timer, during the last 7 days of each active treatment period. The total and combined time includes the setup, preparation, administration and cleaning/disinfection time for all devices.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of P. aeruginosa colony forming units (CFU)</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Sputum samples will be sent to a central laboratory at the start and end of 2 treatment periods. The change in the number of Colony Forming Units of Pseudomonas aeruginosa in sputum at the end of each treatment period, compared to the start, will be determined.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of microbial contamination of the T-326 Inhaler (Podhaler) compared with the contamination of the nebulizer used for the patient's usual nebulised antibiotic</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Devices used to administer the drugs (the Podhaler and nebulisers) will be swabbed for contamination testing at the start and end of each treatment cycle. The Podhaler is replaced after 7 days, hence the frequency of growth (low/ medium/ high) of organisms contaminating the device at the start and end of this period will be reported, and compared with the frequency of organisms contaminating the nebulisers at the start and end of the treatment period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Averse event (AE) rates after each treatment cycle</measure>
    <time_frame>168 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Comparison of the rates of adverse events (AEs) for TIP vs nebulized treatments after each treatment cycle.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of the relevant antibiotic for P. aeruginosa</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC) of a range of antibiotics for P.aeruginosa in sputum and in swabs taken off inhaler devices (nebulizers and Podhalers) will be determined at the start and end of each treatment cycle</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical laboratory abnormalities for TIP vs TIS and colistimethate after upto 28 days of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>All abnormalities in clinical chemistry, hematology and urinalysis data will be recorded and reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Type of microbial contamination of the T-326 Inhaler (Podhaler) compared with the contamination of the nebulizer used for the patient's usual nebulised antibiotic after upto 28 days of treatment in each treatment period</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Devices used to administer the drugs (the Podhaler and nebulisers) will be swabbed for contamination testing at the start and end of each treatment cycle. The Podhaler is replaced after 7 days, hence the type of organisms contaminating the device at the start and end of this period will be reported, and compared with the types of organisms contaminating the nebulisers at the start and end of the treatment period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of P. aeruginosa Colony Forming Units</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Sputum samples will be sent to a central laboratory at the start and end of 2 treatment periods. The change in the number of Colony Forming Units (CFU) of Pseudomonas aeruginosa in sputum at the end of each treatment period, compared to the start, will be determined.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse event (AE) rates after each treatment cycle</measure>
    <time_frame>168 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Comparison of the rates of adverse events (AEs) for treatment via Podhaler vs nebulized treatments after each treatment cycle.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the minimum inhibitory concentration of the relevant antibiotic for P. aeruginosa</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC) of a range of antibiotics for P. aeruginosa in sputum and in swabs taken off inhaler devices (nebulizers and Podhalers) will be determined at the start and end of each treatment cycle.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical laboratory abnormalities for Tobramycin Inhalation Powder vs Tobramycin Inhalation Solution and colistimethate after upto 28 days of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>All abnormalities in clinical chemistry, hematology and urinalysis data will be recorded and reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">67</enrollment>
  <condition>Cystic Fibrosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tobramycin Inhalation Powder</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tobramycin Inhalation Powder administered via the TOBI Podhaler</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tobramycin Inhalation Solution</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tobramycin Inhalation Solution administered via nebulizer.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Colistimethate nebulised</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Colistimethate administered via nebulizer.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tobramycin Inhalation Powder</intervention_name>
    <description>Tobramycin Inhalation Powder 112mg via TOBI® Podhaler, inhaled twice a day for 28 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tobramycin Inhalation Powder</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TIP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tobramycin inhalation solution</intervention_name>
    <description>Tobramycin inhalation solution administered via nebuliser, 300mg twice a day for 28 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tobramycin Inhalation Solution</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TIS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Colistimethate</intervention_name>
    <description>Colistimethate 1 or 2 million units or other administered via nebulizer one to three times a day for 28 days or continuously dependent on local treatment practise</description>
    <arm_group_label>Colistimethate nebulised</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Provide written informed consent, HIPAA authorization, and assent (as appropriate for
             minors) prior to the performance of any study-related procedure

          -  Confirmed diagnosis of Cystic Fibrosis (CF)

          -  Male and female patients  6 years of age or older at screening

          -  Forced Expiratory Volume in 1 second (FEV1) at screening (Visit 1) must be at least
             25% and less than or equal to 90% of normal predicted values for age, sex, and height
             based on the NHANES III values (Hankinson, 1999) for patients 18 years of age or
             greater, and based on values from Wang (Wang 1993) for patients less than 18 years of
             age.

          -  Documented use of any of the nebulized antibiotics based on local practice:

          -  Tobramycin Inhalation Solution, colistimethate, or Tobramycin Inhalation Powder for
             at least 1 cycle within the last 6 months or

          -  Colistimethate continuous use for at least 8 weeks within the last 6 months This
             cycle of treatment (or continuous colistimethate treatment period) is in addition to
             the treatment cycle during which the subject is being screened.

          -  P. aeruginosa must be present in a sputum or deep cough throat swab culture or
             bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) (only for BAL a threshold level of 103 CFU/mL is
             required) within 6 months prior to screening, and in the sputum or deep cough throat
             swab culture at screening or rescreening (Visit 1)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of sputum culture or deep cough throat swab (or BAL) culture yielding
             Burkholderia cenocepacia complex within 2 years prior to prescreening or sputum
             culture yielding B. cenocepacia complex at screening (Visit 1)

          -  History of hearing loss or chronic tinnitus deemed clinically significant by the
             investigator

          -  Serum creatinine 89 μmol/L or greater,  BUN 5.7 μmol/L or greater, creatinine
             clearance 50 mL/min or less, or an abnormal urinalysis defined as 2+ or greater
             proteinuria at screening

          -  Known local or systemic hypersensitivity to aminoglycosides

          -  Regularly receiving more than 1 class of inhaled antipseudomonal antibiotic. to the
             study.

          -  Use of any investigational drug within 30 days or 5 half-lives, whichever is longer,
             prior to screening

          -  Signs and symptoms of acute pulmonary disease, e.g., pneumonia, pneumothorax

          -  Body mass index less than 12 kg/m2

          -  History of malignancy of any organ system, treated or untreated

          -  Clinically significant laboratory abnormalities (not associated with the study
             indication) at screening (Visit 1)

          -  Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women, where pregnancy is defined as the state of a
             female after conception and until the termination of gestation, confirmed by a
             positive human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) laboratory test

          -  Women of child-bearing potential, defined as all women physiologically capable of
             becoming pregnant, unless they are using effective methods of contraception during
             study treatment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>C Novartis Pharmaceuticals, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+41613241111</phone>
    <email>hiran.cooray@novaris.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</last_name>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>13353</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Frankfurt</city>
        <zip>60590</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>20246</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>München</city>
        <zip>81241</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tübingen</city>
        <zip>72076</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <state>Andalucia</state>
        <zip>41013</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valladolid</city>
        <state>Castilla y Leon</state>
        <zip>47011</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <state>Catalunya</state>
        <zip>08035</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <state>Cataluña</state>
        <zip>08950</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <state>Comunidad Valenciana</state>
        <zip>46026</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baracaldo</city>
        <state>Pais Vasco</state>
        <zip>48903</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28046</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oviedo (Asturias)</city>
        <zip>33006</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Basel</city>
        <zip>4031</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Basel</city>
        <zip>4056</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bern</city>
        <zip>3004</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Gallen</city>
        <zip>9007</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zurich</city>
        <zip>8091</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zürich</city>
        <zip>8032</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Southampton</city>
        <state>Hampshire</state>
        <zip>SO16 6YD</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Penarth</city>
        <state>Vale of Glamorgan</state>
        <zip>CF64 2XX</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>West Midlands</state>
        <zip>b9 5ss</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>East Yorkshire</city>
        <zip>HU16 5JQ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Exeter</city>
        <zip>EX2 5DW</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liverpool</city>
        <zip>L14 3PE</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newcastle upon Tyne</city>
        <zip>NE1 4LP</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 27, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 29, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cystic Fibrosis, Pseudomonas aeruginosa, FEV1, tobramycin inhalation powder, TOBI,</keyword>
  <keyword>colistimethate</keyword>
  <keyword>Cystic Fibrosis, Pseudomonas aeruginosa, FEV1, tobramycin inhalation powder, TOBI, colistimethate</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cystic Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Tobramycin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colistin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
