<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="136073">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01783080</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NYSPI5908</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01783080</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Behavioral Activation (BA) for Medication-responsive Chronically Depressed Patients With Impaired Social Functioning</brief_title>
  <official_title>Behavioral Activation (BA) for Medication-responsive Chronically Depressed Patients With Impaired Social Functioning</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York State Psychiatric Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York State Psychiatric Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators aimed to assess the ability of a modified version of Behavioral Activation
      for occupational and social improvement to produce change in: 1. social adjustment, 2. work
      functioning, 3. avoidance behavior and 4. behavioral activation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Psychosocial functioning was assessed before and after BA treatment in medication responsive
      depressed individuals who continued to have impaired social functioning. The primary goal
      was to demonstrate feasibility of recruitment and retention, and obtain an open pilot sense
      as to whether there are benefits from this brief psychotherapy approach in this population.
      The investigators also planned to refine measures and estimate the effect size of any
      treatment response to estimate power and sample size with the goal of completing a future
      controlled study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Paid work hours at week 24</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subject-reported paid work hours per week at week 24 follow-up.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Attainment of work-related goals at week 24</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Attainment of work goals was measured using the Goal Attainment Scale (GAS). A research MD (D.H.) rated the GAS at Week 24 for primary outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Social functioning at week 24 on the Social Adjustment Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Social adjustment was measured using the Social Adjustment Scale (SAS). The SAS is a self-report scale that assesses depressive symptoms and functioning in nine social and work-related domains generating a total score that is indicative of a subject's overall level of social adjustment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavioral activation at week 24</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Level of behavioral activation was measured by the Behavioral Activation for Depression Scale (BADS), a 25-item self-report measure with four subscales corresponding to levels of activation, avoidance, work / school impairment and social impairment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Social adjustment at week 24 on the Quality of Life Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Social adjustment was also measured using the Quality of Life Enjoyment Satisfaction Questionnaire, short form. The Quality of Life Enjoyment Satisfaction Questionnaire is a 16 item inventory designed to assess the degree of enjoyment and satisfaction experienced in areas of daily functioning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavioral Avoidance at week 24</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Behavioral Avoidance was measured with the Cognitive and Behavior Avoidance Scale (CBAS), a 31-item patient rated scale with subscales corresponding to avoidance in 4 areas: cognitive social, cognitive non-social, behavioral social and behavioral non-social.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Medication-responsive Chronic Depression (CD).</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral Activation for Return to Work (BA-W)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BA is a manualized psychotherapy which has demonstrated comparable efficacy to cognitive behavioral treatment and antidepressant medication for the acute treatment of depression.  BA has two primary foci: 1) functional analyses of cognitive and behavioral processes that involve avoidance and 2) using avoided activities to guide activity scheduling. In the current study, BA's focus but not its principles was shifted to target work dysfunction by activating the patient into employment-related goals.  BA-W consisted of 12 50-minute weekly sessions. Conceptualizing work dysfunction as a product of avoidance patterns and low levels of positive reinforcement, the treatment rationale viewed maladaptive coping strategies such as avoidance as maintaining work dysfunction beyond remission of symptoms. Rather than broadly activating patients, activity scheduling focused on tasks such as sending out resumes, calling for job interviews, and networking to meet potential employers.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Behavioral Activation for return to work</intervention_name>
    <description>See Arm Description</description>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral Activation for Return to Work (BA-W)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  adults aged 20-75 years

          -  a primary diagnosis of Dysthymic Disorder, Chronic major depressive disorder or
             double depression

          -  a &gt;50% decrease in 17 item Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression (HRSD-17) score and a
             final HRSD-17 score ≤ 10 with an adequate antidepressant medication (ADM) trial (&gt; 4
             weeks on at least 50% Physician's Desk Reference maximum ADM dose)

          -  a rating of 1 (&quot;very much improved&quot;) or 2 (&quot;much improved&quot;) on the Clinical Global
             Impressions-Improvement scale (CGI-I)

          -  continued functional impairment, defined by scores &gt;1.9 on the Social Adjustment
             Scale (SAS)

          -  unemployment (jobless, looking for work) according to the Bureau of Labor Statistics:
             jobless and looking and available for work, or underemployed.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV Axis I disorders-diagnosed cognitive or
             psychotic disorders

          -  bipolar disorder

          -  active eating disorders

          -  severe borderline personality disorder

          -  alcohol or drug dependence (except nicotine) in the last 6 months

          -  current suicide risk

          -  unstable medical conditions

          -  use of psychotropic medications other than antidepressants
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David J Hellerstein, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>New York State Psychiatric Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York State Psychiatric Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 31, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 25, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>New York State Psychiatric Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David J. Hellerstein</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chronic depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Dysthymic disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Double Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Behavioral Activation therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Work impairment</keyword>
  <keyword>Unemployment</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dysthymic Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
