<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="62082">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01900236</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R01AI103661</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01900236</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Integrating ENGagement and Adherence Goals Upon Entry iENGAGE to Control HIV</brief_title>
  <acronym>iENGAGE</acronym>
  <official_title>Integrating ENGagement and Adherence Goals Upon Entry iENGAGE to Control HIV</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alabama at Birmingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of North Carolina</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Connecticut</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alabama at Birmingham</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: National Institutes of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      iENGAGE is a 4 session, in-clinic behavioral intervention that is delivered to new clinic
      patients during  the first year of HIV care on a flexible delivery schedule, with
      intervention visits scheduled to coincide with HIV medical care visits.  Interventionists
      from each participating collaborating site will be trained centrally to implement the
      iENGAGE protocol. Following study enrollment and baseline assessment, participants will be
      randomized to treatment as usual and intervention groups. For intervention-arm participants,
      each iENGAGE intervention session includes: interventionist-delivered educational content
      for managing HIV medical care appointment-keeping and information sessions for learning to
      manage HIV medications.  The intervention will have a tailored, interactive agenda for each
      of the 4 sessions based on behavioral motivational interviewing (MI) techniques. The goal of
      this intervention is for the participant to establish early behaviors that help him/her to
      arrive at scheduled medical appointments and learn to take medications as prescribed during
      the initial year of HIV care in order to improve overall health.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Centers for Disease Control's Retention In Care (CDC RIC) and the Participating and
      Communicating Together (PACT) antiretroviral therapy (ART) adherence interventions have
      shown success in the literature, and they are well suited to target the two essential HIV
      adherence behaviors needed to achieve better overall health: HIV medical visit adherence and
      ART adherence. While these original interventions target each of these behaviors separately,
      the comprehensive iENGAGE intervention combines these two approaches to address the
      experience of an individual who is initiating HIV care. Upon entry to care, knowledge,
      motivation, and skills for adherence to HIV medical visits and ART must be learned rapidly.
      Jointly targeting these behaviors offers a distinct advantage over addressing them
      separately.

      iENGAGE integrates CDC RIC and PACT through their common intervention targets with the
      assistance of trained interventionists, who will maintain contact with the new patient to
      educate and assist with reinforcing the importance of adherence to care.  While the actions
      required to attend HIV medical care appointments and take medications properly are distinct,
      each is influenced by an individual's personal motivation and skills for self-management of
      HIV infection and overall health; these principles are the focus of the intervention
      sessions for this protocol .

      During this intervention, our team will make every effort to protect all participants'
      confidential and private information in order to minimize possible study-associated risks.
      In addition, the follow up measurement plan for this study is unique, as it aims to utilize
      the X060831001: Unsolicited R24 for the CFAR Network of Integrated Clinical Sciences, CNICS,
      PI Michael Saag) secure electronic data infrastructure, which has existing defined protocols
      for the protection of human subjects data, including a data management core that is housed
      at the collaborating site at the University of Washington.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Viral load suppression (&lt;200c/ml)among patients newly initiating outpatient HIV medical care</measure>
    <time_frame>48 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Viremia copy years (VCY)</measure>
    <time_frame>96 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>VCY is the area under the curve estimate of cumulative VL burden</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Motivation Behavioral Technique</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Behavioral:   4 sessions of tailored, interactive agenda based on behavioral motivational interviewing (MI) techniques</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>4 sessions of tailored, interactive agenda based on behavioral motivational interviewing (MI) techniques</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention will have a tailored, interactive agenda for each of the 4 sessions based on behavioral motivational interviewing (MI) techniques. The goal of this intervention is for the participant to establish early behaviors that help him/her to arrive at scheduled medical appointments and learn to take medications as prescribed during the initial year of HIV care in order to improve overall health.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Motivation Behavioral Technique</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Documented HIV infection

          -  Newly establishing HIV care at study site

          -  Age 19 years or older

          -  English speaking

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not willing or able to provide informed consent

          -  Received prior outpatient HIV care

          -  Completed &gt;1 primary care visits
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Modi</last_name>
    <phone>2059341284</phone>
    <email>Rmodi@uab.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alabama at Birmingham</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael J Mugavero, MD, MHSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Johns Hopkins HIV Care Program</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UNC Infectious Diseases Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>• University of Washington</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 15, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 2, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Patients newly initiating outpatient HIV medical care</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
