<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="158103">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01948193</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A3L33</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1127-6936</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CTRI/2013/09/003997</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01948193</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of DTaP-IPV-Hep B-PRP~T Combined Vaccine in Indian Infants Previously Given a Dose of Hepatitis B Vaccine at Birth</brief_title>
  <official_title>Immunogenicity and Safety of Sanofi Pasteur's DTaP-IPV-Hep B-PRP-T Combined Vaccine Given at 6, 10 and 14 Weeks of Age in Infants From India Who Previously Received a Dose of Hepatitis B Vaccine at Birth</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sanofi Pasteur, a Sanofi Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sanofi</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>India: Drugs Controller General of India</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to describe the immunogenicity and safety of a novel DTaP- IPV-
      Hep B-PRT~T fully liquid combined hexavalent vaccine (Hexaxim™) administered at 6, 10 and 14
      weeks of age in infants born to mothers documented to be serum anti-hepatitis B surface
      antigen (HBsAg) serology negative in India.

      Primary Objective:

        -  To evaluate the immunogenicity of the study vaccine in terms of seroprotection
           [diphtheria toxoid, tetanus toxoid, poliovirus types 1, 2 and 3, Haemophilus influenzae
           type b (Hib) polysaccharide (PRP), hepatitis B (Hep B)] and vaccine response for
           pertussis antigens [pertussis toxoid (PT) and filamentous haemagglutinin (FHA)] one
           month after the third dose.

      Secondary Objectives:

        -  To further describe the immunogenicity of the study vaccine, before the first dose and
           one month after the third dose.

        -  To describe the safety after each and any doses of the study vaccine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      All participants will receive a total 4 doses of Hep B, i.e. one dose of Hep B monovalent
      vaccine given at birth followed by 3 doses of Sanofi Pasteur's hexavalent vaccine given at
      6, 10 and 14 weeks of age in the context of the study. Participants and parents will attend
      four clinic visits; the expected participation in the study is approximately 3 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Summary of levels of antibodies to the vaccine antigens following 3 doses of DTaP-IPV-Hep B-PRP~T, Sanofi Pasteur's hexavalent vaccine</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 30 (post 3rd vaccination)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants reporting solicited injection site reactions, solicited systemic reactions, unsolicited systemic reactions, and serious adverse events after booster administration of DTaP IPV Hep B PRP T vaccine and Infanrix hexa™ vaccine.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 to up to 3 months post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Solicited injection site: Tenderness, Redness, and Swelling: Solicited Systemic Reactions: Fever (temperature), Vomiting, Abnormal crying, Drowsiness, Loss of appetite, and Irritability. Unsolicited averse events including serious adverse events.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">177</enrollment>
  <condition>Diphtheria</condition>
  <condition>Tetanus</condition>
  <condition>Whooping Cough</condition>
  <condition>Hepatitis B</condition>
  <condition>Poliomyelitis</condition>
  <condition>Invasive Hib Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive Sanofi Pasteur's DTaP-IPV-Hep B-PRP~T combined vaccine (investigational vaccine) at 6, 10 and 14 weeks of age.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hexaxim™: DTaP-IPV-Hep B-PRP~T combined vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>0.5 mL, Intramuscular</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Hexaxim™</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged between 42-56 days (6 to 8 weeks) on the day of inclusion

          -  Born at full term of pregnancy (≥37 weeks) and with a birth weight ≥2.5 kg

          -  Informed consent form signed by the parent(s) or any other legally acceptable
             representative

          -  Subject and parent/legally acceptable representative are able to attend all scheduled
             visits and to comply with all trial procedures

          -  Born to known hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) seronegative mother (documented
             laboratory result of HBsAg assay from maternal blood sample performed during last
             trimester of pregnancy available)

          -  Have received one documented dose of Hep B vaccine and oral poliovirus vaccine (OPV)
             from birth as per national recommendations. Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participation in another clinical trial in the 4 weeks preceding the trial inclusion
             or planned participation during the present trial period in another clinical trial
             investigating a vaccine, drug, medical device, or medical procedure

          -  Receipt of any vaccine in the 4 weeks preceding the first trial vaccination (except
             Bacillus Calmette-Guerin [BCG] vaccine) or planned receipt of any other vaccine
             within the period from 8 days before to 8 days after each subsequent trial
             vaccination

          -  Previous vaccination against the diphtheria, tetanus, pertussis, poliomyelitis
             (expect the birth dose of OPV as per national recommendations) and hepatitis B
             (except the birth dose of Hep B vaccine) diseases or Hib infection with the trial
             vaccine or another vaccine

          -  Past or current receipt of immune globulins, blood or blood-derived products or
             planned administration during the trial

          -  Known or suspected congenital or acquired immunodeficiency; or receipt of
             immunosuppressive therapy, such as anti-cancer chemotherapy or radiation therapy
             since birth; or long-term systemic corticosteroid therapy (prednisone or equivalent
             for more than 2 consecutive weeks since birth)

          -  History of diphtheria, tetanus, pertussis, poliomyelitis, hepatitis B, or Hib
             infections (confirmed either clinically, serologically or microbiologically)

          -  Known personal or maternal history of Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) or hepatitis
             C seropositivity

          -  Known systemic hypersensitivity to any of the vaccine components, or history of a
             life-threatening reaction to the trial vaccine or a vaccine containing the same
             substances

          -  Known thrombocytopenia, as reported by the parent/legally acceptable representative

          -  Bleeding disorder, or receipt of anticoagulants in the 3 weeks preceding inclusion,
             contraindicating intramuscular vaccination

          -  In an emergency setting, or hospitalized involuntarily

          -  Chronic illness that, in the opinion of the investigator, is at a stage where it
             might interfere with trial conduct or completion

          -  Moderate or severe acute illness/infection (according to investigator judgment) on
             the day of vaccination or febrile illness (axillary temperature ≥38°C) on the day of
             inclusion (a prospective subject should not be included in the study until the
             condition has resolved or the febrile event has subsided)

          -  Identified as a natural or adopted child of the Investigator, relatives or employee
             with direct involvement in the proposed study

          -  History of seizures.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Weeks</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>8 Weeks</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Sanofi Pasteur SA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Public Registry Sanofi Pasteur</last_name>
    <email>RegistryContactUs@sanofipasteur.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Ludhiana</city>
        <state>Punjab</state>
        <zip>141008</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Pune</city>
        <zip>411043</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.sanofipasteur.com</url>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.sanofi.com</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diphtheria</keyword>
  <keyword>Tetanus</keyword>
  <keyword>Whooping Cough</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatitis B</keyword>
  <keyword>Poliomyelitis</keyword>
  <keyword>DTaP IPV-Hep B-PRP~T combined vaccine (Hexaxim™)</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cough</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diphtheria</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis B</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Poliomyelitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tetanus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tetany</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Whooping Cough</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
