<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="41817">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01846624</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HEMAML0022</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-00868</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>25737</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01846624</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Decitabine and Midostaurin in Treating Older Patients With Newly Diagnosed Acute Myeloid Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Decitabine in Combination With Midostaurin (PKC412) for Elderly Patients With Newly Diagnosed FLT3-ITD/TKD Positive Acute Myeloid Leukemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bruno C. Medeiros</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well giving decitabine together with midostaurin works in
      treating older patients with newly diagnosed acute myeloid leukemia. Decitabine and
      midostaurin may stop the growth of cancer cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed for
      cell growth.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the efficacy of midostaurin when administered in combination with a fixed
      dose of decitabine, administered sequentially, in elderly patients (age &gt;= 60 years) with
      fms-related tyrosine kinase 3 (FLT3)- internal tandem duplication (ITD)/tyrosine kinase
      domain (TKD)-positive acute myeloid leukemia (AML) (as measured by complete remission rate).

      II. To assess the safety profile of this combination in elderly patients with
      FLT3-ITD/TKD-positive AML for both induction and post-remission therapy (adverse events
      [AEs]/serious adverse events [SAEs] as determined by Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse
      Events [CTCAE] version 4.0).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine overall survival for all patients and duration of response during the time
      period of study monitoring.

      OUTLINE:

      INDUCTION THERAPY: Patients receive decitabine intravenously (IV) over 1 hour on days 1-10
      and midostaurin orally (PO) twice daily (BID) on days 11-28. Treatment repeats every 28 days
      until documented bone marrow response is achieved or for up to 12 courses in the absence of
      disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients achieving documented bone marrow
      response by course 6 continue treatment with induction therapy; patients achieving response
      after course 6 proceed to post-remission therapy.

      POST-REMISSION THERAPY: Patients receive decitabine IV over 1 hour on days 1-5 and
      midostaurin PO BID on days 6-28. Treatment repeats every 28 days for up to 12 courses
      (including induction therapy) in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable
      toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for up to 1 year.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete remission (CR) rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myeloid Leukemia With Multilineage Dysplasia Following Myelodysplastic Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With 11q23 (MLL) Abnormalities</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With Del(5q)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With Inv(16)(p13;q22)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With t(16;16)(p13;q22)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With t(8;21)(q22;q22)</condition>
  <condition>Secondary Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Untreated Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (decitabine, midostaurin)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>INDUCTION THERAPY: Patients receive decitabine IV over 1 hour on days 1-10 and midostaurin PO BID on days 11-28. Treatment repeats every 28 days until documented bone marrow response is achieved or for up to 12 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients achieving documented bone marrow response by course 6 continue treatment with induction therapy; patients achieving response after course 6 proceed to post-remission therapy.
POST-REMISSION THERAPY: Patients receive decitabine IV over 1 hour on days 1-5 and midostaurin PO BID on days 6-28. Treatment repeats every 28 days for up to 12 courses (including induction therapy) in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>decitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (decitabine, midostaurin)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>5-aza-dCyd</other_name>
    <other_name>5AZA</other_name>
    <other_name>DAC</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>midostaurin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (decitabine, midostaurin)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>N-benzoyl-staurosporine</other_name>
    <other_name>PKC412</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (decitabine, midostaurin)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Newly diagnosed AML (according to the World Health Organization [WHO] 2008
             classification) except t(15;17), including:

               -  De novo AML

               -  Secondary AML

               -  Secondary AML arising from previously diagnosed myelodysplastic syndromes (MDS)
                  treated with deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) methyltransferase inhibitor (DNMTi)
                  (i.e., decitabine or azacitidine)

          -  Confirmed FLT3-ITD or FLT3-TKD mutation, measured on bone marrow aspirate as part of
             screening prior to study enrollment; sample will be submitted to Stanford clinical
             lab and sent out for commercially available test at Laboratory for Personalized
             Molecular Medicine

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status =&lt; 2

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) =&lt; 2.5 x upper
             limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Serum bilirubin =&lt; 2.5 x ULN

          -  Serum creatinine =&lt; 1.5 mg/dL and/or creatinine clearance &gt;= 50 mL/min

          -  Ejection fraction &gt;= 50% by echocardiogram

          -  Unwillingness or inability to receive conventional chemotherapy

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

          -  Ability to adhere to the study visit schedule and other protocol requirements

          -  Life expectancy of greater than two months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients receiving concomitant treatment with other anti-neoplastic agents, with the
             exception of hydroxyurea; however, prior treatment with DNMTi therapy (i.e.,
             decitabine or azacitidine) for MDS is allowed

          -  Anti-neoplastic treatment less than 4 weeks prior to enrollment, with the exception
             of hydroxyurea

          -  Inability to swallow or absorb drug

          -  Active opportunistic infection or treatment for opportunistic infection within four
             weeks of first day of study drug dosing

          -  Other medical or psychiatric illness or organ dysfunction or laboratory abnormality
             which in the opinion of the investigator would compromise the patient's safety or
             interfere with data interpretation

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to midostaurin and/or decitabine

          -  Known impairment of gastrointestinal (GI) function or GI disease that may
             significantly alter the absorption of midostaurin

          -  Any other known disease (except carcinoma in-situ), concurrent severe and/or
             uncontrolled medical condition (e.g. uncontrolled diabetes, cardiovascular disease
             including congestive heart failure, myocardial infarction within 6 months and poorly
             controlled hypertension, chronic renal disease, or active uncontrolled infection)
             which could compromise participation in the study

          -  A known confirmed diagnosis of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection or active
             viral hepatitis because of uncertain toxicity profile of midostaurin in this patient
             population

          -  Patients who have received any investigational agent within 4 weeks of enrollment

          -  Patients who have had any surgical procedure, excluding central venous catheter
             placement or other minor procedures (e.g. skin biopsy) within 14 days of day 1

          -  Unwillingness or inability to comply with the protocol

          -  Known active central nervous system (CNS) malignancy

          -  Previous or current history of a myeloproliferative disease

          -  Impaired cardiac function including any of the following:

               -  Screening electrocardiogram (ECG) with a corrected QT interval (QTc) &gt; 450 msec

               -  Bradycardia defined as heart rate (HR) &lt; 50 beats per minute (bpm)

               -  Right bundle branch block + left anterior hemiblock (bifascicular block)

               -  Patients with myocardial infarction or unstable angina &lt; 3 months prior to
                  starting study drug

               -  Congestive heart failure (CHF) New York (NY) Heart Association class III or IV

          -  Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women, where pregnancy is defined as the state of a
             female after conception and until the termination of gestation, confirmed by a
             positive human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) laboratory test

          -  Women of child-bearing potential, defined as all women physiologically capable of
             becoming pregnant, unless they are using highly effective methods of contraception
             during dosing and for 3 months after midostaurin medication; highly effective
             contraception methods include:

               -  Total abstinence (when this is in line with the preferred and usual lifestyle of
                  the subject; periodic abstinence (e.g., calendar, ovulation, symptothermal,
                  post-ovulation methods) and withdrawal are not acceptable methods of
                  contraception

               -  Female sterilization (have had surgical bilateral oophorectomy with or without
                  hysterectomy) or tubal ligation at least six weeks before taking study
                  treatment; in case of oophorectomy alone, only when the reproductive status of
                  the woman has been confirmed by follow up hormone level assessment

               -  Male sterilization (at least 6 months prior to screening); for female subjects
                  on the study the vasectomized male partner should be the sole partner for that
                  subject

          -  Combination of any two of the following (a+b or a+c, or b+c):

               -  Use of oral, injected or implanted hormonal methods of contraception or other
                  forms of hormonal contraception that have comparable efficacy (failure rate &lt;
                  1%), for example hormone vaginal ring or transdermal hormone contraception

               -  Placement of an intrauterine device (IUD) or intrauterine system (IUS)

               -  Barrier methods of contraception: Condom or Occlusive cap (diaphragm or
                  cervical/vault caps) with spermicidal foam/gel/film/cream/vaginal suppository

                    -  In case of use of oral contraception women should have been stable on the
                       same pill for a minimum of 3 months before taking study treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bruno C. Medeiros</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University Hospitals and Clinics</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jack Taw</last_name>
      <phone>650-723-2781</phone>
      <email>jtaw@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bruno C. de Medeiros</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 14, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 30, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Stanford University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Bruno C. Medeiros</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Congenital Abnormalities</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Decitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Staurosporine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>4'-N-benzoylstaurosporine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
