<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="23438">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01990313</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>25916</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01990313</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neural Signatures of Parkinson's Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>BrainRadio</acronym>
  <official_title>Neural Signatures of Tremor, Bradykinesia and Freezing in the Subthalamic Region on Parkinson's Disease and Their Acute and Long-Term Modulation by Subthalamic Deep Brain Stimulation.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medtronic</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to provide objective measurements of abnormal movements of the
      body in correlation with neural activity of the brain and track how these change over time.
      This may allow for the development of objective evaluation of the neural activity causing
      abnormal movements, which may lead to the ability of the DBS system to stimulate the brain
      by sensing the abnormal neural activity that is causing abnormal movements.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The changes of neuronal oscillations, measured in power (dB/Hz) and frequency (Hz) that are significantly different during tremor, repetitive movement and freezing episodes from those at rest in people with Parkinson's disease off medications.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 Years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Activa PC+S</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Activa PC+S</intervention_name>
    <description>The Model 37604 Activa PC+S is a multiprogrammable device that can deliver therapeutic electrical stimulation and record bioelectric signals from leads implanted in the brain.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Activa PC+S</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Model 37604</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  a diagnosis of idiopathic Parkinson's disease, with bilateral symptoms at Hoehn and
             Yahr Stage greater than or equal to II.

          -  Documented improvement in motor signs on versus off dopaminergic medication, with a
             change in the Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale motor (UPDRS III) score of &gt;=
             30% off to on medication.

          -  The presence of complications of medication such as wearing off signs, fluctuating
             responses and/or dyskinesias, and/or medication refractory tremor, and/or impairment
             in the quality of life on or off medication due to these factors.

          -  Subjects should be on stable doses of medications, which should remain unchanged
             until the DBS system is activated. After the DBS system is optimized (during which
             time the overall medication dose may be reduced to avoid discomfort and complications
             such as dyskinesias) the medication dose should remain unchanged, if possible, for
             the duration of the study.

          -  Treatment with carbidopa/levodopa, and with a dopamine agonist at the maximal
             tolerated doses as determined by a movement disorders neurologist.

          -  Ability and willingness to return for study visits, at the initial programming and
             after three, six and twelve months of DBS.

          -  Age &gt; 18

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with significant cognitive impairment and/or dementia as determined by a
             standardized neuropsychological battery.

          -  Subjects with clinically active depression, defined according to the Diagnostic and
             Statistical manual of Mental Disorders, Fourth Edition (DSM-IV) criteria and as
             scored on a validated depression assessment scale.

          -  Subjects with very advanced Parkinson's disease, Hoehn and Yahr stage 5 on medication
             (non-ambulatory).

          -  Age &gt; 80.

          -  Subjects with an implanted electronic device such as a neurostimulator, cardiac
             pacemaker/defibrillator or medication pump.

          -  Subjects, who are pregnant, are capable of becoming pregnant, or who are breast
             feeding.

          -  Patients with cortical atrophy out of proportion to age or focal brain lesions that
             could indicate a non-idiopathic movement disorder as determined by MRI

          -  Subjects having a major comorbidity increasing the risk of surgery (prior stroke,
             severe hypertension, severe diabetes, or need for chronic anticoagulation other than
             aspirin).

          -  Subjects having any prior intracranial surgery.

          -  Subjects with a history of seizures.

          -  Subjects, who are immunocompromised.

          -  Subjects with an active infection.

          -  Subjects, who require diathermy, electroconvulsive therapy (ECT), or transcranial
             magnetic stimulation (TMS) to treat a chronic condition.

          -  Subjects, who have an inability to comply with study follow-up visits.

          -  Subjects, who are unable to understand or sign the informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Helen Bronte-Stewart, MD,MSE,FAAN</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 15, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 6, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Stanford University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Helen M. Bronte-Stewart</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Parkinson's Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>DBS</keyword>
  <keyword>Deep Brain Stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Subthalamic Nucleus</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
