<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="87224">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01747551</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-401</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01747551</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>FOLFOX +/- Ziv-Aflibercept for Esophageal and Gastric Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo Controlled Phase II Study of FOLFOX +/- Ziv-Aflibercept in Patients With Advanced Esophageal and Gastric Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research study is a Phase II clinical trial to test the safety and effectiveness of the
      investigational drug Ziv-aflibercept in combination with mFOLFOX6 compared to mFOLFOX6
      alone. The drugs used in mFOLFOX6 include Fluorouracil (5-FU), Leucovorin and Oxaliplatin.

      In patients with esophagogastric cancer, mFOLFOX6 has been used in both clinical trials and
      standard of care. &quot;Investigational&quot; means that the FDA has not yet approved this combination
      for the treatment of esophagogastric cancer.

      Every person has molecules in their bloodstream called vascular endothelial growth factors
      (VEGFs). These molecules help grow and sustain new blood vessels needed by the human body.
      Cancer tumors hijack this mechanism because they need new blood vessels and oxygen to grow.
      Ziv-aflibercept is an antibody, a &quot;targeted therapy&quot; called a &quot;VEGF Trap&quot;, that &quot;traps&quot;
      (binds) these VEGFs and prevents the cancer from using them to grow. Ziv-aflibercept has
      recently been approved by the FDA for patients with treatment-resistant colorectal cancer.
      Patients who received standard 5-fluoruracil based chemotherapy pus ziv-aflibercept lived
      significantly longer than those patients who received standard 5-fluoruracil alone.

      In this research study, investigators will see if adding ziv-aflibercept to standard
      chemotherapy (mFOLFOX6) works better than mFOLFOX6 chemotherapy alone in patients with
      metastatic or unresectable esophagogastric cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      If patients agree to participate in this research study, they will be asked to undergo some
      screening tests or procedures to find out if they are eligible. Many of these tests and
      procedures are likely to be part of regular cancer care and may be done even if it turns out
      that patients do not take part in this research study. If patients have had some of these
      tests or procedures recently, they may or may not have to be repeated. These tests and
      procedures include: a medical history, physical examination, EKG, CT, Blood tests, pregnancy
      test, urine test, additional blood tests for research and a collection of archival tumor
      tissue. The screening tests will be reviewed by the doctor and the study team and if the
      patient meets the eligibility criteria for this study, they will begin treatment. If the
      patient does not meet the eligibility criteria, they will not be able to participate in this
      research study.

      After the screening procedures confirm that a participant is eligible to participate in the
      research study, they will be &quot;randomized&quot; into one of two groups. A participant will receive
      either:

      mFOLFOX6 with Ziv-aflibercept -or- mFOLFOX6 with Placebo (A Placebo contains no medicine)

      Randomization means that a participant is put into a group by chance (like flipping a coin).
      Neither the participant nor the research doctor will choose what group the participant will
      be in. Randomization will be 2:1 (twice as many of the participants in this study will
      receive mFOLFOX6+Ziv-aflibercept). This study is &quot;blinded&quot;, which means neither the patient
      nor the doctor will know if the patient is getting the investigational drug or the placebo
      with the mFOLFOX6.

      Before a participant begins mFOLFOX6 chemotherapy, they will have a central venous line
      inserted for the intravenous (in a vein) chemotherapy administration. This is called a
      &quot;port&quot; or vascular access device. Insertion of the port is a minor outpatient surgical
      procedure that is performed by a surgeon or interventional radiologist depending on where it
      is done. The doctor will arrange for the participant to have this procedure done before the
      participant begins.

      mFOLFOX6 is a combination of chemotherapy including oxaliplatin, leucovorin, and 5-FU. The
      oxaliplatin and leucovorin are given intravenously over 2 hours. The 5-FU is also given
      intravenously. The participant will get a shot of 5-FU by the infusion nurse and then will
      be hooked up to a portable pump which will infuse the rest of the 5-FU slowly over the next
      46-48 hours. The participant can either disconnect the pump at home, or return to the
      infusion unit to have it disconnected. The participant, the caregivers and the nurse will
      discuss the best option for disconnecting the pump and the patient will receive instructions
      on how to do this at home, if applicable.

      Ziv-aflibercept/Placebo will be given over 1 hour intravenously.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimate efficacy of Ziv-aflibercept+mFOLFOX6 in esophagogastric adenocarcinomas, as measured by progression-free survival (PFS).</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To estimate the efficacy of Ziv-aflibercept used in combination with mFOLFOX6 in patients with previously untreated advanced esophagogastric adenocarcinoma, as measured by progression-free survival (PFS), measured from the date of initial treatment to first objective documentation of progressive disease or date of death, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate safety and tolerability of Ziv-aflibercept+mFOLFOX6 by evaluating toxicity and the number of adverse events.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of Ziv-aflibercept in combination with mFOLFOX6 vs. mFOLFOX6 alone in previously untreated patients with advanced esophagogastric adenocarcinoma</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate response rate using RECIST 1.1.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the response rate in previously untreated patients with advanced esophagogastric adenocarcinoma treated with Ziv-aflibercept in combination with mFOLFOX6 vs. mFOLFOX6 alone, using RECIST version 1.1 (Partial Response[PR], Complete Response [CR], Stable Disease [SD])</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimate duration of objective response</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To estimate duration of objective response and overall survival in patients treated with Ziv-aflibercept in combination with mFOLFOX6 vs. mFOLFOX6 alone</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate blood plasma levels</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate blood plasma levels of VEGFA and VEGFR2 (pVEGFA, pVEGFR2) as potential predictive biomarkers for treatment with Ziv-aflibercept, comparing patients treated with mFOLFOX6 alone versus mFOLFOX6 plus Ziv-aflibercept.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate baseline expression of tumor tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the baseline expression of tumor tissue neuropilin 1 (NRP 1), neuropilin 2 (NRP 2), transforming growth factor-b1 (TGFb-type1 receptor), and Smad 2/3 as potential predictive biomarkers for response to treatment with mFOLFOX 6 versus mFOLFOX6 plus Ziv-aflibercept.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">64</enrollment>
  <condition>Esophageal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Gastric Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>mFOLFOX6 + Ziv-aflibercept</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ziv-aflibercept given via intravenous infusion over 1 hour every 2 weeks mFOLFOX6 will be infused every 2 weeks: oxaliplatin IV over 2 hours, Folinic Acid IV over 2 hours, 5-FU IV bolus followed by continuous infusion via ambulatory infusion pump for 46-48 hours</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>mFOLFOX6 + Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ziv-aflibercept placebo given via intravenous infusion over 1 hour every 2 weeks mFOLFOX6 will be infused every 2 weeks: oxaliplatin IV over 2 hours, Folinic Acid IV over 2 hours, 5-FU IV bolus followed by continuous infusion via ambulatory infusion pump for 46-48 hours</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oxaliplatin</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>mFOLFOX6 + Ziv-aflibercept</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>mFOLFOX6 + Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Folinic Acid</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>mFOLFOX6 + Ziv-aflibercept</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>mFOLFOX6 + Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Leucovorin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>5-Fluorouracil</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>mFOLFOX6 + Ziv-aflibercept</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>mFOLFOX6 + Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>5-FU</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ziv-aflibercept</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>mFOLFOX6 + Ziv-aflibercept</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ziv-aflibercept Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>mFOLFOX6 + Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Confirmed adenocarcinoma of esophagus, GE junction or gastric origin

          -  Disease is not amenable to curative resection and is unresectable, locally advanced
             or metastatic

          -  Have not received any prior chemotherapy, investigative or biologic agents for
             esophagogastric cancer except in the neoadjuvant or adjuvant setting

          -  Any major surgery must be completed at least 4 weeks prior to study entry, minor
             procedures must be completed at least 2 weeks prior to study entry

          -  Vascular access device insertion should be performed at least 1 week prior to study
             entry. A central line is recommended for all participants

          -  Willing to use adequate contraception prior to study entry, for the duration of study
             participation and for 3 months after the last dose of Ziv-aflibercept/placebo

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of hypertension unless adequately controlled

          -  Evidence of active bleeding from primary tumor at time of study entry

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding

          -  Squamous cell carcinoma histology

          -  Prior treatment for advanced or metastatic disease

          -  Palliative radiation to &lt; 25% of bone marrow must have been completed 2 weeks prior
             to study entry, palliative RT to &gt; 25% must have been completed 4 weeks prior to
             study entry

          -  Known allergy to study agents

          -  Known dihydropyrimidine dehydrogenase deficiency or thymidylate kinase gene
             polymorphism predisposing participant to 5-FU toxicity

          -  History of symptomatic congestive heart failure

          -  Clinically significant peripheral arterial disease

          -  Grade 2 or higher sensory or motor neuropathy

          -  Serious unhealed wound, ulcers or bone fractures

          -  History of HIV positivity or hepatitis B or C

          -  History of abdominal fistula, wound dehiscence, GI perforation, intra abdominal
             abscess, uncontrolled GI bleeding or diverticulitis that required hospitalization
             within 6 months of study entry

          -  History of arterial thrombotic events

          -  History of CNS hemorrhage in past 6 months

          -  Use of warfarin

          -  History of prior or synchronous malignancy except if treated with curative intent
             more than 3 years prior to enrollment, or adequately treated non-melanoma skin
             cancers, cervical carcinoma in situ or prostatic intraepithelial neoplasia without
             evidence of prostate cancer

          -  Uncontrolled non-malignant illness

          -  Uncontrolled psychiatric illness
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter Enzinger, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Reasearch Line</last_name>
    <phone>617-632-5960</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Peter Enzinger, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-632-5960</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Enzinger, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02214</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eunice Kwak, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-724-4000</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eunice Kwak, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 7, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 5, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Peter C. Enzinger, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Advanced</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stomach Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fluorouracil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oxaliplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leucovorin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Folic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levoleucovorin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
