<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="147920">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01814787</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R01DK092717</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01814787</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Computer Automation for Diagnosis and Management of Childhood Type 2 Diabetes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Computer Automation for Diagnosis and Management of Childhood Type 2 Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Indiana University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Indiana University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Increasing rates of type 2 diabetes among children and adolescents has considerable
      long-term implications not only for the affected individuals, but also for society and the
      health system as a whole. Pediatricians have unique and important opportunities to screen
      for type 2 diabetes and to promote lifestyle modification for those children identified with
      pre-diabetes; yet implementation of these practices within the pediatric primary care
      setting is far from ideal. The purpose of this study is to implement the ADA screening
      guidelines for type 2 diabetes and clinical management prompts within a pediatric primary
      care setting using a computer decision support system (CDSS) developed by the investigators
      research group - the Child Health Improvement through Computer Automation (CHICA) system.
      The investigators hypothesize that the coupling of CDSS with ADA guidelines will result in
      greater compliance with ADA recommended screening procedures as well as better clinical
      management of children identified as having pre-diabetes or type 2 diabetes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      As the prevalence of obesity in the United States has risen, so too has the prevalence of
      type 2 diabetes, a disease typically associated with adults. The American Diabetes
      Association (ADA) has recommended screening children 10 years of age or older who are at
      substantial risk for the presence or development of type 2 diabetes. They also recommend
      that primary prevention efforts, such as lifestyle modification, be directed to high-risk
      children whose glucose levels are elevated but not yet diagnostic of diabetes. The choice of
      screening methodology remains controversial and implementation within the pediatric primary
      care setting is far from ideal. The purpose of this study is to implement the ADA screening
      guidelines for type 2 diabetes within pediatric primary care practices using a computer
      decision support system (CDSS) developed by the investigators research group - the Child
      Health Improvement through Computer Automation (CHICA) system.  Using the CHICA system the
      investigators will also be implementing clinical management prompts for the pediatrician
      caring for children with risk factors for type 2 diabetes, with impaired fasting glucose
      (IFG), or with fasting glucose indicating the possibility of diabetes. One of the greatest
      strengths of the CHICA system is its ability to implement evidence-based recommendations
      from authoritative sources, in this case the ADA, in a format that integrates easily into
      routine pediatric care; the system can therefore overcome many of the barriers described by
      pediatricians to the screening of type 2 diabetes in children.  While the use of CDSS is not
      new, its application within the pediatric population has not been as pervasive as in adult
      medicine.  Moreover, the application of CDSS to the screening, diagnosis and management of
      type 2 diabetes in children is relatively unexplored. The specific aims for this study are
      to: (1) Expand and modify an existing computer-based decision support system (CHICA), to
      identify those children 10 years of age or older who are at increased risk for type 2
      diabetes, to provide pediatric physicians guidelines to screen for type 2 diabetes, and to
      coordinate the diagnosis and long-term management of the condition and (2) Demonstrate both
      the feasibility and effectiveness of the CHICA Type 2 Diabetes Module to recognize those
      children in need of screening for type 2 diabetes and facilitate prompt diagnosis and
      management of the condition.  Phase one (Aim 1) focuses on programming and enhancements to
      the CHICA system and will take 12 months to complete.  Phase two consists of a randomized
      controlled trial conducted in four pediatric clinics in order to evaluate Aim 2.
      Randomization will be by clinic and the investigators hypothesize that the coupling of CDSS
      with ADA guidelines will result in greater compliance with ADA recommended screening
      procedures as well as better clinical management of children identified as having
      pre-diabetes or type 2 diabetes.  Phase two will begin in year 2 and continue through
      quarter 2 of year 4.  Phase three involves statistical analysis and manuscript preparation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Investigator), Primary Purpose: Screening</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children with documented risk factors for type 2 diabetes</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with documented risk factors for type 2 diabetes (&gt;85%BMI and 2 of 4 Risk Factors)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with documented risk factors for type 2 diabetes scheduled for FPG</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with documented risk factors for type 2 diabetes completing FPG</measure>
    <time_frame>12 monthes</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with documented risk factors for type 2 diabetes scheduled for follow-up appointment with pediatrician</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with documented risk factors for type 2 diabetes attending follow-up appointment with pediatrician</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with documented risk factors for type 2 diabetes with &quot;Positive&quot; FPG Lab results (FPG&gt;125)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with documented risk factors for type 2 diabetes &quot;Borderline&quot; FPG Lab results (125&gt;= FPG &gt; 100)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with documented risk factors for type 2 diabetes with &quot;Positive&quot; HbA1C (HbA1C &gt;= 6.5%)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with documented risk factors for type 2 diabetes with &quot;Borderline&quot; HbA1C (6.5% &gt; HbA1C &gt;= 5.7%)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with &quot;Borderline&quot; FPG or HbA1C Labs scheduled for OGTT</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with &quot;Borderline&quot; FPG or HbA1C Labs completing OGTT</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with &quot;Borderline&quot; FPG or HbA1C Labs scheduled for follow-up appointment with pediatrician</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with &quot;Borderline&quot; FPG or HbA1C Labs attending follow-up appointment with pediatrician</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with &quot;Borderline&quot; FPG or HbA1C Labs with &quot;Positive&quot; OGTT (OGTT &gt; 199)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with &quot;Positive&quot; FPG or HbA1C Lab results (FPG &gt; 125) or HbA1C ≥ 6.5%) referred to pediatric endocrinologist</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with &quot;Positive&quot; FPG or HbA1C Lab results (FPG &gt; 125) or HbA1C ≥ 6.5%) attending appointment with pediatric endocrinologist</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with &quot;Positive&quot; FPG or HbA1C Lab results (FPG &gt; 125) or HbA1C ≥ 6.5%) with follow-up letter sent to pediatrician by pediatric endocrinologist</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with OGTT &gt; 199 referred to pediatric endocrinologist</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with OGTT &gt; 199 attending appointment with pediatric endocrinologist</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with OGTT &gt; 199 with follow-up letter sent to pediatrician by pediatric endocrinologist</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with OGTT between 140 and 199) referred to pediatric endocrinologist</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with OGTT between 140 and 199) attending appointment with pediatric endocrinologist</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of children (ages 10 and older) with OGTT between 140 and 199) with follow-up letter sent to pediatrician by pediatric endocrinologist</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1400</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CHICA Type 2 Diabetes Module</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Children treated at the two intervention clinic sites will have be treated using the CHICA system AND will be provided access to the newly developed CHICA Type 2 Diabetes Module.  The CHICA Type 2 Diabetes Module will assist pediatricians in identification of those children 10 years of age or older who are at increased risk for type 2 diabetes, it will provide pediatric physicians guidelines to screen for type 2 diabetes, and it will coordinate the diagnosis and long-term management of the condition.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Those patients who are assigned to the control group will have the CHICA system but will NOT be cared for using the CHICA Type 2 Diabetes Module.  The CHICA system will notify the physician of the child's BMI percentile on the physician worksheet.  However, the CHICA system will not ask for any additional information related to risk factors for type 2 diabetes on the pre-screening form, no advice will be provided to the physician on the physician worksheet, nor will just-in-time documents or automated reminder calls be made available.  Identification of patients at risk for type 2 diabetes and care of those patients will occur through routine practices for that clinic.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CHICA Type 2 Diabetes Module</intervention_name>
    <description>Information with regard to family history of type 2 diabetes, race/ethnicity, and maternal history of gestational diabetes will be gathered for every patient, by asking these questions of parents on the pre-screener form. This data will then be utilized by the CHICA system when a child is age 10 or older and presents to the clinic. Data regarding the child's BMI at that time will be analyzed by the CHICA system. If the child's BMI is greater than the 85th percentile, a prompt will appear on the provider worksheet asking the clinician whether the child has any symptoms or conditions associated with insulin resistance. This information along with the data gathered previously from the pre-screener form will be analyzed to determine whether the child has 2 or more risk factors for the development of type 2 diabetes. If at least 2 risk factors are present, then the CHICA system goes on to coordinate the diagnosis and long-term management of type 2 diabetes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CHICA Type 2 Diabetes Module</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  A patient's chart will be eligible for chart abstraction if the child is age 10 or
             older and is a patient at one of the four clinics involved in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Aaron E Carroll, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Indiana University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tamara Hannon, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Indiana University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 6, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Type 2 Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Pediatrics</keyword>
  <keyword>Computerized Decision Support System</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
