<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="106048">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02092662</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UHai920130001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02092662</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Objective Assessment of Upper Extremity Functioning of Stroke Patients Before and After Rehabilitation</brief_title>
  <acronym>AssStrFunc</acronym>
  <official_title>Objective Assessment of Upper Extremity Functioning of Stroke Patients Before and After Rehabilitation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Carmeli Eli</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Haifa</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Israel: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate by objective measures the improvement in upper
      extremity functioning, as reflection of motor learning, in stroke patients in the sub acute
      phase. The investigators hypothesize that the improvements in daily functioning are
      partially due to compensation strategies and partially due to motor learning.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: Most stroke patients continue to suffer from upper extremity motor deficiencies
      even after prolonged and intense rehabilitation in hospital. Even though guidelines and
      other studies recommend to apply a rehabilitation programs as patient reception. As opposed
      to that there is a scarce evidence for the efficacy of the rehabilitation.

      Objectives: To evaluate by objective measures the improvement in motor performance of the
      upper extremity of stroke patients in the sub acute period. Secondary objective is to
      describe the correlation between proximal and distal motor deficiencies of the upper
      extremity.

      Hypothesis: Patients will show better hand performance at the end of hospitalization. Part
      of it can be attributed to the rehabilitation and part to a spontaneous recovery.
      Correlation will be found for proximal and distal upper extremity motor deficiencies.

      Methods:

      Trial began only after the IRB research approval. All treatment sessions will implemented by
      the physical and occupational staff of the hospital. Assessments for the measures will be
      carry out by a certified physical therapist which is coinvestigator. The coinvestigator
      collect the raw data for analysis in Excel and than in SPSS.

      20 stroke patients who meet the inclusion criteria will participate in the study, after
      signing an informed consent.Patients will undergo the first assessment of all measures, e.g:
      motor abilities by Fugl-Meyer test, handwriting kinematic and kinetic measures and surface
      electromyography for measurement of muscle synergy.Patients will be treated by standard
      rehabilitation of physical and occupational therapy for a period of 3-4 weeks. Before
      discharge from hospital patients will undergo another assessment of all measures, in order
      to evaluate the progression in their upper limb motor abilities from reception. Part of the
      patients will be assessed again two to three weeks after discharge as follow up.

      Outcome Measures: upper limb Fugl-Meyer assessment, handwriting Air-time, pressure and
      velocity, EMG (i.e., muscle onset, muscle amplitude, muscle co-activation ratio).

      Statistical analysis: ANOVA analysis will be used to measure time effect. Correlation
      between measures will be measured by Pearson`s correlation. Sample size (n=20) was
      calculated based on 5 points improvement in Fugl-Meyer test as minimal significant change
      with power of 0.8 and p-level under 0.05 for significance.

      Key words: Stroke, Muscle synergy, Handwriting, Fugl-Meyer
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <target_duration>5 Weeks</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from beginning of hospital stay to end of hospital stay of Upper Extremity Motor Function of Fugl-Meyer Assessment, by numeral point scale.</measure>
    <time_frame>The outcome will be measured twice. First at the beginning of the hospital stay and again at the end of the hospital stay, that is 4 weeks on average.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessment made by a physical therapist for the evaluation of upper extremity motor function.The patient asked to make upper extremity movements/tasks. The therapist gives a score for every task. The maximal score is 66 points indicate a good upper extremity motor function</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from beginning of hospital stay to end of hospital stay of surface Electromyographic Assessment of Muscle co-activation index, in percent from absolute co-activation as 100%.</measure>
    <time_frame>The outcome will be measured twice. First at the beginning of the hospital stay and again at the end of the hospital stay, that is 4 weeks on average.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessed by surface electromyography device. Indicate for the level by which muscles contract at the same time and amplitude. It will be calculated in percentage from 100%, as 100% indicate for complete co-activation between a pair of muscles.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from beginning of hospital stay to end of hospital stay of Handwriting velocity assessment by ComPET analyzing system by cm/sec</measure>
    <time_frame>The outcome will be measured twice. First at the beginning of the hospital stay and again at the end of the hospital stay, that is 4 weeks on average.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessed by electronic tablet with specific software called ComPET. Patient make writing tasks. The velocity of his writing is measured and pass from the tablet to the computer to be processed by the software.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from beginning of hospital stay to end of hospital stay of surface Electromyography assessment of Muscle onset time in mili-seconds units.</measure>
    <time_frame>The outcome will be measured twice. First at the beginning of the hospital stay and again at the end of the hospital stay, that is 4 weeks on average.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessed by surface electromyography device. The time period it takes the muscle to contract from a voice prompting is measured.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from beginning of hospital stay to end of hospital stay of Electromyographic assessment of Muscle amplitude analysis normalized to the maximum voluntary contraction of the same muscle. Calculated in percentage.</measure>
    <time_frame>The outcome will be measured twice. First at the beginning of the hospital stay and again at the end of the hospital stay, that is 4 weeks on average.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assess by surface electromyography device. Measure the level of effort of a specific muscle the patient exert in order to cry out a movement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from beginning of hospital stay to end of hospital stay of Handwriting pressure that will be assessed by ComPET analysis software, in gr. units.</measure>
    <time_frame>The outcome will be measured twice. First at the beginning of the hospital stay and again at the end of the hospital stay, that is 4 weeks on average.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessed by electronic tablet with specific software called ComPET. Patient make writing tasks, and the pressure exerted with the pen on the tablet is recorded. The data from the tablet passed to the computer to be processed by the software.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from beginning of hospital stay to end of hospital stay of Handwriting on-air time that will be assessed by ComPET analyzing system in mili-seconds units.</measure>
    <time_frame>The outcome will be measured twice. First at the beginning of the hospital stay and again at the end of the hospital stay, that is 4 weeks on average.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessed by electronic tablet with specific software called ComPET. Patient make writing tasks. The time the pen is on air is measured. The data from the tablet passed to the computer to be processed by the software.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Cohort will be selected from Fliman Rehabilitation Geriatric Center. Healthy subjects, age
        and gender-matched will be served as a control group.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  diagnosis of cerebral stroke with upper extremity hemiparesis

          -  Ability to understand simple orders

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Other orthopedic pathology

          -  Apraxia

          -  Bilateral Paresis

          -  Other neurologic pathology

          -  sensory aphasia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Emanuel Markovich, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fliman Geriatric Rehabilitation Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sharon Israely, MSc.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Haifa</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eli Carmeli, PhD.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Hifa</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sharon Israely, MSc.</last_name>
    <phone>972-523-755-091</phone>
    <email>sharonis@mh.org.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Eli Carmeli, PhD.</last_name>
    <phone>972-4-8288-397</phone>
    <email>ecarmeli@univ.haifa.ac.il</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fliman Geriatric Rehabilitation Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Haifa</city>
        <zip>31021</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sharon Israely, MSc.</last_name>
      <phone>972-523-755-091</phone>
      <email>sharonis@mh.org.il</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Eli Carmeli, PhD.</last_name>
      <phone>972-4-828-8397</phone>
      <email>ecarmeli@univ.haifa.ac.il</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 22, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 12, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Haifa</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carmeli Eli</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
