<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="75648">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02027844</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>JUNG999ANXIETY</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02027844</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cartoon Distraction and Parental Presence on Anxiety in Pediatric Anesthesia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cartoon Distraction and Parental Presence During Induction of Anesthesia on Preoperative Anxiety and Postoperative Behavior Change in Children Undergoing General Anesthesia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yeungnam University College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Yeungnam University College of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Korea: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Nearly 50% of young children undergoing surgery exhibit high level of anxiety during
      induction of anesthesia because of exposure to unfamiliar environment and people and
      separation from parents. Increased preoperative anxiety may impact postoperative behavior
      changes such as emergence agitation, separation anxiety and sleep disturbance. Although some
      pediatric anesthesiologists routinely permit parental presence to reduce the anxiety during
      induction of anesthesia, previous studies have  reported conflicting results. Recently the
      distraction using video game or animated cartoon has been reported to reduce anxiety of
      young children during induction of anesthesia. However, it was still undetermined whether
      distraction has its own ability to reduce children's anxiety separated from parental
      presence because they evaluated the effect of video method in the parental presence. The
      investigators design to investigated the efficacy of distraction with watching cartoon,
      parental presence and combined with watching cartoon and parental presence on reduction of
      anxiety during inhalational induction of anesthesia using sevoflurane. In addition this
      study includes long-term effect of each intervention such as postoperative emergence
      agitation and postoperative behavior change in children.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is different from previous reports as follow. First, investigators separate the
      effect of cartoon distraction and parental presence on minimizing preoperative anxiety and
      determine whether an interaction between two different interventions is existent. Second,
      investigators evaluate the effect of preoperative anxiety on the long-term behavioral change
      of children. It was not clarified yet in clinical practice. Third, investigators evaluate
      the effect of each intervention on parental anxiety before and after induction of
      anesthesia.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline anxiety at induction of anesthesia</measure>
    <time_frame>1. baseline (10 minute after arrival in the preoperative holding area) 2. on arrival in the operating room, 3. during inhalational induction with sevoflurane</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The investigators measure change in anxiety of children using Modified Yale Preoperative Anxiety scale (m-YPAS): Scale changes from Activities, Vocalization, Expressing emotions, State of arousal, Interaction with family members.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline parental anxiety at postinduction of anesthesia</measure>
    <time_frame>1. baseline:  15 minute  after arrival at preoperative holding area before induction of anesthesia 2. postinduction : after induction of anesthesia</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The investigators measure change of parental anxiety using State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative emergence delirium</measure>
    <time_frame>at 20 minute in postanesthetic care unit</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The investigators measure postoperative emergence delirium of children after recovery of anesthesia using Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario Pain(CHEOP) Scale at 20 minute in postanesthetic care unit</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative behavioral changes</measure>
    <time_frame>1. postoperative 1 day, 2 postoperative 14 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The investigators measure postoperative behavioral change of children after discharge of postanesthetic care unit using posthospital behavioral questionnaires( PHBQ ) at postoperative day (POD) 1 by visiting and followed at POD 14 by phone interview.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">66</enrollment>
  <condition>Anxiety, Separation</condition>
  <condition>Psychomotor Agitation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cartoon</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>cartoon watching by children during inhalational induction of anesthesia in the operating room</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Paretnal presence</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>parental presence with their children during inhalational induction of anesthesia in the operating room</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Combined</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>parental presence and cartoon watching by children during inhalational induction of anesthesia in the operating room</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cartoon</intervention_name>
    <description>Cartoon watching by children during inhalational induction of sevoflurane</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cartoon</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Combined</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cartoon watching by children</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>parental presence</intervention_name>
    <description>parental presence during inhalational induction of sevoflurane</description>
    <arm_group_label>Paretnal presence</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Combined</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>parental presence</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) physical status 1 and 2

          2. 1-7 years old.

          3. elective, single minor surgery under general anesthesia

        Exclusion Criteria:

        1.Chronic illness, psychological or emotional disorder, abnormal cognitive
        development 2.Previous anesthetic experience 3.Closure both eyes after surgery 4.Sedative
        medication or psychoactive drugs medication, 5.History of allergy to the drugs used in our
        study 6.Expected difficult intubation or respiration such as abnormal airway, reactive
        airway disease, upper respiratory infection in recent 3 weeks

        -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>7 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sung Mee Jung, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Yeungnam University College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sung Mee Jung, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+82-53-620-3368</phone>
    <email>applejsm@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yeungnam University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Daegu</city>
        <zip>705-717</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sung Mee Jung, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+82-53-620-3368</phone>
      <email>applejsm@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sung Mee Jung, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23051880</url>
    <description>Streamed video clips to reduce anxiety in children during inhaled induction of anesthesia</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23011563</url>
    <description>Cartoon distraction alleviates anxiety in children during induction of anesthesia</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 26, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 30, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Yeungnam University College of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sung Mee Jung</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychomotor Agitation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anxiety, Separation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
