<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="80761">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02102347</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>24568013.0.0000.5511</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02102347</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Phototherapy Incorporated Into an Exercise Program on Osteoarthritis of the Knee</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Phototherapy Incorporated Into an Exercise Program on Osteoarthritis of the Knee</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Nove de Julho</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Nove de Julho</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Brazil: National Committee of Ethics in Research</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of the proposed study is to analyze the effect of the incorporation of phototherapy
      into a therapeutic exercise program on static balance, pain, functional capacity, range of
      motion, muscle strength and quality of life in individuals with osteoarthritis of the knees.
      The participants will be allocated to different groups through a randomization process using
      opaque envelopes containing cards stipulating one of the three following groups: Group A
      (exercise protocol); Group B (exercise protocol + phototherapy protocol); and Group C
      (exercise protocol + placebo phototherapy protocol). Phototherapy will be performed on the
      knees diagnosed with osteoarthritis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Stabilometry</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This system quantifies the distribution of vertical ground reaction force in a static or dynamic position with a sampling frequency of 40 Hz using four sensors (2 anterior and 2 posterior) capable of supporting 150 Kg. The distribution of force on the four points and changes in body sway in the anteroposterior (Y axis) and mediolateral (X axis) directions will be evaluated using mean displacement and area. The force plate will be placed on a flat surface, which will be verified by levels attached to the extremities of the plate.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dynamometry</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A portable dynamometer will be used. Four five-second readings will be taken of maximum voluntary isometric contraction (MVIC) with a 30-second rest period between contractions. The volunteer hands will be crossed over the chest. Readings will be made of the quadriceps, gluteus medius and gluteus maximus (adapted), bilaterally.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">17</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis of the Knee</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>exercise group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>An exercise program will be performed to increase range of motion, improve motor learning and strengthen the muscles of the lower limb. The program will include three weekly 45-to-60-minute sessions over the course of eight weeks (24 sessions) and will be organized in three phases: 1) weeks 1 and 2, improvements in balance and coordination, each exercise will have 30 repetitions and two sets; 2) weeks 3 to 5, each exercise will have 20 repetitions and three sets; and 3) weeks 6 to 8, each exercise will have 20 repetitions and three sets.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>phototherapy group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Phototherapy will be administered with a portable nine-diode cluster. The portable nine-diode cluster will be used overlapping three quadrants of the knee in random sequence: medial quadrant, lateral quadrant and posterior quadrant.with one 905-nm diode (mean power: 1 milliwatt ; peak power: 10 megawatt; spot size: 0.44 cm2), four 875-nm diodes (mean power of each diode: 17.5 milliwatt; spot size: 1 cm2) and four 670-nm diodes (mean power of each diode: 15 mW; spot size: 1 cm2); frequency: 1000 Hz; 300-second irradiation time in each quadrant; total energy: 39.3 Joules per quadrant. Phototherapy will be included in the exercises group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phototherapy placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Phototherapy will be administered with a portable nine-diode cluster. The portable nine-diode cluster will be used overlapping three quadrants of the knee in random sequence: medial quadrant, lateral quadrant and posterior quadrant), with one 905-nm diode (mean power: 0 milliwatt; peak power: 0 watt; spot size: 0.44 cm2), four 875-nm diodes (mean power of each diode: 0 milliwatt; spot size: 1 cm2) and four 670-nm diodes (mean power of each diode: 0 milliwatt; spot size: 1 cm2); frequency: 0 Hz; 300-second irradiation time in each quadrant; total energy: 0 Joules per quadrant. Phototherapy will be included in the exercises group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>exercise</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>exercise group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>phototherapy group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phototherapy placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Phototherapy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>phototherapy group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phototherapy placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of osteoarthritis  of the knee (bilateral) according to criteria of the
             American College of Rheumatology

          -  age between 40 and 80 years

          -  either gender

          -  knee pain and functional disability for at least three months confirmed by historical
             medical.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Dementia

          -  neurological disorder (sensory or motor)

          -  cancer

          -  diabetes

          -  acute adverse health condition

          -  symptoms of osteoarthritis  of the hip

          -  cardiopulmonary disease that impedes walking

          -  need for wheelchair or gait-assistance device

          -  and having received steroids through intra-articular injection or orally in the
             previous six months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cid A Gomes, Msc</last_name>
    <phone>+5511970941936</phone>
    <email>cid.andre@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Nove de Julho</name>
      <address>
        <city>São Paulo</city>
        <zip>01504-001</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cid Gomes, Master of Science</last_name>
      <phone>+5511970941936</phone>
      <email>cid.andre@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cid Gomes, master of science</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.uninove.br</url>
    <description>Related Info</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 29, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Nove de Julho</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Cid André Fidelis de Paula Gomes</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Mcs</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Physical Therapy Modalities</keyword>
  <keyword>osteoarthritis</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
