<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="65326">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01741038</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ITL-007-ATCR-MBC</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01741038</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of AlloStim In-Situ Vaccine in Pre-Treated Metastatic Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II/III, Randomized, Double Blind, Parallel Arm Study Comparing AlloStim Combined With Cryoablation to Placebo Combined With Cryoablation in Anthracycline, Taxane and Capecitabine Pre-Treated Metastatic Breast Cancer.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Immunovative Therapies, Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Immunovative Therapies, Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Thailand: Ministry of Public Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a personalized anti-cancer vaccine protocol which includes an in-situ (in the body)
      cancer vaccine step which combines killing a single metastatic tumor lesion by use of
      cryoablation in order to cause the release of tumor-specific markers to the immune system
      and then injecting bioengineered allogeneic immune cells (AlloStim) into the lesion as an
      adjuvant in order to modulate the immune response and educate the immune system to kill
      other tumor cells where ever they reside in the body.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Breast cancer is the most prevalent malignancy in women affecting more than 1 million women
      a year and metastatic breast cancer (MBC) is a leading cause of mortality, accounting for
      more than 400,000 deaths annually worldwide. Anthracycline- and taxane-containing regimens
      have been established as the most effective chemotherapeutic agents for first- and
      second-line therapies in MBC with respect to a prolongation of survival time.   Because of
      this, more women are receiving anthracyclines and taxanes early in the treatment of the
      disease. Even despite this recent trend toward aggressive treatment of early stage breast
      cancer with anthracyclines and taxanes, nearly half of these women will have metastatic
      recurrence. The prior exposure to anthracycline and taxane drugs leaves women facing
      first-line therapy for metastatic recurrent disease resistant to anthracycline and taxane
      drugs and, thus, with limited treatment options. US FDA currently approved ixabepilone
      (Ixempra) and Havalan (Eribulin) in this setting, but these drugs have not been shown to
      provide a survival advantage compared to capecitabine (Xeloda). However, only approximately
      25% of MBC patients respond to capecitabine. In addition, these approved drugs and other
      chemotherapy drug options have significant toxicity profiles. Accordingly, there is a need
      for new effective treatments for women with MBC that have been previously pre-treated with
      taxane, anthracycline and capecitabine. This study is designed to determine if AlloStim will
      provide a survival benefit to these woman.

      Resistance to anthracycline and taxane is defined clinically as disease recurrence within 6
      months of completion of adjuvant or neoadjuvant treatment with these agents or tumor
      progression that occurs during treatment or within 3 months of the last dose of treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>the ITT population from randomization within 30 days of accrual to death for any cause followed for up to 2 years from date of randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess whether cryoablation combined with AlloStim treatment (arm 1) provides an overall survival (OS) advantage when compared to treatment with cryoablation combined with placebo (arm 2).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>from randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety will be evaluated by physical exam, changes in laboratory values and patient reported symptoms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunological Response</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>blood samples will be evaluated for immunological response and a determination made as to whether immunological response correlates with survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">208</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AlloStim treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The protocol treatment schedule includes: (1) the priming step with ID injection of study drug (1ml) on Days 0 and 3, both injections in the same location.  Additional ID injection in a different location on day 7 and in the same location as day 7 again on day 10; (2) the ablation step with cryoablation and intralesional study drug injection (3ml) and KLH injection on day 14, and intralesional study drug (3ml) again into the same cryoablated lesion on day 17, and (3) the activation step with an IV study drug infusion on Day 21.  Thereafter, two intravenous booster infusions are provided on days 49 and 77. Protocol follow-up procedures continue until day 168 and at investigator discretion thereafter. All subjects are followed for as long as they are living thereafter.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The placebo protocol treatment schedule is identical to the treatment arm with placebo substituted for the study drug and includes: (1) the priming step with ID injection of placebo(1ml) on Days 0 and 3, both injections in the same location.  Additional ID injection in a different location on day 7 and in the same location as day 7 again on day 10; (2) the ablation step with cryoablation and intralesional placebo injection (3ml) and KLH injection on day 14, and intralesional placebo(3ml) again into the same cryoablated lesion on day 17, and (3) the activation step with an IV placebo infusion on Day 21.  Thereafter, two intravenous booster infusions are provided on days 49 and 77. Protocol follow-up procedures continue until day 168 and at investigator discretion thereafter. All subjects are followed for as long as they are living thereafter.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AlloStim</intervention_name>
    <description>AlloStim is derived from the blood of normal blood donors and is intentionally mismatched to the recipient. CD4+ T-cells are separated from the blood and differentiated and expanded for 9-days in culture to make an intermediary called T-Stim. AlloStim is made by incubating T-Stim cells for 4h with antibody coated microbeads. The cells with the beads still attached are suspended in infusion media and loaded into syringes. The syringes are shipped refrigerated to the point-of-care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>AlloStim treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cryoablation</intervention_name>
    <description>percutaneous ablation of a single metastatic tumor lesion usually in liver or bone.  The procedure is conducted under CT or ultrasound image-guidance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>AlloStim treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women with histologically or cytologically confirmed carcinoma of the breast.

          -  Documented progressive metastatic disease not amenable to curative surgery or
             radiotherapy.

          -  Age ≥18 and ≤70 years

          -  Patients must have prior treatments that have included capecitabine and both an
             anthracycline and a taxane drug and must be resistant to taxane therapy.

               -  Patients must have received a minimum cumulative dose of anthracycline (≥ 180
                  mg/m² of doxorubicin or ≥ 300 mg/m² of epirubicin) or be resistant to an
                  anthracycline and resistant to capecitabine and anti-hormonal therapy (ER+
                  patients).

               -  Resistance is defined as tumor progression while receiving treatment or
                  progression within 4 months of the last dose in the metastatic setting, or
                  recurrence within 12 months in the neoadjuvant or adjuvant setting.

          -  Post-menopausal ER+ and/or PR+ patients must have received at least two lines of
             prior anti-estrogen therapy, which includes an aromatase inhibitor.

          -  Her2+ patients must have received at least one Her2+ targeted regimen containing
             trastuzumab alone or with pertuzumab or with lapatinib.  Patients who have been
             treated with trastuzumab or pertuzumab must have discontinued therapy at least 4
             weeks prior to randomization.

          -  Prior radiation therapy must be completed at least 4 weeks before randomization.

          -  Measurable disease according to revised RECIST v.1.1 guidelines with at least one
             lesion deemed to be safely accessible for serial biopsy.

          -  ECOG &lt;2

          -  Adequate hematological function

               -  Absolute granulocyte count ≥ 1,500/mm3

               -  Platelet count ≥ 100,000/mm3

               -  PT/INR ≤ 1.5

               -  INR correctable to ≤ 1.5 or a PT/PTT correctable to normal limits. Patients
                  receiving anti-coagulation treatment with an agent such as warfarin or heparin
                  may be allowed to participate. For patients on warfarin, the INR should be
                  monitored weekly prior to any intervention to assure INR is stable. However,
                  heparin or warfarin must be withheld prior to biopsy such that the above
                  criteria are met.

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dL (may be corrected by transfusion)

          -  Adequate organ function.

               -  Creatinine ≤  1.5 mg/dL

               -  Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 times upper limit of  normal (ULN)

               -  Alkaline phosphatase ≤ 2.5 times ULN (≤ 5 times normal if liver involvement)

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) or (SGOT) ≤ 5.0 times ULN

               -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or  (SGPT) ≤ 5.0 times ULN

          -  EKG without clinically relevant abnormalities

          -  Pre-menopausal patients with child bearing potential must agree to use adequate
             contraception.

          -  Study specific informed consent in the native language of the subject.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Peritoneal carcinomatosis

          -  Moderate to large ascites accumulation requiring or likely to require paracentesis

          -  Clinical evidence or radiological evidence of brain metastasis or leptomeningeal
             involvement.

          -  Pulmonary lymphangitis or symptomatic pleural effusion (grade ≥ 2) that results in
             pulmonary dysfunction requiring active treatment.

          -  History of second primary malignancy, except: bilateral breast carcinoma, in situ
             carcinoma of the cervix, adequately treated non-melanomatous carcinoma of the skin,
             and other malignancy treated at least 5 years previously with no evidence of
             recurrence.

          -  Patients having received &gt; 3 regimens of prior chemotherapy for metastatic disease

          -  History of severe hypersensitivity to monoclonal antibody drugs or any
             contraindication to any of the study drugs.

          -  Pregnant or breast feeding

          -  Patients who have any serious, concurrent uncontrolled medical disorder

          -  Prior hepatectomy, liver chemoembolization, liver cryoablation or RFA

          -  Symptomatic pulmonary disease

          -  Bevacizumab (Avastin®) within 3 weeks of accrual

          -  Prior allogeneic bone marrow/stem cell or solid organ transplant

          -  Chronic use (&gt; 2 weeks) of greater than physiologic doses of a corticosteroid agent
             (dose equivalent to &gt; 10 mg/day of prednisone) within 30 days of the first day of
             investigational product treatment.

             - Topical and inhaled corticosteroids are permitted

          -  Concomitant active autoimmune disease (e.g., rheumatoid arthritis, multiple
             sclerosis, autoimmune thyroid disease, uveitis)

          -  Prior experimental therapy or cancer vaccine treatment (e.g., dendritic cell therapy,
             heat shock vaccine)

          -  Current immunosuppressive therapy, including: cyclosporine, antithymocyte globulin,
             or tacrolimus within 1 month of study entry.

          -  History of blood transfusion reactions

          -  Known allergy to bovine products

          -  Know allergy to murine products

          -  Progressive viral or bacterial infection

             - All infections must be resolved and the patient must remain afebrile for seven days
             without antibiotics prior to being placed into the study

          -  Cardiac disease of symptomatic nature or cardiac ejection fraction &lt; 45%

          -  History of HIV positivity or AIDS

          -  Psychiatric or addictive disorders or other condition that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, would preclude study participation

          -  Concurrent medication known to interfere with platelet function or coagulation (e.g.,
             aspirin, ibuprofen, clopidogrel, or warfarin) unless such medications can be
             discontinued for an appropriate time period based on the drug half-life and known
             activity (e.g., aspirin for 7 days)  prior to cryoablation/RFA procedure.

          -  Use of low molecular weight heparin preparations unless can be discontinued 8 hours
             prior to cryoablation or RFA.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wirote Lausoontornsiri, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute of Thailand</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zivile Katiliene, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Immunovative Clinical Research, Inc</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Zivile Katiliene, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>1-760-444-9040</phone>
    <email>zivile@immunovative.co.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Thu Bui, BS</last_name>
    <phone>1-760-444-9040</phone>
    <email>thu@immunovative.co.il</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cancer Institute of Thailand</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangkok</city>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Supranee Kongpinyopanich, MS</last_name>
      <phone>+66-2-354-3273</phone>
      <email>mumhoo1@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Wirote Lausoontornsiri, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Thailand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Har-Noy M, Zeira M, Weiss L, Fingerut E, Or R, Slavin S. Allogeneic CD3/CD28 cross-linked Th1 memory cells provide potent adjuvant effects for active immunotherapy of leukemia/lymphoma. Leuk Res. 2008 Sep 30; [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>18834631</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Har-Noy M, Zeira M, Weiss L, Slavin S. Completely mismatched allogeneic CD3/CD28 cross-linked Th1 memory cells elicit anti-leukemia effects in unconditioned hosts without GVHD toxicity. Leuk Res. 2008 Jun 17; [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>18565579</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Har-Noy M, Slavin S. The anti-tumor effect of allogeneic bone marrow/stem cell transplant without graft vs. host disease toxicity and without a matched donor requirement? Med Hypotheses. 2007 Dec 1; [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>18054441</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 21, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 29, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cancer vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>AlloStim</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunovative</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Allogeneic cell therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>cryoablation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
