<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="33635">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02134119</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BRL-23C403</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>BRL-23C403</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02134119</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Echinacea-based Supplement Does Not Improve Markers of Performance in Athletes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Echinacea-based Supplement Does Not Improve Markers of Performance in Athletes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Texas Tech University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Texas Tech University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study was three-fold. We wanted to (1) determine if supplementation with
      an echinacea-based dietary supplement (ECH) would increase several blood parameters that
      could affect oxygen carrying capacity in the body, (2) determine if ECH would increase
      VO2max in trained endurance athletes, and (3) examine the effectiveness of two different
      doses of the ECH on all outcome variables. We hypothesized that supplementation with ECH
      would increase oxygen carrying capacity (as measured by RBCs, EPO, ferritin, hemoglobin
      (Hb), and hematocrit (Hct) levels), improve VO2max, and that the maximum dose would be most
      effective at increasing these outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The supplement industry is a multi-billion dollar industry with many of the products
      targeted toward athletes and achieving optimal performance.  Historically, endurance
      athletes have used a number of methods to try to increase erythrocyte (red blood cell-RBC)
      production in attempts to boost oxygen carrying capacity and perform better during aerobic
      exercise.  A number of growth factors in the body can stimulate RBC production including
      erythropoietin (EPO).  EPO is the primary growth factor that promotes the formation and
      release of RBCs from bone marrow.  Although EPO itself is a banned substance, supplement
      companies have sought other means by which they can increase EPO production in the body in
      order to stimulate RBC synthesis.  One natural product toted to stimulate EPO production is
      Echinacea and can be found in the product EPO-Boost™.  Our global hypothesis is that
      supplementation of EPO-Boost™ will be an effective way to increase oxygen carrying capacity
      and improve maximal oxygen consumption in adult endurance athletes.

      We will test whether EPO-Boost™ affects EPO levels, a number of blood parameters, and VO2max
      (maximal aerobic capacity) by recruiting 40 trained endurance athletes (20 males and 20
      females).  To be included, subjects must already be performing aerobic exercise at least 4
      days per week for a minimum of one hour each day.  Participants will be randomly assigned
      (within gender) to either the placebo (n=20) or supplement group (n=20).  A 25% dropout rate
      may be expected in both genders, therefore we are recruiting a subject number of 40
      participants to ensure that at least 30 subjects will complete the study.  All participants
      will be blinded as to whether they are receiving the placebo or the supplement.
      Participants will report to the Human Nutrition Lab (HNL) and the Exercise Physiology Lab
      for baseline testing.  Height, body weight, body composition, and blood samples will be
      obtained.  Participants will then answer questions regarding their current and usual
      exercise patterns.  These questions will address the type, frequency, duration, and
      intensity of exercise.  Finally, participants will perform a VO2max test in the Exercise
      Physiology Lab.  After baseline testing the participants will be given a supply of either
      EPO-Boost™ or placebo along with extra capsules.  The subjects will not know whether they
      are receiving the product or the placebo.  Participants will also be asked to consume a
      multivitamin pill daily for the entire 35-day intervention period.  Finally, participants
      will be asked to keep an exercise log during the 35-day intervention documenting type,
      duration, intensity, and days of exercise in order for research personnel to ensure that
      exercise training is not changing.  The capsule and exercise logs will be collected at days
      14 and 35.

      Blood collected during all 3 visits will be analyzed for EPO, ferritin, RBCs, white blood
      cells, hemoglobin, hematocrit, mean corpuscular volume, mean corpuscular hemoglobin, and
      mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration.  We will assess changes in blood parameters and
      VO2max to determine whether 35 days of EPO-Boost™ supplementation improves blood parameters
      or maximal aerobic capacity compared to placebo controls.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject)</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>VO2 Max</measure>
    <time_frame>35-days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hematological measures</measure>
    <time_frame>35 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>as measured by red blood cells (RBCs) at day 0 (baseline), day 14 (mid-intervention) and day 35 (post-intervention)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hematological measures</measure>
    <time_frame>35 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>as measured by erythropoietin (EPO) at day 0 (baseline), day 14 (mid-intervention) and day 35 (post-intervention)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hematological measures</measure>
    <time_frame>35 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>as measured by ferritin at day 0 (baseline), day 14 (mid-intervention) and day 35 (post-intervention)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hematological measures</measure>
    <time_frame>35 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>as measured by hemoglobin (Hb) at day 0 (baseline), day 14 (mid-intervention) and day 35 (post-intervention)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hematological measures</measure>
    <time_frame>35 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>as measured by hematocrit (Hct) at day 0 (baseline), day 14 (mid-intervention) and day 35 (post-intervention)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Ineffective Erythropoiesis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Echinacea-based dietary supplement</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Echinacea-based dietary supplement 4,000mg/day or 8,000mg/day by mouth for 35-days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo given 4,000mg/day by mouth</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Echinacea-based dietary supplement</intervention_name>
    <description>Echinacea-based dietary supplement given at 4,000mg/day by mouth</description>
    <arm_group_label>Echinacea-based dietary supplement</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Echinacea-based dietary supplement</intervention_name>
    <description>Echinacea-based dietary supplement given at 8,000mg/day by mouth</description>
    <arm_group_label>Echinacea-based dietary supplement</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Sugar pill manufactured to mimic echinacea-based dietary supplement</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar pill</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sugar pill manufactured to mimic dietary supplement</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and female endurance athletes between the ages of 18-44

          -  Normal body mass index (BMI) between 18.5-24.9kg/m2.

          -  Individuals must currently be performing aerobic exercise at least 4 days per week
             for a minimum of 60 minutes at each session.

          -  They must also be willing to maintain their current training regimen through the
             course of the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any changes in altitude during the study (where they are living or training)

          -  Recent altitude training or use of a hypobaric chamber (within the last 6 months)

          -  Any other supplements or ergogenic aids (excluding multivitamins)

          -  Any participant who will be changing their current exercise training program during
             the study (includes changes in volume, frequency, or intensity)

          -  If any participant is pregnant, breastfeeding, or planning to become pregnant before
             this study would finish

          -  Any blood transfusions or blood donation in the past 16 weeks

          -  Any chronic diseases such as cardiovascular disease, renal disease, or diabetes

          -  Any condition that affects their ability to perform maximal exercise
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>44 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jamie A Cooper, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Texas Tech University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Texas Tech University - Department of Nutritional Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lubbock</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>79409</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Whitehead MT, Martin TD, Scheett TP, Webster MJ. The effect of 4 wk of oral echinacea supplementation on serum erythropoietin and indices of erythropoietic status. Int J Sport Nutr Exerc Metab. 2007 Aug;17(4):378-90.</citation>
    <PMID>17962712</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 6, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 2, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Texas Tech University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jamie Cooper</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>dietary supplement</keyword>
  <keyword>endurance athletes</keyword>
  <keyword>VO2max</keyword>
  <keyword>red blood cells</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
