<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="109270">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01912664</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU00052134</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01912664</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Online Peer Networked Collaborative Learning for Managing Depressive Symptoms</brief_title>
  <official_title>Online Peer Networked Collaborative Learning for Managing Depressive Symptoms</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northwestern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwestern University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The mission of this project is to develop novel systems of care that can provide
      efficacious, scalable, cost-effective, participant friendly technology assisted behavioral
      interventions (TABIs) for the treatment of depression in adults. The investigators define
      TABIs as interventions that use information and telecommunications technologies such as the
      internet, mobile or traditional phones, computers and/or other technologies to support and
      deliver psychological and behavioral interventions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Depression is common, with one-year prevalence rates of major depressive disorder (MDD)
      estimated to be between 6.6-10.3% in the general population. Depression imposes a very high
      societal burden in terms of cost, morbidity, suffering, and mortality.  Research has
      consistently found psychotherapy and pharmacotherapy to be equivalent in efficacy, however,
      primary care patients have consistently been shown to prefer psychotherapy or counseling to
      pharmacotherapy.  Yet only about 20% of all patients referred for psychotherapy ever enter
      treatment and of those who initiate treatment, nearly half drop out before completion.  This
      suggests that there are significant barriers to receiving psychotherapy.  Indeed, 75% of
      depressed primary care patients identify one or more practical barriers that prevent them
      from accessing psychotherapy.

      The need to develop treatments that can be delivered via telecommunications technologies has
      frequently been voiced.   The internet promises to provide inexpensive access to treatment
      at any time of the day or night. In addition internet interventions are very scalable and
      fidelity in clinical implementation should be excellent, since a website tested in a
      randomized controlled trial (RCT) can be delivered thereafter without alterations.
      Unfortunately, the potential for internet delivered services has not been realized.  Studies
      examining treatments that simply provide access to an internet site commonly result in very
      high dropout after the first site visit, and typically little or no improvement target
      symptoms.  To mitigate these problems, investigators have examined whether providing support
      via email or brief calls from research assistants can increase adherence. Both have shown
      promise in increasing adherence. Another type of support recently being investigated is the
      use of social networks where participants encourage each other to adhere to the
      intervention.

      The investigators are developing an intervention that utilizes multiple telecommunications
      technologies to improve mental health care access for individuals with depression.  The
      intervention uses an interactive website, e-mail and an online social network.

      The objective of this study is to examine

        1. To collect pilot data on the efficacy of a web-based intervention with a social network
           to reduce symptoms of depression

        2. To collect pilot data on adherence and usability of the web intervention.

        3. To collect field trial data on the efficacy of web-based interventions on assertiveness
           and depression.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout participation, lasting up to 14 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Depression as measured by the Patient Health Questionnaire 9 (PHQ-9) and Quick Inventory for Depression - Clinician (QIDS-C)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assertiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout participation, lasting up to 14 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assertiveness as measured by the Rathus Assertiveness Scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Assertiveness</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Web-based Peer Networked Support</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Web-based Virtual Human</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  PHQ-9 of 10 or higher.

          -  Has a DSM-IV diagnosis of Major Depressive Episode assessed using the MINI (social
             networking site only).

          -  Score below 50% on Rathus Assertiveness Scale (virtual human site only).

          -  Has a telephone, e-mail account, computer, and broadband access to the Internet.

          -  Is able to speak and read English.

          -  Is at least 19 years of age.

          -  Is able to give informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has hearing or voice impairment that would prevent participation in psychotherapy

          -  Has visual impairment that would prevent use of the workbook and completion of
             assessment materials.

          -  Is diagnosed with a psychotic disorder, bipolar disorder, dissociative disorder,
             current post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD), current substance abuse, or other
             diagnosis for which participation in a clinical trial of psychotherapy may be either
             inappropriate or dangerous. Patients with substance abuse diagnoses who have been
             clean and sober for 3 months will be admitted if otherwise eligible.

          -  Is currently receiving individual psychotherapy or planning to receive psychotherapy
             during the 10-week treatment phase of the study (social networking site only)

          -  Is planning to be out of town or unavailable for treatment for 4 weeks or more during
             the scheduled treatment time.

          -  Exhibits severe suicidality, including ideation, plan, and intent.

          -  Has initiated treatment with an antidepressant in past 10 days.  Once patients have
             been on a stable dose for 10 days and do not have an appointment with a physician or
             psychiatrist to change this dose, the patient will be eligible based on this
             criterion (social networking site only).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marya E Corden, MPH, CPH</last_name>
      <phone>312-503-1849</phone>
      <email>m-corden@northwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Joyce Ho, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>312-503-5387</phone>
      <email>j-ho@northwestern.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David C Mohr, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 30, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 29, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Northwestern University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Mohr</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Center for Behavioral Intervention Technologies; Professor, Department of Preventive Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Assertiveness</keyword>
  <keyword>Web-based Intervention</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
