<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="43359">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01670825</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>373481-3</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01670825</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pulsed Radiofrequency vs. Steroid Injections for Occipital Neuralgia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized, Double-blind, Comparative-effectiveness Study Comparing Corticosteroid Injections to Pulsed Radiofrequency for Occipital Neuralgia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Naval Hospital San Diego</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Landstuhl Regional Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Madigan Army Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Portsmouth Naval Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to determine whether pulsed radiofrequency or steroids are better
      for occipital neuralgia.  Seventy-six patients with ON or migraine with tenderness over the
      occipital nerve who respond to occipital nerve blocks (hereafter included under the broad
      category &quot;ON&quot;) will be randomized in a 1:1 ratio to receive either corticosteroid and local
      anesthetic injections (n=38) or local anesthetic and PRF of the occipital nerve(s) (n=38)
      for occipital neuralgia.  Both patients and the treating &amp; evaluating physicians will be
      blinded.  The first follow-up visit will be at 6 weeks.  Patients who obtain significant
      pain relief will remain in the study.  Those patients who fail to obtain any benefit will
      exit the study and be allowed to crossover to the other treatments or receive alternative
      care.  The second follow-up will be at 3 months and the final follow-up will be at 6-months
      post-procedure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Up to 76 patients referred to one of the participating pain clinic with occipital neuralgia,
      or migraines with occipital nerve tenderness (dual diagnoses) will be randomized in a 1:1
      ratio by a computer generated randomization table to receive one of two treatments.
      Treatments will be randomized at each institution.  Within each group, those patients with
      plain occipital neuralgia, and those with occipital neuralgia with migraines, will be
      sub-randomized in the same 1:1 ratio.  Diagnosis of ON will be made by low-volume (&lt; 3 mL
      bupivacaine per nerve).  Our criterion for a positive response will be &gt; 50% pain relief
      lasting at least 3 hours.  Those individuals who have symptoms in the distribution of both
      the greater and lesser occipital nerves will receive treatment of both nerves.  The greater
      occipital nerve is more frequently affected than the lesser nerve.

      Half (n=38) of the patients will be allocated to receive local anesthetic &amp; corticosteroid
      injections at each nerve (group I), with an equal number allocated to receive local
      anesthetic &amp; PRF at each (group II).  In those patients who request sedation, an intravenous
      will be inserted and light sedation administered with low doses of midazolam and fentanyl,
      in accordance with our standard clinic practice.  Treatment in all patients will be
      accomplished using 20-gauge radiofrequency needles with 10 mm active tips.  Prior to
      treating, electrical stimulation will be performed to ensure ample proximity to the targeted
      nerve(s), with our target threshold being concordant stimulation at &lt; 0.3 volts at each
      site.

      Once proper needle position is ensured, those in group I will receive an injection at each
      nerve containing 30 mg of depomethylprednisolone mixed with 2 mL of a 50:50 mixture of 2%
      lidocaine and 0.5% bupivacaine (2.75 mL).  Anywhere between 1 and 4 nerves can be injected,
      with 4 nerves being targeted if a patient had bilateral lesser and greater occipital nerve
      involvement.  This will be followed by 3 cycles of sham PRF at 120 s per cycle, with slight
      (approximately 30o electrode adjustments between cycles.  For sham PRF, no electrical field
      or heat is generated (i.e. the machine is not set to any radiofrequency cycle after
      stimulation), but the cycle times (120 s per cycle) are adhered to (i.e. we will wait a
      total of 6&quot;, 2&quot; per cycle).  Those patients in group II will receive injections at each
      nerve containing 2.75 mL of a solution with 2 mL of 50:50 2% lidocaine and 0.5% bupivacaine
      + 0.75 mL saline (2.75 mL), followed by 3 cycles of PRF using the following standard
      settings: voltage output 40-60 V; 2 Hz frequency; 20 ms pulses in a 1-second cycle, 120
      second duration per cycle; impedance range between 150 and 400 Ohms; and 42o C plateau
      temperature.

      No patient will be prescribed additional medications or therapy between their procedure and
      first follow-up.  However, they will be allowed to remain on their current, stable analgesic
      regimen.  Rescue medications will consist of tramadol 50 mg 1 to 2 tablets  every 6 hours
      PRN (up to 8/d) and/or acetaminophen or a non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drug such as
      ibuprofen, diclofenac or ketorolac  on an &quot;as needed&quot; basis.

      Follow-ups will be performed by a physician blinded to treatment allocation.  The first
      follow-up visit will be scheduled 6-weeks from the start of treatment.  A positive outcome
      will be defined as a &gt; 50% decrease in headache coupled with a positive satisfaction rating
      (&gt; 3 on a 0-5 scale).  Subjects who obtain a positive outcome at their initial 6-week
      follow-up visit will remain in the study and return for their 3-month follow-up visit.
      Those with a negative outcome will exit the study &quot;per protocol&quot; to receive standard care.
      Subjects who obtain a positive outcome at 1-month but experience a recurrence before their
      3-month follow-up visit will also exit the study per protocol, with their final outcome
      measures recorded before they receive standard care.  Those who obtain a positive outcome at
      3-months will remain in the study for their final 6-month follow-up, while those who obtain
      a negative outcome will exit the study.  Unblinding for both patients and the treating
      physician will be after the patient exits the study or after their final follow-up visit for
      those with continued benefit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Average pain score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks after treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>0-10 pain score at 6 weeks after treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of headache days with severe headache</measure>
    <time_frame>6-weeks after treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of days with headache greater or equal to 7/10 in past week</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>6-weeks after treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measurement of depression 6-weeks after treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disability</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks after treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measurement of headache-related disability 6 weeks after treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Average pain score</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>0-10 pain score 3 months after treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of days with severe headache</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of days per week with headache greater or equal to 7/10 3 months post-treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measurement of depression 3 months after treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disability</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measurement of headache-related disability 3 months after treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Average pain score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>0-10 pain score 6 months after treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of days with severe headache</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of days per week with headache greater or equal to 7/10 6 months post-treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measurement of depression 6 months after treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disability</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measurement of headache-related disability 6 months after treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">76</enrollment>
  <condition>Occipital Neuralgia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pulsed radiofrequency + local anesthetic injection</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Local anesthetic injection plus pulsed radiofrequency over each affected occipital nerve</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Corticosteroid injection + sham pulsed radiofrequency</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Injection with corticosteroid and local anesthetic over the occipital nerve(s)plus &quot;sham&quot; pulsed radiofrequency</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pulsed radiofrequency</intervention_name>
    <description>Local anesthetic injection and pulsed radiofrequency treatment x 6 minutes over each affected occipital nerve</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pulsed radiofrequency + local anesthetic injection</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Corticosteroid injection</intervention_name>
    <description>Corticosteroid and local anesthetic injection plus sham pulsed radiofrequency over each affected occipital nerve</description>
    <arm_group_label>Corticosteroid injection + sham pulsed radiofrequency</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age greater or equal to 18 years

          2. Occipital neuralgia diagnosed based on history &amp; physical exam and diagnostic local
             anesthetic blocks, or migraine with occipital nerve(s) tenderness that responds to
             diagnostic blocks.

             a. Greater or equal to 50% relief based on diagnostic local anesthetic block of the
             greater and/ or lesser occipital nerves that lasts for at least 90 minutes with
             lidocaine or 3 hours with bupivacaine or ropivacaine 20

          3. Baseline Numerical Rating Scale average pain score &gt; 4/10

          4. Frequency of greater or equal to 4/10 pain for at least 10 days per month

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Untreated coagulopathy

          2. Automatic implantable cardiac defibrillator or pacemaker that cannot be temporarily
             disabled for medical reasons

          3. Previous pulsed radiofrequency

          4. Other sources of headache, such as tension-type headache, cervicogenic headache,
             migraine headache without occipital neuralgia, and other causes (e.g. tumors,
             congenital abnormalities etc.).  Those that can be confused with ON must be excluded
             based on history and exam (e.g. cervicogenic headaches), symptoms (tension-type
             headache), response to blocks (all of the above); and lab work (temporal arteritis,
             which would be confirmed by biopsy after an elevated erythrocyte sedimentation rate).

          5. Serious medical or uncontrolled or severe psychiatric -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Steven P Cohen, MD</last_name>
    <phone>410-955-1822</phone>
    <email>scohen40@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Connie Kurihara, RN</last_name>
    <phone>301-400-2595</phone>
    <email>conniekurihara@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven P Cohen, MD</last_name>
      <phone>410-955-1822</phone>
      <email>scohen40@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Lee Peterlin, MD</last_name>
      <phone>410-550-9550</phone>
      <email>lpeterlin@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steven Cohen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lee Peterlin, DO</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Walter Reed National Military Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20889</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Connie Kurihara, RN</last_name>
      <phone>301-400-2595</phone>
      <email>conniekurihara@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steven P Cohen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Jamison, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Jacobs, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huang JH, Galvagno SM Jr, Hameed M, Wilkinson I, Erdek MA, Patel A, Buckenmaier C 3rd, Rosenberg J, Cohen SP. Occipital nerve pulsed radiofrequency treatment: a multi-center study evaluating predictors of outcome. Pain Med. 2012 Apr;13(4):489-97. doi: 10.1111/j.1526-4637.2012.01348.x. Epub 2012 Mar 5. PubMed PMID: 22390409.</citation>
    <PMID>22390409</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vanelderen P, Rouwette T, De Vooght P, Puylaert M, Heylen R, Vissers K, Van Zundert J. Pulsed radiofrequency for the treatment of occipital neuralgia: a prospective study with 6 months of follow-up. Reg Anesth Pain Med. 2010 Mar-Apr;35(2):148-51.</citation>
    <PMID>20301822</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Choi HJ, Oh IH, Choi SK, Lim YJ. Clinical outcomes of pulsed radiofrequency neuromodulation for the treatment of occipital neuralgia. J Korean Neurosurg Soc. 2012 May;51(5):281-5. Epub 2012 May 31.</citation>
    <PMID>22792425</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 19, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Steven P. Cohen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Occipital neuralgia</keyword>
  <keyword>corticosteroid injection</keyword>
  <keyword>pulsed radiofrequency</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neuralgia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics, Local</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
