<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="45089">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01731626</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>I 31104</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2010-02214</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01731626</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pemetrexed Disodium and Cisplatin in Treating Patients Undergoing Surgery For Stage I-III Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Molecular and Genetic Changes in Patients With Resectable Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) Following Neoadjuvant Chemotherapy With Cisplatin and Alimta - Phase II Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eli Lilly and Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well giving pemetrexed disodium and cisplatin works in
      treating patients who are undergoing surgery for stage I-III non-small cell lung cancer.
      Pemetrexed disodium may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking some of the enzymes
      needed for cell growth. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as cisplatin, work in different
      ways to stop the growth of tumor cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from
      dividing. Giving these treatments before surgery may make the tumor smaller and reduce the
      amount of normal tissue that needs to be removed. Giving these treatments after surgery may
      kill any tumor cells that remain after surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. The primary goal is to determine whether or not these two agents given prior to surgery
      increase the chance that the surgical specimen will be pathologically negative (pathological
      complete response).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Document adverse events using this regimen in this setting. II. To document the overall
      and disease free survival. III. To correlate response with markers such as presence or
      absence of excision nuclease within the nucleotide excision repair 1 (ERCC1) and
      dihydrofolate reductase (DHFR), thymidylate synthase (TS), dihydropyrimidine dehydrogenase
      (DPD) and glycinamide ribonucleotide formyl transferase (GARFT).

      IV. Correlate pre- and post chemotherapy effects on fludeoxyglucose F18 (FDG) uptake by the
      tumor on positron emission tomography (PET) scan.

      OUTLINE:

      NEOADJUVANT CHEMOTHERAPY: Patients receive pemetrexed disodium intravenously (IV) over 10
      minutes and cisplatin IV over approximately 1 hour on days 1, 22, and 43. Treatment repeats
      every 21 days for 3 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      SURGERY: Patients undergo surgery between days 70-90.

      ADJUVANT CHEMOTHERAPY: Beginning on day 130, patients receive pemetrexed disodium and
      cisplatin as in neoadjuvant chemotherapy. Treatment repeats every 21 days for 2 courses in
      the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 3 months for 2 years,
      every 6 months for 3 years, and then yearly thereafter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2005</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pathologic complete response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 63</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The frequency and severity of all adverse effects will be tabulated and reported using the Common Toxicity Criteria (CTC) version 3.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 171</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Serious adverse events will be monitored to determine the safety of the combination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimates will be computed using the Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimates will be computed using the Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">52</enrollment>
  <condition>Stage IB Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIA Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIB Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIA Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (chemotherapy and surgery)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>NEOADJUVANT CHEMOTHERAPY: Patients receive pemetrexed disodium IV over 10 minutes and cisplatin IV over approximately 1 hour on days 1, 22, and 43. Treatment repeats every 21 days for 3 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
SURGERY: Patients undergo surgery between days 70-90.
ADJUVANT CHEMOTHERAPY: Beginning on day 130, patients receive pemetrexed disodium and cisplatin as in neoadjuvant chemotherapy. Treatment repeats every 21 days for 2 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cisplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (chemotherapy and surgery)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CACP</other_name>
    <other_name>CDDP</other_name>
    <other_name>CPDD</other_name>
    <other_name>DDP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pemetrexed disodium</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (chemotherapy and surgery)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ALIMTA</other_name>
    <other_name>LY231514</other_name>
    <other_name>MTA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (chemotherapy and surgery)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>positron emission tomography</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (chemotherapy and surgery)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>FDG-PET</other_name>
    <other_name>PET</other_name>
    <other_name>PET scan</other_name>
    <other_name>tomography, emission computed</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fludeoxyglucose F 18</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (chemotherapy and surgery)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>18FDG</other_name>
    <other_name>FDG</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>therapeutic conventional surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo surgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (chemotherapy and surgery)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Microscopically confirmed non-small cell carcinoma of the lung

          -  No prior therapy for lung cancer

          -  Patients must have disease stages IB (T2N0M0), IIA (T1N1M0), IIB (T2N1M0 and T3N0M0),
             or lIlA (T3N1M0 and T1-3N2M0); patients with satellite lesions in one lobe (T4)
             (stage IIIB) will also be eligible

          -  Patients must be deemed surgically resectable by a thoracic surgeon

          -  Patients must have either measurable or evaluable disease; measurable disease: any
             lesion that can be accurately measured in at least one dimension, with the longest
             diameter being &gt;= 10 mm; evaluable disease: lesions apparent on computed tomography
             (CT), which do not meet the criteria for measurability; these include ill-defined
             masses associated with post obstructive changes and mediastinal or hilar adenopathy

          -  Informed consent must be obtained

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0-1

          -  Patients must be &gt; 12 weeks from prior major surgery of the chest and abdomen

          -  Calculated creatinine clearance (CrC1) &gt;= 45 mL/min based on the Cockcroft and Gault
             formula

          -  The ability to take folic acid, Vitamin B12, and dexamethasone according to protocol

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  White bloods cell count &lt; 3000/mm^3

          -  Platelet count &lt; 100,000/mm^3

          -  Hemoglobin &lt; 9 g/dl

          -  Calculated creatinine clearance (CrCl) &lt; 45 mL/min based on the Cockcroft and Gault
             formula

          -  Total bilirubin &gt; 1.5 mg/dl

          -  Serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT) or serum glutamic pyruvate
             transaminase (SGPT) &gt; 1.5 x upper limit of normal

          -  Metastatic disease (except peribronchial/hilar lymph nodes = N1 and
             ipsilateral/subcarinal mediastinal lymph nodes = N2) or malignant pleural effusion
             detected on preoperative evaluation; non-malignant effusions have negative cytology,
             are non-bloody, and are transudates; effusions visible only on CT and not large
             enough for safe thoracentesis will not result in ineligibility; exudative effusions,
             even if cytologically negative are excluded; pleural fluid is considered exudative
             if: the ratio of pleural fluid protein to serum protein is greater than 0.5, the
             ratio of pleural fluid lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) to serum to serum LDH &gt; 0.6,
             pleural fluid LDH is greater than 200 RI/liter

          -  N3 lymph nodes (contralateral mediastinal/hilar and supraclavicular/scalene) or T4
             primary tumor (malignant pleural effusion or mediastinal invasion) by clinical
             staging criteria, (N3 as seen on CT or PET scan; patients may be eligible only if N3
             nodes proven negative by mediastinoscopy and/or excisional biopsy of supraclavicular
             lymph node)

          -  Presence of third space fluid which cannot be controlled by drainage; for patients
             who develop or have baseline clinically significant pleural or peritoneal effusions
             before or during initiation of pemetrexed therapy, consideration should be given to
             draining the effusion prior to dosing; however, if in the investigator's opinion, the
             effusion represents progression of disease then the patient should be discontinued
             from study therapy

          -  Prior chemotherapy, surgery, or radiation therapy for lung cancer

          -  Pregnant or lactating

          -  Other active malignancy within 2 years with the exceptions of nonmelanoma skin cancer
             and cervical carcinoma in situ

          -  Psychological, familial, sociologic or geographic conditions, which do not permit
             medical follow-up and compliance with the study protocol

          -  Inability to interrupt aspirin or other nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAID)
             2 days before, the day of and 2 days after the dose of Alimta (Pemetrexed); if a
             patient is taking a NSAID or a salicylate with a long half-life (for example,
             naproxen, piroxicam, diflunisal, nabumetone, rofecoxib, or celecoxib) it should not
             be taken 5 days before the dose of Alimta (Pemetrexed); (8 day period for long acting
             agents such as piroxicam), the day of, and 2 days after the dose of Alimta
             (Pemetrexed)

          -  Squamous cell carcinoma histology

          -  The screening PET scan will be used to exclude patients; if there are multiple areas
             of FDG uptake, outside the area of the primary tumor in the lung, or evidence of
             malignant pleural disease as evidenced by pleural nodules, the patient will be
             excluded by virtue of having metastatic disease; if however, only one area shows an
             increase in FDG uptake, the area of concern will need further evaluation such as a
             biopsy to exclude metastatic disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Grace Dy</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14263</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rochester General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14621</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 12, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Pemetrexed</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
