<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="77085">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01711645</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11-0035</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HHSN272200800007C</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01711645</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tdap Vaccine in Post-Partum Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase IV, Open Label Trial to Evaluate Immunogenicity of Tdap Vaccine in Post-Partum Women to Optimize Vaccination Schedule for Women Who May Have a Subsequent Child</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Monitoring immune response and longevity in serum and milk after Tdap administration to
      postpartum women. The clinical trial will involve women (aged 18 - 45 years) who have just
      delivered full-term infants (greater than or equal to 37 completed weeks of gestation) at
      Vanderbilt University Medical Center. The enrollment period will be fifteen months. The
      duration is over two years of observation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single site, prospective study involving only one intervention, receipt of a
      single 0.5 mL intramuscular (IM) dose of Adacel (Tetanus toxoid, reduced diphtheria toxoid
      and acellular Pertussis) vaccine, among 55 healthy post partum women.  The purpose of the
      study is to examine the immune responses and subsequent decline in serum and breast milk
      antibody titers over two years of observation.  The clinical trial will involve women (aged
      18 - 45 years) who have just delivered full-term infants (greater than or equal to 37
      completed weeks of gestation) at Vanderbilt University Medical Center.  One particular
      population at Vanderbilt to target will be the &quot;centering prenatal care group&quot; that has
      breastfeeding rates as high as 75 percent at hospital discharge and maintained at 20 percent
      at 6 months.  The enrollment period will be fifteen months. The subjects, staff assessing
      subjects, and laboratory personnel will be aware of receipt of the vaccine. Since only a
      single vaccine product is being utilized, there is no blinding needed of the subjects or
      staff.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with 4-fold rise in ELISA antibody concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to and following Tdap, through 24 months post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Kinetics of the ELISA IgG antibody rise in serum expressed in EU/ml.</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to and following Tdap, through 24 months post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>ELISA Geometric mean fold rise by study day</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to and following Tdap, through 24 months post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>ELISA Geometric mean titers (GMT) of serum IgG to pertussis toxin, filamentous hemaglutinin, pertactin and fimbrae measured and assessed in EU/ml</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to and following Tdap through 24 months post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with 4-fold rise in antibody concentrations by study day.</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to vaccination, 2 weeks, 6 weeks, and 6 months after vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ELISA Geometric mean fold rise by study day</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to vaccination, 2 weeks, 6 weeks, and 6 months after vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ELISA GMT of breast milk IgA to pertussis toxin, filamentous hemagluttin, pertactin and fimbrae by study day.</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to vaccination, 2 weeks, 6 weeks, and 6 months after vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Kinetics of the ELISA IgG antibody decline in breast milk expressed in EU/ml.</measure>
    <time_frame>After Tdap and at 2 weeks, 6 weeks, and 6 months after vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">55</enrollment>
  <condition>Pertussis</condition>
  <condition>Diphtheria</condition>
  <condition>Tetanus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Adacel® Tdap vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>55 postpartum subjects receive a single intramuscular (IM) 0.5 mL dose of Adacel® (Tetanus toxoid, reduced diphtheria toxoid and acellular pertussis vaccine adsorbed).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Adacel® Tdap vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>55 postpartum subjects receive a single intramuscular (IM) 0.5 mL dose of Adacel® (Tetanus toxoid, reduced diphtheria toxoid and acellular pertussis vaccine adsorbed).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Adacel® Tdap vaccine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy, postpartum women as determined by medical history aged 18 - 45 years of age
             inclusive.

          -  Women 1-4 days postpartum from delivery of full-term infants. Full-term will be
             defined as estimated gestational age of greater than or equal to 37 completed weeks
             of pregnancy determined by menstrual dating and concordant with ultrasound findings
             as per ACOG bulletin #101).

          -  Provide written informed consent prior to initiation of any study procedures.

          -  Available for the entire study period.

          -  Able to understand and complete all relevant study procedures during study
             participation (women who ultimately have limited ability to breast feed after
             enrollment will not be excluded from the study).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior receipt of a tetanus or diphtheria-containing vaccine within two years of
             enrollment.

          -  Prior receipt of a tetanus and diphtheria toxoid and acellular pertussis vaccine
             within two years of enrollment.

          -  Known or suspected impairment of immunologic function.

          -  Febrile illness within the last 24 hours or an oral temperature &gt;/= 100.4 degrees F
             (&gt;/= 38 degrees C) at the time of enrollment.

          -  History of documented tetanus, diphtheria, or pertussis disease within the preceding
             5 years.

          -  History of allergic or adverse reaction to diphtheria, tetanus, or pertussis
             vaccines.

          -  Receipt of any steroids, immunoglobulins, other blood products/transfusion within the
             past six months- excluding Rh immunoglobulin (Rhogam™ and Rhophylac™).

          -  Is enrolled or plans to enroll in another clinical trial with an investigational
             product while participating in this study (observational studies are allowed).

          -  Known active infection with HIV, hepatitis B, or hepatitis C.

          -  History of alcohol or drug abuse in the last 5 years.

          -  Any condition which, in the opinion of the investigators, may pose a health risk to
             the subject or interfere with the evaluation of the study objectives.

          -  Any woman with health condition who is currently taking glucocorticoids, i.e., oral,
             parenteral, and high-dose inhaled steroids, and immunosuppressive or cytotoxic drugs.

          -  Sensitive to latex, based on package insert

          -  Progressive or unstable neurologic condition, based on package insert.

          -  Receipt of influenza or other vaccines concomitantly administered or for 42 days
             following Adacel, based on package insert.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt University - Pediatric - Vanderbilt Vaccine Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232-2573</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 18, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tetanus, Diptheria toxoids, Acellular, Pertussis, Tdap, Adacel®, postpartum, women</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diphtheria</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Whooping Cough</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tetanus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tetany</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
