<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="112473">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01688466</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>120197</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>12-C-0197</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01688466</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pomalidomide for Chronic Graft-versus-Host Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Phase 2 Single-Center Study of Pomalidomide for Chronic GvHD</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Pomalidomide is a drug that alters the body   s immune response. It may help people who
      have chronic graft-versus-host disease (GvHD). GvHD may appear after a stem cell transplant,
      when immune cells in the transplant try to attack tissues in the person who received the
      transplant. GvHD is not easy to treat, and often does not respond to standard treatments.
      Researchers want to see if pomalidomide is a safe and effective treatment for GvHD.

      Objectives:

      - To test the safety and effectiveness of pomalidomide for GvHD that has not responded to
      standard treatments.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals at least 18 years of age who have GvHD that has not responded to standard
      treatments.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. Blood and urine
           samples will also be collected. A lung function test and imaging studies will also be
           given.

        -  Participants will take pomalidomide capsules once a day for 4-week periods called
           cycles.

        -  Treatment will be monitored with frequent blood tests and imaging studies. Saliva
           samples and skin and mouth tissue biopsies will also be collected during treatment.

        -  Treatment will continue for six cycles (6 months), unless the GvHD gets worse or side
           effects are too severe. If the GvHD has improved at the end of the six cycles,
           participants may be able to continue to take pomalidomide for up to six more cycles.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

        -  Chronic graft-versus-host disease (cGvHD) is the leading cause of non-relapse morbidity
           and mortality in persons after allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplants.

        -  About 50% of persons with cGvHD have disease refractory to systemic corticosteroids and
           there is no standard second-line therapy.

        -  Thalidomide, a drug with immune-modulating effects, was active in advanced cGvHD but
           was difficult to use at appropriate doses.

        -  Pomalidomide is related to thalidomide but with higher potency and more favorable
           toxicity profile. It is active in multiple myeloma and myeloproliferative neoplasm
           associated myelofibrosis. Preliminary data in humans with cGvHD are encouraging but
           data are limited.

      OBJECTIVES:

        -  Primary: Determine whether pomalidomide is effective in persons with moderate or severe
           cGvHD not controlled by corticosteroids.

        -  Secondary:

        -  Determine whether pomalidomide is safe in persons with moderate or severe

      cGvHD not controlled by corticosteroids.

        -  Determine the immune-modulatory effects of pomalidomide in persons with moderate or
           severe cGvHD.

        -  Determine limited pharmacokinetics after oral administration of pomalidomide.

      ELIGIBILITY:

      Inclusion Criteria

        -  Moderate or severe cGvHD per NIH criteria

        -  Age 18 to 75 years old

        -  Karnofsky performance score greater than or equal to 60%

        -  Has cGvHD that did not respond to high-dose corticosteroids (average 0.5 mg/kg/d
           prednisone for greater than or equal to 8 weeks) or second-line therapy

        -  Receiving stable or tapering doses of systemic therapy in the preceding 4 weeks

        -  Agree to adhere to methods of contraception and other fertility control measures as
           prescribed by the protocol

      Exclusion Criteria

        -  Acute GvHD (classic and late per NIH criteria)

        -  Absolute neutrophils &lt; 1.0x10(9)/L, platelets &lt; 75x10(9)/L, estimated creatinine
           clearance &lt; 50 mL/min/1.73m(2)

        -  NIH lung score 3

        -  Pregnant or lactating

        -  Uncontrolled infection

      DESIGN:

      Randomized phase 2 trial with the single stage selection design. Patients will receive
      either a constant low dose of pomalidomide (0.5 mg/day) for six months or a strategy of
      increasing dose of pomalidomide from 0.5 mg/d up through each individual patients    maximum
      tolerated dose, with escalations by 0.5 mg/d every 2 weeks to a maximum of 2.0 mg/d. As an
      early stopping rule for futility, if after 7 patients have enrolled on either arm, 0 have
      responded, then no further patients will be accrued to that arm as soon as this can be
      determined. To protect patient safety, an early stopping rule will be implemented. With two
      arms, each of which has a maximal accrual of 16 patients, up to 32 evaluable patients will
      be randomized. Response assessments will occur every 3 months with primary efficacy endpoint
      evaluated at 6 months. Patients with responding disease will continue therapy for another 6
      months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Graft vs Host Disease</condition>
  <condition>Graft-Versus-Host Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>0.5 mg/day without Dose Escalation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>0.5 mg/day with Dose Escalation by 0.5 mg/day increments every 2 weeks to a maximum of 2.0 mg/day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pomalidomide</intervention_name>
    <description>0.5 mg/day- 2.0 mg/day PO QD(every day) of each 28 day cycle</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA

          -  Moderate or severe cGvHD diagnosed and staged per NIH criteria

          -  Greater then or equal to18-75 years of age, because no dosing or adverse event data
             are currently available on the use of pomalidomide in persons greater then or equal
             to18 years of age

          -  Has cGvHD that did not respond to high-dose corticosteroids (average 0.5 mg/kg/d
             prednisone for &gt; 8 weeks) or second-line systemic therapy

          -  If taking systemic therapy for cGvHD at the time of enrollment, must be on a stable
             or tapering schedule in the preceding 4 weeks (extracorporeal photopheresis has to be
             stopped at least by 4 weeks before enrollment)

          -  Karnofsky performance score greater then or equal to 60%

          -  Life expectancy &gt; 3 months

          -  Stable primary malignancy for previous 3 months

          -  Agree to adhere to methods of contraception and other fertility control measures as
             prescribed by the protocol

          -  Because agents of this class are known to be teratogenic, women of childbearing
             potential and men must agree to use effective forms of contraception (hormonal or
             barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry and for the
             duration of study participation. Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is
             pregnant while she or her partner is participating in this study, she should inform
             her treating physician immediately.

          -  Females of childbearing potential (FCBP)  (Cross) must have a negative serum or urine
             pregnancy test with a sensitivity of at least 25 mIU/mL within 10

             14 days prior to and again within 24 hours of starting pomalidomide and must either
             commit to continued abstinence from heterosexual intercourse or begin TWO acceptable
             methods of birth control, one highly effective method and one additional effective
             method AT THE SAME TIME, at least 28 days before she starts taking pomalidomide. FCBP
             must also agree to ongoing pregnancy testing. Men must agree to use a latex condom
             during sexual contact with a FCBP even if they have had a vasectomy. All patients
             must be counseled at a minimum of every 28 days about pregnancy precautions and risks
             of fetal exposure. Risks of Fetal Exposure, Pregnancy Testing Guidelines and
             Acceptable Birth Control Methods, AND Education and Counseling Guidance Document.

          -  Male Subjects

          -  Must agree to use a latex condom during sexual contact with females of childbearing
             potential while participating in the study and for at least 28 days following
             discontinuation of study drug even if he has undergone a successful vasectomy

          -  Will be warned that sharing study drug is prohibited and will be counseled about
             pregnancy precautions and potential risks of fetal exposure

          -  Must agree to abstain from donating blood, semen, or sperm during study participation
             and for at least 28 days after discontinuation of study drug.

          -  Must agree that if a pregnancy or a positive pregnancy test does occur in a study
             subject or the partner of a male study subject during study participation, study drug
             must be immediately discontinued.

          -  Patients must agree to not share study drug with anyone during participation in the
             study.

          -  Ability of subject to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed
             consent document.

          -  All study participants must be registered into the mandatory POMALYST REMS (TM)
             program, and be willing and able to comply with the requirements of the POMALYST REMS
             (TM) program.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Acute GvHD, classic (less than or equal to day 100) or late-onset (&gt; day 100)

          -  Systemic immune suppression or systemic therapy for cGvHD started within preceding 4
             weeks including extracorporeal photopheresis

          -  Hypersensitivity to thalidomide, lenalidomide or pomalidomide

          -  Any serious medical condition which places the subject at an unacceptable risk if he
             or she were to participate in the study or confounds the ability to interpret data
             from the study, including, but not limited to, symptomatic congestive heart failure,
             unstable angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social
             situations that would limit compliance with study requirements.

          -  Neutrophil &lt; 1.0x10(9)/L, platelets &lt; 75x10(9)/L, estimated creatinine clearance &lt; 50
             mL/min/1.73m(2) (Cockroft-Gault formula) total bilirubin &gt; 3 mg/dL, transaminase

        &gt; 3xUNL

          -  Uncontrolled infection

          -  Active HIV-1, HBV and/or HCV infection

        Uncontrolled arrhythmias or symptomatic heart disease or LVEF &lt; 45%

          -  Other cancer except that for which the transplant was done &lt; 2 years before study
             entry, except non-melanoma skin cancer or carcinoma in situ of the uterine cervix or
             breast

          -  Taking other investigational drugs

          -  NIH lung score 3

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study because pomalidomide has potential for
             teratogenic effects. Because there is an unknown but potential risk for adverse
             events in nursing infants secondary to treatment of the mother with pomalidomide,
             breastfeeding must be discontinued while the mother is taking study drug and for at
             least 28 days after discontinuation of study drug. These potential risks may also
             apply to other agents used in this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven Z Pavletic, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Steven Z Pavletic, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-4899</phone>
    <email>sp326h@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact National Cancer Institute Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>888-624-1937</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2012-C-0197.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bolaños-Meade J, Vogelsang GB. Chronic graft-versus-host disease. Curr Pharm Des. 2008;14(20):1974-86. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18691108</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee SJ, Vogelsang G, Flowers ME. Chronic graft-versus-host disease. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant. 2003 Apr;9(4):215-33. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12720215</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martin PJ, Weisdorf D, Przepiorka D, Hirschfeld S, Farrell A, Rizzo JD, Foley R, Socie G, Carter S, Couriel D, Schultz KR, Flowers ME, Filipovich AH, Saliba R, Vogelsang GB, Pavletic SZ, Lee SJ; Design of Clinical Trials Working Group. National Institutes of Health Consensus Development Project on Criteria for Clinical Trials in Chronic Graft-versus-Host Disease: VI. Design of Clinical Trials Working Group report. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant. 2006 May;12(5):491-505.</citation>
    <PMID>16635784</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 15, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 15, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Immune Modulatory</keyword>
  <keyword>Systemic Absorption</keyword>
  <keyword>Oral Agent</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Graft vs Host Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
