<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="122569">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01741272</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00001096</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01741272</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Early Mobilization Following Mini-Open Rotator Cuff Repair</brief_title>
  <official_title>Early Mobilization Following Mini-Open Rotator Cuff Repair: A Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shoulder &amp; Upper Extremity Research Group of Edmonton</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shoulder &amp; Upper Extremity Research Group of Edmonton</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Ethics Review Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to determine if early active range of motion after
      mini-open rotator cuff repair in adults results in improved shoulder range of motion at 6
      weeks and 3 months after surgery.  The secondary objective of this study is to determine if
      early mobilization improves disease-specific quality of life and promotes earlier return to
      work/function.

      Hypothesis:  Adults undergoing mini-open rotator cuff repair will have faster recovery of
      range of motion, improved disease specific quality of life and earlier return to
      work/function if allowed to begin early active range of motion compared to subjects who are
      immobilized in a sling for 6 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The rotator cuff is a group of four muscles around the shoulder.  They function to provide
      both shoulder mobility and power as well as stability.  Rotator cuff tears can be a
      significant cause of pain and disability for the patient.  Surgical repair is done to
      reconnect the torn tendon(s) to the bone and has been shown to be an effective treatment in
      the presence of full-thickness tears. The goals of Rotator Cuff (RC)surgery are to decrease
      pain, increase range of motion(ROM) and strength.  This is done with a small incision called
      a mini-open. Standard care following this surgical repair is to be placed in a sling for 6
      weeks to protect the repaired shoulder tendons.  During this time ROM exercises are done
      using the non-operated arm for assistance.  No active or voluntary movement is allowed
      during the first 6 weeks.  Unfortunately, some of these patients develop shoulder stiffness
      which slows their recovery and return to work or daily activities and may result in
      increased use and cost of rehabilitation services.

      The purpose of this study is to determine if following a RC repair, patients can safely stop
      wearing their sling  and  begin active ROM for activities of daily living as early as pain
      and comfort allow.  A total of 190 patients have been recruited to this study (95/group)
      were randomly assigned to one of two study groups.  Patients in Group A (sling for 6 weeks)
      will wear their sling for 6 weeks.  Self-assisted ROM exercises are allowed at any time, but
      active movement will not be allowed until 6 weeks after surgery.  Patients in Group B (Sling
      as needed) will be allowed to remove their sling as early as pain and comfort allow.
      Self-assisted ROM exercises are allowed at any time as are active ROM for activities of
      daily living.  Patients who agree to participate will be seen by their surgeon and the
      research coordinator for a baseline assessment before surgery and again at 2 &amp; 6 weeks, 3,
      6, 12 and 24 months after surgery. Each visit will include a ROM assessment and disease
      specific quality of life questionnaires.  Patients will also undergo an Ultrasound exam at a
      minimum of 2 years after surgery to verify the integrity of their RC repair.  Differences in
      ROM, questionnaire scores, RC integrity and adverse events will be examined between the two
      groups.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Range of Motion (ROM)from baseline to 24 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 3, 6, 12, 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Standing: Active flexion, scaption, abduction, extension, internal rotation (vertebral level).
Supine Lying: Active and passive flexion, abduction, external rotation (arm at side), external rotation (arm at 90 degrees abduction), internal rotation (arm at side), internal rotation (arm at 90 degrees abduction),and horizontal adduction.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>pain questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 weeks, 6 weeks, 3, 6, 12, 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A visual analog rating pain at rest and pain with activity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>WORC questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6, 12, 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A disease specific quality of life measurement tool for patients with rotator cuff disease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ASES questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6, 12, 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>American Shoulder and Elbow Surgeons Standardized Form has a patient self evaluation section to evaluate pain and function during activities of daily living.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Constant Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6, 12, 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Constant Score is an outcome measure that evaluates shoulder function and change of time in a variety of conditions related to the shoulder.  The subjective component includes questions about pain and ADL's and an objective component including ROM and power.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complications</measure>
    <time_frame>2 &amp; 6 weeks, 3, 6, 12, 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Incidence of any surgical or medical complications will be prospectively documented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">190</enrollment>
  <condition>Full Thickness Rotator Cuff Tears</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A (Usual Care)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Will be immobilized in a sling for 6 weeks. Intervention: Procedure: Sling</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B (Early ROM)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Will use the sling for comfort only. Intervention: Procedure: No sling</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sling</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will use a sling for 6 weeks as per usual care.  No active ROM allowed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A (Usual Care)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No sling</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients may discontinue use of the sling as early as pain and comfort allow.  Early active ROM is allowed for activities of daily living.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group B (Early ROM)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Clinical:

          -  males and females over 18 years of age

          -  failed non-operative management defined as persistent pain and/or
             disability following 3 months of conservative medical treatment including
             analgesic/anti-inflammatory medications, intra-articular corticosteroids, activity
             modification and physical therapy.

        Radiological:

          -  confirmed full-thickness rotator cuff tear on arthrogram or MRI

        Surgical:

          -  full-thickness tear of the rotator cuff confirmed through arthroscopy

          -  rotator cuff repairable using mini-open approach

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  previous shoulder surgery

          -  previous fracture of scapula or humerus

          -  history of charcot joint or inflammatory arthropathy

          -  cervical radiculopathy

          -  active joint or systemic infection

          -  neurological disorder

          -  significant paralysis of the rotator cuff, deltoid or shoulder girdle musculature

          -  major medical illness (life expectancy less than 2 years or unacceptably high
             operative risk)

          -  unable to speak or read English

          -  immunosuppressive therapy or chronic steroids (eg. prednisone)

          -  patient unwilling to be followed for 2 years

          -  psychiatric illness that precludes informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Balyk, MD, FRCSC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alberta</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Grey Nuns Community Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6L 5X8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 3, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 29, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>rotator cuff tear</keyword>
  <keyword>arthroscopically assisted</keyword>
  <keyword>health related quality of life(HRQL)</keyword>
  <keyword>functional outcome</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
