<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="105816">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01806662</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>JKR-0737</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01806662</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Study of Ustekinumab for Subjects With Chronic Atopic Dermatitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Pilot Study of Ustekinumab for Subjects With Chronic Atopic Dermatitis Who Have Sub-optimal Response to Prior Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rockefeller University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rockefeller University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Atopic dermatitis (AD) is a chronic disease associated with intense itching,  which affects
      most aspects of everyday life in the majority of patients.  Acute inflammation and
      extensor/facial involvement is common in infants, whereas chronic inflammation increases in
      prevalence with age, as do localization to flexures. AD has a complex background
      characterized by immune activation, increased epidermal thickness in chronic diseased skin,
      and defective barrier function. In normal, healthy skin, the outer layer of the epidermis,
      the stratum corneum is made up flattened dead cells called corneocytes held together by a
      mixture of lipids and proteins. The stratum corneum and, in particular, the lipid layer are
      vital in providing a natural barrier function that locks water inside the skin and keeps
      allergens and irritants out. In people with AD, the barrier function is defective, which
      leads to dry skin. As the skin dries out, it cracks allowing allergens and irritants to
      penetrate.

      Mild AD can be controlled with emollients and topical medications. However, moderate to
      severe AD is extremely difficult to control and requires systemic treatment that is often
      unsatisfactory due to impracticality and lack of effectiveness. Only three therapeutic
      options exist for moderate to severe AD, including: 1) oral steroids 2) cyclosporine A
      (CsA), that is not widely used in the US as it is not FDA approved for AD and 3) ultraviolet
      phototherapy. Oral steroids and CsA treatments have major side effects and UV radiation
      therapy is highly inconvenient for patients.  Several biologic medications, such as
      TNF-alpha inhibitors, are effective, convenient, and relatively safe therapies for
      psoriasis, but have thus far not shown efficacy in AD. Ustekinumab is a unique biologic
      medication that may specifically target AD.

      The investigators study will determine whether there is a reversal of the skin thickness and
      the immune pathways involved in the disease during treatment with Ustekinimab and what
      specific immune cells are involved.  The investigators are also interested to understand how
      the clinical reversal of the disease will correlate with tissue reversal of the disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In psoriasis, epidermal hyperplasia is driven by underlying immune activation, whether as a
      direct response to IL-20 family cytokines that induces hyperplasia and inhibits keratinocyte
      terminal differentiation or as an indirect response to immune-mediated injury to
      keratinocytes. The epidermal reaction in psoriasis is largely restored to normal with
      selective immune suppression. Hence, one might hypothesize that similar epidermal responses
      should occur in the presence of &quot;generalized&quot; cellular immune activation, in diseases with
      similar inflammatory infiltrate and epidermal hyperplasia, such as AD.  In fact, psoriasis
      and AD share features of dense T-cells and dentritic cell infiltrates, as well as
      over-expression of IL-22 in skin lesions. These diseases also share similar epidermal
      hyperplasia in their chronic phases.

      Work from the investigators group showed that IL-22 is a key cytokine in the pathogenesis of
      both AD and psoriasis. The investigators have demonstrated that in psoriasis, ustekinumab
      suppresses the production of IL-12, IL-23, and IL-22. Additionally, by RT-PCR the
      investigators demonstrated that the mRNA expression of p40 cytokine and the IL23R is
      up-regulated in AD as compared to both normal skin and psoriasis. The investigators
      therefore hypothesize that ustekinumab will suppress IL-22 and possibly also p40 production
      in AD lesions and reverse both the epidermal growth/differentiation defects and the
      underlying immune activation, and hence will suppress disease activity. Interestingly, p40
      was also found to be significantly up-regulated in non-lesional AD skin as compared with
      normal skin.

      Although AD is thought to be predominately a disease of Th2-type cells, in the chronic
      stage, there is large Th1 component. To date, the precise mechanism by which sequential
      activation of Th2 and Th1 cells in AD is achieved remains unknown. IL-12 induces the
      differentiation and maturation of human Th cells into Th1-type cells. Recent circumstantial
      evidence suggests that in AD patients IL-12 may facilitate a change from the Th2-type to a
      Th1 cytokine profile. IL-12 was recently shown to be highly elevated in pediatric AD and its
      levels were strongly associated with disease severity.

      Expression of IL-12 p40 mRNA is significantly enhanced in lesional skin from AD, suggesting
      that the enhanced local production of IL-12 in dendritic cells and macrophages may be
      responsible for the increased production of IFN-γ in chronic lesions potentially suggesting
      that IL-12 may have a pivotal role in promoting inflammation in atopic dermatitis. Topical
      steroids which constitute a mainstay of therapy in AD are known to strongly down-regulate
      IL-12 expression, possibly also indicating that targeted anti IL-12 therapy might important
      role in treating AD.

      Recently, the Th1/Th2 paradigm in autoimmunity and allergy has been revisited to include a
      role for a new population of IL-17-producing Th cells known as Th17. Th17 cells are
      characterized by the production of inflammatory cytokines such as IL-17A, IL-17F, IL-22, and
      IL-26.  One of the key factors involved in naive Th-cell commitment to a Th17 phenotype is
      IL-23.

      Patients with acute AD were found to have increased Th17 T-cells in peripheral blood by flow
      cytometry and intracellular cytokine staining 26  as well as by immunohistochemistry (IHC)
      in lesions.   Since IL-23 is the major inducer of Th17 T-cells, as well as &quot;T22&quot; T-cells,
      neutralization of IL-23 could potentially result in both decreased Th17 signal in acute AD
      as well as decreased &quot;T22/IL22&quot; signal. Therefore the investigators postulate that
      ustekinumab in AD will act both inhibiting the IL-12-dependent Th1 shift in chronic AD stage
      as well as the pathogenic IL-22/&quot;T22&quot; axis in this disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>A 50% or greater improvement from their baseline objective SCORAD (SCORing Atopic Dermatitis) at Week 16.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine whether there is a reversal of the pathological epidermal phenotype during ustekinumab therapy and what immune pathways are suppressed during treatment with the drug at week 16.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of subjects who achieve an improvement of 50% or greater from their baseline objective SCORAD at Week 32 (If patient received placebo first).</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 32</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measured effects on patient quality of life using the DLQI (Dermatology Life Quality Index).</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The change in SCORAD from week16 to week 32 for patients that were treated with Ustekinumab from weeks 0-16, to measure maintenance of response after discontinuation of treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 32</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ustekinumab's effect on the pathologic epidermal hyperplasia of lesional and non-lesional AD skin.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 32</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Epidermal hyperplasia pre- and post-treatment will be measured on lesional and non-lesional AD skin by:  epidermal thickness, K16, and Mki67 expression (IHC, RT-PCR, and gene array will be used to determine these determinants). We will also assess for modulation of various epidermal barrier genes during treatment by similar measures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ustekinumab's suppression of expression of excess p40 production in non-lesional AD skin (decreasing systemic immune activation).</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 32</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between clinical response (measured via a decrease in SCORAD) to therapy with ustekinumab and suppression of the immune pathways (Th2, Th17, and Th22).</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the correlation between clinical response to therapy with ustekinumab and suppression of the immune pathways and pathologic epidermal phenotype. In the group of patients that will respond to treatment by a reduction of at least 50% of the SCORAD (&quot;responders), we will correlate the decrease in SCORAD with suppression of Th2, and TH22 immune pathways and with the reduction in epidermal hyperplasia.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Atopic Dermatitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm (Ustekinumab)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Since there is a crossover design, each patient will be in the treatment arm for 16 weeks of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Since there is a crossover design, each patient will be in the placebo arm for 16 weeks of the study.  If a patient begins in the placebo arm, they will switch over to the treatment arm at week 16.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ustekinumab</intervention_name>
    <description>A monoclonal antibody against the p40 subunit of IL-12/23</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm (Ustekinumab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Stelara</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Are male or female and ages 18-75.

          -  Have moderate to severe AD (as determined using the Objective SCORAD scale ≥15) and a
               history of therapeutic failure with at least two of the three different treatment
             categories as listed within the inclusion criteria.

          -  Patients must have tried and failed at least two of the three treatment categories of
             the following treatment modalities:

        Category 1 :  Hydration plus topical steroids and/or antibiotics Category 2:  Systemic
        Steroids and/or Phototherapy Category 3:  Cyclosporine and/or Other Immunomodulators
        (Methotrexate, CellCept, Immuran, topical Calcineurin inhibitors)

          -  Patients who initially respond to cyclosporine but cannot sustain a response after
             the drug is discontinued will also be eligible.

          -  Patients that have contraindications to category 3 drugs will also be allowed to
             participate in the study.

          -  A washout period prior to screening will be required for the following medications:

          -  Cyclosporine/Oral Steroids/Imuran/Mycophenolate Mofetil/Other systemic
             immunosuppressants: 4 weeks

          -  Phototherapy/Moderate to High Potency Topical Corticosteroids: 2 weeks

          -  Women of childbearing potential must test negative for pregnancy and be using
             adequate birth control measures (e.g., Abstinence, oral contraceptives, intrauterine
             device, barrier method with spermicide, or have had a tubal ligation or a
             hysterectomy) during the study and for 6 months after receiving the last treatment.
             Likewise, men capable of fathering children must also use appropriate methods of
             birth control (e.g., abstinence, barrier methods with spermicide, or have had
             surgical sterilization such as vasectomy).

          -  Patients must be in general good health in the opinion of the investigator.

          -  Patients with stable chronic asthma, treated with inhaled corticosteroids, will be
             eligible.

          -  The screening laboratory tests must meet the following criteria:

        Hemoglobin  &gt;9 g/dl WBC count  &gt;3.5 x 109 cells/L Neutrophils  &gt;1.5 x 109 cells/L
        Platelets  &gt;100 x 109 cells/L AST/SGOT and ALT/SGPT levels must be within 2 times the
        upper limit of normal for the laboratory conducting the test.  Alkaline phosphatase levels
        must be within 2 times the upper limit of normal for the laboratory conducting the test.

          -  Are PPD negative at the time of screening.

          -  The patients will be allowed to use topical therapy during the washout period. These
             will include emollients, and mild steroids (class 6 or 7), except on one target area
             that will be the site for the skin biopsies.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous treatment with ustekinumab or other agent that specifically targets IL-12 or
             23.

          -  Have a history of latent or active granulomatous infection, including TB,
             histoplasmosis, or coccidioidomycosis, prior to screening, or are frequently in
             contact with individuals who carry active TB infection.

          -  Have a chest radiograph within 3 months prior to the first administration of study
             agent that show an abnormality suggestive of a malignancy or current active infection
             including TB.

          -  Have a non-tuberculous mycobacterial infection or opportunistic systemic infection
             (e.g., Pneumocystis carinii, and aspergillosis) within 6 months prior to screening.

          -  Are HIV positive by history or POCT on the screening visit.

          -  Have documented current active hepatitis B (surface antigen positive or asymptomatic
             chronic carriers) or hepatitis C infection (anti-HCV positive), by history and/or
             screening test.

          -  Have a history of substance abuse (drug or alcohol) within the past year before
             screening.

          -  Have a serious concomitant illness that could require the use of systemic
             corticosteroids or otherwise interfere with the patient's participation in the trial.

          -  Pregnant women or women that are breast-feeding or plan to breast feed.  Women of
             childbearing age who plan to get pregnant within 15 weeks of stopping study agent.

          -  Evidence of acute or unstable clinically significant disease requiring active
             frequent monitoring.

          -  Evidence of other concomitant skin conditions (eg, psoriasis, or lupus erythematosus)
             other than atopic dermatitis that would interfere with evaluations of the effect of
             study medication on atopic dermatitis.

          -  Clinically important deviation from normal limits in physical examination, vital sign
             measurements, 12-lead electrocardiograms (ECGs), or clinical laboratory tests
             results, not associated with a chronic, well-controlled medical condition

          -  Have shown a previous immediate hypersensitivity response, including anaphylaxis, to
             an immunoglobulin product (plasma-derived, recombinant, e.g. monoclonal antibody).

          -  Have used an investigational agent within 60 days prior to screening or within 5
             half-lives of the investigational agent, whichever is longer.

          -  Have received the BCG vaccine within one year prior to taking ustekinumab or plan on
             receiving the vaccine one year after stopping ustekinumab.

          -  Live vaccines within 3 months before test article administration.

          -  Any medical, psychological or social condition that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, would jeopardize the health or well being of the participant during any
             study procedures or the integrity of the data.

          -  Have a transplanted organ (with the exception of a corneal transplant performed &gt;3
             months prior to screening).

          -  Have concomitant autoimmune disease (such as lupus, multiple   sclerosis, Crohn's
             Disease, etc).

          -  Have a known malignancy or history of malignancy (exception for basal cell carcinoma,
             squamous cell carcinoma, or cervical carcinoma in situ adequately treated without
             evidence of recurrence)

          -  Have had a nontuberculous mycobacterial infection or opportunistic infection (e.g.,
             cytomegalovirus, Pneumocystis carinii, and aspergillosis) within 6 months prior to
             screening.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Recruitment Office</last_name>
    <phone>1-800-782-2737</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rockefeller University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Emma Guttman, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 6, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 28, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Atopic Dermatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Eczema</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis, Atopic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
