<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="38676">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02138422</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014-PT026</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02138422</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase 3 Study to Evaluate Xilonix as an Anticancer Therapy in Patients With Symptomatic Colorectal Cancer</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>XBiotech, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>XBiotech, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Bulgaria: Bulgarian Drug Agency</authority>
    <authority>Czech Republic: State Institute for Drug Control</authority>
    <authority>France:  National Agency for the Safety of Medicine and Health Products</authority>
    <authority>Germany:  Paul Ehrlich Institute</authority>
    <authority>Georgia:  Ministry of Health, Labour and Social Affairs of Georgia</authority>
    <authority>Hungary: National Institute of Pharmacy</authority>
    <authority>Poland: Office for Registration of Medicinal Products, Medical Devices and Biocidal Products</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study will be to assess how effective Xilonix is in the
      treatment of patients with symptomatic colorectal cancer. By blocking a substance that helps
      tumours grow and spread, Xilonix therapy may not only slow tumour growth, but also may
      improve symptoms of muscle loss, fatigue, appetite loss, and pain in patients with
      colorectal cancer. The effectiveness of the therapy will be measured by assessing the change
      in these symptoms for patients treated with Xilonix versus those treated with placebo.
      Reversal of muscle loss will be assessed with a type of X-ray called a DEXA scanner.
      Improvement in pain, appetite loss, and fatigue will be measured with a questionnaire that
      is completed by patients enrolled on the trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">276</enrollment>
  <condition>Symptomatic Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Advanced Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer With Cachexia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo administered intravenously every 2 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Xilonix</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Xilonix administered intravenously every 2 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Xilonix</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Xilonix</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects with pathologically confirmed colorectal carcinoma that is metastatic or
             unresectable and which is refractory to standard therapy.  To be considered
             refractory, a subject must have failed both an oxaliplatin (oxaliplatin may have been
             in the adjuvant setting) and an irinotecan based regimen.

          2. Symptomatic Disease:  One symptom from each domain (metabolic and functional) must be
             present.

               -  Evidence of metabolic dysfunction, defined as the presence of one or more of the
                  following:

               -  Any degree (up to 20%) of unintentional total body weight loss in the previous 6
                  months

               -  Serum Interleukin 6 levels ≥10 pg/ml

               -  Evidence of reduced function or presence of cancer related symptoms as
                  determined by EORTC QLQ-C30.

               -  Appetite reduction, with a score of &gt;10

               -  Presence of fatigue, with a score of &gt;10

               -  Presence of Pain, with a score of &gt;10

               -  Decreased Role, Emotional and Social function, with a score of &lt; 90.

          3. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 1 or 2.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Mechanical obstruction that would prevent adequate oral nutritional intake.

          2. &gt;20% total body weight loss in the previous 6 months.

          3. Serious uncontrolled medical disorder, or active infection, that would impair the
             ability of the patient to receive protocol therapy.

          4. Uncontrolled or significant cardiovascular disease, including:

               -  A myocardial infarction within the past 6 months.

               -  Uncontrolled angina within the past 3 months.

               -  Congestive heart failure within the past 3 months, if defined as NYHC-II.

               -  Diagnosed or suspected congenital long QT syndrome.

               -  Any history of clinically significant ventricular arrhythmias (such as
                  ventricular tachycardia, ventricular fibrillation, Wolff-Parkinson-White (WPW)
                  syndrome, or torsade de pointes).

               -  Any history of second or third degree heart block (may be eligible if currently
                  have a pacemaker).

               -  Heart rate &lt; 50 beats per minute on pre-entry electrocardiogram.

               -  Uncontrolled hypertension (blood pressure &gt;150 mm Hg systolic and &gt;95 mm Hg
                  diastolic).

          5. Dementia or altered mental status that would prohibit the understanding or rendering
             of informed consent.

          6. Subjects who have not recovered from the adverse effects of prior therapy at the time
             of enrollment to ≤ grade 1; excluding alopecia and grade 2 neuropathy.

          7. Subjects who have received extensive prior radiation therapy to the bone marrow.
             Extensive radiation therapy is defined as treatment of more than one axial bony
             metastasis. However for subjects with rectal cancer pelvic irradiation, in addition
             to treatment of one axial bony metastasis, is acceptable.

          8. Immunocompromised subjects, including subjects known to be infected with human
             immunodeficiency virus (HIV).

          9. Known hepatitis B surface antigen and/or hepatitis C antibody or known history of
             infection.

         10. History of tuberculosis (latent or active) or positive Interferon-gamma release assay
             (IGRA).

         11. Receipt of a live (attenuated) vaccine within 1 month prior to Randomization

         12. Subjects with history of hypersensitivity to compounds of similar chemical or
             biologic composition to Xilonix™ or any component of its formulations.

         13. Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding.

         14. WOCBP or men whose sexual partners are WOCBP who are unwilling or unable to use an
             acceptable method of contraception for at least 1 month prior to randomization, for
             the duration of the study, and for at least 3 months after the last dose of study
             medication.

         15. History of progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy or other
                  demyelinating disease.

         16. Subjects on immunosuppressive therapy, including transplant patients.

         17. Subjects with known brain metastases.  Subjects with symptoms of brain metastases
             during screening should undergo CT imaging prior to randomization.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael D Stecher, MD</last_name>
    <phone>512-386-2900</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hong DS, Hui D, Bruera E, Janku F, Naing A, Falchook GS, Piha-Paul S, Wheler JJ, Fu S, Tsimberidou AM, Stecher M, Mohanty P, Simard J, Kurzrock R. MABp1, a first-in-class true human antibody targeting interleukin-1α in refractory cancers: an open-label, phase 1 dose-escalation and expansion study. Lancet Oncol. 2014 May;15(6):656-66. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(14)70155-X. Epub 2014 Apr 17.</citation>
    <PMID>24746841</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 12, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>colorectal cancer</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cachexia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
