<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="131199">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02004977</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1111S06384</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01HL113235</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02004977</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Improving High School Breakfast Environments</brief_title>
  <acronym>breakFAST!</acronym>
  <official_title>Improving High School Breakfast Environments</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goals of this intervention study are to implement best practice strategies to expand and
      promote the school breakfast program and test the impact upon student participation rates
      among a) all 10th and 11th grade students and among a randomly selected cohort of 800
      students  b) total diet and body mass index and percent body fat inin 16 rural Minnesota
      school districts.

      School-wide Primary Aim: Improve participation in the school breakfast program among high
      school students. Hypothesis: School-wide school breakfast program participation will be
      higher in the intervention versus comparison group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We will accomplish the following secondary aims using a random subsample of 800 incoming
      10th and11th grade students.

      Student-level Secondary Aims Secondary Aim 1: High school students in the intervention
      condition will decrease their rate of weight gain relative to height gain as measured by
      change in body mass index and percent body fat compared to students in the control
      condition. Hypothesis: Body mass index and percent body fat will be maintained or reduced in
      the treatment versus control group.

      Secondary Aim 2: High school students in the intervention condition will maintain or
      decrease their energy intake while improving dietary intakes of low fat dairy, whole grains
      and fresh fruits compared to the control students.

      Hypothesis: Energy intake (measured by 3, 24-hour recalls) will be maintained or reduced and
      intakes of low fat dairy, whole grains and fresh fruits will increase more in the
      intervention groups.

      Secondary Aim 3: Compared to students in the control condition, high school students in the
      intervention condition will report receiving more support to eat school breakfast. Support
      will be social (increased peer and school support) or related to the school environment
      (satisfaction with serving locations and times, eating locations, foods and increased
      availability of low fat dairy, fruits and whole grains for breakfast).

      Hypothesis: The treatment group will report receiving more social and school environment
      support for eating school breakfast than the comparison group (measured by a student
      survey).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent students eating the school breakfast</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline in student level breakfast participation at the end of one school year and two school years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>participation in the reimbursable school breakfast program will be evaluated from school provided objective participation data at 3 time points: prior year (baseline), 1 school year later and 24 months later.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objectively measured student height and weight</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline in student body mass index at the end of one school year and two school years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Trained research staff will collect individual heights and weight  from the cohort of student participants at school.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent body fat</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline in student body fat at the end of the school year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Student percent body fat will be measured by trained research staff</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Dietary recalls</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline in dietary intakes at the end of the school year.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Up to 3 dietary intakes will be collected over the phone by trained staff to capture 2 weekday and 1 weekend days.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Social support</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in perceived support from baseline at the end of the school year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The student cohort will take a 10 minute survey capturing social support (peers, teachers, coaches, parents) and school environment (satisfaction with breakfast serving and eating locations and times, food preferences).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">800</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The role of the intervention arm (schools) is to improve access to the school breakfast program</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Comparison arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>the role of the comparison arm (schools) is to maintain usual breakfast program at school</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Improve access to the school breakfast program</intervention_name>
    <description>Access to the school breakfast program is defined as implementation of a grab-n-go cart outside of the school cafeteria, policy change allowing students to eat in the hallway and marketing of the program. in rural high schools.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>improve access to school breakfast</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Must be in 10th or 11th grade in school year 2013-14 Must have access to the internet Must
        have access to a phone

        Exclusion Criteria for the Cohort:

        Unable to read English Unable to speak English Pregnant Plan to move out of the school
        district within school year Not in school most mornings Eat breakfast 4 or more days a
        week
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marilyn S Nanney, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55414</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 3, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
