<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="136311">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02083380</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MMV_OZ439_13_003</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02083380</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase IIb Study to Investigate the Efficacy of OZ439 &amp; Piperaquine Phosphate Co-administered to Adults &amp; Children With Uncomplicated Plasmodium Falciparum.</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomised, Double-blind, Phase IIb Study to Investigate the Efficacy, Safety, Tolerability and Pharmacokinetics of a Single Dose Regimen of Artefenomel (OZ439) in Loose Combination With Piperaquine Phosphate in Adults and Children With Uncomplicated Plasmodium Falciparum Malaria.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medicines for Malaria Venture</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medicines for Malaria Venture</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Gabon: Ministry of Public Health and Public Hygiene (MSPHP)</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A randomised, double-blind single-dose (loose combination) study in patients with
      uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria. The study will test for efficacy/futility
      through analyses, using Bayesian methodology. Adults and children will be included through
      progressive step-down in age following safety analyses.

      This study investigates the efficacy exposure-response of OZ439/PQP combination in the
      target populations and if it meets its efficacy objectives, will inform dose setting for
      Phase III studies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A randomised, double-blind single-dose (loose combination) study in patients spanning the
      age range greater than or equal to 6 months to less than 70 years, with uncomplicated
      Plasmodium falciparum malaria. Three OZ439/PQP treatment arms will be included (for patients
      &gt; 35 kg), with doses scaled to target similar exposures in lighter patients.

      The study aims to recruit predominantly patient populations with the highest probability of
      having 'lower immunity' to P. falciparum, while also including patients with a probability
      of having 'higher immunity'. Hence the study will recruit across a wide age range and across
      geographical regions (Africa, Asia and possibly Latin America). The underlying assumption is
      that children of 5 years or less in Africa and all ages in Asia/Latin America will have the
      lower immunity and hence potentially require the highest drug exposure to achieve effective
      treatment. For this reason, patients of 5 years or less in Africa will form the largest
      proportion of the population while patients of greater than 5 years in Africa will form the
      lowest proportion of the population.

      The study will test for efficacy/futility at Day 28 (including data from patients
      discontinuing prior to Day 28) through interim analyses using Bayesian methodology. Only
      data from patients in Asia/Latin America and patients of 5 years or less in Africa (the
      'lower immunity' population) will be included in the interim analyses. Interim assessment of
      efficacy and futility will occur after recruitment of approximately 50 evaluable patients
      per dose cohort and thereafter approximately every 25 patients.

      Independently of the analyses for efficacy/futility, the safety of OZ439/PQP treatment arms
      will be assessed at scheduled time points by an Independent Safety Monitoring Board (ISMB).

      Adults and children will be included through progressive step-down in age range following
      safety evaluation.

      Following Screening and informed consent, patients will receive study drug and will be
      followed for clinical signs of malaria (parasitaemia and temperature), safety assessments
      and pharmacokinetics up to Day 42 following dosing (Day 63 at selected sites).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PCR-adjusted adequate clinical and parasitological response (ACPR) at Day 28</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PCR-adjusted adequate clinical and parasitological response (ACPR) at Day 28</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PCR - adjusted ACPR at Day 42 and 63</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 42, 63 (subset of patients)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PCR - adjusted ACPR at Day 42 and 63</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>o Non-compartmental analysis (NCA) of concentrations of OZ439 and o Non-compartmental analysis (NCA) of concentrations of OZ439 and piperaquine</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 7,14,28,42,63</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Non-compartmental analysis (NCA) of concentrations of OZ439 and piperaquine</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Day0-Day63</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Incidence of adverse events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">495</enrollment>
  <condition>Uncomplicated Plasmodium Falciparum Malaria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A) OZ439 800mg: PQP  1440mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>OZ439 800mg: Piperaquine phosphate 1440mg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B) OZ439 800mg: PQP  960mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>B) OZ439 800mg: Piperaquine 960mg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>C) OZ439 800mg: PQP  640mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>C) OZ439 800mg: Piperaquine 640mg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>A) OZ439 800mg: PQP  1440mg</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>A) OZ439 800mg: PQP  1440mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>B) OZ439 800mg: PQP  960mg</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>B) OZ439 800mg: PQP  960mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>C) OZ439 800mg: PQP  640mg</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>C) OZ439 800mg: PQP  640mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female patient age &gt;6 months &lt;70 years.

          2. Body weight &gt;5 kg &lt;90 kg.

          3. Presence of mono-infection of P. falciparum with:

               1. Fever, as defined by axillary temperature ≥ 37.5°C or oral/rectal/tympanic
                  temperature ≥ 38°C, or history of fever in the previous 24 hours (history of
                  fever must be documented) and,

               2. Microscopically confirmed parasite infection, in range 1,000 to 100,000 asexual
                  parasites /µL of blood.

          4. Written informed consent provided by the adult patient, or parent or legally
             acceptable representative (LAR) of the minor patient or by an impartial witness (if
             the patient or patient's LAR is illiterate), and by the medically qualified
             Investigator.  Children will be asked to provide assent where appropriate.  The age
             from which this will be sought will be defined by local legislation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Presence of severe malaria (according to WHO definition - WHO 2013)

          2. Anti-malarial treatment:

               1. With piperaquine -based compound, mefloquine, naphthoquine or
                  sulphadoxine/pyrimethamine (SP) within the previous 6 weeks (after their
                  inhibition of new infections has fallen below 50%).

               2. With amodiaquine or chloroquine within the previous 4 weeks.

               3. With quinine, halofantrine, lumefantrine-based compounds and any other
                  anti-malarial treatment or antibiotics with anti-malarial activity (including
                  cotrimoxazole, tetracyclines, quinolones and fluoroquinolones, and azithromycin)
                  within the past 14 days.

               4. With any herbal products or traditional medicines, within the past 7 days.

          3. Known history or evidence of clinically significant disorders such as, respiratory
             (including active tuberculosis), hepatic, renal, gastrointestinal, immunological,
             neurological (including auditory), endocrine, infectious, malignancy, psychiatric,
             history of convulsions or other abnormality (including head trauma).

          4. Family history of sudden death or of congenital or clinical conditions known to
             prolong QTcB or QTcF interval or e.g. patients with a history of symptomatic cardiac
             arrhythmias, with clinically relevant bradycardia or with severe cardiac disease.

          5. History of symptomatic cardiac arrhythmias or with clinically relevant bradycardia.

          6. Any predisposing cardiac conditions for arrhythmia such as severe hypertension, left
             ventricular hypertrophy (including hypertrophic cardiomyopathy) or congestive cardiac
             failure accompanied by reduced left ventricle ejection fraction.

          7. Electrolyte disturbances, particularly hypokalaemia, hypocalcaemia or
             hypomagnesaemia.

          8. Any treatment which can induce a lengthening of QT interval, such as:

               1. Antiarrhythmics (e.g. amiodarone, disopyramide, dofetilide, ibutilide,
                  procainamide, quinidine, hydroquinidine, sotalol),

               2. Neuroleptics (e.g. phenothiazines, sertindole, sultopride, chlorpromazine,
                  haloperidol, mesoridazine, pimozide, or thioridazine),

               3. Anti-depressive agents, certain antimicrobial agents, including agents of the
                  following classes macrolides (e.g. erythromycin, clarithromycin),
                  fluoroquinolones (e.g. moxifloxacin, sparfloxacin), imidazole and triazole
                  antifungal agents, and also pentamidine and saquinavir,

               4. Certain non-sedating antihistamines (e.g. terfenadine, astemizole, mizolastine),
                  cisapride, droperidol, domperidone, bepridil, diphemanil, probucol,
                  levomethadyl, methadone, vinca alkaloids, arsenic trioxide.

               5. Anti-emetics with known QT prolongation potential such as domperidone

          9. Mixed Plasmodium infection

         10. Severe vomiting, defined as more than three times in the 24 hours prior to enrolment
             in the study or inability to tolerate oral treatment, or severe diarrhoea defined as
             3 or more watery stools per day

         11. Severe malnutrition (defined for subjects aged ten years or less as the
             weight-for-height being below -3 standard deviation or less than 70% of median of the
             NCHS/WHO normalised reference values, and for subjects aged greater than ten years, a
             body mass index (BMI) of less than 16 (WFP Manual, Chapter 1)).

         12. Known history of hypersensitivity, allergic or adverse reactions to piperaquine or
             other aminoquinolones or to OZ439 or OZ277

         13. Known active Hepatitis A IgM (HAV-IgM), Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) or
             Hepatitis C antibody (HCV Ab).

         14. If Total Bilirubin is normal, exclude the patient if liver function tests AST/ALT ≥
             2xULN.

         15. If Total Bilirubin is &gt; 1 and ≤ 1.5xULN, exclude the patient if AST/ALT &gt;1.5xULN.

         16. Total Bilirubin &gt; 1.5XULN

         17. Haemoglobin level below 8 g/dL.

         18. Serum creatinine levels ≥2 x ULN

         19. Female patients of child bearing potential must be neither pregnant (as demonstrated
             by a negative pregnancy test) nor lactating, and must be willing to take measures not
             to become pregnant during the study period and safety follow-up period.

         20. Have received an investigational drug within the past 4 weeks.

         21. Previous participation in any malaria vaccine study or received malaria vaccine in
             any other circumstance.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fiona Macintyre, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Medicines For Malaria Venture (MMV)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Ramharter, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CERMEL (Centre de Recherches Médicale de Lambaréné)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael Ramharter, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+43-1-40400-4440</phone>
    <email>michael.ramharter@meduniwien.ac.at</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre National de Recherche et de Formation sur le paludisme (CNRFP) Ouagadougou, Kadiogo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ouagadougou</city>
        <country>Burkina Faso</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alfred Tiono, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(226) 70 28 57 26.</phone>
      <email>t.alfred@fasonet.bf</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alfred Tiono, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical research Unit of Nanoro (CRUN)/CMA Saint Camille de Nanoro, 11 BP 218 Ouagadougou CMS 11</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ouagadougou</city>
        <country>Burkina Faso</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Halidou Tinto, MD</last_name>
      <phone>226 50 44 62 49</phone>
      <email>tintohalidou@yahoo.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Halidou Tinto, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IMBANACO</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cali</city>
        <country>Colombia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Socrates Herrera, MD</last_name>
      <email>sherrera@inmuno.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Socrates Herrera, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre de Recherches Medicales de Lambarene, Albert Schweitzer Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lambarene</city>
        <country>Gabon</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Ramharter, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(+43)1-40400-4440</phone>
      <email>michael.ramharter@meduniwien.ac.at</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Ramharter, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>arielle K. Bouyou-Akotet, Department of Parasitology-Mycology and Tropical Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Université des Sciences de la Santé, BP 4009, Libreville, Gabon</name>
      <address>
        <city>Libreville</city>
        <country>Gabon</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marielle Bouyou Akotet, MD</last_name>
      <phone>241 01 70 48 96</phone>
      <email>mariellebouyou@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marielle Bouyou Akotet, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MANHIÇA HEALTH RESEARCH CENTER, Rua 12, Vila da Manhica, Maputa,</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chefe Maputa</city>
        <country>Mozambique</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Quique Bassat, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(258) 826334350</phone>
      <email>quique.bassat@cresib.cat</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Quique Bassat, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tororo District Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tororo</city>
        <country>Uganda</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Adoke Yeka, MD</last_name>
      <phone>256 414540524</phone>
      <email>yadoke@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Adoke Yeka, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Malariology, Parasitology and Entomology, 245 Luong The Vinh Street, Trung van, Tu Liem, Hanoi, Vietnam</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hanoi</city>
        <country>Vietnam</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Phuc Bui</last_name>
      <phone>8448543034</phone>
      <email>phucnimpe@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Phuc Bui</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Burkina Faso</country>
    <country>Colombia</country>
    <country>Gabon</country>
    <country>Mozambique</country>
    <country>Uganda</country>
    <country>Vietnam</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mmv.org/</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 7, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Plasmodium falciparum malaria</keyword>
  <keyword>malaria</keyword>
  <keyword>OZ 439</keyword>
  <keyword>piperaquine</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Malaria, Falciparum</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Piperaquine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
