<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="60335">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01816035</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>7900</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-00552</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA015704</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01816035</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ado-Trastuzumab Emtansine in Treating Patients With HER2-Positive Metastatic or Locally Advanced Breast Cancer That Cannot Be Removed by Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Thrombokinetic Studies of Trastuzumab Emtansine</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Washington</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial studies the side effects and best way of giving ado-trastuzumab emtansine
      in treating patients with human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)-positive
      metastatic or locally advanced breast cancer that cannot be removed by surgery. Biological
      therapies, such as ado-trastuzumab emtansine may stimulate the immune system in different
      ways and stop cancer cells from growing
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess change in thrombokinetics (platelet circulation life span) and megakaryopoiesis
      effects in bone marrow.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the progression free survival (PFS), duration of response, benefit rate (as
      defined by stable disease, partial response, or complete response by Response Evaluation
      Criteria in Solid Tumors [RECIST] v 1.1), overall response rate (as defined by partial or
      complete response by RECIST v 1.1), and survival.

      II. To evaluate the safety of trastuzumab emtansine (ado-trastuzumab emtansine)
      (non-platelet toxicity).

      III. To evaluate the pharmacokinetics of trastuzumab emtansine.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive trastuzumab emtansine intravenously (IV) over 30-90 minutes on day 1.
      Treatment repeats every 21 days for 2 courses in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity. Patients achieving response may continue treatment.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up periodically.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Thrombokinetic changes in the bone marrow</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 22 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The actual analysis will fit a linear mixed effects model, using a two-sided Wald test to compare pre-therapy to the two post-therapy values, and should have greater power than a matched pairs design. Also, platelet lifespan may be measured in absolute terms (platelet lifespan) or relative terms (percentage relative to pre-therapy lifespan), and may be transformed to decrease the influence of extreme values.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Megakaryocyte toxicity and depletion in bone marrow as assessed by NCI CTCAE v4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 42</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence, type, and severity of adverse events (AEs) graded according to the NCI CTCAE v4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after completion of study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (ORR), based on investigator assessment using RECIST v. 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PFS assessed using RECIST v. 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from study entry to the first occurrence of disease progression, or death from any cause, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of objective response (DOR), based on investigator assessment using RECIST v.1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>First tumor assessment that supports the patient's objective response until the time of disease progression or death from any cause, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical benefit rate, defined as the proportion of patients who achieve an objective response (complete response [CR] or partial response [PR]), or maintain SD for at least 6 months from study entry, based on investigator assessment using RECIST v. 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>HER2-positive Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ado-trastuzumab emtansine)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive trastuzumab emtansine IV over 30-90 minutes on day 1. Treatment repeats every 21 days for 2 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients achieving response may continue treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ado-trastuzumab emtansine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ado-trastuzumab emtansine)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Kadcyla</other_name>
    <other_name>T-DM1</other_name>
    <other_name>trastuzumab-DM1</other_name>
    <other_name>trastuzumab-MCC-DM1</other_name>
    <other_name>trastuzumab-MCC-DM1 antibody-drug conjugate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ado-trastuzumab emtansine)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ado-trastuzumab emtansine)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pharmacological studies</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Signed study-specific informed consent form

          -  Histologically or cytologically documented breast cancer

          -  Metastatic or unresectable locally advanced/recurrent breast cancer

          -  HER2-positive disease documented as in situ hybridization (ISH)-positive and/or 3+by
             immunohistochemistry (IHC) on previously collected tumor tissue

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt; 1500 cells/mm^3

          -  Platelet count &gt; 100,000/mm^3

          -  Hemoglobin &gt; 9.0 g/dL (patients are allowed to receive transfused red blood cells
             [RBC] to achieve this level)

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 × upper limit of normal (ULN), except in patients with
             previously documented Gilbert's syndrome, in which case the direct bilirubin should
             be less than or equal to the ULN

          -  Serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT) (aspartate aminotransferase [AST]) and
             serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase (SGPT) (alanine aminotransferase [ALT]) =&lt; 2.5
             × ULN

          -  Alkaline phosphatase =&lt; 2.5 × ULN (patients with hepatic and/or bone metastases:
             alkaline phosphatase =&lt; 5 × ULN)

          -  Serum creatinine &lt; 1.5 × ULN

          -  International normalized ratio (INR) &lt; 1.5 × ULN

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0, 1, or 2

          -  Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &gt;= 50% by either echocardiogram (ECHO) or
             multigated acquisition scan (MUGA)

          -  Negative results of serum pregnancy test for premenopausal women of reproductive
             capacity and for women &lt; 12 months after entering menopause

          -  For women of childbearing potential and men with partners of childbearing potential,
             agreement by the patient and/or partner to use a highly effective, non-hormonal form
             of contraception or two effective forms of non-hormonal contraception

          -  Willingness and ability to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plans, laboratory
             tests, and other study procedures, including bone marrow biopsy and thrombokinetic
             studies

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known platelet disorder, such as von Willebrand's disease or baseline platelet count
             of &lt; 100,000/mm^3

          -  Chemotherapy =&lt; 21 days before first study treatment

          -  Trastuzumab =&lt; 21 days before first study treatment

          -  Lapatinib =&lt; 14 days before first study treatment

          -  Investigational therapy or any other therapy =&lt; 28 days before first study treatment

          -  Any prior trastuzumab emtansine

          -  Previous radiotherapy for the treatment of unresectable, locally advanced/recurrent
             or metastatic breast cancer is not allowed if:

               -  The last fraction of radiotherapy has been administered within 14 days prior to
                  randomization

               -  The patient has not recovered from any resulting acute toxicity (to grade =&lt; 1)
                  prior to randomization

          -  Brain metastases that are untreated or symptomatic, or require any radiation,
             surgery, or steroid therapy to control symptoms from brain metastases within 30 days
             of first on-study thrombokinetic study; for patients with newly diagnosed brain
             metastases or unequivocal progression of brain metastases on screening scans,
             localized treatment (i.e., surgery, radiosurgery, and/or whole brain radiotherapy) is
             required before study enrollment; subjects with known brain metastases must have
             clinically controlled neurologic symptoms, defined as surgical excision and/or
             radiation therapy followed by 14 days of stable neurologic function prior to the
             first thrombokinetic procedure; patients with small brain metastases not symptomatic
             and deemed requiring treatment by managing clinicians or study investigators may be
             permitted to enroll on study

          -  History of intolerance (including grade 3 or 4 infusion reaction) or hypersensitivity
             to trastuzumab or murine proteins

          -  Current peripheral neuropathy of grade &gt;= 3 per the National Cancer Institute Common
             Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE) v. 4.0

          -  Current unstable ventricular arrhythmia requiring treatment

          -  History of symptomatic congestive heart failure (CHF) (New York Heart Association
             [NYHA] classes II−IV)

          -  History of myocardial infarction or unstable angina within 6 months of enrollment

          -  History of a decrease in LVEF to &lt; 40% or symptomatic CHF with previous trastuzumab
             treatment

          -  Severe dyspnea at rest due to complications of advanced malignancy or requiring
             current continuous oxygen therapy

          -  Current severe, uncontrolled systemic disease (e.g., clinically significant
             cardiovascular, pulmonary, or metabolic disease) resulting in a life expectancy of &lt;
             6 months

          -  Major surgical procedure or significant traumatic injury within 28 days before
             enrollment or anticipation of the need for major surgery during the course of study
             treatment

          -  Current pregnancy or lactation

          -  Current known active infection with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis B,
             and/or hepatitis C virus; for patients who are known carriers of hepatitis B virus
             (HBV), active hepatitis B infection must be ruled out based on negative serologic
             testing and/or determination of HBV deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) viral load per local
             guidelines

          -  Assessed by the investigator to be unable or unwilling to comply with the
             requirements of the protocol
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vijayakrishna Gadi</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Vijayakrishna K. Gadi</last_name>
      <phone>206-288-2222</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vijayakrishna K. Gadi</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 17, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 19, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Trastuzumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Maytansine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
