<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="62019">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01833936</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OH1-12-00389</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01833936</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>E-Stim and Achilles Tendon Repair Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>E-Stim</acronym>
  <official_title>The Use of Electrical Stimulation on Muscle Cross Sectional Area and Muscle Fascicle Length Following Postoperative Achilles Tendon Repair</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Orthopedic Foot and Ankle Center, Ohio</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Don Joy Orthotics</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Orthopedic Foot and Ankle Center, Ohio</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Calf muscle atrophy (muscle degeneration) is common following Achilles tendon repair due to
      the immobilization period necessary to ensure optimal healing.

      The purpose of this study is to determine if the use of neuromuscular electrical stimulation
      (NMES) after Achilles tendon surgery will reduce calf muscle atrophy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The specific aims of this study are to evaluate the use of electrical stimulation on muscle
      cross-sectional area and muscle fascicle length following post-operative Achilles tendon
      surgery.

      Patients will be randomly assigned to receive an electrical stimulation unit (Compex®, DJO
      Global, San Diego, CA). Twenty of these units will be experimental and 20 will be sham.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduce calf muscle atrophy</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks, 6 weeks and 12 weeks post-op</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The use of electrical stimulation will have a positive impact on skeletal muscle cross sectional area and fascicle length.  The cross sectional area and the fascicle length will decrease less in the group receiving electrical stimulation compared to the group receiving the sham electrical stimulation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Achilles Tendon Rupture</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1- Compex active muscle stimulator</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group 1 will receive an active muscle stimulator, which will be placed immediately following surgery.  Eight electrodes will be placed on the lower leg: four electrodes on the gastrocnemius (calf muscle), and two electrodes each on the lateral gastrocnemius (side) and anterior tibialis muscle (front). Subjects will use the stimulator for three 20 minute sessions per day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 -(inactive) muscle stimulator</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group 2 will receive a placebo (inactive) muscle stimulator, which will be placed immediately following surgery.  Eight electrodes will be placed on the lower leg: four electrodes on the gastrocnemius (calf muscle), and two electrodes each on the lateral gastrocnemius (side) and anterior tibialis muscle (front). Subjects will be instructed to use the stimulator for three 20 minute sessions per day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Compex® muscle stimulator</intervention_name>
    <description>The Compex® muscle stimulator is a commercially available muscle stimulator that is approved by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA), a governmental body.  It is not investigational.  The investigational part of this study aims to evaluate if the use of muscle simulation after Achilles tendon surgery will reduce calf atrophy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1- Compex active muscle stimulator</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 -(inactive) muscle stimulator</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Any patient who is having surgery to treat an acute Achilles tendon rupture or any
             surgery that involves reflecting or repairing the distal Achilles tendon.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Body mass index (BMI) greater than or equal to 45

          2. Inability to consent to participate in clinical research

          3. Any patient younger than 18 years old

          4. Any limitations that would interfere with the delivery of electrical stimulation
             including, but not limited to:

               1. Presence of an insulin pump

               2. Pacemaker, defibrillators or other implanted electrical device

               3. Neurostimulation implants

               4. History of epilepsy/seizure

               5. Current pregnancy. A pregnancy test will be performed for any female    prior to
                  surgical intervention per hospital protocol unless she is post-menopausal or has
                  been sterilized.

               6. Active malignancy

               7. Peripheral neuropathy

               8. Diabetes Mellitus

               9. Ischemia of lower limbs

              10. Active infection

              11. Following acute trauma or fracture
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Orthopedic Foot and Ankle Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Westerville</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43082</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Emily Stansbury</last_name>
      <phone>614-895-2424</phone>
      <email>ofacresearch@orthofootankle.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Natalie Henke</last_name>
      <phone>614-895-8747</phone>
      <phone_ext>187</phone_ext>
      <email>ofacresearch@orthofootankle.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christopher Hyer, DPM, MS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gomes AR, Cornachione A, Salvini TF, Mattiello-Sverzut AC. Morphological effects of two protocols of passive stretch over the immobilized rat soleus muscle. J Anat. 2007 Mar;210(3):328-35.</citation>
    <PMID>17331181</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Takano Y, Haneda Y, Maeda T, Sakai Y, Matsuse H, Kawaguchi T, Tagawa Y, Shiba N. Increasing muscle strength and mass of thigh in elderly people with the hybrid-training method of electrical stimulation and volitional contraction. Tohoku J. Exp. Med. 2010; 221: 77-85.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 12, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Orthopedic Foot and Ankle Center, Ohio</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Christopher Hyer</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>DPM, MS</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Achilles</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Rupture</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
