<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="151190">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01698489</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NA_00074308</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01698489</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Very Large Database of Lipids (VLDL)</brief_title>
  <acronym>VLDL</acronym>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Atherotech Diagnostics Lab</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Closer examination of granular lipid data in a large population offers numerous
      opportunities to generate new knowledge, ranging from studies examining concordance between
      commonly used lipid parameters to phenotypic  characterization of rare or extreme disorders
      of lipid metabolism, opening possibilities to better personalize future treatment of
      abnormal blood lipids.

      STUDY POPULATION:

      The Very Large Database of Lipids (VLDL) includes adults and children who were clinically
      referred for a Vertical Auto Profile (VAP).

      LIPID MEASUREMENTS:

      The VAP test (Atherotech, Birmingham, Alabama, USA) directly measures cholesterol
      concentrations of low density lipoprotein, very low density lipoprotein, intermediate
      density lipoprotein, high density lipoprotein, their subfractions, and lipoprotein(a).
      Triglycerides in the database are directly measured using the Abbott ARCHITECT C‐8000 system
      (Abbott Park, Illinois, USA). Lipid distributions in the database closely match those from
      the population-representative National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES)
      2007-2008.

      STUDY PROCEDURES:

      This database was investigator-initiated. Only de-identified data reach the investigational
      site. The first data harvest was in 2011, and encompassed 1,350,908 samples. The second
      harvest is underway; thus far, an updated database suited to assess seasonal variation has
      been established with 2,859,333 samples. The master database is housed at The Johns Hopkins
      Hospital in Baltimore, Maryland, and maintained by Drs. Jones and Martin. Only electronic
      data, and not biospecimens, are sent to Hopkins. The academic investigators have
      unrestricted access to study data, take responsibility for the accuracy of analyses, and
      have authority over manuscript preparation and submission.

      VARIABLES:

      The variables currently in the VLDL database are testing date, age, sex, low density
      lipoprotein, very low density lipoprotein, intermediate density lipoprotein, high density
      lipoprotein, their subfractions, lipoprotein(a), and LDL pattern. From these primary
      variables, many additional variables were derived for inclusion in the master database
      (e.g., non-HDL-C, Friedewald LDL-C, TC/HDL-C, etc.). Other analytes measured by validated
      assays in subsets of the VLDL database include apoB, apoA1, hsCRP, homocysteine, uric acid,
      insulin, hemoglobin A1c, 25-hydroxy vitamin D, cystatin C, Lp-PLA2, TSH, free T3 and T4,
      pro-BNP, direct bilirubin, CPK, creatinine and other components of the comprehensive
      metabolic panel, magnesium, and phosphate.

      DATABASE ORGANIZATION:

      In the current database, each record represents a unique patient. The 1st available VAP test
      for each patient is included. To meet the needs of a variety of research questions, we are
      prospectively planning to organize harvest 2 data into 3-year interval datasets (i.e., VLDL
      2006-2008, 2009-2011, VLDL 2012-2014, etc), a summation dataset (first VAP test for each
      patient), serial lab dataset (patients who have had repeated testing), and ancillary
      datasets (subsets of patients with coexisting data on other measures such as
      apolipoproteins, vitamin D, hs-CRP, TSH/T4, etc).

      INDIVIDUAL STUDIES:

      Individual VLDL studies will be based on a priori hypotheses or aims with statistical
      analysis plans (SAPs) peer-reviewed prior to execution. In the expandable &quot;Detailed
      Description&quot; section below, the VLDL investigators will periodically register individual
      studies and update their status on clinicaltrials.gov.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      REGISTRATION &amp; STATUS OF VLDL STUDIES:

        -  VLDL-1A: Friedewald Estimated versus Directly Measured Low-Density Lipoprotein
           Cholesterol and Treatment Implications (abstract presented; manuscript published;
           citation provided below)

        -  VLDL-1B: Derivation and Validation of a Novel Method for More Accurate Estimation of
           Low-Density Lipoprotein Cholesterol from the Standard Lipid Profile (manuscript under
           review)

        -  VLDL-2: Non-HDL-C, TC/HDL-C, and LDL-C Population Percentiles and Discordance (abstract
           presented; manuscript published; citation provided below)

        -  VLDL-3: Vitamin D Levels and Lipids (abstract presented; manuscript in preparation)

        -  VLDL-4: Correlates of the TG/HDL-C Ratio (abstract submitted; manuscript in
           preparation)

        -  VLDL-5: Ratio of Dense to Buoyant LDL Subclass and LDL Density Phenotype (abstract
           presented; manuscript published; citation provided below)

        -  VLDL-6: Characterization of Fredrickson-Levy Dyslipidemia Classes without Chylomicrons
           (IIa, IIb, III,IV) (abstract presented; manuscript in preparation)

        -  VLDL-7: Characterization of Fredrickson-Levy Dyslipidemia Classes with Chylomicrons
           (I,V) (abstract presented; manuscript in preparation)

        -  VLDL-8: Continuum of Non-Chylomicron Dyslipidemia Phenotype not Classifiable by
           Fredrickson-Levy Criteria (abstract presented; manuscript in preparation)

        -  VLDL-9: Characterization of Those with Extremely Low or High HDL-C Concentrations
           (abstract submitted; manuscript in preparation)

        -  VLDL-10A: Atherogenic Lipid Levels in 662,711 Elderly Persons: The Very Large Database
           of Lipids 10A (abstract submitted; manuscript in preparation)

        -  VLDL-10B: Narrowing Sex Differences in Lipoprotein Cholesterol Subclasses Following
           Menopause: Insights from the Very Large Database of Lipids (abstract submitted;
           manuscript in preparation)

        -  VLDL-11: Triglyceride-Rich Remnant Lipoprotein Cholesterol Concentrations in
           AIM-HIGH-Like Patients (abstract submitted; manuscript in preparation)

        -  VLDL-12: Complementary Information in Common Lipid Classifications (abstract in
           preparation)

        -  VLDL-13: The Relationship between Thyroid dysfunction and Advanced Lipoprotein
           Cholesterol Subfractions in a Contemporary Sample of US Adults (abstract submitted;
           manuscript in preparation)

        -  VLDL-14: Seasonal Differences in Lipid Profiles of 2.8 Million Consecutive, Unique US
           Adults: The Very Large Database of Lipids Seasonal Substudy (abstract submitted;
           manuscript in preparation)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2011</start_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Cross-Sectional</study_design>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2859333</enrollment>
  <condition>Lipid Disorders and Lipid Measurement</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients clinically referred for VAP density gradient ultracentrifugation.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Patients with age and lipid data are included in the master database. Eligibility criteria
        are specific to each individual study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven R Jones, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.benthamscience.com/open/tocbmj/articles/V006/1TOCBMJ.pdf</url>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Martin SS, Blaha MJ, Elshazly MB, Brinton EA, Toth PP, McEvoy JW, Joshi PH, Kulkarni KR, Mize PD, Kwiterovich PO, Defilippis AP, Blumenthal RS, Jones SR. Friedewald Estimated versus Directly Measured Low-Density Lipoprotein Cholesterol and Treatment Implications. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2013 Mar 20. doi:pii: S0735-1097(13)01098-X. 10.1016/j.jacc.2013.01.079. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>23524048</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ahmed, HM, Elshazly MB, Martin SS, Blaha MJ, Kulkarni KR, Jones SR. Ratio of Dense to Buoyant LDL Subclass is Associated with LDL Density Phenotype (VLDL-5). The Open Chemical and Biomedical Methods Journal 2013. 6:1-5.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Elshazly MB, Martin SS, Blaha MJ, Joshi PH, Toth PP, McEvoy JW, Al-Hijji MA, Kulkarni KR, Kwiterovich PO, Blumenthal RS, Jones SR. Non-HDL Cholesterol, Guideline Targets, and Population Percentiles for Secondary Prevention in a Clinical Sample of 1.3 Million Adults The Very Large Database of Lipids (VLDL-2 Study). J Am Coll Cardiol. 2013 Aug 7. doi:pii: S0735-1097(13)03075-1. 10.1016/j.jacc.2013.07.045. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>23973689</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 5, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 1, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Seth S. Martin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Sphingolipidoses</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lipid Metabolism Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
