<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="131260">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02088177</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>#6799</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>DA009236</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02088177</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Long-Acting Injectable Naltrexone to Treat Cannabis Dependence</brief_title>
  <official_title>Open-Label Pilot Study of Long-Acting Injectable Naltrexone Treatment for Cannabis Dependence</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York State Psychiatric Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York State Psychiatric Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an 8 week, outpatient research study testing the use of long-acting naltrexone
      (Vivitrol) as a treatment for marijuana dependence.  Vivitrol is a medication that is
      effective in treating dependence on opiates and opioids, and in treating dependence on
      alcohol.  It is FDA approved for these disorders. It is a long-acting medication that
      contains enough medicine in each injection to last for one month.  One way it works is by
      blocking the effects of opiates, including opiates released by the body in response to drugs
      and alcohol.  In this study, we are interested in testing the effects of Vivitrol in people
      with marijuana dependence.

      Individuals participating in this study will receive two Vivitrol injections, each given
      four weeks apart, (week 1 and week 5).  The injection is given in the muscle of the buttock
      on one side.  Participants will attend clinic visits two times a week during this 8-week
      study for medical management for drug use and for monitoring of physical and psychological
      health.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an 8 week, outpatient, open-label clinical trial of long-acting injectable
      naltrexone as a treatment for cannabis dependence.

      The purpose of the study will be to evaluate marijuana use patterns and tolerability of
      long-acting naltrexone in 7 treatment-seeking, cannabis-dependent outpatients; also to
      assess feasibility of conducting a larger trial with this medication. Cannabis dependent
      patients will have twice weekly clinic visits where they will receive injections of Vivitrol
      four weeks apart, in Week 1 and in Week 5.  The psychosocial intervention for this study
      will be Medical Management, designed to facilitate adherence to the study medication and
      monitoring procedures, as well as to support the participant in achieving his or her
      marijuana use goals.

      Participants will self-report cannabis use, will provide urine toxicology for quantitative
      assessment of THC (Tetrahydrocannabinol, the active ingredient in marijuana), and will
      provide serum samples for safety monitoring, and will answer questionnaires and will report
      on their physical and psychological health weekly.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in marijuana use</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 - 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Reduction in marijuana use, as measured by self reported dollars spent per week will be reported as the percent change in dollars per week comparing the baseline dollar amount per week reported in week 1 to the dollar amount per week reported in the final study week, which will be week 8 or earlier if the participant discontinues.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of participants receiving the second injection of study medication</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 - 5</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>All 7 participants will receive the first injection of study medication.  The proportion of participants who accept the second injection at week 5 will be used as one measure of tolerability.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number and severity of adverse events associated with naltrexone and its injection</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 - 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>All adverse events will be assessed by medical staff using the SAFTEE (Systematic Assessment for Treatment Emergent Events) protocol.  Adverse events deemed to be possibly associated with long-acting naltrexone or its injection will be reported and their severity will be described.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in marijuana use as measured by urine toxicology</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1- 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Urines will be collected twice weekly over the 8 week study.  A mean number of urine toxicologies negative for THC (negative = &lt; 50ng/dL) greater than zero over the 8 weeks of the study will indicate reduction in use.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in marijuana craving</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 - 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Marijuana craving, as measured by the the Marijuana Craving questionnaire self-report form, will be reported by participants weekly.  A lower score at the final study week (week 8 or earlier if participants discontinue) relative to baseline score (week 1) will indicate reduced cravings.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">7</enrollment>
  <condition>Cannabis Dependence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Long-acting injectable naltrexone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Two doses of long-acting injectable naltrexone, 380 mg by intramuscular injection in the gluteal muscle at study day 1 and again between study days 28-30.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Long-acting injectable naltrexone</intervention_name>
    <description>Vivitrol is a long-acting opioid antagonist which blocks opioid agonists from binding at opioid receptors.  It be administered as described above.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Long-acting injectable naltrexone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vivitrol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Between the ages of 18 - 60 years

          -  Meets DSM-IV (Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, edition IV-TR)
             criteria for cannabis dependence

          -  Seeking treatment for cannabis dependence

          -  Reports using cannabis an average of 5 days per week over the past 28 days

          -  Capable of giving informed consent and complying with study procedures

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Lifetime history of DSM-IV diagnosis of schizophrenia, schizoaffective disorder, or
             bipolar disorder

          -  Currently meeting DSM-IV criteria for a psychiatric disorder that, according to the
             investigator's judgment, may require pharmacological or non-pharmacological
             intervention during the course of the study

          -  Receiving opioid analgesic medication

          -  Known history of allergy, intolerance, or hypersensitivity to naltrexone

          -  Pregnancy, lactation, or failure to use adequate contraceptive methods in female
             participants who are actively engaging in sexual activity with men

          -  Unstable medical conditions, such as poorly controlled hypertension or liver disease,
             which might make participation hazardous

          -  Chronic pain conditions

          -  Liver dysfunction as indicated by elevated liver transaminases and GGT
             (gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase) greater than 2 times the upper limit of normal

          -  Current DSM-IV diagnosis of substance dependence other than nicotine or cannabis
             dependence

          -  Legally mandated to participate in a substance use disorder treatment program

          -  Risk for suicide
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Meredith A. Kelly, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia and NY Psychiatric Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Meredith A Kelly, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>646-774-5000</phone>
    <email>mak2102@columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Frances R Levin, M.D.</last_name>
    <email>frl2@columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>STARS clinic, Columbia-New York Presbyterian and New York State Psychiatric Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John J Mariani, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>212-923-3031</phone>
      <email>mariani@nyspi.columbia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Daniel Brooks, M.A.</last_name>
      <phone>212-923-3031</phone>
      <email>brooksd@nyspi.columbia.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Meredith A. Kelly, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>STARS Downtown, Columbia-Presbyterian and New York State Psychiatric Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10019</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John J Mariani, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>212-316-2528</phone>
      <email>marianij@nyspi.columbia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Agnes Mamczur, M.A.</last_name>
      <phone>212-316-2528</phone>
      <email>mamczur@nyspi.columbia.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Meredith A Kelly, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Johnson BA, Ait-Daoud N, Roache JD. The COMBINE SAFTEE: a structured instrument for collecting adverse events adapted for clinical studies in the alcoholism field. J Stud Alcohol Suppl. 2005 Jul;(15):157-67; discussion 140.</citation>
    <PMID>16223067</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 12, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 25, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cannabis</keyword>
  <keyword>Cannabis Dependence</keyword>
  <keyword>Cannabis Use Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Marijuana</keyword>
  <keyword>Naltrexone</keyword>
  <keyword>Long Acting Injectable Naltrexone</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Marijuana Abuse</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Naltrexone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
