<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="158026">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01841593</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SSAT 051</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01841593</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Two Way Cross Over Pharmacokinetic Interaction Study Between Raltegravir and Amlodipine in Healthy Volunteers</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St Stephens Aids Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St Stephens Aids Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to look at the levels of an HIV medication (raltegravir) in the
      blood, and how it is affected if raltegravir is taken at the same time as another medicine
      for high blood pressure (amlodipine). Many patients with HIV will also have high blood
      pressure, so it is important to know which drugs for each of these conditions can be taken
      together without affecting how well they work individually.

      Over a 3 week period, subjects will take amlodipine for 2 weeks, and raltegravir for 2
      weeks, with the middle week being on both drugs. The investigators will look at and compare
      the levels of these two drugs in the blood after subjects have taken them separately and
      both together.

      The duration of involvement in the study will be up to 22 days plus a screening visit which
      will take place up to 4 weeks prior to the start of the study, and a follow up visit which
      takes place  7-14 days after the last dose of study medication.

      This study is randomised (like flipping a coin) into two groups who will receive the same
      study medications, but in a different order (this is known as a crossover study). The
      subject and the study doctor will know which study medications you are taking at all times
      during the study.

      The subject will need to stay at the study centre all day (12-14 hours) on three occasions
      during the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of raltegravir and amlodipine co-administration</measure>
    <time_frame>21/22 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To investigate the pharmacokinetics of raltegravir and amlodipine co-administration. The pharmacokinetic parameters calculated for raltegravir and amlodipine will be trough concentration (Ctrough), defined as the concentration at 24 hours after the observed drug dose, the maximum observed plasma concentration (Cmax), elimination half-life (t1/2), time point at Cmax (Tmax), and total drug exposure, expressed as the area under the plasma concentration-time curve from 0-24 hours after dosing (AUC0-24h).
All pharmacokinetic parameters will be calculated using non-compartmental modeling techniques (WinNonlin®) and all statistical calculations performed and analyzed using SAS version 9.1 or SPSS V17.0.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of raltegravir and amlodipine co-administration</measure>
    <time_frame>21/22 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To investigate the safety and tolerability of raltegravir and amlodipine co-administration. Adverse events observed by the Investigator, or reported by the subject, and any remedial action taken, will be recorded in the subject's CRF and should be verifiable in the subject's notes throughout the study.  The nature of each event, time of onset after drug administration, duration and severity will be documented together with the Investigator's opinion of the causal relationship to the treatment (unrelated, unlikely, possible, probable, and definite).
All patients, whether withdrawn prematurely or not, will be included in the safety analysis.  All safety data and adverse events will be summarised.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">16</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>DAYS 1 to 7: raltegravir 400 mg BID DAYS 8 to 14: raltegravir 400 mg BID PLUS amlodipine 5 mg OD DAYS 15 to 21: amlodipine 5 mg OD</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>DAYS 1 to 7: amlodipine 5 mg OD DAYS 8 to 14: raltegravir 400 mg BID PLUS amlodipine 5 mg OD DAYS 15 to 21: raltegravir 400 mg BID</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Raltegravir</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Amlodipine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Subjects must meet all of the following inclusion criteria within 28 days prior to the
        baseline visit:

          -  The ability to understand and sign a written informed consent form, prior to
             participation in any screening procedures and must be willing to comply with all
             study requirements

          -  Male or non-pregnant, non-lactating females

          -  Between 18 to 65 years, inclusive

          -  Body Mass Index (BMI) of 18 to 35 kg/m2, inclusive.

          -  Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) must be using an adequate method of
             contraception to avoid pregnancy throughout the study and for a period of at least 12
             weeks after the study

          -  Willing to consent to their personal details being entered onto The Over-volunteering
             Prevention Scheme (TOPS) database

          -  Willing to provide photographic identification at each visit.

          -  Registered with a GP in the UK

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects who meet any of the following exclusion criteria are not to be enrolled in this
        study.

          -  Any significant acute or chronic medical illness including hypertension (BP
             persistently &gt;140/90 mmHg) or hypotension (BP persistently &lt;90/60 mmHg)

          -  Evidence of organ dysfunction or any clinically significant deviation from normal in
             physical examination, vital signs, ECG or clinical laboratory determinations

          -  Positive blood screen for hepatitis B surface antigen and/or C antibodies

          -  Positive blood screen for HIV-1 and/or 2 antibodies

          -  Current or recent (within 3 months) gastrointestinal disease

          -  Clinically relevant alcohol or drug use (positive urine drug screen) or history of
             alcohol or drug use considered by the Investigator to be sufficient to hinder
             compliance with treatment, follow-up procedures or evaluation of adverse events.
             Smoking is permitted, but tobacco intake should remain consistent throughout the
             study

          -  Exposure to any investigational drug or placebo within 3 months of first dose of
             study drug

          -  Use of any other drugs (unless approved by the Investigator), including
             over-the-counter medications and herbal preparations, within two weeks prior to first
             dose of study drug, unless approved/prescribed by the Principal Investigator as known
             not to interact with study drugs.

          -  Females of childbearing potential without the use of effective non-hormonal birth
             control methods, or not willing to continue practising these birth control methods
             for at least 12 weeks after the end of the treatment period

          -  Previous allergy to any of the constituents of the pharmaceuticals administered in
             this trial

          -  Lactose intolerance
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dr Marta Boffito</last_name>
    <phone>020 3315 6507</phone>
    <email>Marta.Boffito@chelwest.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St Stephen's AIDS Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SW10 9TH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dr Marta Boffito</last_name>
      <phone>020 8746 5601</phone>
      <email>Marta.Boffito@chelwest.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dr Marta Boffito</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 10, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 16, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Amlodipine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
