<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="3338">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02120001</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DAN1000AM</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02120001</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy Study on Silver-coated ETT Cleaned With a Novel Device</brief_title>
  <official_title>Silver-coated Endotracheal Tube Cleaned With a Novel Mechanism for Secretion Removal: a Randomized Controlled Clinical Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Brigham and Women's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Rhode Island Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Istitutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to test the efficacy of a novel cleaning device in keeping
      silver-coated endotracheal tubes free from bacterial colonization.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Several studies have suggested that biofilm formation inside the ETT plays a pivotal role in
      VAP development and drug-resistance induction. Silver-coated ETT have proven effective in
      delaying but not in preventing ETT colonization and biofilm formation, due to a barrier
      effect of biofilm and accumulated debris. Advanced ETT cleaning devices are able to remove
      debris and biofilm and reduce the total ETT microbial load to a certain extent. The
      Investigators hypothesize that the routine use of endOclear in patients intubated with a
      silver-coated ETT will reduce ETT microbial colonization. The Investigators therefore want
      to assess the reduction of ETT microbial colonization in patients intubated with a
      silver-coated ETT and cleaned with endOclear compared to the current standard of care of
      silver-coated ETT (blind suctioning). They plan to achieve this result by analyzing the
      tubes of each enrolled patient after it has been removed, either because the patient does
      not need it anymore due to his/her better clinical conditions, or because there is a need of
      tracheostomy or because he/she dies. Specifically they will analyze how the endOclear
      cleaning maneuver affects microbial colonization in the inner layer of the ETT and how this
      can determine distal airway inoculation and, ultimately, VAP development.

      Specific AIM #1: Investigators will test the hypothesis that routine use of endOclear in
      patients intubated with a silver-coated ETT will reduce ETT microbial colonization.

      Specific AIM #2: Investigators will test the hypothesis that keeping ETTs free from
      microbial colonization will prevent septic inoculation of distal airways

      Specific AIM #3: Investigators will test the hypothesis that prevention of ETT biofilm
      development will reduce drug resistance rates found in ETT and distal airways isolates

      The investigators will conduct a randomized clinical trial on 40 patients intubated with
      silver-coated ETT and randomized to receive standard ETT cleaning vs cleaning with the
      endOclear device.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Endotracheal tube colonization</measure>
    <time_frame>At extubation (an expected average of 7 days)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Discarded ETTs will be collected after extubation and sent for quantitative and qualitative microbiological analysis after silver ion inactivation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Microbiological colonization of distal airways</measure>
    <time_frame>At extubation (An expected average of 7 days)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigators will collect data about distal airways samples performed for clinical reasons during the study period and, in addition, investigators will collect a sample of tracheal aspirate immediately before extubation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ETT microscopic imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>At extubation (An expected average of 7 days)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Samples of ETT will be collected and stored for Scanned Electron Microscopy and Confocal Laser Scanning Microscopy with dead/alive staining</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>In-vivo respiratory mechanics</measure>
    <time_frame>At extubation (An expected average of 7 days)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Data about respiratory mechanics will be obtained in both groups for each enrolled patient three times a day (q8 hours). These measurements are safe non-invasive. They will require the RT to register pressure, volume and flow parameters from the ventilator in use on the patient.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Drug resistance testing</measure>
    <time_frame>At extubation (An expected average of 7 days)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigators will test drug resistances found in isolates of distal airways, tracheal aspirate and inner ETT surface</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Infective Processes and Clinical Outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>At extubation (An expected average of 7 days)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigators will keep track of patient data regarding ETT-related infections as well as data about ICU clinical outcomes (hours of mechanical ventilation, days of ICU stay, mortality, occurrence of tracheostomy and occurrence of ETT exchange)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Ventilator Associated Pneumonia</condition>
  <condition>Critically Ill</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ETT cleaning maneuver</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized to the treatment group will undergo an ETT cleaning maneuver with endOclear three times a day (every 8 hours) for the whole intubation period in addition to the standard of care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the protocol no intervention is planned for the control group, which will therefore be treated with blind suctioning as per caregiver clinical decision.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ETT cleaning maneuver</intervention_name>
    <description>EndOclear is a commercially available device. It consists of an endotracheal tube cleaning apparatus with a flexible central tube and a cleaning device at its distal end. The cleaning device has a mechanically expandable mesh structure which can be adapted to selectively move between a radially-collapsed position and a radially-expanded one. In operation, the collapsed cleaning apparatus is inserted into the ETT through a Y-shaped connector. The device is then expanded by a safety toggle protected trigger mechanism that, when fired, presses the device's smooth silicone disc against the inside surface of the endotracheal tube. The cleaning apparatus is then pulled out of the endotracheal tube removing mucus deposits and secretions.
We plan to add the use of endOclear to the standard ICU practice, scheduling the systematic use of the device every 8 hours for the whole intubation period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ETT cleaning maneuver</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>endOclear</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Admission to Medical, Surgical or Neuro ICU

          -  Subjects must be enrolled within 24 hours from intubation

          -  Subjects expected to be intubated for at least 48 hours or longer

          -  Subjects have been intubated with a silver-coated ETT

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current and past participation in another interventional trial conflicting with the
             present study

          -  Pregnant women

          -  Prisoner status
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lorenzo Berra, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lorenzo Berra, MD</last_name>
    <email>lberra@mgh.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lorenzo Berra, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 17, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 17, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lorenzo Berra, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Anesthesia and Critical Care MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Medical Devices</keyword>
  <keyword>Ventilator-Associated Pneumonia (VAP)</keyword>
  <keyword>Ventilator-Associated Events (VAE)</keyword>
  <keyword>Endotracheal Tube</keyword>
  <keyword>Microbial Diversity</keyword>
  <keyword>Drug-Resistance</keyword>
  <keyword>biofilms</keyword>
  <keyword>endotracheal intubation</keyword>
  <keyword>mechanical ventilation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Critical Illness</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia, Ventilator-Associated</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
