<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="35078">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01812720</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MC1287</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-00492</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01812720</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Carfilzomib and Dexamethasone in Treating Patients With Multiple Myeloma Who Previously Underwent a Stem Cell Transplant</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2 Trial of Carfilzomib Consolidation After Autologous Stem Cell Transplantation for Multiple Myeloma(CARAMEL 2)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II clinical trial studies how well carfilzomib and dexamethasone work in treating
      patients with multiple myeloma who previously underwent a stem cell transplant. Carfilzomib
      may stop the growth of cancer cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell growth.
      Immunosuppressive therapy, such as dexamethasone, may improve bone marrow function and
      increase blood cell counts. Giving carfilzomib together with dexamethasone may be an
      effective treatment for multiple myeloma
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess the complete response (CR) rate with carfilzomib and dexamethasone
      consolidation following an upfront single stem cell transplant (SCT).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess the toxicity of carfilzomib and dexamethasone when used as consolidation
      therapy in patients post SCT.

      II. To determine the progression free rate at 1 and 2 years post SCT. III. To evaluate
      progression-free survival and overall survival.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the proportion of patients achieving a minimal residual disease (MRD)
      negative status.

      II. To assess the HevyLite assay prior to and during treatment.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive carfilzomib intravenously (IV) over 30 minutes and dexamethasone orally
      (PO) on days 1, 2, 15, and 16. Treatment repeats every 28 days for 6 courses in the absence
      of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study therapy, patients are followed up every 3 months for 3 years and
      then every 6 months for 2 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of complete response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The proportion of successes will be estimated by the number of successes divided by the total number of evaluable patients. Exact binomial 95% confidence intervals for the true success proportion will be calculated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from registration to death due to any cause, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The distribution of survival time will be estimated using the method of Kaplan-Meier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from registration to progression or death due to any cause, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The distribution of progression-free survival will be estimated using the method of Kaplan-Meier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to progression post SCT</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from SCT to the earliest day with documentation of disease progression, assessed at 1 year post-SCT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The distribution of time to progression will be estimated using the method of Kaplan-Meier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to progression post SCT</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from SCT to the earliest day with documentation of disease progression, assessed at 2 years post-SCT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The distribution of time to progression will be estimated using the method of Kaplan-Meier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum grade for each type of adverse event</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after last day of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Frequency tables will be reviewed to determine adverse event patterns.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">43</enrollment>
  <condition>Refractory Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <condition>Stage II Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (carfilzomib, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive carfilzomib IV over 30 minutes and dexamethasone PO on days 1, 2, 15, and 16. Treatment repeats every 28 days for 6 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>carfilzomib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (carfilzomib, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Kyprolis</other_name>
    <other_name>PR-171</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (carfilzomib, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Aeroseb-Dex</other_name>
    <other_name>Decaderm</other_name>
    <other_name>Decadron</other_name>
    <other_name>DM</other_name>
    <other_name>DXM</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (carfilzomib, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Creatinine =&lt; 3 mg/dL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1,000/μL

          -  Platelet count &gt;= 75,000/μL

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 8.0 g/dL

          -  Diagnosis of symptomatic multiple myeloma (MM)

          -  Received single autologous stem cell transplantation 60-120 days prior to
             registration

          -  Received the autologous SCT =&lt; 12 months of their diagnosis of myeloma to be eligible
             for the study

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status (PS) 0, 1 or 2

          -  Recovered from toxicity of previous chemotherapy (excludes grade 1 neurotoxicity and
             hematological toxicity)

          -  Voluntary written informed consent before performance of any study-related procedure
             not part of normal medical care, with the understanding that the subject may withdraw
             consent at any time without prejudice to future medical care

          -  Negative pregnancy test performed =&lt; 7 days prior to registration, for women of
             childbearing potential only

          -  Willingness to return to the Mayo Clinic enrolling institution for follow-up (during
             the Active Monitoring Phase of the study) (NOTE: During the Active Monitoring Phase
             of a study [i.e., active treatment and observation], participants must be willing to
             return to the consenting institution for follow-up)

          -  Measurable disease of multiple myeloma at the time of baseline values for disease
             assessment as defined by at least one of the following:

               -  Serum monoclonal protein &gt;= 1.0 g/dL

               -  &gt;= 200 mg of monoclonal protein in the urine on 24 hour electrophoresis

               -  Serum immunoglobulin free light chain &gt;= 10 mg/dL AND abnormal serum
                  immunoglobulin kappa to lambda free light chain ratio

               -  Bone marrow plasma cells &gt;= 30%

          -  For patients with no relapse prior to transplant, measurable disease at the time of
             diagnosis

          -  For patients who have had a disease relapse prior to transplant, measurable disease
             at the time of the most recent relapse immediately prior to transplant

          -  If the patient had treatment for the relapsed disease prior to transplant, the
             patient must have measurable disease at the time of relapse prior to this therapy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior allogeneic bone marrow/peripheral blood stem cell transplant

          -  Evidence of disease progression post SCT at the time of consideration for the study
             enrollment

          -  Myocardial infarction =&lt; 6 months prior to registration

          -  New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class III or IV heart failure

          -  Uncontrolled angina

          -  Severe uncontrolled ventricular arrhythmias

          -  Electrocardiographic (ECG) evidence of acute ischemia or active conduction system
             abnormalities (NOTE: Prior to study entry, any ECG abnormality at screening has to be
             documented by the investigator as not medically relevant)

          -  Seroreactivity for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), human T-cell lymphotrophic
             virus (HTLV) I or II, hepatitis B virus (HBV), or hepatitis C virus (HCV)

          -  Other active malignancy requiring therapy; EXCEPTIONS: Non-melanotic skin cancer or
             carcinoma-in-situ of the cervix (NOTE: If there is a history or prior malignancy,
             they must not be receiving other specific treatment for their cancer)

          -  Pregnant women or women of reproductive capability who are unwilling to use effective
             contraception

          -  Nursing women

          -  Men who are unwilling to use a condom (even if they have undergone a prior vasectomy)
             while having intercourse with any woman, while taking the drug and for 28 days after
             stopping treatment

          -  Other co-morbidity, which would interfere with patient's ability to participate in
             the trial, e.g. uncontrolled infection, uncompensated lung disease

          -  Concurrent chemotherapy, radiotherapy, or any ancillary therapy considered
             investigational (NOTE: Bisphosphonates are considered to be supportive care rather
             than therapy, and are thus allowed while on protocol treatment)

          -  Known allergies to any of the components of the investigational treatment regimen or
             required ancillary treatments
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shaji Kumar, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mayo Clinic Clinical Trial Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>507-538-7623</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Shaji K. Kumar, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 5, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 14, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Shaji K. Kumar, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone 21-phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
