<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="164865">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01980797</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013P000260</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01980797</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>International Bicuspid Aortic Valve Consortium (BAVCon)</brief_title>
  <acronym>BAVCon</acronym>
  <official_title>International Bicuspid Aortic Valve Consortium (BAVCon)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brigham and Women's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brigham and Women's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Bicuspid aortic valve (BAV) disease is the most frequent congenital cardiac malformation,
      occurring in 0.5-1.2% of the US population.  In young adults, it is generally a benign
      abnormality; but in older adults it is associated with thoracic aortic aneurysm or
      dissection in 20-30% of those with BAV.  BAV is strongly associated with early development
      of aortic valve calcification or incompetence in &gt;50% of BAV patients, and accounts for ~40%
      of the &gt;30,000 aortic valve replacements (AVR) performed in the US each year.  Yet, we know
      little of the etiology, cellular events and modifiers of progression of BAV to calcific
      aortic valve disease and we still do not understand the genetic cause(s) of BAV despite
      evidence for its high heritability.

      The Specific Aims of this study are:

        1. To identify the genetic causes of bicuspid aortic valve disease and its associated
           thoracic aortic disease.

        2. To identify potential pathways to predict the clinical course of BAV disease and for
           treating human BAV disease.

      To achieve these aims, we have created the International Bicuspid Aortic Valve Consortium
      (BAVCon), a consortium of institutions with cohorts of BAV patients and the expertise to
      fulfill the performance of these aims.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The International Bicuspid Aortic Valve Consortium (BAVCon) Registry is the data collection
      arm of the International Bicuspid Aortic Valve Consortium, a 16 institution international
      consortium of investigators with interests in the genetics, molecular biology, imaging,
      surgery and natural history of bicuspid aortic valve disease.

      The BAVCon Registry is a longitudinal cohort study, which is observational by design. The
      cohort will consist of patients with BAV.  Consideration will be given to eventual inclusion
      of a disease-free control or comparison group.  The study will compare genetic risk factors,
      cross-sectional and longitudinal data on risk factors related to the diagnosis, treatment
      and outcomes among groups of enrolled patients.  As part of the natural course of clinical
      care, the patients and their physicians will determine the approach to treatment and the
      study will record the observed related outcomes.  The study will not attempt to interfere
      with the outcomes through any type of planned intervention; therefore, there are no
      anticipated adverse events as a result of study participation.

      Study Design

      The Registry is designed to capture information on patients with bicuspid aortic valve
      disease.  The BAVCon Registry population will be comprised of patients from sixteen BAVCon
      Clinical Centers.  The participating BAVCon Clinical Centers are:

        -  Harvard University / Partners Healthcare, Boston (Dr. Simon Body, Consortium PI)

        -  GenTAC Consortium (Dr. Kim Eagle, PI)

        -  Hospital Vall d'Hebron, Barcelona, Spain (Dr. Arturo Evangelista, PI)

        -  Monaldi Hospital, Naples, Italy (Dr. Giuseppe Limongelli, PI)

        -  Mayo Clinic, Rochester (Dr. Hector Michelena, PI)

        -  Oxford University, Oxford, England (Dr. Malenka Bissell, PI)

        -  Saarland University Medical Center, Saarland, Germany  (Dr. Hans-Joachim Schäfers, PI)

        -  San Donato Hospital IRCCS, Milan, Italy  (PI: Dr. Alessandro Frigiola)

        -  Tufts University, Boston (Dr. Gordon Huggins, PI)

        -  Université de Liège, Liege, Belgium (Dr. Patrizio Lancelotti, PI)

        -  Université Laval, Quebec (Dr. Yohan Bossé, PI)

        -  University of Michigan, Ann Arbor (Dr. Anna Booher, PI)

        -  University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia (Dr. Joseph Bavaria, PI)

        -  University of Salerno, Salerno, Italy (Dr. Eduardo Bossone, PI)

        -  University of Texas Medical School, Houston (Dr. Dianna Milewicz, PI) One center with
           specific expertise, but not enrolling patients, is University of Ottawa (Dr. Mona
           Nemer, PI).

      The data supplied by each participating center are collected from the following sources:

      Patient interview or questionnaire Hospital medical records Surgical records Imaging studies

      Enrollment Information about the Registry will be disseminated to potential study subjects
      using a number of sources.  The principal means of enrollment will be from the Cardiology
      and Surgical Clinics of each Hospital.  In addition, collaborations with the patient
      advocacy groups such as the Bicuspid Aortic Valve Foundation.  These organizations have well
      established resources for providing information to patients such as websites, newsletters,
      and national conferences.  A recruitment brochure has been developed to explain the goals
      and basic procedures of the Registry. Finally, the study website, http://www.bavcon.org,
      will inform potential subjects about the Registry.  All recruitment materials will be
      approved by the DCC and BCC IRBs, as appropriate, prior to dissemination.

      BCC study staff will identify eligible patients using the eligibility criteria developed and
      approved by the Steering Committee. They will both screen their current patient population
      as well as identify new patients that attend the clinic. Eligible patients will be solicited
      during clinic visits according to protocols approved by the local IRB.

      Initially, a care provider will introduce the Registry to the patient or the parent or
      guardian of the patient, and ask if they are interested in talking further with the research
      coordinator. If the patient (or parent or guardian) agrees, the research coordinator will
      meet with the patient for a more comprehensive explanation of the Registry. If there is
      continued agreement, the research coordinator will proceed with the consent and enrollment
      process. Signed informed consent will be obtained prior to any data or sample collection.
      Patients will receive a hard-copy of the consent form to keep. Patients will be able to ask
      questions at any time. One parent or guardian may provide signed consent for a minor child
      or other person with a physical or mental condition that prevents them from doing so
      themselves. Literacy in the native language of the country (English and Spanish in the USA)
      will be required of the consenting patient or parent/guardian.  Child assent will be
      obtained from children at least 8 years of age, or as determined by the local IRB.  Across
      all the sites, we anticipate total enrollment of up to 10,000 patients.

      Eligibility Criteria

      Inclusion criteria for entry into the Registry are:

        -  Patients diagnosed with bicuspid aortic valve

        -  All ages ≥8 years

        -  Able to provide fully informed consent

      Local Site Restrictions Some sites will not be collecting tissue from patients, therefore
      information on tissue collection will be absent.  Some sites do not routinely perform CT or
      MRI on their patients, so these data will also be absent.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2033</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <target_duration>10 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Bicuspid aortic valve disease</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The first specific aim is to identify the genetic causes of bicuspid aortic valve disease.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The development of thoracic aortic disease in patients with bicuspid aortic valve disease</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The second specific aim is to identify genetic and non-genetic factors to cause thoracic aortic disease in BAV patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10000</enrollment>
  <condition>Bicuspid Aortic Valve Disease</condition>
  <condition>Thoracic Aortic Disease in Patients With a Bicuspid Aortic Valve</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bicuspid aortic valve disease</arm_group_label>
    <description>Group/Cohort Label - Bicuspid aortic valve
Group/Cohort Description -
Patients diagnosed with bicuspid aortic valve
All ages ≥8 years
Able to provide fully informed consent</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tricuspid aortic valve control patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Group/Cohort Label - Tricuspid aortic valve control patients
Group/Cohort Description -Control patients will come from approximately matched patients without an identified bicuspid aortic valve who are trace, gender and geographically matched.
Patients not diagnosed with bicuspid aortic valve
All ages ≥8 years
Able to provide fully informed consent</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      We are collecting DNA from either saliva or blood.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with and without bicuspid aortic valves disease
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients diagnosed as having a bicuspid aortic valve

          -  All ages ≥8 years

          -  Able to provide fully informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Simon C Body, MD MPH</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Simon C Body, MD MPH</last_name>
    <phone>617-732-8127</phone>
    <email>sbody@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham and Women's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Simon C Body, MD MPH</last_name>
      <phone>617-732-8127</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Michael Franke, MD MPH</last_name>
      <phone>617-732-8127</phone>
      <email>mfrancke@partners.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.bav-genetics.org</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 8, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 5, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Simon Body</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bicuspid aortic valve disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Thoracic aortic disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Genetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Echocardiography</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiac CT</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiac MRI</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Aortic Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aortic Valve Stenosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
