<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="73720">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01713543</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HSRG10MAY002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01713543</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Community-based Falls Prevention Program for the Elderly</brief_title>
  <official_title>Multifactorial, Evidence-based Program of Screening, Risk Modification and Physical Therapy to Prevent Falls Among Vulnerable Elderly Recently Discharged From Hospital to the Community.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National University, Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ministry of Health, Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Duke-NUS Graduate Medical School</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Singapore General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Changi General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Health Promotion Board, Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Agency for Integrated Care, Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National University, Singapore</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Singapore: Domain Specific Review Boards</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Falls are the leading cause of injury among older adults in Singapore. However,
      far from being inevitable, falls among elderly are preventable and risk is predictable.
      Translating this understanding of falls etiology into an integrated clinical and public
      health program that is accessible to all elderly persons is a critical health services
      delivery challenge.

      Hypothesis: An evidence-based program of screening, risk modification and physical therapy
      delivered in a community setting will reduce falls incidence among a high-risk group of
      elderly who have been recently transitioned from the hospital to the community.

      Methodology: Randomized controlled trial. Patients transitioning from the hospital to the
      community will be identified at the Emergency Department. Eligible patients are those who
      are: 1) more than 65 years old, 2) discharged from the Emergency Department or hospital for
      a fall or injury related to a fall. The intervention is a multifactorial program of
      screening, risk modification and physical therapy focused on progressive strength, balance
      and gait training. It is provided as an individualized program or in a group setting in the
      community. The primary outcome measure is number of fallers assessed from a falls prevention
      diary maintained by (or for) each participant.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective:

      To develop and demonstrate the feasibility and effectiveness of a multifactorial,
      community-based falls prevention program of screening, risk modification, and progressive
      physical therapy that targets vulnerable elderly Singaporeans at high-risk of falls.

      Methodology:

      This study is a two-year randomized control trial that tests the effectiveness of a
      multifactorial, community based falls prevention program targeting vulnerable Singaporeans
      at high risk of falls. To maximize the likelihood of long-term sustainability, we will
      engage hospital Physiotherapists (PT)to deliver the home based assessment and intervention
      and the group exercise program in the community.

      The study will have two arms (intervention and control), and will be divided into three
      phases: (1) pre-intervention (2) intervention and (3) analysis. In the pre-intervention
      phase, overseas experts will train local PTs and CHWs on how to administer and deliver the
      falls prevention program.  The program will be delivered to the intervention arm during
      phase 2 of the study. The intervention is a multifactorial program of screening, risk
      modification and physical therapy focused on progressive strength, balance and gait
      training. It is provided as an individualized program or in a group setting in the
      community. The primary outcome measure is the number of fallers assessed from a falls
      prevention diary maintained by (or for) each participant. Data will be analyzed in the third
      and final phase.

      Procedures:

      All study participants will be given an assessment at baseline which will consist of the
      measurement of: sociodemographic characteristics, functional status, history of falls,
      cognitive impairment, depression, quality of life, healthcare utilization and expenditures,
      and medical history. The Short Physical Performance Battery (SPPB) will be used to assess
      gait, balance and mobility. Cognitive assessment will be performed using the Montreal
      Cognitive Assessment (MoCA). Presence of depression will be evaluated using the Geriatrics
      Depression Scale. Subjects in the intervention group will receive a detailed multifactorial
      falls risk evaluation and tailored physical therapy or group exercise program focused on
      improving gait, balance and mobility.  Before the start of the physical therapy,
      participants in the intervention group will need to complete the PAR-Q and a medical
      evaluation by Physician to recommend that they are fit for physical activity using HPB
      Medical Advisory Form. For interview assessments, we will use validated Chinese and Malay
      versions when necessary, as many of the elderly patients are either Mandarin or
      Malay-speaking.

      The questionnaire at baseline will be conducted by the PTs and the outcome measurements will
      be collected at 3 months and 9 months by independent blinded assessors.

      The intervention will be divided into two phases: a 3-month &quot;Active Intervention Phase&quot; and
      a 6-month &quot;Maintenance Phase.&quot; At the onset of the active intervention phase, those patients
      in the intervention sites will receive a detailed falls risk assessment at baseline from a
      physical therapist. The risk factors that will be assessed and the corresponding
      interventions are as follows:

        1. Poor vision: Referral to ophthalmologist for correction

        2. Polypharmacy: Referral to AIC for management of medications if use of four medications
           or use of high risk medications such as benzodiazepines, neuroleptics,
           anti-depressants, anticonvulsants or class 1A antiarrhythmics.

        3. Environmental hazards: Caregiver education and suitable recommendations to modify risk
           such as removal of rugs, chang to safer footwear, use of non-slip bath mats, additional
           lighting at night; broadly following the CDC guidelines.

        4. Deficiencies in gait, balance or mobility: Physical therapist supervised program of
           gait training, balance and strengthening exercises.

      Briefly, the assessments include a review of current drugs for polypharmacy, orthostatic
      vital signs, vision acuity testing, and a brief environmental assessment. Impairments in
      gait, balance and mobility will be assessed using the SPPB and a 2 minute walk. Manuals will
      be developed for physical therapists to guide the evaluation risk factor assessments, home
      assessments, appropriate referrals, and selection of exercise programs, that will be
      progressive, challenging and of optimal intensity and durations. Existing protocols and
      procedures for the OTAGO-type programs will be available. These activities are specially
      developed for the purpose of this study.

      Based on the SPPB score at baseline assessment, participants will be categorized as either
      high-risk (SPPB≤6) or low-to-moderate-risk (SPPB&gt;6) for falls. High-risk patients will be
      given a PT supervised program of physical therapy that specifically targets impairments that
      interfere with engaging in exercise in group setting. The goal of the tailored physical
      therapy sessions is to modify impairments and transition these patients to an evidence-based
      exercise program. Low-to-moderate risk patients will be directly enrolled into an
      evidence-based group exercise program. The group exercise programs will be offered in 1-hour
      sessions, twice weekly over the intervention phase.

      At the end of the active intervention phase (3 months after baseline), participants will
      transition to a maintenance phase in which they will be encouraged to continue with the
      exercise on their own and will also be referred to the HPB's STEP program. Patient
      participation in the program and their falls incidence will be monitored for 9 months after
      the baseline assessment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of fallers who have fallen at least once during the 9-month intervention phase</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of injurious falls and healthcare utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">350</enrollment>
  <condition>Falls Prevention</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>active exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>Tailored physical therapy sessions to modify impairments and transition participants to an evidence-based group exercise program.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Falls Prevention</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 65 years

          -  Seen in the Emergency Department for a fall or injury related to a fall

          -  Able to follow 3 step commands

          -  Singapore citizen or Permanent Resident

          -  Living at home upon discharge

          -  Provision of informed consent

          -  If admitted to the hospital, the illness or disability is one from which they are
             expected to recover basic ADLs or weight bearing of the lower extremity within the
             next one month

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Those patients with severe physical and/or mental impairments which preclude
             participation in a program of physical therapy (as determined by a primary physician)
             will NOT be eligible for participation.

          -  Unable to participate in the exercise program due to conflicting schedules (e.g.
             full-time employment, on dialysis)

          -  Serious life limiting illness

          -  Road traffic accident

          -  Unable to walk even with assistance

          -  Not community dwelling prior to ED visit

          -  Total blindness

          -  Needs emergency inpatient surgery and (8) if admitted to the hospital, the illness or
             disability is one from which they are not expected to recover basic ADLs or weight
             bearing in the lower extremity within the next one month.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David B Matchar, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke-NUS Graduate Medical School</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rita Sim</last_name>
    <phone>(65) 6601 2453</phone>
    <email>rita.sim@duke-nus.com.sg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Singapore General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>169608</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marcus Ong, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(65) 6321 4873</phone>
      <email>marcus.ong.e.h@sgh.com.sg</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marcus Ong, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Changi General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>529889</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christopher Lien, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(65) 6850 3604</phone>
      <email>chris_lien@cgh.com.sg</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christopher Lien, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 17, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 22, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National University, Singapore</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. David Matchar</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>falls</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
