<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="62031">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01843036</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00017478_Amd6</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01843036</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Durham Connects Evaluation II</brief_title>
  <official_title>Second RCT Evaluation of the Durham Connects Nurse Home Visiting Program</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Duke Endowment</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this randomized controlled trial (RCT) is to conduct a second, independent
      evaluation the implementation and impact of the Durham Connects (DC) brief universal nurse
      home-visiting program to prevent child maltreatment and improve child and family health and
      well-being. Durham Connects is the first home-visiting program that is designed to prevent
      child maltreatment and improve health and well-being outcomes in an entire community
      population.

      Program evaluation will test four hypotheses: 1) The program can be implemented with
      population reach, fidelity to the manualized intervention protocol, and reliability in
      assessment of family risk; 2) Random assignment to the Durham Connects program will be
      associated with lower rates of child maltreatment and emergency department
      maltreatment-related injuries, better pediatric care, better parental functioning, and
      better child well-being than assignment as control; 2) Intervention effect sizes will be
      larger for higher-risk groups; and 3) Community resource use and enhanced family functioning
      will mediate the positive impact of Durham Connects on outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Durham Connects program is an innovative, community-based, universal nurse home-visiting
      program that aims to lower the population rate of child maltreatment and improve child and
      family health and well-being. The Durham Connects Program is implemented jointly by the
      Durham County (North Carolina) Health Department, the Center for Child &amp; Family Health, and
      Duke University. It is designed to be brief and inexpensive per family so that communities
      can afford its costs. Its goals are consistent with those of more intensive nurse
      home-visiting programs: 1) to connect with the mother in order to enhance maternal skills
      and self-efficacy; and 2) to connect the mother with needed community services such as
      health care, child care, mental health care, and financial and social support; so that 3)
      the mother can connect with her child.

      From August 1, 2013, through June 30, 2014, all residential births in Durham County, North
      Carolina (~2,950) will be randomly assigned according to birthdate, with odd-birth-dates
      assigned to receive DC. Even-birth-dates will be assigned to receive services-as-usual and
      serve as the randomized control group. Program implementation will be evaluated for all
      odd-birth-date families.

      Durham Connects begins with a visit during the birthing hospital stay, followed by 1-3 nurse
      home visits between 4-12 weeks of infant age, and then a follow-up contact one month later.
      During the visits, the nurse engages with the mother and completes a health and psychosocial
      assessment, during which she systematically assesses risk and family needs in 12
      empirically-derived areas of family functioning across 4 domains (i.e., healthcare,
      parenting/childcare, family violence/safety, and maternal well-being). For each area found
      to be at risk, the nurse intervenes directly to support the mother (mild risk) or connects
      the mother with ongoing evidence-based interventions in the community (moderate or
      significant risk). Although Durham Connects is implemented universally, it focuses on
      triaging families according to assessed risk and then connecting them with ongoing
      collaborating community resources that can &quot;carry the family's baton&quot; after the nurse
      home-visitor leaves the family.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>DSS Investigated and Substantiated Child Maltreatment Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>0 - 66 months of child age</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>North Carolina Department of Social Services (DSS) reported lifetime caseness of investigated and substantiated maltreatment caseness</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child Emergency Room (ER) Presentation Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>0 - 66 Months of Child Age</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Lifetime child emergency department visit reported in hospital records.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child Overnights in Hospital</measure>
    <time_frame>0-66 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Lifetime child overnights in hospital for all overnights unrelated to the birthing stay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pediatric Well-Care Visit and Child Immunization Compliance Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>0-66 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Lifetime rates of compliance with well-care pediatric visits and immunizations as reported by primary caregiver</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mother Postnatal Well-Care Compliance Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>0-12 Months Postnatal</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Rates of mother compliance with postnatal well-care as reported by the mother</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mother Emergency Room (ER) Presentation Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>0-66 Months of Child Age</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Total mother emergency department visits reported in hospital records</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1650</enrollment>
  <condition>Unspecified Child Maltreatment, Suspected</condition>
  <condition>Unspecified Child Maltreatment, Confirmed</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Durham Connects Eligible</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>From August 1, 2013 - June 30, 2014, all odd-birth-date residential births in Durham County, North Carolina will be randomly assigned to receive the Durham Connects nurse home visiting program.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>From August 1, 2013 - June 30, 2014, all even-birth-date residential births in Durham County, North Carolina will be randomly assigned to a control group condition. These families will be assigned to receive services as usual and serve as the randomized comparison group for evaluating Durham Connects program impact.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Durham Connects</intervention_name>
    <description>Durham Connects begins with a visit during the birthing hospital stay, followed by 1-3 nurse home visits between 4-12 weeks of infant age, and then a follow-up contact one month later. During the visits, the nurse engages with the mother and completes a health and psychosocial assessment, during which she systematically assesses risk and family needs in 12 important empirically-derived areas of family functioning across 4 domains (i.e. - healthcare, parenting/childcare, family violence/safety, and maternal well-being). For each domain found to be at risk, the nurse intervenes directly to support the mother (mild risk) or connects the mother with matched community resources as needed to address individualized long-term family needs (moderate or severe risk).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Durham Connects Eligible</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Infant born between August 1, 2013 and June 30, 2014

          -  Infant born at a Durham County, NC hospital (Duke or Durham Regional)

          -  Family of infant resides in Durham County, NC

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Infant born between August 1, 2013 and June 30, 2014

          -  Infant not born at a Durham County, NC hospital (Duke or Durham Regional)

          -  Family of infant resides outside of Durham County, NC
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>6 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kenneth A Dodge, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Murphy, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Center for Child &amp; Family Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen O'Donnell, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Center for Child &amp; Family Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>W. Benjamin Goodman, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ben Goodman, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+1 (919) 668-4126</phone>
    <email>ben.goodman@duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center for Child and Family Policy, Duke University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27708</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ben Goodman, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>919-668-4126</phone>
      <email>ben.goodman@duke.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://durhamconnects.org/</url>
    <description>Durham Connects Project Website</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.childandfamilypolicy.duke.edu/</url>
    <description>Center for Child and Family Policy, Duke University</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ccfhnc.org/</url>
    <description>Center for Child &amp; Family Health</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 6, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 26, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Child Abuse</keyword>
  <keyword>Child Neglect</keyword>
  <keyword>Child Hospital Emergency Room Presentations</keyword>
  <keyword>Child Well-Care Compliance</keyword>
  <keyword>Child Immunization Compliance</keyword>
  <keyword>Mother Well-Care Compliance</keyword>
  <keyword>Mother Hospital Emergency Room Presentations</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
