<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="99247">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02017158</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HS-11-00158</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R25RR032159</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02017158</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Virtual Sprouts: Web-based Gardening Games to Teach Nutrition and Combat Obesity</brief_title>
  <official_title>Virtual Sprouts: Web-based Gardening Games to Teach Nutrition and Combat Obesity</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Southern California</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Center for Research Resources (NCRR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Southern California</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to develop, disseminate, and evaluate a web-based nutrition and
      gardening game using interactive, multiplatform and mobile gaming, rich narrative, a
      pedagogical agent, meaningful play, and experiential learning to prevent/treat obesity in
      minority 3-5th grade youth and their families.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A. Research Education Program Plan

      A.1: Novel approaches to educate the community on NIH-funded research and health-related
      issues, and prevent obesity in minority youth through meaningful play - Changing the field:
      We propose to develop, disseminate and evaluate Virtual Sprouts: Web-Based Gardening Games
      in a game- based environment that has the potential for broad dissemination. In the virtual
      garden, children learn to select what to plant, plant their garden, watch it grow, tend,
      water and weed, and harvest the crops. It has been argued convincingly that games and game
      technologies enhance children's learning and achievement (Gee, J., 2003) through fun (Kim,
      B., Park, H., &amp; Baek, Y., 2009), meaningful play (Gee, J., 2003), enhanced involvement in
      the subject matter (Kim, B., Park, H., &amp; Baek, Y., 2009), increased motivation and more
      independent engagement (Tüzün H, YIlmaz-Soylu M, Karakus T, Inal Y, KIzIlkaya G., 2009).
      Therefore, a virtual gardening environment has great promise as a learning tool.
      Furthermore, the realm of gardening provides rich and deep curriculum opportunities, while
      at the same time increasing access to fresh, low-cost produce, improving nutrition, building
      bridges between neighbors and creating stronger communities (Twiss, J., Dickinson, J., Duma,
      S., Kleinman, T., Paulsen, H., &amp; Rilveria, L., 2003). Because gardening covers a broad
      spectrum of knowledge, from basic sciences through nutrition to human behavior, gardening
      education offers an excellent opportunity to address Science, Technology, Engineering, and
      Mathematics (STEM) education. Although access to fresh produce remains extremely poor across
      great swaths of Los Angeles (Kipke, M.D., Iverson, E., Moore, D., et al., 2007), the city is
      not a stranger to gardening efforts. For example, Los Angeles has been home to the Common
      Ground gardening program since 1978. This program is dedicated to excellence in Master
      Gardening, developing school gardens, and teaching families how to garden, grow their own
      food and prepare it in a healthful manner. Virtual Sprouts Web-Based Gardening Games is
      poised to have broad reach and high impact because a) internet technology is widely
      accessible and extremely popular among youth and b) games and virtual environments enhance
      learning and improve achievement.

      B. Innovation

      B.1: A Virtual guide in a virtual garden: Innovative approaches to learning, teaching and
      changing behavior: When designed in accordance with proven instructional principles, the use
      of games and game technologies have been shown to enhance children's learning and
      achievement (Gee, J., 2003). Emerging literatures suggest that narratively rich, (Tanenbaum,
      K., &amp; Tanenbaum, J., 2009) socially interactive and developmentally appropriate (Barab, S.,
      Thomas, M., Dodge, T., Carteaux, R., &amp; Tuzun, H., 2005) games that incorporate interactive
      storytelling and believable agents (Riedl, M., &amp; Stern, A., 2006) have the potential to
      strengthen learning and motivation. Research on effective communication shows that the
      perceived characteristics of an agent or guide (i.e., gender, social status, believability,
      integrity) will influence behavioral choices in real and virtual worlds (Frankenhuis, W.E.,
      Dostsch, R., Karremans, J.C., &amp; Wigboldus, D.I.H.J., 2010), and that children  are quite
      sensitive to the believability and status of the agent (Robinson, E.J., &amp; Mitchell, P.,
      1992). Diffusion of innovation delineates the importance of the characteristics of opinion
      leaders to the speed of adaptation of new ideas (Rogers, E., 1995). Therefore using
      state-of-the-art, award winning technologies available at USC'a Interactive Media Division
      (IMD) of the School of Cinematic Arts (SCA) and the Institute for Creative Technologies
      (ICT), we will develop a highly credible, personable and attractive  pedagogical agent to
      play the role of Virtual Guide through the Virtual Sprouts learning experience. The guide
      will simultaneously assume the roles of coach, mentor, collaborator, and friend. This will
      include orienting the player to the game, providing explanations of game events, making
      suggestions about ideal actions to take, participating in the game activities, and conveying
      elements of the underlying narrative.

      C. Approach

      C.1: Research Education Plan

      C.1.a: Overview of the Plan: This project will proceed in three iterative phases:
      Development, Dissemination and Evaluation. Development of a) curriculum, b) virtual garden
      and c) pedagogical agent will proceed in parallel, and be integrated during testing and
      evaluation. A participatory research group comprised of key community members, teachers,
      clinicians, education experts, 8-11 year old youth and their parents will be formed to
      provide iterative rounds of input and evaluation throughout the development of Virtual
      Sprouts. This participatory research group will provide input through focus groups, beta
      testing, idea-building and advisement throughout the development of Virtual Sprouts. We have
      successfully used this model in previous health and intervention studies. The participatory
      research group is composed of about 20 diverse members so as not to tax individual members
      with study needs and to ensure diverse input. Sub-groups of the larger participatory
      research group are formed for specific tasks, depending on research needs and group
      interest. The Virtual Sprouts Game will be developed around a virtual pedagogical agent, who
      will guide the player through the game using cognitive and affective learning principles.
      The Virtual Environment will be a game system developed using deep narrative and dramatic
      elements. Both the pedagogical agent and game environment will be extensively and
      iteratively tested with members of our participatory  research  group  during  development.
      The  Virtual  Sprouts game will then be introduced into three of the USC Family of Schools
      Elementary schools, three of the CTSI clinics and the California Science Center  (see
      letters  of  support).  Dissemination  at  the  schools  will  use school internet
      capabilities. Dissemination at the CTSI clinics and the Science Center will use Virtual
      Sprouts interactive kiosks that will be placed by the study. Children will be able to access
      their Virtual Sprouts accounts from any computer. Prior to dissemination and kiosk
      placement, teachers, clinicians and   Science Center staff will receive a series of
      workshops and seminars on childhood obesity in general, and the Virtual Sprouts game in
      particular. Teachers,  Science Center staff and clinicians will also receive the Virtual
      Sprouts Game Manual, which will be developed by the Virtual Sprouts team as an on-paper and
      virtual web- based interactive module-by-module teacher's aide.

      C.1.b: Curriculum Development: During the first year of this grant, we will work on
      developing and focus group testing the nutrition and gardening curriculum. Curriculum will
      be tested iterative through focus groups and beta testing with members of the participatory
      research group. The gardening and nutrition program will  not  only  teach  children  about
      the  health  benefits  of  fruits  and vegetables but children will learn additional skills
      in math, science, and history. The program will include lessons relating to culture,
      including growing crops that have cultural significance such as nopales, beans, corn and
      squash (the latter three crops are historically referred to as &quot;the three sisters&quot;).
      Gardening provides an ideal vehicle for teaching Science, Technology, Engineering, and
      Mathematics (STEM) topics such as how plants grow and how gardens can be managed in an
      environmentally sound manner (science including biology, earth sciences, agriculture, and
      the study of weather and climate), how to make good nutrition choices with the produce they
      harvest (nutrition sciences, health behavior). Furthermore, thinking about planting,
      harvesting, and climate involves a great deal of math and engineering. The web-based
      interactive nature of the Virtual Sprouts game will introduce children to new uses for
      advanced technologies.

      C.1.c: Game, Pedagogical Agent and Virtual Environment Integration: The game will contain
      the Pedagogical Agent and Virtual Environment and will provide the interaction framework
      through play mechanics. Rather than a serial task-driven game, we envision a persistent
      virtual environment in which the player will explore Virtual Sprouts and be challenged and
      nurtured by the agent in joint social play activities. Play experience will be episodic,
      requiring a few minutes of play per day over several weeks. Certain interactions in the
      virtual environment will be joint activities (such as watering or harvesting vegetables),
      and challenges issued by the agent will involve the agent personally. For example, the agent
      may challenge the learner to plant, grow, and harvest ingredients for a certain recipe, then
      prepare it. Based on the quality of the learners work, the agent may like or dislike the
      resulting meal. Use of this kind of intrinsic feedback blurs the line between learning and
      gameplay, and makes the agent an integral and thus indispensable part of the experience.
      During the first year, we will determine the breadth (variety) and depth (challenge) of the
      game experience in relation to gardening and cooking tasks appropriate for the target
      population through paper prototyping and iterative play testing (Fullerton T, Swain C,
      Hoffman S., 2008). Iterative Play testing Methods. Iterative play testing process, involves
      the following steps:

        1. Self-testing of paper prototypes with project team in order to come up with core
           mechanics. This will occur during regularly scheduled face-to-face meetings and
           prototyped concepts will concentrate on subject- specific behavioral role-play and
           technical feasibility;

        2. Testing of digital prototypes with colleagues, friends or family in order to gain
           third-party perspective. This will occur in phases based on the software development
           progress and will involve direct observation through informal usability studies.

        3. Testing of partially complete digital game prototype with random strangers (N=15) who
           partially fit the target population criteria (recruited through advertising) in order
           to gain objectivity. Testers will play for a few hours, report bugs and answer custom
           pre/post-questionnaires on play mechanics and usability.

        4. Testing completed digital game prototype with sample (N=20) of target audience (obese
           youth and their families). Testers will be required to use the game for several days at
           a time, report bugs and answer custom questionnaires about game mechanics, reward
           mechanisms and other game-specific measures.

      C.1.d: Pedagogical Agent Components: The pedagogical agent will consist of several key
      components that, when combined, provide a knowledgeable, friendly, and entertaining
      companion for learning in the Virtual Sprouts environment through cognitive-affective
      approaches. These components include:

        1. Expert knowledge: The character will possess of cognitive model of effective gardening
           and cooking that will allow it to support the activities of the Virtual Sprouts game.
           This will enable the agent to explain how to create and maintain a healthy garden,
           harvest and cook items from the garden, and provide explanations of the health benefits
           of eating organically prepared foods. The expert model will also form the basis for
           assessment of learner activities to give them credit when they take a correct action
           (e.g., water at the correct time and amount) and to know when they've made a mistake
           (e.g., planted two seeds  too close to one another). These assessments will feed into
           the pedagogical decision system.

        2. Pedagogical knowledge: The provision of guidance requires a delicate balance of
           providing timely (and wanted) support while allowing the learner to feel a sense of
           freedom and remain stay in control to feel a sense of ownership of the garden. Care
           must therefore be taken in decisions of how and when to provide guidance. Too little
           guidance can lead to frustration for many users (i.e., the agent should be helpful),
           while  too  much  may  threaten  users'  feelings  of  autonomy  and  freedom  in  the
           game environment (i.e., the agent should not be perceived as controlling). Thus,
           through a combination of unsolicited guidance triggered by evidence of confusion and/or
           lack of domain knowledge and solicited guidance, when the learner requests help, the
           agent will seek to be a productive helper while ensuring that the learner is acquiring
           the needed knowledge and skills to succeed at Virtual Sprouts, and in their regular
           lives as the relate to eating and exercise.

        3. Emotion/affect knowledge: In addition to supporting game play and providing
           explanations for game events, the agent will also support the learner's affective
           state. Cultivating and nurturing interest, motivation, and positive feelings about the
           domain are critical in the pursuit of behavior change, and expressions of empathy from
           the agent can play into the learner's willingness to remain engaged (McQuiggan, S.W.,
           Rowe, J.P., &amp; Lester, J.C., 2008). These intervention techniques will be implemented in
           concert with the game- and cognitive-focused tactics described above. For example, a
           user who is just beginning and has completed his or her first vegetable will receive
           high praise, which will diminish with time for that specific accomplishment. Similarly,
           for learners who express a negative perception of gardening and vegetables, the agent
           will work harder to motivate and entertain.

        4. Animation and sound: As discussed above, the appearance of the agent will have an
           impact on the learner's affective state, both during and after the interaction. A
           well-known and respected character, such as one modeled after the First Lady (if
           possible), will increase the chances of establishing familiarity and credibility from
           the outset. Use of appealing animations and joint activity, such as watering the garden
           simultaneously, will bolster feelings of co-presence and teamwork. The character's
           voice, which will be delivered along with subtitles for English as a second language
           learners, will be chosen based on the preferences of users from the target audience in
           early testing of the system.

      C.1.e: Game, Pedagogical Agent and Virtual Environment Development: The phases of
      development are outlined below:

        1. Domain knowledge and learning objective analysis: During year 1, we will gather and
           formalize the domain knowledge in a way that can be represented in the game for use by
           the agent. This will feed into the expert modeling and provide the overarching
           structure for tracking the learner's understanding of the domain. We will also play
           test new game types and existing games for cooking and gardening through  one-on-one
           observational  studies  and  interviews  to  determine  fun  and  engaging  play
           mechanics and design principles using GAP Methodology (Desurvire, H., &amp; Wiberg, C.,
           2008).

        2. Expert modeling and feedback: Using the identified learning objectives and game
           mechanics defined during year 1, in year 2 we will build computational models of the
           skills needed to succeed at the Virtual Sprouts game. These models will mirror skills
           needed to tend to an actual garden and cook actual food. As discussed, these models
           will play a key role in building the assessment and pedagogical models to drive the
           agent's interactions with the learner. Feedback content will be authored to correspond
           to knowledge components represented in the expert model.

        3. Pedagogical  agent  design  &amp;  prototyping:  In  spiral  development  with  the  expert
            model,  the pedagogical and affect decision modules will be developed. Functionality
           for solicited and unsolicited feedback will be implemented. By the end of year 2, the
           agent will be providing support for learning and affect.

        4. Agent and game integration: In this stage, the agent will be fully integrated with the
           Virtual Sprouts practice environment (during year 3). This will include completing
           animations that involve the agent working in the virtual world, as well as resolving
           any underlying discrepancies between the game design and the models driving the agent's
           behaviors. Play testing of game while agent is development will occur through role-play
           using real people, a technique commonly used at USC's Game Innovation Usability Lab.
           For example, early design phases of the Wellness Partners study, play testing of the
           game system (which was meant to be operated by a virtual character that did not yet
           exist) was done through email and text messaging via a human in real-time. This was
           highly engaging and captured positive and negative affective states between agent and
           player.

        5. Agent visual and content revisions: The agent and underlying representations will be
           modified and extended based on user and subject-matter expert feedback. By the end of
           year 3, the agent will be ready for full pilot testing and summative evaluation

      C.1.f: Dissemination to USC Family of Schools, CTSI/CTSA community clinics and California
      Science Center: In years 4 and 5, Virtual Sprouts will be rolled out to 7 elementary schools
      that are members of the USC  Family  of  Schools,  3  CTSI/CTSA clinics  and  the
      California  Science  Center.  These  activities  are extensively detailed below in sections
      C.1.h: Partnerships and Collaborations, C.1.j.3. Program Faculty/ Staff (under Consultation
      and Dissemination Experts), C.2. Evaluation Plan, and C.3. Dissemination Plan. Briefly, we
      will conduct a Randomized Clinical Trial (RCT) for the school-based  implementation of the
      game. In our  dissemination venues (science center, museum and community clinics) no control
      conditions will be applied.  For  these  venues,  descriptive  and  regression  approaches
      will  be  used  in  the  venues  to  test intervention and dissemination evaluation. A major
      element of implementation and dissemination will be the Virtual Sprouts Website, which will
      be developed by Co-I Marientina Gotsis and maintained by Co-PI Spruijt- Metz's team. Each
      participant (including children, teachers, parents and other interested community members)
      will join the Virtual Sprouts community and study via the website. Consent and assent will
      be available virtually. Each player will have their own account, so that they can play from
      any computer with a web interface, or from a mobile phone with web access. All evaluative
      surveys and logs will be available and administered through the Virtual Sprouts website.
      Paper and pencil versions will be made available for the school environment as requested.
      All participants will receive a Personal Sprout Identifier (PSI). Their PSI will be
      confidential and they will use their PSI to log in to the Virtual Sprouts Website, continue
      game play, receive rewards, and complete evaluations.

      C.1.g: Teacher Professional Development: The vehicle for training teachers to use the
      Virtual Sprout game is a hybrid approach and includes a Summer Teacher Academy (STA) serving
      as a kick off program with face to case and USC Distance Education Network (DEN) mediated,
      school site follow-up professional development in elementary school classrooms using a
      lesson study approach. Teacher academies have been recognized in the teacher education
      literature as a powerful and impactful way of comprehensively training and supporting
      teachers (Crowther, D.T., Vilá J.S., Fathman A.K., 2006).

      The Summer Teacher Academy: A summer teacher academy (STA) will occur in August each
      implementation year immediately after year one of the program's development phase and in
      years 2-5. Through the STA, teachers will be trained annually. The academies will be three
      days long at USC's campus as each of the target schools are in relative close proximity with
      USC. Mornings in the academy will be spent learning the nutrition conceptual knowledge,
      exploring the application and practicing using a guided experiential learning approach to
      facilitating the game use. The content for the training will be aligned with grades 6-12
      California health content standards focused on nutrition and related health. Lesson study,
      beginning with observational demos and progressing to teacher created role-play will be of
      focus of the professional development. The teacher participants will spend a portion of the
      morning observing and practicing Virtual Sprouts game, discussing the application and use of
      the game in their classrooms. As academic year follow-up, teacher participants will practice
      using the Virtual Sprouts game application and engage in peer review of game facilitation
      with fellow teachers (lesson study) in tandem with the USC teacher education experts in
      their classrooms.

      Stigler's Lesson Study Model of Teacher Development Model: Throughout the Project's teacher
      training, participant teachers will use a research-based lesson study approach to build and
      study implementation of the nutrition and facilitation of Virtual Sprouts intervention with
      their students. Lesson study, according to Stigler (McQuiggan, S.W., Rowe, J.P., Lester,
      J.C., 2008), refers to a process whereby teachers closely examine their lesson facilitation
      with a focus on addressing student need via data-driven decision-making. In the lesson study
      model, teachers learn together. Participants plan, observe, and refine instruction and
      learning facilitation (Desurvire, H., &amp; Wiberg, C., 2008). Lesson study compels teachers to
      examine their own practice in depth in the context of student learning, connects teachers
      with their students and their professional community, and inspires them to continue to
      improve. This model of teacher professional development has been applied widely and
      successfully in Japan and has recently been initiated by teachers across the US as a
      scientifically-based best practice. For the purpose of the summer academy, participant
      teachers will &quot;study&quot; videotaped lesson exemplars using the facilitations cycle with the
      Virtual Sprouts game.

      Teacher Academy Follow-up - The Professional Learning Communities (PLCs): Follow-up meetings
      for teachers with the teacher training lead (co-PI Ragusa) will occur during the ensuing
      academic years of the Virtual Sprouts. Each participant teacher will meet quarterly with
      school site administrative members, and the project PIs. Additionally, participant teachers
      will enroll in an online computer mediated virtual classroom community of practice using
      USC's DEN courseware platform aligned to the teacher resource web portal to share ideas with
      teacher participant peers and the PIs. Teachers will engage in &quot;virtual&quot; lesson study
      (McQuiggan, S.W., &amp; Rowe, J.P., 2008) and post their Virtual Sprouts activities and
      implementation plan for the intervention specific to their classroom. Continued lesson study
      will continue via this web portal, as teacher participants will be required to &quot;attend&quot; on
      line at least four times monthly. This allows for maximum PLC participation with minimum
      teacher burden and enables a collaborative focus in the PLCs. Additionally, this allows for
      the PLCs to continue across schools beyond the SEPA funding period as a sustainability
      strategy. The PLC structure is designed to create a sustained community of practice with all
      participant teachers (Desurvire, H., &amp; Wiberg, C., 2008).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Nutrition knowledge</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-intervention and post-intervention (approximately 8 weeks apart)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in scores on nutrition knowledge as measured by questionnaire administered one week pre-intervention and one week post intervention. Length of intervention is approximately six weeks, depending upon how schools schedule the 12 game modules</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dietary intake</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-intervention and post-intervention (approximately 8 weeks apart)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in scores on dietary intake as measured by the Block dietary screener, administered one week pre-intervention and one week post intervention. Length of intervention is approximately six weeks, depending upon how schools schedule the 12 game modules</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Preference for fruits and vegetables</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-intervention and post-intervention (approximately 8 weeks apart)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in scores on preference for fruit and vegetables as measured by a taste test administered in class one week pre-intervention and one week post intervention. Length of intervention is approximately six weeks, depending upon how schools schedule the 12 game modules</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gardening knowledge</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre and post intervention (approximately 8 weeks apart)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in scores on gardening knowledge as measured by questionnaire administered one week pre-intervention and one week post intervention. Length of intervention is approximately six weeks, depending upon how schools schedule the 12 game modules</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3000</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Virtual Sprouts</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Virtual Sprouts intervention arm will play Virtual Sprouts in a school-based implementation of the game.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group will consist of students who will not play the Virtual Sprouts game at school.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Virtual Sprouts</intervention_name>
    <description>The Virtual Sprouts intervention group will play Virtual Sprouts in a school-based implementation of the game.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Virtual Sprouts</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Child in 3rd, 4th, or 5th grade

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Child in grades earlier than 3rd or later than 5th
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>11 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Donna Spruijt-Metz, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Southern California</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chad Lane, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Southern California</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Giselle Ragusa, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Southern California</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marientina Gotsis, MFA</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Southern California</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jaimie Davis, PhD, RD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Texas Austin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Donna Spruijt-Metz, PhD</last_name>
    <email>dmetz@usc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Southern California</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Los Angeles Unified School District</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Donna Spruijt-Metz, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://virtualsprouts.com/</url>
    <description>Virtual Sprouts project website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Twiss J, Dickinson J, Duma S, Kleinman T, Paulsen H, Rilveria L. Community gardens: lessons learned from California Healthy Cities and Communities. Am J Public Health. 2003 Sep;93(9):1435-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12948958</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kipke MD, Iverson E, Moore D, Booker C, Ruelas V, Peters AL, Kaufman F. Food and park environments: neighborhood-level risks for childhood obesity in east Los Angeles. J Adolesc Health. 2007 Apr;40(4):325-33. Epub 2007 Feb 5.</citation>
    <PMID>17367725</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Robinson EJ, Mitchell P. Children's interpretation of messages from a speaker with a false belief. Child Dev. 1992 Jun;63(3):639-52.</citation>
    <PMID>1600828</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 15, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 9, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Southern California</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Donna Spruijt-Metz</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, USC/CESR Mobile and Connected Health Program</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Nutrition</keyword>
  <keyword>Children</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
