<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="13338">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01981707</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013-003058-25</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01981707</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>F-choline PET in Early Response Assessment for Castration Resistant Prostatic Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>PRECHOL</acronym>
  <official_title>F-choline PET in Early Response Assessment for Castration Resistant Prostatic Cancer Treated by Abiraterone Acetate or Enzalutamide</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Grenoble</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Grenoble</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>France: Agence Nationale de Sécurité du Médicament et des produits de santé</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Until today no current diagnostic tool exists to identify an early objective response when
      patients with castration-resistant prostate cancer were treated by abiraterone acetate or
      enzalutamide. According to the Prostate Cancer Working Group, the investigators have to wait
      12 weeks before the first evaluation. To know soon that the treatment is effective will be
      decisive for the oncologist, even more in palliative situation where second effects can't be
      imposed to patients.

      In post-docetaxel, the F-choline PET-CT could be used to assess the response of this new
      therapy. Moreover, the investigators suppose that we can assess an early stage if there is
      an objective therapeutic response, at 6 weeks of treatment, in order to avoid unnecessarily
      and expansive treatment.

      The aim of this study is to assess if it is possible to determine early (6 weeks of
      treatment)if a F-choline PET-CT could predict the response to abiraterone acetate or
      enzalutamide in post-docetaxel.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity and specificity of 6 weeks PET-CT performed on the response after 12 weeks of abiraterone acetate treatment or enzalutamide</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A centralized review will be carried out by 2 independent reviewers. The gold-standard to evaluate tumoral response to abiraterone acetate or enzalutamide will be the pain, the Prostate Specific Antigen rate, and imagery at 3 months according to prostate cancer working group.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Study of global survival and progression-free survival according to the results of baseline F-choline PET .</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Study of global survival and progression-free survival at 12 weeks of treatment according to the results of 6 weeks treatment F-choline PET.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of Area Under the Curve receiver operating characteristic curve for maximum standardized uptake value (SUVmax) different values.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 and 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Study of global survival and progression-free survival at 24 weeks of treatment according to the results of 6 weeks treatment F-choline PET.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">31</enrollment>
  <condition>Castration-resistant Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>F-Choline PET</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The F-Choline-PET will be performed before and at 6 weeks of the beginning of treatment by abiraterone acetate or enzalutamide.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>F-Choline-PET</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>F-Choline PET</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &gt; 18 years

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG)performance status score of 2 or less

          -  Histologically or cytologically confirmed adenocarcinoma prostate cancer without
             neuroendocrine component (component with minority neuroendocrine) or small cell, or
             neuroendocrine cells or small minority component prostate who underwent surgical or
             medical castration

          -  Disease progression during or after a docetaxel-based chemotherapy

          -  serum testosterone level of 50 ng per deciliter or less (≤2.0 nmol per liter)

          -  Biologic criteria :

          -  platelets ≥ 100 000/μl,

          -  Creatinine &lt;1.5 x upper limit or creatinine clearance ≥ 60 ml / min,

          -  Serum potassium ≥ 3.5 mmol / l,

          -  Bilirubin &lt;1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g / dl without any transfusion.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  abnormal aminotransferase levels (levels of aspartate aminotransferase or alanine
             aminotransferase that were ≥2.5 times the upper level of the normal range;
             patients with known liver metastasis who had levels of aspartate aminotransferase or
             alanine aminotransferase that were ≤5 times the upper level of the normal range were
             eligible to participate

          -  previous therapy with ketoconazole

          -  serious coexisting nonmalignant disease :

          -  active or symptomatic viral hepatitis or chronic liver disease,

          -  uncontrolled hypertension,

          -  a history of pituitary or adrenal dysfunction,

          -  clinically significant heart disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jean-Philippe Vuillez, MD PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Grenoble</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Julien Dubreuil, resident</last_name>
    <phone>+33 6 75 21 43 42</phone>
    <email>jdubreuil@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service d'Oncologie Médicale, Institut Daniel Hollard, Groupement Hospitalier Mutualiste</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grenoble</city>
        <zip>38 000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laura Dupuy-Brousseau, MD</last_name>
      <email>l.dupuybrousseau@ghm-grenoble.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Laura Dupuy-Brousseau, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jérome Long, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Danièle Fric, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Odile Brun, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marie-Virginie Claeys, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinique Universitaire d'Oncologie Médicale, CHU de Grenoble</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grenoble</city>
        <zip>38 000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mathieu Laramas, MD</last_name>
      <email>mlaramas@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mathieu Laramas, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christina Costan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinique Universitaire de Médecine Nucléaire, CHU de Grenoble</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grenoble</city>
        <zip>38 000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jean-Philippe Vuillez</last_name>
      <email>jpvuillez@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Julien Dubreuil, Resident</last_name>
      <phone>+33 6 75 21 43 42</phone>
      <email>jdubreuil@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jean-Philippe Vuillez, MD-PHD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Céline Galazzini-Crépin, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alex Calizzano, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Julie Roux, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Jong IJ, Pruim J, Elsinga PH, Vaalburg W, Mensink HJ. 11C-choline positron emission tomography for the evaluation after treatment of localized prostate cancer. Eur Urol. 2003 Jul;44(1):32-8; discussion 38-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12814672</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scattoni V, Picchio M, Suardi N, Messa C, Freschi M, Roscigno M, Da Pozzo L, Bocciardi A, Rigatti P, Fazio F. Detection of lymph-node metastases with integrated [11C]choline PET/CT in patients with PSA failure after radical retropubic prostatectomy: results confirmed by open pelvic-retroperitoneal lymphadenectomy. Eur Urol. 2007 Aug;52(2):423-9. Epub 2007 Mar 20.</citation>
    <PMID>17397992</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rinnab L, Mottaghy FM, Blumstein NM, Reske SN, Hautmann RE, Hohl K, Möller P, Wiegel T, Kuefer R, Gschwend JE. Evaluation of [11C]-choline positron-emission/computed tomography in patients with increasing prostate-specific antigen levels after primary treatment for prostate cancer. BJU Int. 2007 Oct;100(4):786-93.</citation>
    <PMID>17822459</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Giovacchini G, Picchio M, Coradeschi E, Bettinardi V, Gianolli L, Scattoni V, Cozzarini C, Di Muzio N, Rigatti P, Fazio F, Messa C. Predictive factors of [(11)C]choline PET/CT in patients with biochemical failure after radical prostatectomy. Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging. 2010 Feb;37(2):301-9. doi: 10.1007/s00259-009-1253-3. Epub 2009 Sep 15.</citation>
    <PMID>19756592</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Breeuwsma AJ, Pruim J, van den Bergh AC, Leliveld AM, Nijman RJ, Dierckx RA, de Jong IJ. Detection of local, regional, and distant recurrence in patients with psa relapse after external-beam radiotherapy using (11)C-choline positron emission tomography. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2010 May 1;77(1):160-4. doi: 10.1016/j.ijrobp.2009.04.090. Epub 2009 Sep 23.</citation>
    <PMID>19783375</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heinisch M, Dirisamer A, Loidl W, Stoiber F, Gruy B, Haim S, Langsteger W. Positron emission tomography/computed tomography with F-18-fluorocholine for restaging of prostate cancer patients: meaningful at PSA &lt; 5 ng/ml? Mol Imaging Biol. 2006 Jan-Feb;8(1):43-8.</citation>
    <PMID>16315004</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bolla M, de Reijke TM, Van Tienhoven G, Van den Bergh AC, Oddens J, Poortmans PM, Gez E, Kil P, Akdas A, Soete G, Kariakine O, van der Steen-Banasik EM, Musat E, Piérart M, Mauer ME, Collette L; EORTC Radiation Oncology Group and Genito-Urinary Tract Cancer Group. Duration of androgen suppression in the treatment of prostate cancer. N Engl J Med. 2009 Jun 11;360(24):2516-27.</citation>
    <PMID>19516032</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bolla M, Collette L, Blank L, Warde P, Dubois JB, Mirimanoff RO, Storme G, Bernier J, Kuten A, Sternberg C, Mattelaer J, Lopez Torecilla J, Pfeffer JR, Lino Cutajar C, Zurlo A, Pierart M. Long-term results with immediate androgen suppression and external irradiation in patients with locally advanced prostate cancer (an EORTC study): a phase III randomised trial. Lancet. 2002 Jul 13;360(9327):103-6.</citation>
    <PMID>12126818</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Messing EM, Manola J, Yao J, Kiernan M, Crawford D, Wilding G, di'SantAgnese PA, Trump D; Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group study EST 3886. Immediate versus deferred androgen deprivation treatment in patients with node-positive prostate cancer after radical prostatectomy and pelvic lymphadenectomy. Lancet Oncol. 2006 Jun;7(6):472-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16750497</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tannock IF, de Wit R, Berry WR, Horti J, Pluzanska A, Chi KN, Oudard S, Theodore C, James ND, Turesson I, Rosenthal MA, Eisenberger MA; TAX 327 Investigators. Docetaxel plus prednisone or mitoxantrone plus prednisone for advanced prostate cancer. N Engl J Med. 2004 Oct 7;351(15):1502-12.</citation>
    <PMID>15470213</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Petrylak DP, Tangen CM, Hussain MH, Lara PN Jr, Jones JA, Taplin ME, Burch PA, Berry D, Moinpour C, Kohli M, Benson MC, Small EJ, Raghavan D, Crawford ED. Docetaxel and estramustine compared with mitoxantrone and prednisone for advanced refractory prostate cancer. N Engl J Med. 2004 Oct 7;351(15):1513-20.</citation>
    <PMID>15470214</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scher HI, Halabi S, Tannock I, Morris M, Sternberg CN, Carducci MA, Eisenberger MA, Higano C, Bubley GJ, Dreicer R, Petrylak D, Kantoff P, Basch E, Kelly WK, Figg WD, Small EJ, Beer TM, Wilding G, Martin A, Hussain M; Prostate Cancer Clinical Trials Working Group. Design and end points of clinical trials for patients with progressive prostate cancer and castrate levels of testosterone: recommendations of the Prostate Cancer Clinical Trials Working Group. J Clin Oncol. 2008 Mar 1;26(7):1148-59.</citation>
    <PMID>18309951</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Effert PJ, Bares R, Handt S, Wolff JM, Büll U, Jakse G. Metabolic imaging of untreated prostate cancer by positron emission tomography with 18fluorine-labeled deoxyglucose. J Urol. 1996 Mar;155(3):994-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8583625</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beheshti M, Vali R, Waldenberger P, Fitz F, Nader M, Loidl W, Broinger G, Stoiber F, Foglman I, Langsteger W. Detection of bone metastases in patients with prostate cancer by 18F fluorocholine and 18F fluoride PET-CT: a comparative study. Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging. 2008 Oct;35(10):1766-74. doi: 10.1007/s00259-008-0788-z. Epub 2008 May 9.</citation>
    <PMID>18465129</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Daut RL, Cleeland CS, Flanery RC. Development of the Wisconsin Brief Pain Questionnaire to assess pain in cancer and other diseases. Pain. 1983 Oct;17(2):197-210.</citation>
    <PMID>6646795</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 1, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>castration-resistant prostate cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>abiraterone acetate</keyword>
  <keyword>enzalutamide</keyword>
  <keyword>choline pet</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Choline</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
