<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="45292">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01986426</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C12-315-03</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01986426</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dose Escalation Study of LTX-315 in Patients With Transdermally Accessible Tumours</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I, Open-label, Multi-centre, Multi-dose, Dose Escalation Study of LTX-315 in Patients With Transdermally Accessible Tumours</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lytix Biopharma AS</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Theradex</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aptiv Solutions</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Lytix Biopharma AS</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Norway: Norwegian Medicines Agency</authority>
    <authority>Belgium: Federal Agency for Medicines and Health Products, FAMHP</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study will assess the safety, PK and efficacy of different dosing regimens of LTX-315; a
      lytic-peptide that induces long-term anti-cancer immune responses.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this phase I, open-label, multicentre, multi-dose study in patients with transdermally
      accessible tumours; the safety, PK and efficacy of different dosing regimens of LTX-315 will
      be asessed. The study will consist of two parts: Dose Escalation and Dose Expansion. In the
      Dose Escalation, each patient will have at least two lesions: a first index lesion for the
      Induction treatment and a second lesion for repeated Induction treatment and Maintenance
      treatment. The Dose Escalation consists of four periods: First induction treatment (up to 6
      weeks of LTX-315) in the first index lesion; Second induction (up to 6 weeks of LTX-315) and
      Maintenance treatment (up to 20 weeks of LTX-315) in the second index lesion; Follow-up.

      In the Dose Expansion each patient will have at least two lesions: a first index lesion for
      Induction and Maintenance treatment and a second lesion as a target (reference) lesion. The
      Dose Expansion will be done as determined by the Safety Review Committee and the Sponsor.
      The the optimal regimen will be based on the results of the Dose Escalation from the
      following information:

        1. Safety parameters including blood samples and cardiovascular effects

        2. Immunohistology and ultrasound confirmation of necrosis and tumour infiltrating
           lymphocytes

        3. Systemic inflammatory response such as total lymphocyte count, C-reactive protein (CRP)
           or cytokines

        4. Evidence of clinical responses

      Cohorts may be utilised to:

        1. Evaluate different doses of LTX-315

        2. Explore potential modifications to the Induction and/or the Maintenance phases

        3. Evaluate the potential to include appropriate combination therapies with LTX-315

        4. Gain further information on clinical efficacy

      Maintenance treatment may be extended for patients who have not progressed according to
      immune-related response criteria (irRC), as long as it is considered beneficial to the
      patient. Only adverse events and efficacy data will be collected on the extended Maintenance
      treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose limiting toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>At each dosing timepoint up to 32 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Dose limiting toxicities (DLT) and the overall safety profile (adverse events (AE), laboratory assessments, physical findings and symptomatic assessment) of LTX-315 will be measured at each dosing point (may be weekly) up to 32 weeks post first dosing</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti tumour effects</measure>
    <time_frame>First index lesion at week 7. Second index lesion week 22 and end of treatment week 32</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Tumour necrosis will be assessed based on ultrasound imaging and scored according to irRC.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>General systemic inflammatory response</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8, week 13 week 28 and week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Immunological response prameters will be monitored from blood samples to investigate and characterize the immune status of the patient and the nature of the anti tumour response.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Local inflammatory responses</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 7 and end of treatment (Week 32)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Biopsies and tumour resection samples will be collected and prepared for histological and immunohistochemical evaluation of the local inflammatory response.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Head and Neck Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LTX-315</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>First induction treatment (6 weeks): In week 1 the first index lesion will be injected twice daily on 3 consecutive days. During week 2-6 the injection will be once a week.
Second induction treatment (6 weeks) and Maintenance treatment (20 weeks)- At week 7 the second index lesion will be injected with same dosing schedule as the first index lesion.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LTX-315</intervention_name>
    <description>Dose escalation:
Cohort 1: 2 mg twice per day (4 mg) Cohort 2: 3 mg twice per day (6 mg) Cohort 3: 4 mg twice per day (8 mg)</description>
    <arm_group_label>LTX-315</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Advanced disease for which conventional anti-tumour treatment is not appropriate.

          -  Have at least two transdermally injectable tumours (such as, but not limited to,
             melanoma, breast cancer, head/neck cancer or lymphoma) each of at least 10 mm and no
             greater than 100 mm in diameter.

          -  Have at least a single (irRC) measurable lesion in addition to the lesions chosen for
             transdermal injection (Expansion cohorts only).

          -  Be willing to undergo repeat tumour biopsy and/or tumour resection procedures.

          -  Have an ECOG Performance status (PS): 0 - 1.

          -  Meet the following laboratory requirements:

               1. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 x 109/L

               2. Absolute lymphocyte count ≥ 0.8 x 109/L

               3. Platelet count ≥ 75 x 109/L

               4. Haemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dL

               5. aPTT/PT within the institution's normal range

               6. Total bilirubin level ≤ 1.5 x ULN

               7. ASAT and ALAT ≤ 2.5 x ULN (≤5 x ULN if liver metastasis present)

               8. Creatinine ≤ 1.5 x ULN

               9. Albumin ≥ 30 g/L

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Have received an investigational drug within 4 weeks prior to study drug
             administration, or are scheduled to receive one during the treatment or the
             post-treatment period.

          -  Have received cancer immunotherapy within 6 weeks prior to study drug administration
             or have not recovered from adverse events (to ≤ CTCAE grade 1) due to such agents.

          -  Have received any external radiotherapy to the index lesions or lesions identified as
             target lesions.

          -  Have index lesions scheduled to be resected within 6 weeks prior to study drug
             administration.

          -  Have received external radiotherapy or cytotoxic chemotherapy within 4 weeks prior to
             study drug administration, or have not recovered from adverse events (≤ CTCAE grade
             1) due to agents administered more than 4 weeks earlier. Palliative radiotherapy to
             non-target lesions within 4 weeks of study drug administration is allowed provided
             that it is not in close proximity to a target lesion to be used of irRC assessment.

          -  Have received imiquimod within 12 weeks prior to study drug administration or have
             not recovered from adverse events (to ≤ CTCAE grade 1) due to this agent.

          -  Receiving full dose anticoagulation.

          -  Are currently taking any agent with a known effect on the immune system. Patients are
             allowed to be on a stable dose of corticosteroids (up to 10 mg daily prednisolone or
             equivalent) for at least 2 weeks prior to study drug administration (please see
             Appendix III for prohibited medications).

          -  Have any other serious illness or medical condition such as, but not limited to:

               1. Uncontrolled infection or infection requiring antibiotics

               2. Uncontrolled cardiac failure: Classification III or IV (New York Heart
                  Association)

               3. Uncontrolled systemic and gastro-intestinal inflammatory conditions

               4. Bone marrow dysplasia

          -  Have a history of systemic auto-immune disease requiring anti-inflammatory or
             immunosuppressive therapy within the last 3 months. Patients with history of
             autoimmune thyroiditis are eligible provided the patient requires only thyroid
             hormone replacement therapy AND disease has been stable for ≥ 1 year.

          -  Have a known history of positive tests for HIV/AIDS, hepatitis B or C.

          -  Have a history of cerebrovascular or cardiac disorders and would be at particular
             risk of sequelae following a short hypotensive episode.

          -  Are breast feeding and/or have a positive pregnancy test during screening.

          -  Are expected to need any other anti-cancer therapy or immunotherapy to be initiated
             during the study period (induction and maintenance phases).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James Spicer, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Guy's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Wenche M Olsen, PhD</last_name>
    <email>w.m.olsen@lytixbiopharma.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Berit Nicolaisen</last_name>
    <email>berit.nicolaisen@lytixbiopharma.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cliniques Universitaires St-Luc, Service d'oncologie médicale</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bruxelles</city>
        <zip>1200</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jean-Francois Baurain, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jules Bordet Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bruxelles</city>
        <zip>1000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ahmed Awada, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oslo University Hospital Radiumhospitalet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oslo</city>
        <zip>0379</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paal Fr Brunsvig, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+47 22934000</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paal Fr Brunsvig, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Guy's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SE1 9RT</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James Spicer, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Norway</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 28, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Transdermal accessible tumours</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
