<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="144440">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01678885</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Energy Balance</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01678885</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of Energy Balance</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessment of Energy Balance</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to test different methods of measuring energy balance,
      including food intake and energy expenditure. Another purpose of this study is to see if
      energy expenditure predicts weight and change after a weight loss diet.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will take place over a period of one year. Participants will spend 3 weeks
      completing Phase I, and eight weeks completing Phase II (the weight loss phase of the
      study). Then, participants will return to the center at months 6 and 12 for a follow-up
      visit. During these visits, body weight, blood pressure, and pulse will be recorded, and
      questionnaires about eating attitudes and habits will be collected and assessed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>TEST THE VALIDITY OF BOTH SIDES OF ENERGY BALANCE EQUATION.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A new method of digital photography of foods to measure the energy intake and macronutrient intake of free-living humans will be tested. Digital photography Energy Intake will be tested against measured food provisions during an in-feeding period and against energy intake measured with doubly labeled water during free-living conditions. Energy Intake measured by directly weighing food provisions in the clinic over two days and measuring food intake during free-living conditions over one week with the doubly labeled water.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Posture allocation</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Posture allocation refers to the amount of time spent engaging in certain behaviors e.g., sitting, walking, running, changing positions and the energy burned during these activities which the secondary aim is to test if posture allocation predicts weight change over one year following a period of weight loss.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Caloric Intake and Energy Metabolism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>During the first week of the doubly labeled water period (day 0 to 7), participants in group 1 will use digital photography of foods. During the second week of the doubly labeled water phase, participants in this group will wear the Intelligent Device for Energy Expenditure and Activity (IDEEA) monitor and an accelerometer.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1 Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in Phase I Group 2 will complete the same procedures as participants in Phase I Group 1, but in the opposite order.  They will wear the Intelligent Device for Energy Expenditure and Activity (IDEEA) monitor and an accelerometer for the first week of the doubly labeled water, and use digital photography of foods during the second week of the doubly labeled water period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase II</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants who complete Phase I of the study will receive a partial supplement low-calorie diet (LCD) for 8 weeks.  This diet plan is a 1000-1150 kcal/day diet composed of HealthOne shakes and prepackaged portion controlled foods or home-cooked meals that participants will complete in a free-living environment. Participants will return to follow-up at six and twelve months after they completed the LCD. During these assessments, anthropometric and questionnaire data will be collected.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Digital Photography of Foods</intervention_name>
    <description>The digital photography of foods method was developed to unobtrusively measure energy intake in naturalistic settings (e.g., cafeterias). Participants will be provided with cell-phones with digital cameras and cellular network capability.  Participants were trained to take pictures of their food selection and plate waste and to send these pictures to the researchers over the cellular network.  The participant will collect data in free-living conditions and these data will be collected in near real time.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1 Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>digital photography</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>doubly labeled water</intervention_name>
    <description>Doubly labeled water, considered the gold standard for measuring energy intake in humans, was used to measure total daily energy expenditure during free-living conditions. DLW is used to obtain an accurate measure of total daily energy expenditure, which is equal to energy intake during energy balance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1 Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>DLW</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IDEEA</intervention_name>
    <description>The Intelligent Device for Energy Expenditure and Activity (IDEEA) will be used to measure the time spent engaging in active vs. sedentary behaviors, and the energy costs of these behaviors.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1 Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Intelligent Device for Energy Expenditure and Activity</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>low-calorie diet</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be instructed to consume five packets of Health One per day, which provides 800 kcal and 125% of Recommended Daily Intake of vitamins and minerals. Additionally participants will be instructed to consume a meal consisting of 200 kcal to 350 kcal daily, which could consist of a portion-controlled meal replacement or a home-cooked meal. Participants will meet with a Registered Dietitian at weeks 0, 2, 4, and 6 and receive instructions on adhering to the meal plan.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase II</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LCD</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18-65 years

          -  Body Mass Index 25-40

          -  Willing to eat foods provided for two days.

          -  Willing to wear the IDEEA( Intelligent Device for Energy Expenditure and Activity),
             which is a device that attaches to the body and records movement and activity.

          -  Willing to wear an accelerometer, which is similar to a pager that attaches to belt
             or clothing and measures activity.

          -  Willing to use a cell phone equipped with a digital camera to take pictures of foods
             for one week.

          -  Willing to undergo an 8 week weight loss diet, consisting of supplement or powdered
             shakes, portion-controlled entrees, or home-cooked meals.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A diagnosis of diabetes, cardiovascular disease, or cancer.

          -  Females who are pregnant or planning to become pregnant during the trail.

          -  Medications that influence appetite or body weight (weight loss medications such as
             sibutramine, antipsychotic medications such as olanzapine, or herbal weight loss
             products) taken during the previous three months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Corby K Martin, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baton Rouge</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70808</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 31, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 31, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Corby K. Martin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
