<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="147921">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01819987</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HomeTech healthy lifestyle</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01819987</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>HomeTech Healthy Lifestyle Program for Mothers With Young Children</brief_title>
  <official_title>Home-based &amp; Technology-centered Childhood Obesity Prevention for Mothers With Young Children</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      About 17% of Chinese American preschool children are obese, compared to 12.4%of all children
      from age three to five years residing in the US; the prevalence of obesity is expected to
      increase in the future. Therefore, the proposed study  will adapt a home-based and
      technology-centered childhood obesity prevention program for low-income Chinese American
      mothers of children three to five years old. The aims of the study are to assess the
      feasibility of the intervention and estimate the effect sizes on children's and mothers'
      outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to adapt and implement a family-centered and technology-based intervention
      to prevent obesity in young Chinese American children from low-income families with
      overweight mothers. The proposed study framework is based on the Information Motivation
      Behavioral Skills Model, which includes the mothers' gained knowledge/information, increased
      personal and social motivators, and acquired behavioral skills towards behavioral changes.
      The intervention will be developed with a Community Advisory Committee and validated for
      cultural appropriateness through a beta-testing process. The validated intervention will be
      implemented thereafter. Eligible overweight mothers with young Chinese American children
      (ages three to five years) will be recruited from local day care settings, low-income
      housing and Head Start programs to participate in the study. Participants will be randomized
      into either the intervention (N=15) or control group (N=15). Participants in the
      intervention group will receive the 8-week online interactive sessions and activities
      delivered through tablet computers. Participants in the control group will receive general
      health promotion topics relevant to preschool-age children via mailing materials weekly for
      eight weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline body mass index at 5 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and at 5 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants will have their weight and height measured and body mass index will be calculated. Change of BMI from baseline will be assessed at 5 months post baseline</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline physical activity at 2 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 2 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants will wear Actigraphy for 7 days at baseline and at 2 months. Change of physical activity from baseline will be assessed at 2 months post baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Sedentary activity at 2 months</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 2 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants will complete Family Eating and Activity Habits Questionnaire at baseline and at 2 month.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Parental Feeding Practice at 2 months</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 2 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants will complete Child Feeding Questionnaire at baseline and at 2 months . Change of parental feeding practice from baseline will be assessed at 2 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Self-efficacy regarding diet and physical activity at 2 months</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 2 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants will complete self-efficacy questionnaire regarding nutrition and physical behavior at baseline and at 2 months. Change of self-efficacy from baseline will be assessed at 2 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline physical activity level at 5 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 5 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in baseline physical actiivty level will be measured at 5 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Sedentary activity at 5 months</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 5 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants will complete Family Eating and Activity Habits Questionnaire at baseline and at 5 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Parental Feeding Practice at 5 months</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 5 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants will complete Child Feeding Questionnaire at baseline and at 5 months . Change of parental feeding practice from baseline will be assessed at 5 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Self-efficacy regarding diet and physical activity at 5 months</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 5 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants will complete self-efficacy questionnaire regarding nutrition and physical behavior at baseline and at 5 months. Change of self-efficacy from baseline will be assessed at 5 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Overweight</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mailing information</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the mailing information group will receive general health promotion topics relevant to preschool-age children (such as immunization, injury prevention and school readiness) via mailing materials that are bilingual weekly for eight weeks. These materials will be obtained from CDC and AAP.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tablet computer</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the intervention group will receive eight weekly online sessions and interactive activities delivered through tablet computers. Intervention participants will receive instructions for accessing the program via the tablet at an in-person session. Automated weekly emails will be sent to participating mothers for the intervention duration to encourage study engagement.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tablet computer</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in the intervention group will receive eight weekly online sessions and interactive activities delivered through tablet computers. Intervention participants will receive instructions for accessing the program via the tablet at an in-person session. Automated weekly emails will be sent to participating mothers for the intervention duration to encourage study engagement.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tablet computer</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mailing information</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in the control group will receive general health promotion topics relevant to preschool-age children (such as immunization, injury prevention and school readiness) via mailing materials that are bilingual weekly for eight weeks. These materials will be obtained from CDC and AAP.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mailing information</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children:

          -  must be between ages three and five

          -  have a mother who identifies her child as Chinese;

          -  be healthy-defined as free of chronic or acute illness.

          -  Mothers:

          -  must identify themselves as Chinese

          -  the primary provider of the child,

          -  be able to speak and read Chinese or English;

          -  with a BMI &gt;= 23.0;

          -  meet low-income requirements in the Bay Area.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Have acute or chronic conditions that prevent performing daily activities
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jyu-Lin Chen, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jyu-Lin Chen, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>415-502-6015</phone>
    <email>jyu-lin.chen@nursing.ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California San Francisco</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>64143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jyu-Lin Chen, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>415-502-6015</phone>
      <email>jyu-lin.chen@nursing.ucsf.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jyu-Lin Chen, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 23, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Overweight</keyword>
  <keyword>mother</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood obesity prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Chinese American</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
