<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="85479">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01656850</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PV0805</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01656850</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Whole Almonds on Biomarkers of Cardiovascular Disease in Chinese Patients With Type 2 Diabetes</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Whole Almonds on Glucoregulation, Endothelial Function, Inflammation, Lipid Profile, and Oxidative Stress in Chinese Patients With Type 2 Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Taipei Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Taipei Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Taiwan: Department of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to examine whether almond consumption for 3 month will help
      Chinese patients with type 2 diabetes control blood glucose and decrease risk factors of
      cardiovascular disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Our previous study demonstrated almonds (~60 g/d) improved lipid profile, glucoregulation,
      inflammation, and oxidative stress in 20 Chinese patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus
      (T2DM). To follow-up and expand this work with a more robust trial, the investigators
      propose a larger (n = 40), longer-term (90-d) investigation of the effect of almonds (~60
      g/d) on adipokine regulation, endothelial function, glucoregulation, inflammation, lipid
      profile, and oxidative stress in Chinese patients with T2DM as compared to a placebo
      control. The investigators will conduct a 7-mo randomized, cross-over, placebo controlled
      clinical trial in which all meals will be provided to all subjects (n = 40). During the
      first 2 weeks (run-in period), all subjects will receive a control diet resembling a typical
      Taiwan diet, prepared based on the NCEP Step 2 guidelines. During the following 3 mo (Phase
      I), subjects will be randomized to receive either the control diet or the control diet with
      whole almonds (~60g/d) incorporated to replace 20% calories. After a 2-wk washout period
      during which all subjects will once again receive the control diet, subjects will receive
      the opposite diet to the one assigned during the Phase I for the other 3 months (Phase II).
      The caloric content of each diet will be adjusted to each subjects' energy needs to prevent
      any change in body weight. The following biomarkers will be determined at the baseline and
      end of each dietary intervention: Glucoregulation: fasted serum HbA1c, glucose and insulin,
      postprandial serum glucose and insulin, and urinary C-peptide; Endothelial Function:
      brachial artery FMD and serum nitric oxide, e-selectin, endothelial-1 (ET-1), and
      intracellular adhesion molecule-1 (ICAM-1); Adipokine Regulation: serum adiponectin, leptin,
      and resistin; Inflammation: serum high-sensitivity C-reactive protein (CRP), interleukin
      (IL)-6, IL-10, retinol binding protein-4 (RBP-4), and tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α;
      Oxidative Stress: urinary isoprostanes (adjusted for creatinine) and serum protein carbonyls
      and oxidized LDL; and Lipid Profile: serum cholesterol, triglycerides, and apolipoproteins
      A1 and B.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2011</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in HbA1c</measure>
    <time_frame>at the baseline and at the end of 3-month dietary intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The change in HbA1c values between the baseline and at the end of dietary intervention serves as the primary outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Whole almonds</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>whole almonds to replace 20% daily calorie intake</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NCEP step 2 diet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>whole almonds</intervention_name>
    <description>Whole almonds will be incorporated into a control diet which is a NCEP step 2 diet.  Whole almonds will replace 20% daily calorie intake.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Whole almonds</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NCEP Step 2 diet</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>NCEP step 2 diet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects will be diagnosed with diabetes larger than 5 years,

          -  aged between 40-70 years,

          -  with BMI = 24-35 kg/m2,

          -  serum cholesterol larger than 200 mg/dL,

          -  HbA1c 6.5-9 %, and

          -  regular use of oral hypoglycemic agents.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Use of medications known to affect lipid metabolism, i.e., hypolipidemic or
             cholesterol-lowering agents

          -  Use of insulin to control blood glucose

          -  Regular use of oral steroids

          -  Regular use of anti-inflammatory agents (prescribed [Rx] or over-the-counter [OTC])

          -  Gain or loss of larger than 5% of body weight in the last 6 months

          -  CVD: coronary artery disease, left ventricular hypertrophy evidenced by
             echocardiogram, congestive heart failure, cerebrovascular disease, stroke, peripheral
             vascular disease, dysautonomia

          -  Gastrointestinal: diseases, conditions, or medications influencing gastrointestinal
             absorption including active peptic ulcer disease, inflammatory bowel disease,
             treatment with acid-lowering drugs

          -  Renal: chronic kidney disease due to any condition, renovascular disease, history of
             nephrolithiasis, diabetic nephropathy, serum creatinine &gt; 1.5 mg/dL

          -  Endocrine: disease, untreated thyroid disease, adrenal disease, pheochromocytoma,
             parathyroid disease, hyperuricemia

          -  Rheumatologic: gout, inflammatory arthritis

          -  Active treatment for cancer of any type (except basal cell carcinoma) 1 year

          -  Systolic blood pressure larger than 150 mmHg, and diastolic blood pressure larger
             than 95 mmHg.

          -  Any history of or known allergies to nuts of any kind

          -  Frequent nut consumption, defined as ≥ 3 oz/wk; however, subjects who are willing to
             refrain from eating all nuts and nut products for 6 wk prior to their initial visit
             (Visit 1) may be considered eligible

          -  Regular use of any dietary supplements containing vitamins, minerals, herbal or other
             plant-based preparations, fish oil supplements (including cod liver oil) or
             homeopathic remedies; however, subjects who are willing to refrain from the use of
             these supplements for 1 mo prior to their initial visit (Visit 1) and throughout the
             entire study may be considered eligible

          -  Usual daily ethanol intake of larger or equal to 2 drinks (24 oz beer, 8 oz wine, 2
             oz hard liquor)

          -  Illicit drug use

          -  Specific laboratory blood or urine analysis parameters of: creatinine larger than 1.5
             mg/dL, ALT and AST larger than 1.5 nmol/L, and urinalysis - hematuria and proteinuria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jen-Fang Liu, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Taipei Medical University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jennifer Wu, MS</last_name>
    <phone>011-886-220153183</phone>
    <email>goues2000@yahoo.com.tw</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Taipei Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei City</city>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jen-Fang Liu, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 2, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 13, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Taipei Medical University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jen-Fang Liu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hyperglycemia</keyword>
  <keyword>hyperinsulinemia</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
