<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="8160">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01816204</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>539-2012</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01816204</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Therapist Assisted Online Treatment for Anxiety</brief_title>
  <acronym>TAO-anxiety</acronym>
  <official_title>Therapist Assisted Online Treatment for Anxiety</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Therapist assisted, internet-based cognitive behavioral therapy (TAI-CBT) has been shown to
      be effective with patients who have Generalized Anxiety Disorder (GAD) in multiple studies
      from several countries, including: the United Kingdom, Australia, Sweden, and the
      Netherlands.  Despite strong evidence of efficacy, TAI-CBT has not been offered in the USA.
      TAI-CBT could provide an effective alternative to face-to-face psychotherapy that would
      expand the availability and convenience of evidence- based treatment anywhere clinical
      availability is limited. The University of Florida (UF) has historically had greater demand
      for psychotherapy than the available supply of psychotherapy hours resulting in waiting
      lists for students needing to receive treatment for anxiety.   Anxiety disorders interfere
      with memory and concentration thus impairing academic functioning.  Students who must wait
      for treatment for 3-4 weeks are at risk for failing courses or dropping out of school.  If
      TAI-CBT proved to be effective with UF students, providing it could increase the number of
      students who would receive effective and timely treatment.  This project will create a 6-8
      session therapist assisted on-line treatment for anxiety disorder.  The investigators will
      offer TAI-CBT as an experimental treatment in summer and fall, 2013 comparing outcomes to
      face-to-face individual therapy, group therapy, and wait-list controls.  The investigators
      hypothesize that students receiving TAI-CBT will have a reduction in anxiety symptoms
      comparable to face-to-face counseling and greater than wait list controls.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Participation is restricted to currently enrolled students at the University of Florida who
      have paid the health fee, and who are seeking treatment for anxiety and the Counseling and
      Wellness Center.  Students who meet criteria and agree to participate will select from three
      treatments, individual face-to-face, group therapy, or therapist assisted on-line treatment.
       Prior to each session of individual therapy, group therapy, or on-line treatment
      participants will complete three short measures of psychological symptoms, one of these, the
      Behavioral Health Measure-20 is a normal part of treatment at the CWC.  In addition
      participants will complete the GAD-7, which contains seven, 4-point Likert-type items, and
      the Penn State worry questionnaire (PSWQ), which consists of 16 Likert-type items.  These
      additional instruments will take about 2-5 minutes to complete prior to each session.

      In addition, the researchers will contact participants by e-mail 6 months after completion
      of treatment to ask them to complete the instruments as a follow-up.  If a participant is
      assigned to individual or group therapy he/she will receive this mode of treatment as usual
      at the Counseling and Wellness Center at the University of Florida.

      If a particpant is assigned to the Therapist-assisted on-line (TAO) treatment he/she will be
      asked to complete a seven module on-line treatment.  Each module includes interactive,
      educational materials and weekly assignments.  Subjects may participate in an on-line
      discussion forum with other participants for each module.  The forum will use only first
      names or a pseudonym to protect  confidentiality.  In addition, participants in the TAO
      treatment will receive a 10-20 minute videoconference weekly with a doctoral level
      therapist.  Therapists will review assignments, answer questions, and help  to apply the
      educational materials contained in the modules to the subjects life.

      The video conference will be on Adobe Connect.  This involves a free download for a
      computer, tablet, or smart phone.  Medical records will be kept for ten years, per UF
      policy.  Adobe connect is HIPAA and HITECH compliant.  Research records will be
      de-identified and use an identifier number that cannot be connected to individual
      participants.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Generalized Anxiety Disorder 7 item (GAD-7)</measure>
    <time_frame>The three measures will be administered weekly from initial enrollment in the study for 7 weeks and again at 6 month follow up.  The first assessment of patients will begin May 7 and will continue through January, 2014.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>7 item likert scale measure of anxiety.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Penn State Worry Questionnaire (PSWQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>The three measures will be administered weekly from initial enrollment in the study for 7 weeks and again at 6 month follow up.  The first assessment of patients will begin May 7 and will continue through January, 2014.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>16 item likert-type measure of worrying.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavioral Health Measure-20 (BHM-20)</measure>
    <time_frame>The three measures will be administered weekly from initial enrollment in the study for 7 weeks and again at 6 month follow up.  The first assessment of patients will begin May 7 and will continue through January, 2014.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>twenty item likert-type measure of distress, well-being, overall mental health functioning.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Anxiety Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Therapist assisted online treatment (TAO)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Students assigned to treatment with weekly online modules and weekly 10-15 minute video conference with counselor.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>face-to-face individual therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>weekly individual 50 minute psychotherapy sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group face-to-face counseling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Weekly group psychotherapy for anxiety.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Therapist assisted online treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>7 weekly interactive online modules with 10-15 minute counselor consultation via video conference.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Therapist assisted online treatment (TAO)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>face-to-face individual therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>weekly individual counseling as usual.</description>
    <arm_group_label>face-to-face individual therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Group face-to-face counseling</intervention_name>
    <description>weekly group psychotherapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group face-to-face counseling</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  students,

          -  mild to moderate anxiety,

          -  has appropriate computer equipment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Severe depression or anxiety,

          -  suicidal in past 12 months,

          -  not stable on medications for at least 30 days prior to beginning study treatments
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>26 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sherry A Benton, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Counseling and Wellness Center, University of Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32611-2662</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 23, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 11, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>anxiety treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>anxiety online treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>anxiety electronic treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>anxiety therapist assisted</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
