<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="56927">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01789333</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAF4157</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01789333</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Higher Irradiance in Keratoconus Ectasia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Study of the Safety and Effectiveness of Photochemically Induced Collagen Cross- Linking at Higher Irradiances in Patients With Keratoconus or Ectasia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stephen Trokel</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to see if brighter lights will allow us to shorten the treatment
      time required to stabilize the eyes of patients with keratoconus or a bulging cornea.  The
      investigators will be comparing the therapeutic effects of two different higher brightnesses
      of ultra violet light on a riboflavin treated eye.  One light will be twice as bright as the
      other and the exposure time of these brighter lights to deliver equivalent energy to the
      cornea will be reduced from the standard 30 minutes to 10 and 5 minutes.  Riboflavin is
      vitamin B12 and the investigators are trying to determine if they can get an identical
      clinical effect when they use the brighter treatment lights for shorter times.  The
      investigators will also monitor the clinical effect and the status of the cornea to see if
      additional risks are associated with the brighter light.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Total Optical Aberrations of the Cornea following Cross-Linking</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The change in corneal topography and optical properties from baseline will be evaluated at 3 and 6 months for all eyes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Uncorrected Visual Acuity (UCVA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Best Spectacle Corrected Visual Acuity (BSCVA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Manifest Refraction</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in depth of the effect with Optical Coherence Tomography (OCT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess the hypothesis the higher irradiance produces the same pattern of change, we will measure the depth and intensity of the stromal changes using Optical Coherence Tomography. An identical pattern of depth and intensity o fstromal change in the cornea for both the low and high irradiances will demonstrate that the nature of the photochemical interaction is identical.  If, on the other hand, the higher irradiance creates a different effect as seen on the OCT, then the hypothesis of equivalence must be questioned.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Keratoconus</condition>
  <condition>Ectasia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>9 mw/cm2 group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Three patients will be treated at 9 mw/cm2.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>18 mw/cm2 group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Three patients will be treated at 9 mw/cm2.  If the endothelial studies show no damage then the next three patients will be treated at 18 mw/cm2.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>UVA Light with irradiance exposure of 9 mW/cm2</intervention_name>
    <description>The device's light emitting diode (LED) is used to deliver a metered dose of UV-A light to a targeted treatment area for illuminating the cornea during corneal collagen cross-linking.
The aperture setting will be set at 10 mm, and the eye will be irradiated for 10 minutes for the high irradiance exposure of 9 mW/cm2.  During the exposure, instillation of riboflavin will continue (1 drop every 3 minutes).</description>
    <arm_group_label>9 mw/cm2 group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Riboflavin 0.1% ophthalmic solution</intervention_name>
    <description>The speculum is removed and one (1) drop of Riboflavin 0.1% ophthalmic solution will be instilled topically in the eye every 3 minutes for 30 minutes. At the end of the 30 minute riboflavin pre-treatment period, the eye will be examined to assure the presence of a yellow flare in the anterior chamber, indicating riboflavin saturation of the corneal tissue. If the yellow flare is not detected, riboflavin will continue to be instilled until the presence of the yellow flare in the anterior chamber is confirmed.
During UVA irradiation, instillation of riboflavin will be continued every 3 minutes. For a 30-minute pre-treatment and 30-minute irradiation, the total dose of riboflavin solution is approximately 32 drops, or 1.6 ml (1 drop = 0.05 ml; 1.6 mL = 1.6 mg riboflavin).</description>
    <arm_group_label>9 mw/cm2 group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>18 mw/cm2 group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Riboflavin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>UVA Light with irradiance exposure of 18 mW/cm2</intervention_name>
    <description>The device's light emitting diode (LED) is used to deliver a metered dose of UV-A light to a targeted treatment area for illuminating the cornea during corneal collagen cross-linking.
The aperture setting will be set at 10 mm, and the eye will be irradiated for 5 minutes at 18 mW/cm2. During the exposure, instillation of riboflavin will continue (1 drop every 3 minutes).</description>
    <arm_group_label>18 mw/cm2 group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Subjects who have one or both eyes that meet two of the following criteria will be
        considered candidates for this study:

          1. 18 years of age or older

          2. Having a diagnosis of progressive keratoconus or pellucid marginal degeneration.

               1. Characteristic pattern of deformity as analyzed by the Pentacam map.

               2. Minimal thickness of 350 microns

          3. Signed written informed consent

          4. Willingness and ability to comply with schedule for follow-up visits

          5. Contact lens removal prior to evaluation and treatment

        Inclusion criteria for ectasia

          1. History of having undergone a keratorefractive procedure and:

               1. Steepening by topography, either Pentacam or Humphrey

               2. Thinning of cornea

               3. Shift in the position of thinnest portion of cornea

               4. Unstable refraction with increasing myopia and astigmatism

               5. Development of irregular astigmatism

          2. At least two of the above criteria must be present.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects meeting any of the following criteria will be excluded from this study:

          1. Eyes classified as either normal, atypical normal,

          2. Corneal pachymetry ≤ 350 microns at the thinnest point measured by Pentacam.

          3. A history of chemical injury or delayed epithelial healing.

          4. Pregnancy (including plan to become pregnant) or lactation during the course of the
             study

          5. A known sensitivity to study medications

          6. Patients with nystagmus or any other condition that would prevent a steady gaze
             during the treatment

          7. Inability to cooperate with diagnostic tests.

          8. Patients with a current condition that, in the investigator's opinion, would
             interfere with or prolong epithelial healing.

          9. Taking Vitamin C (ascorbic acid) supplements within 1 week of the cross-linking
             treatment.

         10. Patients who are unable to remain supine and tolerate a lid speculum.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen Trokel, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>MaEdylin Bautista</last_name>
    <phone>212-305-5922</phone>
    <email>mmb2225@columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Edward Harkness Eye Institute-Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>MaEdylin Bautista</last_name>
      <phone>212-305-5922</phone>
      <email>mmb2225@columbia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephen Trokel, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 19, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 20, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Columbia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Stephen Trokel</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Clinical Ophthalmology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Keratoconus</keyword>
  <keyword>Ectasia</keyword>
  <keyword>UVA light</keyword>
  <keyword>riboflavin</keyword>
  <keyword>post-LASIK</keyword>
  <keyword>irregular astigmatism</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dilatation, Pathologic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Keratoconus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Riboflavin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
