<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="48451">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01724528</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FLO-01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-000776-42</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01724528</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Febuxostat for Tumor Lysis Syndrome Prevention in Hematologic Malignancies</brief_title>
  <acronym>FLORENCE</acronym>
  <official_title>Febuxostat for Tumor Lysis Syndrome Prevention in Hematologic Malignancies: a Randomized, Double Blind, Phase III Study Versus Allopurinol</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Menarini Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Menarini Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Italy: The Italian Medicines Agency</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <authority>Russia: Ministry of Health of the Russian Federation</authority>
    <authority>Ukraine: State Pharmacological Center - Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Agencia Española de Medicamentos y Productos Sanitarios</authority>
    <authority>Brazil: National Health Surveillance Agency</authority>
    <authority>Croatia: Ministry of Health and Social Care</authority>
    <authority>Czech Republic: State Institute for Drug Control</authority>
    <authority>Hungary: National Institute of Pharmacy</authority>
    <authority>Poland: Office for Registration of Medicinal Products, Medical Devices and Biocidal Products</authority>
    <authority>Romania: National Agency for Medicines and Medical Devices</authority>
    <authority>Serbia and Montenegro: Agency for Drugs and Medicinal Devices</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether febuxostat is superior to allopurinol in
      the prevention of tumor lysis syndrome (TLS) in patients with hematological malignancies at
      intermediate or high risk of TLS (according to Cairo-Bishop classification) who undergo
      chemotherapy
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed as a randomised, double-blind, active-controlled, parallel-group
      study to be conducted in approximately 80 sites.

      Approximately 340 male or female patients aged 18 or older suffering from hematologic
      malignancies (de novo patients or relapsing patients) at intermediate to high risk of TLS
      and scheduled for receiving the first cycle of cytotoxic chemotherapy, regardless of the
      line of treatment, will be randomized in this study. Eligible patients (as per screening
      visit) will be randomly allocated in a 1:1 ratio to Febuxostat or Allopurinol. The
      double-blind treatment period starts two days prior to the planned beginning of chemotherapy
      and continues for 7 to 9 consecutive days, according to Investigator judgment and on the
      basis of the actual duration of chemotherapy regimen administered to the patient.  Along the
      study treatment, uric acid levels, creatinine levels, Laboratory TLS/Clinical TLS and
      Adverse Events represent the major clinical findings to be monitored on a daily basis.
      Overall the study encompasses 10 to 11 planned visits at site, including screening,
      randomisation, on treatment and final follow up visits.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>serum uric acid (sUA) level control</measure>
    <time_frame>8 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Area under the curve of sUA from baseline (Day 1) to the evaluation visit (Day 8)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Preservation of renal function</measure>
    <time_frame>8 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in serum creatinine level from baseline (Day 1) to the evaluation visit (Day 8)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment responder rate</measure>
    <time_frame>6 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessment of treatment responder rate, where treatment response is defined as the maintenance of sUA &lt; 7.5 mg/dL from Day 3 to Day 8</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of laboratory tumor lysis syndrome (LTLS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessment of LTLS, from Day 3 to  Day 8. According to Cairo-Bishop definition LTLS is defined by the presence of 2 or more laboratory abnormalities including: a 25% increase or levels above normal for serum uric acid, potassium, and phosphate or a 25% decrease or levels below normal for calcium.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of clinical tumor lysis syndrome (CTLS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessment of CTLS, from Day 3 to Day 8. According to Cairo-Bishop definition, CTLS is defined by the presence of LTLS in addition to 1 or more of the following significant clinical complications: renal insufficiency, cardiac arrhythmias, sudden death and seizures. The grade of CTLS is defined by the maximal grade of the clinical manifestation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment emergent signs or symptoms (TESS)</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Incidence, severity, seriousness and treatment-causality of TESS</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">346</enrollment>
  <condition>Tumor Lysis Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Febuxostat for 7-9 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Allopurinol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Allopurinol for 7-9 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Febuxostat</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard dose PO (per os) from Day 1 to Day 7 (can be continued up to DAY 9 at investigator's discretion)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Adenuric</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Allopurinol</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard dose, low dose or high dose (as per investigator's judgement at the time of randomization) from DAY 1 to DAY 7 (can be continued up to DAY 9 at investigator's discretion)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Allopurinol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Zyloric</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients scheduled for first cytotoxic chemotherapy cycle, regardless of the line of
             treatment, because of hematologic malignancies at intermediate or high risk of TLS
             (according to the TLS risk stratification, Cairo M et al, British Journal of
             Haematology, 2010)candidate to Allopurinol treatment or have no access to Rasburicase

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 to 3

          -  Life expectancy &gt; 1 month

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients known to be hypersensitive to Febuxostat or Allopurinol or to any of the
             components of the formulations

          -  Patients with sUA levels ≥ 10 mg/dL at randomization

          -  Patients receiving Febuxostat, Allopurinol or any other urate lowering therapy (e.g.
             Rasburicase, probenecid) within 30 days prior to randomization

          -  Patients with severe renal and/or hepatic insufficiency

          -  Patients with diagnosis of LTLS or CTLS at randomization
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michele Spina, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centro Riferimento Oncologico (CRO) National Cancer Institute-Aviano-Italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Angela Capriati, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Menarini Ricerche S.p.A. - Florence-Italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 12, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 7, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Febuxostat, Tumor lysis syndrome, leukemia, lymphoma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Tumor Lysis Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hematologic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Allopurinol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Febuxostat</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
