<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="31848">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01997918</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KTS 2. Haplo HSCT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01997918</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Secondary Haplo HSCT for Relapse After Initial Allogeneic HSCT</brief_title>
  <official_title>Haploidentical Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation (HSCT) in the Treatment of Relapse After a First Allogeneic HSCT: a Retrospective Cohort Study by the German Cooperative Transplant Study Group</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital Tuebingen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ludwig-Maximilians - University of Munich</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Klinikum Augsburg, Germany</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Tuebingen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Ethics Commission</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Relapse of underlying hematologic malignancies after allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell
      transplantation (HSCT) is frequently treated by a second allogeneic HSCT (HSCT2). Choosing
      an alternative donor is often advocated to maximize chances of a graft versus tumour (GVT)
      effect. We and others published that success of this strategy when using an alternative
      human leukocyte antigen (HLA) identical donor is limited, at least when acute leukemia is
      the underlying disease. The aggressivity of the rapidly proliferating leukemia seems to
      prevail over GVT effects. A more potent alloimmune response is observed following
      haploidentical HSCT, especially early after haploidentical HSCT. This might be related to a
      fast and large expansion of natural killer (NK)-cells. Their alloreactive effect might
      translate into higher rates of tumor control. On the other hand, non-relapse complications
      (treatment related mortality, TRM) might be high in advanced relapsed tumour patients with
      heavy pretreatment and due to delayed immune reconstitution after haploidentical HSCT. The
      use of a haploidentical donor for HSCT2 following a first allogeneic HSCT from an HLA
      identical donor has been so far only systematically evaluated in small retrospective single
      center reports. Thus, in this multicenter study we aim to collect data on the extent to
      which participating centers employ haploidentical transplantation in the situation of
      relapse after HSCT2.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Relapse of underlying hematologic malignancies after allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell
      transplantation (HSCT) is frequently treated by a second allogeneic HSCT (HSCT2). Choosing
      an alternative donor is often advocated to maximize chances of a graft versus tumour (GVT)
      effect. We and others published that success of this strategy when using an alternative HLA
      identical donor is limited, at least when acute leukemia is the underlying disease. The
      aggressivity of the rapidly proliferating leukemia seems to prevail over GVT effects. A more
      potent alloimmune response is observed following haploidentical HSCT, especially early after
      haploidentical HSCT. This might be related to a fast and large expansion of NK-cells. Their
      alloreactive effect might translate into higher rates of tumor control. On the other hand,
      non-relapse complications (treatment related mortality, TRM) might be high in advanced
      relapsed tumour patients with heavy pretreatment and due to delayed immune reconstitution
      after haploidentical HSCT. The use of a haploidentical donor for HSCT2 following a first
      allogeneic HSCT from an HLA identical donor has been so far only systematically evaluated in
      small retrospective single center reports. Thus, in this multicenter study we aim to collect
      data on the extent to which participating centers employ haploidentical transplantation in
      the situation of relapse after HSCT2. We will describe and quantify the specific patient,
      donor, treatment, graft and outcomes characteristics associated with the course of
      treatment. To assess and control for the bias that is associated with the retrospective
      nature of this study, we will emphasize to collect clearly stated reasons for the decision
      to use a haploidentical transplant, e.g. as opposed to drug therapy or a second transplant
      from the original or an alternative HLA identical donor. This is a retrospective
      observational cohort study. German centers performing allogeneic HSCT are asked to
      contribute. Data will be validated and missing information will be further retrieved by the
      four principal investigators through phone. Final follow up will be performed in April 2014,
      2014. To be able to supply durable data on the primary endpoints, only patients receiving a
      haploidentical HSCT2 between 01.07.2003 and 30.06.2013 will be included.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Retrospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment related mortality (TRM) of haploidentical HSCT2</measure>
    <time_frame>up to day 365</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity of haploidentical HSCT2</measure>
    <time_frame>up to day 365</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) v.4</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>complete remission (CR) rate after haploidentical HSCT2</measure>
    <time_frame>day 100</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS) at 2 years after haploidentical HSCT2</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Graft versus host disease (GVHD) after haploidentical HSCT2</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of rejection after haploidentical HSCT2</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease free survival (DFS) at 2 years after haploidentical HSCT2</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Relapse of Hematological Malignancies</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients receiving salvage secondary haploidentical allogeneic HSCT after failure of
        primary allogeneic HSCT
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &gt;18 years at time of HSCT2

          -  Malignant hematologic disease

          -  Informed consent signed by the patients on the use of data in registry analyses

          -  1st allogeneic HSCT performed from any donor, including haploidentical HSCT1

          -  Hematological or extramedullary relapse after HSCT1

          -  Haploidentical 2nd allogeneic HSCT (i.e. &gt;= 2 Antigen mismatch family donor) between
             01.07.2003 and 30.06.2013

        Third or higher allogeneic HSCT does not preclude analysis as long as HSCT2 was
        haploidentical.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wolfgang A Bethge, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital Tuebingen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christoph Schmid, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Klinikum Augsburg</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Johanna Tischer, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ludwig-Maximilians University Hospital Munich</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maximilian Christopeit, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital of Halle</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 27, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 29, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Secondary allogeneic HSCT</keyword>
  <keyword>Haploidentical HSCT</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Recurrence</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hematologic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
