<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="60462">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01994135</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MEEC 12-037</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01994135</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Carbohydrase-inhibiting Polyphenols on Glycaemic Response in Vivo</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Leeds</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Leeds</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: University of Leeds</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Consumption of carbohydrate containing foods or sugary drinks brings about changes to the
      blood glucose levels. After a meal or drink, blood glucose levels rise until it reaches a
      peak concentration usually after 30 minutes. When the body senses the increase in blood
      glucose, a hormonal process involving insulin takes place to ensure that the glucose is
      taken up from the blood for storage and where it is needed for energy in the body. This
      process then brings about a decrease in the concentration of glucose until it reaches
      approximately the starting concentration. The original concentration of glucose is attained
      approximately 2 hours after eating or drinking a carbohydrate food or sugary drink
      respectively.

      Different carbohydrates and sugary drinks have different effects on blood glucose response
      depending on the amount as well as the type of carbohydrate. Those that give rise to a high
      glucose response compared to a reference carbohydrate (usually glucose) are said to be high
      glycaemic index (GI) foods and those with a lower glucose response compared to a reference
      carbohydrate (usually glucose) are said to be low glycaemic index (GI) foods.(1)

      Research has shown that diets that give rise to a high glucose response are associated with
      a number of abnormalities like increased metabolic syndrome (2). Metabolic syndrome mostly
      comprises of insulin resistance and glucose intolerance which gives an increased risk of
      type 2 diabetes. (3) It also gives rise to other conditions like high blood pressure
      (arterial hypertension), elevated blood insulin levels (hyper-insulinemia), elevated amounts
      of fat in the liver (fatty hepatosis) and elevated amounts of lipids in the blood
      (dyslipidemia). After type 2 diabetes become clinically apparent, the risk of cardiovascular
      disease also rises. (4) Research has also shown that foods/drinks which raise blood glucose
      levels gradually (low GI) rather than rapidly (high GI) have health benefits which include
      reducing the risk of metabolic syndrome (5). In vitro studies have shown that polyphenols
      found in fruits, vegetables and plant based foods have a positive effect on carbohydrate
      metabolism and can lower the blood glucose levels. (6)

      This research will determine whether the presence of polyphenols in the diet has any
      lowering effect on the blood glucose levels and hence the glycaemic index of foods. This
      will be determined by asking volunteers to consume polyphenol rich drink/food together with
      white bread and determine the glycaemic response. The GI of bread will be determined
      initially as a reference.

      Analysis will be done by measuring blood glucose response to white bread alone as reference
      and then to white bread with test sample containing polyphenols and then determine GI and
      see how the GI of bread will be affected. Other analyses to be done are plasma insulin,
      glucagon, gastric inhibitory polypeptide (GIP) and glucagon like peptides-1 (GLP-1) as they
      all relate to glycaemic response.

      Study hypothesis is that glucose metabolism will be affected.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Incremental Area Under the Curve for glucose, insulin, GIP and GLP-1 will be determined</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood will be collected at different time points within 3 hours, twice a week, for two weeks per volunteer</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Hyperglycaemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Reference food</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The reference food is white bread</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Test food dose 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Test food dose 1 response will be compared to reference test food</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Test food dose 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Test food dose 2 response will be compared to reference test food as well as to test food dose 1</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Reference food</intervention_name>
    <description>Reference food will be used to which test food samples will be compared to.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Reference food</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Test food dose 1</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Test food dose 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Test food dose 2</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Test food dose 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Group 1 - Healthy subjects

        Not diabetic Fasting glucose (blood glucose level before breakfast) 3.9 -5.9mmol/L Not on
        long term prescribed medication (except contraceptives) Not pregnant or lactating Not on
        special diet (for losing weight or fruit extracts supplements) Aged 18-75

        Group 2 - Metabolic syndrome risk group

        Not diabetic With fasting glucose (blood glucose level before breakfast) in the range of
        6.0 - 8.0mmol/l Not on long term prescribed medication (except contraceptives) Not
        pregnant or lactating Not on special diet (for losing weight or fruit extracts) Aged 18-75

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Group 1 - Healthy subjects

        Not healthy Diabetic Fasting glucose (blood glucose level before breakfast) 3.9 -5.9mmol/L
        On long term prescribed medication (except contraceptives) Pregnant or lactating On
        special diet (for losing weight or fruit extracts supplements) Aged below 18years or above
        75years

        Group 2 - Metabolic syndrome risk group

        Not diabetic With fasting glucose (blood glucose level before breakfast) above 8.0mmol/l
        On long term prescribed medication (except contraceptives) Pregnant or lactating On
        special diet (for losing weight or fruit extracts) Aged below 18years or above 75 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gary Williamson</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Leeds</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hilda Nyambe</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Leeds</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hilda Nyambe</last_name>
    <phone>+44 1133432957</phone>
    <email>fs07hs@leeds.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>School of Food Science and Nutrition</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leeds</city>
        <state>West Yorkshire</state>
        <zip>LS2 9JT</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hilda Nyambe</last_name>
      <phone>+44 1133432957</phone>
      <email>fs07hs@leeds.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hilda Nyambe</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 27, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 19, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Leeds</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hilda Nyambe</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD candidate</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hyperglycemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
