<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="42042">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02133924</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UMCC # 2014.051</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02133924</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Multicenter Study Of Natalizumab Plus Standard Steroid Treatment For High Risk Acute Graft-Versus-Host Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>PHASE II Multicenter Study Of Natalizumab Plus Standard Steroid Treatment For High Risk Acute Graft-Versus-Host Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>John Levine, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Biogen Idec</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Data and Safety Monitoring Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research trial is designed to study the safety and effectiveness of combining the study
      drug, Natalizumab (Tysabri®) with the standard treatment, the use of steroids, as a new
      treatment for acute graft versus host disease (acute GVHD). GVHD is the most common serious
      complication, after bone marrow transplant. GVHD occurs when the donor cells (the graft),
      treat the recipient's body as &quot;foreign&quot; and attack the cells in the recipient's body.
      During this immune system response, donor cells damage body tissues, such as the skin,
      liver, stomach, and/or intestines. Acute GVHD can be severe and if severe, potentially fatal
      to the transplant recipient. Acute GVHD usually happens within the first several months
      after transplant.

      The goal of this research is to develop a safer and more effective treatment for acute GVHD,
      and particularly for acute GVHD that affects the gastrointestinal (or GI) tract, with the
      ultimate goal being safer and more effective transplant therapies for blood cancers such as
      leukemia, lymphoma, and multiple myeloma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The only proven effective treatment for patients with acute graft vs host disease is
      steroids. Patients who do not respond to steroid treatment are at high risk for death.
      Unfortunately, based on the early symptoms, it is not possible to tell whether a patient
      will respond to steroids, when GVHD is diagnosed and treatment with steroids, such as
      prednisone, is started.

      This research trial is designed to study the safety and effectiveness of combining the study
      drug, Natalizumab (Tysabri®) with the use of steroids to treat acute GVHD in patients who
      are at the earliest stages of their clinical symptoms, but  who, by using a proprietary
      method developed at the University of Michigan, are  predicted to be at high risk for not
      responding to steroid therapy, the standard of care.

      Investigators at the University of Michigan have developed a research method, they believe
      might make it possible to predict who is at high risk for not responding to steroids. This
      method, called Ann Arbor GVHD grading, uses the levels of naturally occurring chemicals in
      the blood (called biomarkers) to determine a patient's GVHD grade (1, 2, or 3).

      A hypothesis is that most patients with Ann Arbor grade 3 GVHD, will not respond well to
      steroid treatment. The investigators research shows that almost half of the patients with
      Ann Arbor grade 3 GVHD, will die within 6 months of their GVHD diagnosis. Most of the deaths
      are due to intestinal GVHD, which sometimes does not develop, until after standard steroid
      treatment has already begun.

      Only patients who have Ann Arbor grade 3 GVHD, will be eligible for this study treatment. It
      is important to understand that Ann Arbor GVHD grading is not approved for clinical use. It
      can only be used as a test for research purposes. In this study, patients must have their
      blood tested to determine, if they qualify asre Ann Arbor grade 3 GVHD, and must start the
      study treatment within 3 days of their  clinical diagnosis of acute GVHD.

      The study will test whether the investigators can improve steroid response and prevent death
      from GVHD with the combination therapy, by blocking the donor cells from getting to the
      intestine and causing damage. Natalizumab (Tysabri®) is a drug that works by blocking the
      signals that cause immune cells like donor cells, to travel to organs like the intestine or
      brain.

      Natalizumab is FDA-approved in adults, to treat Crohn's disease, a chronic condition where
      immune cells cause damage to the digestive system (such as the stomach, intestines). It is
      also used to treat multiple sclerosis where immune cells cause damage to the nervous system
      in the brain. Its intended use is for patients whose disease has not responded to the
      standard treatment, or who cannot tolerate the side effects from standard treatments.

      Natalizumab has never been used for treating GVHD. It is an experimental drug for this
      study, because the investigators are investigating a new use for the drug, as a GVHD
      treatment, and also because it has not been studied in pediatric patients (patients under
      the age of 18), even for its approved uses.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete Response (CR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary endpoint for this clinical study is the proportion of complete response, CR (that is, the percent of patients with skin, liver, and GI GVHD - all stage 0) at day 28 of study treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Non-Relapse Mortality (NRM)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Cumulative incidence of Non-Relapse Mortality (NRM)at 6 months and 1 year</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>incidence of treatment-refractory GVHD</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Cumulative incidence of treatment-refractory GVHD (defined as absence of CR or PR on day 28 of treatment or who receive additional immunosuppression prior to day 28)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to discontinuation of steroid therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of additional GVHD therapies</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of additional GVHD therapies (defined as the initiation of a new acute GVHD therapy, regardless of duration)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of serious infections</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of serious infections (defined as grade 3 by the Blood and Marrow Transplant Clinical Trials Network)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate (CR + PR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall response rate (CR + PR) at day 28. Partial Response (PR) is defined as improvement in one  or more organs involved with GVHD symptoms without progression in others. For a response to be scored as PR on day 28, the patient must be in PR on day 28 and have had no intervening non-study therapy for acute GVHD.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Graft Versus Host Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Natalizumab with  steroids</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>For subjects whose GVHD assay is Ann Arbor Grade 3, the study treatment will consist of two drugs, prednisone (or methylprednisolone) which is the  standard treatment for acute GVHD and natalizumab, the experimental drug under study.
The standard therapy regimen will be initially, prednisone 2mg/kg/d (or methyl-prednisolone IV equivalent) and the experimental therapy regimen will be natalizumab 300mg (or 4.3 mg/kg for subjects &lt;18y or &lt;50kg) on days 0 and 14.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>natalizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Protocol treatment must start within 3 days of the subject's diagnosis of acute GVHD.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Natalizumab with  steroids</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tysabri</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>steroids</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard therapy, day 0 to 5, then tapered according to clinical criteria</description>
    <arm_group_label>Natalizumab with  steroids</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Prednisone (or methylprednisolone equivalent IV)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  New onset high risk acute GVHD (Ann Arbor grade 3 as defined in Appendix C of the
             protocol) following allogeneic bone marrow transplantation. Any clinical severity
             (Glucksberg grade I-IV) is eligible.

          -  Any donor type (e.g., related, unrelated) or stem cell source (bone marrow,
             peripheral blood, cord blood). Recipients of non-myeloablative and myeloablative
             transplants are eligible.

          -  No prior systemic treatment for acute GVHD except for a maximum of 72 hours of
             prednisone ≤2 mg/kg/day (or IV methylprednisolone equivalent). Topical skin steroid
             treatment is permissible. Non-absorbable oral steroid treatment for GI GVHD is
             prohibited.

          -  Age 12 years or older.

          -  If the patient is a woman of child-bearing potential, the patient and their sexual
             partner must agree to practice effective contraception.

          -  Written informed consent from patient, parent, or guardian.

          -  Written assent from patients age 12 to 17 years.

          -  Biopsy of acute GVHD target organ is strongly recommended, but not required.
             Enrollment should not be delayed for biopsy or pathology results. Patients who do not
             enroll within 72 hours of new onset acute GVHD are not permitted to participate.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Progressive or relapsed malignancy

          -  Uncontrolled active infection

          -  Patients with chronic GVHD

          -  Known seropositivity for JC virus

          -  History of Progressive Multifocal Leukoencephalopathy (PML)

          -  Known hypersensitivity to natalizumab

          -  Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women

          -  Use of other drugs for the treatment of acute GVHD

          -  Patients on dialysis

          -  Patients requiring ventilator support

          -  Investigational agent within 30 days of enrollment without approval from the
             Sponsor-Investigator
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John E Levine, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>John E Levine, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(734) 936-8456</phone>
    <email>jelevine@med.umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>James Ferrara, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(734) 615-1340</phone>
    <email>ferrara@med.umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John E Levine, MD</last_name>
      <phone>734-936-8456</phone>
      <email>jelevine@med.umich.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>James Ferrara, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(734) 615-1340</phone>
      <email>ferrara@med.umich.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John E Levine, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James Ferrara, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Thomas Braun, Ph.D</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mark Litzow, MD</last_name>
      <phone>507-284-5362</phone>
      <email>litzow.mark@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark Litzow, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven Devine, MD</last_name>
      <phone>614-293-5655</phone>
      <email>steven.devine@osumc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steven Devine, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania, Abramson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Porter, MD</last_name>
      <phone>215-662-2862</phone>
      <email>david.porter@uphs.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Porter, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 6, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan Cancer Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>John Levine, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Pediatrics and Communicable Diseases</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Graft vs Host Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Graft vs Host Reaction</keyword>
  <keyword>allogeneic bone marrow transplantation/adverse effects</keyword>
  <keyword>allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation/adverse effects</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Graft vs Host Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone Hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone phosphate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
