<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="13199">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01798407</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GCO 12-1815</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HSM#12-00467</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01798407</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pilot Study of Deep Brain Stimulation to the Lateral Habenulae in Treatment-Resistant Depression</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Clinical Pilot Study Examining Bilateral Inhibition of the Lateral Habenula as a Target for Deep Brain Stimulation in Intractable Depression</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wayne Goodman</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research study will investigate the safety, tolerability, and benefit of bilateral deep
      brain stimulation (DBS) to the lateral habenula for patients with treatment-resistant major
      depressive disorder (TRD). Six adult patients with TRD will be treated in this single-site
      study at Mount Sinai Medical Center; patients will be chronically symptomatic with
      significant functional disability, and will have demonstrated resistance to standard somatic
      and pharmacotherapeutic treatments. The primary outcome measure will be the change in the
      17-item Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (HDRS17) six months after the commencement of
      stimulation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This research study includes the following parts: 1. medical and psychiatric evaluation, 2.
      implantation of the brain stimulation system, and 3. follow up including programming and
      psychiatric testing after the implantation

        1. Medical and psychiatric evaluation:

           During this part of the study, the investigator will ask detailed questions about the
           patient's psychiatric and medical history, and will ask for a list of medications along
           with response to previous treatments. As part of the medical evaluation, the patient
           will be asked to give a sample of both blood and urine for standard lab evaluation. All
           patients will be tested for the presence of drugs of abuse in their urine. All women of
           child bearing potential will also be tested for pregnancy. If any of the test results
           are positive, the patient cannot continue to be part of this study, but can receive
           other clinical care by a treating psychiatrist.

        2. Implantation of the brain stimulation system:

      Description of the Medical Devices

      The brain stimulation system is implanted inside the patient's body.  The implanted system
      is made up of three major parts:

        -  The lead is made of four insulated wires with four electrodes at the end.

        -  The extension connects the lead to the neurostimulator (power source).

        -  The neurostimulator (battery) is the power source of the system.

      The neurostimulator is a metal &quot;can&quot;, which depending on the model the patient receives,
      will be in the range of about 2 or 3 inches in diameter and about ½ inch thick.  It contains
      a small battery and produces the electrical impulses needed for stimulation.  For this study
      a rechargeable battery will be used.  Although battery life varies for each patient
      depending on the type and intensity of stimulation needed for good symptom relief, the use
      of a rechargeable battery will extend the time before it must be replaced.

      Patients will have two neurostimulators implanted,. The surgeon may place the
      neurostimulators either near the collarbones, within the abdomen, or both as needed to allow
      for the proper distance between the neurostimulators.

      Patients will be admitted to the hospital either the night before or the morning of the
      surgery. The day of surgery, the following steps may occur:

        1. A metal frame will be attached to the head.  The frame is a special instrument that
           allows the surgeon to find the correct path to the target site in the brain. Local
           anesthetic will be given so that the pins, which hold the frame to the head, do not
           hurt.

        2. Pictures of the brain will be taken using MRI (magnetic resonance imaging) and/or
           computer-aided tomography (CAT) scans.  This will allow the surgeon to determine the
           area in the brain where the leads will be placed.

        3. The patient will then go to the operating room where two small holes will be drilled in
           the skull, one for each lead to be implanted.  The patient will receive local
           anesthesia before this procedure.

        4. The lead is then passed into the brain to the desired site.

        5. A cap will be placed over the hole in the skull. The cap also holds the lead in
           position.

        6. The metal frame is then removed from the patient's head.  If the extension and the
           neurostimulator are not implanted right away, patients will typically be allowed to go
           home in approximately 24-48 hours.  The study doctor will decide the length of the
           patient's hospital stay.

        7. The extensions and neurostimulator may be placed one to two weeks after the leads are
           implanted. If so, this is an outpatient procedure that is performed under general
           anesthesia (ie patient is asleep). Patients will be discharged home on the same day
           once it is determined that they are in stable condition.

      3) Follow-up programming and psychiatric assessments The study physician will want to see
      patients for follow up after surgery.  Follow up visits are scheduled after patients are
      implanted. During these visits, the study physicians or other clinicians will assess the
      patient's condition using various standardized questionnaires.

      Frequent, non-invasive adjustment to the stimulation parameters may be required to achieve
      optimal symptom response.  This adjustment period may take weeks or months.

      4) Duration of treatment The optimization period generally lasts 6 months, after which
      modulation appointments are scheduled monthly or on an as needed basis. If a patient
      responds to the treatment, treatment may be temporarily discontinued between months 12 and
      18 to find out if the response is because of the treatment.  The patient will not be told
      when this discontinuation occurs and they will be carefully monitored during this time. If
      symptoms worsen, the patient will be informed if treatment has been discontinued, and they
      will have the option to have treatment restarted. If the patient continues to do well
      without stimulation, they may be offered the opportunity to continue without stimulation,
      consider removing the device, or to restart stimulation.

      Because the battery life is approximately 7-9 years, every 7-9 years batteries will need to
      be replaced. This requires patients to undergo a brief surgery to have the neurostimulator
      replaced - the neurostimulator contains a small rechargeable battery and produces the
      electrical impulses needed for stimulation. When the battery can no longer be recharged, the
      neurostimulator must be replaced. Once a patient has exited the study, their insurance may
      not pay for device replacements or other medical care related to the device.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in HDRS17 score from baseline to 6 months after the commencement of stimulation</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>'Response' is categorically defined as a ≥ 50% reduction in the HDRS17 score relative to the baseline assessment.  'Remission' is defined as an absolute HDRS17 score &lt; 8.  Study success criteria will be defined as ≥ 3 of the 6 patients meeting the individual subject success criteria of response or remission by HDRS17 score at the 6 month time point.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression severity rating</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>including the Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression (HDRS17), the Quick Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology (QIDS-SR), the 30 item Inventory of Score comprised of Depressive Symptomatology (IDS-C, and the Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS)], Clinical Global Impression of Severity and Improvement (CGI), the Quality of Life Assessment (SF-36), the Hamilton Anxiety Scale (HAM-A), Profile of Mood States (POMS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Young Mania Rating Scale (YMRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Young Mania Rating Scale (YMRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Young Mania Rating Scale (YMRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropsychological Battery</measure>
    <time_frame>at 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropsychological Battery</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropsychological Battery</measure>
    <time_frame>at 18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Treatment Resistant Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Medtronic Activa Tremor Control System</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Deep brain stimulation is regularly used to treat Parkinson's Disease and movement disorders though recently there has been renewed interest in a psychosurgical approach using deep brain stimulation in treatment of severely treatment resistant depressive patients. (Goodwin and Insel, 2009)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Medtronic Activa Tremor Control System</intervention_name>
    <description>DBS system consists of the Activa RC 37612 System (Implantable Pulse Generator with Model 37085 Extensions, Activa Patient Programmer, and Medtronic Model 3389 DBS Lead).  This system is commercially approved for the treatment of chronic, intractable Parkinson's Disease.  It will be used with the Model SP-10344 Memory Mod Software which enables the physician to program the Implantable Pulse Generator to a higher frequency.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Medtronic Activa Tremor Control System</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Deep Brain Stimulation System</other_name>
    <other_name>DBS</other_name>
    <other_name>Activa RC System</other_name>
    <other_name>Medtronic DBS Lead</other_name>
    <other_name>Activa Patient Programmer</other_name>
    <other_name>N'Vision Clinical Programmer</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men and women (non-pregnant) between ages 21 and 70

          -  DSM-IV diagnosis ( assessed by Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV Axis I
             disorders, SCID-I) of unipolar major depressive disorder (MDD), non-psychotic, single
             or recurrent episode, with first episode before age 45

          -  Chronic illness with current episode ≥ 24 months duration and/or recurrent illness
             with at least a total of 4 lifetime episodes (including current episode ≥ 12 months)

          -  Treatment Resistance (defined by criteria on the Antidepressant Treatment History
             Form): Failure (i.e.,  persistence of the major depressive episode) to respond to a
             minimum of three adequate depression treatments from at least two different treatment
             categories (e.g., SSRI's, TCA's, other antidepressants, lithium-addition,
             irreversible MAO-inhibitor, antidepressant augmentation with an atypical
             antipsychotic medication)

          -  Previous trial of ECT (lifetime)

          -  Symptom severity: HDRS17 ≥ 21

          -  The Hamilton Depression score must remain greater than 20 on two separate assessments
             (at initial screening and 1 week before surgery), over a 1-month period

          -  Normal brain MRI within 3 months of surgery

          -  Stable antidepressant medical regimen for the month preceding surgery

          -  Modified Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) score ≥ 27

          -  Normal thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH) level within 12 months of study entry

          -  Other medical conditions must be stable for at least 1 year

          -  Anticipates a stable psychotropic medication regiment in the next 24 months

          -  Patient must be able to identify a family member, physician, or friend who will
             participate in the Treatment Contract

          -  Able and willing to give informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Axis I disorders (assessed by Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV Axis I
             disorders, SCID-I): Bipolar I or II disorder; Bipolar NOS; any lifetime history of
             psychotic disorder (e.g., schizophrenia, schizoaffective disorder, or non-affective
             psychosis); presence of primary or serious (requiring additional treatment)
             disorders: comorbid obsessive compulsive disorder, post-traumatic stress disorder,
             panic disorder, bulimia or anorexia, in the last year

          -  Cluster A or B personality disorder

          -  Alcohol or substance abuse/dependence within 6 months, excluding nicotine

          -  Current substantial suicidal risk as defined by a plan or clear immediate intent for
             self-harm, or had a serious suicide attempt within the last year

          -  Neurological disease that impairs motor, sensory or cognitive function or that
             requires intermittent or chronic medication (e.g., Parkinson's disease, MS, stroke)

          -  Any history of seizure disorder or hemorrhagic stroke

          -  Any medical contraindication to surgery, including infection or coagulopathy

          -  Participation in another drug, device, or biological trial within 30 days

          -  Current implanted stimulation devices including cardiac pacemakers, defibrillators,
             and neurostimulators including spinal cord stimulators, deep brain stimulators, and
             vagus nerve stimulators

          -  Does not have adequate family/friend support as determined by psychological screening
             and/or interview

          -  Abnormal brain MRI

          -  Unable to maintain a stable psychotropic medication regiment in the next 24 months

          -  Pregnant or has plans to become pregnant in the next 24 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wayne K Goodman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Wayne K Goodman, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(212) 659-8860</phone>
    <email>wayne.goodman@mssm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kyle Lapidus, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(212) 659-8804</phone>
    <email>kyle.lapidus@mssm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Wayne K Goodman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-659-8860</phone>
      <email>wayne.goodman@mssm.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kyle Lapidus, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(917) 969-3445</phone>
      <email>kyle.lapidus@mssm.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Wayne K Goodman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Fritz Henn, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Brian Kopell, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kyle Lapidus, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dan Iosifescu, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James Murrough, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 26, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 21, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Wayne Goodman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor and Chair of Psychiatry</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Deep Brain Stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Major Depressive Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Lateral Habenula</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
