<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="157928">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01711593</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012P0001076</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1U19AI095261-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01711593</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Induced Tolerogenic Dendritic Cells as Modulators of Allergic Asthma</brief_title>
  <acronym>MGH-002</acronym>
  <official_title>Induced Tolerogenic Dendritic Cells as Modulators of Allergic Asthma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Andrew D. Luster, M.D.,Ph.D.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Despite advances in medications, allergic diseases, including allergic asthma continue to
      rise in prevalence.  For this reason, there is a need for a better understanding of the
      mechanisms of allergic diseases and novel insights into modulating allergic inflammation.
      The investigators hypothesize that much remains to be learned about the behavior of T
      effector and T regulatory cells in allergic disease.  Furthermore, the investigators
      hypothesize that novel mechanisms of allergic tolerance may exist, and elucidation of these
      mechanisms may provide insights into novel therapeutic strategies to control allergic
      diseases.  The investigators will investigate the capacity for T cell tolerance induction in
      allergic subjects by a novel type of immune tolerizing dendritic cell (it-DC).  The
      investigators will assess whether in vitro generated it-DCs have the capacity to induce
      antigen-specific T regulatory cells and suppress allergen-specific T effector cell function
      in vitro.

      Standardized Cat Allergen extract and Dust Mite Allergens will be used to generate changes
      in the airways that occur during exposure to allergen.  For this investigation, the route of
      administration will be topical application of the titrated allergen to a bronchoscopically
      isolated subsegment of one lobe of one lung.  The dose of biologic will be determined from
      prior skin-prick testing.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-center, open-label, controlled mechanistic study before-and-after allergen
      instillation study that uses each subject as his/her own control.  Reliability of study
      measurements of expression is accomplished by comparing repeated measurements.  Additional
      controls are provided by measuring the expression of markers known to have stable
      expression, including cell structural proteins and chemokine markers that the investigators
      know are induced in this experimental paradigm from our previous studies.  This is an
      investigational study.  Subjects will receive an investigational product, either
      Standardized Cat Allergen Extract or Standardized Dust Mite Allergen (Dermatophagoides
      farinae or D. pteronyssinus).   No subject will be given a placebo.  There are 2 cohorts,
      allergic asthmatics (AA) and healthy controls (HC).  The main comparisons will be
      measurement of primary and secondary outcome measures in: (1) diluent versus
      allergen-challenged segments of the lung in each asthmatic subject and (2) comparison of
      these responses in allergic asthmatics (AA) and healthy controls (HC).

      The investigators will enroll 10 AA subjects and 5 HC subjects.  There will be no
      randomization.  The choice of allergen will be determined by allergy skin testing.  When a
      subject is allergic to both cat and dust mite, one will be selected with a goal of having a
      representative sample of cat and dust mite challenges in each cohort. The 10 allergic
      asthmatic (AA) subjects will undergo SAC with either standardized cat or mite allergen.
      These subjects will also donate 200 ml of blood on two occasions separated by a minimum of 8
      weeks and not more than 12 weeks.   The HC subjects will undergo preliminary screening tests
      and provide 200 ml of blood for DC and T cell studies on two occasions separated by a
      minimum of 8 weeks and not more than 12 weeks.  The HC subjects will not undergo
      bronchoscopy, bronchoalveolar lavage, or segmental allergen challenge.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of it-DC on the phenotype, function, proliferation and survival of allergen-specific effector T cells.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will generate induced tolerogenic dendritic cells (it-DCs) in vitro from peripheral blood monocytes and dendritic cells isolated from each allergic asthmatic subject and assess their capacity to (a) attenuate effector CD4+ T cell (Teff) responses and/or (b) induce T regulatory (Treg) cells from Teff cells as well as CD4+ naïve and memory T cells. Attenuation of T cell responses (a) will be assessed by proliferation assays and cytokine production. Moreover, in order to evaluate the functionality of the it-DC induced Tregs (b), co-culture suppression assays using cat or house dust-mite allergen-specific Teff cells isolated from BAL following segmental allergen challenge (SAC) as responder cells, will be examined. The percent suppression of responding Teff cells will be assessed by examining Teff cell proliferation and survival/apoptosis, and by cytokine production.
(Note: SAC samples from healthy controls are not involved in the primary analysis.)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent distribution of peripheral blood DC subsets</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will determine the frequency of each peripheral blood DC subset from allergic asthmatic subjects at 0 and 8 weeks using cell surface staining/flow cytometry analysis. Results will be expressed in terms of percent distribution of each DC subset within the total DC pool.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent suppression of naïve T cells (Tn) and memory T cells (Tmem) proliferation by it-DC-induced Tregs from each subject.</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The ability of it-DC-induced Tregs from each allergic asthmatic to suppress proliferation of autologous CD4+ Tn and Tmem cells in response to anti-CD3 will be assessed and expressed as a percent suppression of proliferation using an in vitro proliferation assay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences in proliferation by allergen-specific Teff cells from BAL and blood.</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will measure the proliferative responses in it-DC co-culture assays by allergen-specific CD4+ Teff cells obtained from the BAL of allergic asthmatic subjects as compared to those of blood-derived CD4+ Tmem cells from the same subjects and from 5 healthy controls.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <condition>Allergies</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Allergic Asthmatic, Non-allergic non-asthmatics(HC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Adult subjects who are allergic asthmatics will receive segmental allergen challenge to the lung and have their blood drawn at 2 time points.  Adult subjects who are non-allergic non-asthmatics(Healthy Controls) will not receive segmental allergen challenge to the lung but will have their blood drawn at 2 time points.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bronchoscopy, Segmental Allergen Challenge and Bronchoalveolar Lavage</intervention_name>
    <description>On the day of the first bronchoscopy, BAL will first be performed in the lingual without instillation of diluent or allergen.Then, a 2-ml aliquot of isotonic diluent is instilled into the right upper lobe.Then, the procedure will be repeated in the right middle lobe with instillation of 2-ml of standardized cat or mite allergen solution.A&quot;test dose&quot;concentration of allergen is administered first consisting of 2 ml of allergen at 1/10th the threshold concentration.If on visual inspection through the bronchoscope there is no evidence of mucosal inflammation, a second segmental allergen challenge will be done in the right middle lobe using 2-ml of full-dose allergen at the threshold concentration.  This dose will be predetermined by quantitative skin prick testing.A second bronchoscopy is performed 24 hours after delivery of allergen extract and diluent to obtain BAL fluid from the RUL and RML.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Allergic Asthmatic, Non-allergic non-asthmatics(HC)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>One of 3 Standardized allergen extracts will be used:</other_name>
    <other_name>1)Cat hair allergen extract</other_name>
    <other_name>2)Mite Dermatophagoides farinae</other_name>
    <other_name>3)Mite Dermatophagoides pteronyssinus</other_name>
    <other_name>Phenolized saline diluent will also be used in this study.</other_name>
    <other_name>All will be purchased from Greer Laboratories Lenoir,NC.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Phlebotomy</intervention_name>
    <description>200 (40 teaspoons) ml of blood will be obtained from the subjects to collect different leukocyte populations. A second 200 ml of blood will be obtained from the subjects 8 weeks later for isolation of T lymphocytes for functional studies.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Allergic Asthmatic, Non-allergic non-asthmatics(HC)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Blood Draw</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bronchoscopy, Segmental Allergen Challenge and Bronchoalveolar Lavage</intervention_name>
    <description>On the day of the first bronchoscopy, BAL will first be performed in the lingual without instillation of diluent or allergen.Then, a 2-ml aliquot of isotonic diluent is instilled into the right upper lobe.Then, the procedure will be repeated in the right middle lobe with instillation of 2-ml of standardized cat or mite allergen solution.A&quot;test dose&quot;concentration of allergen is administered first consisting of 2 ml of allergen at 1/10th the threshold concentration.If on visual inspection through the bronchoscope there is no evidence of mucosal inflammation, a second segmental allergen challenge will be done in the right middle lobe using 2-ml of full-dose allergen at the threshold concentration. This dose will be predetermined by quantitative skin prick testing.A second bronchoscopy is performed 24 hours after delivery of allergen extract and diluent to obtain BAL fluid from the RUL and RML.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Allergic Asthmatic, Non-allergic non-asthmatics(HC)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>One of 3 Standardized allergen extracts will be used:</other_name>
    <other_name>1)Cat hair allergen extract</other_name>
    <other_name>2)Mite Dermatophagoides farinae</other_name>
    <other_name>3)Mite Dermatophagoides pteronyssinus</other_name>
    <other_name>Phenolized saline diluent will also be used in this study.</other_name>
    <other_name>All will be purchased from Greer Laboratories Lenoir,NC.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Subjects with Allergic Asthma (AA subjects):

          1. All subjects will have a baseline FEV1 no less than 75 % of the predicted value.

          2. All subjects will have both a clinical history of allergic symptoms to cat or dust
             mite allergen and a positive allergen prick test (3 mm diameter greater than diluent
             control)

          3. Life-long absence of cigarette smoking (lifetime total of &lt; 5 pack-years and none in
             5 years).

          4. Willing and able to give informed consent.

          5. Expressed the desire to participate in an interview with the principal investigator.

          6. Age between 18 and 50 years.

          7. A methacholine PC20 &lt; 16 mg/ml.

          8. Asthma of severity defined as: requiring no more than step 3 therapy (NHLBI
             Guidelines, 2007), well-controlled and having a validated asthma control test (ACT)
             score of &gt; 19 for one month prior to the screening visit, and able to tolerate a 2
             week stoppage of inhaled corticosteroids prior to Visit 2.

        Healthy Control Subjects (HC subjects):

        Normal control subjects will be individuals who are in good overall health, age and sex
        matched to the asthmatic group, age 18 - 50 and nonallergic, i.e. entirely negative on the
        panel of prick skin tests with no history of allergic rhinitis or asthma, no history of
        allergic symptoms caused by cats or dust mite allergen exposure, life-long nonsmokers of
        cigarettes (defined as a lifetime total of less than 5 pack-years and none in 5 years),
        normal spirometry (i.e. FEV1 and FVC of at least 90% of predicted) and with a methacholine
        PC20 of &gt; 16 mg/ml.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects with Allergic Asthma (AA subjects):

          1. Women of childbearing potential who are pregnant (based on urine beta-HCG testing),
             are sexually active and not using contraception, are seeking to become pregnant, or
             who are nursing.

          2. The presence of spontaneous asthmatic episode or clinical evidence of upper
             respiratory tract infection within the previous 6 weeks.

          3. Participation in a research study involving a drug or biologic during the 30 days
             prior to the study.

          4. Intolerance to albuterol, atropine, lidocaine, fentanyl, or midazolam.

          5. Antihistamines within 7 days of the screening visit.

          6. Presence of diabetes mellitus, congestive heart failure, ventricular arrhythmias,
             history of a cerebrovascular accident, renal failure, history of anaphylaxis, or
             cirrhosis.

          7. Use of systemic steroids, increased use of inhaled steroids, beta blockers and MAO
             inhibitors or a visit for an asthma exacerbation within 1 month of the screening
             visit.

          8. Antibiotic use for respiratory disease within 1 month of the characterization visit
             or a respiratory tract infection within 6 weeks of the bronchoscopy visits.

          9. A history of asthma-related respiratory failure requiring intubation.

         10. Quantitative skin-prick test positive reaction down to an allergen concentration of
             0.056 BAU or AU/ml.

         11. Subjects with a high possibility of poor compliance with the study.

         12. Have a history of cigarette smoking within the past 5 years or &gt; 5 pack years total.

         13. Have indoor animal or second-hand cigarette smoke exposure

         14. Other lung diseases, such as sarcoidosis, bronchiectasis or active lung infection.

         15. Use of Xolair (omalizumab - anti-IgE monoclonal antibody) for 6 months.

         16. Immunotherapy with cat or dust mite extract now or in the   past.

         17. Use of prophylactic aspirin for cardiovascular disease

        Healthy Normal Control Subjects (NC subjects):

          1. A history of allergy, asthma, nasal or sinus disease.

          2. Exclusion criteria #1, 3-8 and 10-17from (A.) above.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrew D Luster, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 22, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 28, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Andrew D. Luster, M.D.,Ph.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief, Division of Rheumatology, Allergy, and Immunology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Asthma</keyword>
  <keyword>Allergic</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>Airway</keyword>
  <keyword>Challenge</keyword>
  <keyword>Chemokines</keyword>
  <keyword>Tolerization</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
