<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="70585">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02023541</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201310084</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02023541</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Esophageal Quality of Life (QoL)</brief_title>
  <acronym>QoL</acronym>
  <official_title>Prospective Quality of Life and Toxicity Associated With Proton Beam Therapy in the Treatment of Esophageal Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Assess patient-reported outcomes of proton beam therapy (PBT) for esophageal cancer at 6
      months following chemoradiation and physician-reported toxicity of PBT for esophageal
      cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case Control, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient-reported outcomes of proton beam therapy (PBT) for esophageal cancer at 6 months following chemoradiation
We will calculate descriptive statistics (mean, standard deviation, etc.) for all QOL data (EQ-5D, SF-12) in addition to other PROs (depressive symptoms, social support) at each evaluation period.  Univariate tests will explore the associations among QOL and PROs using analysis of variance (ANOVA) and Fisher's exact test for correlation.  Changes over time in QOL and PROs will be analyzed utilizing repeated-measures modeling techniques (repeated measures analysis of covariance).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>We will compare the proportion of ≥Grade 3 gastrointestinal or pulmonary toxicity events against historical controls utilizing Binomial tests for proportion.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-reported outcomes of PBT for esophageal cancer at 12 months following chemoradiation.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will calculate descriptive statistics (mean, standard deviation, etc.) for all QOL data (EQ-5D, SF-12) in addition to other PROs (depressive symptoms, social support) at each evaluation period. Univariate tests will explore the associations among QOL and PROs using analysis of variance (ANOVA) and Fisher's exact test for correlation. Changes over time in QOL and PROs will be analyzed utilizing repeated-measures modeling techniques (repeated measures analysis of covariance).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assess progression-free survival (PFS) of PBT for patients with resectable vs. unresectable esophageal cancer.
PFS and OS will be assessed using the Kaplan-Meier estimate. A. Definitive chemoradiation - We are currently completing an internal Phase II trial that used intensity-modulated radiation therapy (IMRT) to a dose of 60 Gy with concurrent chemotherapy.  The 2-year PFS and overall survival rates (OS) from that experience are 25% (95% CI of 11 - 62%) and 36% (95% CI of   7 - 49%), respectively. These results are consistent with the literature.
B. Neoadjuvant chemoradiation followed by esophagectomy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Esophageal Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Adenocarcinoma Of Esophagus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>resected</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>unresected</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients diagnosed with esophageal cancer and are scheudled to be treated wtih
        chemoradiation using proton beam therapy
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically documented adenocarcinoma or squamous cell carcinoma of the cervical
             or thoracic esophagus or gastroesophageal junction or cardia of stomach.

          -  Staged by PET/CT and esophagogastroduodenoscopy (EGD) OR CT w/contrast and EGD to
             have stage II or III disease.  Endoscopic ultrasound (EUS) is encouraged but not
             required.

          -  Prior endoscopic mucosal resection (EMR) with a diagnosis of stage II or III
             esophageal cancer is eligible, irrespective of margin status.

          -  Induction chemotherapy prior to concurrent chemoradiation is allowed.

          -  Prior thoracic radiation is allowable if degree of overlap with the esophageal
             radiotherapy treatment is deemed to be safe by the treating radiation oncologist.

          -  At least 18 years of age.

          -  ECOG performance status ≤ 2 (Karnofsky &gt; 60%)

          -  Normal bone marrow and organ function as defined below:

               -  WBC &gt; 2,500/mcL

               -  Platelets ≥ 75,000/mcl

               -  Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x IULN

               -  AST(SGOT)/ALT(SGPT) ≤ 3.0 x IULN

               -  Creatinine ≤1.5 x IULN OR creatinine clearance ≥ 50 mL/min/1.73 m2 for patients
                  with creatinine levels above institutional normal

          -  Women of childbearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
             (hormonal or barrier method of birth control, abstinence) prior to study entry and
             for the duration of study participation.  Should a woman become pregnant or suspect
             she is pregnant while participating in this study, she must inform her treating
             physician immediately.

          -  Ability to understand and willingness to sign an IRB approved written informed
             consent document.

          -  English speaker.

          -  Financial coverage for proton therapy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Planned treatment with radiation therapy alone without concurrent chemotherapy or
             chemotherapy alone.

          -  Previous or concomitant cancers within the past 3 years other than curatively treated
             carcinoma in situ of the cervix, basal cell carcinoma of the skin, curative treatment
             for transitional cell carcinoma of the bladder, and low risk prostate cancer.  Except
             for prostate cancer (which can be observed if low risk), other cancers listed must
             have been treated in the past 3 years without evidence of recurrence at the time of
             registration.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia not controlled by pacer device, myocardial infarction within 3 months of
             registration, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance
             with study requirements

          -  Pregnant and/or breastfeeding.  Patient must have a negative pregnancy test within 7
             days of study entry.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeffrey Bradley, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jeffrey Bradley, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>314-362-8610</phone>
    <email>jbradley@wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jeffrey Bradley, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>314-362-8610</phone>
      <email>jbradley@wustl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cliff Robinson, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Todd DeWees, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eric Klein, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tianyu Zhao, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>A. Craig Lockhart, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bryan Meyers, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Beth Bottani, CMD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Donna Jeffe, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maria Perez, M.A.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.siteman.wustl.edu</url>
    <description>Alvin J. Siteman Cancer Center at Barnes-Jewish Hospital and Washington University School of Medicine</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 23, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
