<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="164723">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01774097</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CCTRN 581</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>UM1HL087318-06</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01774097</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Patients With Intermittent Claudication Injected With ALDH Bright Cells</brief_title>
  <acronym>PACE</acronym>
  <official_title>Clinical and MR Imaging Assessments in Patients With Intermittent Claudication Following Injection of Bone Marrow Derived ALDH Bright Cells</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aldagen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Center for Cell and Gene Therapy, Baylor College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Data and Safety Monitoring Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to find out if aldehyde dehydrogenase bright (ALDHbr) cells
      taken from a patient's bone marrow can be placed safely, via intramuscular injections, into
      their affected calf and lower thigh muscles and improve blood flow and/or peak walking time
      in patients experiencing pain associated with blocked blood vessels in the leg.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Peripheral Artery Disease (PAD) occurs when arteries in the arms and legs (most often the
      legs) become narrowed by plaque. Because of this plaque, patients with PAD are also at
      increased risk for heart attacks and strokes.  Those with PAD often have intermittent
      claudication (blockage of blood vessels in the leg). This blockage decreases blood flow to
      the leg muscles, which can cause pain in one or both legs during exercise (such as during
      walking).  Intermittent means the pain comes and goes.  Because PAD interferes with
      circulation, worsening of this condition can increase pain in the leg; sometimes even during
      periods of rest.

      Bone marrow contains special stem cells that may promote blood vessel growth, prevent cell
      death, and transform themselves into a number of tissues including new muscle. There is a
      small subpopulation of bone marrow mononuclear cells, called aldehyde dehydrogenase-bright
      (ALDHbr) cells, that is highly enriched in these types of stem cells.  The enzyme in ALDHbr
      cells responds to damage signals and may play an important role in tissue repair.

      In this study we investigate the safety and efficacy of bone marrow derived stem cells with
      particular characteristics in PAD patients with intermittent claudication and explore new
      end-points to evaluate therapeutic effects using novel MRI imaging modalities as well as
      traditional endpoints.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak Walking Time (PWT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The placebo adjusted average change over time in the maximum time (in seconds) walked by a patient on a treadmill under standardized conditions. The patient continues the test until walking can no longer be tolerated because of claudication symptoms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Leg collateral artery anatomy (via contrast enhanced-MR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The placebo adjusted average change in the number of patent vessels over time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vascular Flow (Phase Contrast MRA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The placebo adjusted average change in peak flow (mL/s) over time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perfusion (Cuff-induced Ischemia using Perfusion MR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The placebo adjusted average change in hyperemic fractional microvascular blood plasma volume over time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pre-exercise Ankle-Brachial Index (ABI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The placebo adjusted average change over time in arm and pedal blood pressure will be obtained routinely with the patient supine immediately prior to the treadmill test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pre-exercise Ankle-Brachial Index (ABI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The placebo adjusted average change over time in arm and pedal blood pressure will be obtained routinely with the patient supine immediately prior to the treadmill test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-exercise Ankle-Brachial Index (ABI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The placebo adjusted average change over time in arm and pedal blood pressure will be obtained routinely with the patient supine immediately following the treadmill test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-exercise Ankle-Brachial Index (ABI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The placebo adjusted average change over time in arm and pedal blood pressure will be obtained routinely with the patient supine immediately following the treadmill test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Claudication Onset Time (COT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The placebo adjusted average change over time (in seconds) in the time walked by a patient on a treadmill under standardized conditions before the onset of claudication symptoms, regardless of whether this is manifested or characterized as muscle pain, ache, cramp, numbness or fatigue. This does not include joint pain or other pain not associated with claudication.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Claudication Onset Time (COT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The placebo adjusted average change over time (in seconds) in the time walked by a patient on a treadmill under standardized conditions before the onset of claudication symptoms, regardless of whether this is manifested or characterized as muscle pain, ache, cramp, numbness or fatigue. This does not include joint pain or other pain not associated with claudication.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak Walking Time (PWT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The placebo adjusted average change in maximum time (in seconds) walked by a patient on a treadmill under standardized conditions. The patient continues the test until walking can no longer be tolerated because of claudication symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between PWT and leg collateral artery anatomy</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Quantitate the relationship between the placebo adjusted change over time in PWT and the change over time in leg collateral artery anatomy using the general linear model.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between PWT and Vascular Flow</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Quantitate the relationship between the placebo adjusted change over time in PWT and the change over time in vascular flow using the general linear model.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between PWT and Perfusion</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Quantitate the relationship between the placebo adjusted change over time in PWT and the change over time in perfusion using the general linear model.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Walking Impairment Questionnaire (WIQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 1 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The placebo adjusted average change in WIQ score over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peripheral Artery Questionnaire (PAQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 1 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The placebo adjusted average change in PAQ score over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Walking Impairment Questionnaire (WIQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The placebo adjusted average change in WIQ score assessed over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peripheral Artery Questionnaire (PAQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The placebo adjusted average change in PAQ score over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Walking Impairment Questionnaire (WIQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The placebo adjusted average change in WIQ score over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peripheral Artery Questionnaire (PAQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The placebo adjusted average change in PAQ score over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Peripheral Artery Disease</condition>
  <condition>Intermittent Claudication</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ALD-301</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive ALD-301 via intramuscular injection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo (vehicle)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive placebo (vehicle)via intramuscular injection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ALD-301</intervention_name>
    <description>Ten 1ml injections of ALD-301 in the index calf and posterior, lower thigh</description>
    <arm_group_label>ALD-301</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ALDH Bright Cells</other_name>
    <other_name>ALDHbr</other_name>
    <other_name>Aldehyde dehydrogenase-bright cells</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo (vehicle)</intervention_name>
    <description>Ten 1ml injections of placebo in the index calf and posterior, lower thigh</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo (vehicle)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
    <other_name>Vehicle</other_name>
    <other_name>HSA</other_name>
    <other_name>Human Serum Albumin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with atherosclerotic peripheral artery disease with classic claudication
             (exercise-induced pain, cramps, fatigue, or other equivalent discomfort involving
             large muscle groups of the leg(s) that is consistently relieved by rest) or atypical
             leg pain  (exertional leg pain that does not begin at rest or does not resolve
             consistently with rest) as defined by the San Diego Claudication Questionnaire.

          2. Age ≥40 years

          3. Resting ankle-brachial index &lt;0.90 or a resting toe-brachial index of &lt;0.70 at
             baseline testing

          4. Presence of significant stenosis or occlusion of infrainguinal arteries including the
             superficial femoral artery, popliteal artery and/or infrapopliteal arteries as
             determined by: Duplex ultrasound imaging (occlusion or focal doubling of peak
             systolic velocity of one or more affected segments) OR lower extremity computed
             Tomography Angiography (CTA) OR lower extremity magnetic resonance angiography (MRA)
             OR lower extremity catheter-based contrast arteriography.  Each of these noninvasive
             and invasive anatomic assessments will identify patients with at least a 50% stenosis
             in the affected segment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Presence of any musculoskeletal disease, cardiac or pulmonary disease, or
             neurological disease that limits the patient's ability to walk to fulfill protocol
             requirements (claudication must be the consistent primary exercise limitation)

          2. Inability to complete treadmill testing per protocol requirements.

          3. Ability to walk for more than 11 minutes on the treadmill during treadmill testing.

          4. Patients who identify both legs as equivocally symptomatic or alternate between
             symptomatic legs on the baseline treadmill tests.

          5. Patients with critical limb ischemia (ischemic rest pain or ischemia-related non
             healing wounds or tissue loss (Rutherford categories 4-6).

          6. Recent (&lt;3 months) infrainguinal revascularization (surgery or endovascular
             revascularization) or revascularization planned during study period

          7. Patients with a patent bypass graft in the index limb, with or without evidence of a
             hemodynamically significant stenosis or other defect (kinking, pseudoaneurysm, or
             fistula).

          8. Patients with &gt;2+ lower extremity pitting edema

          9. Patients with myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS)

         10. Patients who are pregnant or lactating, planning to become pregnant in the next 12
             months, or are unwilling to use acceptable forms of birth control during study
             participation.

         11. Congestive Heart Failure hospitalization within the last 1 month prior to enrollment

         12. Acute coronary syndrome in the last 1 month prior to enrollment

         13. Human Immunodeficiency Virus positive, active Hepatitis B Virus or Hepatitis C Virus
             Disease

         14. History of cancer within the last 5 years, except basal cell skin carcinoma

         15. Any bleeding diathesis defined as an International Normalized Ratio ≥ 2.0 (off
             anticoagulation therapy) or history of platelet count less than 100,000 or hemophilia

         16. Contraindication to magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) (including knee/tibial/fibular
             replacement hardware in the index leg) or known allergy to MRI contrast media

         17. Chronic kidney disease [effective Glomerular Filtration Rate &lt;30 by modification of
             diet in renal disease (MDRD) or Mayo or Cockcroft-Gault formula]

         18. Uncontrolled diabetes [Hemoglobin A1C (HbA1C)&gt;8.5]

         19. Planned change to (initiate or terminate) active involvement in a supervised exercise
             program (e.g., with a trainer, exercise protocol, and goals, such as in a peripheral
             arterial disease, cardiac or pulmonary rehabilitation program) during study
             participation

         20. Plans to change medical therapy during the duration of the study, (i.e. patients who
             use cilostazol should remain on a stable dose for four weeks prior to enrollment and
             should not change doses for the 6 months of the study duration.)  As always,
             cilostazol can be discontinued if new heart failure or intolerance occurs during
             study participation.

         21. Any condition requiring immunosuppressant medications (e.g., for treatment of organ
             transplants, psoriasis, Crohn's disease, alopecia areata).

         22. History of inflammatory or progressively fibrotic conditions (e.g. rheumatoid
             arthritis, systemic lupus erythematosis, vasculitic disorders, idiopathic pulmonary
             fibrosis, retroperitoneal fibrosis).

         23. Patients with any untreated stenosis &gt; 70% of the distal aorta, common iliac, or
             external iliac arteries by CT, Angiography or MRI imaging will be excluded from
             enrollment (patients with previously successfully revascularized inflow stenoses may
             enroll in PACE).   Subjects who were screen failures for a flow-limiting proximal
             lesion  may  be rescreened 3 months after successful angioplasty/stenting.

         24. Inability to provide written informed consent due to cognitive or language barriers
             (interpreter permitted)

         25. Concurrent enrollment in another clinical interventional investigative trial.

         26. Presence of any clinical condition that in the opinion of the principal Investigator
             or the sponsor makes the patient not suitable to participate in the trial
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Simari, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Cardiovascular Cell Therapy Research Network</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lemuel A Moye, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>832-721-6736</phone>
    <email>lemmoye@msn.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Shelly L Sayre, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>713-500-9529</phone>
    <email>Shelly.L.Sayre@uth.tmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University School of Medicine (Falk Cardiovascular Research Center)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Fouzia Khan</last_name>
      <phone>650-736-1410</phone>
      <email>fouziak@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Phil Yang, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida-Department of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32610</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dana Leach, DNP</last_name>
      <phone>352-273-8930</phone>
      <email>Dana.Leach@medicine.ufl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carl Pepine, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Miami-Interdisciplinary Stem Cell Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Darcy DiFede, RN, BSN</last_name>
      <phone>305-243-9106</phone>
      <email>ddifede@med.miami.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Josh Hare, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana Center for Vascular Biology and Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pat G'Sell</last_name>
      <phone>317-278-6585</phone>
      <email>pgsell@iu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kristen Wanczyk</last_name>
      <phone>317-278-0130</phone>
      <email>keevans@iu.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Murphy, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Louisville</name>
      <address>
        <city>Louisville</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shari Williams</last_name>
      <phone>502-407-3259</phone>
      <email>SLWILL06@louisville.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Roberto Bolli, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Minneapolis Heart Institute Foundation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55407</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>JoAnne Goldman, RT, RCIS, CCRC</last_name>
      <phone>612-863-3793</phone>
      <email>joanne.goldman@allina.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sarah Smith, BS, CCRC</last_name>
      <phone>612-863-6286</phone>
      <email>Sarah.Smith2@allina.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jason Alexander, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical and Translational Science Institute at University of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Barb Bruhn-Ding, RN</last_name>
      <phone>612-625-5949</phone>
      <email>bruhn028@umn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Emily Caldwell, RN</last_name>
      <phone>612-626-3656</phone>
      <email>caldw076@umn.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alan Hirsch, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Texas Heart Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jennifer Chambers</last_name>
      <phone>832-355-9408</phone>
      <email>jchambers@texasheart.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Nichole Piece</last_name>
      <phone>832-355-9173 or 1-866-924-7836</phone>
      <email>npiece@texasheart.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Emerson Perin, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cctrn.org</url>
    <description>Cardiovascular Cell Therapy Research Network</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/</url>
    <description>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://stemcells.nih.gov/info/basics/basics1.asp</url>
    <description>Information on stem cells at the National Institutes of Health Stem Cell Basics</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hirsch AT, Haskal ZJ, Hertzer NR, Bakal CW, Creager MA, Halperin JL, Hiratzka LF, Murphy WR, Olin JW, Puschett JB, Rosenfield KA, Sacks D, Stanley JC, Taylor LM Jr, White CJ, White J, White RA, Antman EM, Smith SC Jr, Adams CD, Anderson JL, Faxon DP, Fuster V, Gibbons RJ, Hunt SA, Jacobs AK, Nishimura R, Ornato JP, Page RL, Riegel B; American Association for Vascular Surgery; Society for Vascular Surgery; Society for Cardiovascular Angiography and Interventions; Society for Vascular Medicine and Biology; Society of Interventional Radiology; ACC/AHA Task Force on Practice Guidelines Writing Committee to Develop Guidelines for the Management of Patients With Peripheral Arterial Disease; American Association of Cardiovascular and Pulmonary Rehabilitation; National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute; Society for Vascular Nursing; TransAtlantic Inter-Society Consensus; Vascular Disease Foundation. ACC/AHA 2005 Practice Guidelines for the management of patients with peripheral arterial disease (lower extremity, renal, mesenteric, and abdominal aortic): a collaborative report from the American Association for Vascular Surgery/Society for Vascular Surgery, Society for Cardiovascular Angiography and Interventions, Society for Vascular Medicine and Biology, Society of Interventional Radiology, and the ACC/AHA Task Force on Practice Guidelines (Writing Committee to Develop Guidelines for the Management of Patients With Peripheral Arterial Disease): endorsed by the American Association of Cardiovascular and Pulmonary Rehabilitation; National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute; Society for Vascular Nursing; TransAtlantic Inter-Society Consensus; and Vascular Disease Foundation. Circulation. 2006 Mar 21;113(11):e463-654. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16549646</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perin EC, Silva G, Gahremanpour A, Canales J, Zheng Y, Cabreira-Hansen MG, Mendelsohn F, Chronos N, Haley R, Willerson JT, Annex BH. A randomized, controlled study of autologous therapy with bone marrow-derived aldehyde dehydrogenase bright cells in patients with critical limb ischemia. Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2011 Dec 1;78(7):1060-7. doi: 10.1002/ccd.23066. Epub 2011 May 18.</citation>
    <PMID>21594960</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 15, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr Lemuel A Moye III</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor - School of Public Health</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Peripheral Artery Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Intermittent Claudication</keyword>
  <keyword>Autologous Stem Cells</keyword>
  <keyword>ALDH cells</keyword>
  <keyword>Claudicants</keyword>
  <keyword>PAD</keyword>
  <keyword>Peak Walking Time</keyword>
  <keyword>MRI</keyword>
  <keyword>Vascular Flow</keyword>
  <keyword>Anatomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Perfusion</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Intermittent Claudication</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Arterial Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
