<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="99298">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02109458</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NA_00086035</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02109458</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Study of Navigational Bronchoscopy and Transthoracic Needle Biopsy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Navigational Bronchoscopy and Transthoracic Needle Biopsy for the Diagnosis of Peripheral Pulmonary Nodules: A Safety and Feasibility Pilot</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Veran Medical Technologies</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to evaluate the feasibility and safety of navigation guided
      virtual transthoracic needle biopsy combined with navigational bronchoscopy for the
      diagnosis of peripheral pulmonary nodules (PPN).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Accessing peripheral pulmonary nodules is problematic because they are often not visible
      endobronchially, not large enough to be visualized by x-ray fluoroscopy for transbronchial
      biopsy (TBBx), and/or do not lie within an accessible airway. In this study, investigators
      hope to evaluate new technologies to aid in PPN biopsy using navigation bronchoscopy (NB)
      combined with navigation transthoracic needle aspiration (N-TTNA) sampling of a PPN.

      Patients meeting inclusion criteria who consent will undergo a convex EBUS bronchoscopy for
      evaluation and sampling of the mediastinum and hilum.  Following this, NB will be performed
      with an ultrathin bronchoscope (4mm outer diameter with a 2 mm working channel) with R-EBUS
      and fluoroscopy.  If the lesion is localized by NB and/or radial EBUS in conjunction with
      NB, TBBX  will be taken.  At the conclusion of TBBX sampling, a fluoroscopic evaluation to
      assess for the presence of pneumothorax will be performed and if one is present, appropriate
      clinical measures will be taken at the discretion of the treating team (tube thoracostomy,
      observation, etc.) and no further sampling techniques will be utilized.  If the lesion was
      not able to be localized via NB and/or the physician feels insufficient sample was acquired
      for diagnosis and there is no evidence of pneumothorax, the patient will undergo N-TTNA at
      the same PPN during the same procedure time.  It is envisioned that between 8-12 patients
      will require a N-TTNA to complete diagnosis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluating the diagnostic yield of using navigation guided transthoracic needle aspiration (N-TTNA) and navigation guided bronchoscopy (NB) in the evaluation of PPN.</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients will be followed for up to 6 months or until a definitive diagnosis has been made</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Primary outcome of diagnostic yield will be determined from the results of the bronchoscopy. A biopsy that results in a specific diagnosis, either malignant or benign, will be assumed to be a true positive. Plan for further diagnostic management for patients who have a non-diagnostic biopsy will be determined by the attending physician. Those patients will be followed for up to 6 months until a definitive diagnosis has been made (such as from surgical pathology), or the lesion has decreased on repeat CT imaging.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse event rates of hemoptysis and pneumothorax</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients will be followed for up to six months or until a definitive diagnosis is made</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Monitor the safety of the navigational bronchoscopy combined with the navigation transthoracic needle aspiration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Peripheral Pulmonary Nodules</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Assessing peripheral pulmonary nodules</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>To evaluate the feasibility and safety of a procedure path including convex EBUS lymph node sampling, navigation guided bronchoscopy (NB) and navigation guided transthoracic needle aspiration (N-TTNA).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Navigation guided bronchoscopy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Assessing peripheral pulmonary nodules</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Veran Medical Technologies, Inc.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Target patient population: Patients with a peripheral pulmonary nodule as identified
             on CT chest ≤3cm from the pleura will be recruited. A PPN will be defined as a lesion
             &gt;10mm and &lt;3cm in diameter surrounded by lung parenchyma on CT chest. The decision
             for biopsy of the PPN will be made by the treating physician and agreed upon by the
             patient.

          -  Participants must be at least 18 years old or older

          -  No bleeding disorders

          -  Provide informed consent.

        Exclusion criteria

          -  less than 18 years

          -  lack of fitness for flexible bronchoscopy as determined by the physician performing
             the bronchoscopy before the procedure

          -  inability to give informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lonny Yarmus, DO</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karen Oakjones-Burgess</last_name>
    <phone>410-955-5288</phone>
    <email>kfriel2@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ricardo Ortiz</last_name>
    <email>rortiz7@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karen Oakjones-Burgess</last_name>
      <phone>410-955-5288</phone>
      <email>kfriel2@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lonny Yarmus, DO</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 17, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lonny Yarmus</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Lung nodule biopsy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
