<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="70651">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02108041</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999914075</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>14-HG-N075</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02108041</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Personalized Medicine Decision-Making in a Virtual Clinical Setting</brief_title>
  <official_title>Medical Decision-Making in a Virtual Clinical Setting</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - How people respond to drugs depends in part on their genes. For some drugs, doctors can
      use an individuals genetic background to help in dosing the drug.  Researchers want to know
      how doctors incorporate personalized or genomic medicine into clinical practice.

      Objective:

      - To study how physicians make personalized treatment decisions

      Eligibility:

      - Healthy adult primary care physicians who are internal (or family) medicine residents.

      Design:

        -  Participants will complete a screening form.

        -  Participants will manage a mock patient in an immersive virtual environment.  They will
           get Emergency Department discharge data about a 27-year-old virtual patient.

        -  Participants will put on a helmet. This will have a head-mounted display showing a
           virtual reality environment.

        -  The environment will contain an exam room and a virtual patient to interact with.

        -  Participation will last for about 60 minutes. The virtual patient interaction will be
           audio taped.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine factors related to primary care physicians    decision making around
      pharmacogenetic testing for warfarin response. Warfarin is a commonly prescribed
      anticoagulant (blood thinner) medication and it is one of the few drugs in primary care
      practice for which genotype-guided drug dosing is available in clinical practice. Warfarin
      is also difficult for primary care physicians to manage, as the dose necessary to remain in
      a therapeutic range of anticoagulation varies widely. Patients    responses to warfarin are
      affected by several variables, including age, sex, diet, and genetic makeup. Pharmacogenetic
      testing for warfarin response is one tool to help primary care physicians better manage
      warfarin dose. This kind of testing is not widely used in clinical practice due to a lack of
      scientific evidence that primary clinical outcomes are improved, although there are ongoing
      clinical trials examining this issue. As a result, the decision of whether or not to order
      warfarin pharmacogenetic testing is currently left to individual primary care physicians.
      This study will use a virtual clinical interaction experiment to assess primary care
      physicians knowledge of the clinical utility of genotype guided dosing of warfarin and the
      current research in its effectiveness. The study will also explore how physicians interact
      with and make decisions about pharmacogenetic testing warfarin dosing in patients of diverse
      racial and socioeconomic (SES) groups. We will assess whether physicians believe this
      pharmacogenetic test is useful. Physicians will be asked to respond to a virtual patient who
      presents with concerns about taking warfarin after she experienced a deep venous thrombosis
      (DVT). Primary care physicians will be randomized to one of six four possible combinations
      of racial and SES groups for the virtual patient. Physicians    implicit and explicit biases
      related to race and SES will be assessed as possible independent variables that may be
      correlated with their decisions about ordering genotype-guided drug dosing. Self-report
      measures will also be used to assess physicians    knowledge and beliefs about racial groups
      and human genetic variation. These variables will all be examined as possible factors that
      might impact physicians    decision making around warfarin pharmacogenetic testing. The
      central aim of this study is to assess how physicians make decisions about warfarin-related
      pharmacogenetic testing.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To examine how physicians make decisions about pharmacogenetic  testing related to anticoagulant (warfarin) response for patients</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <condition>Deep Vein Thrombosis</condition>
  <condition>Blood Clots</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  All physicians will be healthy adult volunteers who are medical residents in the
             internal medicine specialty.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. persons with seizure or vestibular disorders;

          2. persons who are highly prone to motion sickness;

          3. those without normal or normal to corrected vision or hearing;

          4. all current and past employees and contractors of NHGRI; and

          5. persons who have received information about the study purpose or procedure from a
             past participant.

        NHGRI employees are excluded for this protocol because they are likely to have specialized
        genomic knowledge and may think differently about genomics in the clinical interaction.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vence L Bonham, J.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Vence L Bonham, J.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 594-3973</phone>
    <email>bonhamv@nhgri.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Harvard School of Public Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan, School of Public Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109-2029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Madian AG, Wheeler HE, Jones RB, Dolan ME. Relating human genetic variation to variation in drug responses. Trends Genet. 2012 Oct;28(10):487-95. doi: 10.1016/j.tig.2012.06.008. Epub 2012 Jul 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22840197</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haga SB, Burke W, Ginsburg GS, Mills R, Agans R. Primary care physicians' knowledge of and experience with pharmacogenetic testing. Clin Genet. 2012 Oct;82(4):388-94. doi: 10.1111/j.1399-0004.2012.01908.x. Epub 2012 Jul 3. PubMed PMID: 22698141; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3440554.</citation>
    <PMID>22698141</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shields AE, Lerman C. Anticipating clinical integration of pharmacogenetic treatment strategies for addiction: are primary care physicians ready? Clin Pharmacol Ther. 2008 Apr;83(4):635-9. doi: 10.1038/clpt.2008.4. Epub 2008 Mar 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18323859</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 5, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 5, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Physicians</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacogenetic Testing</keyword>
  <keyword>Implicit Bias</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Thrombosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Venous Thrombosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
