<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="148125">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02065687</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GOG-0286B</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-02284</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>GOG-0286B</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>GOG-0286B</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U10CA027469</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02065687</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Paclitaxel and Carboplatin With or Without Metformin Hydrochloride in Treating Patients With Stage III, IV, or Recurrent Endometrial Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Phase II/III Study of Paclitaxel/Carboplatin/Metformin (NSC#91485) Versus Paclitaxel/Carboplatin/Placebo as Initial Therapy for Measurable Stage III or IVA, Stage IVB, or Recurrent Endometrial Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Gynecologic Oncology Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Gynecologic Oncology Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized phase II/III trial studies how well paclitaxel, carboplatin, and metformin
      hydrochloride works and compares it to paclitaxel, carboplatin, and placebo in treating
      patients with stage III, IV, or recurrent endometrial cancer. Drugs used in chemotherapy,
      such as paclitaxel and carboplatin, work in different ways to stop the growth of tumor
      cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing. Metformin
      hydrochloride may help paclitaxel and carboplatin work better by making cancer cells more
      sensitive to the drugs. It is not yet known whether paclitaxel and carboplatin is more
      effective with or without metformin hydrochloride in treating endometrial cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine if the addition of metformin (metformin hydrochloride) to the standard
      regimen of carboplatin and paclitaxel prolongs progression-free survival (PFS) in women with
      advanced or recurrent endometrial cancer. (Phase II) II. To determine if the addition of
      metformin to the standard regimen of carboplatin and paclitaxel prolongs overall survival
      (OS) in the same population if a phase III study is conducted. Both clinical trials (phase
      II and III) will utilize OS as a primary endpoint if a phase III trial is opened.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To estimate the proportion of patients with objective response (response rate [RR]) in
      the population of patients with measurable disease by treatment.

      II. To estimate the duration of response in the population of patients with measurable
      disease who respond by treatment.

      III. To estimate overall survival (OS) and relative hazards of death for each treatment arm
      if the study stops after the phase II trial is completed. If the study continues with a
      phase III clinical trial, then PFS will be a secondary endpoint.

      IV. To determine the nature, frequency and degree of toxicity as assessed by Common
      Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) for each treatment arm.

      V. To estimate possible differences in RR, PFS, OS, and toxicity rates for the treatment
      regimens by the patients' level of obesity.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To explore the association of metabolic factors (i.e. body mass index [BMI], hip-to-waist
      ratio, diabetes status, hemoglobin A1c [HgbA1C], fasting insulin and glucose levels,
      homeostatic model assessment [HOMA] scores) with treatment response to
      metformin/paclitaxel/carboplatin.

      II. To correlate expression of the metformin transporter proteins (i.e., organic cation
      transporters [OCT] 1-3, multidrug and toxin extrusion [MATE] 1/2 and plasma membrane
      monoamine transporter [PMAT]) and key targets of the metformin/mammalian target of rapamycin
      (mTOR) signaling pathway with treatment response to metformin/paclitaxel/carboplatin.

      III. To estimate differences in physical functioning, physical activity, and fatigue between
      treatment arms.

      IV. To explore the association between metabolic factors (i.e., BMI, hip-to-waist ratio,
      diabetes status, HgbA1C, fasting insulin and glucose levels, HOMA scores) and physical
      functioning, physical activity, and fatigue.

      OUTLINE: Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 treatment arms.

      ARM I: Patients receive paclitaxel intravenously (IV) over 3 hours, carboplatin IV over 30
      minutes on day 1, and metformin hydrochloride orally (PO) twice daily (BID) on days 1-21
      (once daily [QD] in course 1). Treatment repeats every 21 days for 6 courses in the absence
      of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients then receive maintenance therapy
      comprising metformin hydrochloride PO BID on days 1-21. Courses repeat every 21 days in the
      absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      ARM II: Patients receive paclitaxel IV and carboplatin IV as in Arm I. Patients also receive
      placebo PO BID on days 1-21 (QD in course 1). Treatment repeats every 21 days for 6 courses
      in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients then receive
      maintenance therapy comprising placebo PO BID on days 1-21. Courses repeat every 21 days in
      the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 3 months for 2 years and
      then every 6 months for 3 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of study entry to time of progression or death, whichever occurs first, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (Phase II and III)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of study entry to time of death or the date of last contact, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients responding to therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessed using a 95% confidence interval (CI).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response by treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of response to disease progression, death, or date last seen assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Duration will be characterized by treatment using Kaplan-Meier curves and quartile estimates.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of study entry to time of death or the date of last contact, assessed up to 26 months , assessed up to 6 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PFS (Phase III)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of study entry to time of progression or death, whichever occurs first, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events as assessed by CTCAE v4 within each arm</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Toxicities will be assessed by organ or organ system. For each category of toxicity, each patient will be evaluated by the worst grade experienced during the course of therapy. Data will be summarized by frequency and severity according to the regimen administered. Comparisons between regimens will be examined through exact Chi-Square methods by breaking the severity of the worst toxicities experienced by each patient into severe versus not severe (or into groups of none to mild, moderate, and severe or worse).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Level of obesity</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Obesity will be quantitative assessed by BMI and will be assessed for its predictive and prognostic significance. The interaction between BMI and metformin treatment will be examined with an interaction term in a Cox proportional hazards model.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Metabolic factor levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Hip-to-waist ratio, diabetes status, HgBA1C, fasting insulin glucose levels, and HOMA scores will be assessed for their predictive and prognostic significance. Variables will be analyzed as continuous covariates (or as appropriate with transformations such as the logarithm) with Cox models or logistic regression.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of metformin transporter proteins</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Metformin transporter proteins include OCT 1-3, MATE 1/2 and PMAT. Levels before and after treatment will be assessed for their predictive and prognostic significance.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of key targets of the metformin/mTOR signaling pathway</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Levels before and after treatment will be assessed for their predictive and prognostic significance.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of PIK3 mutations/amplifications</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PIK3CA mutations/amplifications and PIK3R1/PIK3R2 mutations will be examined for prognostic and predictive significance.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">540</enrollment>
  <condition>Endometrial Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Endometrial Clear Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Endometrial Papillary Serous Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Endometrial Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIA Endometrial Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Endometrial Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Endometrial Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Endometrial Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Endometrial Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (paclitaxel, carboplatin, metformin hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive paclitaxel IV over 3 hours, carboplatin IV over 30 minutes on day 1, and metformin hydrochloride PO BID on days 1-21 (QD in course 1). Treatment repeats every 21 days for 6 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients then receive maintenance therapy comprising metformin hydrochloride PO BID on days 1-21. Courses repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (paclitaxel, carboplatin, placebo)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive paclitaxel IV and carboplatin IV as in Arm I. Patients also receive placebo PO BID on days 1-21 (QD in course 1). Treatment repeats every 21 days for 6 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients then receive maintenance therapy comprising placebo PO BID on days 1-21. Courses repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (paclitaxel, carboplatin, metformin hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (paclitaxel, carboplatin, placebo)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Anzatax</other_name>
    <other_name>Asotax</other_name>
    <other_name>TAX</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (paclitaxel, carboplatin, metformin hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (paclitaxel, carboplatin, placebo)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Carboplat</other_name>
    <other_name>CBDCA</other_name>
    <other_name>JM-8</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplat</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>metformin hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (paclitaxel, carboplatin, metformin hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Glucophage</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (paclitaxel, carboplatin, placebo)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PLCB</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (paclitaxel, carboplatin, metformin hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (paclitaxel, carboplatin, placebo)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>quality-of-life assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (paclitaxel, carboplatin, metformin hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (paclitaxel, carboplatin, placebo)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>quality of life assessment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>questionnaire administration</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (paclitaxel, carboplatin, metformin hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (paclitaxel, carboplatin, placebo)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have measurable stage III, measurable stage IVA, stage IVB (with or
             without measurable disease) or recurrent (with or without measurable disease)
             endometrial carcinoma

               -  Histologic confirmation of the original primary tumor is required; patients with
                  the following histologic epithelial cell types are eligible:

                    -  Endometrioid adenocarcinoma, serous adenocarcinoma, undifferentiated
                       carcinoma, clear cell adenocarcinoma, mixed epithelial carcinoma,
                       adenocarcinoma not otherwise specified (N.O.S.)

          -  Measurable disease is defined by Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors
             (RECIST) (version 1.1); measurable disease is defined as at least one lesion that can
             be accurately measured in at least one dimension (longest diameter to be recorded);
             each lesion must be &gt;= 10 mm when measured by computed tomography (CT), magnetic
             resonance imaging (MRI) or caliper measurement by clinical exam; or &gt;= 20 mm when
             measured by chest x-ray; lymph nodes must be &gt;= 15 mm in short axis when measured by
             CT or MRI

          -  Patients must have a Gynecologic Oncology Group (GOG) performance status of 0, 1, or
             2

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) greater than or equal to 1,500/mcl

          -  Platelets greater than or equal to 100,000/mcl

          -  Creatinine less than or equal to 1.5 x institutional/laboratory upper limit of normal
             (ULN)

          -  Bilirubin less than or equal to 1.5 x ULN

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) less than or
             equal to 3 x ULN

          -  Alkaline phosphatase less than or equal to 2.5 x ULN

          -  Patients must NOT have received prior chemotherapy or targeted therapy, including
             chemotherapy used for radiation sensitization for treatment of endometrial carcinoma

          -  Patients may have received prior radiation therapy for treatment of endometrial
             carcinoma; prior radiation therapy may have included pelvic radiation therapy,
             extended field pelvic/para-aortic radiation therapy, and/or intravaginal
             brachytherapy; all radiation therapy must be completed at least 4 weeks prior to the
             first date of study therapy

          -  Patients may have received prior hormonal therapy for treatment of endometrial
             carcinoma; all hormonal therapy must be discontinued at least one week prior to the
             first date of study therapy

          -  Patients must be able to swallow and retain orally-administered medication

          -  Patients must have signed an approved informed consent and authorization permitting
             release of personal health information; individuals with impaired decision-making
             capacity are not eligible to participate on the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must NOT be taking metformin or have been on metformin in the past 6 months

          -  Patients with a history of other invasive malignancies, with the exception of
             non-melanoma skin cancer are excluded if there is any evidence of other malignancy
             being present within the last three years

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements

          -  Patients who are pregnant or nursing; if patients are of reproductive age and have
             not undergone hysterectomy, they must use an effective contraceptive method for the
             duration of this study

          -  Any condition associated with increased risk of metformin-associated lactic acidosis.
             (e.g. congestive heart failure defined as New York Heart Association [NYHA] class III
             or IV functional status, history of acidosis of any type; habitual intake of 3 or
             more alcoholic beverages per day)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Victoria Bae-Jump</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Gynecologic Oncology Group</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Case Western Reserve University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven E. Waggoner</last_name>
      <phone>800-641-2422</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steven E. Waggoner</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Abington Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Abington</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19001</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Parviz Hanjani</last_name>
      <phone>215-481-2402</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Parviz Hanjani</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gynecologic Oncology Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Victoria L. Bae-Jump</last_name>
      <phone>919-843-4899</phone>
      <email>vbae@unch.unc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Victoria L. Bae-Jump</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 25, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 14, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endometrial Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma, Clear Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adenomyoepithelioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cystadenocarcinoma, Serous</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
