<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="52013">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01989130</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>071346</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01989130</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Immediate v. Delayed CT/NG Test for Treatment in the ED</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Cepheid Xpert CT/NG For Management of STI in the ED: Immediate V. Delayed Test Results</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>George Washington University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cepheid</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>George Washington University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine if immediate availability of GeneXpert® CT/NG test
      results reduces the overtreatment rate for ED patients with suspected gonorrhea or chlamydia
      and to assess changes in clinician management decisions with real-time test results.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators will conduct a randomized controlled trial in patients aged 18 and older
      where the treating clinician is ordering a CT/NG test. Clinicians will be approached by a
      research assistant while they are in the ED and asked whether a CT/NG swab will be ordered
      and if CT/NG is in the differential diagnosis.  Then, potentially eligible patients will be
      approached and asked for consent to enroll. For patients that consent, simple randomization
      procedure (i.e. random number generator) will be used to assign patients to either immediate
      test results or delayed test results. Typically, in the ED these tests are ordered for
      diagnostic rather than screening purposes (symptoms of vaginal discharge, abdominal pain,
      etc).  Patients will be randomized to batched testing with the Roche AMPLICOR CT/NG
      (standard of care, control group) or immediate testing of clinical specimens with Cepheid
      CT/NG with real-time result reporting (within 90 minutes) to the treating clinician in the
      ED. Patient interview and clinician survey will be conducted to ascertain perceptions of
      illness and the test.  A follow up interview will be conducted with the patient to determine
      clinical and public health outcomes.

      A validation of the Cepheid CT/NG test will be conducted against the hospital standard of
      care on &lt;/= 40 pilot participants. Pilot participants will be asked to provide 2
      endocervical swabs and a urine specimen. All surveys and interviews will be conducted on
      pilot patients.

      While many outcomes can be measured in this study, the investigators will power this study
      to reduce the overtreatment rate with antibiotics. Assuming a baseline overtreatment rate of
      88% (# treated with antibiotics/# without disease), to reduce this rate by 50% (to 44%), at
      a power of 80% and alpha of 0.05, the investigators will need to enroll 42 patients (21
      controls and 21 study patients) with negative tests. Given an estimated positive rate of 6%,
      and that approximately 50% of patients who receive these tests for any reason will be
      treated empirically with antibiotics, the investigators think that enrolling a total of 70
      patients with full data (enrollment survey, clinician survey, and follow up survey) would be
      sufficient to identify trends with this subject matter. Due to the sensitive nature of the
      subject matter and the high percentages of lost-to-follow up with ED patients, the
      investigators estimate approximately 50% will have incomplete data. Therefore, the
      investigators request to enroll 150 patients in the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Antibiotic Prescription</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measurement of the number and type of antibiotics prescribed to CT/NG + v. CT/NG - in both groups</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Quantify the number of visits to healthcare facilities/providers and non-ED related medications purchased in 7-10 days after enrollment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Healthcare Cost</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To quantify the amount billed to insurance companies and out of pocket expenses for initial encounter</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Resolution of Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of patients that report having no symptoms 7 to 10 days after initial encounter</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Reproductive Tract Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Real-time results with Cepheid Xpert CT/NG Test</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Diagnosis of +/- CT/NG within 2 hours of specimen entering laboratory</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Batched results with Roche AMPLICOR CT/NG test</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Diagnosis of +/- CT/NG within 1 to 4 days of visit to the ED</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Roche AMPLICOR CT/NG</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Batched results with Roche AMPLICOR CT/NG test</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cepheid Xpert CT/NG Test</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Real-time results with Cepheid Xpert CT/NG Test</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  greater than 18 years

          -  clinical suspicion of CT/NG

          -  able to give informed consent

          -  willingness to wait for test result

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  less than 18 years

          -  pregnancy

          -  prisoners

          -  unable to give informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The George Washington University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20036</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Catherine Zatorski, BA</last_name>
      <phone>202-677-6422</phone>
      <email>czatorski@mfa.gwu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Gillian Brooks, BA</last_name>
      <phone>202-677-6423</phone>
      <email>gbrooks@mfa.gwu.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Larissa May, MD, MSPH, MSHS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andric B, Drowos J, Trepka MJ, Suciu G, Alonso A, Hennekens CH. High frequencies of negative pretreatment results following presumptive antibiotic treatment for chlamydia and gonorrhea. South Med J. 2013 May;106(5):321-6. doi: 10.1097/SMJ.0b013e318291b3c2.</citation>
    <PMID>23644641</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Levitt MA, Johnson S, Engelstad L, Montana R, Stewart S. Clinical management of chlamydia and gonorrhea infection in a county teaching emergency department--concerns in overtreatment, undertreatment, and follow-up treatment success. J Emerg Med. 2003 Jul;25(1):7-11.</citation>
    <PMID>12865101</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gaydos CA, Van Der Pol B, Jett-Goheen M, Barnes M, Quinn N, Clark C, Daniel GE, Dixon PB, Hook EW 3rd; CT/NG Study Group. Performance of the Cepheid CT/NG Xpert Rapid PCR Test for Detection of Chlamydia trachomatis and Neisseria gonorrhoeae. J Clin Microbiol. 2013 Jun;51(6):1666-72. doi: 10.1128/JCM.03461-12. Epub 2013 Mar 6.</citation>
    <PMID>23467600</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 14, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 6, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>antimicrobial stewardship</keyword>
  <keyword>Cepheid Xpert CT/NG</keyword>
  <keyword>chlamydia</keyword>
  <keyword>gonorrhea</keyword>
  <keyword>emergency department</keyword>
  <keyword>Diagnostic Techniques, Obstetrical and Gynecological</keyword>
  <keyword>Diagnostic Techniques, Urological</keyword>
  <keyword>Antimicrobial stewardship</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
