<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="154645">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01822691</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MCC-17280</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>I-24360-12-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01822691</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase II INCB024360 Study for Patients With Myelodysplastic Syndromes (MDS)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study to Determine the Safety and Efficacy of INCB024360 in Patients With Myelodysplastic Syndromes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Incyte Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of this research study is to assess whether the participant's disease,
      Myelodysplastic Syndromes (MDS), responds favorably to INCB024360. The study will also
      evaluate the long-term outcomes of the participant's disease after they have finished taking
      INCB024360.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Best Overall Response Rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>On Study Through Follow-up - Approximately 36 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Primary Endpoint is best Overall Response, measured by Response Criteria for Patients with MDS According International Working Group (IWG) 2006 criteria (Cheson et al, 2006). Complete Remission (CR), Partial Remission (PR), Marrow CR, and Hematological Improvement (HI)(any cell line).
Treatment Duration is 17 weeks plus optional continuation phase. Study Duration is Treatment Phase followed by 24 months survival follow-up.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML) Progression</measure>
    <time_frame>On Study Through Follow-up - Approximately 36 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Disease progression is defined as progression to int-2 or high risk International Prognostic Scoring System (IPSS) score or AML, based on World Health Organization (WHO) AML Criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>On Study Through Follow-up - Approximately 36 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall Survival (OS) is defined as the time between the randomization and death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Study Related Serious Adverse Events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>On Study Through Follow-up - Approximately 36 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events Version 4.0 (CTCAE V4.0) Version 4 will be used to determine the severity of toxicity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>INCB024360 Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive the study drug in 28 day (4 week) cycles of treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>INCB024360</intervention_name>
    <description>INCB024360 is an inhibitor of the enzyme indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase (IDO) that is proposed for development for the treatment of malignant diseases.</description>
    <arm_group_label>INCB024360 Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>inhibitor of indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase 1 (IDO1)</other_name>
    <other_name>IDO1 inhibitor</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Confirmed diagnosis of myelodysplastic syndromes (MDS)

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status ≤ 2

          -  Adequate organ function:

               -  Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 × Upper Limit of Normal (ULN)

               -  Aspartic transaminase (AST)/alanine transaminase (ALT) ≤ 2.5 × ULN

               -  Creatinine ≤  2 × ULN or Creatinine clearance of &gt; 30 mL/min (using the
                  Cockcroft and Gault Equation)

          -  Females of childbearing potential must have a negative urine or serum pregnancy test
             at Screening.

          -  Women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
             (surgical tubal ligation or vasectomy, double-barrier method of birth control condom
             with spermicide in conjunction with use of an intrauterine device (IUD) or diaphragm;
             or sexual abstinence) prior to study entry and for the duration of study
             participation.  Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant, or a male
             impregnate his female partner, while participating in this study, he/she should
             inform their treating physician immediately.

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior MDS therapy within 4 weeks of the first dose of study medication. For erythroid
             stimulating agent and growth factors: prior therapy with epoetin (Procrit) or G-CSF
             (neupogen) or GM-CSF (leukine) within 2 weeks of the first dose of study medication.

          -  Has participated in any other trial in which receipt of an investigational study drug
             occurred within 28 days.

          -  Has undergone a stem cell, bone marrow or solid organ transplant.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit by the
             investigator opinion compliance with study requirements

          -  History of hepatitis or positive serology as follows:

               -  Hepatitis B (HepB) screening testing required: HepB SAg (hepatitis B surface
                  antigen); Anti-HepB SAg (antibody against hepatitis B surface antigen);
                  Anti-Hepatitis B core IgG (antibody against hepatitis B core antigen);
                  Anti-Hepatitis B core IgM antibody Note: Subjects with no prior history of
                  hepatitis B infection who have been vaccinated against hepatitis B and who have
                  a positive anti-HepB SAg test as the only evidence of prior exposure may
                  participate in the trial.

               -  Hepatitis C screening required: antibody against hepatitis C virus
                  (HCV-antibody); HCV-RNA (serum test for circulating virus, based on detecting
                  RNA)

          -  Known history human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)

          -  Is receiving any compound that is known to be a potent inducer or inhibitor of CYP3A4

          -  Being treated with a monoamine oxidase inhibitor (MAOI), or drug which has
             significant monoamine oxidase inhibitory activity (meperidine, linezolid, methylene
             blue) within 3 weeks prior to screening

          -  Has, by the investigator assessment, an active autoimmune process such as rheumatoid
             arthritis, psoriasis, multiple sclerosis, inflammatory bowel disease, etc. or is
             receiving therapy for an autoimmune disease. Subjects with vitiligo, hypothyroidism
             or eczema may be enrolled after approval by the sponsor.

          -  Receiving any immunologically based treatment for any reason, including chronic use
             of systemic steroid at doses ≥ 7.5 mg/day prednisone equivalents; use of inhaled or
             topical steroids is acceptable.

          -  Prior malignancies other than MDS for which the subject has not been disease free for
             ≤ 3 years, except treated and cured basal or squamous cell skin cancer, superficial
             bladder cancer, or carcinoma in situ of the cervix.

          -  Use of any UGT1A9 inhibitor including:  diclofenac, imipramine, ketoconazole,
             mefenamic acid, and probenecid from screening through follow-up period.

          -  Have had prior Serotonin Syndrome

          -  Any unresolved toxicity greater than Grade 2 from previous anticancer therapy, except
             for stable chronic toxicities not expected to resolve, such as peripheral
             neurotoxicity
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rami Komrokji, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lisa Nardelli</last_name>
      <phone>813-745-4731</phone>
      <email>lisa.nardelli@moffitt.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rami Komrokji, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jeffrey Lancet, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alan List, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bijal Shah, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lubomir Sokol, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Timothy Kubal, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kendra Sweet, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.moffitt.org/research--clinical-trials/clinical-trials</url>
    <description>Moffitt Cancer Center Clinical Trials website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 28, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>myelodysplastic syndromes (MDS)</keyword>
  <keyword>neoplastic stem cell disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>refractory cytopenias</keyword>
  <keyword>dysplastic morphological features</keyword>
  <keyword>acute myeloid leukemia (AML)</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
