<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="67318">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02143739</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NIS-RCN-XXX-2013/2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02143739</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Severity of Newly Diagnosed Asthma Patients and the Result of Initial 12 Weeks Treatment in China</brief_title>
  <acronym>INITIAL</acronym>
  <official_title>The Severity of Newly Diagnosed Asthma Patients and the Result of Initial 12 Weeks Treatment in China</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AstraZeneca</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>China: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of the NIS is to evaluate the severity of newly diagnosed asthma
      patients based on Global Initiative for Asthma (GINA) severity category (GINA 2006 update).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-centre, prospective non-interventional  study planned to be conducted in
      China. The study aims to recruit about 5000 newly diagnosed patients from about 50 tier 3
      hospitals with respiratory department. Each site recruits about 50-150 patients.

      The primary variable will be distribution of severity based on GINA definition (GINA 2006
      update) at baseline in the total population.

      There will be 4 visits for this study, Informed consent and following study procedures
      (ACQ-5(asthma control questionnaire), severity assessment) will be done at visit 1. After
      that, according to clinical practice in China patients usually go to the clinic every 4
      weeks. Asthma control status, ACQ-5 and sever exacerbation will be assessed at each clinic
      visit till 12 weeks (visit 2, 3, 4).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <target_duration>12 Weeks</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Asthma Severity assessment based on GINA definition (GINA 2006 update) at baseline in the total population</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>severity based on GINA definition (GINA 2006 update) at baseline in the total population.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>evaluate the control level of initial 12 weeks treatment based on Assessment of Current Clinical Control in GINA (GINA 2012 update).</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The asthma control status assessment will be based on Assessment of Current Clinical Control in GINA (GINA 2012 update).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5000</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Newly diagnosed asthma patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>The patient population will be outpatients, men or women, ≥18 years of age, Newly diagnosed asthma patients who are not on inhaled gluococorticosteroid within 3 months.The patient population should not have COPD(chronic obstructive pulmonary diseases) history, or asthma exacerbation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The patient population will be outpatients, men or women, ≥18 years of age, Newly
        diagnosed asthma patients who are not on inhaled gluococorticosteroid within 3 months.The
        patient population should not have COPD history, or asthma exacerbation.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Newly diagnosed asthma patients who are not on inhaled gluococorticosteroid within 3
             months.

          2. Out-patient with an age of 18 years and above

          3. Signed and dated informed consent The prescription of the medicinal product is
             clearly separated from the decision to include the subject in the NIS. Generally,
             asthma medication refers to those recommended in GINA guideline (GINA2012 update) and
             decided by investigator.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Participating in any clinical trial during the last 90 days

          2. Have COPD

          3. With asthma exacerbation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lin Ji Tao, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>China-Japan Friendship Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Liu Ying, project manager</last_name>
    <phone>+86 21 60301287</phone>
    <email>ying.liu8@astrazeneca.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Liu Qiang, line manager</last_name>
    <phone>+86 21 60301346</phone>
    <email>qiang.liu@astrazeneca.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>China-Japan Friendship Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100029</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Juniper EF, O'Byrne PM, Roberts JN. Measuring asthma control in group studies: do we need airway calibre and rescue beta2-agonist use? Respir Med. 2001 May;95(5):319-23.</citation>
    <PMID>11392570</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lin JT, Chen P, Zhou X, Sun TY, Xie CM, Xiu QY, Yao WZ, Yang L, Yin KS, Zhang YM. Budesonide/formoterol maintenance and reliever therapy in Chinese patients with asthma. Chin Med J (Engl). 2012 Sep;125(17):2994-3001.</citation>
    <PMID>22932169</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rabe KF, Vermeire PA, Soriano JB, Maier WC. Clinical management of asthma in 1999: the Asthma Insights and Reality in Europe (AIRE) study. Eur Respir J. 2000 Nov;16(5):802-7.</citation>
    <PMID>11153575</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thompson PJ, Salvi S, Lin J, Cho YJ, Eng P, Abdul Manap R, Boonsawat W, Hsu JY, Faruqi RA, Moreno-Cantu JJ, Fish JE, Ho JC. Insights, attitudes and perceptions about asthma and its treatment: findings from a multinational survey of patients from 8 Asia-Pacific countries and Hong Kong. Respirology. 2013 Aug;18(6):957-67. doi: 10.1111/resp.12137.</citation>
    <PMID>23730953</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhao J; National Parents of Asthmatic Children KAP Project Team. [Asthma control status in children and related factors in 29 cities of China]. Zhonghua Er Ke Za Zhi. 2013 Feb;51(2):90-5. Chinese.</citation>
    <PMID>23527968</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Juniper EF, O'Byrne PM, Guyatt GH, Ferrie PJ, King DR. Development and validation of a questionnaire to measure asthma control. Eur Respir J. 1999 Oct;14(4):902-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10573240</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 22, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 19, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>asthma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
