<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="107608">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01936363</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EMR 200066_012</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-000902-40</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01936363</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of Pimasertib With SAR245409 or Placebo in Ovarian Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Randomized Double Blind Placebo Controlled Trial of Combination of Pimasertib With SAR245409 or of Pimasertib With SAR245409 Placebo in Subjects With Previously Treated Unresectable Low Grade Ovarian Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>EMD Serono</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sanofi</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>EMD Serono</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a double blind, randomized, placebo-controlled, 2-arm,  Phase 2 trial  investigating
       the  efficacy  and safety  of combination therapy of pimasertib  plus SAR245409 and
      pimasertib placebo administered once per day compared to pimasertib administered twice per
      day plus SAR245409  placebo  administered  once  per  day in subjects with previously
      treated unresectable low-grade  ovarian  cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective tumor response defined as complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) according to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors Version 1.1 (RECIST v.1.1) as determined by the investigator</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2.5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Objective tumor response will be measured from baseline until disease progression or death assessed every 8 weeks up to week 32, and thereafter every 12 weeks up to 2.5 years</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from randomization until first observation of progressive disease or death, when death occurs within 12 weeks of the last tumor assessment (whichever comes first), up to 30 days after last treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Time from randomisation to the first documentation of objective disease progression according to RECIST v.1.1 as determined by the Investigator or death, whichever comes first. Death will be considered as a Progression-free survival (PFS) event only if it is reported within 12 weeks after the last tumor assessment without progression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with disease control according to RECIST v.1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 8, 16, 24 and 32, and thereafter every 12 weeks up to 30 days after last treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Disease control defined as the proportion of subjects with stable disease (SD) for at least 16 weeks, PR or CR according to RECIST v.1.1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival time</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from randomization to death up to 12 months after last subject randomized</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Related Quality of Life (HrQoL) assessed using European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire C30 (EORTC QLQ-C30) Version 3.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Day 29, and Week 8, 16, 24 and 32, and thereafter every 12 weeks up to 30 days after last treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The QLQ-C30 is a 30-item questionnaire comprising of five functional scales (physical, role, cognitive, emotional, and social), three symptom scales (fatigue, pain, and nausea/vomiting), six single items (dyspnea, insomnia, appetite loss, constipation, diarrhea, and financial impact), and a global QoL scale summarized from two 7-point scales (overall QoL and overall general health)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HrQoL assessed using EORTC QLQ-C30 Version 3.0 - ovarian-specific module QLQ-OV28</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Day 29, and Week 8, 16, 24 and 32, and thereafter every 12 weeks up to 30 days after last treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The ovarian cancer module EORTC QLQ-OV28 assesses disease and treatment-related symptoms of ovarian cancer. The 28-item module comprises of 6 symptom scales (abdominal/gastrointestinal symptoms, peripheral neuropathy, other chemotherapy side-effects, hormonal symptoms, body image, attitude to disease and treatment), and sexual functioning. Both measures have been developed and validated in cross-cultural settings, exhibit good psychometric properties, and take between 10-15 minutes to complete</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Subjects with Treatment Emergent Adverse Events (TEAEs), Adverse Events (AEs) of special interest, Serious Adverse Events (SAEs), discontinuation of treatment due to TEAEs, death</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 30 days after last treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>TEAEs, SAEs and AEs will be assessed according to the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI-CTCAE) Version 4.0. An Adverse Event (AE) is defined as any new untoward medical occurrences/worsening of pre-existing medical condition without regard to possibility of causal relationship. Treatment-emergent adverse events are events from first dose of study drug that were absent before treatment or that worsened relative to pretreatment state.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Plasma Concentration (Cmax) After Dose of pimasertib and SAR245409</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-dosing to 0.5, 1.5, 4.5 and 8 hours after the morning dose at day 15, 29, 43</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the curve (AUC) After Dose of pimasertib and SAR245409</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-dosing to 0.5, 1.5, 4.5 and 8 hours after the morning dose at day 15, 29, 43</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Molecular Alterations in MAPK and/or PI3K signaling pathway components/modulators in tumor tissue and blood</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening visit (day -28 to 1)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pimasertib (once daily) plus SAR245409 and Pimasertib placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pimasertib (twice daily) plus SAR245409 placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pimasertib once daily</intervention_name>
    <description>Pimasertib will be administered as oral capsule at a dose of 60 milligram (mg) once daily  until  disease progression,  death, intolerable  toxicity or withdrawal of informed consent, whichever comes first.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pimasertib (once daily) plus SAR245409 and Pimasertib placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pimasertib placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo matching Pimasertib will be administered once daily in evening until disease progression,  death,  intolerable  toxicity or withdrawal of informed consent, whichever comes first.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pimasertib (once daily) plus SAR245409 and Pimasertib placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SAR245409  placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo matching SAR245409 will be administered once daily in morning until disease progression, death, intolerable toxicity or withdrawal of informed consent, whichever comes first.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pimasertib (twice daily) plus SAR245409 placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SAR245409</intervention_name>
    <description>SAR245409 will be administered as oral capsule at a dose of 70 milligram (mg) once daily until disease progression, death, intolerable toxicity or withdrawal of informed consent, whichever comes first.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pimasertib (once daily) plus SAR245409 and Pimasertib placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pimasertib twice daily</intervention_name>
    <description>Pimasertib will be administered as oral capsule at a dose of 60 milligram (mg)  twice daily until  disease progression, death, intolerable toxicity or withdrawal of informed consent, whichever comes first.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pimasertib (twice daily) plus SAR245409 placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The female subject has a diagnosis of one of the following: a) low-grade serous
             ovarian or peritoneal carcinoma, or grade 1 serous ovarian or peritoneal carcinoma or
             well-differentiated serous ovarian or peritoneal carcinoma or b) serous borderline
             ovarian or peritoneal tumor, ovarian or peritoneal tumor of low-malignant potential,
             ovarian or peritoneal atypical proliferative serous tumor that recurs as low grade
             serous carcinoma or has invasive peritoneal implants.

          -  The subject had at least one prior line of systemic therapy and has a tumor, which is
             not amenable to potentially curative surgical resection.

          -  The subject has measurable disease by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors
             (RECIST) v1.1.

          -  The subject is at least 18 years old.

          -  The subject has read and understood the written informed consent form (ICF) and is
             willing and able to give informed consent, fully understands the requirements of the
             trial and is willing to comply with all trial visits and assessments, including
             completion of patient-reported measures. Consent must be given before any trial
             related activities.

          -  Subjects of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test at the
             screening visit.

          -  Subjects of childbearing potential must be willing to avoid pregnancy by using an
             adequate method of contraception for 2 weeks prior to screening, during and at least
             4 weeks after the last dose of trial medication.

          -  Other protocol defined inclusion criteria may apply.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The subject has previously been treated with a PI3K inhibitor and taken off treatment
             due to treatment related AEs.

          -  The subject has been previously treated with a Mitogen-activated
             protein/extracellular signal-regulated kinase (MEK) inhibitor.

          -  The subject has received chemotherapy, immunotherapy, hormonal therapy, biologic
             therapy, or any other anti-cancer therapy within 28 days or within 5 times the half
             life of a relevant agent prior to day 1 of trial drug treatment, whichever is
             shorter, or has been treated with nitrosoureas or mitomycin C within the last 6
             weeks.

          -  The subject has not recovered from toxicity due to prior therapy to Baseline level or
             National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events Version 4.0
             (NCI CTCAE v4.0) Grade 1 or less (except alopecia).

          -  The subject has poor organ and marrow function as defined in the protocol.

          -  The subject has creatine phosphokinase (CPK) elevation NCI CTCAE grade &gt;=2, and/or a
             previous history of myositis or rhabdomyolysis.

          -  The subject has difficulty swallowing, malabsorption or other chronic
             gastrointestinal disease or conditions that may hamper compliance and/or absorption
             of the trial drug.

          -  The subject has a history of delayed healing/open wounds or diabetic ulcers.

          -  The subject has a history of congestive heart failure, unstable angina, myocardial
             infarction, cardiac conduction abnormalities including corrected QT interval
             prolongation of &gt; 480ms or a pacemaker, clinically relevant impaired cardiovascular
             function (New York Heart Association (NYHA) class III/IV) or stroke within 3 months
             prior to enrollment.

          -  The subject has a history of retinal degenerative disease (hereditary retinal
             degeneration or age-related macular degeneration), uveitis or retinal vein occlusion
             (RVO), or has other relevant abnormalities identified on screening opthalmologic
             examination, which may increase the risk of serous retinal detachment (SRD) or RVO.

          -  The subject has a history of uncontrolled intercurrent illness including but not
             limited to an active infection, hypertension, or uncontrolled diabetes (e.g.
             glycosylated hemoglobin &gt;= 8%) that would limit compliance with treatment
             requirements.

          -  Other protocol defined exclusion criteria may apply.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Responsible</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Merck KGaA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>US Medical Information</last_name>
    <phone>888-275-7376</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Merck KGaA Communication Center</last_name>
    <phone>+49-6151-72-5200</phone>
    <email>service@merckgroup.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Please Contact U.S. Medical Information Located in</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rockland</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>for US Recruiting Sites</last_name>
      <phone>888-275-7376</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Please contact the Merck KGaA Communication Center located in</name>
      <address>
        <city>Darmstadt</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>for EU Recruiting Sites</last_name>
      <phone>+49-6151-72-5200</phone>
      <email>service@merckgroup.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 17, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 23, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ovarian Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Pimasertib</keyword>
  <keyword>Placebo</keyword>
  <keyword>SAR245409</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
