<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1376">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01758900</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>rjer2011-70k</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01758900</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CO2 Versus Air Insufflation for Single-balloon Enteroscopy</brief_title>
  <official_title>CO2 Versus Air Insufflation for Single-balloon Enteroscopy: a Randomized, Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Zhizheng Ge</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>China: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Small-balloon enteroscopy(SBE) is a novel endoscopy system for examination of the deep small
      intestine.Initial reports indicated that CO2 was effective during the colonoscopy ,ERCP and
      DBE examination, but it is still uncertain to the SBE procedure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Currently, air is more frequently used to insufflate gas into the lumen to ensure the
      visualization of the mucosa. However, there're some limitations, for instance, significant
      amounts of air are usually retained in the small bowel, which will lead to the distention
      and the pain of the gastrointestinal tract during and after the procedure.

      Carbon dioxide(CO2), comparing to the air, is rapidly absorbed from the intestine, which
      allows the bowel to decompress more quickly and potentially decreases intraprocedural and
      postprocedural pain, sedation medication requirements, procedure time, and recovery time. It
      is also to the benefit of deeper intubation depth so that higher total enteroscopy rate and
      diagnostic rate will be achieved.

      Initial reports indicated that CO2 was effective during the colonoscopy ,ERCP and DBE
      examination, but it is still uncertain to the SBE procedure
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intubation depth</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 5 minutes after the examination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total enteroscopy rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 1 week after all the examinations are finished</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diagnostic rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 1 week after all the examinations are finished</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient's acceptability</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours after the examination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Procedure time</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 5 minutes after the examination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Circumstances of bowel</measure>
    <time_frame>10 minutes before/after the examination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complication rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 1 week after all the examinations are finished</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">214</enrollment>
  <condition>Intubation Depth</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Air insufflation regulator</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Room air will be used for insufflation as the Active Comparator arm</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CO2 insufflation regulator</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Device: CO2 insufflation regulator</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CO2 insufflation regulator</intervention_name>
    <description>The CO2 insufflation regulator is Olympus UCR(Olympus Optical Co., Ltd., Tokyo, Japan). The device connect the medical gas pipe joints and CO2 cylinders, then the CO2 gas will be pumped into the delivery tube which links to the water bottle until it insufflate the bowel through the SBE.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CO2 insufflation regulator</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Air insufflation</intervention_name>
    <description>The air will be pumped into the delivery tube which links to the water bottle until it insufflate the bowel through the SBE.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Air insufflation regulator</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patients referred for SBE at the trial centre

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age under 18 years, over 75 years Refusal of participation GIST, apparent tumor, post
             surgery Crohn's disease, Intestinal obstruction, stenosis, radiation enteritis Severe
             cardiopulmonary dysfunction
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zhizheng Ge, Ph.D. MD.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Gastroenterology, Renji Hospital, Shanghai Institute of Digestive Diseases, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine   Shanghai</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Zhizheng Ge, MD. Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>18621890923</phone>
    <email>zhizhengge@yahoo.com.cn</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Gastroenterology, Renji Hospital, Shanghai Institute of Digestive Diseases, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200127</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Zhizheng Ge, MD. Ph.D</last_name>
      <phone>18621890923</phone>
      <email>zhizhengge@yahoo.com.cn</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Zhizheng Ge, MD. Ph.D</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tsujikawa T, Saitoh Y, Andoh A, Imaeda H, Hata K, Minematsu H, Senoh K, Hayafuji K, Ogawa A, Nakahara T, Sasaki M, Fujiyama Y. Novel single-balloon enteroscopy for diagnosis and treatment of the small intestine: preliminary experiences. Endoscopy. 2008 Jan;40(1):11-5. Epub 2007 Dec 4.</citation>
    <PMID>18058613</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kawamura T, Yasuda K, Tanaka K, Uno K, Ueda M, Sanada K, Nakajima M. Clinical evaluation of a newly developed single-balloon enteroscope. Gastrointest Endosc. 2008 Dec;68(6):1112-6. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2008.03.1063. Epub 2008 Jul 2.</citation>
    <PMID>18599052</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frantz DJ, Dellon ES, Grimm IS, Morgan DR. Single-balloon enteroscopy: results from an initial experience at a U.S. tertiary-care center. Gastrointest Endosc. 2010 Aug;72(2):422-6. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2010.03.1117. Epub 2010 Jun 11.</citation>
    <PMID>20541189</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Domagk D, Bretthauer M, Lenz P, Aabakken L, Ullerich H, Maaser C, Domschke W, Kucharzik T. Carbon dioxide insufflation improves intubation depth in double-balloon enteroscopy: a randomized, controlled, double-blind trial. Endoscopy. 2007 Dec;39(12):1064-7.</citation>
    <PMID>18072057</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dellon ES, Hawk JS, Grimm IS, Shaheen NJ. The use of carbon dioxide for insufflation during GI endoscopy: a systematic review. Gastrointest Endosc. 2009 Apr;69(4):843-9. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2008.05.067. Epub 2009 Jan 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19152906</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hirai F, Beppu T, Nishimura T, Takatsu N, Ashizuka S, Seki T, Hisabe T, Nagahama T, Yao K, Matsui T, Beppu T, Nakashima R, Inada N, Tajiri E, Mitsuru H, Shigematsu H. Carbon dioxide insufflation compared with air insufflation in double-balloon enteroscopy: a prospective, randomized, double-blind trial. Gastrointest Endosc. 2011 Apr;73(4):743-9. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2010.10.003. Epub 2011 Jan 14.</citation>
    <PMID>21237455</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>May A, Färber M, Aschmoneit I, Pohl J, Manner H, Lotterer E, Möschler O, Kunz J, Gossner L, Mönkemüller K, Ell C. Prospective multicenter trial comparing push-and-pull enteroscopy with the single- and double-balloon techniques in patients with small-bowel disorders. Am J Gastroenterol. 2010 Mar;105(3):575-81. doi: 10.1038/ajg.2009.712. Epub 2010 Jan 5.</citation>
    <PMID>20051942</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iddan G, Meron G, Glukhovsky A, Swain P. Wireless capsule endoscopy. Nature. 2000 May 25;405(6785):417.</citation>
    <PMID>10839527</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yamamoto H, Sekine Y, Sato Y, Higashizawa T, Miyata T, Iino S, Ido K, Sugano K. Total enteroscopy with a nonsurgical steerable double-balloon method. Gastrointest Endosc. 2001 Feb;53(2):216-20.</citation>
    <PMID>11174299</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ramchandani M, Reddy DN, Gupta R, Lakhtakia S, Tandan M, Rao GV, Darisetty S. Diagnostic yield and therapeutic impact of single-balloon enteroscopy: series of 106 cases. J Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2009 Oct;24(10):1631-8. doi: 10.1111/j.1440-1746.2009.05936.x. Epub 2009 Aug 3.</citation>
    <PMID>19686408</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aktas H, de Ridder L, Haringsma J, Kuipers EJ, Mensink PB. Complications of single-balloon enteroscopy: a prospective evaluation of 166 procedures. Endoscopy. 2010 May;42(5):365-8. doi: 10.1055/s-0029-1243931. Epub 2010 Feb 22.</citation>
    <PMID>20178072</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Upchurch BR, Sanaka MR, Lopez AR, Vargo JJ. The clinical utility of single-balloon enteroscopy: a single-center experience of 172 procedures. Gastrointest Endosc. 2010 Jun;71(7):1218-23. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2010.01.012. Epub 2010 Apr 20.</citation>
    <PMID>20409544</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 18, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 18, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Shanghai Jiao Tong University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Zhizheng Ge</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Shanghai Institute of Digestive Disease，Renji Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Single-Balloon Enteroscopy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
