<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="142879">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01827384</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130105</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-C-0105</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01827384</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>NCI-MPACT: Molecular Profiling-Based Assignment of Cancer Therapy for Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>Molecular Profiling-based Assignment of Cancer Therapy for Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Variations in the genes in some tumors play an important role in how a cancer grows and
      develops. Looking at these variations and finding drugs that target them is one possible way
      to treat cancer. However, researchers do not yet know if this way works better than standard
      cancer treatments. Researchers are interested in studying people who have tumor gene
      variations in different types of cancer cells. They want to see if these people benefit more
      from being treated with a drug that specifically targets that variation than from being
      treated with drugs that do not. To do so, they will look at the genes from people with
      different sorts of cancers. Based on this analysis, they will offer treatments based on the
      specific gene variations found on the tumor cells.

      Objectives:

      - To see if choosing specific treatment options for tumor gene variations is more safe and
      effective than standard cancer treatments.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals at least 18 years of age who have advanced solid tumors that have not
      responded to standard treatments.

      Design:

        -  This study will try four different drugs or drug combinations for cancer treatment.
           Some of these treatments target specific tumor gene variations, while others do not.
           However, all drugs are intended to be used as possible cancer treatment options.

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. Blood and urine
           samples will be collected. Imaging studies and heart and lung function tests will also
           be performed.

        -  Participants will provide a tumor tissue sample for study. This sample will be used to
           determine possible tumor gene variations.

        -  Participants will be divided into groups based on their tumor gene variation. Within
           these groups, they will be further divided into two possible study arms. One arm will
           receive a drug or drug combination designed to target the tumor gene variation. The
           other arm will receive a drug or drug combination that is not designed to target the
           variation.

        -  Participants will receive their study drugs according to the standard dosing schedule
           for their treatment. Treatment will be monitored with frequent blood tests and imaging
           studies. If the cancer gets worse while a participant is on a study drug not designed
           to work on the tumor   s gene variation, the study doctors may change the drug to one
           thought to work on that variation.

        -  Participants will have frequent follow-up visits to monitor the outcome of the
           treatment. These visits may include additional tumor biopsies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      -Targeted therapy based on identifying underlying genetic aberrations within the tumor is
      the goal of personalized medicine. This pilot trial aims to establish whether advanced
      cancer patients who have no treatment options with proven benefit, and with tumor
      mutations/amplifications in one of 3 genetic pathways (DNA repair, PI3K, or RAS/RAF) are
      more likely to derive clinical benefit if treated with agents targeting that pathway than if
      treated with agents that do not. Each patient will be randomly assigned to receive the
      recommended Phase II dose of either a study drug identified to work on their tumor   s
      mutation/aberrant pathway, or an agent from the complementary set not identified to work on
      the mutations/amplifications of interest.

      Objectives:

      -Compare the response rate (CR+PR) and/or 4-month PFS for treatment with agents chosen based
      on the presence of specific mutations/amplifications in patient tumors with the response
      rate for treatment with agents randomly chosen from the complementary set of agents not
      identified to work on the mutations/amplifications of interest.

      Eligibility:

        -  Adult patients with histologically documented solid tumors whose disease has progressed
           following at least one line of standard therapy and/or for which no standard treatment
           is available that has been shown to improve survival.

        -  Tumor amenable to percutaneous biopsy, and willingness to undergo tumor biopsy.

      Study Design:

        -  Patients enrolled on study will have a tumor biopsy sequenced in a CLIA-certified lab
           for specific mutations/amplifications of interest: DNA repair pathways, PI3K pathway,
           or RAS/RAF/MEK pathway. If such mutations are not detected, the patient will be taken
           off study.

             -  Patients with melanoma and known BRAF V600E mutations need to have received and
                progressed on specific BRAF inhibitor therapy.

             -  Patients with ovarian or breast cancer and BRCA mutations will not receive ABT-888
                on study for the treatment of BRCA-positive tumors. They will only be eligible to
                receive any of the study treatments if they have other mutations of interest.

             -  Patients with NSCLC should have been previously tested for the presence of EGFR
                and ALK mutations, and, if detected, should have received and progressed on EGFR
                or ALK TKI therapy.

        -  Patients in whom a mutation of interest is detected will be randomized 2:1 into Arms A
           or B: Arm A will receive an agent prospectively identified to target that
           mutation/pathway; Arm B will receive an agent from the complementary set (not
           prospectively identified to target one of their mutations). Patients in Arm B will be
           allowed to cross over at the time of disease progression to a treatment regimen based
           on their mutational analysis.

        -  Targeted drugs will be administered at recommended Phase II doses and schedules: (1)
           ABT-888 (PARP inhibitor) with temozolomide for defects in the DNA repair pathway; (2)
           MK-1775 (Wee1 inhibitor) plus carboplatin for defects in DNA repair pathway; (3)
           Everolimus (mTOR inhibitor) for mutations in the PI3K pathway; or (4) Trametinib DMSO
           (MEK inhibitor) for mutations in the RAS/RAF/MEK pathway.

        -  Given the relative frequencies of the mutations, approximately 700 patients will need
           to be enrolled to acquire 180 evaluable patients; the initial feasibility part of the
           trial will be conducted in the first 60 evaluable patients, requiring enrollment of
           100-150 patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare response rate and/or 4-month PFS for agents chosen based on presence of specific tumor mutations/amplifications with response rate for agents randomly chosen from complementary set of agents not identified to target mutations of interest...</measure>
    <time_frame>1.5 - 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">700</enrollment>
  <condition>Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Receive an agent from the set corresponding to one of their mutation/amplication categories.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Receive an agent chosen, by physician choice, from the complementary set (not corresponding to one of their mutation/amplication categories).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Temozolomide</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Everolimus</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trametinib DMSO</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ABT-888</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MK-1775</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA: Tumor Biopsy Sequencing

          -  Patients with histologically documented solid tumors whose disease has progressed
             following at least one line of standard therapy and/or no standard of treatment
             exists that has been shown to prolong survival.

          -  Patient must have tumor amenable to percutaneous biopsy and be willing to undergo a
             tumor biopsy.

          -  Patients must have measurable disease, defined as at least one lesion that can be
             accurately measured in at least one dimension (longest diameter to be recorded) as
             greater than or equal to 20 mm with conventional techniques or as greater than or
             equal to 10 mm with spiral CT scan.

          -  Patients with bone metastases or hypercalcemia on intravenous bisphosphonate
             treatment are eligible to participate and may continue this treatment.

          -  Age greater than or equal 18 years. Children are excluded from this study, but may be
             eligible for future pediatric trials.

          -  Karnofsky performance status greater than or equal 70

          -  Life expectancy greater thatn 3 months.

          -  Patients must have adequate organ and marrow function as defined below:

               -  absolute neutrophil count greater than or equal to 1,500 per microliters (mcL)

               -  platelets greater than or equal to 100,000 per microliters (mcL)

               -  total bilirubin less than 1.5 times institutional upper limit of normal

               -  AST(SGOT)/ALT(SGPT) less than or equal to 3 times institutional upper limit of
                  normal

               -  creatinine less than 1.5 times institutional upper limit of normal

        OR

          -  creatinine clearance greater than or equal to 60 mL/min for patients with creatinine
             levels greater than  or equal to 1.5 times institutional upper limit of normal.

          -  PTT less than or equal to 40 seconds unless due to lupus coagulant

               -  The effects of these targeted agents on the developing human fetus are unknown.
                  For this reason, women of childbearing potential and men must agree to use
                  adequate contraception prior to study entry, for the duration of study
                  participation, and for 3 months after completion of study. Because there may be
                  a risk for adverse events in nursing infants secondary to treatment of the
                  mother with these agents, breastfeeding should be discontinued while the patient
                  is on this trial and for 30 days following last dose of study drug.

               -  Patients with history of CNS metastases who have received treatment and who
                  either have not had seizures or have been on stable doses of anti-seizure
                  medicine and had no seizures for 2 weeks will be eligible. Enzyme-inducing
                  anticonvulsants are contraindicated.

               -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent
                  document.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA: Tumor Biopsy Sequencing

          -  Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding.

          -  Patients who are receiving any other investigational agents.

          -  Patients with uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to
             psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study
             requirements, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, myocardial infarction in the past 6 months, or left ventricular ejection
             fraction (LVEF) less than or equal to the institutional lower limit of normal (by
             ECHO or MUGA), invasive fungal infections, or active hepatitis B infection are not
             eligible to participate. Testing for hepatitis B or other infections

        for eligibility will be performed only if clinically indicated.

          -  Patients who have had prior treatment with any PARP inhibitor are ineligible to
             receive treatment with a PARP inhibitor on this study.

          -  Patients who have received prior temozolomide should not be excluded solely because
             of receiving prior temozolomide, unless it was in combination with a PARP inhibitor.
             Such patients will not be offered ABT-888 with temozolomide, but are eligible to
             receive other treatment regimens on study based on identified genetic mutations.

          -  Patients with gastrointestinal conditions that might predispose for drug
             intolerability or poor drug absorption (e.g., inability to take oral medication or a
             requirement for IV alimentation, prior surgical procedures affecting absorption,
             malabsorption syndrome, and active peptic ulcer disease) are excluded. Subjects with
             ulcerative colitis, inflammatory bowel disease, or a partial or complete small bowel
             obstruction are also excluded, as are any patients who cannot swallow tablets or
             capsules whole. Tablets or capsules must not be crushed or chewed; nasogastric or
             G-tube administration is not allowed.

          -  HIV-positive patients on combination antiretroviral therapy are ineligible because of
             the potential for PK interactions.

          -  Patients who require use of coumarin-derivative anticoagulants such as warfarin are
             excluded. Low molecular weight heparin is permitted for prophylactic or therapeutic
             use. Only patients who meet the screening criteria and have a tumor biopsy determined
             to have one of the specific mutations/amplifications of interest will be eligible to
             participate in the treatment part of this protocol.

        INCLUSION CRITERIA: Treatment

          -  Patient must have predefined targeted mutation in tumor biopsy.

          -  Patients with histologically documented solid tumors whose disease has progressed
             following at least one line of standard therapy or for which no standard therapy
             exists that has been shown to prolong survival.

          -  Patients must have measurable disease, defined as at least one lesion that can be
             accurately measured in at least one dimension (longest diameter to be recorded) as
             greater than or equal to 20 mm with conventional techniques or as greater than or
             equal 10 mm with spiral CT scan.

          -  Any prior therapy, radiotherapy, or major surgery must have been completed greater
             than or equal 3 weeks (greater than 6 weeks for nitrosoureas or mitomycin C) prior to
             enrollment on protocol, and the participant must have recovered to eligibility levels
             from prior toxicity. RFA of localized lesions should have been performed greater than
             or equal 2 weeks prior to enrollment.

          -  Patients who have had prior treatment with any of the other investigational agents on
             this protocol are eligible but will not receive the same investigational agent;
             instead, patients will receive an investigational agent prospectively identified to
             work on a different target in their tumor   s mutation/aberrant pathway.

          -  Patients with bone metastases or hypercalcemia on intravenous bisphosphonate
             treatment are eligible to participate and may continue this treatment.

          -  Age greater than or equal 18 years. Because no dosing or adverse event data are
             currently available on the use of study investigational agents in patients less than
             18 years of age, children are excluded from this study, but may be eligible for
             future pediatric trials.

          -  Karnofsky performance status greater than or equal 70%.

          -  Life expectancy greater than 3 months.

          -  Patients must have adequate organ and marrow function as defined below:

               -  absolute neutrophil count greater than or equal 1,500 per microliters (mcL)

               -  platelets greater than or equal 100,000 per microliters (mcL)

               -  total bilirubin less than 1.5 times institutional upper limit of normal

               -  AST(SGOT)/ALT(SGPT) less than or equal to 3 times institutional upper limit of
                  normal

               -  creatinine less than 1.5 times institutional upper limit of normal

        OR

          -  creatinine clearance greater than or equal 60 mL/min for patients with creatinine
             levels greater than or equal 1.5 times institutional upper limit of normal.

               -  The effects of these targeted agents on the developing human fetus are unknown.
                  For this reason, women of childbearing potential and men must agree to use
                  adequate contraception (abstinence; female use of hormonal methods, or barrier
                  methods of birth control; male use of a condom) prior to study entry, for the
                  duration of study participation, and for 3 months after completion of study.
                  Because there may be a risk for adverse events in nursing infants secondary to
                  treatment of the mother with these agents, breastfeeding should be discontinued
                  while the patient is on this trial and for 30 days following last dose of study
                  drug.

               -  Patients with melanoma and known BRAF V600E mutations must have received and
                  progressed on specific BRAF inhibitor therapy.

               -  Patients with NSCLC must have previously been tested for the presence of EGFR
                  mutations, and, if detected, should have received and progressed on EGFR
                  tyrosine kinase inhibitor (TKI) therapy.

               -  Patients with ovarian or breast cancer and BRCA mutations will not receive ABT-
                  888 on study. There is already some evidence of clinical benefit of treating
                  patients with known BRCA-positive tumors with PARP inhibitors. Such patients can
                  pursue therapy on trials specifically testing PARP inhibitors in BRCApositive
                  patients with advanced tumors. If these patients have other mutations of
                  interest as defined in the protocol, they will be eligible to receive agents
                  based on that mutation.

               -  Patients who have poorly controlled diabetes (defined as fasting blood glucose
                  of greater than 160 mg/dL (CTCAE Grade greater than or equal to 2) and HgA1c
                  greater than 8%) are ineligible to receive treatment with everolimus on study.

               -  Patients with a known immediate or delayed hypersensitivity reaction or
                  idiosyncrasy to drugs chemically related to Trametinib DMSO, its excipients, or
                  DMSO, are ineligible to receive treatment with Trametinib DMSO.

               -  Patients with a history or current evidence/risk of retinal vein occlusion (RVO)
                  or central serous retinopathy (CSR) or predisposing factors to RVO or CSR (e.g.,
                  uncontrolled glaucoma or ocular hypertension, uncontrolled systemic disease such
                  as hypertension, diabetes mellitus, or history of hyperviscosity or
                  hypercoagulability syndromes), are ineligible to receive treatment with
                  Trametinib DMSO. Visible retinal pathology (as assessed by ophthalmic exam) that
                  is considered a risk factor for RVO or CSR includes evidence of new optic disc
                  cupping or new visual field defects, or intraocular pressure greater than 21 mm
                  Hg.

               -  Patients with a history of seizures are not eligible to receive ABT-888.
                  Patients with brain metastatic disease must have remained stable for greater
                  than 3 months and be off steroid treatment to be eligible to receive ABT-888.

               -  Patients who have received prior carboplatin or MK-1775 would not be excluded
                  unless the two drugs were administered in combination. Patients who have
                  received prior carboplatin in combination with MK 1775 would still be eligible
                  to receive other study treatment regimens based on identified genetic
                  mutation(s), other than carboplatin plus MK-1775.

               -  Patients who have had prior treatment with any PARP inhibitor are ineligible to
                  receive treatment with a PARP inhibitor on this study. Patients who have
                  received prior temozolomide should not be excluded solely because of receiving
                  prior temozolomide, unless it was in combination with a PARP inhibitor. Patients
                  who have received temozolomide with a PARP inhibitor in the past are eligible to
                  participate but will not receive ABT-888 with temozolomide on study. Such
                  patients are eligible to receive other treatment regimens on study based on
                  identified genetic mutations.

               -  Patients who have received prior everolimus or other mTOR inhibitors would not
                  be eligible to receive everolimus on study. If these patients have mutations of
                  interest in pathways other than the pI3K pathway as defined in the protocol,
                  they will be eligible to receive agents based on that mutation.

               -  Patients who have received prior MEK inhibitors would not be eligible to receive
                  trametinib DMSO on study. If these patients have mutations of interest in
                  pathways other than the RAS pathway as defined in the protocol, they will be
                  eligible to receive agents based on that mutation.

               -  Patients with a history of interstitial lung disease or pneumonitis will not be
                  assigned treatment with everolimus.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA: Treatment

          -  Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding.

          -  Patients who are receiving any other investigational agents.

          -  Patients with active brain metastases or carcinomatous meningitis are excluded from
             this clinical trial. Patients whose brain metastatic disease status has remained
             stable for greater than 3 months and are off steroid treatment are eligible to
             receive ABT-888; patients whose brain metastatic disease status has remained stable
             for greater than or equal to 4 weeks following treatment of the brain metastases are
             eligible for other study agents. Patients who have a history of seizures are not
             eligible to receive ABT- 888, but patients who have either not had seizures or who
             have been on stable doses of anti-seizure medicine and had no seizures for 1 month
             will be eligible for other study agents. Enzyme-inducing anticonvulsants are
             contraindicated.

          -  Patients with uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to
             psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study
             requirements, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, myocardial infarction in the past 6 months, or left ventricular ejection
             fraction (LVEF) less than or equal to the institutional lower limit of normal (by
             ECHO or MUGA), invasive fungal infections, or active hepatitis B infection are not
             eligible to participate. Testing for hepatitis B or other infections for eligibility
             will be performed only if clinically indicated.

          -  Patients with gastrointestinal conditions that might predispose for drug
             intolerability or poor drug absorption (e.g., inability to take oral medication or a
             requirement for IV alimentation, prior surgical procedures affecting absorption,
             malabsorption syndrome, and active peptic ulcer disease) are excluded. Subjects with
             ulcerative colitis, inflammatory bowel disease, or a partial or complete small bowel
             obstruction are also excluded, as are any patients who cannot swallow tablets or
             capsules whole. T...
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shivaani Kummar, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ramya Anthony</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 594-4949</phone>
    <email>parthasarathyr@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Shivaani Kummar, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 435-0517</phone>
    <email>kummars@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact National Cancer Institute Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>888-624-1937</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-C-0105.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pallis AG, Karamouzis MV. DNA repair pathways and their implication in cancer treatment. Cancer Metastasis Rev. 2010 Dec;29(4):677-85. doi: 10.1007/s10555-010-9258-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20821251</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schreiber V, Amé JC, Dollé P, Schultz I, Rinaldi B, Fraulob V, Ménissier-de Murcia J, de Murcia G. Poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase-2 (PARP-2) is required for efficient base excision DNA repair in association with PARP-1 and XRCC1. J Biol Chem. 2002 Jun 21;277(25):23028-36. Epub 2002 Apr 10.</citation>
    <PMID>11948190</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Memisoglu A, Samson L. Base excision repair in yeast and mammals. Mutat Res. 2000 Jun 30;451(1-2):39-51. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10915864</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 4, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Targeted Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Genetic Sequencing</keyword>
  <keyword>Advanced Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacodynamics</keyword>
  <keyword>Tumor Mutations</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sirolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Temozolomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
