<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="28462">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01949116</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A5314</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>11875</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01949116</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluating Safety and Effectiveness of Low-Dose Methotrexate at Reducing Inflammation in HIV-Infected Adults Taking Antiretroviral Medications</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Reducing Inflammation With Low Dose Methotrexate on Inflammatory Markers and Endothelial Function in Treated and Suppressed HIV Infection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      People with HIV infection who are taking antiretroviral therapy (ART) may be at risk for
      cardiovascular disease (CVD), which can be caused by inflammation. Methotrexate (MTX) is a
      medication used to treat inflammation in people with rheumatoid arthritis. This study will
      evaluate the safety and effectiveness of low-dose methotrexate (LDMTX) at reducing
      inflammation in HIV-infected adults.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      HIV-infected people taking ART have a higher than expected risk of premature CVD. Many
      factors likely contribute to this risk, including chronic inflammation. Strategies to reduce
      inflammation in HIV-infected people may be beneficial in reducing CVD risk, as well as other
      conditions, including kidney disease, bone disease, and neurologic complications. MTX is an
      anti-inflammatory medication used to treat people with rheumatoid arthritis. This study will
      evaluate the safety and effectiveness of LDMTX at treating inflammation and on endothelial
      function in virologically suppressed HIV-infected adults who have CVD or are at increased
      risk of CVD.

      The total study duration will be 36 weeks. Prior to enrolling in the study, participants
      will have a chest X-ray. Participants will be randomly assigned to receive LDMTX or placebo
      for 24 weeks. Participants will continue taking their antiretroviral (ARV) medications as
      usual; ARVs will not be provided by the study. At study entry, participants will undergo a
      medical and medication history, physical examination, blood collection, and adherence
      assessments. From study entry through Week 1, participants will receive either 5 mg of MTX
      or placebo once a week. For participants who are clinically stable at the Week 1 study
      visit, the dose of MTX or placebo will be increased to 10 mg once a week through Week 12.
      For participants who are clinically stable at the Week 12 study visit, the dose of MTX or
      placebo will be increased to 15 mg once a week through Week 24. Participants who do not meet
      the criteria for dose escalation will be re-evaluated at the following study visit. In
      addition to LDMTX or placebo, all participants will also receive 1 mg of folic acid once a
      day from study entry throughout Week 24.

      Additional study visits will occur at Weeks 1, 2, 4, 8, 12, 18, 24, and 36. They will
      include a physical examination, blood collection, and adherence assessments; an arm
      ultrasound test will also be performed at Weeks 12 and 24. At Week 2, some participants will
      also take part in a pharmacokinetic (PK) assessment, which will involve undergoing a blood
      collection several times over a 24-hour period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>For participants with entry CD4 T-cell count less than 700 cells/mm^3: confirmed CD4 decline greater than 33% of baseline AND to less than 350 cells/mm^3</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Week 36</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>For participants with entry CD4 T-cell count greater than or equal to 700 cells/mm^3: confirmed CD4 decline greater than 50% of baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Week 36</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Confirmed HIV-1 RNA level greater than 200 copies/mL in the absence of an interruption in ART</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Week 36</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>New or recurrent Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) category C AIDS-indicator condition</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Week 36</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evidence of HIV-associated infection, including cytomegalovirus (CMV) end-organ disease, varicella zoster, or Epstein-Barr virus (EBV)-related clinical disease</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Week 36</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Requirement for LDMTX discontinuation for confirmed Grade 3 or higher toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Week 36</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Lymphoproliferative malignancies</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Week 36</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulmonary toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Week 36</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Defined as Grade 3 or 4 dyspnea, cough, shortness of breath, which in the opinion of the local investigator, is related to the study drug but not related to other clinical causes such as asthma, influenza, etc.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline to Week 24 in brachial artery flow-mediated vasodilation (FMD) (%)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Defined as the maximum FMD (%) calculated from reactive hyperemia (RH) 60 and RH 90 relative to resting artery diameter (baseline).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline to Week 12 in brachial artery FMD (%)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline to Week 12 in brachial artery diameter (mm)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline to Week 24 in brachial artery diameter (mm)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline to Week 24 in brachial artery hyperemic flow velocity (time-integrated, cm)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline to Week 24 in levels of high-sensitivity C-reactive protein (hsCRP), interleukin-6 (IL-6), sCD163, and D-dimer</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline to Week 24 in monocyte levels, adhesion and activation indices, and CX3CR1 expression</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low-dose methotrexate (LDMTX)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>From study entry through Week 1, participants will receive 5 mg of LDMTX once a week. For participants who are clinically stable at the Week 1 study visit, the dose will be increased to 10 mg once a week through Week 12. For participants who are clinically stable at the Week 12 study visit, the dose will be increased to 15 mg once a week through Week 24. In addition to LDMTX, all participants will also receive 1 mg of folic acid once a day from study entry throughout Week 24.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>From study entry through Week 1, participants will receive 5 mg of placebo once a week. For participants who are clinically stable at the Week 1 study visit, the dose will be increased to 10 mg once a week through Week 12. For participants who are clinically stable at the Week 12 study visit, the dose will be increased to 15 mg once a week through Week 24. In addition to placebo, all participants will also receive 1 mg of folic acid once a day from study entry throughout Week 24.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methotrexate (MTX)</intervention_name>
    <description>MTX 5 mg: one 5-mg capsule by mouth once weekly
MTX 10 mg: two 5-mg capsules by mouth once weekly
MTX 15 mg: three 5-mg capsules by mouth once weekly</description>
    <arm_group_label>Low-dose methotrexate (LDMTX)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo 5 mg: one 5-mg capsule by mouth once weekly
Placebo 10 mg: two 5-mg capsules by mouth once weekly
Placebo 15 mg: three 5-mg capsules by mouth once weekly</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Folic acid</intervention_name>
    <description>1-mg tablet of folic acid by mouth once a day</description>
    <arm_group_label>Low-dose methotrexate (LDMTX)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV-1 infection, documented by any licensed rapid HIV test or HIV enzyme or
             chemiluminescence immunoassay (E/CIA) test kit at any time prior to study entry and
             confirmed by a licensed Western blot or a second antibody test by a method other than
             the initial rapid HIV and/or E/CIA, or by HIV-1 antigen, plasma HIV-1 RNA viral load.
             More information on this criterion can be found in the protocol.

          -  Currently on continuous ART for greater than or equal to 24 weeks prior to study
             entry. This is defined as continuous active therapy for the 24-week period prior to
             study entry with no treatment interruption longer than 7 consecutive days and a total
             duration off treatment of no more than 14 days in the 90 days prior to study entry.

          -  CD4 T-cell count greater than or equal to 400 cells/mm^3 obtained within 60 days
             prior to study entry by any U.S. laboratory that has a Clinical Laboratory
             Improvement Amendments (CLIA) certification or its equivalent

          -  HIV-1 RNA level below the limit of quantification (e.g., less than 40, less than 50,
             or less than 75 copies/mL, depending on the assay) using a Food and Drug
             Administration (FDA)-approved assay for at least 24 weeks prior to study entry and
             confirmed within 60 days prior to study entry. The assay used for eligibility can be
             performed by any U.S. laboratory that has a CLIA certification or its equivalent.
             NOTE: Single determinations that are between the assay quantification limit and 200
             copies/mL are allowed as long as the preceding and subsequent determinations are
             below the level of quantification.

          -  The following laboratory values obtained within 60 days prior to study entry by any
             U.S. laboratory that has a CLIA certification or its equivalent:

               1. Fasting glucose less than 180 mg/dL

               2. Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) [serum glutamic pyruvic transaminase (SGPT)] less
                  than 2 times the upper limit of normal (ULN)

               3. Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) [serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase
                  (SGOT)] less than 2 times the ULN

               4. Estimated creatinine clearance (CrCl) greater than or equal to 50 mL/min by
                  Cockcroft-Gault. NOTE: Participants who are taking tenofovir disoproxil fumarate
                  (TDF) as part of their ART regimen must have an estimated CrCl greater than or
                  equal to 60 mL/min.

               5. White blood cell (WBC) greater than 3,000/mm^3

               6. Hemoglobin greater than 12.0 g/dL

               7. Platelets greater than 150,000/mm^3

          -  Female participants who are postmenopausal (i.e., of non-childbearing potential),
             defined as having either:

               1. Appropriate medical documentation of prior complete bilateral oophorectomy
                  (i.e., surgical removal of the ovaries, resulting in &quot;surgical menopause&quot; and
                  occurring at the age at which the procedure was performed), OR

               2. Permanent cessation of previously occurring menses as a result of ovarian
                  failure with documentation of hormonal deficiency by a certified healthcare
                  provider (i.e., &quot;spontaneous menopause&quot;). More information on this criterion can
                  be found in the protocol.

          -  Male participants must agree not to participate in a conception process (i.e., active
             attempt to impregnate, sperm donation). If participating in sexual activity that
             could lead to pregnancy, the male participant must agree to the use of TWO reliable
             forms of contraceptives simultaneously while on study and for a minimum of 3 months
             after therapy. More information on this criterion can be found in the protocol.

          -  Participants who are not of reproductive potential (defined as women who have been
             postmenopausal for at least 24 consecutive months or men who have documented
             vasectomy) are eligible for the study without requiring the use of contraceptives.
             More information on this criterion can be found in the protocol.

          -  Moderate or high CVD risk defined as:

        A) Documented CVD as assessed by meeting at least 1 of 3 criteria below:

          1. Coronary artery disease (CAD): prior myocardial infarction (MI) due to
             atherosclerosis, coronary artery bypass graft surgery, percutaneous coronary
             intervention, or angiographic CAD with luminal diameter stenosis of at least one
             coronary artery at least 50%.

          2. Cerebrovascular disease: prior ischemic stroke of carotid origin, carotid
             endarterectomy or stenting, or angiographic carotid stenosis of at least 50%.

          3. Peripheral arterial disease: prior lower extremity arterial surgical or percutaneous
             revascularization procedure, or angiographic lower extremity arterial stenosis of at
             least 50%.

        OR

        B) Controlled type II diabetes mellitus (HbA1C less than or equal to 8.0% within the past
        90 days prior to study entry, regardless of use of medications)

        OR

        C) Two of the following CVD risk factors below:

          1. Current smoking: participant report of smoking at least a half a pack of cigarettes a
             day, on average, in the past month.

          2. Hypertension (HTN): two consecutive blood pressure (BP) readings with either systolic
             greater than 140 mm Hg or diastolic greater than 90 mm Hg; or on antihypertensive
             medications.

          3. Dyslipidemia: defined as non-high-density lipoprotein (HDL)-C greater than 160 mg/dL,
             regardless of medication use.

        OR

        D) One of the CVD risk factors listed in C above and a high-sensitivity C-reactive protein
        (hsCRP) greater than or equal to 2 mg/L obtained at screening.

          -  Ability and willingness of participant to provide informed consent

          -  For participants taking tenofovir (TFV) as part of their ART regimen, willingness and
             intent to participate in PK component. NOTE: The requirement for participation in the
             pharmacology component may be removed as the study progresses.

          -  Completion of the pre-entry FMD assessment. NOTE: At least one FMD must be performed
             at the site and confirmed as acceptable by the University of Wisconsin
             Atherosclerosis Imaging Research Program (UW AIRP) core lab prior to study entry.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Acute or serious illness requiring systemic treatment and/or hospitalization within
             60 days prior to study entry. NOTE: Treatment must have ended at least 60 days prior
             to study entry for eligibility.

          -  Documentation of any CDC category C AIDS-indicator condition or oropharyngeal
             candidiasis (thrush) within 90 days prior to study entry

          -  Receipt of antibiotic therapy within 30 days prior to study entry

          -  Latent tuberculosis (TB) infection (defined as a positive purified protein derivative
             [PPD] greater than or equal to 5 mm or positive interferon-gamma release assay at any
             time in the past) or evidence of latent TB on the screening chest x-ray

          -  Any treatment for latent TB within the past 6 months prior to study entry. NOTE:
             Completion of treatment for latent TB more than 6 months prior to study entry is
             permitted.

          -  TB disease requiring treatment within 48 weeks prior to study entry. NOTE:
             Participants with a history of active TB must have completed treatment at least 48
             weeks prior to study entry.

          -  Life-threatening fungal infection requiring treatment, in the opinion of the site
             investigator, within 48 weeks prior to study entry

          -  Herpes-zoster viral infection requiring treatment within 90 days prior to study entry

          -  A history of or current, active hepatitis B infection defined as positive hepatitis B
             surface antigen (HBsAg) test or positive hepatitis B virus (HBV) DNA in participants
             with isolated hepatitis B core antibody (HBcAb) positivity, defined as negative
             HBsAg, negative hepatitis B surface antibody (HBsAb), and positive HBcAb within 24
             weeks prior to study entry

          -  Chronic hepatitis C infection defined as a positive hepatitis C antibody and positive
             hepatitis C RNA at any time prior to study entry. NOTE: Participants who are positive
             for hepatitis C antibody but who are  hepatitis C virus (HCV) RNA negative are
             permitted in the study.

          -  Previously diagnosed myelodysplasia syndrome

          -  Treated lymphoproliferative disease less than or equal to 5 years prior to study
             entry

          -  Clinically significant lung disease on the screening chest x-ray that, in the opinion
             of the site investigator, places the participant at increased risk of lung toxicity
             (e.g., history of pulmonary fibrosis, interstitial lung disease, or pulmonary
             lymphoproliferative disease)

          -  Use of immunomodulators (e.g., interleukins, interferons, cyclosporine), HIV vaccine,
             systemic cytotoxic chemotherapy, or investigational therapy within 30 days prior to
             study entry

          -  Change in the ART regimen in the 12 weeks prior to study entry or intended
             modification of ART during the study. NOTE: Modifications of ART doses during the 12
             weeks prior to study entry are permitted. In addition, the change in formulation
             (e.g., from standard formulation to fixed-dose combination) is allowed within 12
             weeks prior to study entry. A within class single drug substitution (e.g., switch
             from nevirapine to efavirenz or from atazanavir to darunavir) is allowed within 12
             weeks prior to study entry, with the exception of a switch from any other nucleoside
             reverse transcriptase inhibitor (NRTI) to abacavir. No other changes in ART in the 12
             weeks prior to study entry are permitted.

          -  Known allergy/sensitivity or any hypersensitivity to components of study drug(s) or
             their formulation

          -  Average daily consumption of three or more alcoholic beverages for 4 weeks prior to
             study entry or intention to consume an average of two or more alcoholic beverages a
             day during the study. NOTE: An alcohol-containing beverage is defined as 12 ounces of
             beer, 4 ounces of wine, or 1 ounce of spirits.

          -  Active drug or alcohol use or dependence that, in the opinion of the site
             investigator, would interfere with adherence to study requirements

          -  Changes in lipid-lowering or antihypertensive medication within 90 days prior to
             study entry or expected need to modify these medications during the study. NOTE:
             Lipid-lowering medication includes: statins, fibrates, niacin (dose greater than or
             equal to 250 mg daily), and fish-oil/omega 3 fatty acids (dose greater than 1000 mg
             of marine oils daily).

          -  Vaccination (e.g., influenza, pneumococcal polysaccharide) within 14 days prior to
             study entry

          -  Anticipated need to receive vaccination (e.g., influenza, pneumococcal
             polysaccharide) within 1 week prior to Week 4, 12, 24, or 36 study visits

          -  Excess extracompartmental fluids including ascites, pericardial fluid, and pleural
             effusions which, in the opinion of the study investigators, would result in
             difficulty in monitoring the dose of MTX

          -  Use of drugs that alter folic acid metabolism such as trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole
             or reduce tubular excretion such as probenecid within 14 days prior to study entry

          -  New York Heart Association Class IV congestive heart failure

          -  Diabetes mellitus with HbA1C greater than 8.0% within the past 90 days prior to study
             entry
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Priscilla Hsue, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>San Francisco General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Judith Currier, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>UCLA CARE Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alabama Therapeutics CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294-2050</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alabama CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karen Savage, R.N., B.S.N.</last_name>
      <phone>205-975-7925</phone>
      <email>kgsavage@uab.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA CARE Center CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90035</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Arezou S. Akha</last_name>
      <phone>310-557-3798</phone>
      <email>asadighi@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSD Antiviral Research Center CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jill Kunkel</last_name>
      <phone>619-543-8080</phone>
      <email>jkunkel@ucsd.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ucsf Hiv/Aids Crs</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jay Dwyer</last_name>
      <phone>415-476-4082</phone>
      <phone_ext>353</phone_ext>
      <email>jdwyer@php.ucsf.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Harbor-UCLA CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Torrance</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90502</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mario Guerrero</last_name>
      <phone>424-201-3000</phone>
      <phone_ext>7318</phone_ext>
      <email>mguerrero@labiomed.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Hospital CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mary Graham Ray, R.N., M.S.N.</last_name>
      <phone>303-724-0712</phone>
      <email>graham.ray@ucdenver.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Baiba Berzins, M.P.H.</last_name>
      <phone>312-695-5012</phone>
      <email>Baiba@northwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ilene Wiggins, R.N.</last_name>
      <phone>410-614-2766</phone>
      <email>iwiggin1@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital CRS (MGH CRS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Theresa Flynn, R.N., M.S.N., A.N.P.</last_name>
      <phone>617-724-0072</phone>
      <email>tflynn@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham and Women's Hospital Therapeutics Clinical Research Site (BWH TCRS) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cheryl E. Keenan</last_name>
      <phone>617-732-5635</phone>
      <email>ckeenan2@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University Therapeutics (WT) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110-1010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael K. Klebert, R.N.,C., Ph.D., A.N.P.</last_name>
      <phone>314-747-1098</phone>
      <email>mklebert@dom.wustl.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New Jersey Medical School Clinical Research Center CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newark</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Janet Forcht, R.N.</last_name>
      <phone>973-972-1005</phone>
      <email>janet.forcht@rutgers.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Rochester Adult HIV Therapeutic Strategies Network CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chapel Hill CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Susan Pedersen</last_name>
      <phone>919-966-6713</phone>
      <email>spederse@med.unc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Greensboro CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Greensboro</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27401</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kim Epperson, R.N., B.S.N., CRC</last_name>
      <phone>336-832-3262</phone>
      <email>kim.epperson@conehealth.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cincinnati CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45219</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tammy Miller, R.N., A.C.R.N.</last_name>
      <phone>513-584-8373</phone>
      <email>tammy.miller@uc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Case CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jane Baum, R.N.</last_name>
      <phone>216-844-2546</phone>
      <email>jb@clevelandactu.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Penn Therapeutics, CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joseph Quinn, R.N., B.S.N.</last_name>
      <phone>215-349-8093</phone>
      <email>joseph.quinn@uphs.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carol Oriss, R.N.</last_name>
      <phone>412-383-1434</phone>
      <email>orissca@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Miriam Hospital Clinical Research Site (TMH CRS) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02906</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pamela Poethke, R.N.</last_name>
      <phone>401-793-4971</phone>
      <email>ppoethke@lifespan.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt Therapeutics (VT) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37204</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Deborah Sutherland, R.N., B.S.N., C.C.R.P.</last_name>
      <phone>615-936-8516</phone>
      <email>deborah.sutherland@vanderbilt.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Houston AIDS Research Team CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maria L. Martinez</last_name>
      <phone>713-500-6718</phone>
      <email>Maria.L.Martinez@uth.tmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 27, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 19, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Folic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin B Complex</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
