<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="102546">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01951560</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VPA-C-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01951560</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Safety and Tolerability of Valproic Acid in Healthy Volunteers or Trauma Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Single Ascending Dose, Double Blind, Placebo Controlled Study to Evaluate the Safety and Tolerability of Valproic Acid in Healthy Volunteers or Trauma Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dr. Hasan Alam</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Data and Safety Monitoring Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the first part of this study is to determine the safety and tolerability of
      ascending doses of valproic acid (also known as Depacon) administered as intravenous
      infusion (IV) in doses ranging from 15 mg/kg to 250 mg/kg in healthy subjects.

      The second part of the study will also be to determine the safety and tolerability of single
      ascending doses of valproic acid administered as IV in trauma subjects with hemorrhagic
      shock.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Part 1 of the study will be a single center study intended to assess the safety and
      tolerability of valproic acid dosages at 15 mg/kg, 30 mg/kg, 60 mg/kg, 90 mg/kg, 120 mg/kg,
      150 mg/kg 180 mg/kg, 210 mg/kg and 250 mg/kg. Up to 72 healthy subjects (9 dose groups of 8
      subjects) will receive single doses of valproic acid or placebo via a 60-min IV infusion in
      a ratio of 3:1 active drug: placebo.

      Part 2 of the study will be a multicenter, double blind, placebo-controlled study in trauma
      patients with hemorrhagic shock who are able to give consent or severe trauma patients with
      hemorrhagic shock in whom a legally authorized representative can give consent. Up to 12
      patients (2 dose groups of 6 patients) will receive single doses of valproic acid or placebo
      via a 60-min IV infusion in a ratio of 2:1 active drug : placebo. The dose levels in Part 2
      will be the two highest doses that are demonstrated to have acceptable safety profile based
      on the review of safety data from Part 1.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose limiting toxicity (DLT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Subjects will be monitored for 4 days after the one hour infusion. Dose escalation may occur if less than 2 subjects in any cohort of 8 experience DLT.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Dose limiting toxicity (DLT) will be defined as drug-related grade 2 (moderate) or higher toxicity (excluding fever, chills, nausea or other possible infusion-related effects). The maximum tolerated dose (MTD) will be declared at the dose below which 2 or more subjects experience DLT.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">88</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Individuals Safety Study</condition>
  <condition>Shock,Hemorrhagic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>valproic acid (Depacon)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Valproic acid by IV infusion over one hour</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Isotonic saline solution</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The placebo  administered by IV infusion over 1 hour</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Valproic Acid</intervention_name>
    <description>By infusion over 1 hour</description>
    <arm_group_label>valproic acid (Depacon)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Depacon</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Isotonic saline solution</intervention_name>
    <description>By infusion over 1 hour</description>
    <arm_group_label>Isotonic saline solution</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Isotonic saline solution</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female volunteers between the ages of 18 and 65 years, inclusive, in good
             health based on medical history, physical examination, ECG, and routine laboratory
             tests (blood chemistry, hematology, urinalysis, and drug screen).

          2. Female subjects must be surgically sterilized or postmenopausal. Criteria for
             menopause are surgical menopause (hysterectomy, oophorectomy) or age &gt; 45 years with
             absence of menses for greater than 12 months or a serum follicle stimulating hormone
             (FSH) elevation &gt; 25mIU/mL.(mIU/mL is the unit used to measure hCG in pregnancy
             test). Tubal ligation with menses within the past 12 months is not considered to be
             surgical sterilization.

          3. Negative urine pregnancy test in female volunteers

          4. Body mass index (BMI) between 18 kg/m2 and 30 kg/m2

          5. Subjects must be non-smokers

          6. Negative alcohol screen

          7. Willing and able to be confined to the clinical research facility as required by the
             protocol.

          8. Willing and able to comply with the investigational nature of the study and able to
             communicate well with investigators.

          9. Ability to comprehend and willingness to provide written informed consent in
             accordance with institutional and regulatory guidelines.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects with evidence or history of clinically significant hematological, renal,
             endocrine, pulmonary, gastrointestinal, cardiovascular, hepatic, psychiatric,
             neurologic, or allergic disease (including drug allergies; however, subjects with
             untreated, asymptomatic, seasonal allergies may be enrolled).

          2. Subjects with a-amylase &gt;130 U/L or lipase &gt;300 U/L or creatinine &gt; upper limit of
             normal (ULN)

          3. Subjects with &gt;2times ULN aspartate aminotransferase (AST) or ALT or &gt;1.5 times total
             bilirubin

          4. Subjects whose screening ECG demonstrates at least one of the following: heart rate &gt;
             100 bpm for more than 30 minutes,  (the combination of three of the graphical
             deflections seen on a typical ECG is called the(QRS)) &gt; 120 msec, corrected QT
             interval (QTc) &gt; 430 msec if male or 450 msec if female, prevalence rate (PR) &gt; 220
             msec or any rhythm other than sinus rhythm, sinus bradycardia (HR &lt;50 bpm), or sinus
             arrhythmia.

          5. Subjects with a history of alcohol consumption exceeding 14 drinks/week on average
             within the 6 months before study entry.

          6. Subjects whose sitting blood pressure is above 140/90 mmHg on 2 evaluations at least
             10 minutes apart at screening.

          7. Subjects who have donated blood in excess of 500 mL within 60 days prior to the first
             dose of study medication.

          8. Subjects with a positive result on drug screen, hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg),
             hepatitis C (HCV), or human immunodeficiency (HIV) tests

          9. Subjects who have used prescription or non-prescription drugs, vitamins, herbal
             supplements or dietary supplements within 14 days prior to the first dose of study
             medication. Subjects who have used acetaminophen at doses of &lt; 2 grams/day will be
             eligible for study entry.

         10. Subjects who have been treated with an investigational drug within 30 days.

         11. Subjects who have previously received or are currently taking valproic acid.

         12. Subjects who have a history of drug abuse.

         13. Subjects who are not willing to abstain from consuming products containing caffeine
             (including chocolate), methyl xanthine, or alcohol from Day -1 through the end of the
             pharmacokinetics (PK) study (day 4 for part 1 subjects).

         14. Subjects who have had a febrile illness within 5 days prior to the first dose of
             study medication.

         15. Subjects with inadequate venous access.

         16. Subjects vaccinated within 30 days prior to the first dose of study medication. -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hasan Alam, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tess Bonham, BS, CCRP</last_name>
    <email>tbonham@umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bonham</last_name>
      <email>tbonham@umich.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hasan Alam, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://umclinicalstudies.org/</url>
    <description>University of Michigan Clinical Studies Registry</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 23, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 23, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Hasan Alam</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Hasan Alam, MD, Norman Thompson Professor of Surgery Section Head, General Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Shock, Hemorrhagic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Valproic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
