<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="55444">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02043132</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013-060</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02043132</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tranexamic Acid in Reverse Total Shoulder Arthroplasty</brief_title>
  <acronym>TXA</acronym>
  <official_title>Intravenous Tranexamic Acid to Reduce Blood Loss in Reverse Total Shoulder Arthroplasty</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>William Beaumont Hospitals</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>William Beaumont Hospitals</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To the Investigators' knowledge, TXA has not been studied in the setting of reverse total
      shoulder arthroplasty.  We propose a double-blinded, randomized, controlled trial comparing
      perioperative administration of TXA to placebo in the setting of RTSA. The purpose of this
      study is to examine the efficacy of TXA in reducing overall blood loss and transfusion rates
      in patients undergoing reverse total shoulder arthroplasty.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Shoulder arthroplasty is a procedure used to relieve pain and dysfunction associated with
      arthritic destruction of the gleno-humeral joint.  It has been demonstrated that in patients
      with concomitant rotator cuff deficiency, reverse total shoulder arthroplasty (rTSA) is an
      efficacious procedure that relieves pain as well as increases the lever-arm of the deltoid
      muscle, thus improving post-operative strength and range of motion.

      However, perioperative blood loss in total shoulder arthroplasty can be significant, with an
      overall rate of allogeneic blood transfusion reported to be 7.4%-43% [1-5]. Patients
      undergoing reverse total shoulder arthroplasty are at even further risk of requiring a
      postoperative blood transfusion [2]. Blood transfusions are associated with significant
      risks to patient health that range from mild to life threatening.

      Tranexamic acid (TXA) is an antifibrinolytic medication (reduces the destruction of blood
      clots, thus promoting the ability to stop bleeding) that is frequently used to reduce
      perioperative blood loss, blood transfusions and associated costs in major cardiac,
      vascular, obstetric, and orthopedic procedures.   Currently, TXA is increasingly used in
      orthopedic joint reconstructive surgery and has proven to be safe and effective in reducing
      blood loss following total knee arthroplasty (TKA) and total hip arthroplasty (THA) [11-33].
       Multiple recent meta-analyses have found that use of TXA in the setting of TKA and THA
      leads to significantly less overall blood loss and lower rates of blood transfusion without
      increasing rates of venous thromboembolism (VTE) or other complications [34-37].  TXA is now
      on formulary at William Beaumont Hospital.

      100 patients slated to undergo elective reverse total shoulder arthroplasty will be
      recruited and randomized to receive either an infusion of the standard dose of TXA (10mg/kg)
      or placebo (an equivalent volume of normal saline) within 60 minutes prior to surgery and at
      wound closure.

      Adult subjects 18 years of age or older will participate in this study after the objectives,
      methods, and potential hazards of the study have been fully explained, and after they have
      signed the informed consent form.  The Investigator or designee is responsible for keeping a
      record of all subjects who sign an informed consent form for entry into this study

      DATA AND SAFETY MONITORING PLAN Beaumont Research will follow their standard operating
      policy and procedure for establishing a group of designated Beaumont Hospital faculty that
      will be responsible for data and safety monitoring. This group will include a clinician,
      physician, scientific member and statistician. They will meet twice throughout the course of
      the study. A medical monitor was not appointed since this is a single-site study; Dr. J.
      Michael Wiater will personally oversee the health and well-being of all patients and submit
      AE reports, and the designated group will directly review all adverse event reports.
      Beaumont's Human Investigation Committee will review the data safety monitoring plan as part
      of their IRB approval process.

      Study data will be transcribed by study personnel from the source documents into an
      electronic database maintained in Excel.  The data collections forms are to be completed by
      the research nurse at the time of the data collection so that they always reflect the latest
      observations on the subjects participating in the study. Demographic data will be filled in
      preoperatively, intraoperative blood loss will be recorded in the OR, postoperative blood
      loss and transfusion will be collected retrospectively, and complications will be recorded
      as they occur or at 2 and 6 week follow-up.  All data entries, corrections and alterations
      must be made by the investigator or other authorized study personnel.  The Research
      Institute will complete internal auditing at random intervals during the study for data
      integrity, proper informed consent process implementation and documentation, protocol
      adherence, and patient safety reporting compliance to regulatory bodies.

      Descriptive statistics will be provided for all data collected. Missing data will remain
      missing and will not be replaced by substitutions or interpolations. Statistical software
      (SPSS, IBM, Inc) will be used for all analyses. Baseline and demographic data will be
      compared between the 2 randomization arms to determine if any imbalances exist. Categorical
      variables will be shown as counts and % frequencies. They will be examined using Pearson's
      Chi-square where appropriate (expected frequency&gt;5), otherwise a Fisher's Exact test will be
      used. Continuous variables will be examined for normality. Normally distributed variables
      will be analyzed using t-tests and non-normally distributed variables will be examined using
      non-parametric Wilcoxon rank tests. All continuous variables will be shown as means+/- the
      standard deviation followed by the median and (25th, 75th percentiles) where needed.

      The primary outcome of intraoperative and postoperative blood loss and postoperative drop in
      Hb will be examined for normality. Normally distributed variables will be analyzed using
      t-tests and non-normally distributed variables will be examined using non-parametric
      Wilcoxon rank tests. Total number of postoperative transfusions and total number of patients
      requiring postoperative transfusions will be shown as counts and % frequencies. They will be
      examined using Pearson's Chi-square where appropriate (expected frequency&gt;5), otherwise a
      Fisher's Exact test will be used.

      The secondary outcomes of systemic and surgical site complications will be examined between
      the two randomization arms using Pearson's Chi-square where appropriate (expected
      frequency&gt;5), otherwise a Fisher's Exact test will be used.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perioperative blood loss</measure>
    <time_frame>Surgery start time to 36 hours post start time</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The minimum hemoglobin in the postoperative period (Hbmin (g/L)) will be compared to the preoperative baseline levels. Total hemoglobin loss in grams will be estimated using the formula for total blood volume and by the method of Good et al.
Blood Volume (mL) Total blood Loss (mL) Intraoperative blood loss (total volume of cell-saver transfused) + total drain output Total number of postoperative transfusions</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>systemic complication</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6-weeks post-operatively</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The occurrence of the following systemic and surgical site complications within 6 weeks of surgery will be recorded. Data will be obtained from EMR and from patient at standard of care 2 week and 6 week follow-up appointment.
Pulmonary Embolism</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>systemic complication</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6-weeks post-operatively</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The occurrence of the following systemic and surgical site complications within 6 weeks of surgery will be recorded. Data will be obtained from EMR and from patient at standard of care 2 week and 6 week follow-up appointment.
Myocardial infarction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Systemic complication</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6-weeks post-operatively</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The occurrence of the following systemic and surgical site complications within 6 weeks of surgery will be recorded. Data will be obtained from EMR and from patient at standard of care 2 week and 6 week follow-up appointment.
Deep venous thrombosis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Surgical site complication</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6-weeks post-operatively</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The occurrence of the following systemic and surgical site complications within 6 weeks of surgery will be recorded. Data will be obtained from EMR and from patient at standard of care 2 week and 6 week follow-up appointment.
Hematoma</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Surgical site complication</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6-weeks post-operatively</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The occurrence of the following systemic and surgical site complications within 6 weeks of surgery will be recorded. Data will be obtained from EMR and from patient at standard of care 2 week and 6 week follow-up appointment.
Infection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Myocardial infarction indicator CK-MB</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 weeks post-operatively</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>CK-MB of 100 µg/L or more</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>myocardial infarction indicator Troponin</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6-weeks post-operatively</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>troponin-I of 3.0 µg/L or more</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Myocardial Infarction indicator EKG</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6-weeks postoperatively</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Appearance of new postoperative Q waves on the EKG of more than 0.03 seconds</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Myocardial infarction indicator Echocardiogram</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6-weeks post-operatively</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>A new hypokinetic or akinetic area in the left or right ventricle by echocardiography</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Shoulder Joint Disease</condition>
  <condition>Complications; Arthroplasty</condition>
  <condition>Intraoperative Complications</condition>
  <condition>Blood Loss, Surgical</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tranexamic acid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Infusion Tranexamic acid on study subjects. They will be randomized to receive  an infusion of the standard dose of Tranexamic acid (10mg/kg)  One dose will be given by the bedside nurse within 60 minutes prior to surgery and a second dose will be given at wound closure. Infusion will be given along with standard preoperative and operative infusion; no additional infusion will be necessary.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Saline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Infusion of placebo on study subjects. They will be randomized to receive  an infusion of placebo (an equivalent volume of normal saline). One dose will be given by the bedside nurse within 60 minutes prior to surgery and a second dose will be given at wound closure. Infusion will be given along with standard preoperative and operative infusion; no additional infusion will be necessary.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Infusion Tranexamic acid or placebo.</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be randomized in a 1:1 ratio to either an infusion of the standard dose of Tranexamic acid (10mg/kg) or placebo (an equivalent volume of normal saline) within 60 minutes prior to surgery and at wound closure. The day before each patient's surgery the research coordinator will contact the research pharmacy to inform them that a patient is participating in the study.  The pharmacy will use the randomization list in sequential order and determine whether that patient will receive Tranexamic acid or placebo and will provide two unlabeled IV bags (patient receives two doses) of the appropriate solution.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tranexamic acid</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TXA</other_name>
    <other_name>Tranexamic acid</other_name>
    <other_name>Antifibrinolytic</other_name>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
    <other_name>Normal saline</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients undergoing scheduled primary reverse total shoulder arthroplasty performed
             by J. Michael Wiater, MD.

          2. Patients age 18 and older

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant* or breast-feeding women

          2. Allergy to tranexamic acid

          3. Acquired disturbances of color vision

          4. Use of estrogen containing medications (i.e. oral contraceptive pills)

          5. Hormone replacement therapy

          6. Preoperative anemia [Hemoglobin (Hb) &lt; 11g/dL in females, Hb &lt; 12 g/dL in males]

          7. Refusal of blood products

          8. Preoperative use of anticoagulant therapy within 5 days prior to surgery

               1. Coumadin

               2. Heparin

               3. Low molecular weight heparin

               4. Factor Xa inhibitors

          9. Thrombin inhibitors

         10. Coagulopathy

         11. Thrombophilia

         12. Antithrombin deficiency

         13. Factor V Leiden

         14. Antiphospholipid Syndrome

         15. Protein C and S deficiency

         16. History of heparin induced thrombocytopenia

         17. Sickle cell anemia

         18. Myeloproliferative disorders

         19. Platelet &lt; 150,00 mm3

         20. International Normalized Ratio (INR) &gt; 1.4

         21. Partial Thromboplastin Time (PTT) &gt; 1.4 times normal

         22. A history of arterial or venous thromboembolism

         23. Cerebral Vascular Accident

         24. Deep Vein Thrombosis

         25. Pulmonary Embolism

         26. Subarachnoid hemorrhage

         27. Active intravascular clotting

         28. Major comorbidities

         29. Coronary artery disease (New York Heart Association Class III or IV)

         30. Previous MI

         31. Severe pulmonary disease (FEV &lt;50% normal)

         32. Plasma creatinine &gt; 115 μmol/L in males, &gt; 100 μmol/L in females, or hepatic failure)

        34. Participation in another clinical trial 35. *All women of child bearing potential must
        have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael J Wiater, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>William Beaumont Hospitals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kevin Baker, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>William Beaumont Hospitals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael J Wiater, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>248-644-3920</phone>
    <email>mwiater@beaumont.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tessa Buhovecky, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>248-551-6059</phone>
    <email>Tessa.Buhovecky@beaumont.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>William Beaumont Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Royal Oak</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48073</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tessa Buhovecky, R.N.</last_name>
      <phone>248-551-6059</phone>
      <email>tessa.buhovecky@beaumont.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Brian M Walker, M.S.</last_name>
      <phone>248-551-7930</phone>
      <email>bwalker@beaumont.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Brett Wiater, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kevin Baker, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hardy JC, Hung M, Snow BJ, Martin CL, Tashjian RZ, Burks RT, Greis PE. Blood transfusion associated with shoulder arthroplasty. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2013 Feb;22(2):233-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jse.2012.04.013. Epub 2012 Aug 29.</citation>
    <PMID>22938787</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gruson KI, Accousti KJ, Parsons BO, Pillai G, Flatow EL. Transfusion after shoulder arthroplasty: an analysis of rates and risk factors. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2009 Mar-Apr;18(2):225-30. doi: 10.1016/j.jse.2008.08.005. Epub 2008 Dec 31.</citation>
    <PMID>19119020</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schumer RA, Chae JS, Markert RJ, Sprott D, Crosby LA. Predicting transfusion in shoulder arthroplasty. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2010 Jan;19(1):91-6. doi: 10.1016/j.jse.2009.05.001. Epub .</citation>
    <PMID>19664937</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Millett PJ, Porramatikul M, Chen N, Zurakowski D, Warner JJ. Analysis of transfusion predictors in shoulder arthroplasty. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2006 Jun;88(6):1223-30.</citation>
    <PMID>16757754</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sperling JW, Duncan SF, Cofield RH, Schleck CD, Harmsen WS. Incidence and risk factors for blood transfusion in shoulder arthroplasty. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2005 Nov-Dec;14(6):599-601.</citation>
    <PMID>16337526</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Samama CM. A direct antifibrinolytic agent in major orthopedic surgery. Orthopedics. 2004 Jun;27(6 Suppl):s675-80. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15239556</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dunn CJ, Goa KL. Tranexamic acid: a review of its use in surgery and other indications. Drugs. 1999 Jun;57(6):1005-32. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10400410</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hardy JF, Desroches J. Natural and synthetic antifibrinolytics in cardiac surgery. Can J Anaesth. 1992 Apr;39(4):353-65. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>1373346</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burry M. The decerebrate patient. J Neurosurg Nurs. 1979 Mar;11(1):6-9.</citation>
    <PMID>255562</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prentice CR. Basis of antifibrinolytic therapy. J Clin Pathol Suppl (R Coll Pathol). 1980;14:35-40. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>6159375</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alvarez JC, Santiveri FX, Ramos I, Vela E, Puig L, Escolano F. Tranexamic acid reduces blood transfusion in total knee arthroplasty even when a blood conservation program is applied. Transfusion. 2008 Mar;48(3):519-25. Epub 2007 Dec 7.</citation>
    <PMID>18067499</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benoni G, Fredin H. Fibrinolytic inhibition with tranexamic acid reduces blood loss and blood transfusion after knee arthroplasty: a prospective, randomised, double-blind study of 86 patients. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 1996 May;78(3):434-40.</citation>
    <PMID>8636182</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Camarasa MA, Ollé G, Serra-Prat M, Martín A, Sánchez M, Ricós P, Pérez A, Opisso L. Efficacy of aminocaproic, tranexamic acids in the control of bleeding during total knee replacement: a randomized clinical trial. Br J Anaesth. 2006 May;96(5):576-82. Epub 2006 Mar 10.</citation>
    <PMID>16531440</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ellis MH, Fredman B, Zohar E, Ifrach N, Jedeikin R. The effect of tourniquet application, tranexamic acid, and desmopressin on the procoagulant and fibrinolytic systems during total knee replacement. J Clin Anesth. 2001 Nov;13(7):509-13.</citation>
    <PMID>11704449</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Good L, Peterson E, Lisander B. Tranexamic acid decreases external blood loss but not hidden blood loss in total knee replacement. Br J Anaesth. 2003 May;90(5):596-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12697586</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hiippala ST, Strid LJ, Wennerstrand MI, Arvela JV, Niemela HM, Mantyla SK, Kuisma RP, Ylinen JE. Tranexamic acid radically decreases blood loss and transfusions associated with total knee arthroplasty. Anesth Analg. 1997 Apr;84(4):839-44.</citation>
    <PMID>9085968</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jansen AJ, Andreica S, Claeys M, D'Haese J, Camu F, Jochmans K. Use of tranexamic acid for an effective blood conservation strategy after total knee arthroplasty. Br J Anaesth. 1999 Oct;83(4):596-601.</citation>
    <PMID>10673876</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kakar PN, Gupta N, Govil P, Shah V. Efficacy and Safety of Tranexamic Acid in Control of Bleeding Following TKR: A Randomized Clinical Trial. Indian J Anaesth. 2009 Dec;53(6):667-71.</citation>
    <PMID>20640094</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>MacGillivray RG, Tarabichi SB, Hawari MF, Raoof NT. Tranexamic acid to reduce blood loss after bilateral total knee arthroplasty: a prospective, randomized double blind study. J Arthroplasty. 2011 Jan;26(1):24-8. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2009.11.013. Epub 2010 Feb 19.</citation>
    <PMID>20171048</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Orpen NM, Little C, Walker G, Crawfurd EJ. Tranexamic acid reduces early post-operative blood loss after total knee arthroplasty: a prospective randomised controlled trial of 29 patients. Knee. 2006 Mar;13(2):106-10. Epub 2006 Feb 17.</citation>
    <PMID>16487712</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tanaka N, Sakahashi H, Sato E, Hirose K, Ishima T, Ishii S. Timing of the administration of tranexamic acid for maximum reduction in blood loss in arthroplasty of the knee. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 2001 Jul;83(5):702-5.</citation>
    <PMID>11476309</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Veien M, Sørensen JV, Madsen F, Juelsgaard P. Tranexamic acid given intraoperatively reduces blood loss after total knee replacement: a randomized, controlled study. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2002 Nov;46(10):1206-11.</citation>
    <PMID>12421192</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wong J, Abrishami A, El Beheiry H, Mahomed NN, Roderick Davey J, Gandhi R, Syed KA, Muhammad Ovais Hasan S, De Silva Y, Chung F. Topical application of tranexamic acid reduces postoperative blood loss in total knee arthroplasty: a randomized, controlled trial. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2010 Nov 3;92(15):2503-13. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.I.01518.</citation>
    <PMID>21048170</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhang F, Gao Z, Yu J. [Clinical comparative studies on effect of tranexamic acid on blood loss associated with total knee arthroplasty]. Zhongguo Xiu Fu Chong Jian Wai Ke Za Zhi. 2007 Dec;21(12):1302-4. Chinese.</citation>
    <PMID>18277670</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Claeys MA, Vermeersch N, Haentjens P. Reduction of blood loss with tranexamic acid in primary total hip replacement surgery. Acta Chir Belg. 2007 Jul-Aug;107(4):397-401.</citation>
    <PMID>17966532</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ido K, Neo M, Asada Y, Kondo K, Morita T, Sakamoto T, Hayashi R, Kuriyama S. Reduction of blood loss using tranexamic acid in total knee and hip arthroplasties. Arch Orthop Trauma Surg. 2000;120(9):518-20.</citation>
    <PMID>11011672</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Niskanen RO, Korkala OL. Tranexamic acid reduces blood loss in cemented hip arthroplasty: a randomized, double-blind study of 39 patients with osteoarthritis. Acta Orthop. 2005 Dec;76(6):829-32.</citation>
    <PMID>16470437</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Garneti N, Field J. Bone bleeding during total hip arthroplasty after administration of tranexamic acid. J Arthroplasty. 2004 Jun;19(4):488-92.</citation>
    <PMID>15188109</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benoni G, Fredin H, Knebel R, Nilsson P. Blood conservation with tranexamic acid in total hip arthroplasty: a randomized, double-blind study in 40 primary operations. Acta Orthop Scand. 2001 Oct;72(5):442-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11728069</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ekback G, Axelsson K, Ryttberg L, Edlund B, Kjellberg J, Weckstrom J, Carlsson O, Schott U. Tranexamic acid reduces blood loss in total hip replacement surgery. Anesth Analg. 2000 Nov;91(5):1124-30.</citation>
    <PMID>11049894</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johansson T, Pettersson LG, Lisander B. Tranexamic acid in total hip arthroplasty saves blood and money: a randomized, double-blind study in 100 patients. Acta Orthop. 2005 Jun;76(3):314-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16156456</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lemay E, Guay J, Cote C, Roy A. Tranexamic acid reduces the need for allogenic red blood cell transfusions in patients undergoing total hip replacement. Can J Anaesth. 2004 Jan;51(1):31-7.</citation>
    <PMID>14709457</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yamasaki S, Masuhara K, Fuji T. Tranexamic acid reduces blood loss after cementless total hip arthroplasty-prospective randomized study in 40 cases. Int Orthop. 2004 Apr;28(2):69-73. Epub 2003 Oct 10.</citation>
    <PMID>15224162</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yang ZG, Chen WP, Wu LD. Effectiveness and safety of tranexamic acid in reducing blood loss in total knee arthroplasty: a meta-analysis. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2012 Jul 3;94(13):1153-9. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.K.00873.</citation>
    <PMID>22623147</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alshryda S, Sarda P, Sukeik M, Nargol A, Blenkinsopp J, Mason JM. Tranexamic acid in total knee replacement: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 2011 Dec;93(12):1577-85. doi: 10.1302/0301-620X.93B12.26989. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22161917</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sukeik M, Alshryda S, Haddad FS, Mason JM. Systematic review and meta-analysis of the use of tranexamic acid in total hip replacement. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 2011 Jan;93(1):39-46. doi: 10.1302/0301-620X.93B1.24984. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21196541</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kagoma YK, Crowther MA, Douketis J, Bhandari M, Eikelboom J, Lim W. Use of antifibrinolytic therapy to reduce transfusion in patients undergoing orthopedic surgery: a systematic review of randomized trials. Thromb Res. 2009 Mar;123(5):687-96. Epub 2008 Nov 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19007970</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nadler SB, Hidalgo JH, Bloch T. Prediction of blood volume in normal human adults. Surgery. 1962 Feb;51(2):224-32.</citation>
    <PMID>21936146</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brecher ME, Monk T, Goodnough LT. A standardized method for calculating blood loss. Transfusion. 1997 Oct;37(10):1070-4.</citation>
    <PMID>9354828</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aderinto J, Brenkel IJ. Pre-operative predictors of the requirement for blood transfusion following total hip replacement. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 2004 Sep;86(7):970-3.</citation>
    <PMID>15446520</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 22, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 15, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>reverse shoulder arthroplasty</keyword>
  <keyword>Rotator cuff</keyword>
  <keyword>Orthopedic joint surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Total shoulder</keyword>
  <keyword>Perioperative bleeding</keyword>
  <keyword>Tranexamic acid</keyword>
  <keyword>Orthopedic complications</keyword>
  <keyword>Hemorrhage</keyword>
  <keyword>Postoperative Hemorrhage</keyword>
  <keyword>Pathologic Processes</keyword>
  <keyword>Arthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Joint Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Musculoskeletal Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Postoperative Complications</keyword>
  <keyword>Antifibrinolytic Agents</keyword>
  <keyword>Fibrin Modulating Agents</keyword>
  <keyword>Molecular Mechanisms of Pharmacological Action</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacologic Actions</keyword>
  <keyword>Hemostatics</keyword>
  <keyword>Coagulants</keyword>
  <keyword>Hematologic Agents</keyword>
  <keyword>Therapeutic Uses</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Intraoperative Complications</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Joint Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Blood Loss, Surgical</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antifibrinolytic Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tranexamic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibrin Modulating Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Molecular Mechanisms of Pharmacological Action</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
