<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="25027">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01865214</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>156-KOB-1201i</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01865214</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Outcome and Treatment Quality Study of Tolvaptan to Treat Hyponatremia in Patients With Heart Failure.</brief_title>
  <acronym>AQUATIC</acronym>
  <official_title>Assessment of Clinical Outcome and Treatment Quality Under Adequate Use of Tolvaptan In Correction of Hyponatremia in Patients Hospitalized With Worsening Heart Failure and Hyponatremia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Korea Otsuka International Asia Arab</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Korea Otsuka Pharmaceutical Co.,Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Korea Otsuka International Asia Arab</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Korea: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective is to evaluate the efficacy and safety on the tolvaptan for increasing serum
      Na levels in patients with worsening heart failure and hyponatremia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase 4, multicenter, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, parallel-group
      interventional study comparing tolvaptan (15 to 60 mg) to placebo in adult patients
      hospitalized (or admission to emergency room) due to worsening of heart failure and
      dilutional hyponatremia. All patients will be on standard therapy for heart failure.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Average daily AUC of change from baseline in serum Na level to day 4 within the double-blind treatment period</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to day 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Failure With Hyponatremia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tolvaptan</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tolvaptan</intervention_name>
    <description>to titrate upwards to 15mg to 60mg, once a daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tolvaptan</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Patients hospitalized due to heart failure with clinically significant
             hyponatremia (except hypovolemic) (defined as serum Na &lt; 125 mEq/L or less marked
             hyponatremia that is symptomatic and has resisted correction with fluid restriction
             [Appendix 4]) prior to randomization.

             2. Male and female patients aged ≥ 20 years. 3. Subject who diagnosed with heart
             failure and New York Heart Association (NYHA) class III/Ⅳ.

             4. Signs of extracellular volume expansion, defined as two or more of the following:
             JVD, peripheral edema, dyspnea or pulmonary congestion.

             5. B-type natriuretic peptide (BNP) ≥ 150 pg/mL or N terminal (NT)-proBNP ≥ 450
             pg/mL.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  &quot;1. Women who are pregnant, breast feeding, or of childbearing potential who are not
             using acceptable contraceptive methods (such as barrier contraceptives or methods
             that result in a failure rate of less than 1%).

             2. Patients with hyponatremia in hypovolemic states, defined as the presence of
             clinical and historical evidence of extracellular fluid volume depletion, including
             but not limited to skin turgor, orthostatic changes in blood pressure (BP) or heart
             rate (HR), dry mucous membranes, or a response to i.v. saline challenge.

             3. Patients unable to sense or respond to thirst. 4. Patients who are likely to
             require prolonged hospitalization for reasons other than chronic heart failure (CHF),
             e.g. new femoral fracture surgery requiring extended recovery.

             5. Patients with recent prior treatment for hyponatremia, such as hypertonic saline
             (within 8 h, just before the  administration) or urea, lithium or tolvaptan (within 4
             days, just before the administration) .

             6. Patients with severe hyponatremia symptoms requiring immediate intervention with
             hypertonic saline; or who are expected to require such therapy within 48 h after
             randomization.

             7. Patients with causes of neurological symptoms, which are attributable to
             psychological (psychoses), structural (dementia of the Alzheimer's type, post-infarct
             dementia) or other metabolic causes (e.g. hyper- or hypo- oxemia, glycaemia,
             calcemia, ammonemia, etc.) 8. Patients with acute and transient hyponatremia
             associated with head trauma or severe neurological injury (e.g. stroke, subdural
             hematoma).

             9. Patients with a history of hyponatremia known to be due to severe, untreated
             hypothyroidism/adrenal insufficiency.

             10. Patients with psychogenic polydipsia. 11. Patients with systolic BP &lt; 90 mmHg at
             screening. Note, if it is confirmed under the BP&lt;90mmHg at the first attempt, in
             addition, conduct a test twice more. And if it fits two results out of three in the
             criteria, the subject can be enrolled.

             12. Patients with a history of hypersensitivity and/or idiosyncratic reaction to
             benzazepine or benzazepine derivatives (such as benazepril), or tolvaptan.

             13. Patients with a history of drug or medication abuse within the 3 months prior to
             screening, or current alcohol abuse.

             14. Patients with uncontrolled diabetes mellitus defined as glucose &gt; 300 mg/dL (16.7
             mmol/L) without regard to meals.

             15. Patients with a current urinary tract obstruction (e.g. obstructive benign
             prostatic hypertrophy).

             16. Anuric patients. 17. Patients with a serum creatinine &gt; 3.5 mg/dL at screening.
             18. Terminally ill patients or patients with a moribund condition who have little
             chance of short-term (e.g. 30 day) survival.

             19. Patients whose hyponatremia is the result of any medication that cannot safely be
             withdrawn, such as anti-convulsants (e.g. carbamazepine) and anti psychotics (e.g.
             haloperidol).

             20. Patients receiving desmopressin within 2 days of screening. 21. Patients who have
             participated in another investigational drug trial within the past 30 days(except for
             Non-interventional study).

             22. Any patient who, in the opinion of the investigator, would not be able to comply
             with the study drug administration or study procedures, or whose overall medical
             condition would prohibit their participation in the study. (ex, severe pneumonia,
             infectious disease and etc.) 23. Patients treated and/or to be treated with strong
             cytochrome P450 (CYP) 3A inhibitors (clarithromycin, ketoconazole, itraconazole,
             ritonavir, indinavir, nelfinavir, saquinavir, nefazodone, telithromycin).

             24. Patients with rare hereditary problems of galactose intolerance, Lapp lactase
             deficiency or glucose- galactose malabsorption.

             25.Patients with Aspartate transaminase(AST) or alanine transaminase(ALT) &gt;2.5 times
             the upper limit of normal(UNL), total bilirubin &gt; 2mg/dL or who under any medication
             treatment for liver disease at screening&quot;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dong Ju Choi, Doctor</last_name>
    <phone>82-31-787-7007</phone>
    <email>djchoi@snubh.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seoul National University Bundang Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seongnam-si</city>
        <state>Gyeonggi-do</state>
        <zip>463-707</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dong Ju Choi, Doctor</last_name>
      <phone>82-31-787-7007</phone>
      <email>djchoi@snubh.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 27, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 27, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyponatremia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
