<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="88890">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01706952</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-251-SDR</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01706952</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Topical Vasoconstriction in Endoscopic Sinus Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of Topical Vasoconstriction in Endoscopic Sinus Surgery: Cocaine Versus Adrenaline</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Marc Tewfik</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>McGill University Health Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Ethics Review Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of our study is to assess the effect of topical vasoconstriction (cocaine 4%
      versus adrenaline 1/1000) on the surgical field during endoscopic sinus surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic Rhinosinusitis (CRS) is one of the most common chronic illnesses in North America,
      with an incidence of approximately 13 per cent in the US.

      Endoscopic sinus surgery (ESS) has become standard treatment for patients with chronic
      rhinosinusitis (CRS) unresponsive to maximum medical treatment. The success of surgery
      depends on several factors, an adequate surgical field is among the most important factors
      in preventing complications in ESS.

      Topical vasoconstrictors, such as adrenaline and cocaine has been widely used. To date no
      studies exist comparing the use of topical cocaine with adrenaline in ESS.

      The purpose of this study is to assess the effect of topical cocaine 4% versus adrenaline on
      intra-operative bleeding during ESS and to describe the phisiologic changes with the use of
      topical vasocontrictors. A secondary objective is to describe the phisiologic changes with
      the use of topical vasocontrictors

      Study Design:

      A prospective randomized single-blind controlled trial will be conducted. The surgeon
      performing the ESS and evaluating the bleeding will not be present at the time of injection,
      and so will remain blinded.

      All patients over the age of 18 years undergoing bilateral ESS for chronic sinusitis at
      McGill University Health Center will be invited to participate. The study will be conducted
      from November 2012 until the number required of patients is enrolled.

      Topical vasoconstriction technique After oral intubation, vital signs and all anaesthetic
      parameters will be kept as constant as possible for the duration of the surgery. Three
      cotton neuropatties will be soaked with 4% cocaine. One neuropattie will be placed in the
      sphenoethmoidal recess, one in the middle meatus, and one in the anterior end of the middle
      turbinates on the side that the randomization has determined. In the other side, three
      cotton neuropaties will be soaked with adrenaline 1:1000 and placed in the same positions
      than the others. Then the patient will be draped and both sides will be injected with
      xylocaine 2% and adrenaline 1:100.000. After this we will wait for 10 minutes and the
      surgery will be initiated.

      At the commencement of surgery and at regular 15-minute intervals, the operating surgeon
      will estimate the intensity of bleeding in the operative field. The extent of nasal bleeding
      will be evaluated according to the validated scale used by Boezaart. At each assessment,
      other parameters including mean arterial blood pressure (MAP), heart rate, and end tidal CO2
      will be recorded into a chart by the co-investigator.

      The total blood loss will be collected and recorded separately for each side. Separate
      suction tubes and canisters will be used for each side. The total blood loss will be
      measured by subtracting the amount of saline solution used to rinse the surgical field from
      the amount of blood and fluids suctioned from the surgical field. Although this method of
      estimating the intra operative blood loss is not flawless as some blood and fluids usually
      fall posteriorly into the nasopharynx and are later suctioned by the anesthesiologist prior
      to extubation, this amount is deemed to be negligible.

      Proposed data analysis: The data will be collected by the co-investigator. Patient names and
      other specific identifiers will not be included. Data will be entered into an Excel
      spreadsheet and statistical analysis will be applied with SPSS vs.13.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Caregiver)</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>to estimate the change in bleeding category (surgical field improvement) as measured on a six-point scale, measured from 0 (best case) to 5 (worst case).</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 15 minutes until 300 minutes</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>0 No bleeding.
Slight bleeding - no suctioning of blood required.
Slight bleeding - occasional suctioning required. Surgical field not threatened.
Slight bleeding - frequent suctioning required. Bleeding threatens surgical field a few seconds after suction is removed.
Moderate bleeding - frequent suctioning required. Bleeding threatens surgical field directly after suction is removed.
Severe bleeding - constant suctioning required. Bleeding appears faster than can be removed by suction. Surgical field severely threatened and surgery not possible.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 15 minutes until 300 minutes</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The heart rate (heart beats for minutes) will be recorded every 15 minutes, until the surgery is over or until 300 minutes.
The Co-investigator will record this data in a special data sheeet</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 15 minutes or until 300 minutes</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The mean blood pressure, defined as the average arterial pressure during a single cardiac cycle, will be recorded every 15 minutes, until the surgery is over or until 300 minutes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>End tidal CO2</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 15 minutes or until 300 minutes</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The concentration of carbon dioxide (CO2) in the respiratory gases will be recorded every 15 minutes or until 300 minutes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Sinusitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cocaine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cocaine 4%. Three cotton neuropatties will be soaked with 4% cocaine. One neuropattie will be placed in the sphenoethmoidal recess, one in the middle meatus, and one in the anterior end of the middle turbinates on the side that the randomization has determined.
This intervention will be done before the beginning of the surgery, and will be left in the nose for 10 minutes, this will be done just once. After the 10 minutes, the neuropatties will be taken out of the nose.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Adrenaline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Adrenaline 1/1.000 Three cotton neuropatties will be soaked with Adrenaline 1/1,000. One neuropattie will be placed in the sphenoethmoidal recess, one in the middle meatus, and one in the anterior end of the middle turbinates on the side that the randomization has determined.
This will be done before the beginning of the surgery, and will be left in the nose for 10 minutes, this will be done just once. After the 10 minutes, the neuropatties will be taken out of the nose.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cocaine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cocaine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Adrenaline</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Brand Name: Cocaine Hydrochloride Sterile Topical Solution</other_name>
    <other_name>Generic Name: Cocaine Hydrochloride Sterile Topical Solution</other_name>
    <other_name>Active Ingredients: Cocaine hydrochloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Concentration: 4%</other_name>
    <other_name>Code: 1200</other_name>
    <other_name>Format: 5 x 5 mL</other_name>
    <other_name>DIN: 01962388</other_name>
    <other_name>UPC: 057513012006</other_name>
    <other_name>Preservative: Yes</other_name>
    <other_name>Special feature: Latex Free Stopper</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Adrenaline</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cocaine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Adrenaline</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Epinephrine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        - Patients older than 18 years undergoing bilateral ESS for chronic sinusitis.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with heart disease

          -  History of bleeding diathesis

          -  Patients with untreated or poorly controlled high blood pressure

          -  Aspirin, anticoagulant or natural herbal medication usage in the last 4 weeks

          -  Hypersensitivity to adrenaline or cocaine

          -  Significant asymmetry between the right and left side disease extent as determine by
             findings on their pre-operative CT scan and nasal endoscopy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marc A Tewfik, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>McGill University Health Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Constanza J Valdes, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>McGill University Health Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Samaha, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>McGill University Health Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marc A Tewfik, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+15149341934</phone>
    <phone_ext>34971</phone_ext>
    <email>marc.tewfik@mcgill.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Constanza J Valdes, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+15144332602</phone>
    <email>cjvaldes@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery. McGill University Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H3A 1A1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marc A Tewfik, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+1-514-934-1934</phone>
      <phone_ext>34971</phone_ext>
      <email>marc.tewfik@mcgill.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Constanza J Valdes, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+15144332602</phone>
      <email>cjvaldes@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marc A Tewfik, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Constanza J Valdes, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark Samaha, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 23, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 3, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>McGill University Health Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marc Tewfik</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Endoscopic sinus surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Bleeding</keyword>
  <keyword>Topical Vasocontriction</keyword>
  <keyword>Cocaine</keyword>
  <keyword>Adrenaline</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Sinusitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chronic Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Epinephrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epinephryl borate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cocaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
