<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="156210">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01670292</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRiSM Study</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U19AT004663</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01670292</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Patient Response to Spinal Manipulation</brief_title>
  <acronym>PRiSM</acronym>
  <official_title>Patient Response to Spinal Manipulation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Palmer College of Chiropractic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Iowa</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Center for Complementary and Alternative Medicine (NCCAM)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Palmer College of Chiropractic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a biomechanical study which is Project 1 in the Developmental Center for Clinical
      and Translational Research in Chiropractic (DCRC I) (NIH/NCCAM grant 1 U19 AT004663-01;
      principal investigator Christine Goertz, DC, PhD). This study is designed to monitor both
      physiological and patient self-report outcome variables. In addition, as there is little
      quantitative information on Spinal Manipulation Technique procedures reported in clinical
      trials, the study is designed to collect preliminary kinetic measures of the spinal
      manipulation technique delivery (i.e. force-time profiles).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Participants with narrowly defined chronic low back pain will be included in this study.
      Each participant will be treated 12 times over the course of 6 weeks. The following data
      will be collected: participant characteristics that may predict outcome or be modifiers of
      force used by provider (gender, age, height, weight, and Body Mass Index); spinal segment
      load during the pre-load and thrusting phases (force and moment in the pre-load phase, peak
      load, loading rate, and thrust duration; physiological measures (posterior-anterior global
      stiffness and flexion-relaxation); patient-centered outcomes of back pain and function; and
      concomitant medications and treatments.

      Study participants (n= 80) will be recruited from the Quad Cities metro area. A team of
      experienced chiropractic clinicians working at the Palmer Center for Chiropractic Research
      will treat study participants. Each of the study participants will receive 2 High Velocity
      Low Amplitude Spinal Manipulation treatment visits per week over a 6 week period. The
      physiological assessments will be performed immediately before and after Spinal Manipulation
      delivery during treatment visits 1, 5 &amp; 12 (6 sets of assessments in total). During these
      same treatment visits, we will also capture the kinetic measures during Spinal Manipulation
      delivery for spinal segment load analysis. We will further collect thrusting force-time
      profiles of all Spinal Manipulation delivered in the course of treatment for thrust contact
      force analysis. Participant patient-centered outcomes will be measured at baseline 1,
      treatment visits 1, 6, and 13.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-Centered Outcome Measurements (Visual Analog Scale, Roland-Morris, Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information Scale-29)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Visual Analog Scale, Roland-Morris, Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information Scale-29, Lumbar-spine Stiffness, and Flexion-Relaxation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Kinetic Measures (Thrust Contact Force &amp; Spinal Segment Load)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Lumbar-spine Stiffness, Flexion-Relaxation, Thrust Contact Force &amp; Spinal Segment Load</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Low Back Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental: HVLA-SM</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Experimental High Velocity Low Amplitude Spinal Manipulation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HVLA-SM</intervention_name>
    <description>High Velocity Low Amplitude Spinal Manipulation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental: HVLA-SM</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  NRS score, AVERAGE within the past 24 hours

          -  Must be &gt;4 at the phone screen or baseline 1 visit

          -  Must be &gt;2 at phone screen, baseline 1 and baseline 2 visits

          -  Roland Morris Disability &gt;6

          -  Age 21-65

          -  Signed informed consent document

          -  Chronic (12+ weeks) low back pain

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Compliance concerns

          -  No manipulable lesion in L1-L5 or SI joints

          -  The absence of typical palpatory characteristics as well as the absence of a global
             assessment that would indicate that spinal manipulation is likely to generate a
             positive therapeutic effect, even without the presence of standard palpatory findings

          -  Ongoing treatment for low back pain by outside provider

          -  Comorbid conditions

          -  Serious concomitant illness

          -  Inflammatory or destructive spinal tissue change

          -  Ankylosing Spondylytis

          -  Fibromyalgia

          -  Rheumatoid Arthritis

          -  Confirmed or suspected disc herniation with neurological signs

          -  Neuromuscular disease (e.g. Parkinson's, Muscular Dystrophy, Cerebral Palsy, or
             Myasthenia gravis

          -  Spinal surgery &lt;6 months

          -  Suspicion of drug or alcohol dependence or abuse

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension

          -  Lower extremity peripheral arterial disease

          -  Undetermined, infections or visceral source of low back pain

          -  Other comorbid conditions prohibiting treatment and/or testing

          -  Safety concerns

          -  Bleeding disorders

          -  Contraindications to High Velocity Low Amplitude Spinal Manipulation

          -  Inability to tolerate or obtain positon for flexion-relaxation test without condition
             aggravation

          -  Inability to tolerate or perform/receive any study procedure without condition
             aggravation

          -  Quebec Task Force (QTF) criterion 4-11:

          -  QTF 4: Pain + radiation to upper/lower limb with neurologic signs

          -  QTF 5: Presumptive compression of a spinal nerve root on a simple roentgenogram

          -  QTF 6: Compression of a spinal nerve root confirmed by specific imaging techniques

          -  QTF 7: Spinal Stenosis

          -  QTF 8: Postsurgical status, 1-6 months after intervention

          -  QTF 9: Postsurgical status, &gt;6 months after intervention

          -  QTF 10: Chronic pain syndrome

          -  QTF 11: Other diagnoses

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Pacemaker or defibrillator

          -  Inability to read or verbally comprehend English

          -  Joint replacement

          -  Use of spinal manipulation within past 4 weeks

          -  Sensitivity to adhesive

          -  Diagnostic procedures other than x-ray/UA necessary

          -  BDI-II &gt;29

          -  Retension of legal advice and open or pending case related to low back pain

          -  BMI &gt;40

          -  Unwilling to have low back and wrist shaved

          -  Moving from Quad Cities area within next 8 weeks

          -  Unwilling to postpone treatments for low back pain from another provider

          -  Seeking or receiving compensation for any disability
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ting Xia, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Palmer College of Chiropractic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Palmer College of Chiropractic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Davenport</city>
        <state>Iowa</state>
        <zip>52803</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 2, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Low Back Pain</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
