<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="75471">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01810744</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>001-FANI-2012</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01810744</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Microcirculatory Effects of Bevacizumab in Patients Treated for Metastatic Colon Cancer or Glioblastoma</brief_title>
  <acronym>BEVACAPI</acronym>
  <official_title>Study of Microcirculatory Effects of Bevacizumab in Patients Treated for Metastatic Colon Cancer or Glioblastoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre Georges Francois Leclerc</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre Georges Francois Leclerc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>France: Agence Nationale de Sécurité du Médicament et des produits de santé</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The treatment of the most common cancers (colon, breast, lung, liver and kidney) has
      recently added a new therapeutic class known as the &quot;anti-angiogenic&quot;. It was born from a
      better understanding of tumor growth requires the development of neo-vessels. These new
      vessels are of major importance for the viability of the tumor but also the birth of
      metastases. This neo-angiogenesis is complex and results from an imbalance between
      pro-angiogenic factors and anti-angiogenic factors. Growth factor VEGF and its receptors
      (VEGFR-1, VEGFR-2 and VEGFR-3) are a way of survival of endothelial cells required for tumor
      neoangiogenesis. The anti-angiogenic drugs currently available on the market are bevacizumab
      (Avastin ®), sunitinib (Sutent ®) and sorafenib (Nexavar ®). The mechanism of
      anti-angiogenic action of these three main drugs are pharmacological inhibition of the VEGF
      pathway.

      These new anti-angiogenic therapies, however, have significant adverse effects are common
      and some other more serious but rare.

      Hypertension is the most common side effect observed in patients treated with anti-VEGF.
      This is usually iatrogenic hypertension controlled by antihypertensive therapy and rarely
      compromises the pursuit of anti-angiogenic therapy. More rarely, it can have serious
      consequences malignant hypertension, severe hypertension refractory reversible posterior
      leukoencephalopathy associated with severe hypertension have also been reported.

      The pathophysiology of hypertension may be due to the neutralization of major physiological
      effects of VEGF in endothelial cell and therefore the vascular wall.

      The study of the microcirculation is not only useful in the diagnosis of microvascular but
      also macrovascular disease in the evaluation of chronic arterial and venous severe it
      determines the prognosis. In these indications, capillaroscopy remains the gold standard for
      all work pathophysiological because visualization of phenomena measured avoids artifacts and
      difficulties of interpretation. It then appealed to additional technology to directly
      measure the capillary pressure, capillary flow velocity, and indirectly assess capillary
      permeability and function of lymphatic canaliculi. The simplest of these technological
      inputs: video microscopy and digital image analysis, have also improved the practice of
      routine clinical capillaroscopy in its main field of application, evaluation of
      microangiopathy connective. The examination can be performed more quickly and easily
      archived and quantified.

      Only two studies on 14 and 16 patients were able to see a decrease in capillary density
      correlated with the therapeutic activity of anti-angiogenic the tumor mass and metastasis.

      Thus, we propose to quantify in a number of relatively large patient patients the decrease
      in capillary density as well as the relationship between the decrease in the number of
      capillaries and anti-tumor response.

      The study will also aim to measure the prevalence of hypertension in patients treated with
      bevacizumab and to establish the link between these data and the modification of the
      capillary microcirculation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change in the density of capillaries</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and after 15 days of bevacizumab treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The change in the density of capillaries visualized by periungual capillaroscopy will be quantify after 15 days of treatment with bevacizumab, in patients with metastatic colon cancer or a brain tumor.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">98</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Glioblastoma</condition>
  <condition>Bevacizumab</condition>
  <condition>Capillaroscopy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>metastatic colorectal cancer</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients treated by bevacizumab will be follow up by capillaroscopy and blood pressure measurements.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>glioblastoma</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients treated by bevacizumab will be follow up by capillaroscopy and blood pressure measurements.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>capillaroscopy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>metastatic colorectal cancer</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>glioblastoma</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>blood pressure measurement</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>metastatic colorectal cancer</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>glioblastoma</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 18 years

          -  signed informed Consent

          -  Medical Examination

          -  Patients with metastatic colorectal cancer

          -  Patients with a glioblastoma

          -  patient to receive treatment with bevacizumab not yet started

          -  MRI for patients with glioblastoma or scanner TAP for patients carrying a metastatic
             colon cancer performed within 3 weeks before inclusion.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Bevacizumab already initiated or history of antiangiogenic treatment

          -  Inability legal (persons deprived of liberty or under guardianship)

          -  Pregnant or lactating women

          -  Can not sign consent or unable to undergo medical follow up for geographical, social
             or psychological reasons

          -  Patients not covered by Medicare including CMU

          -  Estimated life of over 3 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>François Ghiringhelli, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centre Georges Francois Leclerc</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jérémy SKRZYPSKI, PHD</last_name>
    <phone>3 80 73 75 00 (3461)</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>jskrzypski@cgfl.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sandrine TIAGO</last_name>
    <phone>3 45 34 80 51</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>stiago@cgfl.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre Georges François Leclerc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dijon</city>
        <zip>21079</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>François Ghiringhelli, Professor</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 25, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Colonic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Bevacizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
