<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="121096">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02002871</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EczemaCT01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CIV-13-08-011581</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02002871</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Blue Light for Treating Eczema</brief_title>
  <official_title>Monocenter, Randomized, Intraindividual, Open Label, Exploratory Study Comparing 4 Weeks of Treatment With 453nm Blue Light With no Treatment in Patients With Eczema</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Light and Health Venture</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Light and Health Venture</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Ethics Commission</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Monocenter, randomized, intraindividual, open label, exploratory study comparing 4 weeks of
      treatment with 453nm blue light with no treatment in patients with Eczema. Patients will be
      screened up to 28 days before start of treatment. During the screening visit, the purpose
      and procedures of the study will be explained to potential patients and informed consent
      will be obtained. In addition, fungal superinfection of the target area will be examined
      using direct preparations and mycology cultures. At the baseline visit, patients with Eczema
      will be determined and all inclusion and exclusion criteria will be assessed. For eligible
      patients, two comparable treatment areas will be randomized to treatment with blue light
      (target area) or to serve as untreated control area. After randomization, patients will
      receive treatment of the target area with 3 applications per week at the investigational
      site for a total treatment period of 4 weeks. During those 4 weeks, safety and effectiveness
      assessments will be performed at weekly intervals. After end of treatment, the patients will
      be followed-up for another 2 weeks. In case no full resolution of adverse events occurred at
      the 2 week follow-up visit, a follow-up call will be performed after another 2 weeks.
      Treatment responses will be photo documented
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline (visit 2) of the sum score of local Eczema rating of the target area as compared to the control area at end of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Week 4 of the sum score of local Eczema rating as compared to the control area at end of follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>week 6</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline of the individual symptoms of the sum score of local Eczema rating of the target area as compared to the control area</measure>
    <time_frame>week 4, 6</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Week 4 (end of treatment) of the individual symptoms of the sum score of local Eczema rating of the target area as compared to the control area at end of follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>week 6</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline of inflammation (erythema) evaluated by mexameter of the target area as compared to the control area</measure>
    <time_frame>week 4, 6</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Week 4 (end of treatment) of inflammation (erythema) evaluated by mexameter of the target area as compared to the control area at end of follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>week 6</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline of patient rating of itching of the target area as compared to the control area</measure>
    <time_frame>week 4, 6</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Week 4 (end of treatment) of patient rating of itching of the target area as compared to the control area at end of follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>week 6</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Hyperpigmentation - evaluation by Mexameter</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0, 2, 4, 6</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Structured patient assessment of tolerability of blue light exposure using the symptoms burn and pain (range: 0-4 per symptom) applied to a. Target area (exposed to blue light) b. Control area (not exposed to blue light)</measure>
    <time_frame>week 2, 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events (serious and non-serious)</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0, 2, 4, 6</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse device events (serious and non-serious)</measure>
    <time_frame>over 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Device deficiencies</measure>
    <time_frame>over 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Thermal comfort</measure>
    <time_frame>week 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Recovery of hyperpigmentation during follow up period</measure>
    <time_frame>week 6</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Patient acceptance of hyperpigmentation</measure>
    <time_frame>week 6</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">21</enrollment>
  <condition>Eczema</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Blue light vs control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Light wavelength 453nm, compared to contralateral untreated control plaque on the same patient.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PSO-CT02 device</intervention_name>
    <description>The PSO-CT02 device is worn on the affected skin area where it irradiates the target Eczema area for 30 minutes with blue light. A contralateral eczema area is left untreated and serves as control.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Blue light vs control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Signed and dated informed consent prior to any study-mandated procedure

          2. Good health as determined by the Investigator according to physical examination

          3. Willing and able to comply with study requirements

          4. Skin type I-IV according to Fitzpatrick

          5. Eczema, severity defined by an Eczema Area Severity Index (EASI)smaller/equal 20

          6. Comparable clinical symptomatology of both intended treatment Areas

        8. Reliable method of contraception for women of childbearing potential (i.e. low failure
        rate less than 1% per year; e.g. oral contraceptives, intrauterine device [IUD] or
        transdermal contraceptive patch) 9. Willing to abstain from excessive sun / UV exposure
        (e.g. sunbathe, solarium) during the course of the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Inmates of psychiatric wards, prisons, or other state institutions

          2. Investigator or any other team member involved in the conduct of the clinical study

          3. Participation in another clinical trial within the last 30 days

          4. Pregnant and lactating women

          5. Photodermatosis and/or Photosensitivity

          6. Porphyria and/or hypersensitivity to porphyrins

          7. Congenital or acquired immunodeficiency

          8. Patients with any of the following conditions present on the study areas; Malignoma
             of the skin or severe actinic damage of the skin, atypical naevi or signs of
             hyperpigmentation, precancerosis viral (e.g. herpes or varicella) lesions of the
             skin, fungal and bacterial skin infections, parasitic infections and atrophic skin

          9. Patients with genetic deficiencies attached with increased sensitivity to light or
             increased risk to dermatologic cancer (i.e. Xeroderma pigmentosum, Cockayne Syndrome,
             Bloom- Syndrome)

         10. Current diagnosis of exfoliative or toxic dermatitis.

         11. Evidence of superinfection of the intended treatment areas
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Verena von Felbert, PD Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Klinik for Dermatology and Allergy, medical faculty of the RWTH Aachen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Klinik for Dermatology and Allergology, medical faculty of the RWTH Aachen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aachen</city>
        <state>NRW</state>
        <zip>52074</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 2, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Eczema</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
