<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="73950">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02016443</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TIZANIDIN</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02016443</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tizanidin and Pain After Herniorrhapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Investigation of the Effectiveness of Tizanidin on Pain After Herniorrhapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Diskapi Teaching and Research Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Diskapi Teaching and Research Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Turkey: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Herniorrhaphy is the most frequent general surgical procedure. There are moderate pain
      complaints after herniorrhaphy. Besides causing discomphort to the patients, pain, can delay
      recovery and discharge and cause cognitive disfunction and difficulty with returning to
      normal daily activity.

      A combination of analgesics with different effect sites can reduce the doses needed and
      analgesic related side effects wich is called multimodal analgesia .

      Opiods,acetaminophe, nonsteroid anti-inflamatory drugs and cox-2 inhibitors, alfa-2 receptor
      agonistsi, steroids, gabapentin and pregabalin have been used for this purpose(4).

      Tizanidin is an alfa-2 receptor agonist, and is used for musclosceletal pain conditions.
      Tizanidin reduced the local anesthetic requerement in spinal anesthesia.

      The aim of this study is to investigate the hypothesis that: Tizanidin can reduce the pain
      scores, analgesic consumption, analgesic related side effects and provide early return to
      normal daily activity compared to placebo after inguinal herniorrhapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Age, body mass index (BMI), concomitant diseases, and the ASA physiologic state will be
      recorded.

      Simple randomization will accomplished with a computer-generated sequence of numbers and
      sealed envelopes were used to allocate patients into 2 groups. Group Tizanidin (Group T)
      will receive 4 mg tizanidin per oral twice a day during the postoperative first week and the
      first dose was administered 1 hour before surgery. Group Placebo (Group P) will receivedthe
      same treatment with a placebo sugar pil Heart rate (HR), peripheral oxygen saturation
      (SpO2), systolic arterial pressure (SAP), diastolic arterial pressure (DAP) and mean
      arterial pressure (MAP), end tidal CO2 pressure (EtCO2), end tidal desflurane concentration
      (Et Des) and the bispectral index (BIS) will be monitored. Baseline values will recorded.

      All patients will receive dexketoprofen 50 mg intravenous before the induction of
      anesthesia. Anesthesia induction and muscle relaxation will be standardized with 2 mg kg-1
      propofol, 0.6 mg kg-1 rocuronium and 50 µg fentanyl. Anesthesia will be maintained with
      oxygen in nitrous oxide and desflurane. The desflurane concentration will be titrated to
      keep BIS between 40-60. The patients will receive 50 µg fentanyl boluses in case hemodynamic
      variables changed ≥30% from baseline values. Hypotension will be defined as ≥20% decrease in
      MAP from baseline values and will be treated with fluid boluses and efedrin. Bradycardia
      will be defined as a heart rate &lt;50 beat min and will be treated with atropine. All
      treatments will be recorded. At the end of surgery volatile anesthesia will be discontinued
      and the patients will be extubated according to clinical extubation criteria. The time
      elapsed from discontinuation of volatile anesthesia  to eye opening with verbal commands
      will be recorded as time to emergence. The patients will be transferred to the post
      anesthesia care unit (PACU). The modified Aldrete score will be used to evaluate recovery in
      the PACU and the patients will be discharged from the PACU when the Aldrete score is ≥9 ( ).
      Time spent in the PACU will be recorded. Post operative pain will be evaluated with a Visual
      Analogue Scale (VAS) score of 0-10 (0= no pain and 10= worst imaginable pain) at 1, 6 and 24
      hours postoperatively. Dexketoprofen 25 mg oral 3X1 will be used for post operative
      analgesia. Acetaminophen 500 mg iv will be used for rescue analgesia if pain scores are &gt;3.
      On discharge, patients will be instructed to use dexketoprofen 25 mg 3 times a day, the
      study drug twice a day and as rescue analgesic acetaminophen 500 mg up to 4 times a day. The
      patients will be instructed to contact the hospital if they have pain despite all three
      medications. During the control visit 1 week after surgery total analgesic consumption and
      analgesic related adverse events (nausea, vomiting, dizziness…) will be evaluated.
      Difficulty with normal daily activity will  also be evaluated during this visit with the
      Likert score (1; no difficulty, 2; mild difficulty, 3; difficulty,  4; severe difficulty, 5;
      unable to perform daily activity due to pain). Return to daily activity will also be
      evaluated 6 weeks after surgery; the SF-36 will be used for this purpose ( ).

      Main outcome measures are the postoperative VAS scores, Likert scores and the SF-36 scores
      of the patients. Total analgesic consumption and analgesic related side effects, intra
      operative hemodynamic variables and desflurane consumption, will also becompared.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual analog scale pain score</measure>
    <time_frame>postoperative first hour</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Post operative pain will be evaluated with a Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) score of 0-10 (0= no pain and 10= worst imaginable pain) at 1, 6 and 24 hours postoperatively.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Likert score</measure>
    <time_frame>Postoperative 1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Difficulty with normal daily activity will be evaluated during the first week control visit with the Likert score (1; no difficulty, 2; mild difficulty, 3; difficulty,  4; severe difficulty, 5; unable to perform daily activity due to pain</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SF-36 score</measure>
    <time_frame>Postoperative 6 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Return to daily activity will be evaluated 6 weeks after surgery; the SF-36 will be used for this purpose</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>hemodynamic parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>intraoperative with 5 minutes intervals</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>systolic, diastolic, mean arterial pressures and heart rate will be measured with 5 minutes intervals</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>end tidal desfflurane</measure>
    <time_frame>intraopreative with 5minutes intervals</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>end tidal desfflurane will be measured intraopreative with 5minutes intervals</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>total anagesic consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>postoperative 1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>total anagesic consumption will be determined at postoperative 1 week</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Unilateral Inguinal Hernia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tizanidine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group Tizanidine (Group T) will receive 4 mg tizanidine per oral twice a day during the postoperative first week and the first dose will be administered 1 hour before surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group Placebo (Group P) will receive  a sugar pill per oral twice a day during the postoperative first week and the first dose will be administered 1 hour before surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tizanidine</intervention_name>
    <description>Group Tizanidine (Group T) will receive 4 mg tizanidine per oral twice a day during the postoperative first week and the first dose will be administered 1 hour before surgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tizanidine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tizanidine</other_name>
    <other_name>Sirdalud</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Group Placebo (Group P) will receive a sugar pill per oral twice a day during the postoperative first week and the first dose will be administered 1 hour before surgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
    <other_name>Sugar pill</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        -American Society of Anesthesiologist's physiologic state I-III patients undergoing
        unilateral inguinal herniorrhaphy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  chronic pain

          -  bleeding disorders

          -  renal or hepatic insufficiency

          -  patients on chronic non steroidal anti-inflammatory medications

          -  recurrent hernias

          -  emergency cases
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dilek Yazicioglu, Dr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Netherlands: Ministry of Health, Welfare and Sports</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dilek yazicioglu, Dr</last_name>
    <phone>+90 312 596 2553</phone>
    <email>dilek.yazicioglu@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Diskapi Yildirim Beyazit training and research hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ankara</city>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Murat Sayın, Ass Prof</last_name>
      <phone>+903125962580</phone>
      <email>muratsayin@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dilek yazicioglu, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ward A, Brenner M. Guanylate cyclase from Dictyostelium discoideum. Life Sci. 1977 Oct 1;21(7):997-1008.</citation>
    <PMID>22014</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roseboom H, Perrin JH. Oxidation kinetics of phenothiazine and 10-methylphenothiazine in acidic medium. J Pharm Sci. 1977 Oct;66(10):1392-5.</citation>
    <PMID>21948</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 15, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 10, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Diskapi Teaching and Research Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>DILEK YAZICIOGLU</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>inguinal hernia</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hernia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hernia, Inguinal</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Tizanidine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Clonidine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
