<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="106063">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02129062</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2014-00886</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2014-00886</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-0459</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>9543</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>N01CM00039</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016672</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02129062</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ibrutinib in Treating Patients With Relapsed or Refractory B-cell Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2 Study to Determine the Efficacy of the BTK Inhibitor Ibrutinib (PCI-32765) in Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Precursor-B Lymphoblastic Leukemia (B-ALL)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well ibrutinib works in treating patients with B-cell acute
      lymphoblastic leukemia that has come back after treatment or has not responded to other
      treatment. Ibrutinib may stop the growth of cancer cells by blocking some of the enzymes
      needed for cell growth.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the efficacy of ibrutinib in patients with relapsed or refractory B-cell
      acute lymphoblastic leukemia (B-ALL) as measured by objective response rate (ORR).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the global safety profile of ibrutinib in patients with relapsed or
      refractory B-ALL.

      II. To assess response duration. III. To assess Bruton's tyrosine kinase (BTK) target
      inhibition, biomarkers, and gene expression profiles in B-ALL patient samples before and
      during treatment with ibrutinib.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive ibrutinib orally (PO) once daily (QD) on days 1-28. Courses repeat every 4
      weeks in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for 30 days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>ORR will be presented with 95% confidence intervals. The association between ORR and patient and clinical characteristics will be examined by Wilcoxon's rank sum test or Fisher's exact test. The two-sided log-rank test will be used to assess the differences of time to events between groups such as age groups, or Philadelphia chromosome-positive versus Philadelphia chromosome-negative B-ALL.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival time</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after completion of study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall survival time will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method. The two-sided log-rank test will be used to assess the differences of time to events between groups such as age groups, or Philadelphia chromosome-positive versus Philadelphia chromosome-negative B-ALL.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>B-cell Adult Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Philadelphia Chromosome Positive Adult Precursor Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ibrutinib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive ibrutinib PO QD on days 1-28. Courses repeat every 4 weeks in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ibrutinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ibrutinib)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Bruton's tyrosine kinase inhibitor PCI-32765</other_name>
    <other_name>BTK inhibitor PCI-32765</other_name>
    <other_name>CRA-032765</other_name>
    <other_name>Imbruvica</other_name>
    <other_name>PCI-32765</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ibrutinib)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Relapsed or refractory B-ALL due to receive salvage 1, 2 or 3; Philadelphia
             chromosome-positive (Ph+) B-ALL patients must have failed treatment with at least 1
             second generation tyrosine kinase inhibitor; patients in salvage 1 with late relapse
             should be deemed poor candidates for reinduction with initial therapy; patients with
             acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) of T cell origin (T-ALL) can NOT be treated

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status =&lt; 2 (Karnofsky &gt;= 60%)

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 × upper limit of normal (ULN) (unless Gilbert's syndrome or
             disease infiltration of the liver is present)

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase
             [SGOT])/alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT])
             =&lt; 2.0 × institutional ULN

          -  Creatinine clearance estimated (est.) glomerular filtration rate (GFR) &gt;= 30
             mL/min/1.73 m^2 (Cockcroft-Gault)

          -  For any surgery or invasive procedure requiring sutures or staples for closure,
             ibrutinib should be held at least 7 days prior to the intervention and should be held
             at least 7 days after the procedure, and restarted at the discretion of the
             investigator when the surgical site is reasonably healed without serosanguineous
             drainage or the need for drainage tubes

          -  Bone marrow involvement with &gt;= 5% lymphoblasts, peripheral blast count less than
             5,000 per uL

          -  Women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
             (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry and
             for the duration of study participation; should a woman become pregnant or suspect
             she is pregnant while she or her partner is participating in this study, she should
             inform her treating physician immediately; female patients need a negative serum or
             urine pregnancy test within 14 days of study start (applies only if patient is of
             childbearing potential); non-childbearing is defined as &gt;= 1 year postmenopausal or
             surgically sterilized; men treated or enrolled on this protocol must also agree to
             use adequate contraception prior to the study, for the duration of study
             participation, and 4 months after completion of ibrutinib administration

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who receive other chemotherapy; patients must have been off previous therapy
             for &gt;= 2 weeks and must have recovered from clinically significant toxicity (to grade
             1 or less) of all previous therapy prior to enrollment (consent signing) with the
             following exceptions: steroids, hydroxyurea, oral mercaptopurine, methotrexate,
             vincristine (including prophylactic intrathecal medication), thioguanine, and
             tyrosine kinase inhibitors are permitted within 2 weeks of randomization as
             maintenance or to reduce the peripheral blood blast counts; during ibrutinib therapy,
             only steroids and hydroxyurea are permitted to reduce peripheral blood blast counts;
             patients who have had chemotherapy or radiotherapy within 4 weeks (6 weeks for
             nitrosoureas or mitomycin C) prior to entering the study or those who have not
             recovered from adverse events due to agents administered more than 4 weeks earlier

          -  Patients who are receiving any other investigational agents

          -  Active central nervous system (CNS) leukemia, as defined by unequivocal morphologic
             evidence of lymphoblasts in the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF), use of CNS-directed local
             treatment for active disease within the prior 28 days, symptomatic CNS leukemia
             (i.e., cranial nerve palsies or other significant neurologic dysfunction) within 28
             days; prophylactic intrathecal medication is not a reason for exclusion; patients
             with known brain metastases should be excluded from this clinical trial

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to ibrutinib

          -  Concomitant use of drugs that strongly inhibit cytochrome P450, family 3, subfamily
             A, polypeptide 45 (CYP3A4/5)

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection or an infection requiring systemic antibiotics, symptomatic congestive
             heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric
             illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study requirements

          -  Pregnant and breastfeeding women are excluded from this study; breastfeeding should
             be discontinued if the mother is treated with ibrutinib

          -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-positive patients on combination antiretroviral
             therapy are eligible, unless the patient's cluster of differentiation (CD)4 count is
             below the institutional lower limit of normal, or the patient is taking prohibited
             CYP3A4/5 strong inhibitors or inducers

          -  Uncontrolled autoimmune hemolytic anemia or idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)
             resulting in (or as evidenced by) declining platelet or hemoglobin (Hgb) levels
             within the 4 weeks prior to first dose of study drug

          -  Presence of transfusion-dependent thrombocytopenia

          -  Prior exposure to ibrutinib

          -  History of prior malignancy, with the exception of the following:

               -  Malignancy treated with curative intent and with no evidence of active disease
                  present for more than 3 years prior to screening and felt to be at low risk for
                  recurrence by treating physician

               -  Adequately treated non-melanomatous skin cancer or lentigo maligna melanoma
                  without current evidence of disease

               -  Adequately treated cervical carcinoma in situ without current evidence of
                  disease

          -  Burkitt's or mixed lineage leukemia, T cell ALL

          -  Isolated extramedullary relapse (i.e., testicular or CNS)

          -  Patients with a cardiac ejection fraction (as measured by either multi gated
             acquisition scan [MUGA] or echocardiogram) &lt; 45% are excluded; currently active
             clinically significant cardiovascular disease such as uncontrolled arrhythmia,
             congestive heart failure, any class 3 or 4 cardiac disease as defined by the New York
             Heart Association Functional Classification, or history of myocardial infarction
             within 6 months prior to first dose with study drug

          -  Unable to swallow capsules, or disease significantly affecting gastrointestinal
             function and/or inhibiting small intestine absorption, such as malabsorption
             syndrome, resection of the small bowel, or poorly controlled inflammatory bowel
             disease affecting the small intestine

          -  Serologic status reflecting active hepatitis B or C infection; patients that are
             hepatitis B core antibody positive but antigen negative will need a negative
             polymerase chain reaction (PCR) prior to enrollment; (hepatitis B antigen or PCR
             positive patients will be excluded;) (this may not be a necessary exclusion for an
             ibrutinib monotherapy protocol)

          -  History of stroke or intracranial hemorrhage within 6 months prior to enrollment

          -  Current life-threatening illness, medical condition, or organ system dysfunction
             which, in the Investigator's opinion, could compromise the patient's safety, or put
             the study at risk; any other severe concurrent disease, or have a history of serious
             organ dysfunction or disease involving the heart, kidney, liver or other organ system
             that may place the subject at undue risk to undergo therapy with ibrutinib

          -  Any serious medical condition, laboratory abnormality, or psychiatric illness that
             places the subject at unacceptable risk if he/she were to participate in the study

          -  Received anticoagulation therapy with warfarin or equivalent vitamin K antagonists
             within the last 28 days

          -  Evidence of clinically significant bleeding diathesis or coagulopathy

          -  Major surgical procedure, open biopsy, or significant traumatic injury, within 28
             days prior to day 1, anticipation of need for major surgical procedure during the
             course of the study; (minor surgical procedures, fine needle aspirations or core
             biopsies within 7 days prior to day 1; bone marrow aspiration +/- biopsy is allowed)

          -  Prior allogeneic stem cell transplant in previous 3 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jan Burger</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>M D Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jan A. Burger</last_name>
      <phone>713-792-1865</phone>
      <email>jaburger@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jan A. Burger</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 30, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Burkitt Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Philadelphia Chromosome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
