<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="141432">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02153983</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>140119</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>14-CH-0119</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02153983</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Colchicine in Non-Diabetic Adults With Metabolic Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot Study of the Effects of Colchicine in Non-Diabetic Adults With Metabolic Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Being overweight may cause low-level inflammation. This inflammation may cause some of the
      medical problems of obesity, like high blood sugar (diabetes) and heart disease. This study
      will test whether a medication called colchicine can improve metabolism in adults who are
      overweight but have not yet developed diabetes.

      Objectives:

      - To learn whether colchicine improves sugar regulation and metabolism.

      Eligibility:

      - Healthy overweight adults at least 18 years old.

      Design:

        -  Participants must fast before each visit, including the screening visit.

        -  Participants will be screened with blood tests, stool sample, medical history, and
           physical exam. They will have to drink sugar water, and have blood drawn to find out if
           they are healthy.

        -  For visit 1, participants will have a medical history and physical exam and answer
           questions. They will have blood taken with an intravenous (IV) line, and give a stool
           sample.

        -  Also, subjects will get sugar water through one IV. Blood will be drawn from the other.
           This measures sugar and insulin levels.  During this, participants will lie in a bed
           and can watch TV.

        -  Participants will have a full-body X-ray, lying on a table while a camera passes over
           them. They will also have an abdominal CT scan, lying on a table that moves through a
           ring that takes pictures.

        -  Participants will have a small fat tissue sample taken from their abdomen.  It is like
           getting a mini-liposuction.

        -  Participants will be given the study drug or placebo. They will take it twice daily for
           3 months.

        -  For visit 2, participants will have blood tests, medical history, and physical exam.
           They will give a stool sample.

        -  For visit 3, participants will repeat the tests in visit 1.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Obesity affects one-third of the adult U.S. population and is a major risk factor for the
      development of type 2 diabetes and cardiovascular disease.  Mouse models and human data
      suggest that obesity-induced chronic inflammation is one mechanism promoting
      obesity-associated comorbid conditions.  In obesity, innate immunity is activated by
      circulating molecules such as fatty acids and cholesterol crystals bind to
      nucleotide-binding oligomerization (NOD)-like receptor family, pyrin domain containing 3
      (NLRP3) receptors in adipocyte tissue macrophages (ATMs).  This binding stimulates NLRP3
      oligomerization, inflammasome formation, and proinflammatory cytokine activation.  The
      resultant inflammatory cascade leads to insulin resistance and decreased pancreatic
      beta-cell reserve.  It has been proposed that the suppression of this chronic low-level
      inflammatory state may impede the onset of diabetes and cardiovascular disease.

      Recent studies have shown colchicine, a potent microtubule inhibitor commonly used for the
      treatment of gout and some rare inflammatory conditions, disrupts intracellular localization
      of NLRP3, thereby blocking inflammasome assembly.  As there are limited medical therapies
      proven effective to improve obesity-related metabolic dysregulation, we propose to determine
      the efficacy of colchicine 0.6 mg twice daily in non-diabetic obese adults with metabolic
      syndrome. We will conduct a randomized, double-blinded, placebo-controlled pilot trial of
      colchicine in forty subjects.  We will study changes in insulin resistance, beta-cell
      reserve, and systemic inflammation.  Using adipose tissue obtained from biopsies, we will
      also study colchicine   s local effects on inflammation and insulin resistance.  Should
      results prove promising, this pilot study will allow determination of the sample size needed
      for an adequately powered study of the effects of colchicine in obese adults with metabolic
      syndrome.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in insulin sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in metabolic parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in other inflammatory markers</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Metabolic Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Colchicine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Experimental treatment with colchicine</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Drug</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo capsules identical to</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Colchicine 0.6 mg given</intervention_name>
    <description>Colchicine 0.6 mg given twice daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Colchicine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo capsules given</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo capsules given twice daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Drug</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Subjects will qualify for inclusion if they meet the following criteria:

          -  Good general health.  In general subjects should take no medications.  However,
             individuals taking medications for obesity-related co-morbid conditions, who have not
             had changes in dosage for more than 6 months, may be included, at the discretion of
             the principal investigator.

          -  Obesity, defined as a body mass index (BMI)   (Bullet) 30 kg/m2, but weight less than
             450 lbs in order for subjects to undergo Dual-Energy X-ray Absorptiometry (DXA)
             scanning.

          -  Age greater than or equal to 18 years.

          -  Metabolic Syndrome, as per NCEP/ATPIII Guidelines

             --(Any 3 of the following 5):

               -  FPG greater than or equal to 100 mg/dl, or on treatment

               -  Triglycerides greater than or equal to 150 mg/dl, or on treatment

               -  Waist Circumference: Men greater than or equal to 40 in (greater than or equal
                  to 102 cm); Women greater than or equal to 35 in (greater than or equal to 88
                  cm)

               -  Reduced HDL-C: Men &lt;  40 mg/dl; Women &lt;  50 mg/dl, or on treatment

               -  Hypertension: greater than or equal to 130 mmHg systolic, or greater than or
                  equal to 85 mmHg diastolic, or on treatment

          -  HOMA-IR greater than or equal to 2.6.  Our goal is to enroll participants who have
             pre-existing insulin resistance.

          -  hsCRP greater than or equal to 2.0 mg/L. We aim to recruit participants with
             increased baseline level of inflammation. Individuals with hsCRP above 2.0 mg/L have
             been shown to have an increased risk for cardiovascular events.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        For subjects and controls:

        &lt; TAB&gt;

          -  Type 2 diabetes mellitus, as determined by a fasting plasma glucose greater than or
             equal to 126 mg/dL, hemoglobin A1c greater than or equal to 6.5%, or an oral glucose
             tolerance test glucose concentration of greater than or equal to 200 mg/dL at 2
             hours.

          -  Presence of a significant active or chronic illness likely to limit life span and/or
             increase risk of intervention, including renal (GFR less than or equal to 60
             ml/min/1.73m(2)), cardiovascular, hepatic (other than obesity-related steatosis),
             gastrointestinal, immunologic, endocrinologic (e.g. Cushing syndrome), pulmonary
             (other than either asthma not requiring continuous medication or sleep apnea-related
             disorders), or other disorders at the discretion of the investigators.

          -  Recent use of colchicine or anorexiant medications in the last 3 months.

          -  Known allergy to colchicine.

          -  Previous history of agranulocytosis, gout, or significant myositis.

          -  Females who are pregnant, planning to become pregnant, currently nursing an infant,
             or have irregular menses, defined as cycles less than 21 days or greater than 45
             days.

          -  Individuals who have current substance abuse or a psychiatric disorder or any other
             condition that in the opinion of the investigators would impede competence,
             compliance, or participation in the study.

          -  Subjects who regularly use prescription medications unrelated to the complications of
             obesity, especially those known to affect enzymes involved in colchicine metabolism,
             such as CYP3A4 or P-glycoprotein (P-gp).  Oral contraceptive use will be permitted,
             provided the contraceptive has been used for at least two months before starting
             study medication.  The use of over-the-counter and prescription medications will be
             reviewed on a case-by-case basis; depending on the medication, subjects who have
             continued to take prescription medication for at least 3 months prior to study entry
             may be eligible.

          -  Participation in a formal weight loss program (e.g. Weight Watchers) or recent weight
             change of more than 3% of body weight in the past two months.

          -  Use of anti-inflammatory medications (e.g. prednisone, NSAIDs) chronically or in the
             last 7 days prior to fat biopsy.

          -  History of keloid formation.

          -  Current users of tobacco products.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jack A Yanovski, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Andrew P Demidowich, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 594-1176</phone>
    <email>demidowicha@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jack A Yanovski, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-0858</phone>
    <email>jy15i@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2014-CH-0119.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wen H, Gris D, Lei Y, Jha S, Zhang L, Huang MT, Brickey WJ, Ting JP. Fatty acid-induced NLRP3-ASC inflammasome activation interferes with insulin signaling. Nat Immunol. 2011 May;12(5):408-15. doi: 10.1038/ni.2022. Epub 2011 Apr 10. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>21478880</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vandanmagsar B, Youm YH, Ravussin A, Galgani JE, Stadler K, Mynatt RL, Ravussin E, Stephens JM, Dixit VD. The NLRP3 inflammasome instigates obesity-induced inflammation and insulin resistance. Nat Med. 2011 Feb;17(2):179-88. doi: 10.1038/nm.2279. Epub 2011 Jan 9.</citation>
    <PMID>21217695</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 31, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Colchicine</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>Metabolic Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Dyslipidemia</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Syndrome X</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Colchicine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
