<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="23221">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01708213</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CP 10664</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01708213</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety Evaluation of Aline HA</brief_title>
  <official_title>Safety Evaluation of Aline HA</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>TauTona Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>TauTona Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The protocol hypothesis is that treatment with Aline HA™ will be safe through 6 months as
      determined by clinical assessment of treatment sites and routine tracking of adverse events.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety Evaluation of Aline HA</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary endpoint of this study is to assess treatment site responses and adverse events through 6 months post procedure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety Evaluation of Aline HA</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Secondary endpoints include an independent reviewer (IR) and the investigator's assessment of wrinkle severity score (WSS), if the NLF is treated, and; qualitative patient and investigator standardized questionnaires using the Global Aesthetic Improvement Scale (GAIS) if an area besides the NLF is treated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Correction of Wrinkles</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dermal Filler - Aline HA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single armed study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aline HA</intervention_name>
    <description>Implantable dermal filler</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dermal Filler - Aline HA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. The patient must be ≥ 21 and ≤ 70 years of age.

          2. The patient must be willing and able to provide informed consent.

          3. The patient must be able to read.

          4. The patient is willing and able to comply with the study protocol.

          5. The patient is seeking soft tissue augmentation

          6. The patient has a pre-treatment Wrinkle Severity Score (WSS) ≥ 2 for any NLF to be
             treated.

          7. The patient agrees to follow-up examinations out to 6 months post final treatment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Exclusion Criteria: 1) The patient has had (or plans to have) cosmetic procedures to
             treat the intended treatment area, such as:

               1. Ablative or non-ablative resurfacing procedures including but not limited to
                  medium depth or deeper chemical peeling, dermabrasion, laser resurfacing or
                  fractional resurfacing that would affect the treatment area within the last 12
                  months.

               2. Laser or light based therapy that would affect the treatment area within the
                  last 6 months.

               3. Face, neck or brow lift or other surgical procedure of the head and neck that
                  would affect the treatment area in the last 18 months.

               4. Non-permanent dermal filler treatment in the treatment area within the last 9
                  months.

               5. Permanent implant or dermal filler treatment in the treatment area at any point
                  in time.

               6. Neurotoxin treatment that would affect the treatment area in the last 6 months,
                  if the treatment area is below the eyes.

               7. Neurotoxin treatment that would affect the treatment area in the last 9 months,
                  if the treatment area is above the eyes.

                  2) The patient has had or plans to use a pharmaceutical (topical or oral)
                  anti-wrinkle product or other products (e.g., topical retinoids, hormone creams)
                  affecting inflammation in the treatment area within 30 days of the study 3) The
                  patient has inflammatory or infectious skin conditions or unhealed wounds in the
                  treatment areas.

                  4) The patient has a cancerous or pre-cancerous lesion and/or has had radiation
                  exposure in the treatment area in the last 24 months.

                  5) The patient has a history of anaphylaxis, multiple severe allergies, atopy,
                  or is allergic to lidocaine or amide-based anesthetics, hyaluronic acid
                  products, Streptococcal proteins or proteins from other gram positive organisms.

                  6) The patient has a history of significant bleeding disorders. 7) The patient
                  has scleroderma or fibrotic tissue disease. 8) The patient is female and of
                  child bearing potential and/or is pregnant or lactating or is not using
                  medically effective birth control, such as hormonal methods in use at least 30
                  days prior to implantation, or barrier methods such as a condom and spermicide
                  in use at least 14 days prior to implantation.

                  9) The patient is using a Legally Authorized Representative. 10) The patient is
                  an employee or employee's family member of either the Study Sponsor or a Study
                  Site.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dr. Nowell Solish</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5R3N8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Westmount Institute of Plastic Surgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H3Z1B7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 6, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 12, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>soft tissue</keyword>
  <keyword>augmentation</keyword>
  <keyword>correction</keyword>
  <keyword>wrinkles</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
