<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="65431">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01856738</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHEVAL</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-001722-25</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01856738</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cholinesterase Inhibitors to Slow Progression of Visual Hallucinations in Parkinson's Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>CHEVAL</acronym>
  <official_title>Cholinesterase Inhibitors to Slow Progression of Visual Hallucinations in Parkinson's Disease:a Multi-center Placebo-controlled Trial.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VU University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Atrium Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Medical Centre Groningen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Leiden University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Medical Center Nijmegen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Internationaal Parkinson Fonds</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>ZonMw: The Netherlands Organisation for Health Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VU University Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Netherlands: The Central Committee on Research Involving Human Subjects (CCMO)</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Rationale: Visual hallucinations (VH) are the most common non-motor symptoms in Parkinson's
      disease (PD). As an independent predictor for cognitive decline and nursing home placement
      they form an important disability milestone in the course of PD. According to current
      clinical guidelines minor VH do not require treatment per se. But as minor VH precede the
      stage of major VH without insight and PD associated psychosis (PDP) they offer an
      opportunity for early intervention. Neuroleptic drugs delay the transition into PDP but are
      unsuitable for early treatment of VH due to their side effects. We hypothesize that
      cholinesterase inhibitors (ChEI) are a well-tolerated alternative for the early treatment of
      minor VH to delay the progression to PDP.

      Objective: Investigate whether early treatment with ChEI delays the progression of minor VH
      to major VH without insight or PDP. In addition, we will measure motor control, psychotic
      symptoms, cognitive impairment, mood disorders, daytime sleepiness, adverse events and
      compliance, disability, caregiver burden and care use. We assess the cost-effectiveness of
      early chronic treatment of VH with ChEI.

      Study design: A randomized, double blind, placebo-controlled, multi-center trial with an
      economic evaluation.

      Study population: 168 patients with PD and VH after fulfilling the in-and exclusion
      criteria.

      Intervention: Rivastigmine capsule 6 mg BID or placebo BID for 24 months.

      Main study parameters/endpoints: The primary outcome measure is the median time until PD
      patients with minor VH progress to major VH without insight. The clinical endpoint is
      defined as the start with antipsychotic treatment. Secondary outcome measures are changes in
      motor control, psychotic symptoms, cognitive impairment, mood disorders, daytime sleepiness,
      cholinergic deficiency, the number of adverse events, compliance, disability and caregiver
      burden. All relevant costs will be measured and valued.

      Nature and extent of the burden and risks associated with participation, benefit and group
      relatedness: The burden of participation consists of a total of 5 clinical visits (every 6
      months), 4 telephone interviews on adverse events during the escalation phase and 9 internet
      questionnaires (every 3 months). There is a risk for adverse reactions with rivastigmine
      treatment; the most common are nausea and vomiting.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study parameters/endpoints

      Main study parameter/endpoint: The primary outcome measure is the time until PD patients
      with minor VH progress to major VH without insight. The clinical endpoint is defined as the
      start with antipsychotic treatment. This decision is left to the discretion of the treating
      neurologist. In this manner the design represents clinical practice. (The severity of VH is
      measured as a secondary outcome with the UPDRS 1 - MDS, to confirm insight is lost.)

      Secondary study parameters/endpoints: Secondary outcomes measures are changes in the
      following assessments after 6,12,18 and 24 months:

        1. Motor control measured with the UPDRS - MDS part 3 and Levodopa Equivalent Daily Dose;

        2. Psychotic symptoms using the UPDRS - MDS part 1 (hallucinations item) and the Schedule
           for Assessment of Positive Symptoms (SAPS); Besides changes in the severity of
           psychotic symptoms, the proportion of patients that progresses to a score ≥ 3 (i.e.
           loss of insight) in the two treatment groups (rivastigmine and placebo) is measured
           after 24 months.

        3. Cognitive function based on the Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE), Montreal
           Cognitive Assessment (MOCA) and Parkinson's Disease-Cognitive Rating Scale (PD-CRS);

        4. Mood disturbance according to the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS);

        5. Daytime sleepiness on the Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS);

        6. Cholinergic deficiency, as a possible predictor for response to treatment, measured
           with the Cholinersterase Inhibitor Prognosticator (ChIP)

        7. Number and type of adverse events;

        8. Compliance to treatment measured by the number of remaining capsules after every 6
           months of follow-up;

        9. Disability based on the AMC Linear Disability Score (ALDS);

       10. Caregiver burden according to the Zarit Caregiver Burden Inventory (ZCBI);

       11. Care use measured with the EuroQol-5D (EQ-5D).

      Other study parameters include:

        -  patient characteristics (age, sex, smoking, medical history and current use of
           medication)

        -  disease specific characteristics (age at disease onset, disease duration, Hoehn and
           Yahr stage)

      Randomisation, blinding and treatment allocation: After inclusion, the patient will be
      randomized by the web based database. The server of the website will operate from the VU
      University Medical Center. Eligible patients will be randomized by a computer in a 1:1 ratio
      to the rivastigmine group or the placebo group in a double-blind design. Untill the
      computerized randomization is fully operational, patients will be randomized by the research
      nurse or, in her absence, by T.J.M. van Mierlo or E.M.J. Foncke.

      Randomization will be stratified by type of hospital (University Medical Center versus
      Non-University Medical Center), age (below 65 years or 65 years and older), and disease
      duration (&lt;10 years, &gt;10 years) using variable permuted blocks. Code-breaking sheets for
      emergency use will be kept in a safe.

      Study personnel, research nurses, neurologists, and the patients are blinded to the
      treatment allocation at all times. All data will be entered in the central database before
      the treatment codes are broken. The randomization code can be broken in case of an
      emergency.

      Study procedures: The treating neurologist will check the inclusion and -exclusion criteria.
      He asks the patient for permission to send contact information to the research nurse. If the
      patient is eligible and agrees, the neurologist will complete the patient registration form
      with name, gender, date of birth, telephone number and in- and exclusion criteria. After
      registration, a research nurse will contact the patient by phone within 10 working days. She
      will introduce the study to the patient, inform the patient on the gross outline of the
      trial and discuss the possible benefits and disadvantages.  She will answer any additional
      question about the study. If the patient agrees an appointment will be made (visit 1). All
      study visits will take place in the same outpatient clinic. Preferably this is in (or near)
      the same clinic where patients are treated by their neurologist.

      During Visit 1 Informed Consent will be obtained. The baseline characteristics will be
      recorded, as well as medication history, year and type of first PD symptoms (e.g. tremor,
      bradykinesia) and year of PD diagnosis. Current medication is noted and the Levodopa
      Equivalent Daily Dose (LEDD) will be calculated. During Visit 1 patients will undergo
      several assessments by the research nurse as mentioned before.At the end of the visit the
      research nurse will randomize the patient by a central web-based computer program.

      Medication is sent by mail through a central pharmacy during the complete study period. The
      research nurse inquires the patient about the medication received, medication intake and
      side effects by telephone after 2, 4, 6 and 8 weeks of treatment.

      Four specified assessment visits will take place after Visit 1: at 6 months, 12 months, 18
      months and 24 months (respectively Visits 2, 3, 4 and 5; see table 1). The assessments of
      Visit 1 are repeated by the research nurse and completed with a monitor for side effects,
      any change in (non-parkinsonian) medication and calculation of the LEDD. Patients are asked
      to bring the remaining number of capsules. These will be counted as a measure of compliance.

      The endpoint (starting treatment with neuroleptics) or any other important event (in the
      opinion of the treating neurologist) is reported to the neurologist in one of the four main
      study centers, who has been appointed as local research coordinator. The treating
      neurologist fills out the trial termination form. This form includes the date and the
      primary outcome measure, the UPDRS-1 MDS score (3 or 4 on the hallucinations item,
      indicating that insight is lost). If the clinical endpoint is reached, the experimental
      treatment with rivastigmine or placebo is discontinued. As soon as possible, but not before
      the subjects condition allows participation and not later than  2 weeks from the end of
      treatment, the research nurse plans the next clinical visit. During this clinical visit the
      research nurse will follow the same protocol as with regular visits 2-5. The local research
      coordinator is acknowledged.

      When the endpoint is reached and after the clinical visit, costs will continued to be
      measured every 3 months until 24 months from the start of treatment. If possible, even when
      treatment is discontinued, patients are visited after 24 months for the final clinical
      assessment (visit 5).

      The consequences of an important event are discussed by the local research coordinator. The
      local research coordinator decides a patients needs to withdraw from the study and whether a
      final clinical visit must be completed. The research coordinator of the head study center is
      acknowledged.

      Withdrawal of individual subjects: Subjects can leave the study at any time for any reason
      if they wish to do so without any consequences. Specific criteria for withdrawal are not
      predefined.

      The investigator can decide to withdraw a subject from the study if the treating neurologist
      points out urgent medical reasons, which make it necessary to withdraw the patient from the
      study. Subjects can also be withdrawn in case of protocol violations.

      The datasets from withdrawn patients will be kept in the study database to facilitate
      analysis according to the intention-to-treat principle.

      Replacement of individual subjects after withdrawal: Subjects will not be replaced. Drop out
      has been accounted for in our power calculation. Moreover the analysis will be done
      according to the intention-to-treat principle.

      Follow-up of subjects withdrawn from treatment: If a patient violates the study medication
      protocol this will be registered. All further study procedures and measurements will be
      conducted according to the study protocol.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>time to start with antipsychotic treatment for visual hallucinations</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>the time until Parkinson's disease patients with minor visual hallucinations progress to major visual hallucinations without insight (according to UPDRS 1 - MDS). The clinical endpoint is defined as the start with antipsychotic treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>motor control</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>change in motor control measured by UPDRS 3 - MDS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>psychotic symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>change in occurence or severity of psychotic symptoms according to Scale of Assessment of Positive Symptoms (SAPS) and UPDRS 1 MDS.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>cognitive function</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>change in cognitive function as measured by Mini Mental State Examination, Montreal Cognitive Assessment, Parkinson's Disease - Cognitive Rating Scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>mood disturbance</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Mood disturbance according to the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>daytime sleepiness</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Daytime sleepiness on the Epworth Sleepiness Scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>cholinergic deficiency</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Cholinergic deficiency, as a possible predictor for response to treatment, measured with the Cholinersterase Inhibitor Prognosticator</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Number and type of adverse events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>compliance</measure>
    <time_frame>24 monhts</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Compliance to treatment measured by the number of remaining capsules after every 6 months of follow-up</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>disability</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Disability based on the AMC Linear Disability Score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>caregiver burden</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Caregiver burden according to the Zarit Caregiver Burden Inventory</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>care use</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Care use measured with the EuroQol-5D</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">168</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>placebo capsule for oral use 6,0 mg BID during 24 months of follow-up</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rivastigmine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>rivastigmine capsule for oral use 6,0 mg BID during 24 months of follow-up</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rivastigmine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Rivastigmine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Exelon</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  idiopathic PD with bradykinesia and at least two of the following signs; resting
             tremor, rigidity, and asymmetry (in accordance with clinical diagnostic criteria of
             the UK PD Society Brain Bank);

          -  the presence of minor VH for at least 4 weeks, defined by a score of 1 or 2 on the
             hallucinations item of the Unified Parkinson's Disease rating Scale (UPDRS)1-MDS;

          -  age 40 years and over.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Parkinson's Disease Psychosis, defined as the need for antipsychotic drug treatment
             in the opinion of the treating neurologist;

          -  Parkinson's Disease Dementia, defined by a score &lt; 24 on the Mini Mental State
             Examination (MMSE);

          -  current delirium (caused by infection or metabolic disturbance);

          -  current treatment with amantadine (Symmetrel) or anti-cholinergics, such as
             trihexyfenidyl (Artane) or biperideen (Akineton);

          -  current or recent (&lt;6 months) treatment with Cholinesterase inhibitor, such as
             rivastigmine (Exelon) or galantamine (Reminyl);

          -  recent (&lt;1 month) change in dopaminergic therapy;

          -  history of psychosis or severe ophtalmologic disease (e.g. Charles Bonnet syndrome);

          -  permanent stay in a nursing home;

          -  no informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elisabeth Foncke, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VU University Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tom van Mierlo, drs</last_name>
    <phone>0031204440708</phone>
    <email>t.vanmierlo@vumc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Elisabeth Foncke, dr</last_name>
    <phone>0031204442834</phone>
    <email>e.foncke@vumc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Academic Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <zip>1100 DD</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rob de Bie, dr</last_name>
      <phone>003120-5663415</phone>
      <email>r.m.debie@amc.uva.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rob de Bie, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Medical Center Groningen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Groningen</city>
        <zip>9700 RB</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Teus van Laar, Dr</last_name>
      <phone>003150-3612449</phone>
      <email>t.van.laar@umcg.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Teus van Laar, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Atrium Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Heerlen</city>
        <zip>6401 CX</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gerrit Tissingh</last_name>
      <phone>003145-5766666</phone>
      <email>g.tissingh@atriummc.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gerrit Tissingh, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Medical Center St Radboud</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nijmegen</city>
        <zip>6500 HB</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bart Post, dr</last_name>
      <phone>003124-3615202</phone>
      <email>b.post@neuro.umcn.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bart Post, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.chevalstudie.nl</url>
    <description>Related info, instructions for inclusion and study protocol</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 14, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 14, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>VU University Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tom van Mierlo</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>drs T.J.M. van Mierlo</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Parkinson's disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Visual hallucinations</keyword>
  <keyword>Rivastigmine</keyword>
  <keyword>Cholinesterase inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Randomized controlled trial</keyword>
  <keyword>Cost-effectiveness analysis</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hallucinations</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cholinesterase Inhibitors</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rivastigmine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
