<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="168252">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02017899</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H03_01TP</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02017899</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase 1, Dose Escalation Study, to Evaluate a New Shigella Sonnei Vaccine in Healthy Adults.</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Randomized, Observer Blinded, Placebo Controlled, Single Center, Dose Escalation Study to Evaluate the Safety and Immunogenicity of 3 Vaccinations With Shigella Sonnei Vaccine (1790GAHB) Administered Intramuscularly in Healthy Adults.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Novartis</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Novartis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>France: Agence Nationale de Sécurité du Médicament et des produits de santé</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This Phase 1 clinical trial is aimed to evaluate the safety and immunogenicity of 3 doses of
      5 sequentially escalating dosages of a candidate vaccine against Shigella sonnei (1790GAHB
      vaccine) administered by intramuscular route in healthy adults (18 to 45 years of age at
      enrollment). The safety profile of the 1790GAHB vaccine is evaluated in comparison to that
      of placebo (GAHB-Placebo), constituted by an aluminum hydroxide suspension having the same
      concentration as study vaccine formulations. A total of 50 eligible subjects will be
      assigned to one of five sequential cohorts of 10 subjects each.

      Within each cohort, in an observer-blind fashion, subjects will be randomized to receive
      three vaccinations, four weeks apart, of either 1790GAHB vaccine (at five antigen
      concentrations) or GAHB placebo. A Data Safety Monitoring Board will be in place to receive
      a summary of all safety data obtained during one week follow-up post-first vaccination with
      the lower dose. Based on evaluation of the safety data, the Data Safety Monitoring Board
      will make a recommendation, as to whether the next cohort should be vaccinated with higher
      antigen concentration or not.

      Expected duration of the study for an individual subject is 9 months. Each subject will be
      followed-up for 6 months after the 3rd vaccination.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the safety profile of 5 different dosages of 1790GAHB vaccine in healthy adults.</measure>
    <time_frame>7 and 28 days after each vaccination and entire study duration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Numbers of subjects with deviations from normal values of hematological, haematochemical blood tests and urinalysis after vaccination.
Numbers of subjects with solicited local and systemic reactions during 7 days following each vaccination.
Numbers of subjects with reported unsolicited adverse events during 28 days following each vaccination.
Number of subjects with reported Serious Adverse Events throughout the study duration.
Number of subjects with reported reactive arthritis (AE of special interest).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the immunogenicity profile of 5 different dosages of 1790GAHB vaccine in healthy adults.</measure>
    <time_frame>At 28 days after 1st vaccination, 28 days after 2nd vaccination and 28 and 168 days after 3rd vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>IgG Geometric mean concentrations (GMCs) before (day 1), 28 days after 1st vaccination, 28 days after 2nd vaccination, 28 and 168 days after 3rd vaccination as determined by ELISA, and applicable geometric mean ratios between post vaccination and baseline samples.
Percentage of subjects achieving at least a four-fold rise in IgG ELISA antibody concentration 28 days after 1st vaccination, 28 days after 2nd vaccination, and 28 and 168 days after 3rd vaccination relative to the baseline concentration.
Stool IgA Geometric mean concentrations (GMCs as determined by ELISA, and applicable geometric mean ratios relative to the baseline concentration), may be calculated in the stool specimens of at least one cohort , provided before (day 1), 28 days after 1st vaccination, 28 days after 2nd vaccination, and 28 days after 3rd vaccination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>10</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Shigellosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>COHORT A / 1790GAHB vaccine - 1 µg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects receiving treatment in cohort A</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>COHORT B / 1790GAHB vaccine - 5 µg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects receiving treatment in cohort B</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>COHORT C / 1790GAHB vaccine - 25 µg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects receiving treatment in cohort C</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>COHORT D / 1790GAHB vaccine - 50 µg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects receiving treatment in cohort D</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>COHORT E / 1790GAHB vaccine - 100 µg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects receiving treatment in cohort E</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>COHORT A / GAHB-Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects receiving placebo in cohort A</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>COHORT B / GAHB-Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects receiving placebo in cohort B</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>COHORT C / GAHB-Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects receiving placebo in cohort C</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>COHORT D / GAHB-Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects receiving placebo in cohort D</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>COHORT E / GAHB-Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects receiving placebo in cohort E</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>1790GAHB vaccine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>COHORT A / 1790GAHB vaccine - 1 µg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>COHORT B / 1790GAHB vaccine - 5 µg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>COHORT C / 1790GAHB vaccine - 25 µg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>COHORT D / 1790GAHB vaccine - 50 µg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>COHORT E / 1790GAHB vaccine - 100 µg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Shigella sonnei vaccine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GAHB-Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>COHORT A / GAHB-Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>COHORT B / GAHB-Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>COHORT C / GAHB-Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>COHORT D / GAHB-Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>COHORT E / GAHB-Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Males and females of age ≥18 years to ≤45 years.

          2. Individuals who, after the nature of the study has been explained to them, and prior
             to any protocol specific procedures being performed, have given written consent
             according to local regulatory requirements.

          3. Individuals in good health as determined by the outcome of medical history, physical
             examination, hematological / hematochemical blood tests (including presence of high
             antibody titers against S. sonnei by agglutination test), urinalysis and clinical
             judgment of the investigator.

          4. If women of child-bearing potential, have a negative pregnancy test prior study
             vaccination and willingness to use acceptable birth control measures for the entire
             study duration.

          5. Individuals affiliated to a social security regimen.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Individuals with behavioral or cognitive impairment or psychiatric disease that, in
             the opinion of the investigator, may interfere with the subject's ability to
             participate in the study.

          2. Individuals with any progressive or severe neurological disorder, seizure disorder or
             Guillain-Barré syndrome.

          3. Individuals who are not able to understand and to follow all required study
             procedures for the whole period of the study.

          4. Individuals with history of any illness that, in the opinion of the investigator,
             might interfere with the results of the study or pose additional risk to the subjects
             due to participation in the study.

          5. Individuals human leukocyte antigen (HLA) -B27 positive and/or with history of
             reactive arthritis.

          6. Individuals with known or suspected HIV infection or HIV related disease, with
             history of an autoimmune disorder or any other known or suspected impairment
             /alteration of the immune system, or under immunosuppressive therapy including use of
             systemic corticosteroids or chronic use of inhaled high-potency corticosteroids (i.e.
             prednisone, or equivalent ≥10 mg/day) within the previous 28 days, or in chemotherapy
             treatment within the past 168 days.

          7. Individuals with a known bleeding diathesis, or any condition that may be associated
             with a prolonged bleeding time.

          8. Individuals with any serious chronic or progressive disease according to judgment of
             the investigator (e.g., neoplasm, insulin dependent diabetes, cardiac, renal or
             hepatic disease).

          9. Individuals who have any malignancy or lymphoproliferative disorder.

         10. Individuals with history of allergy to vaccine components.

         11. Individuals participating in any clinical trial with another investigational product
             28 days prior to first study visit or intent to participate in another clinical study
             at any time during the conduct of this study.

         12. Individuals who received any other vaccines within 4 weeks prior to enrollment in
             this study or who are planning to receive any vaccine within the entire study
             duration except influenza vaccination, which is not allowed within the period
             included between 28 days before 1st vaccination and 28 days after 3rd vaccination.

         13. Individuals who have received blood, blood products, and/or plasma derivatives
             including parenteral immunoglobulin preparations in the past 12 weeks.

         14. Individuals who are part of study personnel or close family members to the personnel
             conducting this study or employees of the clinical trial site institution.

         15. Individuals with body temperature &gt; 38.0 degrees Celsius within 3 days of intended
             study vaccination.

         16. Individuals with Body Mass Index (BMI)&gt; 30 kg/m2

         17. Individuals with history of substance or alcohol abuse within the past 2 years.

         18. Women who are pregnant or are breast-feeding, or are of childbearing age who have not
             used or do not plan to use acceptable birth control measures, for the duration of the
             study.

         19. Females with history of stillbirth, neonatal loss, or previous infant with anomaly.

         20. Individuals who have a previously laboratory confirmed or suspected disease caused by
             S. sonnei.

         21. Individuals who have had household contact with/and or intimate exposure to an
             individual with laboratory confirmed S. sonnei.

         22. Any condition, which, in the opinion of the investigator may pose an increased and
             unreasonable safety risk to the subject if participating to the present study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Odile Launay, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centre d'Investigation Clinique en Vaccinologie Cochin-Pasteur (CIC1417)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Audino Podda, NVGH</last_name>
    <phone>+39 0577 243496</phone>
    <email>audino.podda@novartis.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre d'Investigation Clinique en Vaccinologie Cochin-Pasteur (CIC1417)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <state>Paris cedex 14</state>
        <zip>75679</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Odile Launay, Prof</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Odile Launay, Prof</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 17, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Shigella sonnei</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dysentery, Bacillary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
