<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="139431">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01744782</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RP103-08</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01744782</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety/Effectiveness Study of Cysteamine Delayed-release Capsules (RP103) in Cysteamine Treatment Naive Patients With Cystinosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label Safety and Effectiveness Study of Cysteamine Delayed-release Capsules (RP103) in Cysteamine Treatment Naive Patients With Cystinosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Raptor Pharmaceuticals Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Raptor Pharmaceuticals Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a long-term, open-label study of the safety, tolerability and effectiveness of RP103
      in cystinosis patients who are naïve to any form of cysteamine treatment.  Subjects will
      receive RP103 treatment for at least 12 months and will continue to participate in the study
      and receive RP103, until it is available through the appropriate marketing approval (In the
      US, following FDA approval; In Brazil, once it is a regularly registered medication and
      available at no personal cost), or a subject withdraws or is withdrawn from the study, or
      the Sponsor terminates development of RP103 for cystinosis.

      The purpose of this study is to gather information about the safety and effectiveness (how
      well it works to treat cystinosis) of a new drug called RP103.

      In cystinosis, the body builds up cystine.  When taken regularly, the active ingredient of
      an older, already approved drug called Cystagon® (cysteamine bitartrate) reduces cystine in
      the body.  RP103 has the same active ingredient as Cystagon® and is designed to reduce
      cystine in a similar way that Cystagon® does.  RP103 is also different from Cystagon®:
      Instead of the cysteamine bitartrate being absorbed from the stomach, RP103 is designed to
      be absorbed from the small intestine.  This may make the effects of the drug last longer, so
      that it can be taken twice a day instead of four times a day like Cystagon®.

      To decide if RP103 is effective, the study will look at two types of blood tests.  One test
      is pharmacodynamics (PD), which measures the amount of white blood cell (WBC) cystine after
      taking study drug.  WBC cystine is a laboratory test used to find out if cysteamine
      bitartrate is reducing cystine levels in the body.  The second test is pharmacokinetics
      (PK), which measures the amount of cysteamine in the blood after taking the drug.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>White Blood Cell (WBC) Cystine Levels</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Steady-state cysteamine-trough WBC cystine levels 30 minutes post RP103 dose at each study visit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Long-Term Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months minimum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The safety profile of RP103 will be investigated with the following assessments: physical exam, vital signs, ECG, clinical laboratory testing and adverse events.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Cystinosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RP103 Q12H</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>From Day 1 and throughout the duration of participation, subjects will take RP103 (Cysteamine Bitartrate Delayed-release Capsules) every 12 hours, supplied in 75mg and 25mg capsules.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RP103 Q12H</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>RP103 Q12H</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>(Cysteamine Delayed-release Capsules)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female with a documented diagnosis of cystinosis

          -  No clinically significant change in liver function tests, i.e. 1.5 times ULN for ALT
             and AST, and/or 1.5 times ULN for total bilirubin, within 6 months prior to Screening

          -  No clinically significant change in renal function, i.e. estimated GFR within 6
             months prior to Screening

          -  Must have an estimated GFR &gt; 20 mL/minute/1.73m2 (using the equation from Schwartz
             2009 J Am Soc Nephrol 20:629-647)

          -  Female subjects who are sexually active and of childbearing potential, i.e. not
             surgically sterile (tubal ligation, bilateral oophorectomy, or hysterectomy) or at
             least 2 years naturally postmenopausal must agree to use an acceptable form of
             contraception from Screening through completion of the study.  Acceptable forms of
             contraception for this study include hormonal contraceptives (oral, implant,
             transdermal patch, or injection) at a stable dose for at least 3 months prior to
             Screening, barrier (spermicidal condom or diaphragm with spermicide), IUD, or a
             partner who has been vasectomized for at least 6 months

          -  Subject or their parent or guardian must provide written informed consent and assent
             (where applicable) prior to participation in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with current history of the following conditions or any other health issues
             that make it, in the opinion of the investigator, unsafe for study participation:

          -  Inflammatory bowel disease if currently active, or prior resection of the small
             intestine

          -  Heart disease (e.g., myocardial infarction, heart failure, unstable arrhythmias, or
             poorly controlled hypertension) within 90 days prior to Screening

          -  Active bleeding disorder within 90 days prior to Screening

          -  History of malignant disease within 2 years prior to Screening

          -  Hemoglobin level of &lt; 10 g/dL at Screening or, in the opinion of the investigator, a
             hemoglobin level that would make it unsafe for study participation

          -  Known hypersensitivity to cysteamine and penicillamine

          -  Female subjects who are nursing, planning a pregnancy, or are known or suspected to
             be pregnant

          -  Subjects who, in the opinion of the investigator, are not able or willing to comply
             with study requirements
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Craig B. Langman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ann &amp; Robert H Lurie Children's Hospital of Chicago</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mary Jo Bagger, Clinical Operations, Raptor Pharmaceuticals Inc.</last_name>
    <phone>1-415-408-6210</phone>
    <email>mbagger@raptorpharma.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ann &amp; Robert H. Lurie Children's Hospital of Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60614</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Heather Price, MS</last_name>
      <phone>773-755-6368</phone>
      <email>hprice@luriechildrens.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Craig B Langman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital das Clínicas da Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de Sao Paulo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sao Paulo</city>
        <state>SP</state>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maria Helena Vaisbich, MD</last_name>
      <phone>55-11-2661-8833</phone>
      <email>vaisbich@terra.com.br</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Juliiana de Oliveria Achili</last_name>
      <phone>55-11-2661-8833</phone>
      <email>juliana.caires@hc.fm.usp.br</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schwartz GJ, Muñoz A, Schneider MF, Mak RH, Kaskel F, Warady BA, Furth SL. New equations to estimate GFR in children with CKD. J Am Soc Nephrol. 2009 Mar;20(3):629-37. Epub 2009 Jan 21.</citation>
    <PMID>19158356</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 8, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 5, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Nephropathic Cystinosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Cysteamine</keyword>
  <keyword>Delayed-release Cysteamine</keyword>
  <keyword>CTNS Protein, Human</keyword>
  <keyword>Orphan Disease</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cystinosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nephrotic Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cysteamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
