<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="58664">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01860534</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB-11-039</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01860534</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>&quot;Eye Protection After Mydriatic Use for ROP Screening: Impact on Vitals Signs and Pain Scores&quot;</brief_title>
  <acronym>ROP patches</acronym>
  <official_title>&quot;Eye Protection After Mydriatic Use for ROP Screening: Impact on Vitals Signs and Pain Scores&quot;</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Texas, Galveston</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Texas, Galveston</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pupillary dilation induced by mydriatic agents during Retinopathy of Prematurity exams can
      persist for hours.  Despite regular use of eye protection for mydriatic-induced light
      sensitivity for infants, children and adults, eye protection after mydriasis has not been
      addressed in neonates.  This study examines the use of eye patches to protect the dilated
      pupil from light exposure and their impact on vital signs and pain scores.   prevents
      tachycardia, tachypnea and discomfort in neonates after ROP screening.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pain management for Retinopathy of prematurity (ROP) screening focuses on pharmacological
      and non-pharmacological interventions during the actual eye examination.  Management of pain
      related to increased light sensitivity during the post-mydriasis period has not been
      described.

      This prospective, randomized study evaluated the impact of protecting the eyes from ambient
      light exposure post mydriasis.  Vital signs and pain scales were recorded in infants
      randomized to either wear or not wear eye patches after mydriasis for their ROP exam.
      Infants less than 30 weeks gestational age or less than 1500 grams at birth were included.
      Standard statistical methods were used to compare vital signs and pain scores for each group
      at baseline, 1 and 3 hours after mydriasis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-mydriasis, 1 hour and 3 hours after mydriatic drops</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>At 3 times (pre-mydriasis, 1 hour and 3 hours after Cyclomydril drops), subjects were exposed to ambient lighting for a period of five minutes.  This usually entailed removing isolette covers and exposing the patient to the ambient room light.  During this time, pain and vital signs were recorded every minute. Heart rate was recorded directly from their cardio-respiratory monitor (Agilent M1106C).  The mean of the five recorded values for each variable was used</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Respiratory rate</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-mydriasis, 1 hour and 3 hours after mydriatic drops</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>At 3 times (pre-mydriasis, 1 hour and 3 hours after Cyclomydril drops), subjects were exposed to ambient lighting for a period of five minutes.  This usually entailed removing isolette covers and exposing the patient to the ambient room light.  During this time, pain and vital signs were recorded every minute. Respiratory rate was recorded directly from their cardio-respiratory monitor (Agilent M1106C).  The mean of the five recorded values for each variable was used</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oxygen saturation</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-mydriasis, 1 hour and 3 hours after mydriatic drops</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>At 3 times (pre-mydriasis, 1 hour and 3 hours after Cyclomydril drops), subjects were exposed to ambient lighting for a period of five minutes.  This usually entailed removing isolette covers and exposing the patient to the ambient room light.  During this time, pain and vital signs were recorded every minute. Oxygen saturation was recorded directly from their cardio-respiratory monitor (Agilent M1106C).  The mean of the five recorded values for each variable was used</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-mydriasis, 1 hour and 3 hours after mydriatic drops</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>At 3 times (pre-mydriasis, 1 hour and 3 hours after Cyclomydril drops), subjects were exposed to ambient lighting for a period of five minutes.  This usually entailed removing isolette covers and exposing the patient to the ambient room light.  During this time, pain and vital signs were recorded every minute. Pain scores were recorded by direct observation using the Neonatal and Infant Pain Scale (NIPS).  The mean of the five recorded values for each variable was used</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Light Sensitivity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Eye patches covers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The infants were randomly assigned by alternating enrolled patients between one of two groups prior to their first ROP screening.  Group A was patched for their first ROP exam and then unpatched for their second exam while group B was unpatched for their first ROP exam and unpatched for their second exam.  The patched subjects had eye covers after their eyes were dilated, and the unpatched subjects had comfort measures similar to the patched subjects but their eyes were not covered.  The patching of the eyes was done in the same way that it is done for eye protection during phototherapy, with the same model of eye patches (Natus biliband) and with the same nursing care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>no eye patches covers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The infants were randomly assigned by alternating enrolled patients between one of two groups prior to their first ROP screening.  Group A was patched for their first ROP exam and then unpatched for their second exam while group B was unpatched for their first ROP exam and unpatched for their second exam.  The patched subjects had eye covers after their eyes were dilated, and the unpatched subjects had comfort measures similar to the patched subjects but their eyes were not covered.  The patching of the eyes was done in the same way that it is done for eye protection during phototherapy, with the same model of eye patches (Natus biliband) and with the same nursing care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>eye covers</intervention_name>
    <description>The infants were randomly assigned by alternating enrolled patients between one of two groups prior to their first ROP screening.  Group A was patched for their first ROP exam and then unpatched for their second exam while group B was unpatched for their first ROP exam and unpatched for their second exam.  The patched subjects had eye covers after their eyes were dilated, and the unpatched subjects had comfort measures similar to the patched subjects but their eyes were not covered.  The patching of the eyes was done in the same way that it is done for eye protection during phototherapy, with the same model of eye patches (Natus biliband) and with the same nursing care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Eye patches covers</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>model of eye patches (Natus biliband) - routinely used for phototherapy eye protection</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All infants with gestational age at birth of 30 weeks or less or with birth weight
             less than 1500g undergoing their first ROP exam in the ISCU at UTMB.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Infants were excluded if they had any congenital malformation or syndrome; a history
             of eye surgery or were receiving inotropics medications.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Erika M. Espino-Torres, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UTMB</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas Medical Branch</name>
      <address>
        <city>Galveston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77555</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 20, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 20, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Texas, Galveston</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Erkia Espino-Torres</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pain</keyword>
  <keyword>mydriasis</keyword>
  <keyword>light</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Photophobia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Mydriatics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
