<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="105973">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02018562</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NA_00086689</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02018562</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of a Tracheostomy Tube That Enables Communication</brief_title>
  <acronym>BLUSA</acronym>
  <official_title>Prospective Evaluation of a Tracheostomy Tube That Enables Communication in Ventilator Dependent Patients - A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Verbal communication is vital to critically ill mechanically ventilated patient's quality of
      life (Hess, 2005).  Patients who have a tracheostomy tube may be able to communicate using a
      speaking valve, however, some patients may not be able to tolerate cuff deflation for use of
      speaking valve.  There are talking tracheostomy tubes that do not require cuff deflation to
      facilitate speech in this population.  Unfortunately, not all candidates are offered these
      options due to lack of awareness.  Recently, at our institution, there has been an increase
      in the use of these tubes to facilitate speech.  One of the talking tracheotomy tubes that
      has proven to be effective is the Portex Blueline Ultra Suctionaid (BLUSA).

      In 2010, we conducted a retrospective review of 4 cases and found that BLUSA tracheostomy
      helped facilitate communication in this unique population (IRB #: NA_00041547).  We would
      now like to formally conduct a prospective pilot study to evaluate the feasibility of
      measuring outcomes of patients with a BLUSA using a pretest-posttest research design.

      Communication empowers patients and allows healthcare staff to obtain a more accurate
      assessment of patients' condition and tailor care accordingly.  Identifying the predictors
      of speech intelligibility and the impact of BLUSA on quality of life will promote
      communication between patients and healthcare providers.

      Study Hypothesis: Determine the impact of a talking tracheostomy tube on quality of life in
      patients requiring prolonged mechanical ventilation in the hospital.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sentence intelligibility</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Level of independence with talking tracheostomy tube</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction with a talking tracheostomy tube</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Evaluate the Effect of a Talking Tracheostomy Tube on Quality of Life.</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The talking tracheostomy trial involves placement of a talking tracheostomy tube (Portex Blueline Ultra Suctionaid Tracheostomy Tube) by respiratory therapist after obtaining an order from an authorized prescriber (MD, PA, or NP).  The Speech-Language Pathologist (SLP) sets up the tracheostomy tube for speech and then determines the optimal air flow required for voicing. This amount of air flow is communicated to the ICU staff for further use.
We will ensure that the SLP meets with the patient for a minimum of 3 sessions within a week to optimize the use of a talking tracheostomy tube.
i. SLP will also assess the duration of successful speech during each session
ii. Sentence intelligibility will also be assessed during the 3rd session.  This session will be audio-taped and reviewed by a second rater for sentence intelligibility.
iii. SLP will determine the level of independence with talking tracheostomy during the 3rd session.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will also receive talking tracheostomy tube trial as standard of care but a week later after the pre and post assessments have been completed</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Portex Blueline Ultra Suctionaid Tracheostomy Tube</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Mechanically ventilated via tracheostomy

          -  Awake, alert, and attempting to communicate

          -  Able to understand English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Delirium

          -  Fresh tracheostomy within 48 hours

          -  Laryngectomy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Vinciya Pandian, PhD, RN, ACNP-BC</last_name>
    <phone>443-655-3482</phone>
    <email>vpandia1@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Therese K Cole, MA, CCC-SLP</last_name>
    <phone>410-955-6758</phone>
    <email>tkling1@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Johns Hopkins Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Batty S. Communication, swallowing and feeding in the intensive care unit patient. Nurs Crit Care. 2009 Jul-Aug;14(4):175-9. doi: 10.1111/j.1478-5153.2009.00332.x.</citation>
    <PMID>19531034</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frost SA, Azeem A, Alexandrou E, Tam V, Murphy JK, Hunt L, O'Regan W, Hillman KM. Subglottic secretion drainage for preventing ventilator associated pneumonia: A meta-analysis. Aust Crit Care. 2013 Nov;26(4):180-8. doi: 10.1016/j.aucc.2013.03.003. Epub 2013 Apr 11.</citation>
    <PMID>23583261</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hess DR. Facilitating speech in the patient with a tracheostomy. Respir Care. 2005 Apr;50(4):519-25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15807915</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Husain T, Gatward JJ, Harris RD. Use of subglottic suction port to enable verbal communication in ventilator-dependent patients. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2011 Aug 1;184(3):384.</citation>
    <PMID>21804129</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Coffman HM, Rees CJ, Sievers AE, Belafsky PC. Proximal suction tracheotomy tube reduces aspiration volume. Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg. 2008 Apr;138(4):441-5. doi: 10.1016/j.otohns.2007.11.013.</citation>
    <PMID>18359351</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hofhuis JG, Spronk PE, van Stel HF, Schrijvers AJ, Rommes JH, Bakker J. Experiences of critically ill patients in the ICU. Intensive Crit Care Nurs. 2008 Oct;24(5):300-13. doi: 10.1016/j.iccn.2008.03.004. Epub 2008 May 9.</citation>
    <PMID>18472265</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lacherade JC, De Jonghe B, Guezennec P, Debbat K, Hayon J, Monsel A, Fangio P, Appere de Vecchi C, Ramaut C, Outin H, Bastuji-Garin S. Intermittent subglottic secretion drainage and ventilator-associated pneumonia: a multicenter trial. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2010 Oct 1;182(7):910-7. doi: 10.1164/rccm.200906-0838OC. Epub 2010 Jun 3.</citation>
    <PMID>20522796</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nomori H. Tracheostomy tube enabling speech during mechanical ventilation. Chest. 2004 Mar;125(3):1046-51.</citation>
    <PMID>15006967</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pandian V, Maragos C, Turner L, Mirski M, Bhatti N, Joyner K. Model for best practice: nurse practitioner facilitated percutaneous tracheostomy service. ORL Head Neck Nurs. 2011 Spring;29(2):8-15.</citation>
    <PMID>21675700</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pandian V, Miller CR, Mirski MA, Schiavi AJ, Morad AH, Vaswani RS, Kalmar CL, Feller-Kopman DJ, Haut ER, Yarmus LB, Bhatti NI. Multidisciplinary team approach in the management of tracheostomy patients. Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg. 2012 Oct;147(4):684-91. Epub 2012 Jun 5.</citation>
    <PMID>22675004</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 17, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 3, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Vinciya Pandian</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Tracheostomy Nurse Practitioner; Nursing Director, Percutaneous Tracheostomy Service</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Quality of Life</keyword>
  <keyword>Talking Tracheostomy Tube</keyword>
  <keyword>Speech</keyword>
  <keyword>Mechanically ventilated patients</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
