<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="16647">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01913509</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NSC102-2314-B-182-003</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NMRPD1C0071</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01913509</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Post-Stroke Pain and Fatigue: Clinical Evaluation and Treatment Effect</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study of Post-Stroke Pain and Fatigue: Clinical Evaluation and Treatment Effect</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chang Gung University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mackay Memorial Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chang Gung University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Taiwan: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators anticipate this research will shed light on metric properties of outcome
      measures of pain and fatigue and the effects of the combined therapy for stroke patients.
      The overall findings will contribute to guide the choice of proper assessment tool and the
      development of effective rehabilitation programs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hemiplegic shoulder pain affects from 16%-84% of stroke patients and fatigue occurs among
      39%-72% of stroke victims, which can have an adverse impact on rehabilitation outcomes by
      interrupting treatment process, daily functions, and quality of life (QOL) for stroke
      patients. Considering the high prevalence and detrimental effects of poststroke shoulder
      pain and fatigue, it is vital for monitoring these symptoms and therapeutic interventions to
      be developed for those suffering from poststroke pain and fatigue. Therefore, to validate
      existing assessments of pain/fatigue, and to evaluate the efficacy of potential pain/fatigue
      interventions are needed.

      A vertical Numerical Rating Scale with Face Rating Scale (NRS-FRS) could be used by all
      stroke patients as pain and fatigue measurement. The Brief Pain Inventory (BPI) and Brief
      Fatigue Inventory (BFI) measure intensity and interference, which might provide more
      information. The first aim of this research will be to examine the psychometric properties
      of the vertical NRS-FRS, BPI, and BFI.

      Functional electrical stimulation (FES) appears to offer benefits in relieving painful
      hemiplegic shoulder. Electrical stimulation of the posterior deltoid and supraspinatus
      muscles has shown beneficial effects on pain, subluxation, range of motion, and arm
      function. It is suggested that graded treadmill training (GTT) could be useful in relieving
      fatigue by improving fitness reserve and lowering of the energy cost of hemiparetic gait.
      For non-ambulatory stroke patients, body weight supported treadmill training (BWSTT) is an
      encouraging intensive, task-specific practice. Therefore, the second aim of this research
      will investigate whether the combined therapy of FES and GTT (FES-GTT) or that of FES and
      BWSTT (FES-BWSTT) could reduce hemiplegic shoulder pain and poststroke fatigue as compared
      with conventional rehabilitation (CR). Whether interventions could lead to better functional
      performance and higher QOL would be of interest.

      This 3-year project will be implemented in four stages and will recruit 160 patients with
      chronic stroke. At the first stage, we will conduct a test-retest study to investigate the
      reliability and validity of outcome measures on hemiplegic shoulder pain and poststroke
      fatigue in 80 patients. At the second stage, we will conduct a randomized controlled trial
      (RCT) to investigate the relative effects of the FES-GTT versus CR for 40 ambulatory stroke
      patients with hemiplegic shoulder pain, poststroke fatigue, and moderate-to-mild motor
      impairment. At the third stage, we will conduct another RCT to investigate the relative
      effects of the FES-BWSTT versus CR for 40 non-ambulatory stroke patients with hemiplegic
      shoulder pain, poststroke fatigue, and moderate motor impairment. Treatment regimens will be
      designed to ensure that patients in the 2 groups at stage 2 and 3 receive an equivalent
      intensity of treatment (1 hour/day, 3 days/week for 4 weeks). The fourth stage determines
      clinimetric properties of the outcome measures.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vertical Numerical Rating Scale with Face Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>3 minutes</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The NRS supplemented with the Wong-Baker FRS is a combination of the 0- to 10-point vertical NRS with word anchors and the six facial expressions of the FRS facilitating scoring the intensity of participants' pain/fatigue. The question for measuring pain/fatigue will be: &quot;How much hemiplegic shoulder pain/poststroke fatigue do you feel today? Please point to the number that best reflects your current level of hemiplegic shoulder pain/poststroke fatigue&quot;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Brief Pain Inventory (BPI)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 to 10 minutes</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The BPI includes four ratings of the intensity of pain (items 3-7), and seven that cover the impact of pain. Since pain can be quite variable over a day, the BPI asks patients to rate their pain at the time of responding to the questionnaire (pain now), and also at its worst, least, and average over the previous day, with 0 being &quot;no pain&quot; and 10 being &quot;pain as bad as you can imagine.&quot; The pain now, worst, least, and average rating will be combined to give a composite index of pain severity. Interference of pain is to estimate the degree to which pain limits patients' functions in the past one week, with 0 being &quot;no interference&quot; and 10 being &quot;interferes completely.&quot; The BPI asks for ratings of the degree to which pain interferes with general activity, mood, walking ability, normal work, relations with others, sleep, and enjoyment of life. The mean of these scores will be used as a pain interference score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Brief Fatigue Inventory (BFI)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 to 10 minuttes</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The BFI was developed to measure the severity of fatigue and the impact of fatigue on daily functioning in cancer populations. The BFI uses a 0-10 numeric rating scale to measure fatigue severity (worst fatigue, usual fatigue, fatigue now) and interference with life activities (general activity, mood, walking ability, normal work, relationships to others, sleep, and enjoyment of life) in the past 24 hours, with 0 (no fatigue/no interference) to 10 (fatigue as bad as you can imagine/completely interferences). A composite fatigue severity score is the average of the three severity items and a composite fatigue interference score is the average of the six interference items. A global fatigue score will be obtained by averaging all the items on the BFI.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Combined Therapy of FES and GTT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with ambulatory ability will be applied functional electrical stimulation and walking on a treadmill one hour daily, 3 days per week for 4 weeks and a total of 12 sessions to stimulate the supraspinatus muscle with an active electrode over the posterior deltoid muscle avoid shaking of the shoulder.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Rehabilitation 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The ambulatory stroke patients in CR group will receive a structure protocol using electrical modality such as TENS and conventional physical therapy techniques such as neurodevelopmental techniques with emphasis on functional tasks and muscle strengthening.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Combined Therapy of FES and BWSTT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with non-ambulatory ability will receive combined Therapy of Functional electrical stimulation and Body Weight Supported Treadmill Training (FES-BWSTT).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Rehabilitation 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The non-ambulatory patients in CR group is designed to control for the duration of patient-therapist interactions and therapeutic activities (1 hours/day, 3 days/week, for 4 weeks).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Combined Therapy of FES and GTT</intervention_name>
    <description>FES treatment will be applied to stimulate the supraspinatus muscle with an active electrode over the posterior deltoid muscle avoid shaking of the shoulder. At the same time, patients will walk on the treadmill while supported in a harness with a comfortable speed, using gradually increasing inclination angles and by increasing the total walking time. At the start of the training, patients walk twice for 10 minutes at 40% maximum heart rate (maxHR) and the HR is kept constant for one week, during which the walking duration increases to twice 20 minutes. In week 2, the training heart rate is set at 50% maxHR with gradually increasing durations, which is gradually increased every week to 70% maxHR at the end of 4-week intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combined Therapy of FES and GTT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional Rehabilitation 1</intervention_name>
    <description>Ambulatory patients in CR group will receive the protocol which includes (1) TENS; (2) passive range of motion exercises, stretching of the affected limb, or facilitatory and inhibitory techniques for 15 to 20 minutes; (3) gross motor training for 20 minutes; (4) muscle strengthening of the affected limb for 15 to 20 minutes; and (5) assisted overground walking with aids such as ankle-foot orthoses for 15 to 20 minutes. The activities will be adapted based on the level of motor impairment, walking capacity, and functional needs of individual patients.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Rehabilitation 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Combined Therapy of FES and BWSTT</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention group at Stage 3 will walk on a treadmill while body weight supported (BWSTT) in a harness, which offers the safety and mobility. Initial body weight support will be set so that the knee is within 15 degrees of extension. Initial speed of the treadmill will be set so that the therapist has time to assist the leg to swing through while maintaining a reasonable step length. The amount of body weight support will be reduced once participants can (1) swing their affected leg through without help, (2) maintain a straight knee during stance phase without hyperextension, and (3) maintain an adequate step length without help.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combined Therapy of FES and BWSTT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional Rehabilitation 2</intervention_name>
    <description>The non-ambulatory patients in CR group will receive a structure protocol using electrical modality such as TENS and conventional physical therapy techniques such as neurodevelopmental techniques with emphasis on functional tasks and muscle strengthening. The protocol will include (1) TENS; (2) passive range of motion exercises, stretching of the affected limb, or facilitatory and inhibitory techniques for 15 to 20 minutes; (3) gross motor training for 20 minutes; (4) muscle strengthening of the affected limb for 15 to 20 minutes; and (5) assisted overground walking with aids such as ankle-foot orthoses for 15 to 20 minutes. The activities will be adapted based on the level of motor impairment, walking capacity, and functional needs of individual patients.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Rehabilitation 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. first-ever stroke with onset duration more than 6 months;

          2. self-reported at least mild intensity of hemiplegic shoulder pain and poststroke
             fatigue in the past 7 days (the NRS score ≥ 1);

          3. Brunnstrom stage IV or above and an initial Fugl-Meyer Assessment score of 65 to 100
             indicating moderate or mild movement impairment for Stage 2 and Brunnstrom stage III
             or above and an initial Fugl-Meyer Assessment score of 56 to 79 indicating moderate
             motor impairment for Stage 3;

          4. no serious cognitive deficits (a score of more than 20 on the Mini Mental State
             Exam);

          5. no excessive spasticity in the hip and knee joints of the affected lower extremity
             (Modified Ashworth Scale score ≤3)  ;

          6. no lower extremity fracture within 6 months;

          7. no participation in any experimental rehabilitation or drug studies during the study
             period; and (8) willing to provide written informed consent prior to study entry.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. history of ventricular arrhythmias, or with a cardiac pacemaker, especially those
             with cardiac failure with conduction problems;

          2. previous contralateral stroke with persistent neurological deficit;

          3. a shoulder pathology not related to the stroke (tumor, infection, scapular
             instability, winged scapula);

          4. complicated regional pain syndrome or brachial plexus lesion;

          5. diagnosis of epilepsy with history of recurring seizures in the past six months;

          6. under irregular analgesia or other fatigue-relieving treatment during the study
             period because we expect that pain/fatigue medications might complicate measurements
             of shoulder pain and fatigue. If patients are on regular treatment, it has been so
             for more than one week;

          7. acute pain after operation; and

          8. auditory, visual, physical, or mental disabilities that would interfere with
             patients' ability to comprehend instructions for completing the outcome measures.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Li-Ling Chuang, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Chang Gung University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Li-Ling Chuang</last_name>
    <phone>886-3-2118800</phone>
    <phone_ext>3177</phone_ext>
    <email>lchuang@mail.cgu.edu.tw</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tao-Yuan</city>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Li-Ling Chuang, Ph.D</last_name>
      <phone>886-3-2118800</phone>
      <phone_ext>3177</phone_ext>
      <email>lchuang@mail.cgu.edu.tw</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Li-Ling Chuang, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lerdal A, Bakken LN, Kouwenhoven SE, Pedersen G, Kirkevold M, Finset A, Kim HS. Poststroke fatigue--a review. J Pain Symptom Manage. 2009 Dec;38(6):928-49. doi: 10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2009.04.028. Epub . Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19811888</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Naess H, Lunde L, Brogger J. The effects of fatigue, pain, and depression on quality of life in ischemic stroke patients: the Bergen Stroke Study. Vasc Health Risk Manag. 2012;8:407-13. doi: 10.2147/VHRM.S32780. Epub 2012 Jun 27.</citation>
    <PMID>22910531</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 31, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 30, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Chang Gung University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Li-Ling Chuang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hemiplegic shoulder pain</keyword>
  <keyword>poststroke fatigue</keyword>
  <keyword>functional electrical stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>graded treadmill training</keyword>
  <keyword>stroke rehabilitation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fatigue</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
