<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="149501">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01687088</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MJM/Olfactory/002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01687088</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Smell Sensitivity in Chronic Migraine: A Case-Control Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Olfactory Acuity in Chronic Migraine: A Case-Control Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Thomas Jefferson University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Thomas Jefferson University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Olfactory impairment is a common symptom of neurologic disorders and may be related to
      dopaminergic dysfunction.  Studies show that patients with migraine show increased
      sensitivity to light and sound.  In our previous study in episodic migraineurs, olfaction
      was similar to age and sex-matched controls outside of attacks, but lower during acute
      attacks.

      Our hypothesis is that olfactory function in chronic migraine (CM) will have mild impairment
      of olfaction at baseline but a more significant impairment during migraine or headache
      exacerbations.

      We have two objectives:

        -  To determine baseline olfactory acuity in subjects with CM and compare them to age and
           sex-matched controls

        -  To determine how olfaction changes during acute exacerbations of migraine in those with
           CM

      To execute this study, we will interview subjects and controls to ensure that they meet
      inclusion and exclusion criteria.  After obtaining informed consent, subjects and controls
      will complete a questionnaire survey regarding their history or lack of history of
      headaches, smell sensitivity, osmophobia and current medication use and answer questions
      about attack frequency, location of headache, duration of disease, use of medication for
      pain, and disability.  Both migraineurs and controls will take the University of
      Pennsylvania Smell Identification Test (UPSIT) in the office.

      After the first visit, migraineurs and controls will self-administer the UPSIT at home.
      They will be required to return the second test to the Jefferson Headache Center.

      We will use analysis of variance (ANOVA) to determine variance in UPSIT scores between
      subjects and controls.  To achieve a 90% power that the study will detect a statistically
      significant difference between the mean UPSIT scores at a two-sided 5 percent significance
      level, our sample size for both subjects and controls is 50.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We will interview subjects and controls to ensure that they meet inclusion criteria and do
      not meet exclusion criteria.  After obtaining informed consent, subjects and controls will
      complete a questionnaire survey with the interviewer regarding their history of headaches,
      smell sensitivity, osmophobia and current medication use.  Subjects will also answer
      questions about attack frequency, location of headache, duration of disease, use of
      medication for pain, and disability.

      After completing the questionnaire survey, migraineurs and controls will take the University
      of Pennsylvania Smell Identification Test (UPSIT) in the office.  During this visit we will
      demonstrate and give instructions on how to perform UPSIT at home.

      After the first visit, migraineurs will self-administer the UPSIT during a migraine attack
      day at home.  They will be required to mail or drop off the second test at the Jefferson
      Headache Center.

      Age and sex matched controls will take the first UPSIT in the office.  They will take second
      UPSIT 2 weeks later at home and call the Headache Center to notify the staff that they have
      completed the second UPSIT.  They will be asked to mail or drop off the test at the
      Jefferson Headache Center.

      The UPSIT is a standardized, validated test for olfaction.  There are a total of 40
      odorants, with four booklets each containing ten odorants.  The stimuli are embedded in
      &quot;scratch and sniff&quot; microcapsules at the bottom of each page.  Subjects must choose one
      answer among four possible answers for each odorant - a forced choice test.  The validity
      and reliability of the UPSIT, as well as the basis for using these particular odorants, has
      been demonstrated in multiple studies.  The tests kits will be supplied by Dr. Richard Doty
      at University of Pennsylvania.

      We will use analysis of variance (ANOVA) to determine variance in UPSIT scores between
      subjects and controls.  We will also use ANOVA to examine differences based on subject
      characteristics, including attack frequency, duration of illness, osmophobia during attacks,
      and if odors trigger headaches.  We will also use Chi-square and the Wilcoxon rank sum test
      to determine categorical outcomes such as gender and statistical significance between
      groups.

      To achieve a 90% power that the study will detect a statistically significant difference
      between the mean UPSIT scores at a two-sided 5 percent significance level, our sample size
      for both subjects and controls is 50.  This is based on the assumption that the standard
      deviation of the response variable is 3 units.  Our assumptions about effect size are based
      on previous studies using the UPSIT to detect differences in subjects and controls in other
      neurologic disorders, such as schizophrenia.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case Control, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>difference in UPSIT scores between subjects and controls</measure>
    <time_frame>Chronic migraineurs up to 12 months. Controls up to 2 weeks.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Migraineurs and controls will take the University of Pennsylvania Smell Identification Test (UPSIT) in the office.  After the first visit, migraineurs will self-administer the UPSIT during a migraine attack day at home.
Age and sex matched controls will also take the first UPSIT in the office.  They will take second UPSIT 2 weeks later at home.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Migraine</condition>
  <condition>Olfactory Acuity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>chronic migraineurs</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>controls</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Male and female subjects, over age 18 years who meet criteria for diagnosis of chronic
        migraine Controls will be age and sex-matched and will have no history of migraine
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female subjects over the age of 18 with Chronic Migraine (&gt;15 headache
             days/month, at least 8 days meet criteria for migraine)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with sinus/nasal disease

          -  Subjects with a history of head trauma or degenerative disease

          -  Subjects who are decisionally impaired.

          -  Controls will be age and sex-matched with no history of migraine.  They cannot have
             any disability from headache as determined by the MIDAS (Migraine Disability
             Assessment) questionnaire.  Only controls with a MIDAS score of &quot;0&quot; (no disability)
             will be allowed in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael McNamara, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Thomas Jefferson University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 13, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Migraine Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
