<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="73953">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02003443</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>N015749</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>5968</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02003443</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Acupressure for Knee Pain</brief_title>
  <acronym>AKP</acronym>
  <official_title>Acupressure for the Treatment of Pain in Older Adults With Symptomatic Knee Osteoarthritis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Regents of the University of Michigan Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Knee osteoarthritis (KOA) is a leading cause of disability in the elderly and this
      disability is commonly attributed to knee pain. Current treatments for knee pain are only
      modestly efficacious, and some common treatments like non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs
      (NSAIDS) have adverse long-term effects. Acupressure is an inexpensive and noninvasive
      treatment that has the potential to be a useful long-term self-management strategy for pain.
      Acupressure can be easily taught and is safe enough to self-apply without supervision. The
      primary objective of this project is to determine whether self-administered acupressure is
      an effective and feasible self-management strategy for older adults with symptomatic KOA.
      Participants will be randomized to three treatment groups: pain-relief acupressure, sham
      acupressure, and usual care (UC). The intervention will last for 8 weeks during which
      participants in the pain-relief and sham acupressure  groups will be taught the assigned
      treatment by a trained research assistant who is blinded to the treatment arm, and provided
      with a digital video disc to aid their practice at home. The research assistant will make
      weekly phone calls to support the participants' adherence to treatment. The UC group will
      receive no intervention from the research team. Data will be collected at baseline,
      mid-point (4 weeks after baseline) and the end ( 8 weeks) of the intervention. These results
      will help us assess the efficacy of pain-relief acupressure on knee pain in older adults,
      and allow us to calculate  effect sizes to determine the appropriate sample size for a
      larger future study. Since no studies have involved older adults in self-administered
      acupressure, information about feasibility of and adherence to using this method in older
      adults would be invaluable.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>4 and 8 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Western Ontario McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Function</measure>
    <time_frame>4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Both objective and subjective assessments of physical function will be used. The 6 minute walk and the timed up and go (TUG) tests are the objective measures.  The 6 minute walk test has been demonstrated to yield reliable measurements of exercise capacity and is frequently used in OA trials.  The TUG is a test of functional ability and measures the time (in seconds) to get up from a chair, walk 20 feet and return to the chair.  For subjective assessment, we will use the physical function subscale (17 items) of WOMAC.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Fatigue</measure>
    <time_frame>4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Fatigue will be measured by the Brief Fatigue Inventory (BFI).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Acupressure</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants assigned to sham acupressure will receive similar instruction as those assigned to pain-relief acupressure, except that they will be taught to apply pressure to 10 acupoints that are unrelated to pain.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants assigned to the UC group will receive no intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pain-Relief Acupressure</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants assigned to pain-relief acupressure will be taught to apply physical pressure, using a wooden hand-held device designed for acupressure (see picture below), to 10 acupoints on their body.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Self-Administered Acupressure</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Acupressure</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Pain-Relief Acupressure</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 65 or older

          -  Community-living (i.e., own home, senior residence, apartment)

          -  Have a physician diagnosis of knee OA

          -  Current persistent pain (pain ≥ 4 on a 1-10 Visual Analogue Scale on 50% or more of
             days) that has lasted for 3 months or longer

          -  Ability to speak and write in English

          -  Adequate cognitive status (score &gt; 5 on the 6-item screener)

          -  Adequate functional ability to administer the acupressure protocol (e.g., able to use
             fingers or device to apply pressure to acupoints, able to easily reach feet to access
             acupoints)

          -  Ability to demonstrate understanding of treatment protocol through demonstration
             after being instructed

          -  Ambulatory with or without an assistive device

          -  Adequate hearing and vision to follow study protocol

          -  Agree not to start any new therapy for pain control during the study period

          -  Have a telephone and television

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Receiving active cancer treatment

          -  Have a bleeding diathesis condition

          -  Have health conditions that could confound the effect of acupressure (e.g.,
             rheumatoid arthritis, lupus, diabetic neuropathy)

          -  Had knee replacement surgery

          -  Planned or current involvement in physical therapy, acupuncture or acupressure during
             the study period or receipt of any of these in the previous 3 months

          -  Knee injection in prior 6 weeks with no planned injection during the study period

          -  Chronic use of opioid therapy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lydia Li, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Regents of the University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dana Wolford, MS</last_name>
    <phone>734 763 3435</phone>
    <email>dminnick@umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Katherine Scott, RN</last_name>
    <phone>734 998 7022</phone>
    <email>jrsj@med.umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan Chronic Pain and Fatigue Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dana Wolford</last_name>
      <email>dminnick@umich.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kathy Scott</last_name>
      <email>jrsj@umich.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lydia Li, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 2, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 2, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lydia W Li</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Acupressure</keyword>
  <keyword>Older Adults</keyword>
  <keyword>Knee pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain Treatment</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
