<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="90592">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01746953</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Progress-06</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>G0902393/99558</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01746953</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Red Blood Cells Transfusion in Trauma Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Red Blood Cells Transfusion in Trauma Patients: A Risk Stratified Analysis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Progress</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Progress</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: National Institute for Health Research</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      We will evaluate the effect of red blood cell (RBC) transfusion on fatal and non fatal
      events according to baseline risk of death in an international cohort of  trauma patients
      (CRASH-2 trial). The following outcomes will be considered: death from all causes, death due
      to bleeding, death due to multiorgan failure, death due to vascular occlusive events and non
      vascular occlusive events. Non fatal outcomes include: myocardial infarction, stroke, deep
      vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aims: Primary objective: Evaluate the effect of RBC transfusion on all cause mortality
      according to baseline risk of death due to bleeding. Secondary objectives: Evaluate the
      effect of RBC transfusion on specific causes of death. Evaluate the effect of RBC
      transfusion on non fatal vascular occlusive events.

      Sample: Patients from the Clinical Randomisation of an Antiﬁbrinolytic in Signiﬁcant
      Haemorrhage (CRASH-2) trial. The trial included 20,127 trauma patients with, or at risk of,
      significant bleeding, within 8 hours of injury, and was undertaken in 274 hospitals in 40
      countries.

      Outcomes: Death from all causes, death due to bleeding, death due to multiorgan failure,
      death due to vascular occlusive events and non vascular occlusive events. Vascular occlusive
      events include: myocardial infarction, stroke, deep vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism.
      All events were measured at 28 days or hospital discharge Interventions and comparisons: We
      will compare the effect of red cells transfusion versus no red cells transfusion. We will
      also evaluate the effect of the number of units of red cells transfusion.

      Methods: We will stratify patients according to baseline risk of death from all causes into
      four strata (&lt;6%, 6%-20%, 21%-50% and &gt;50%). We will then evaluate the effect of RBC
      transfusion according to baseline risk on fatal and non fatal outcomes. Formal statistical
      test to detect heterogeneity will be conducted analyzing baseline risk as a continuous
      variable.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>fatal and non fatal vascular occlusive events</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20211</enrollment>
  <condition>Trauma</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients from the Clinical Randomisation of an Antiﬁbrinolytic in Signiﬁcant Haemorrhage
        (CRASH-2) trial. The trial included 20,127 trauma patients with, or at risk of,
        significant bleeding, within 8 hours of injury, and was undertaken in 274 hospitals in 40
        countries.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients eligible for inclusion in the trial were &quot;adult trauma patients with ongoing
             significant haemorrhage, within 8 hours of injury.&quot;

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>December 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 10, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 7, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
