<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="143098">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02134184</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SU-25199</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1U19AI090019-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02134184</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Influence of Chronic CMV Infection on Influenza Vaccine Responses</brief_title>
  <acronym>SLVP025</acronym>
  <official_title>The Influence of Chronic Cytomegalovirus Infection on Influenza Vaccine Responses</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study we are trying to understand whether previous infection with a particular
      virus, namely cytomegalovirus (CMV), influences the ability of the immune system to respond
      to influenza vaccination.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators want to compare the T- and B-cell response to conventional intramuscular
      trivalent influenza vaccine (TIV) in elderly individuals dependent on the presence and
      duration of CMV infection by analyses of vaccine-induced plasmablasts, antibodies and
      antigen-specific T cells.This work may help in the improved design of new vaccines, both for
      influenza and for other respiratory pathogens as well. Healthy volunteers, &gt; 60 years of
      age, will be identified by the Stanford Blood Center based on their history of positive or
      negative CMV serologies.  Baseline blood samples will be drawn from all study participants
      prior to immunization. All participants will receive a single dose of 2012-2013 licensed
      TIV.  Volunteers will complete 3 study visits at Day 0, Day 7 and Day 28.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HAI antibody response to 2012-2013 influenza vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 to Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluate change in HAI (hemagglutination inhibition assay ) antibody titer from pre-immunization to Day 28 post-immunization</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure frequencies of vaccine-specific T cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 to Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluate change in flu-specific T-cell frequencies from baseline Day 0 to Days 7 and 28.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">78</enrollment>
  <condition>Cytomegalovirus Infections</condition>
  <condition>Influenza</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CMV negative group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive Fluzone® 2012-2013 Formula</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CMV positive,  longstanding infection and recent converters</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will  receive Fluzone® 2012-2013 Formula</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluzone® 2012-2013 Formula</intervention_name>
    <description>This vaccine is given intramuscularly</description>
    <arm_group_label>CMV negative group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>CMV positive,  longstanding infection and recent converters</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Trivalent inactivated influenza vaccine (TIV)</other_name>
    <other_name>FDA-licensed seasonal influenza vaccine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Otherwise healthy, ambulatory adult 60 years of age or above.

          -  Self-identified by a participant after notification by Stanford Blood Center (SBC) of
             their group assignment  based review of SBC CMV data:

               -  CMV-negative: Donor has donated at least twice during the last 3 years AND
                  donor's most recent two donations tested CMV antibody negative.

               -  CMV positive longstanding infection: Donor has donated at least once within the
                  &quot;recent&quot; timeframe (past three years) AND donor's most recent donation tested
                  CMV antibody positive AND donor had at least one donation prior to 2000 that
                  tested CMV antibody positive.

               -  Recent CMV converters: Donor has donated at least once within the &quot;recent&quot;
                  timeframe (past three years) AND donor's most recent two donations tested CMV
                  antibody positive AND donor had at least two CMV negative donations in the past.

          -  Willing to complete the informed consent process.

          -  Availability for follow-up for the planned duration of the study at least 28 days
             after immunization.

          -  Acceptable medical history by review of inclusion/exclusion criteria and vital signs.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior off-study vaccination with the current 2012-2013 seasonal influenza vaccine

          -  Allergy to egg or egg products, or to vaccine components or thimerosal (TIV multidose
             vials only)

          -  Life-threatening reactions to previous influenza vaccinations.

          -  Active systemic or serious concurrent illness, including febrile illness on the day
             of vaccination

          -  Weight less than 110 lbs

          -  History of immunodeficiency (including HIV infection)

          -  Known or suspected impairment of immunologic function, including, but not limited to,
             clinically significant liver disease, diabetes mellitus treated with insulin,
             moderate to severe renal disease, or any other chronic disorder which, in the opinion
             of the investigator, might jeopardize volunteer safety or compliance with the
             protocol.

          -  Blood pressure &gt;150 systolic or &gt;95 diastolic at first study visit

          -  Hospitalization in the past year for congestive heart failure or emphysema.

          -  History of chronic Hepatitis B or C.

          -  Recent or current use of immunosuppressive medication, including systemic
             glucocorticoids (corticosteroid nasal sprays and topical steroids are permissible in
             all groups)

          -  Malignancy, other than squamous cell or basal cell skin cancer (includes solid tumors
             such as breast cancer or prostate cancer with recurrence in the past year, and any
             hematologic cancer such as leukemia).

          -  Autoimmune disease (including rheumatoid arthritis treated with immunosuppressive
             medication such as Plaquenil, methotrexate, prednisone, Enbrel) which, in the opinion
             of the investigator, might jeopardize volunteer safety or compliance with the
             protocol.

          -  History of blood dyscrasias, renal disease, or hemoglobinopathies requiring regular
             medical follow up or hospitalization during the preceding year

          -  Use of any anti-coagulation medication such as Coumadin or Lovenox, or anti-platelet
             agents such as aspirin (except up to 325 mg aspirin per day), Plavix, or Aggrenox
             must be reviewed by investigator to determine if this would affect the volunteer's
             safety.

          -  Receipt of blood or blood products within the past 6 months or planned receipt of
             blood products prior to completion of study visits.

          -  Medical or psychiatric condition or occupational responsibilities that preclude
             participant compliance with the protocol

          -  Inactivated vaccine 14 days prior to vaccination or planned non-study vaccination
             prior to completion of Visit 03 (~Day 28 after the study vaccination)

          -  Live, attenuated vaccine within 60 days of vaccination  or planned non-study
             vaccination prior to completion of Visit 03 (~Day 28 after the study vaccination)

          -  Need an allergy immunization (that cannot be postponed) during the study period V01
             to V03 (~Day 28)

          -  History of Guillain-Barré Syndrome

          -  Use of investigational agents within 30 days prior to enrollment or planned use of
             investigational agents prior to completion of study visits

          -  Donation of the equivalent of a unit of whole blood within 6 weeks or a unit of
             platelets within 2 weeks prior to enrollment or planned blood donation prior to
             completion of study visits.

          -  Any condition which, in the opinion of the investigator, might interfere with
             volunteer safety, study objectives or the ability of the participant to understand or
             comply with the study protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cornelia L Dekker, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jorg J Goronzy, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://vaccines.stanford.edu/completed_studies.html</url>
    <description>Stanford LPCH Vaccine Program Clinical Trials Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 7, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Stanford University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Cornelia L. Dekker</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cytomegalovirus Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
