<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="139492">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01830582</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-019</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01830582</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Advanced MR Imaging for Early Biologic Tumor Changes to Neoadjuvant Chemoradiation Treatment for Rectal Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot Study of Advanced MR Imaging for Early Biologic Tumor Changes to Neoadjuvant Chemoradiation Treatment for Rectal Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to see whether three new types of MRI techniques used during
      magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the pelvis to look at rectal cancer can help doctors to
      tell if the tumor is getting better in response to the radiation and/or chemotherapy
      treatments.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a pilot study of dynamic contrast enhanced magnetic resonance imaging (DCE-MRI, aka
      perfusion MRI), diffusion-weighted MRI (DWI-MRI), and proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy
      (MRS), herein referred to in combination as advanced MRI (aMRI) in the investigation of
      early tumor response to standard multi-dose, fractionated external beam radiotherapy (EBRT)
      of the pelvis given in the neoadjuvant setting concurrent with chemotherapy for primary
      rectal adenocarcinoma. This protocol aims to expand upon the growing body of knowledge
      concerning early changes in tumor neovascularity as a potential biomarker of therapy
      efficacy. It further aims to address the trend towards more refined treatment stratification
      for lower risk tumors to avoid morbidity from potentially unnecessary radiation,
      chemotherapy or even radical surgery, by assessing the earliest changes that occur in
      microvasculature, perfusion and diffusion of water molecules and metabolic constituents such
      as choline and lactate during this treatment to see if these can be predictive of long-term
      efficacy of therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>determine the best schedule</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>of early and midterm imaging times using DWI-MRI which will distinguish between near complete (90-99%)/complete responders and partial/non-responders</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine if the best imaging schedule for DCE is the same as for DWI</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The analysis plan will be identical to the one for the primary endpoint: six change measures will be computed for each DCE-MRI parameter (parameters Ktrans, Ve, kep, AUC 90, AUC 180) and each of these change measures will be evaluated as a predictor using the reference standard nCR/CR. ROC curves and the area under them will be estimated and used to rank the predictors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Rectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1 A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>15 patients: The patients will undergo the standard pre chemoradiation MRI scan, followed by a repeat research scan 24 hours (+/- 6 hours) after their first radiation treatment. Then they will get another research MRI scan during the second week (+/- 5 days) of radiation. Finally they will get a standard post chemoradiation MRI scan prior to surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1 B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>15 patients: The patient will undergo the standard pre chemoradiation MRI scan, followed by a repeat research scan 48 hours (+/- 6 hours) after their first radiation treatment. Then they will get another research MRI scan during the third week (+/- 5 days) of radiation. Finally they will get a standard post chemoradiation MRI scan prior to surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1 C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>15 patients: The patient will undergo the standard pre chemoradiation MRI scan, followed by a repeat research scan 72 hours (+/- 6 hours) after their first radiation treatment. Then they will get another research MRI scan during the fourth week (+/- 5 days) of radiation. Finally they will get a standard post chemoradiation MRI scan prior to surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The last 15 patients will get one of the early time points (24, 48 and 72 hours) (+/- 6 hours) and one of the mid-term time points (2, 3 and 4wk) (+/- 5 days) depending on the data from cohorts 1A, 1B and 1C.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Advanced MR Imaging</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>1 A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>1 B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>1 C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with primary locally advanced rectal adenocarcinoma (0-18cm from the anal
             verge) confirmed by MSKCC pathologist and eligible to undergo chemoradiation and
             surgical resection at MSKCC.

          -  Written informed consent

          -  Age equal to or greater than 21 years

          -  Willing and able to undergo all study procedures

          -  Patients must have a planned surgical resection of the rectum

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients younger than 21 years

          -  Pregnant and nursing women

          -  Contraindications for MRI (such as claustrophobia, pacemaker, non MR-compatible
             artificial heart valves, cochlear implants, surgical clips in the brain, metal
             fragments in eye)

          -  Estimated GFR (using Cockcroft formula Appendix 2) less than 30 ml/min/1.73m2 (FDA
             advises caution in using gadolinium-based contrast agents in patients with severe
             renal impairment).

          -  History of allergic reaction to MR contrast media

          -  Inability to give informed consent in person
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marc J. Gollub, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marc J. Gollub, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-639-2183</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Karyn Goodman, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-639-3983</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marc J. Gollub, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-2183</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Karyn Goodman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-3983</phone>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marc J. Gollub, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mskcc.org/</url>
    <description>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 1, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 10, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>MRI</keyword>
  <keyword>rectum</keyword>
  <keyword>13-019</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Rectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
