<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="40239">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01980823</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAM2306</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01980823</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pre-Surgical Trial of the Combination of Metformin and Atorvastatin in Newly Diagnosed Operable Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pre-Surgical &quot;Window of Opportunity&quot; Trial of the Combination of Metformin and Atorvastatin in Newly Diagnosed Operable Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kevin Kalinsky</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Data and Safety Monitoring Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the effects of combining metformin and
      atorvastatin treatment in patients with newly diagnosed breast cancer during the interval
      between breast biopsy and surgery. Metformin is a medication used to treat patients with
      diabetes. It has been shown to have anti-tumor properties in breast cancer. Atorvastatin is
      widely used for the treatment of elevated cholesterol and has also shown to have anti-tumor
      properties in breast cancer. Both have safely been used in patients without diabetes or
      elevated cholesterol. This study will assess the impact of combined metformin and
      atorvastatin on breast tumor tissue markers as well as blood levels, including cholesterol
      and insulin. Both medications will be given for two weeks prior to your scheduled breast
      surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Utilizing a pre-surgical model, we plan to conduct a pilot study of 40 women with newly
      diagnosed invasive breast cancer or ductal carcinoma in-situ (DCIS) who will receive oral
      metformin and atorvastatin daily for at least two weeks, in the interval between diagnostic
      breast biopsy and definitive breast surgery. In this pre-surgical trial, patients will
      receive metformin and atorvastatin at bedtime. Women with histologically-confirmed invasive
      breast cancer or DCIS will be recruited by the medical oncologist and will start the dual
      therapy at least two weeks prior to their scheduled surgery.

      The primary objective of this study is to evaluate changes in tissue levels of the
      proliferation marker Ki-67. These will be compared to a) historical control group of
      metformin treated patients and b) historical control matched by age, body mass index, and
      tumor stage who did not receive metformin or statin.  Secondary endpoints include assessment
      of changes in protein expression of AMPK/mTOR signaling; modulation of apoptosis markers
      such as bax, bid, and various caspase levels; and changes in fasting serum markers of the
      insulin growth factor pathway such as insulin, glucose, and lipids.  The goal is to
      determine if dual combination treatment with metformin plus atorvastatin significantly
      impacts tumor-based markers, such as proliferation, and blood-based biomarkers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 0</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Natural log expression of Ki-67 staining of breast tumor cells</measure>
    <time_frame>At least 2 weeks after start of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Tumor proliferation, as measured by the natural log expression of Ki-67 staining of breast tumor cells, is reduced.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Breast Tumors</condition>
  <condition>Cancer of Breast</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Metformin,  Atorvastatin combination</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive oral metformin and atorvastatin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metformin, Atorvastatin combination</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Metformin,  Atorvastatin combination</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female subjects with histologically-confirmed operable invasive breast cancer or
             DCIS, who undergo core needle biopsy followed by surgical excision at least 2 weeks
             after enrollment

          -  &gt; 5 mm by imaging/pathology of core to ensure enough pre- and post-treatment tissue
             for analysis

          -  Age ≥ 21 years.  Breast cancer is uncommon in patients less than this age.

          -  No prior chemotherapy, radiation therapy, or breast resection within 6 months of
             study entry

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status 0-1

          -  Signed informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Currently on medication for diabetes or hypercholesterolemia

          -  Treatment with other investigational drugs within 6 months of study entry

          -  Strong CYP 3A4 inhibitors (e.g., clarithromycin, HIV protease inhibitors, and
             itraconazole), given potential interactions with atorvastatin

          -  Renal impairment with a creatinine &gt; 1.4 mg/dl

          -  Hepatic impairment: Aspartate transaminase (AST)/(SGOT), Alanine
             Transaminase(ALT)/(SGPT) &gt; 2.5 x upper limit of normal range (ULN), OR Total
             bilirubin &gt; 1.5 x ULN (subjects with Gilbert's syndrome can have bilirubin of up to
             1.5 x ULN), OR Alkaline phosphatase &gt; 2.5 x ULN
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Keven Kalinsky, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Stephanie Aguilar</last_name>
    <phone>212-342-4591</phone>
    <email>sa3146@columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University Medical Center- Herbert Irving Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manhattan</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stephanie Aguilar</last_name>
      <phone>212-342-4591</phone>
      <email>sa3146@columbia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kevin Kalinsky, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 5, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 5, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Columbia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kevin Kalinsky</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Medicine, Columbia University Medical Center</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Metformin</keyword>
  <keyword>Atorvastatin</keyword>
  <keyword>Ki-67</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atorvastatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
