<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="30001">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01768117</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>B1971042</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01768117</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study To Describe The Safety, Tolerability, And Immunogenicity Of Bivalent Rlp2086 Vaccine In Laboratory Workers ≥18 To ≤65 Years Of Age</brief_title>
  <acronym>B1971042</acronym>
  <official_title>A Single-Arm, Open-Label Study To Describe The Safety, Tolerability, And Immunogenicity Of Bivalent Rlp2086 Vaccine In Laboratory Workers ≥18 To ≤65 Years Of Age</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pfizer</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will assess the safety, tolerability and immunogenicity of bivalent rLP2086
      vaccine in laboratory workers ≥18 to ≤65 years of age administered on a Month 0, 2, and 6
      schedule. The study will recruit laboratory personnel (inclusive of Pfizer staff) who work
      directly with pathogenic Neisseria meningitidis in the context of the bivalent rLP2086
      vaccine development program.  The study will provide descriptive safety and immunogenicity
      data following vaccination of these individuals with bivalent rLP2086 vaccine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with titer ≥ lower limit of quantitation (LLOQ) for each of the 4 primary test strains at 1 month after the third vaccination with bivalent rLP2086 vaccine.</measure>
    <time_frame>7 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects reporting local reactions and systemic events for 7 days after each vaccination visit.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects reporting the use of antipyrectic medication for 7 days after each vaccination visit</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with at least 1 SAE 30 days after each vaccination, 30 days after any vaccination, during the vaccination phase, during the follow-up phase, and throughout the study period.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with at least 1 medically attended adverse event 30 days after each vaccination, 30 days after any vaccination, during the vaccination phase, during the follow-up phase, and throughout the study period.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with at least 1 newly diagnosed chronic medical condition 30 days after each vaccination, 30 days after any vaccination, during the vaccination phase, during the follow-up phase, and throughout the study period.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with at least 1 adverse event 30 days after each vaccination, 30 days after any vaccination and during the vaccination phase.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects reporting at least 1 immediate AE after each vaccination.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Subject's days missing school or work due to AEs during the vaccination phase</measure>
    <time_frame>7 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with a titer ≥ lower limit of quantitation for each of the 4 primary test strains 1 month after the first vaccination with bivalent rLP2086 vaccine.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with a titer ≥ lower limit of quantitation for each of the 4 primary test strains 1 month after the second vaccination with bivalent rLP2086 vaccine.</measure>
    <time_frame>4 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with a titer ≥ lower limit of quantitation for each of the 4 primary test strains immediately prior to the third vaccination with bivalent rLP2086 vaccine.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects achieving an hSBA titer ≥ lower limit of quantitation (LLOQ) for all 4 primary test strains combined, 1 month after the third vaccination with bivalent rLP2086 vaccine</measure>
    <time_frame>7 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects achieving at least a 4-fold increase in hSBA titer from baseline to 1 month after the third vaccination with bivalent rLP2086 vaccine for each of the 4 primary test strains</measure>
    <time_frame>7 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">13</enrollment>
  <condition>Meningitis, Meningococcal, Serogroup B</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>rLP2086</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>rLP2086</intervention_name>
    <description>0.5 ml intramuscular injection of 120 microgram bivalent rLP2085 administered at 0, 2 and 6 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>rLP2086</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Laboratory personnel (inclusive of Pfizer staff) who work directly with pathogenic
             Neisseria meningitidis in the context of the bivalent rLP2086 vaccine development
             program.

          2. Male or female subject aged ≥18 to ≤65 years at the time of enrollment.

          3. Negative urine pregnancy test.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects receiving any allergen immunotherapy with a nonlicensed product or receiving
             allergen immunotherapy with a licensed product and are not on stable maintenance
             doses.

          2. A known or suspected defect of the immune system that would prevent an immune
             response to the vaccine, such as subjects with congenital or acquired defects in B
             cell function or those receiving immunosuppressive therapy.  Subjects with terminal
             complement deficiency are excluded from participation in this study.

          3. Significant neurological disorder or history of seizure (excluding simple febrile
             seizure).

          4. Current chronic use of systemic antibiotics.

          5. Received any investigational drugs, vaccines, or devices within 28 days before
             administration of the first study vaccination.

          6. Any neuroinflammatory or autoimmune condition, including, but not limited to,
             transverse myelitis, uveitis, optic neuritis, and multiple sclerosis.

          7. Prior receipt of any vaccine specifically targeting fHBP or LP2086 antigens.

          8. History of microbiologically proven disease caused by Neisseria meningitidis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pfizer CT.gov Call Center</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Pfizer</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pfizer Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hackensack</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://trialinfoemail.pfizer.com/pages/landing.aspx?StudyID=B1971042&amp;StudyName=Study%20To%20Describe%20The%20Safety%2C%20Tolerability%2C%20And%20Immunogenicity%20Of%20Bivalent%20Rlp2086%20Vaccine%20In%20Laboratory%20Workers%20%u226518%20To%20%u226465%20</url>
    <description>To obtain contact information for a study center near you, click here.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 17, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 8, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Meningitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Meningitis, Meningococcal</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
