<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="68706">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01740440</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SRG-BMR Face01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01740440</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of a Transcutaneous Electrical Nerve Stimulation (TENS) Device on Overall Facial Appearance</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of a Transcutaneous Electrical Nerve Stimulation (TENS) Device on Overall Facial Appearance</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bio-Medical Research, Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bio-Medical Research, Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this clinical study is to evaluate the clinical performance of the
      BMR Face device (manufactured by Bio-Medical Research) for the overall facial appearance
      using a grading scale. Secondary objectives are to evaluate safety and further evaluate the
      subject's and investigator's satisfaction (both a live and blinded assessor) with the BMR
      Face treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the efficacy of the BMR Face device in relation to facial appearance at 12 weeks compared to baseline.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Efficacy will be assessed by overall facial improvement assessed live by the Investigator and a subject assessment of facial appearance  including the Global Aesthetic Improvement Scale (GAIS).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary objectives are to evaluate safety and further evaluate the subject's and investigator's satisfaction (both a live and blinded assessor) with the BMR Face treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Adverse events will be monitored to assess safety.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subject satisfaction with the BMR Face Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subject satisfaction will be measured using subject-completed questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subject photographs taken to assess outcome of using BMR Face</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subject photographs will be used to assess the overall facial appearance including
Subject photographs will be used to assess overall facial appearance using the Global Aesthetic Improvement Scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Investigator satisfaction of BMR Face Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigator's satisfaction with the BMR Face treatment using questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Facial Aging</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BMR Face treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>BMR Face treatment used once a day for 12 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BMR Face</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>BMR Face treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who are able to give voluntary, written informed consent to participate in
             this study and from whom consent has been obtained including HIPAA authorization

          -  Subjects who are healthy females between 35 and 55 years of age

          -  Subjects with a Body Mass Index (BMI) between 15-35 kg/m2 (light     underweighted to
             light obese)

          -  Subjects may have all skin types

          -  Subjects with age related skin laxity in the treatment area

          -  Subjects who agree not to have any procedures affecting facial volume (any fillers or
             fat transfer) for the duration of the study

          -  Subjects who agree not to have any other procedures affecting skin quality
             (microdermabrasion, resurfacing, peels, lasers, acne treatments, etc.) for the
             duration of the study

          -  Subjects who agree to make no changes in their existing skincare regime during the
             study period

          -  Subjects who agree to avoid excessive sun radiation or use appropriate sun protection
             with SPF 30 or higher

          -  Subjects who agree not to alter their diet for the duration of the study

          -  Subjects who understand this study and are able to follow study instructions and are
             willing to attend the required study visits

          -  Subjects who agree to be photographed for the purposes of the study and give consent
             for these photographs to be used in marketing advertisements where their identity
             will not be concealed in these photographs

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who are pregnant, planning to become pregnant or breastfeeding. A urine
             pregnancy test will be done to rule out pregnancy.

          -  Subjects of child-bearing potential who are not using an approved method of birth
             control (oral contraceptives, IUD, contraceptive implant, barrier methods with
             spermicide or abstinence)

          -  Subjects who cannot understand or are not willing to comply with the requirements of
             the study

          -  Subjects who have any dermatologic conditions including acne, rosacea, eczema,
             psoriasis, severe sun damage or scars within the treatment area

          -  Subjects who have any known cancer including skin cancers (Basal Cell Carcinoma,
             Squamous Cell Carcinoma and Melanoma)

          -  Subjects with a history of heart disease or stroke

          -  Subjects who have any active implanted medical devices (pacemaker, pump etc)

          -  Subjects having any metal implants. Dental implants and fillings are allowed as well
             as piercings as long as they are not in the treatment area.

          -  Subjects who have used a tanning bed in the past four weeks or plan to use a tanning
             bed for the duration of the study

          -  Subjects who are HIV positive

          -  Subjects who have had systemic corticosteroid therapy in the past 6 months

          -  Subjects who have had a facial dermabrasion, chemical peel, laser, or IPL treatment
             in the past 6 months

          -  Subjects who have used botulinum toxin, hyaluronic acid, collagen, fat injections and
             /or other methods of skin augmentation (enhancement with injected or implanted
             material) in the past 6 months

          -  Subjects who have had ablative resurfacing procedure, brow lift, blepharoplasty or
             face lift in treated area in the past 12 months

          -  Subjects who have had any other surgery in treated area in the past 12 months

          -  Subjects who have an existing medical condition that the Investigator considers may
             put the subject at risk or compromise their participation in the study

          -  Subjects who have participated in another research study in the past 30 days

          -  Subjects who are currently involved in any injury litigation claims

          -  Subjects who have used the BMR Face device previously
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Neil Sadick, Dr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sadick Research Group</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sadick Research Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>10075</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 25, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 21, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Healthy females</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Facies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
