<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="111080">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02076165</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IIR 13-058</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02076165</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Insomnia Treatment for Women Veterans</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Patient-Focused Approach to Insomnia Treatment for Women Veterans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Women Veterans have high rates of insomnia. Prior research and our preliminary findings show
      that insomnia impacts the health and quality of life of women Veterans and that those with
      insomnia prefer non-medication treatments over sleeping pills. The proposed study will
      compare two non-medication behavioral treatments for insomnia to determine impacts on
      adherence rates and sleep/wake patterns. The results of this study will ultimately improve
      the repertoire of available behavioral treatments for insomnia within VA and improve
      important health and quality of life outcomes among women Veterans who receive VA
      healthcare.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The number of women Veterans is increasing due to changes in the composition of the active
      duty military, and understanding the healthcare needs of this growing segment of the
      patients we serve is critical. Insomnia complaints are more common among women than men,
      with a mean prevalence of over 23% among US women. Insomnia (defined as sleep disturbance
      that is sufficiently severe to cause distress or impact functioning), is a significant
      public health concern that contributes to lost productivity, psychological distress, medical
      morbidity, and mortality risk. In a recent paper on transformation of care for women
      Veterans, Yano et al. included &quot;sleep issues&quot; as part of the &quot;VA Women's Health Research
      Agenda for the Future&quot;; however, systematic reviews of VA women's health research (2006 and
      2011) did not identify any prior studies of sleep disorders among women Veterans. In 2011 we
      completed the first descriptive study of sleep problems among women Veterans who receive VA
      Healthcare (HSRD PPO 09-282-1; PI: Martin). We found high rates of insomnia (54% of
      respondents) and comorbid conditions that may impact treatment acceptability and delivery.
      We also found that women Veterans with insomnia preferred non-medication treatments over
      medications, and that they were most likely to access this treatment if it were delivered in
      individual format (rather than groups). There is a growing literature on treatment of
      insomnia among individuals with comorbid conditions, suggesting that insomnia treatment may
      lead to meaningful and durable improvements in sleep quality and other symptoms.

      The proposed study is a randomized trial to compare two non-medication behavioral treatments
      for insomnia. The objectives are: 1) to compare dropout rates and adherence to behavioral
      recommendations between the two treatment programs, 2)  to compare the effectiveness of the
      two treatment programs in improving sleep/wake patterns from baseline to post-treatment, and
      3) to compare the maintenance of improvements in sleep/wake patterns across the two
      treatment programs 3-months after the end of treatment.

      A brief survey will be mailed to approximately 5,000 women Veterans who have received
      healthcare within 6 months from the VA Greater Los Angeles Healthcare System. All women who
      return the survey indicating symptoms of insomnia will be contacted by phone and invited to
      participate in the treatment study. Exclusion criteria will be limited to severe or unstable
      medical/psychiatric disorders, the presence of moderate-to-severe sleep apnea, or barriers
      to attending the treatment sessions (e.g., live too far away, no access to transportation).
      The insomnia treatment programs will be provided in 5 one-on-one sessions to women Veterans
      with insomnia by a trained interventionist. Women Veterans will be randomized to one of the
      two treatment programs (n=74 in each group). Adherence and attrition will be measured in
      both treatment groups. Sleep quality (self-reported and objectively measured), psychiatric
      symptom severity and quality of life will be assessed at baseline, post-treatment and at
      3-month follow-up. ANOVA will be used to test for differences between groups in adherence
      and attrition. Equivalency/noninferiority methods will be used to determine whether
      sleep-related outcomes are comparable between the two groups, using both intent to treat and
      per protocol analyses. With the proposed sample size, we will have sufficient power to test
      the study hypotheses.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence with behavioral treatment for insomnia</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after end of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Adherence to behavioral recommendations and attrition will be measured.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep/wake patterns</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months following randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Insomnia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ABC-I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will participate in 5 individual sessions with a trained instructor.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CBT-I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will participate in 5 individual sessions with a trained instructor.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Behavioral treatment for insomnia-Group I</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will attend 5 individual sessions with a trained instructor.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ABC-I</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Behavioral treatment for insomnia-Group II</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will attend in 5 individual sessions with a trained instructor.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CBT-I</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female Veteran

          -  Community-dwelling

          -  Age   18 years

          -  Received care from VA Greater Los Angeles Healthcare System in the past six months

          -  Responses to postal survey indicate symptoms of insomnia

          -  Did not check &quot;opt-out&quot; box for further contact on postal survey

          -  Live within 50 mile radius of Sepulveda VA Ambulatory Care Center

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unstable housing

          -  No transportation to the medical center

          -  Current pregnancy

          -  Significant health or emotional problems, or use of drugs or alcohol

          -  Untreated sleep apnea

          -  Restless legs syndrome that accounts for the sleep disturbances reported

          -  Circadian rhythm sleep disorder that accounts for the sleep disturbances reported

          -  Active substance users or in recovery with less than 90 days of sobriety

          -  Unstable medical or psychiatric disorders (which is a contraindication for behavioral
             treatment of insomnia)

          -  Remission of insomnia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jennifer Martin, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Greater Los Angeles Healthcare System, Sepulveda, CA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jennifer Martin, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(818) 891-7711</phone>
    <phone_ext>9173</phone_ext>
    <email>jennifer.martin@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Karen J Camacho, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>(818) 891-7711</phone>
    <phone_ext>9167</phone_ext>
    <email>Karen.Camacho@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 11, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 27, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>insomnia</keyword>
  <keyword>women</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Sleep Initiation and Maintenance Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
