<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="4875">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01920802</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>6525</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01920802</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment and Comparison of Metabolic Changes in Non-psychotic Adults Taking Iloperidone or Olanzapine or Placebo</brief_title>
  <official_title>Quantitative Assessment and Comparison of Metabolic Changes in Non-psychotic Adults Taking the Antipsychotic Medications Fanapt (Iloperidone) or Zyprexa (Olanzapine) or Placebo</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York State Psychiatric Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York State Psychiatric Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this pilot randomized clinical trial is to begin to delineate the
      pathophysiological changes associated with antipsychotic associated metabolic side effects.
      The study will be performed in 36 healthy people between the ages of 18 and 30, who have
      never taken an antipsychotic, will undergo baseline laboratory tests before being randomized
      to 5mg BID of olanzapine or 6mg BID of iloperidone or placebo to take for up to 4 weeks. The
      primary outcome measure will be a correlation of early changes in leptin with weight gain.
      We will also record changes in food intake, resting metabolic rate, oral glucose tolerance
      and fasting insulin and glucose levels, lipids and inflammation markers. Subjects will be
      followed closely to monitor for safety throughout the 4-week study and will be discontinued
      if there is a medically significant change in metabolic status or other antipsychotic side
      effects. Metabolic assessments will be performed again at the time of discontinuation or at
      the end of an 4-week period, and change from baseline in the two treatment groups will be
      compared.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study hypotheses:

        1. Early changes (baseline vs day 3) in leptin will correlate with later changes in weight
           (at study termination.)

             1. Olanzapine will cause the greatest increase in calorie consumption     from
                baseline on the multi-item meal compared with iloperidone or placebo.

             2. Olanzapine subjects will report the greatest frequency/quantity of eating in food
                diaries, and report increased preference for calorically dense foods (ie, higher
                fat content) compared to iloperidone or placebo.

             3. Early markers of endocrine changes caused by olanzapine will be greater than those
                caused by iloperidone or placebo, and these early changes will correlate with
                weight gain.

        2. Olanzapine will have greater effects on glucose homeostasis than iloperidone or
           placebo, and these effects will be separate from effects on body weight and
           composition.

             1. Early signs of metabolic disturbance, including glucose intolerance (greater
                excursion on OGTT) and insulin resistance (higher plasma insulin) will precede any
                significant weight gain.

             2. Early evidence of glucose intolerance and/or insulin resistance will predict
                greater metabolic derangements with further dosing of olanzapine, as evidenced by
                exacerbated glucose intolerance on OGTT or higher plasma glucose/insulin levels.
                These effects may not necessarily parallel weight gain.

             3. Olanzapine will be associated with greater markers of inflammation than
                iloperidone or placebo.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between initial change in leptin level and 6-week weight change</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 6 week visit</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Delineate a pathophysiological mechanism of antipsychotic induced weight gain through downstream correlations with specific, early endocrine changes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in leptin</measure>
    <time_frame>change in baseline to Day 3</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Early change in leptin will correlate with later changes in weight (at study termination) by treatment group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in body composition, glucose, insulin and lipid metabolism, food intake and resting metabolic rate in people taking olanzapine or iloperidone</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to study termination (about 12 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To quantify, prospectively, changes in body composition, glucose, insulin and lipid metabolism, food intake and resting metabolic rate in people taking olanzapine or iloperidone. The data collected will help guide future research in the early pathophysiology of antipsychotic induced metabolic side effects.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>olanzapine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>5mg BID olanzapine for up to 4 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>iloperidone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>6mg BID iloperidone up to 4 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>BID placebo up to 4 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>olanzapine</intervention_name>
    <description>5mg BID up to 4 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>olanzapine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Zyprexa</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>iloperidone</intervention_name>
    <description>6 mg BID up to 4 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>iloperidone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fanapt</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female between the ages of 18-35 with no history of any Axis-I diagnosis

          -  Does not meet criteria for substance abuse or dependence in the past six months

          -  Female subjects will use barrier-method, non-hormonal contraception

          -  Capacity to understand all the relevant risks and potential benefits of the study
             (informed consent)

          -  Must be able to speak and read English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current or past Axis I psychiatric diagnosis, including alcohol or substance abuse or
             dependence (except nicotine or caffeine), but not including minor Axis I disorders
             (e.g. simple phobia)

          -  Lifetime use of psychotropic medications, including antipsychotics, antidepressants,
             mood stabilizers, and anxiolytics

          -  Presence or history of medical or neurological illness that, in the judgment of the
             investigator, could influence the results of the study

          -  Diagnosis of diabetes, hemoglobin A1C &gt; 6.5, hypertension, or dyslipidemias, or
             elevated random or fasting glucose, abnormal lipid levels, BP 130/85

          -  BMI 25 or &lt; 19, history of BMI &gt;35, and/or waist circumference &gt;35 inches for
             females, 40 inches for males

          -  Subjects who are pregnant or breast-feeding or planning to become pregnant during the
             study

          -  Acute suicidality

          -  Meets criteria for a Diagnostic and Statistical Manual, Version 4 (DSM-IV) defined
             eating disorder

          -  Use of, or clinical indication for, one or more of the following medications:
             lithium, anti-epileptic medication, steroids (oral or inhaled), stimulants, serotonin
             reuptake inhibitors, mirtazapine, tricyclic antidepressants, thyroid supplementation,
             sibutramine, metformin, thiazolidinediones, beta-blockers, clonidine, niacin

          -  Subjects who have had &gt;10% change in their body weight within the three months prior
             to enrollment

          -  HIV positive subjects

          -  Presence of mental retardation or pervasive developmental disorder

          -  History of recent (within 6 months) significant self-injurious behavior or violence

          -  Daily multivitamin or B-complex vitamin use

          -  A known history of dieting and difficulty with weight loss

          -  A strong family history of diabetes and/or heart disease

          -  History of congenital long QT syndrome or prolonged corrected QT interval (QTc) on
             screening EKG (&gt;450ms)

          -  Concomitant use of any medication that inhibits 2D6 or 3A4 metabolism

          -  Low serum potassium or magnesium
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeffrey Lieberman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>New York State Psychiatric Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jacob Ballon, MD</last_name>
    <phone>646-774-5205</phone>
    <email>jsb2187@columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York State Psychiatric Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jacob Ballon, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-774-5205</phone>
      <email>jsb2187@columbia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jacob Ballon, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 19, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 8, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Olanzapine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
