<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="137929">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01977781</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-067H</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01977781</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy of Topical Tacrolimus 0.05% in the Treatment of Ocular Graft-Versus-Host Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Safety and Efficacy of Topical Tacrolimus 0.05% in the Treatment of Ocular Graft-Versus-Host Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts Eye and Ear Infirmary</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts Eye and Ear Infirmary</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety and tolerability of topical tacrolimus
      0.05% twice a day in the treatment of ocular graft versus host disease (GVHD). A secondary
      objective is to compare the efficacy of topical tacrolimus 0.05% drops compared with topical
      methylprednisolone sodium succinate 0.5% drops in patients with ocular GVHD. 40 patients
      with ocular GVHD who meet the inclusion criteria of the study as determined by a screening
      visit will be divided into two equal groups. In addition to their current medication, one
      group will receive the topical tacrolimus 0.05% drops and the other group will receive the
      topical methylprednisolone sodium succinate 0.5% drops. The participants will then have two
      follow-up visits at the week 5 and week 10 markers after their screening visit.

      To evaluate the purpose of the study as well as the patient's safety, the following
      procedures will be performed at each visit: a comprehensive eye examination, tear break-up
      time (TBUT), Schirmer's test, intraocular pressure (IOP), fundoscopy and grading scores of
      lid margin and corneal fluorescein staining. The following questionnaires will be
      administered at each visit: Ocular Surface Disease Index (OSDI) and Symptom Assessment in
      Dry Eye (SANDE). Impression cytology specimens will be taken only at the screening visit and
      at the week 10 visit.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of topical tacrolimus 0.05% twice a day in the treatment of patients with ocular GVHD.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety and tolerability of topical tacrolimus 0.05% twice a day will be monitored by the occurrence of systemic and ocular adverse events in addition to symptoms directly related to the instillation or use of the investigational medication. The severity of each adverse event and relation to the study medication will be graded possibly, probably, or definitely related. Tolerability measures will be graded from trace to severe using a direct query method at each visit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare the efficacy of topical tacrolimus 0.05% twice a day to the efficacy of topical methylprednisolone sodium succinate 0.5% twice a day in reducing signs and symptoms of dry eye in patients with ocular GVHD.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Comparison of the efficacy of topical tacrolimus 0.05% and topical methylprednisolone sodium succinate 0.5% in reducing ocular signs and symptoms. Signs and symptoms will be evaluated using the following methods:
Ocular Signs
Corneal epitheliopathy (corneal fluorescein staining using the NEI grading scheme).
Tear Film Break Up Time (TBUT)
Schirmer's Test I
Expression of cellular markers of inflammation (HLA DR, ICAM-1, IL-1b, IL-2, IL-6,  IL-8, IL-10, IL-17, IL-23, IFN-g and TNF-α) using real-time polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR)  and flow cytometry (FC), on impression cytology specimens.
Ocular Symptoms
Ocular Surface Disease Index (OSDI) questionnaire.
Symptom Assessment in Dry Eye (SANDE) questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Ocular GVHD</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tacrolimus</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Topical tacrolimus suspension will be formulated and aseptically prepared from commercially available intravenous tacrolimus, PROGRAF® (Astellas Pharma US, Inc), and transferred into a sterile dropper container by the MEEI pharmacy. A formulation of 0.05% (5mg/10ml) concentration of tacrolimus with diluting solvent, LiquiTears Ophthalmic Solution (Major Pharmaceuticals, Inc.) will be used. Patients will be instructed to keep refrigerated each bottle after opening for 9 days and keep frozen the unopened bottles up to 45 days. They will also be instructed to shake the bottles at least 20 times before using it.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Methylprednisolone Sodium Succinate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Topical methylprednisolone sodium succinate suspension will be formulated and aseptically prepared from commercially available sterile dry powder vial preservative-free for intravenous use, SOLU-MEDROL® (Pfizer, Inc.). A formulation of 0.5% (5mg/1ml) concentration of methylprednisolone with diluting solvents, LiquiTears Ophthalmic Solution (Major Pharmaceuticals, Inc.) will be used. Patients will be instructed to keep refrigerated each bottle after opening for 9 days and keep frozen the unopened bottles up to 45 days. They will also be instructed to shake the bottles at least 20 times before using it.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tacrolimus</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Tacrolimus</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methylprednisolone Sodium Succinate</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Methylprednisolone Sodium Succinate</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥18 years.

          -  Willing and able to provide written informed consent.

          -  Willing and able to comply with study assessments for the full duration of the study.

          -  Diagnosis of ocular GVHD.

          -  Minimum corneal fluorescein staining of 4 (NEI grading scheme, 0-15) in at least one
             eye.

          -  Ocular Surface Disease Index score &gt;22.

          -  In good stable overall health.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of immune disease other than GVHD.

          -  Ocular or periocular malignancy.

          -  Significant change, as judged by the principal investigator, in systemic
             immunosuppressive regimen within 2 weeks of study entry.

          -  Any history of topical tacrolimus use.

          -  Any change in dosage of tetracycline compounds (tetracycline, doxycycline, and
             minocycline) within the last month.

          -  Any change in frequency of preserved anti-glaucoma medications within 2 weeks of
             study entry.

          -  Current use of topical steroids more than twice a day.

          -  Change in frequency of serum tears, topical cyclosporine and/or topical kineret
             within the last month.

          -  Corneal epithelial defect &gt;1mm2.

          -  Any history of herpetic keratitis.

          -  Participation in another simultaneous medical research study.

          -  Signs of current infection, including fever and current treatment with antibiotics.

          -  Intra-ocular surgery or ocular laser surgery within 3 months.

          -  Pregnancy (positive pregnancy test) or lactating

          -  Has worn contact lenses, except for bandage contact lens or rigid gas permeable lens,
             for the last 2 weeks prior to the study or would be unable to stay off contact lenses
             for the study duration.

          -  Any condition (including language barrier) that precludes patient's ability to comply
             with study requirements including completion of study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Reza Dana, MD, MPH, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts Eye and Ear Infirmary</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cornea Research</last_name>
    <phone>617-573-3313</phone>
    <email>Cornea_Research@meei.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts Eye and Ear Infirmary</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cornea Research</last_name>
      <phone>617-573-3313</phone>
      <email>Cornea_Research@meei.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Reza Dana, MD, MPH, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 18, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 31, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>GVHD</keyword>
  <keyword>Ocular GVHD</keyword>
  <keyword>Tacrolimus</keyword>
  <keyword>Methylprednisolone</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Graft vs Host Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone Hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tacrolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
