<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="70375">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01711541</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2012-02009</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-02009</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>A091101</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>A091101</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U10CA031946</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA014236</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>N01CM62201</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01711541</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Combination Chemotherapy With or Without Veliparib in Treating Patients With Stage IV Head and Neck Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>TPF INDUCTION CHEMOTHERAPY AND ABT-888 (VELIPARIB) - A PHASE 1/RANDOMIZED PHASE 2 STUDY IN PATIENTS WITH LOCOREGIONALLY ADVANCED SQUAMOUS CELL CARCINOMA OF THE HEAD AND NECK</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This partially randomized phase I/II trial studies the side effects and best dose of
      veliparib when given together with combination chemotherapy and how well they work in
      treating patients with IV head and neck cancer. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as
      docetaxel, cisplatin, and fluorouracil, work in different ways to stop the growth of tumor
      cells, either by killing the cells or stopping them from dividing. Veliparib may stop the
      growth of tumor cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell growth. It is not yet
      known whether combination chemotherapy is more effective when given with or without
      veliparib in treating head and neck cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD), recommended phase II dose, dose limiting
      toxicity (DLT), and safety of ABT-888 (veliparib) with cisplatin, 5FU (fluorouracil), and a
      taxane (TPF) induction chemotherapy in locoregionally advanced head and neck (LAHNC)
      patients. (Phase I) II. Compare magnitude of tumor shrinkage (response) following 2 cycles
      of induction chemotherapy consisting of TPF with and without ABT-888 in LAHNC. (Phase II)

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Compare progression-free (PFS), disease-specific (DSS), and overall survival (OS) in
      subjects treated with or without ABT-888. (Phase II)

      OUTLINE: This is a phase I, dose-escalation study of veliparib followed by a phase II study.

      PHASE I: Patients receive veliparib orally (PO) twice daily (BID) on days 1-7, docetaxel
      intravenously (IV) over 60 minutes on day 2, cisplatin IV over 60 minutes on day 2, and
      fluorouracil IV continuously over 120 hours on days 2-6. Treatment repeats every 3 weeks for
      2 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients then
      continue on to concomitant chemoradiotherapy.

      PHASE II: Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 treatment arms.

      ARM I: Patients receive veliparib, docetaxel, cisplatin, and fluorouracil as in Phase I.
      Treatment repeats every 3 weeks for 2 courses in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity. Patients then continue on to concomitant chemoradiotherapy.

      ARM II: Patients receive placebo PO BID on days 1-7. Patients also receive docetaxel,
      cisplatin, and fluorouracil as in Phase I. Treatment repeats every 3 weeks for 2 courses in
      the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients then continue on to
      concomitant chemoradiotherapy.

      CONCOMITANT CHEMORADIOTHERAPY: Patients are assigned to 1 of 2 regimens of concomitant
      chemoradiotherapy based on the guidelines of the institution where they are being treated.

      CONCOMITANT CHEMORADIATION WITH CISPLATIN: Patients receive cisplatin IV on days 1 and 22 or
      2 and 23 and undergo radiation therapy five days a week for 6 weeks.

      CONCOMITANT CHEMORADIATION WITH TFHX: Patients receive hydroxyurea PO every 12 hours on days
      1-6 (11 doses), fluorouracil IV over 120 hours on days 2-6, paclitaxel IV on day 2, and
      undergo radiation therapy BID on days 2-6. Treatment repeats every 2 weeks for 5 courses.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 2 weeks, 1 and 3 months,
      every 3 months for 2 years, every 6 months for 1 year, and then annually for 2 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Temporarily stopped for assessment. Contact ctsucontact@westat.com for specifics
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MTD of veliparib, graded according to the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE) (Phase I)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Relative change in tumor size following 2 courses of induction as measured by RECIST (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Treatment arms will be compared using the nonparametric Wilcoxon rank-sum test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity rates during induction and overall</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Toxicity rates will be summarized by group, and compared between groups using the chi-squared or Fisher's exact test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PFS</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Summarized using the method of Kaplan-Meier, and compared between groups using the log-rank test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Summarized using the method of Kaplan-Meier, and compared between groups using the log-rank test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to local or distant progression</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Summarized using the method of Kaplan-Meier, and compared between groups using the log-rank test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-specific survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Summarized using cumulative incidence, and will be compared between groups using Gray's test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Summarized using the method of Kaplan-Meier, and compared between groups using the log-rank test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Human Papilloma Virus Infection</condition>
  <condition>Salivary Gland Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Nasopharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Salivary Gland Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Lip and Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Oropharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Verrucous Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Verrucous Carcinoma of the Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Salivary Gland Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Lip and Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Oropharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Verrucous Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Verrucous Carcinoma of the Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Tongue Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (veliparib, combination chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive veliparib PO BID on days 1-7, docetaxel IV over 60 minutes on day 2, cisplatin IV over 60 minutes on day 2, and fluorouracil IV continuously over 120 hours on days 2-6. Treatment repeats every 3 weeks for 2 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients then continue on to concomitant chemoradiotherapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (placebo, combination chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive placebo PO BID on days 1-7. Patients also receive docetaxel, cisplatin, and fluorouracil as in Arm I. Treatment repeats every 3 weeks for 2 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients then continue on to concomitant chemoradiotherapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>veliparib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (veliparib, combination chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ABT-888</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (placebo, combination chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PLCB</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>docetaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (veliparib, combination chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (placebo, combination chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>RP 56976</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxotere</other_name>
    <other_name>TXT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cisplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (veliparib, combination chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (placebo, combination chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CACP</other_name>
    <other_name>CDDP</other_name>
    <other_name>CPDD</other_name>
    <other_name>DDP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fluorouracil</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (veliparib, combination chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (placebo, combination chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>5-fluorouracil</other_name>
    <other_name>5-Fluracil</other_name>
    <other_name>5-FU</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo radiation therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (veliparib, combination chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (placebo, combination chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>irradiation</other_name>
    <other_name>radiotherapy</other_name>
    <other_name>therapy, radiation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>hydroxyurea</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (veliparib, combination chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (placebo, combination chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>HU</other_name>
    <other_name>HYD</other_name>
    <other_name>Hydrea</other_name>
    <other_name>Hydroxycarbamide</other_name>
    <other_name>Hydurea</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (veliparib, combination chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (placebo, combination chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Anzatax</other_name>
    <other_name>Asotax</other_name>
    <other_name>TAX</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  PHASE I:

          -  Patients who are treatment naïve, high risk, stage IVa/IVb (all other sites) and
             histologically proven squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck (SCCHN) with no
             definitive evidence of metastatic disease, excluding patients with oropharynx
             HPV-positive tumors; in summary, those patients eligible are newly diagnosed and
             treatment naive:

               -  Stage IVa-b Squamous Cell Carcinoma other than Oropharyngeal Cancer (OPC), OR

               -  Oropharyngeal Cancer (OPC) HPV-negative, Stage IVa-b

          -  PHASE II:

          -  Patients who are treatment naïve, high risk, stage IVa/IVb (all other sites) and
             histologically proven squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck (SCCHN) with no
             definitive evidence of metastatic disease, excluding patients with oropharynx
             HPV-positive tumors; in summary, those patients eligible are newly diagnosed and
             treatment naive:

               -  Stage IVa-b Squamous Cell Carcinoma other than Oropharyngeal Cancer (OPC), OR

               -  Oropharyngeal Cancer (OPC) HPV-negative, Stage IVa-b

          -  PHASE I AND II:

          -  Patients must have at least one measurable site of disease according to Response
             Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) criteria; i.e., patients must have
             measurable disease, defined as at least one lesion that can be accurately measured in
             at least one dimension (longest diameter to be recorded for non-nodal lesions and
             short axis for nodal lesions) as &gt;= 20 mm with conventional techniques or as &gt;= 10 mm
             with spiral computed tomography (CT) scan magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), or
             calipers by clinical exam

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0-1

          -  Patients must be able to swallow the drug

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

          -  Leukocytes &gt;= 3,000/mm^3

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1,500/mm^3

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100,000/mm^3

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; institutional upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT) (aspartate aminotransferase [AST]) and
             serum glutamic pyruvate transaminase (SGPT) (alanine aminotransferase [ALT]) =&lt; 2.5 X
             institutional ULN

          -  Creatinine clearance &gt;= 60 mL/min/1.73 m^2 for patients with creatinine levels above
             ULN

          -  Patients who are receiving any other investigational agents are not eligible

          -  Patients with active seizure or a history of seizure are not eligible

          -  Patients with a history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar
             chemical or biologic composition to ABT-888 or other agents used in study, including
             Cremophor, docetaxel, cisplatin, 5-fluorouracil, hydroxyurea, or any compounds of
             similar chemical or biologic composition are not eligible

          -  Patients with impairment of gastrointestinal function or gastrointestinal disease
             that may significantly alter the absorption of ABT-888 (e.g., ulcerative disease,
             uncontrolled nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, malabsorption syndrome or small bowel
             resection) are not eligible to participate in this study

          -  Patients with uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to,
             ongoing or active infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina
             pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would
             limit compliance with study requirements are not eligible to participate in the study

          -  Pregnant women are not eligible to participate in this study; NOTE: women of child
             bearing potential must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test within 7 days
             prior to registration; ABT-888 is a poly adenosine diphosphate ribose (ADP) ribose
             polymerase (PARP) inhibitor with the potential for teratogenic or abortifacient
             effects;

               -  Women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate
                  contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to
                  study entry and for the duration of study participation; should a woman become
                  pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while she or her partner is participating in
                  this study, she should inform her treating physician immediately;

               -  Because there is an unknown but potential risk for adverse events in nursing
                  infants secondary to treatment of the mother with ABT-888, breastfeeding should
                  be discontinued if the mother is treated with ABT-888; these potential risks may
                  also apply to other agents used in this study

          -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-positive patients on combination antiretroviral
             therapy are not eligible because of the potential for pharmacokinetic interactions
             with ABT-888

          -  Patients receiving chronic, systemic treatment with corticosteroids or another
             immunosuppressive agent are not eligible to participate in this study; topical or
             inhaled corticosteroids are allowed

          -  Patients with other malignancies within the past 2 years, except for adequately
             treated carcinoma of the cervix or basal or squamous cell carcinomas of the skin or
             surgically treated early stage solid tumors are ineligible to participate in this
             study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jonas De Souza</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cancer and Leukemia Group B</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 18, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Laryngeal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Papilloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Virus Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tongue Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Verrucous</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Salivary Gland Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Laryngeal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Warts</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paranasal Sinus Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Papillomavirus Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oropharyngeal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nasopharyngeal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluorouracil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydroxyurea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
