<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="55375">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01962532</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR102388</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>42756493GAC1001</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01962532</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Safety, Pharmacokinetics, and Pharmacodynamics of JNJ-42756493 in Patients With Advanced or Refractory Solid Tumors or Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1 Study to Evaluate the Safety, Pharmacokinetics, and Pharmacodynamics of JNJ-42756493, a Pan-Fibroblast Growth Factor Receptor (FGFR) Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor, in Subjects With Advanced or Refractory Solid Tumors or Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Japan: Pharmaceuticals and Medical Devices Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine a dose for future development and the safety,
      pharmacokinetics, pharmacodynamics, and efficacy profiles of JNJ-42756493 in Japanese and
      other Asian patients with advanced or refractory solid tumors or lymphoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-label (identity of assigned study drug will be known), 2-part
      dose-escalation study to evaluate the safety, pharmacokinetics (study of what the body does
      to a drug), and pharmacodynamics (study of what a drug does to the body) of JNJ-42756493
      administered by mouth once daily in 21-day cycles to Japanese and Asian participants &gt;=20
      years of age with advanced or refractory solid tumors or lymphoma who are not candidates for
      approved or available therapies. Approximately 54 participants will be enrolled.
      Participants will be required to be hospitalized after the first dose on Day 1 of Cycle 1
      until Day 2 of Cycle 2. The Part 1 dose-escalation phase is designed to determine the
      recommended Phase 2 dose based on safety, pharmacokinetic, and pharmacodynamic data of
      JNJ-42756493. Participants will be enrolled in sequential cohorts based on the 3+3
      dose-escalation scheme; the first cohort will receive the starting dose and subsequent
      cohorts will receive increased doses of JNJ-42756493. After the last participants in each
      cohort completes Cycle 1, the Safety Evaluation Team (SET) will evaluate the safety and
      pharmacokinetic data according to protocol-defined criteria and make the decision whether to
      escalate the dose in a new cohort. To determine the recommended Phase 2 dose, the SET will
      review all safety, pharmacokinetic, and pharmacodynamic data from Part 1 before initiation
      of Part 2. The total number of participants enrolled in Part 1 will depend on the dose level
      at which the recommended Phase 2 dose is established. After the recommended Phase 2 dose is
      established, the Part 2 dose-expansion phase will be opened. In Part 2, approximately 36
      participants will be treated at the recommended Phase 2 dose in order to evaluate fibroblast
      growth factor receptor target modulation in tumor, to further elaborate safety,
      pharmacokinetics, and pharmacodynamics of JNJ-42756493, as well as to evaluate preliminary
      clinical responses. Participants who are tolerating study drug treatment and achieve
      clinical responses or stable disease will continue to receive study drug at the same dose
      until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, or withdrawal of consent. Serial
      pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic samples will be collected, and safety and efficacy will
      be monitored throughout the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants affected by adverse events by MedDRA system organ class (SOC) and Preferred term (PT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after the last dose of study medication</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum observed plasma concentration of JNJ-42756493</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Part 2 Cycle 4 Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Minimum observed plasma concentration of JNJ-42756493</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Part 2 Cycle 4 Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time correspondent to the maximum observed plasma concentration of JNJ-42756493</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Part 2 Cycle 4 Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time 0 to 24 hours of JNJ-42756493</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Part 2 Cycle 4 Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Half-life of JNJ-42756493</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Part 2 Cycle 4 Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent volume of distribution of JNJ-42756493</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Part 2 Cycle 4 Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total clearance of drug of JNJ-42756493</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Part 2 Cycle 4 Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Accumulation index of JNJ-42756493</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Part 2 Cycle 4 Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with complete response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Part 2 Day 84 (Cycle 4, Day 21)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with partial response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Part 2 Day 84 (Cycle 4, Day 21)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with stable disease</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Part 2 Day 84 (Cycle 4, Day 21)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with progressive disease</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Part 2 Day 84 (Cycle 4, Day 21)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">54</enrollment>
  <condition>Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1: Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose escalation of JNJ-42756493 is to occur until a dose at which &lt;33 percent of participants experience a dose-limiting toxicity, the maximum concentration of JNJ-42756493 is less than the protocol-defined cardiovascular threshold, and JNJ-42756493 is biologically active.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2: Dose Expansion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive the recommended Phase 2 JNJ-42756493 dose determined in Part 1. Participants who are tolerating study drug treatment and achieve clinical responses or stable disease will continue to receive study drug at the same dose until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, or withdrawal of consent.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Part 1: JNJ-42756493</intervention_name>
    <description>JNJ-42756493 dose escalation starting at 2 mg daily by mouth will be taken for 21-day cycles up to the maximum tolerated dose in order to determine the recommended Phase 2 dose.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1: Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Part 2: JNJ-42756493</intervention_name>
    <description>Recommended Phase 2 JNJ-42756493 dose determined in Part 1 administered by mouth once daily (21-day cycles).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2: Dose Expansion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically or cytologically confirmed solid malignancy or lymphoma that is
             metastatic or unresectable, and for which standard curative treatment is no longer
             effective

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status score 0 or 1

          -  Adequate bone marrow, liver, and renal function according to protocol-defined
             criteria within the 7 days prior to Day 1 of Cycle 1

          -  Laboratory values within protocol -defined parameters

          -  Agrees to protocol-defined use of effective contraception

          -  Negative urine pregnancy test at screening for women of child bearing potential

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has had chemotherapy, radiotherapy, immunotherapy, or treatment with an
             investigational anticancer agent within 3 weeks (nitrosoureas and mitomycin C within
             6 weeks) before the first administration of study drug (localized radiation therapy
             for palliative purposes and ongoing luteinizing hormone-releasing hormone agonists
             and antagonists for patients with prostate cancer are permitted

          -  History or current condition of uncontrolled cardiovascular disease as defined in the
             protocol

          -  Taking medications known to have a risk of causing QTc prolongation and Torsades de
             Pointes or known as strong CYP3A inhibitors or inducers

          -  Left ventricular ejection fraction &lt;50 percent as assessed by echocardiography
             performed at screening

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, poorly controlled
             hypertension or diabetes, ongoing active infection, psychiatric illness, or a risk of
             gastrointestinal perforation

          -  Woman who is pregnant, breast-feeding, or planning to become pregnant or a man who
             plans to father a child while enrolled in this study or within 3 months after the
             last dose of study drug

          -  Not recovered from reversible, clinically significant toxicity of prior anticancer
             therapy

          -  Presence of any medical condition that requires intact wound healing capacity and is
             expected to endanger participant safety if wound healing capacity would be severely
             reduced during administration of the investigational agent

          -  Major surgery within 4 weeks before enrollment

          -  Known human immunodeficiency virus infection

          -  Known hepatitis B or C (except hepatocellular carcinoma)

          -  Active, symptomatic, or untreated brain metastasis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Use link at the bottom of the page to see if you qualify for an enrolling site (see list). If you still have questions:</last_name>
    <email>JNJ.CT@sylogent.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kashiwa</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Matsuyama</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Tokyo</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://pam.sylogent.com/cr/CR102388</url>
    <description>To learn how to participate in this trial please click here.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 8, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 26, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neoplasms</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Advanced or refractory solid tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>Advanced or refractory lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>JNJ-42756493</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Japanese</keyword>
  <keyword>Asian</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacodynamics</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
