<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="40045">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01701323</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2584.00</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-01724</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2584.00</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA015704</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01701323</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Laboratory-Treated Donor Cord Blood Cell Infusion Following Combination Chemotherapy in Treating Younger Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Acute Myeloid Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot Study Evaluating the Use of Ex Vivo Expanded Cord Blood Progenitors as Supportive Care Following Induction Chemotherapy (FLAG) in Patients With Relapsed/Refractory AML</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Seattle Children's Research Institute Center for Clinical and Translational Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bayley Family Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This pilot clinical trial studies infusion of laboratory-grown donor cord blood cells
      following combination chemotherapy in treating younger patients with relapsed or refractory
      acute myeloid leukemia. Chemotherapy drugs work in different ways to stop the growth of
      cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing. Chemotherapy
      also kills healthy infection-fighting cells, increasing the risk of infection. The infusion
      of laboratory-grown cord blood cells may be able to replace blood-forming cells that were
      destroyed by chemotherapy. This may decrease the risk of infection following chemotherapy,
      and allow for more chemotherapy to be given so that more cancer cells are killed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Assess the safety of infusing &quot;off-the-shelf&quot; non-human leukocyte antigen (HLA) matched
      expanded cord blood cells as supportive care following administration of FLAG (fludarabine
      phosphate, cytarabine, and filgrastim) reinduction chemotherapy in pediatric and young adult
      patients with relapsed/refractory acute myeloid leukemia (AML).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Assess the kinetics of autologous recovery when compared to historical cohorts.

      II. Assess the ability of the product to provide transient myeloid engraftment/recovery.

      III. Examine the in vivo persistence of the ex vivo expanded cord blood cells by determining
      the kinetics and durability of potential engraftment.

      IV. Estimate the incidence of clinically significant infections (e.g. bacterial, viral, or
      fungal) observed in patients treated with FLAG reinduction chemotherapy followed by
      &quot;off-the-shelf&quot; non-HLA matched expanded cord blood cells.

      V. Assess the percentage of patients that achieve complete remission (CR)/complete remission
      with incomplete blood count recovery (CRi)/complete remission with partial recovery of
      platelet count (CRp) with this therapy approach.

      VI. Assess long term efficacy (overall survival [OS]/disease free survival [DFS]) of FLAG
      reinduction chemotherapy followed by &quot;off-the-shelf&quot; non HLA matched expanded cord blood
      cells in pediatric relapsed AML patients during long term follow up.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive filgrastim subcutaneously (SC) or intravenously (IV) on days 1-7,
      fludarabine phosphate IV over 30 minutes on days 2-6, cytarabine IV over 4 hours on days
      2-6, and ex vivo-expanded cord blood progenitor cells IV over 30 minutes on day 8.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 6 months for 2 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of grade &gt; 3 infusional toxicity with administration of ex vivo expanded cord blood therapy according to the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of transfusion associated graft-versus-host disease (GVHD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of platelet refractoriness in the presence of alloimmunization as a direct result of ex vivo expanded cord blood product infusion</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Delayed marrow recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>After day 42</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of treatment related mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to neutrophil recovery (absolute neutrophil count [ANC] &gt; 100/ul and 500/ul)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>In vivo persistence of ex vivo expanded cellular therapy by peripheral blood cell sorted deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) chimerisms of the cluster of differentiation myeloid and lymphoid cell lineages as well as whole marrow chimerisms</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of grade 3 or 4 infections per NCI CTCAE version 4 in the neutropenic period following FLAG administration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of grade &gt; 3 chemotherapy-related toxicity in the first 30 days following FLAG therapy defined by NCI CTCAE version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of CR</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of CRi</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of CRp</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Leukemia-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Leukemias of Ambiguous Lineage</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With 11q23 (MLL) Abnormalities</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With Del(5q)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With Inv(16)(p13;q22)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With t(15;17)(q22;q12)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With t(16;16)(p13;q22)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With t(8;21)(q22;q22)</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Childhood Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ex vivo expanded cord blood progenitors)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive filgrastim SC or IV on days 1-7, fludarabine phosphate IV over 30 minutes on days 2-6, cytarabine IV over 4 hours on days 2-6, and ex vivo-expanded cord blood progenitor cells IV over 30 minutes on day 8.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>filgrastim</intervention_name>
    <description>Given SC or IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ex vivo expanded cord blood progenitors)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>G-CSF</other_name>
    <other_name>Neupogen</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fludarabine phosphate</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ex vivo expanded cord blood progenitors)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>2-F-ara-AMP</other_name>
    <other_name>Beneflur</other_name>
    <other_name>Fludara</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cytarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ex vivo expanded cord blood progenitors)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ARA-C</other_name>
    <other_name>arabinofuranosylcytosine</other_name>
    <other_name>arabinosylcytosine</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytosar-U</other_name>
    <other_name>cytosine arabinoside</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ex vivo-expanded cord blood progenitor cell infusion</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ex vivo expanded cord blood progenitors)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have a diagnosis of AML or acute leukemia of ambiguous lineage
             according to World Health Organization (WHO) classification with &gt;= 5% of disease in
             bone marrow (BM), with or without extramedullary disease or biopsy-proven isolated
             myeloid sarcoma (myeloblastoma, chloroma, including leukemia cutis) in the absence of
             marrow involvement

          -  AML or acute leukemia of ambiguous lineage:

               -  If relapse AML or acute leukemia of ambiguous lineage:

                    -  Must have a prior diagnosis of AML or acute leukemia of ambiguous lineage
                       and be in 1st or greater relapse

                    -  Must not have received prior reinduction therapy for this relapse

               -  If primary refractory AML or acute leukemia of ambiguous lineage:

                    -  Must have had a prior diagnosis of AML or acute leukemia of ambiguous
                       lineage and

                    -  Must not have received more than 3 previous induction attempts

               -  Patients meeting above criteria are eligible regardless of central nervous
                  system (CNS) classification

          -  Recipients of prior allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation are eligible
             if they have quiescent graft versus host disease (GVHD) whether or not they are
             receiving immunosuppressive therapy

          -  Must have a Lansky or Karnofsky performance status of &gt;= 50; use Karnofsky for
             patients &gt; 16 years of age and Lansky for patients =&lt; 16 years of age

          -  Patients must have recovered from the acute toxicity of all prior chemotherapy;
             patients may not have received cytotoxic chemotherapy within 2 weeks of first dose of
             G-CSF (filgrastim) therapy, with exception of hydroxyurea, which is allowed for up to
             24 hours prior to first dose of G-CSF, and intrathecal chemotherapy, which is allowed
             prior to, or in the 1st 72 hours after start of G-CSF therapy

          -  The following amounts of time must have elapsed prior to entry on study:

               -  2 weeks from local radiation therapy (XRT)

               -  8 weeks from prior craniospinal or if &gt; 50% of the pelvis has been irradiated

               -  6 weeks must have elapsed if other bone marrow radiation has occurred

          -  Creatinine within normal range for age (per institutional defined lab value ranges)

          -  Direct bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 upper limit of normal (ULN) age unless elevation thought to
             be due or hepatic infiltration by the hematologic malignancy

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &lt; 5 x ULN age

          -  Adequate cardiac function as defined as shortening fraction of &gt; 27% OR ejection
             fraction of &gt; 50%

          -  Patients must have a calculated QT (QTc) interval &lt; 450 ms on baseline echocardiogram

          -  Patients must demonstrate a respiratory rate that is within normal limits for age,
             measured when afebrile and at rest (measured for a full minute) and pulse oximetry &gt;
             93% on room air

          -  Signed informed consent

          -  Patient must have a life expectancy of at least 2 months

          -  Females of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test performed
             within 7 days prior to the start of treatment

          -  Females of childbearing potential and males should agree to use adequate
             contraception (barrier method of birth control) prior to study entry and for the
             duration of study participation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Recipients of prior allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT) with active
             acute or chronic GVHD

          -  Patients with history of Down's syndrome, Fanconi anemia or other known marrow
             failure condition

          -  Patients currently receiving other investigational drugs are not eligible

          -  Current concomitant chemotherapy, radiation therapy, or immunotherapy other than as
             specified in the protocol with the exception of intrathecal chemotherapy; this
             includes the tyrosine kinase inhibitor sorafenib which must not be initiated until
             patient demonstrates count recovery

          -  Patients with a systemic fungal, bacterial, viral, or other infection not controlled
             despite appropriate antibiotics or other treatment; uncontrolled systemic infections
             require infectious disease consultation for verification

          -  Patients who are platelet refractory prior to initiation of protocol therapy;
             platelet refractoriness is defined by platelet count &lt; 50K when platelet count is
             obtained 1 hour post platelet transfusion

          -  Pregnant or lactating patients

          -  Any significant concurrent disease, illness, or psychiatric disorder that would
             compromise patient safety or compliance, interfere with consent, study participation,
             follow up, or interpretation of study results
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ann Dahlberg</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Muna Qayed</last_name>
      <phone>404-268-6806</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Muna Qayed</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ann E. Dahlberg</last_name>
      <phone>206-667-1959</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ann E. Dahlberg</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 3, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Congenital Abnormalities</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cytarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine monophosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vidarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lenograstim</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
