<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="14770">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01651208</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1RC1MD004327</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01651208</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Improving Adherence to Post PCI Antiplatelet Therapy in Minority Populations</brief_title>
  <official_title>Improving Adherence to Post PCI Antiplatelet Therapy in Minority Populations</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Miami</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Humana, Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Miami</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The use of a phone based motivational interviewing among minority populations who received a
      coronary stent will improve adherence to antiplatelet agents from approximately 51% to 66%
      (15 percentage point increase) at 12 months post stent placement when compared to a mailed
      educational DVD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Other aims are: 1) Improve the self reported adherence of antiplatelet medications
      2)Identify specific barriers for the use of post PCI anti-platelet therapy among minority
      populations enrolled in Humana by administering a short survey at the baseline recruitment
      call and at the 12 month follow up call, 3) identify predictors of never filling an
      anti-platelet therapy prescription post PCIS.

      Inclusion criteria:

      We will include black or Hispanic patients having coronary stenting using the following
      codes for bare metal or drug eluting stents: ICD-9 procedure codes (36.06) or (36.07),
      MS-DRG codes 247-249 or CPT codes 92980, 92981, C1984 G0290, G0291. The identification
      period will last approximately 10 months.

      Primary Outcome: Medication Possession ratio as a dichotomous variable (appropriate/not
      appropriate adherence) and as a continuous variable Secondary outcome: Self reported
      adherence by Morisky score Barriers to appropriate adherence Predictors of adherence
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Medication possession ratio (MPR)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after receiving coronary stent</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Mean Possession ratio (MPR) is a continuous multiple interval measure of medication availability. This is a validated method of estimating medication adherence . The medication possession ratio is defined as the sum of the days' supply of medication divided by the number of days between the first fill and the last refill plus the days' supply of the last refill.We will use the previously validated cutpoint of MPR&gt;=.80 to define the binary outcome of Appropriate Adherence</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Morisky Score</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at 12 month post stent placement</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will use a 4 item validated survey to capture self reported adherence to antiplatelet medications</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">452</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Motivational interviewing (MINT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The MINT intervention will consist of 4 to 7 telephone encounters between a nurse trained in Motivational interviewing and a minority subject who recently received a coronary stent. All subjects in the MINT arm will be contacted every 3 months to complete 4 encounters.MINT is a well-known, scientifically tested behavioral counseling strategy developed as an amalgamation of principles drawn from several theoretical paradigms, the most important of which are Self-Determination Theory, Patient-Centeredness, Self-Efficacy theory, and the Stages of Change model.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mailed DVD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A DVD that re-enforces an adequate behavior regarding adherence to anti-platelet will be compared to a MINT intervention. The DVD will also address many questions and concerns patients have after stent placement. The intervention is based on role theory and the effects of vicarious learning via electronic media with respect to Cardiovascular behaviors.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Motivational Interviewing (MINT)</intervention_name>
    <description>We will hire a Latino and an AA nurse to deliver the interventions and will match their race/ethnicity with that of the subject. Past experience suggests that at 4-7 calls per subjects each lasting about 30-45 minutes, a nurse can carry a caseload of about 125-150 subject (we propose 125 per nurse) Each telephone encounter will have a patient centered approach having the following basic structure and goals:
a)Establishing a connection and reinforcing autonomy b)Empathizing with ambivalence and rolling with resistance.c)Coach the subject towards expressions of commitment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Motivational interviewing (MINT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mailed DVD</intervention_name>
    <description>The DVD will have a documentary format that will engage subjects as the portrayed real patients relate their struggles and successes, that will entertain and ultimately motivate subjects to succeed in a similar way as the role models in the video. That personal connection will activate patients to address their own adherence issues and will show real life ways to deal with the health behaviors recommended post PCIS. Key concepts regarding adherence to medications and other behaviors will be imbedded in the story telling. The DVD will also feature a humanistic perspective of a cardiologist talking about his concerns for his patients that do not adhere to the antiplatelet therapy, the difficulties that his patients face, and the merit of the success stories he witnesses.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mailed DVD</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  We will identify prospectively all subjects who undergo coronary stenting using the
             following codes for bare metal or drug eluting stents: ICD-9 procedure codes (36.06)
             or (36.07), MS-DRG codes 247-249 or CPT codes 92980, 92981, C1984 G0290, G0291

          -  We will select subjects identified as Black or Hispanics by a validated algorithm
             that uses the Medicare race code, geocoding techniques and the Spanish Surname list.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Lack of medical files to document stent placement.

          2. Not receiving  informed consent.

          3. Subjects with contraindications for antiplatelet therapy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ana M Palacio, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Miami</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Miami</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Palacio AM, Tamariz LJ, Uribe C, Li H, Salkeld EJ, Hazel-Fernandez L, Carrasquillo O. Can claims-based data be used to recruit black and Hispanic subjects into clinical trials? Health Serv Res. 2012 Apr;47(2):770-82. doi: 10.1111/j.1475-6773.2011.01316.x. Epub 2011 Aug 30.</citation>
    <PMID>22091834</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 24, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 24, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Miami</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ana M. Palacio</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Clinical Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Coronary stents</keyword>
  <keyword>Medication adherence</keyword>
  <keyword>Antiplatelet medications</keyword>
  <keyword>Motivational Interviewing</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
