<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="25051">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01880814</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>5K23MH093491</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01880814</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Using SMART Experimental Design to Personalize Treatment for Child Depression</brief_title>
  <acronym>SMART</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase 1 of Using SMART Experimental Design to Personalize Treatment for Child Depression</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: National Institute of Mental Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Child depression is among the most prevalent and impairing pediatric conditions and
      constitutes a major public health concern. Unfortunately, treatment benefits are relatively
      modest and short-lived with sizeable percentages of children who maintain depressive
      symptoms following treatment. This problem may be addressed in part by personalizing
      treatment, including determining which children will benefit from caregiver involvement in
      treatment. The goal of the current proposal is to pilot test an innovative experimental
      design called Sequential, Multiple Assignment, Randomized Trial (SMART), which is used for
      development of personalized treatments, and assess the acceptability and feasibility of
      using this design, in preparation for a full-scale SMART in a larger clinical trial and for
      the development of personalized treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Childhood depression constitutes a major public health concern, requiring effective
      interventions. The effects of treatments for childhood depression are relatively modest and
      short-lived, with sizeable percentages of children who maintain depressive symptoms
      following treatment. A potential barrier to treatment success is the single uniform format
      of treatment protocols, addressing all depressed children similarly, regardless of clinical
      presentation. One strategy for addressing this barrier is to personalize treatment, fitting
      intervention to the specific needs of the children being targeted. This approach is
      consistent with the strategic plan of the National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH) to
      emphasize the development of personalized interventions.

      Studies have documented the importance of family context in the development and maintenance
      of childhood depression; however, the limited number of clinical trials that involved
      caregivers provided mixed results, with only some youths benefiting from caregiver
      involvement in treatment. A logical first step in personalizing treatment is to develop
      decision rules about which children are likely to benefit from caregiver involvement in
      treatment, and at what point in treatment caregiver involvement should occur. The proposed
      study will take the first step toward addressing these key personalizing questions, using
      the Sequential, Multiple Assignment, Randomized Trial (SMART) design, an experimental method
      that is well-suited to the development of personalized treatments.

      The proposed project will focus on the first step in the development of personalized
      treatment for depressed children, piloting use of the SMART design. The study has two aims.
      Aim 1 includes the refinement of the individual CBT and caregiver-child treatment manuals
      for use in the SMART trial. Aim 2 includes a pilot study of the SMART experimental design,
      with 48, 7-14 year-old children who meet criteria for Major Depressive Disorder and/or
      Dysthymic Disorder. The pilot study will provide information about the acceptability of the
      treatment manuals, assessments, and study procedures and about the feasibility of the
      two-step randomization used in the SMART design. The resulting information will inform the
      development of a full-scale properly-powered SMART trial (for a later study). The long-term
      objective is to use the SMART trial methods to guide development of personalized treatment
      for child depression.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Factorial Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Schedule for Affective Disorders and Schizophrenia for School-Aged Children-Present and Lifetime Versions (K-SADS-PL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment, 6 weeks, 12 weeks, 3-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Semi-structured diagnostic interview with children and caregivers assessing present episode and lifetime history of psychiatric illness. All modules will be administered at pre-treatment to establish depression as a primary disorder. In later assessment points, only depression module will be administered.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Children's Depression Rating Scale-Revised (CDRS-R)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment, 6 weeks, 12 weeks, 3-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Semi-structured child interview of depression.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Children's Depression Inventory 2: Self Report (CDI2:SR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment, 6 weeks, 12 weeks, 3-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Child self-report questionnaire assessing depressive symptoms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Children's Depression Inventory 2:Parent (CDI 2:P)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment, 6 weeks, 12 weeks, 3-month follow-up, before each treatment session</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Parent report questionnaire assessing child's depressive symptoms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Children's Depression Inventory 2: Self Report Short Version (CDI 2:SR[S])</measure>
    <time_frame>Before each treatment session</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Child self-report questionnaire assessing depressive symptoms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impression (CGI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment, 6 weeks, 12 weeks, 3-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessor assessment of child's symptom severity and level of improvement.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Automatic Thoughts Questionnaire (ATQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment,  6 weeks, 12 weeks, 3-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Child self-report questionnaire assessing negative self-thoughts.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Children's Negative Cognitive Error Questionnaire (CNCEQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment,  6 weeks, 12 weeks, 3-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Child self-report questionnaire assessing cognitive distortions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent Child Relationship Questionnaire - Child (PCRQ-C)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment,  6 weeks, 12 weeks, 3-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Child self-report questionnaire assessing relationship with the parent.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent Child Relationship Questionnaire - Parent (PCRQ-P)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment,  6 weeks, 12 weeks, 3-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Parent self-report questionnaire assessing relationship with the child.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parenting Stress Index - Short Form (PSI-SF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment, 6 weeks, 12 weeks, 3-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Parent self-report questionnaire assessing parenting stress.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Five Minute Speech Sample (FMSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment, 6 weeks, 12 weeks, 3-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Parent verbal report that is coded by a coder in order to assess expressed emotion (EE).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beck Depression Inventory II (BDI-II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment, 6 weeks, 12 weeks, 3-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Parent self-report questionnaire assessing depressive symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Brief Symptom Inventory (BSI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment, 6 weeks, 12 weeks, 3-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Parent self-report questionnaire assessing psychopathology.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Family Information Form</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Parent questionnaire of demographic information.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment Services</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks, 12 weeks, 3-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Parent report questionnaire of additional therapeutic services received throughout treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Therapeutic Alliance Scale for Children-Revised (TASC-r)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Child self-report questionnaire assessing the quality of alliance with the therapist.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Therapeutic Alliance Scale for Caregivers and Parents (TASCP)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Parent self-report questionnaire assessing the quality of alliance with the therapist.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Child Satisfaction Scale (CSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Child self-report questionnaire assessing satisfaction with the treatment.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Parent  Satisfaction Scale (PSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Parent self-report questionnaire assessing satisfaction with the treatment.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Therapist Satisfaction Index (TSI)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Therapist self-report questionnaire assessing satisfaction with the treatment.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Behavioral Treatment (CBT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Children will first be randomized into one of two initial treatments: individual Cognitive Behavioral Treatment (CBT) or Caregiver-Child Treatment. The individual CBT arm will be conducted once per week for six weeks. After the initial treatment, child's response to treatment will be evaluated. Responders will be re-randomized into no treatment or individual CBT (these sessions will focus on mastering the skills and enhancing fluency in use of the skills). Non-responders will be re-randomized into one of two treatments: individual CBT or Caregiver-Child Treatment. Sessions will be conducted once per week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Caregiver-Child Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Children will first be randomized into one of two initial treatments: individual Cognitive Behavioral Treatment (CBT) or Caregiver-Child Treatment. The caregiver-child treatment arm will be conducted once per week for six weeks. After the initial treatment, child's response to treatment will be evaluated. Responders will be re-randomized into no treatment or Caregiver-Child Treatment (these sessions will focus on mastering the skills and enhancing fluency in use of the skills). Non-responders will be re-randomized into one of two treatments: Caregiver-Child Treatment or individual CBT. Sessions will be conducted once per week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Behavioral Treatment (CBT)</intervention_name>
    <description>The components of the individual CBT manual include: (1) Problem Solving - operationalization of problems and solution brainstorm and evaluation, (2) Activity Scheduling - engagement in positive and mood enhancing activities, (3) Cognitive Restructuring - identification and change of negative and unrealistic thoughts into positive and realistic thoughts, (4) Relaxation - progressive muscle relaxation and brief relaxation, and (5) Social Skills Self-Modeling - strategies for presentation of positive and engaging self (e.g., smile) in social interactions, starting conversations, and joining groups.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Behavioral Treatment (CBT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Caregiver-Child Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Caregiver-Child Treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>The components of the Caregiver-Child Treatment manual include: (1) Special Time - increasing quality time of caregiver with child; (2) Family Problem Solving - operationalization of problems that involve the caregiver and the child, solution brainstorming and systematic evaluation; (3) Positive Communication - praise, active listening, reflection, reducing blame, and increasing positive exchanges; (4) Communication: Negotiation and Conflict Resolution - communication skills, compromise, and realistic expectations; and (5) Positive Mood and Behavior Management - positive reinforcement of positive mood behaviors (e.g., positive affect and prosocial behaviors) and positive behavior (e.g., contingency management and behavioral contracting).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Behavioral Treatment (CBT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Caregiver-Child Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Current Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) and/or Dysthymic Disorder (DD) diagnosis.

          2. If receiving psychiatric medication, dose should be stable for at least three months
             at enrollment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. A disorder other than depression as primary diagnosis.

          2. Autism Spectrum Disorders.

          3. Psychotic Disorders.

          4. Suicidal behavior.

          5. Participation in additional psychotherapy.

          6. Caregiver and/or children do not speak English.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>14 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dikla Eckshtain, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>617-643-7821</phone>
    <email>deckshtain@mgh.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dikla Eckshtain</last_name>
      <phone>617-643-7821</phone>
      <email>deckshtain@mgh.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.partners.org/trials.aspx?tId=6279</url>
    <description>ClinicalTrials@Partners</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.massgeneral.org/psychiatry/services/child_cbt_cope_study.aspx</url>
    <description>Child Cognitive-Behavioral Therapy (CBT) Program at Massachusetts General Hospital</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 28, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 10, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dikla Eckshtain, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Instructor in Psychology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Depression, child, cognitive behavioral treatment, parent training, personalized treatment</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
