<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="8379">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02086604</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201404056</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02086604</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Brentuximab Vedotin and Lenalidomide for Relapsed or Refractory Diffuse Large B-cell Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Trial of Brentuximab Vedotin in Combination With Lenalidomide in Relapsed or Refractory Diffuse Large B-cell Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This Phase I clinical trial studies the side effects and maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of the
      combination of brentuximab vedotin (BV) and lenalidomide  in the treatment of patients with
      relapsed or refractory diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This Phase I clinical trial studies the side effects and maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of the
      combination of brentuximab vedotin (BV) and lenalidomide  in the treatment of patients with
      relapsed or refractory diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL). This study will also evaluate
      the effectiveness of the drug combination as measured by overall response rate, duration of
      response and progression free survival.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>21 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Hematologic DLT is defined as any of the following that occur during the first cycle that are attributed as possibly, probably, or definitely related to the study treatment:
Grade 4 neutropenia &gt; 7 day duration
Grade 4 infection with grade 3 or 4 neutropenia (life-threatening sepsis)
Grade 4 thrombocytopenia associated with life-threatening bleeding or requiring more than 1 transfusion
Treatment delay &gt; 14 days due to hematologic toxicity
Non-hematologic DLT is defined as any possibly, probably, or definitely related grade 3 or grade 4 non-hematologic toxicity that occurs during the first cycle with the following specific exceptions:
Grade 3 or 4 nausea, vomiting, or anorexia that returns to Grade 1 prior to the start of Cycle 2
Grade 3 metabolic abnormalities (e.g., hyperglycemia)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD)</measure>
    <time_frame>21 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Hematologic DLT is defined as any of the following that occur during the first cycle that are attributed as possibly, probably, or definitely related to the study treatment:
Grade 4 neutropenia &gt; 7 day duration
Grade 4 infection with grade 3 or 4 neutropenia (life-threatening sepsis)
Grade 4 thrombocytopenia associated with life-threatening bleeding or requiring more than 1 transfusion
Treatment delay &gt; 14 days due to hematologic toxicity
Non-hematologic DLT is defined as any possibly, probably, or definitely related grade 3 or grade 4 non-hematologic toxicity that occurs during the first cycle with the following specific exceptions:
Grade 3 or 4 nausea, vomiting, or anorexia that returns to Grade 1 prior to the start of Cycle 2
Grade 3 metabolic abnormalities (e.g., hyperglycemia)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between CD30 expression on tumor cells and clinical efficacy of the combination of brentuximab vedotin and lenalidomide.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Positive CD30 expression is defined as ≥1% staining on the malignant cells</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of BV and lenalidomide in the subtypes of DLBCL</measure>
    <time_frame>21 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Activated B cell-like and germinal center B cell-like DLBCL based on the Hans criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of brentuximab vedotin and lenalidomide in relapsed/refractory DLBCL</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured by the overall response rate the proportion of patients with complete remission (CR) or (PR) partial response according to Revised Response Criteria for Malignant Lymphoma (Cheson 2007), duration of response defined as the time from start of first documented CR to the first documentation of tumor progression (including radiographic and clinical progression) or death from any cause whichever comes first, and progression free survival (PFS) defined as the time from start of study treatment to first documentation of tumor progression (including radiographic and clinical progression) or death from any cause whichever comes first.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Lymphoma, Large B-Cell, Diffuse</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Brentuximab Vedotin 1.2mglkg and Lenalidomide 20mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Brentuximab Vedotin 1.2mg/kg given IV on Day 1 every 21 days.
Lenalidomide 20mg Days 1-14,  given oral in pill form.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Brentuximab Vedotin 1.2mg/kg and Lenalidomide 25mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Brentuximab Vedotin 1.2mg/kg given IV on Day 1 every 21 days.
Lenalidomide 25mg Days 1-14,  given oral in pill form.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Brentuximab Vedotin 1.8mg/kg and Lenalidomide 25mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Brentuximab Vedotin 1.8mg/kg given IV on Day 1 every 21 days.
Lenalidomide 25mg Days 1-14,  given oral in pill form.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Brentuximab Vedotin and Lenalidomide</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Brentuximab Vedotin 1.2mglkg and Lenalidomide 20mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Brentuximab Vedotin 1.2mg/kg and Lenalidomide 25mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Brentuximab Vedotin 1.8mg/kg and Lenalidomide 25mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Adcetris®</other_name>
    <other_name>Revlimid®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Relapsed or refractory de novo or transformed DLBCL disease following at least one
             prior systemic therapy (for DLBCL).

          -  CD30 immunohistochemical staining using the anti-CD30 BerH2 antibody must be
             available on the most recent biopsy specimen.

          -  Post-ASCT or not a candidate for ASCT.  Prior allogeneic stem cell transplant is
             allowed if patient is off all immunosuppressives and has no evidence of active GVHD.

          -  Prior treatment with brentuximab vedotin is allowed provided the patient did not
             progress on BV or within 30 days of last dose of BV.  Patients must be at least 3
             months from the last dose of BV.

          -  Bidimensional measurable disease of at least 1.5 cm in the greatest transverse
             diameter as documented by CT or PET/CT.

          -  At least 18 years of age.

          -  ECOG performance status ≥ 2

          -  Bone marrow and organ function as defined below:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1,000/mcl

               -  Platelets ≥ 50,000/mcl

               -  Serum bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x institutional upper limit of normal (IULN) OR serum
                  bilirubin ≤ 3.0 x IULN for patients with Gilbert's disease or documented hepatic
                  involvement with NHL

               -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) ≤ 2.5 x IULN
                  OR ALT and AST ≤ 5.0 x IULN for patients with documented hepatic involvement
                  with NHL

               -  Creatinine clearance ≥ 60 mL/min/1.73 m2 as calculated by Cockcroft-Gault

          -  Women of childbearing potential  must follow pregnancy testing requirements as
             outlined in the Revlimid REMS® program material. This is defined as either commit to
             continued abstinence from heterosexual intercourse or begin TWO acceptable methods of
             contraception (one highly effective method and one additional effective method AT THE
             SAME TIME at least 28 days prior to the start of lenalidomide, for the duration of
             study participation, and for 28 days following the last doses of brentuximab vedotin
             and lenalidomide.  Women of childbearing potential must also agree to ongoing
             pregnancy testing.  Men must agree to use a latex condom during sexual contact with a
             woman of childbearing potential even if they have had a successful vasectomy.  All
             patients must be counseled at a minimum of every 28 days about pregnancy precautions
             and risks of fetal exposure.  Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is
             pregnant while participating in this study, she must inform her treating physician
             immediately.

          -  All study participants must be registered into the mandatory Revlimid REMS® program
             and be willing to comply with its requirements. Per standard Revlimid REMS® program
             requirements, all physicians who prescribe lenalidomide for research subjects
             enrolled into this trial, must be registered in, and must comply with, all
             requirements of the Revlimid REMS® program.

          -  Able to understand and willing to sign an IRB approved written informed consent
             document (or that of legally authorized representative, if applicable).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Primary mediastinal B-cell lymphoma

          -  A history of other primary invasive malignancy that has not been in remission for at
             least 3 years or a current diagnosis of myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS) or an immature
             leukemia such as acute myeloid leukemia (AML).

          -  Known active cerebral/meningeal lymphoma.

          -  Present or history of progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML).

          -  NYHA Class III or IV congestive heart failure.

          -  Active CTCAE version 4.03 grade 3 or higher viral, bacterial, or fungal infection.

          -  Known to be positive for hepatitis B by surface antigen expression and hepatitis B
             core antibody.

          -  Known to have active hepatitis C infection (positive by polymerase chain reaction) or
             on antiviral therapy for hepatitis C within 6 months prior to the first doses of
             brentuximab vedotin and lenalidomide.

          -  Known to be positive for HIV.

          -  Receiving chemotherapy, radiotherapy, biologics, and/or other antitumor treatment
             with immunotherapy that is not completed at least 3 weeks prior to study entry,
             unless underlying disease is progressing on therapy.

          -  Currently receiving any other investigational agents.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to any excipient contained in the drug formulation of
             brentuximab vedotin or lenalidomide.

          -  Pregnant and/or breastfeeding.  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative
             serum or urine pregnancy test with a sensitivity of at least 50 mIU/mL within 10-14
             days prior to and again within 24 hours of starting lenalidomide.

          -  Receiving immunosuppressive therapy.

          -  Refractory to prior therapy with brentuximab vedotin (evidence of progression within
             30 days of the last dose).

          -  Prior therapy with lenalidomide.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nancy Bartlett, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nancy Bartlett, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>314-362-5654</phone>
    <email>nbartlet@dom.wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nancy Bartlett, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>314-362-5654</phone>
      <email>nbartlet@dom.wustl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jeffrey Ward, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amanda Cashen, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kenneth Carson, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Todd Fehniger, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nina Wagner-Johnston, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.siteman.wustl.edu</url>
    <description>Alvin J. Siteman Cancer Center at Barnes-Jewish Hospital and Washington University School of Medicine</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 11, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large B-Cell, Diffuse</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
