<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="138021">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02099981</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Protocol 22503</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02099981</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Restoration of Retinal Vascular Responses in Diabetic Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Restoration of Retinal Vascular Responses in Diabetic Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Diabetic retinopathy is the leading cause of blindness in the developed world. The causes of
      the disease are poorly understood. One of the earliest changes that occur in the retinas of
      diabetic patients, well before overt retinopathy is observed, is a reduction in light-evoked
      increases in blood flow in retinal vessels. The loss of this vascular response may lead to
      retinal hypoxia and it has been suggested that hypoxia could be a principal cause of
      diabetic retinopathy

      The long-term goals of this project are to determine whether decreased blood flow in
      diabetic patients and the resulting retinal hypoxia contributes to the development of
      diabetic retinopathy and whether restoration of normal blood flow in diabetic patients slows
      or prevents the development of retinopathy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We have recently demonstrated that the drug aminoguanidine (AG) reverses the loss of
      light-evoked vasodilation in an animal model of type 1 diabetes. The immediate goal of the
      proposed project is to determine whether administration of AG restores light-evoked
      vasodilations in the retinas of patients with newly diagnosed diabetes. We will also
      determine whether AG improves contrast sensitivity in diabetic patients. The specific aims
      of the proposed project are to determine whether administration of AG restores light-evoked
      vasodilations and improves contrast sensitivity in patients with newly diagnosed diabetes.
      Subjects with type 1 diabetes will be recruited for participation from the University of
      Minnesota Endocrine Clinic-based registry maintained by Dr. Seaquist. Vascular dilations to
      flickering light will be measured using a Heidelberg Spectralis scanning laser
      ophthalmoscope and custom MatLab software under the direction of Dr. Newman. We will assess
      whether oral administration of AG reverses the loss of light-evoked vasodilation in the
      diabetic subjects. Contrast sensitivity will be measured at 3,6,12, and 18 cycles per degree
      using a LKC UTAS Visual Diagnostic Testing System. Measurements on 20 healthy control and 20
      diabetic subjects will be conducted in the Ophthalmology clinic of the University of
      Minnesota under the direction of co-investigator van Kuijk and the severity of retinopathy
      in diabetic patients will be graded by co-investigators van Kuijk and Koozekanani. The
      proposed experiments are an essential first step in determining whether a reduction in blood
      flow and the resulting retinal hypoxia contribute to the development of diabetic
      retinopathy. The experiments will provide preliminary results for future grant proposals to
      the National Institutes of Health.

      On the study day, control and diabetic subjects will present to the Ophthalmology research
      unit.  Prior to the imaging examination, each subject will receive dilating eye drops (1%
      Tropicamide) to prevent accommodation of the pupil. Measurement of resting vessel diameter
      and light-evoked vessel dilation will be made using a Heidelberg Spectralis scanning laser
      ophthalmoscope (SLO) in the Ophthalmology clinic. Subjects will be instructed to look at a
      fixation spot and a 50 s sequence of SLO images will be acquired at 9 frames per s. A trial
      will consist of a 15 s control period, a 20 s test period during which a flickering white
      light is presented, and a 15 s recovery period. The vascular response will be defined as the
      ratio of the maximal vessel diameter observed during the stimulation period, compared to the
      mean diameter during the control period. Five measurements of the vasodilatory response,
      repeated at 5 min intervals, will be obtained and averaged from each subject. After
      completion of the initial vasodilation measurements, both control and diabetic subjects will
      be given 150 mg aminoguanidine by mouth and measurement of resting vessel diameter and
      lightevoked vasodilation repeated two hours later. Contrast sensitivity will be assessed in
      un-dilated control and diabetic subjects. Contrast sensitivity will be determined both
      before and after AG administration using a LKC UTAS Visual Diagnostic Testing System and
      will be measured at 3, 6, 12, and 18 cycles per degree using an orientation free
      two-alternative quasi-forced choice paradigm.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case Control, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The vascular response.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The vascular response will be defined as the ratio of the maximal vessel diameter observed during the stimulation period, compared to the mean diameter during the control period</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetic Retinopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Case Study Group</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects with type 1 diabetes between the ages of 18 and 65 will be recruited for
        particiation.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with type 1 diabetes between 18 and 65 years of age will be recruited.

          -  Subjects will be included in the study if the duration of their diabetes since
             diagnosis is between 1 to 6 years.

          -  Normal report on a dilated eye exam

          -  Healthy subjects on no medications between the ages 18 and 65 years of age will be
             recruited for participation as controls. They will be selected to match the diabetic
             subjects with respect to age (within 5 years), gender, and body mass index (within 2
             kg/m2).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current diagnosis or history of hypertension, dyslipidemia, epilepsy, glaucoma or
             other ocular disease, history of renal insufficiency/failure (creatinine &gt;1.5 mg/dL),
             pregnancy or breastfeeding.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elizabeth Seaquist, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Elizabeth Seaquist, MD</last_name>
    <phone>612-626-4833</phone>
    <email>seaqu001@umn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Anjali Kumar, PA-C, MPAS</last_name>
    <phone>612-624-0470</phone>
    <email>kumar045@umn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota Medical Center Fairview</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elizabeth Seaquist, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 20, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 26, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetic</keyword>
  <keyword>Retinopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Ophthalmology</keyword>
  <keyword>Eye</keyword>
  <keyword>Eyes</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Retinopathy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Retinal Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
