<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="26665">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01799915</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>08-1408</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01799915</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Phenotype and Natural History of Primary Autonomic Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Phenotype and Natural History of Primary Autonomic Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Data and Safety Monitoring Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Primary autonomic disorders are a group of diseases that usually begin in adulthood with the
      inability to stand because of dizziness, lightheadedness and fainting. Symptoms are the
      result of a dysfunction in the autonomic nerves that regulate blood pressure and heart rate,
      and are either related to the accumulation of abnormal protein deposits and a primary
      neurodegenerative process (like Parkinson's disease, pure autonomic failure, dementia with
      Lewy bodies and multiple system atrophy), secondary to genetic abnormalities
      (dopamine-beta-hydroxylase deficiency), an autoimmune process (autoimmune ganglionopathy),
      or because of a direct injury to the nerves involved in buffering blood pressure
      fluctuations (acquired baroreflex failure). Furthermore, there are a group disorders that
      are characterized by disabling orthostatic intolerance such as the postural tachycardia
      syndrome (POTS) in which the underlying cause is unclear. The purpose of this study is to
      characterize the clinical features and biological markers of the different types of primary
      autonomic disorders and better understand how these disorders evolve over time.  The study
      will involve a series of follow-up visits to Centers participating in the Autonomic
      Disorders Consortium.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Studying primary autonomic disorders poses special researches challenges, primarily because
      these disorders are rare and affect a small number of patients. Because the medical
      literature often consists of individual case reports or small case series, good clinical
      descriptions of the features and clinical evolution of many rare autonomic diseases are
      lacking. The Autonomic Disorders Consortium was established with the objective of combining
      the medical expertise of leading autonomic sites within the United States to develop a
      clearer understanding of primary autonomic disorders, with the hope of developing new
      treatments and providing better guidance and recommendations for patient care to the medical
      community.

      The first purpose of this project is to create a database that will serve as a phenotyping
      core. We will use a comprehensive, integrated approach that will combine standardized
      clinical, physiological and biochemical studies to characterize the autonomic phenotypes of
      rare autonomic disorders, including both disorders already known and others still
      undiscovered.  Specifically, we will screen patients with orthostatic intolerance and
      conduct careful autonomic, medical and neurological evaluations to characterize the features
      of the rare autonomic disorders. This database will also allow us to identify adequate
      candidates for the therapeutic trials and natural history study of the Autonomic RDCRC.

      The second purpose of this project is to identify patients with neurogenic orthostatic
      hypotension that will be followed in a longitudinal observational study with yearly visits
      to map the natural history of the different types of primary autonomic failure and better
      characterize how these diseases evolve over time. As part of the natural history study, we
      will determine whether the neurodegenerative process always damages neurons in the brain
      (resulting in a movement disorder and/or signs of dementia) or can, in certain cases, remain
      confined to the autonomic neurons outside the brain. We will also develop biological markers
      that can distinguish between the different disorders that cause chronic autonomic failure.

      Study Hypothesis: There are a number of unclassified autonomic disorders yet to be
      discovered. There is a group of patients with a neurodegenerative disorder who have
      autonomic failure but do not develop a movement disorder or cognitive problems. These
      patients may have some genetic &quot;advantage&quot; that protects their brain from progressive
      neuronal damage.

      Comparison(s): Based on the final diagnosis established after 5 years, we will compare
      disease biomarkers in patients with various different types of autonomic disorders in order
      to determine their predictive value.

      2. Objective and Research Questions

      SPECIFIC AIM 1. THE FIRST SPECIFIC AIM IS TO CREATE A PHENOTYPING DATABASE TO DEFINE THE
      CLINICAL CHARACTERISTICS OF PRIMARY AUTONOMIC DISORDERS.  The overall goal of specific aim 1
      is to conduct detailed standardized autonomic, clinical and neurological evaluations to
      create a phenotyping database that will define the clinical characteristics of the different
      autonomic disorders that are associated with orthostatic intolerance.  We also hope to
      discover novel types of rare autonomic disorders, as we have done in the past with
      dopamine-beta-hydroxylase deficiency, norepinephrine transporter deficiency and autoimmune
      autonomic ganglionopathy. To avoid duplication of efforts, the phenotyping database will
      also function as an enrollment database that will identify patients who are eligible for
      inclusion in the natural history study of neurogenic orthostatic hypotension and therapeutic
      clinical trials that will be conducted in collaboration with other members of our Autonomic
      RDCRC.

      SPECIFIC AIM 2. THE SECOND SPECIFIC AIM IS TO DETERMINE THE NATURAL HISTORY OF NEUROGENIC
      ORTHOSTATIC HYPOTENSION AND IDENTIFY PREDICTIVE BIOMARKERS OF AUTONOMIC DISORDERS. The
      second specific aim will focus exclusively on patients with neurogenic orthostatic
      hypotension using a longitudinal observational study that will define the natural history of
      chronic autonomic failure. To determine whether autonomic function progressively worsens
      over time in patients with isolated autonomic failure, we will measure blood pressure and
      heart rate responses to a battery of standardized autonomic function tests at yearly office
      visits. To determine which patients with primary autonomic failure develop end-organ target
      damage we will monitor organ function with a series of routine clinical tests, including
      creatinine clearance. We will also define the prevalence of sleep disorders such as REM
      behavior disorder, restless leg syndrome and sleep apnea (obstructive or central) using
      questionnaires and sleep studies in selected patients. In addition, the natural history
      study will test the hypothesis that there is a group of patients with primary autonomic
      failure in whom the accumulation of alpha synuclein and the neurodegenerative process
      remains confined to the peripheral autonomic nervous system and does not develop into a
      motor or cognitive disorder. By banking DNA and looking at the genes that may promote
      neuronal sprouting or impede alpha synuclein aggregation, we will ascertain whether patients
      with the pure autonomic failure (PAF) phenotype have some genetic &quot;neuro-protective&quot;
      advantage that prevents the disorder from spreading to the striatal or other cortical
      structures. Within the natural history project we will also develop predictive biomarkers
      that can distinguish between the different types of autonomic failure. After baseline
      phenotyping, selected patients with neurogenic orthostatic hypotension will undergo a series
      of biomarker measurements. At the end of the 5-year follow-up a final diagnosis will be
      established and based on this diagnosis, we will determine which biomarkers have the best
      predictive value and are the most useful in the differential diagnosis of patients with PAF
      from those with early (i.e., &quot;pre-motor&quot;) MSA, PD or autonomic failure as a result of
      another disorder.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2011</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To create a database of primary autonomic disorders that will serve as a phenotyping core.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will create an enrollment database of patients with primary autonomic disorders. All patients will have standardized phenotyping evaluations that will combine clinical, physiological and biochemical strategies to characterize complex autonomic phenotypes, both known and still undiscovered.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To define the natural history of neurogenic orthostatic hypotension and identify predictive biomarkers of autonomic disorders</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will map the natural history of primary autonomic failure and test the hypothesis that pure autonomic failure (PAF) is a neurodegenerative synucleinopathy that remains confined to the autonomic nervous system. We will also identify biomarkers that can distinguish patients with PAF from those with early (i.e., &quot;pre-motor&quot;) MSA, PD, DLB or autonomic failure as a result of another disorder.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>6</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Neurogenic Orthostatic Hypotension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neurogenic othostatic hypotension</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients that have sever fall in blood presure due to failure in increase sympathetic vasoconstriction activity appropriately when standing.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>multiple system atrophy</arm_group_label>
    <description>is a neurodegenerative disorder charaterized by abnormal alpha-synuclein deposition in the cytoplasm of oligodendroglial cells in the CNS, and typically sparing peripheral autonomic nerves.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pure Autonomic failure</arm_group_label>
    <description>A neurodegenerative disorder characterized by loss of peripheral noradrenergic fibers, with low levels of plasma norepinephine.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Parkinson disease</arm_group_label>
    <description>A degenerative disorder of the central nervous system that leads to termors, difficulty walking, movement and coordination.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dementia with Lewy bodies</arm_group_label>
    <description>A neurodegenerative disorder similar to PAF and PD with the accumulation of Alpha-synuclein in the CNS however DLB patients develop dementia.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>autoimmune autonomic ganglionopathy</arm_group_label>
    <description>is a rare disorder characterized by the presence of autonomic failure in association with specific antibodies directed against a specific receptor of the autonomic ganglia</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood Sample for DNA processing
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Primary autonomic disorders are a group of diseases that usually begin in adulthood with
        the inability to stand because of dizziness, lightheadedness and fainting. Symptoms are
        the result of a dysfunction in the autonomic nerves that regulate blood pressure and heart
        rate, and are either related to the accumulation of abnormal protein deposits and a
        primary neurodegenerative process (like Parkinson's disease, pure autonomic failure,
        dementia with Lewy bodies and multiple system atrophy), secondary to genetic abnormalities
        (dopamine-beta-hydroxylase deficiency), an autoimmune process (autoimmune ganglionopathy),
        or because of a direct injury to the nerves involved in buffering blood pressure
        fluctuations (acquired baroreflex failure).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Both male and female patients will be included

          2. Aged 18 or over

          3. Referred to any of the participating consortium sites with orthostatic intolerance,
             defined as symptoms of dizziness or lightheadedness in the standing position that
             disappear when supine.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Diabetes according to the American Diabetes Association criteria

          2. Congestive heart failure

          3. Lupus or other collagen vascular disease

          4. Systemic illness thought to be responsible for the orthostatic intolerance

          5. Drug-induced orthostatic hypotension (i.e., the use of alpha-blockers, diuretics,
             tricyclic antidepressants or others thought by the investigator to play an important
             role in the patient's orthostatic hypotension)

          6. Isolated vasovagal syncope

          7. Inability to comply with the protocol, e.g. uncooperative attitude, inability to
             return for follow-up visits, and unlikelihood of completing the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Horacio C Kaufmann, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NYU MEDICAL CENTER</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NYU Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jose Martinez, MA</last_name>
      <phone>212-263-7225</phone>
      <email>jose.martinez@nyumc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Horacio Kaufmann, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 22, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 25, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Autonomic Nervous System Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Primary Dysautonomias</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypotension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypotension, Orthostatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
