<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="164848">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01952197</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EP-PCEH-2013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01952197</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Passive Leg Raise (PLR) During CPR Increase the Effect of Chest Compressions</brief_title>
  <acronym>EP-PCEH</acronym>
  <official_title>Study and Comparison of the Effectiveness by Passive Leg Raise During Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation Outhospital.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Rovira i Virgili</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Public Health Service of Cataluña</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital Universitari Joan XXIII de Tarragona.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital Universitari Sant Joan de Reus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Rovira i Virgili</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Spain: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      1. Hypothesis Early leg  raise (20 - 45 grader) during CPR, increase the effect of  chest
      compression through the increase in the coronary perfusion. Consequently survival will
      increase in out-of hospital cardiac arrest.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. Background information Survival after out-of hospital Cardiac arrest (OHCA) is still
           remarkable low. According to the Swedish OHCA registry only 10% of all OHCA, where CPR
           was started, survive to one month.

           Different factors predicting outcome has been described in previous studies such as:
           The present of ventricular fibrillation (VF), bystander CPR before arrival of the
           rescue team, ambulance delay, if the cardiac arrest was witnessed or not, increased age
           and female sex.

           Regarding CPR performed by laypeople or professionals, the quality e.g. the coronary
           perfusion pressure (the pressure performing blood flow through the heart muscle) seems
           to be direct related to outcome.

           Of this reason the interest has focused on methods to optimize the coronary perfusion
           pressure (CPP), after cardiac arrest and during CPR.

           During the last decade it has been speculated up on if elevated legs during CPR
           increase the venous return (and thereby the CPP and cardiac output). This treatment was
           recommended in CPR guidelines before 1992 but thereafter deleted, probably because of
           lack in evidence.

        2. Clinical significance of preliminary A previous made pilot study from Goteborg (Bilaga
           1), approved by the ethical committee (S-696 02), indicate that elevated legs (20
           degrees) during cardiac arrest resulted in increased End tidal CO2 (EtCO2). EtCO2
           measured during cardiac arrest is a rough measure of blood flow in artery pulmonalis
           and consequently a rough measure of the blood circulation during CPR. In comparison
           with patients having CPR in plain position the EtCO2 value increased among patients
           with elevated legs nor having manual or mechanical chest compression. Survival to one
           month among the studied group with elevated legs was 7 % in comparison with 1 % among
           patients treated in plain position. The low survival rates in this study were explained
           by the experimental design. The intervention was made 20 minutes after cardiac arrest
           and the majority of survivors were at that time already resuscitated (and not included
           in the analysis).

           Further, Dragoumanos et. al have previous published a study (Bilaga 1) about passive
           leg raise (PLR) in a porcine model. They found that the CPP during CPR increased. They
           also found improved neurologic status after ROSC among pigs having PLR. This study was
           presented on the CPR congress at Malta in October 2011.

        3. Design In Sweden PLR is studied in a multi-center registry study. The intervention
           (PLR) is included in the CPR guidelines among a cluster of ambulance district (Halland,
           Dalarna, Värmland och VG region).  Primary and secondary endpoints will be compared
           with retrospective data and prospective with other districts not using PLR in the CPR
           guidelines. In Sweden the intervention started 1/4 2012.

           In Spain (Catalonia) PLR is studied by an envelope randomized design. The study started
           in Tarragona city ambulance 8/6 2013 and will continue in all Tarragona district 1/1
           2014.

        4. Method The intervention is made on all adult patients receiving CPR by the ambulance
           crew. The leg raise is performed during the first minutes of CPR (limit 5 min) and will
           continue as long as the patients receive chest compression. In Spain the patient is
           immediate randomized by envelope. If the patient is randomized to PLR, the ambulance
           crews use a special folding stool that allows the legs to be raised about 20 degrees.

           In Sweden the studied data is register via the web based national OHCA registry.
           Separately additional information (PLR: Yes/No) is attached to the website only in the
           districts performing PLR. Other information (survival) is obtained from hospital
           records. In Spain data is obtained by ambulance and hospital records. In Span we also
           perform a retrospective study to mapping the OHCA population and survival rates in
           Tarragona district according to Utstein variables.

           Inclusion criteria: Cardiac arrest where the rescue team perform chest compression.

           Exclusion criteria: persons under 18 years Informed consent Patients included in the
           study are by definition unconscious and of this reason not able to give informed
           consent. Relatives or next of kin are in this situation mentally affected and have
           difficulty in respond. To ask them about informed consent seems very unethical and will
           probably be answered with: &quot;Do the thing you think is the best&quot;. The situation is also
           hard for the rescue team with limited time and upset relatives. To identify who is a
           relative or not and ask for informed consent is very time consuming in the acute
           situation. The method to perform the intervention within guidelines in some district is
           advocated and approved by the ethical committee in Goteborg. In Spain (Catalonia) the
           study is approved by the ethical committee to be envelope randomized without informed
           consent.

        5. Endpoints

      Primary endpoint:

      1.Survival to one month.

      Secondary endpoint:

        1. Survival to hospital admission

        2. Survival to one month with acceptable cerebral function (CPC-score 1, 2)

        3. Survival to one year with acceptable cerebral function (CPC-score 1, 2). Evaluation of
           other result Sub analysis:  PLR in relation to initial rhythm, age, sex and ambulance
           delay. Statistical analysis The hypothesis is that PLR during CPR increase survival to
           one month from 7% to 10%. To demonstrate this with 80% power and two tailed significant
           on 5%, 2 x 1490 patients is needed.

      To power this analyze the study needs last for three years. In Sweden we compare different
      districts both historical and with other districts not performing PLR. The result will be
      adjusted to differences in baseline. In Spain a retrospective analysis (1 Aug 2010 - 8 June
      2013) will be performed to make a more proper power analysis and map the Spanish OHCA
      population.

      6. Study time April 1, 2012 -Mars 31 2015 (Sweden) Jun 8, 2013 - Jun 2016 (Catalonia)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Increase the Effect of Chest Compressions in cpr</measure>
    <time_frame>up to  5 min</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The leg raise is performed during the first minutes of CPR (limit 5 min) and will continue as long as the patients receive chest compression. In Spain the patient is immediate randomized by envelope. If the patient is randomized to PLR, the ambulance crews use a special folding stool that allows the legs to be raised about 20 degrees.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival to hospital admission after ROSC</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Know the survival after arrived to the hospital after ROSC</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival to one month after ROSC</measure>
    <time_frame>one month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Know the survival to one month</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival to one year</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Know survivals to one year and what is the cerebral function (CPC-score 1, 2).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2980</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Passive Leg Raise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention is made on all adult patients receiving CPR by the ambulance crew. The leg raise is performed during the first minutes of CPR (limit 5 min) and will continue as long as the patients receive chest compression. In Spain the patient is immediate randomized by envelope. If the patient is randomized to PLR, the ambulance crews use a special folding stool that allows the legs to be raised about 20 degrees.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Passive Leg Raise</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention is made on all adult patients receiving CPR by the ambulance crew. The leg raise is performed during the first minutes of CPR (limit 5 min) and will continue as long as the patients receive chest compression. In Spain the patient is immediate randomized by envelope. If the patient is randomized to PLR, the ambulance crews use a special folding stool that allows the legs to be raised about 20 degrees.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Passive Leg Raise</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PLR</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Cardiac arrest where the rescue team perform chest compression.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Persons under 18 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maria Jiménez, phD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universitat Rovira i Virgili. Tarragona. Spain</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Maria Jimenez, phD</last_name>
    <phone>+34609960648</phone>
    <email>maria.jimenez@urv.cat</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Christer Axelsson, phD</last_name>
    <phone>+46705400304</phone>
    <email>christer.axelsson@hb.se</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Departament of Nursing. Universitat Rovira i Virgili.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tarragona</city>
        <zip>43007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maria Jimenez, phD</last_name>
      <phone>+34977299418</phone>
      <email>maria.jimenez@urv.cat</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christer Axelsson, phD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 26, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 13, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Rovira i Virgili</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Maria F. Jimenez Herrera</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr. Jiménez Herrera</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Passive Leg Raise</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiac arrest</keyword>
  <keyword>Survival after CPR</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
