<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="105751">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01715662</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H11-01246</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01715662</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pilot RCT to Investigate the Use of a Home-based Nintendo Wii Program for Rehabilitation in Older Adults With Lower Limb Amputation</brief_title>
  <official_title>WiiHOME-AMPS: A Pilot Randomized Controlled Trial to Investigate the Use of a Home-based Nintendo Wii Program for Rehabilitation in Older Adults With a Unilateral Transtibial or Transfemoral Amputation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of British Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a pilot randomized controlled trial to assess the feasibility of a home-based
      Nintendo Wii program in rehabilitation of individuals with a lower limb amputation. Twenty
      individuals with a unilateral below-knee or above-knee amputation will be randomly allocated
      to experimental or control arm. The experimental arm will receive weight-shifting and
      balance games and exercises using the Wii balance board. The control arm will receive
      cognitive computer games and exercises using Lumosity Brain Training program. Both groups
      will receive the intervention for 40-minute sessions, 3x/week for 4 weeks. The interventions
      will be administered in combination of onsite group training and individualized home-based
      training. Outcome measurements will be done by a blinded evaluator at baseline, end of
      treatment, and 3 weeks after the end of treatment.

      Hypothesis: Our guiding primary hypothesis is that the Wii will result in improved
      functional walking capacity of older adults with a mature (≥1 year post) unilateral
      transtibial or transfemoral amputation. Secondary hypotheses are that the Wii will lead to
      improvement in lower extremity strength and balance, inter-limb gait symmetry, balance
      confidence, participation in daily and social activities, locomotor capabilities, and
      increase in physical activities.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Purpose: To assess the feasibility of a randomized controlled trial (RCT) to investigate the
      utility of a home -based Nintendo Wii Fit Plus (Wii) program in rehabilitation of
      individuals with a unilateral transtibial or transfemoral amputation. This study will
      provide seed data and information (e.g. sample size calculation) to leverage funds for a
      future RCT.

      Hypothesis: Our guiding primary hypothesis is that the Wii will result in improved
      functional walking capacity of older adults with a mature (≥1 year post) unilateral
      transtibial or transfemoral amputation. Secondary hypotheses are that the Wii will lead to
      improvement in lower extremity strength and balance, inter-limb gait symmetry, balance
      confidence, participation in daily and social activities, locomotor capabilities, and
      increase in physical activities.

      Justification: It is estimated that approximately 1 million individuals were living with a
      lower extremity amputation in the United States in the year 2005. This number is projected
      to more than double by the year 2050. This imposes a serious public health issue and
      increases the demand for more rehabilitation resources to become available to this
      population.

      Following a unilateral lower limb amputation the position of the centre of mass over the
      base of support is altered, resulting in weight distribution asymmetry over the amputated
      and contralateral legs. Miller et al. have reported that about 52.4% of persons with a lower
      extremity amputation have fallen at least once in the past year due to poor balance.
      Therefore, a well-planned rehabilitation program is crucial for improving and retaining the
      balance and walking patterns of lower limb amputees. An optimal rehabilitation program has
      to be challenging, repetitive, task-specific, intensive, and motivating. Given the pressure
      to discharge patients earlier in order to reduce rehabilitation costs, standard
      rehabilitation programs often fail to provide all these important elements. Virtual reality
      (VR) rehabilitation has been introduced as a solution to this problem. VR is a
      computer-human interface that creates an interactive, immersive virtual environment where
      the user engages in real-time. VR technologies have the potential to provide an optimal
      rehabilitation program in terms of repetition, task-specificity, motivation, and challenge.

      Recently there has been a growing interest in integrating VR into rehabilitation. Due to the
      cost and lack of commercial availability of most of these VR systems, the notion of using
      off-the-shelf commercial VR technologies, such as gaming systems has been introduced. The
      Nintendo Wii Fit Plus (Wii) is a low-cost VR gaming system which is widely available to the
      general population. The Wii balance board has force sensors that measure the user's center
      of balance and weight distribution. Users stand on the balance board and interact with the
      games through weight shifting. Due to the weight-shifting, balance and aerobic training
      nature of the Wii games, the Wii may serve as a suitable therapeutic agent for
      rehabilitation in individuals with lower extremity amputation.

      Although the number of studies using the Wii as a therapeutic agent is growing, there is
      still a dearth of research in the field of amputation rehabilitation. Promising results are
      reported regarding safety, feasibility, and efficacy of the Wii in rehabilitation of
      individuals who had stroke, acquired brain injury (ABI), cerebral palsy, developmental
      disabilities, and cystic fibrosis.

      Previously we conducted 6 case studies in order to develop a Wii oriented intervention
      protocol for individuals with lower extremity amputation. We believe that our intervention
      will provide an excellent augmentative program to standard amputee rehabilitation; however
      the only way to definitively determine the efficacy is to conduct a robust RCT. These study
      designs are, however, expensive and require feasibility data in order to attract appropriate
      funding. We propose to conduct a pilot RCT in order to assess the feasibility of our
      intervention with the intention of submitting to the Canadian Institutes of Health Research
      for a larger definitive RCT.

      Objectives: The objectives of this study are to: 1) pilot the methodologies and
      randomization procedures, 2) obtain preliminary effect size data to inform power analysis
      and sample size calculation for a future RCT, 3) estimate the recruitment, refusal,
      compliance, and attrition rates, and 4) determine safety and adverse event information
      related to the intervention.

      Research Method: This pilot study is a parallel, single-blind RCT. Twenty individuals with a
      unilateral transtibial or transfemoral will be randomly assigned to either the Wii, or the
      Lumosity arm (10 in each arm) using computer-generated block randomization. The
      randomization will be done by a statistician who will not be involved in any part the study.

      Subjects (n=10) in the experimental arm will be trained using the Wii for 40-minute
      sessions, 3 times a week for a period of 4 weeks. Subjects will stand on the Wii balance
      board and interact with the Wii games through weight shifting. The intervention protocol
      includes: 1) Yoga (static single and double leg exercises), 2) Balance games (lateral and
      poster/anterior weight shifting exercises in standing), 3) Aerobics (running on spot and
      step class), and 4) Strength training (dynamic single and double leg exercises). Each
      component will be practiced for 10 minutes in each session. For onsite training sessions, a
      trained research assistant will administer the intervention and will provide external cueing
      and correction of the pose if the participants use unsafe technique.

      Subjects (n=10) in the control arm will play cognitive computer games using Lumosity Brain
      Training program for the same frequency and duration as the experimental arm. For onsite
      training sessions a separate research assistant will administer the intervention and will
      provide supervision. Lumosity is an online program which has games and exercises to improve
      cognitive function (www.lumosity.com).

      The interventions will be administered in combination of onsite group training and
      home-based individualized training.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in 6-Minute Walk Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, end of treatment, 3 weeks post treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The 6-Minute Walk Test will be employed to measure the functional walking capacity of subjects. Subjects will be instructed to walk as far as they can over an 80-meter course in 6 minutes. The distance covered in 6 minutes will be recorded.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Short Physical Performance Battery (SPPB)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, end of treatment, 3 weeks post treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Short Physical Performance Battery (SPPB) will be used to measure subjects' lower extremity function by scoring their ability to perform four tasks: double-leg standing balance (feet together, semi-tandem, tandem), single-leg standing balance, gait speed over 4 meters, and lower extremity strength (5x chair stands). Each task is scored from 0 (poor) to 4 (excellent). A total score will be generated by adding up the scores for individual tasks. We will look at overall and balance component scores.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Inter-limb gait symmetry ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, end of treatment, 3 weeks post treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The inter-limb gait symmetry ratio will be measured by GAITRite walkway system. The GAITRite walkway system (CIR Systems Inc., Havertown, PA) is an electronic walkway carpet that quantifies the spatial and temporal parameters of footstep patterns of the subjects. As the subject ambulates along the walkway, the sensors embedded along the length of the carpet capture the gait pattern data. The carpet is connected to a computer where the gait parameters are calculated using software algorithms. The inter-limb gait symmetry ratio will be computed according to the following formula: [(non-prosthetic leg stance time/swing time) / (prosthetic leg stance time/swing time)]. A ratio of 1 represents a perfect inter-limb symmetry. The higher the score is above 1, the higher the gait asymmetry is toward the non-prosthetic leg (i.e. more load on non-prosthetic leg).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Walking While Talking Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, end of treatment, 3 weeks post treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Walking While Talking Test is a test of divided attention while locomotion. Subjects will be timed walking a 40 feet course twice while: 1) reciting the letters of the alphabet (a, b, c, ...) aloud (WWT-simple), and 2) reciting the alternate letters of the alphabet (a, c, e, …) aloud (WWT-complex). Subjects will be asked to pay attention to both walking and talking. The WWT outcomes will include total time, total numbers of alternate letters correctly recited and the total errors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Activities-specific Balance Confidence scale (ABC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, end of treatment, 3 weeks post treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The 16-item Activities-specific Balance Confidence scale (ABC) will be used to assess self-efficacy associated with confidence to perform specific tasks without losing balance. Subjects report their confidence level on a scale of 0-100%. The individual item scores are summed and divided by 16 to derive a mean overall score with higher scores indicating higher confidence.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Frenchay Activities Index (FAI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, end of treatment, 3 weeks post treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Frenchay Activities Index (FAI) captures information about daily and social activities by asking about the frequency with which individuals perform these activities. This 15-item questionnaire is partitioned into two parts: the first 10 items ask individuals to estimate the frequency of their participation in daily chores and activities such as preparing meals or washing clothes during the past three months. The next 5 items ask individuals to estimate their participation in other activities such as travelling, or gardening during the past six months. Response options range from 0 (never) to 3 (at least once a week). A summary score is derived by adding up the response of all items. The total score ranges from 0 (no participation) to 45 (frequent participation).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Locomotor Capabilities Index in Amputees (LCI-5)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, end of treatment, 3 weeks post treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Locomotor Capabilities Index in Amputees (LCI-5) is a subjective scale designed for people with lower limb amputation. It is composed of 14 items that ask questions about subject's ability to perform different locomotor activities with their prosthesis on. Items are scored on a 5-level ordinal scale from 0 (not able) to 4 (able to accomplish the activity alone without ambulation aids). The total score ranges from 0 to 56, with higher scores indicating greater locomotor capabilities with the prosthesis and less dependence on assistance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical activity level</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, end of treatment, 3 weeks post treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>An accelerometer will be attached to the prosthetic ankle of the subjects throughout the study. The accelerometer will gather information on subject's physical activities using total energy expenditure (kcal/d), and total step counts.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Lower Limb Amputation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nintendo Wii</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects (n=10) in the experimental arm will be trained using the Wii for 40-minute sessions, 3 times a week for a period of 4 weeks. Subjects will stand on the Wii balance board and interact with the Wii games through weight shifting. The intervention protocol includes: 1) Yoga (static single and double leg exercises), 2) Balance games (lateral and poster/anterior weight shifting exercises in standing), 3) Aerobics (running on spot and step class), and 4) Strength training (dynamic single and double leg exercises). Each component will be practiced for 10 minutes in each session. For onsite training sessions, a trained research assistant will administer the intervention and will provide external cueing and correction of the pose if the participants use unsafe technique.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive games</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects (n=10) in the control arm will play cognitive computer games using Lumosity Brain Training program for the same frequency and duration as the experimental arm. For onsite training sessions a separate research assistant will administer the intervention and will provide supervision. Lumosity is an online program which has games and exercises to improve cognitive function (www.lumosity.com).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nintendo Wii</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will receive the intervention for 40-minute sessions, 3x/week for 4 weeks. The interventions will be administered in combination of onsite group training and individualized home-based training.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nintendo Wii</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  at least 1 year post a unilateral transtibial or transfemoral amputation

          -  60 years of age or older

          -  have been using a prosthesis for at least 6 months prior to participation in the
             study

          -  have poor balance confidence as indicated by a score of &lt; 80% on the
             Activities-specific Balance      Confidence scale at screening

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  are not able to provide an informed consent form

          -  have significant medical conditions that contraindicate participation in exercise
             program

          -  have prosthetic socket fit issues, as indicated by scores ≤6 on the Prosthetic Socket
             Fit Comfort Scale

          -  are currently participating in another formal exercise or training program.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William C. Miller, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of British Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bita Imam, Bsc</last_name>
    <phone>604-714-4108</phone>
    <email>bita.imam@vch.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GF Strong</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V5Z 2G9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bita Imam, MA</last_name>
      <phone>604-714-4108</phone>
      <email>bita.imam@vch.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>William C. Miller, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>604-714-4107</phone>
      <email>bcmiller@telus.net</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>William C. Miller, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bita Imam, MA</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Paul's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V6Z 1Y6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bita Imam, MA</last_name>
      <phone>604-714-4108</phone>
      <email>bita.imam@vch.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>William C. Miller, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>604-714-4107</phone>
      <email>bcmiller@telus.net</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>William C. Miller, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bita Imam, MA</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Holy Family Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V5P 3L6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bita Imam, MA</last_name>
      <phone>604-714-4108</phone>
      <email>bita.imam@vch.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>William C. Miller, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>604-714-4107</phone>
      <email>bcmiller@telus.net</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>William C. Miller, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bita Imam, MA</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 15, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>lower limb amputation</keyword>
  <keyword>unilateral transtibial amputation</keyword>
  <keyword>unilateral transfemoral amputation</keyword>
  <keyword>older adults</keyword>
  <keyword>cognitive computer games</keyword>
  <keyword>home-based training</keyword>
  <keyword>Nintendo Wii</keyword>
  <keyword>virtual reality</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
