<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="45419">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02146326</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IH-1304-6597</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02146326</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Impact of Burnout on Patient-Centered Care: A Comparative Effectiveness Trial in Mental Health</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Impact of Burnout on Patient-Centered Care: A Comparative Effectiveness Trial in Mental Health</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Indiana University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Four County Counseling Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Places for People</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Indiana University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Indiana University IRB</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Healthcare providers play an important role in helping patients be actively involved in
      treatment and recover from mental illness. But mental health clinicians, like other
      healthcare providers, are at risk for experiencing burnout—feeling emotionally drained from
      their work, having cynical thoughts toward patients and others, and feeling little
      accomplishment in their work. Burnout can lead to problems for the clinician including poor
      overall health, depression, and lower job satisfaction. Burnout also can impact how
      clinicians perform on the job; for example, people with high levels of burnout take more
      time off, show lower commitment to their job, and are more likely to quit or be fired. There
      is some evidence that burnout can affect the quality of care for patients, but very little
      rigorous research has tested this assumption. The purpose of our study is threefold. First,
      we will investigate how patients perceive burnout in clinicians and whether (and/or how)
      burnout impacts the care they receive. Next, we will test an intervention to reduce
      clinician burnout called Burnout Reduction: Enhanced Awareness, Tools, Handouts, and
      Education (BREATHE). BREATHE brings together tools that mental health clinicians are already
      familiar with, including relaxation and mindfulness exercises, setting boundaries, using
      social supports, and changing negative thought patterns and replacing them with more helpful
      ways of thinking. We have found this intervention effective in reducing burnout in other
      organizations, but have yet to study whether it also can improve patient outcomes.
      Clinicians (approximately 200) who participate will receive either the BREATHE intervention
      or training in motivational interviewing, which could also improve patient involvement in
      treatment and patient outcomes, but is unlikely to significantly reduce clinician burnout.
      We will also recruit 600 adult patients served by participating clinicians. We will survey
      clinicians and interview patients over a 12-month period after the intervention to determine
      how the intervention impacts clinician burnout and patient perceptions of care (relationship
      with the clinician, degree of autonomy in decision making), patient involvement in care, and
      outcomes (confidence in managing mental health, symptoms, functioning, and hope). Finally,
      this study will use a statistical procedure called Structural Equation Modeling to test a
      theoretical model of the relationship between burnout and patient outcomes. Findings from
      this study will show whether reducing clinician burnout can improve patient outcomes and the
      quality of care that patients receive. Our intervention will have the potential to be easily
      implemented in a variety of settings where burnout is a problem. Knowing how clinician
      burnout impacts patient outcomes, and whether improving burnout can improve patient care,
      can help improve the healthcare system.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maslach Burnout Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured 4 times over 1 year.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Staff and Client rated Quality of Care</measure>
    <time_frame>Staff measured 4 times over 1 year. Clients measured 3 times over 1 year.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Burnout</condition>
  <condition>Quality of Care</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Motivational Interviewing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BREATHE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Burnout reduction training for mental health staff.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Training Staff in Motivational Interviewing or BREATHE</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Motivational Interviewing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>BREATHE</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  A staff member with client contact at either Four County Counseling or Places for
             People.

          -  Randomly chosen client from the participating staff lists. Must be 18 years old or
             older.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Clients younger than 18 years old.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michelle Salyers, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>844-496-0002</phone>
    <email>mpsalyer@iupui.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Four County Counseling</name>
      <address>
        <city>Logansport</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46947</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Places for People</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 21, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
