<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="82323">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01933048</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IDCRP-070</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01933048</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Self-Administered Nasal Influenza Feasibility Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>SNIF</acronym>
  <official_title>Self-Administered Nasal Influenza Vaccine: Immunogenicity and Feasibility of Group Administration</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this prospective, open-label clinical trial is to evaluate the immunogenicity
      of self-administered (SA) live, attenuated influenza vaccine (LAIV) in comparison with
      healthcare worker administered (HCWA) LAIV and to evaluate the feasibility of group
      self-administration of LAIV.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-vaccination geometric mean titer ratios between HCWA and SA subjects</measure>
    <time_frame>28+/- 7 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference and Proportion in Seroresponse and Seroconversion</measure>
    <time_frame>28+/- 7 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>proportion with seroresponse, defined as the percentage of subjects achieving a post-vaccination hemagluttinin antibody inhibition (HAI) titer ≥ 1:40
proportion with seroconversion, defined as the percentage of subjects with either a pre-vaccination HAI titer &lt; 1:10 and a post vaccination HAI titer ≥ 1:40 or a pre-vaccination HAI titer ≥ 1:10 and a minimum four-fold rise in post-vaccination HAI titer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility Measures</measure>
    <time_frame>28 +/- 7 days post vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>reactogenicity outcomes captured in the first 7 days post-vaccination as well as responses to study questionnaires that assess preference for HCWA-LAIV versus SA-LAIV, the proportion of SA-LAIV vaccinees reporting difficulties solicited through the questionnaire, and evaluating the time required for vaccine administration using metrics such as aggregate or mean time of vaccine administration for HCWA and SA subjects</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1100</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthcare Worker Administration</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>FluMist administered by a Healthcare Worker</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Self-Administration</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>FluMist self-administered by subject</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FluMist</intervention_name>
    <description>FluMist Intranasal Vaccine</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthcare Worker Administration</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Self-Administration</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy males or healthy, non-pregnant females

          -  18-49 years of age

          -  Department of Defense beneficiary including active duty members

          -  Able to speak and understand English, and provide written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known hypersensitivity to eggs, egg-proteins, gentamicin, gelatin, or arginine or
             life-threatening reactions to previous influenza vaccination

          -  Prior receipt of the 2012-2013 seasonal influenza vaccine for 2012-2013 season or
             prior receipt of the 2013-2014 seasonal influenza vaccine for 2013-2014 season

          -  Known clinical diagnosis of reactive airway disease, wheezing, or asthma (excluding
             exercise-induced asthma)

          -  Reported febrile upper respiratory illness (oral or tympanic temperature greater than
             100°F or a subjective fever) at the time of or within the 24 hours prior to
             immunization

          -  Known to be pregnant, possibly pregnant or breast-feeding

          -  Known diagnosis of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection, chronic active
             hepatitis B infection, or chronic hepatitis C infection

          -  History of Guillain-Barre Syndrome

          -  Household member known to be immunocompromised (either a known disease or disorder
             such as HIV, or other acquired or congenital immunodeficiency disorder, or taking
             systemic steroids (any dose) or high daily dose inhaled steroids, tumor necrosis
             factor-alpha inhibitors, or monoclonal antibodies used to treat autoimmune disease)

          -  Receipt of medications with activity against influenza A and/or B (ex: Tamiflu®,
             Relenza®, amantadine, or rimantadine) within 48 hours prior to vaccine administration

          -  Use of any oral or intravenous systemic steroids (any dose) or any daily dose inhaled
             steroids

          -  At the time of enrollment, any person who is trained to administer intranasal
             vaccines or who has been involved in any recurring role associated with the
             administration of intranasal vaccines to others in the clinic or military treatment
             facility (MTF)

          -  Prior participation in this research study

          -  Any acute or chronic medical condition that, in the opinion of the investigator,
             would render vaccination unsafe, interfere with the evaluation of responses, or
             render the subject unable to meet the requirements of the protocol. These conditions
             may include, but are not limited to: history of significant renal impairment
             (dialysis and treatment for kidney disease, including diabetic and hypertensive
             kidney disease); poorly controlled diabetes mellitus or patients with diabetes
             mellitus on insulin (subjects with well-controlled diabetes mellitus on oral agents
             may enroll  as long there has been no dosage increase within the past 6 months);
             cardiac insufficiency, if heart failure is present; an arteriosclerotic event during
             the 6 months prior to enrollment (e.g., history of myocardial infarction, stroke,
             recanalization of femoral arteries, or transient ischemic attack).

          -  If the individual received a live virus vaccine (e.g., Varicella,
             Measles-Mumps-Rubella, Yellow Fever, Smallpox) in the past 4 weeks, they should wait
             28 days before receiving LAIV. There is no reason to defer vaccination if the
             individual was vaccinated with an inactivated vaccine or if they have recently
             received blood or other antibody-containing blood products.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>49 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Timothy Burgess, MD, MPH, Capt, MC, USN</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Naval Medical Center San Diego</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92134</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>San Antonio Military Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Sam Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78234</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 8, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Timothy Burgess</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Captain, Medical Corps, US Navy</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>influenza</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
