<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="78920">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01890746</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>117146</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01890746</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Safety and Efficacy Study of Eltrombopag in Subjects With AML</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Blinded, Placebo-Controlled, Dose Finding Study to Assess the Safety and Efficacy of the Oral Thrombopoietin Receptor Agonist, Eltrombopag, Administered to Subjects With Acute Myelogenous Leukaemia (AML) Receiving Induction Chemotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Russia: Roszdrav Nadzor</authority>
    <authority>Russian Federation: Ministry of Health and social development of Russian Federation, Federal</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this randomized, blinded, placebo-controlled study is to provide clinical
      safety and exploratory efficacy data on the use of Eltrombopag in adult subjects with Acute
      Myeloid Leukemia (AML) receiving standard induction chemotherapy with daunorubicin plus
      cytarabine. These safety data are considered necessary to further development of Eltrombopag
      in both adult and paediatric patients suffering from malignant diseases with secondary
      thrombocytopenia. A minimum of 120 evaluable subjects with newly diagnosed with AML will be
      stratified by antecedent malignant hematologic disorder and age.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with adverse events (AE) as a measure of safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>AEs will be graded by the investigator according to the National Cancer Institute-Common terminology criteria for adverse events version 4 (NCI-CTCAE (version 4.0). AEs will be collected from the time the first dose of study treatment is administered until 30 days following discontinuation of investigational product (IP) regardless of initiation of a new cancer therapy or transfer to hospice.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in the left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF).</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 42 of most recent chemotherapy cycle (up to 8 weeks).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>LVEF will be assessed by either an echocardiogram (ECHO) or Multiple Gated Acquisition scan (MUGA). The evaluation will be performed at baseline, during the screening evaluation period, and within 14 days of final disease response assessment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical laboratory assessment as measure of safety and tolerability.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 42 of most recent chemotherapy cycle (up to 8 weeks).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Clinical laboratory assessment includes hematology, clinical chemistry, and urinalysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of platelet transfusions</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 42 of most recent chemotherapy cycle (up to 8 weeks).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of platelet transfusion will be collected during the study until the response bone marrow biopsy or until the time of subject withdrawal from the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to platelet counts &gt;=20 (Giga units per liter) Gi/L and &gt;=100 Gi/L</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 42 of most recent chemotherapy cycle (up to 8 weeks).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Platelet recovery is defined as platelet counts &gt;=20 Gi/L for 3 consecutive days, unaided by transfusions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects who achieve platelet count recovery by Day 21</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 21</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Summary of platelet counts</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 42 of most recent chemotherapy cycle (up to 8 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of platelet transfusion independence</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 42 of most recent chemotherapy cycle (up to 8 weeks).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Duration of platelet transfusion independence is defined as a time period where subjects do not receive any platelet transfusions during the treatment period and follow-up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to absolute neutrophil count (ANC) engraftment defined as ANC recovery 0.5 Gi/L sustained for 3 days.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 42 of most recent chemotherapy cycle (up to 8 weeks).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of bleeding events</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 42 of most recent chemotherapy cycle (up to 8 weeks).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessment of bleeding using World Health Organization (WHO) scale will be performed throughout the study from screening until the response bone marrow biopsy assessment. Number of bleeding events will be recorded to assess the incidence and severity of haemorrhagic events.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall survival is defined as the time from randomization until death due to any cause. OS will be assessed to evaluate the effect on Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML) disease control.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Off-treatment Medical resource utilization (MRU).</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 42 of most recent chemotherapy cycle (up 8 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MRU information pertaining to unscheduled (not scheduled per protocol) hospitalizations (i.e., total hospital days), unscheduled office visits, unscheduled laboratory tests, and unscheduled procedures will be recorded during therapy and follow-up periods</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite of pharmacokinetic (PK) parameters of daunorubicin and daunorubicinol on Cycle 1 Day 3.</measure>
    <time_frame>PK samples will be collected at pre-dose, 1 minute, 0.5, 1, 3, 7, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 144 hours post-Day 3 dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PK parameters include: half-life and dose-normalized plasma area under the concentration-time curve from time zero extrapolated to infinite time (AUC[0-infinity]), area under the concentration-time curve from time zero to time of last quantifiable concentration (AUC[0-t]), area under the concentration-time curve from time 24 hours to time of last quantifiable concentration (AUC[24-t]), and maximum observed concentration (Cmax).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite of PK parameters of daunorubicin and daunorubicinol on Cycle 2 Day 1</measure>
    <time_frame>PK samples will be collected at pre-dose, 1 minute, 0.5, 1, 3, 7, and 24 hours post-Day 1 dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PK parameters include: dose-normalized plasma rea under the concentration-time curve from time zero to time 24 hours (AUC [0-24]) and Cmax.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in absolute neutrophil counts</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 42 of most recent chemotherapy cycle (up to 8 weeks).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in hemoglobin</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 42 of most recent chemotherapy cycle (up to 8 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Leukaemia, Acute</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Eltrombopag arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subject will receive induction chemotherapy consisting of daunorubicin bolus intravenous (IV) infusion on Days 1-3 + cytarabine continuous IV infusion on Days 1-7 followed by Eltrombopag once daily orally starting on Day 4 of initial induction chemotherapy. If platelet count is not greater than 100 Gi/L after 7 days the dose will be increased until a platelet count of at least 200 Gi/L is achieved/until remission is assessed/ maximum of 42 days from the start of the chemotherapy induction. Subjects who are not aplastic after first cycle of induction chemotherapy will receive second induction chemotherapy with a modified daunorubicin dose on Days 1-3 + cytarabine on Days 1-7.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subject will receive induction chemotherapy consisting of daunorubicin bolus IV infusion on Days 1-3 + cytarabine continuous IV infusion on Days 1-7  followed by matching placebo once daily oral dose starting on Day 4 of initial induction chemotherapy. If platelet count is not greater than 100 Gi/L after 7 days the matching placebo  will be given until a platelet count of at least 200 Gi/L is achieved/ until remission is assessed/ maximum of 42 days from the start of the chemotherapy induction. Subjects who are not aplastic after first cycle of induction chemotherapy will receive a second induction chemotherapy with a modified daunorubicin dose on Days 1-3 + cytarabine on Days 1-7.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Daunorubicin</intervention_name>
    <description>For subjects between the ages of 18 and 60 years, 90 mg/m2/day by bolus IV injection through a freshly established free-flowing IV line for 10-15 minutes on days 1, 2, and 3. For subjects &gt; 60 years: daunorubicin dose is adjusted to 60mg /m2.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Eltrombopag arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cytarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>100 mg/m2/day continuous IV infusion on Days 1 through 7.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Eltrombopag arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Eltrombopag</intervention_name>
    <description>200 mg orally, once daily, beginning on Day 4 of the first cycle of induction. After 7 days, the dose of IP will be increased to 300 mg if platelet counts are &lt;100 Gi/L. IP continues until achievement of platelet count of at least 200 Gi/L or assessment of remission of bone marrow status or a maximum of 42 days after initiation of most recent induction. In subjects of East Asian heritage 100 mg orally once daily (a 50% dose reduction) will be used and after 7 days, the dose of IP will be increased to 150 mg if platelet counts are &lt;100 Gi/L</description>
    <arm_group_label>Eltrombopag arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Orally, once daily, beginning on Day 4 of the first cycle of induction. After 7 days, the dose given will be matching 300 mg Eltrombopag if platelet counts are &lt;100 Gi/L. Placebo continues until achievement of platelet count of at least 200 Gi/L or assessment of remission of bone marrow status or a maximum of 42 days after initiation of most recent induction. In subjects of East Asian heritage placebo matching 100 mg Eltrombopag orally once daily will be used and after 7 days, the placebo matching 150 mg Eltrombopag will be given if platelet counts are &lt;100 Gi/L.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          -  Age &gt;=18 years

          -  Diagnosed with AML according to the WHO 2008 classification. Note: subjects with
             secondary AML following Myelodysplastic syndrome or secondary to previous
             leukemogenic therapy are allowed provided that a record of previous MDS history or
             leukemogenic therapy history is available.

          -  Eligible for induction by daunorubicin + cytarabine.

          -  Eligible to give informed consent to participate in the study.

          -  Have adequate baseline organ function defined by the following criteria:

        Total bilirubin &lt;=1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) except for Gilbert's syndrome, or
        other conditions that are not indicative of inadequate liver function (i.e. elevation of
        indirect bilirubin (haemolytic) in the absence of alanine aminotransferase [ALT]
        abnormality).

        ALT &lt;=3 x ULN. Serum Creatinine &lt;=2.5 x ULN.

          -  Adequate cardiac function with LVEF &gt;=50% as assessed by echocardiogram (ECHO) or
             Multi Gated Acquisition Scan (MUGA.

          -  Subjects with a QT interval corrected for heart rate according to Bazett's formula
             (QTcB) &lt;450millisecond (msec) or &lt;480msec for subjects with bundle branch block. The
             QTc should be based on single or averaged QTc values of triplicate electrocardiograms
             (ECGs) obtained over a brief recording period.

          -  Women must be either of non-childbearing potential or women with child-bearing
             potential and men with reproductive potential must be willing to practice acceptable
             methods of birth control during the study.

          -  Men with a female partner of childbearing potential must have either had a prior
             vasectomy or agree to use effective contraception from time of randomization until 30
             days after the last dose of investigational product.

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test within 7
             days of first dose of study treatment and agree to use effective contraception during
             the study and for 30 days following the last dose of investigational product.

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  A diagnosis of acute promyelocytic (M3) or acute megakaryocytic leukaemia (M7).

          -  Previous history of exposure to an anthracycline compound.

          -  Previous AML treatment (other than hydroxyurea).

          -  Any serious medical condition, laboratory abnormality, or psychiatric illness that,
             in the view of the treating physician, would place the participant at an unacceptable
             risk if he or she were to participate in the study or would prevent that person from
             giving informed consent.

          -  History of thromboembolic event or other condition requiring ongoing use of
             anticoagulation either with warfarin or low molecular-weight heparin. Note: Occlusion
             of a central line is not exclusion.

          -  Treatment with an investigational drug within 30 days or 5 half lives, whichever is
             longer, preceding the first dose of study medication.

          -  Current and continued use during study treatment period of known Breast cancer
             resistance protein (BCRP) inhibitors or known P-gp inhibitors.

          -  Known active hepatitis B, hepatitis C or Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV)
             infection.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to any of the study drugs or its excipients.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
    <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32806</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02906</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02903</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kogarah</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2217</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3004</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Parkville</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3050</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brussels</city>
        <zip>1070</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <zip>3000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 2M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H2L 4M1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <zip>11527</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Patra</city>
        <zip>26500</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Debrecen</city>
        <zip>4012</zip>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Szeged</city>
        <zip>6720</zip>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Haifa</city>
        <zip>31096</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jerusalem</city>
        <zip>91120</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jerusalem</city>
        <zip>91031</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kfar Saba</city>
        <zip>44281</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tel Aviv</city>
        <zip>64239</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seocho-ku, Seoul</city>
        <zip>137-701</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>138-736</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>135-710</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Slupsk</city>
        <zip>76-200</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kaluga</city>
        <zip>248007</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>115478</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nizhniy Novgorod</city>
        <zip>603126</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Penza</city>
        <zip>440071</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>St'Petersburg</city>
        <zip>197341</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tula</city>
        <zip>300053</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>Greece</country>
    <country>Hungary</country>
    <country>Israel</country>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 15, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 27, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>de novo AML</keyword>
  <keyword>Eltrombopag</keyword>
  <keyword>leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>sAML/MDS</keyword>
  <keyword>acute myeloid leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>secondary acute myeloid</keyword>
  <keyword>thrombocytopenia</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cytarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Daunorubicin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
