<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="102479">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01851460</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130117</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-I-0117</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01851460</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Radiofrequency Ablation for Liver Abscesses From Chronic Granulomatous Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Radiofrequency Ablation (RFA) for the Treatment of Liver Abscesses in Patients With Chronic Granulomatous Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Abscesses are a pocket of infection in an organ or tissue. Patients with a disease called
      chronic granulomatous disease (CGD) often develop these abscesses. CGD is an inherited
      disorder that affects how white blood cells function. Liver abscesses in people with CGD
      often require surgery to remove them and treat the infection. However, some people with CGD
      cannot have full surgery because it would be too risky. Researchers want to try a procedure
      called radiofrequency ablation (RFA) to treat these liver abscesses. RFA can usually be done
      without a major operation. This study will see if RFA is a safe and effective treatment for
      liver abscesses in patients with CGD.

      Objectives:

      - To see if RFA is a safe and effective treatment for CGD-related liver abscesses.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals between 18 and 75 years of age with CGD who have liver abscesses that cannot
      be treated with surgery.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. Blood and urine
           samples will be collected. Imaging studies will be performed on the liver.

        -  Participants will have RFA for the abscesses. RFA is an image-guided technique that
           heats and destroys specific tissue, such as tumor tissue. It will target any abscesses
           on the liver.

        -  After the procedure, participants will stay in the hospital for monitoring before being
           released.

        -  Participants will have regular follow-up visits for up to 1 year after treatment. Blood
           and urine samples will be collected. Additional imaging studies will be performed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Radiofrequency Ablation (RFA) has become an increasingly common therapeutic treatment for
      neoplasms in the liver. A number of devices are now Food and Drug Administration cleared for
      this indication, and a growing body of literature supports this technique as a therapeutic
      option for patients with primary or metastatic hepatic malignancies. In vivo animal studies
      have also shown that this technique can also be used to treat infections. Insertion of the
      thermal energy delivery probe into an infected liver abscess destroys the bacteria while
      preserving surrounding tissue. Off-label use of RFA was successfully used to treat 22
      abscesses in 4 patients with chronic granulomatous disease who had inoperable liver
      abscesses. The proposed clinical trial will specifically evaluate the feasibility, safety,
      and to a lesser extent, efficacy of RFA to treat liver abscesses in subjects with previously
      diagnosed chronic granulomatous disease. This will be a non-randomized case study conducted
      at the Clinical Center at the National Institutes of Health. One RFA device will be used.
      Ten subjects will be enrolled. If the method proves to be both feasible and safe, detailed
      analysis on efficacy will be performed. RFA eventually could play an important clinical role
      in patients with chronic granulomatous disease and liver abscesses that are not amenable to
      surgical management and are without other effective therapeutic options, or might otherwise
      be incompletely treated with surgical resection and debridement alone.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary endpoint for this study is patient safety, defined as no occurrences of Grade 3 or higher toxicities and are at least possibly related to the study intervention.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Radiofrequency Ablation</condition>
  <condition>Liver Abscesses -Staphylococcus Infection</condition>
  <condition>CGD</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Granulomatous Disease</condition>
  <condition>RFA</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RFA - Radiofrequency Ablation</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Scans - Liver</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Liver</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Drawn</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION/ELIGIBILITY CRITERIA:

        A patient will be included if he or she meets all of the following criteria:

          1. Has documented chronic granulomatous disease

          2. Age 18 - 75

          3. Has a liver abscess infected with Staphylococcus aureus, but is not an optimal
             candidate for curative surgical resection either due to location of disease,
             multiplicity of disease, or previous surgery or other comorbidities, such as
             pulmonary insufficiency, or has other contraindications to general anesthesia or
             perioperative management or refuses surgery.

          4. Is willing to return to NIH for imaging scans

          5. Is willing to undergo testing or procedures associated with this protocol

          6. Has failed long term antibiotic treatment and abscess drainage if applicable.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        A patient will be excluded if he or she satisfies 1 or more of the following criteria:

          1. Positive results for toxin-producing bacteria obtained from liver biopsy in the
             pertinent abscess.

          2. Is a good candidate for liver-curative open surgical resection and does not refuse
             the surgery

          3. Is not a candidate for RFA therapy due to lesion size, location, and/or infection
             with a non staphylococcal bacteria.

          4. Has a prothrombin time (PT) or partial thromboplastin time (PTT) &gt; 1.5 times normal
             (except in patients who have a known lupus anticoagulant or other condition which a
             hematologist deems will not cause excessive bleeding despite the abnormal coagulation
             parameters).

          5. Has a platelet count &lt; 50,000/mm(3) which cannot be maintained despite platelet
             transfusions.

          6. If you are pregnant.

          7. Any condition that, in the investigator   s opinion, places the patient at undue risk
             by participating in the study

        Please Note: Co-morbidities in critically ill patients will not themselves constitute
        exclusion criteria because the cause of their illness/condition may require the use of RFA
        as a less invasive treatment than surgery.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elizabeth M Kang, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Patricia L Littel, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-5964</phone>
    <email>plittel@cc.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Elizabeth M Kang, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-7567</phone>
    <email>ekang@niaid.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-I-0117.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rossi S, Di Stasi M, Buscarini E, Cavanna L, Quaretti P, Squassante E, Garbagnati F, Buscarini L. Percutaneous radiofrequency interstitial thermal ablation in the treatment of small hepatocellular carcinoma. Cancer J Sci Am. 1995 May-Jun;1(1):73-81.</citation>
    <PMID>9166457</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siperstein AE, Rogers SJ, Hansen PD, Gitomirsky A. Laparoscopic thermal ablation of hepatic neuroendocrine tumor metastases. Surgery. 1997 Dec;122(6):1147-54; discussion 1154-5.</citation>
    <PMID>9426432</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rossi S, Di Stasi M, Buscarini E, Quaretti P, Garbagnati F, Squassante L, Paties CT, Silverman DE, Buscarini L. Percutaneous RF interstitial thermal ablation in the treatment of hepatic cancer. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 1996 Sep;167(3):759-68.</citation>
    <PMID>8751696</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 8, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Radiofrequency Ablation (RFA)</keyword>
  <keyword>Liver Abscesses</keyword>
  <keyword>Congenital Immunodeficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Granulomatous Disease (CGD)</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-toxin producing Staphylococcus Aureus</keyword>
  <keyword>Inoperable Liver Abscesses</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Abscess</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Granulomatous Disease, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Abscess</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Staphylococcal Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Granuloma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
