<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="120894">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01744171</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>I 215912</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-02231</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01744171</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Vaccine Therapy in Treating Patients With Advanced Stage III-IV Melanoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Trial of a Recombinant Human hsp110-gp100 Chaperone Complex Vaccine for Advanced Stage IIIB/C or IV Melanoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial studies the side effects and the best dose of vaccine therapy in treating
      patients with advanced stage III-IV melanoma. Vaccines made from peptides or antigens may
      help the body build an effective immune response to kill tumor cells
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To estimate the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of human hsp (heat shock protein)110-gp100
      chaperone complex melanoma vaccine (recombinant hsp110-gp100 chaperone complex vaccine) to
      recommend a phase II dose in stage IIIB/C and stage IV metastatic melanoma patients.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To examine the effect of the recombinant human hsp110-gp100 chaperone complex vaccine on
      measurable clinical tumor.

      II. To determine gp100 and hsp110 specific cell mediated and humoral immune responses
      elicited by the chaperone complex vaccine.

      III. To determine the effect of dose and serial administration of the chaperone complex
      vaccine on cell mediated and humoral immune responses.

      IV. To quantify patient characteristics (human leukocyte antigen [HLA] subtype, immune cell
      function, etc.) that may correlate with immune response to the chaperone complex vaccine.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study.

      Patients receive recombinant hsp110-gp100 chaperone complex vaccine intradermally on days 1,
      15, and 43 in the absence of unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for 6 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MTD of recombinant human hsp110-gp100 chaperone complex melanoma vaccine based on the probability of dose-limiting toxicity (DLT), graded according to National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after the last vaccine dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>DLT is defined as grade 3 or 4 toxicity or grade 3 injection site toxicity, with the exception of grade 3 rigors/chills which will be tolerated for 48-72 hours if attributable to vaccine reaction.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective tumor response according to RECIST version 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Recurrent Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (recombinant hsp110-gp100 chaperone complex vaccine)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive recombinant hsp110-gp100 chaperone complex vaccine intradermally on days 1, 15, and 43 in the absence of unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>recombinant hsp110-gp100 chaperone complex vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given intradermally</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (recombinant hsp110-gp100 chaperone complex vaccine)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0-2

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt; 1500/uL

          -  Platelets &gt;= 120,000/uL

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 mg/dL

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) =&lt; 1.5 x upper
             limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Serum creatinine =&lt; 1.5 mg/dL (if &gt; 1.5 mg/dL, then creatinine clearance should be &gt;
             60 mL/min)

          -  Blood urea nitrogen (BUN) =&lt; 1.5 x ULN

          -  Have measurable disease per Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1
             criteria or physical exam

          -  An anticipated overall survival of at least 6 months

          -  Patients of child-bearing potential must agree to use acceptable contraceptive
             methods (e.g., double barrier) during treatment

          -  Patient or legal representative must understand the investigational nature of this
             study and sign an Independent Ethics Committee/Institutional Review Board approved
             written informed consent form prior to receiving any study related procedure

          -  Patients must have undergone/undergo testing for BRAF V600 mutation status

          -  Patients must have documented, clinically measurable 7th edition American Joint
             Committee on Cancer (AJCC) stage IIIB/C (bulky nodal and/or in transit disease) or
             stage IV (distant metastatic) melanoma; patients with brain metastases that have been
             appropriately treated with surgical resection and/or radiation are eligible for
             inclusion if they meet the performance status and life expectancy criteria; patients
             who are BRAF V600E mutation positive need to have failed, refused, or be ineligible
             for at least 2 lines of therapy (vemurafenib plus one other regimen)

          -  Stage IIIB/C patients must have refused, be ineligible for, or have failed at least
             one standard of care regional therapy (isolated limb perfusion or infusion) or one
             non-vaccine based systemic therapy (such as, high dose interleukin (IL)-2,
             dacarbazine/temozolomide, vemurafenib, ipilimumab, or participation in a clinical
             trial); stage IV patients must have refused, be ineligible for, or have failed at
             least one non-vaccine based systemic therapy (such as, high dose IL-2,
             dacarbazine/temozolomide, vemurafenib, ipilimumab, or participation in a clinical
             trial)

          -  Stage IV patients must have refused, be ineligible for, or have failed at least one
             non-vaccine based systemic therapy (such as, high dose interleukin [IL]-2,
             dacarbazine/temozolomide, ipilimumab, or participation in a clinical trial); patients
             who are BRAF V600E mutation positive need to have failed, refused, or be ineligible
             for at least 2 lines of therapy (vemurafenib plus one other regimen)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant or nursing female patients

          -  Unwilling or unable to follow protocol requirements

          -  Any condition which in the Investigator's opinion deems the patient an unsuitable
             candidate to receive study drug

          -  Received an investigational agent within 30 days prior to enrollment

          -  Melanoma specific systemic therapy within 30 days of enrollment

          -  A history of AJCC stage IIIB/C or stage IV melanoma but no current clinical evidence
             of metastatic disease

          -  Known immunosuppressed conditions or active immunosuppressive therapy such as organ
             transplantation (including bone marrow transplant), high dose steroids, or human
             immunodeficiency virus (HIV); although a documented negative HIV test is not
             mandatory for enrollment, patients felt to have a high clinical suspicion for HIV
             will need to test negative prior to enrollment; use of topicals or eye drops
             containing steroids is acceptable; inhaled steroids are excluded

          -  Known autoimmune conditions including but not limited to rheumatoid arthritis,
             multiple sclerosis, lupus, scleroderma, sarcoidosis, vitiligo, inflammatory bowel
             disease, idiopathic thrombocytopenia purpura, Graves' disease, or Hashimoto's
             thyroiditis

          -  Previous history of splenectomy or whole spleen radiation

          -  Systemic immunoglobin therapy within the last 30 days

          -  Previous history of anaphylaxis or severe allergic reaction to hsp110, gp100, other
             vaccines, or unknown allergens

          -  Previous or active non-melanoma malignancies (excluding non-melanoma skin cancer or
             carcinoma in situ of the cervix) diagnosed/treated within the last 5 years

          -  Active uncontrolled bacterial, viral, or fungal infection until these conditions are
             corrected or controlled

          -  Concomitant systemic treatment with anti-histamine or non-steroidal anti-inflammatory
             drugs; specific cyclooxygenase (COX)-2 inhibitors are permitted
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Kane</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14263</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Roswell Park</last_name>
      <phone>877-275-7724</phone>
      <email>ASKRPCI@roswellpark.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John M. Kane</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 4, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
