<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="120940">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01797471</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UMIAMI-20100446</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01797471</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 1 Study Evaluating Safety of LEAD Radiotherapy Plus Chemoradiation in Patients With Bulky Stage III Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1 Study for Evaluating the Safety of Lattice Extreme Ablative Dose (LEAD) Radiotherapy Followed by Standard-Dose Chemoradiation for Patients With Bulky Stage III Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Miami Sylvester Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Miami Sylvester Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators aim to evaluate the safety of delivering a one-time single fraction of
      Lattice Extreme Ablative Dose (LEAD) radiotherapy followed one day later by standard-dose,
      conventionally fractionated concurrent chemotherapy and radiation delivered over 6 weeks in
      patients with bulky stage III non-small cell lung cancer in the setting of a single-arm
      phase I clinical trial.  The investigators hypothesize that the addition of a one-time
      single fraction of LEAD radiation is safe and feasible, and will not result in additional
      toxicity above that expected with standard-dose concurrent chemotherapy and radiation alone.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of treatment-related adverse events experienced by participants</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Toxicity will be graded by CTCAE v 4.0. The two toxicities that will be monitored as primary endpoints are esophagitis and pneumonitis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subject experiencing Loco-regional failure</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Loco-regional failure is defined as any evidence of disease progression within the primary primary tumor or regional lymph nodes, detected by any method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects achieving CT RECIST Response</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of subjects achieving complete response or partial response according to CT RECIST Response Criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects achieving Complete or Partial Response via PET response criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of subjects achieving as detected by PET Scan: Complete response (CR) is defined as no residual focal FDG uptake or decrease in average FDG uptake by more than 80% in all tumor manifestations. Partial response is defined as standardized uptake value (SUV) decrease by 0 - 80%.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>NSCLC</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lattice Extreme Ablative Dose Radiation Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>A single fraction of LEAD RT, dose of 18 Gy will be delivered to subjects on day 1</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LEAD Radiotherapy</other_name>
    <other_name>LEAD Radiation Therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventionally Fractionated Radiation</intervention_name>
    <description>Conventionally fractionated radiation therapy will be delivered to subjects beginning on day 2 at 2 Gy per fraction for 30 fractions for a total dose of 60 Gy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Platinum-based Chemotherapy Doublet</intervention_name>
    <description>Platinum-based chemotherapy doublet administered beginning day 2 via wither weekly or every 3 week regimen. Platinum-based agent selection is at the discretion of the treating medical oncologist</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histologically or cytologically documented stage III non-small
             cell lung cancer including squamous cell, adenocarcinoma, large cell carcinoma and
             poorly differentiated non-small cell lung cancer.

          -  Patients must have a minimum of 4 cm of measureable disease in any one continuous
             dimension as seen on diagnostic CT scan.

          -  Pulmonary function tests with FEV1 &gt;= 1.45 liters/second.

          -  Patients must be 21 years of age or older.  There is no maximum age restriction.

          -  Patients must have a Zubrod performance status of 0 or 1.

          -  Patients must have normal organ and marrow function as defined below:

               -  leukocyte &gt; 3,000/:I

               -  absolute neutrophil count &gt;1,500/:1

               -  platelets &gt;100,000/:1

               -  bilirubin within normal institutional limits

               -  AST(SGOT)/ALT(SGPT) 2.5 X institutional upper limit of normal

               -  Creatinine within normal institutional limits  OR creatinine clearance &gt; 60
                  mL/min/1.73 m2 for patients with creatinine levels above institutional normal.

          -  Patients must have weight loss ≤ 10% over the past three months.

          -  Women of child-bearing potential and men will be asked to use adequate contraception.

          -  Patients must have the ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written
             informed consent document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients may not have had prior thoracic radiation at any time, or prior chemotherapy
             for the study cancer at any time.

          -  Patients may not be receiving any other investigational agents for the study cancer.

          -  Patients may not have evidence of brain metastases on baseline CT scan or MRI.

          -  Patients may not have measurable gross disease in the thorax &lt;4 cm in any one
             continuous dimension.

          -  Patients may not have a cytologically positive pleural effusion.

          -  Patients may not have a prior invasive malignancy (unless disease-free for at least 3
             years).

          -  Patients may not have had surgical resection of the present cancer.

          -  Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding will be excluded.

          -  Patients must not have any co-morbidity with life expectancy ≤ 6 months, or any
             uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements.

          -  Patients must not have severe lung disease defined by a history of severe COPD
             requiring 3 or more hospitalizations over the past year, or history of interstitial
             pneumonitis.

          -  Patients must not have any concurrent active malignancy.

          -  Patients must not have evidence of metastatic disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jean L Wright, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Miami Sylvester Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Miami Sylvester Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 28, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 20, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>NSCLC</keyword>
  <keyword>Lung Cancer</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
