<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="121178">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02113371</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>e5473</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U19OH010154-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02113371</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of COMmunity of Practice And Safety Support (COMPASS) for Home Care Workers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Creating Health and Safety Communities of Practice for Home Care Workers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oregon Health and Science University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health (NIOSH/CDC)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oregon Health and Science University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The current project is a cluster-randomized controlled trial of a safety and health
      intervention for home care workers conducted within the Oregon Healthy Workforce Center
      (OHWC), a NIOSH Center of Excellence in Total Worker Health.

      The objective of this three-year project is to create sustainable health and safety
      &quot;communities of practice&quot; within a population of typically isolated home care workers. The
      intervention is a 12-month team-based, peer-led scripted curriculum that integrates health
      promotion and protection topics, as well as proven elements of social support groups for
      caregivers. The investigators hypothesize that this intervention will increase measures of
      experienced community of practice, well-being, and diet, exercise, and safety behaviors, as
      compared to a usual practices control condition.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Home care workers have an injury rate that is nearly four times higher than the US average
      and are at elevated risk for mental and physical health problems. These low income workers,
      who are predominantly female and older than 40, assist the elderly and disabled with
      self-care and mobility in private homes. Although interventions developed for other
      caregiver populations improve well being and knowledge, they have largely failed to address
      illness and injury prevention behaviors. No prior study has addressed the lack of
      occupational social support structures for home care workers. The long term goal of this
      project is to create a model work structure for promoting and protecting home care worker
      health that can be disseminated to other states. The objective of this study is to develop
      and evaluate a new team-based intervention for self-employed home care workers enrolled in
      Oregon public programs. Workers will be organized into neighborhood based Total Worker
      Health teams that meet regularly for education and social support. The proposed curriculum
      will integrate health promotion and protection topics, and will use established team-based
      education methods as well as proven elements of social support groups for caregivers.

      The primary hypotheses are that organizing home care workers into Total Worker Health teams
      will increase (1) Experienced community of practice, (2) Well-being, and (3) Prevention
      behaviors in the domains of diet, exercise, and safety.

      To test these hypotheses the investigators will conduct a cluster randomized controlled
      trial of the intervention.

      The project will take place over three years and accomplish three specific aims:

        1. Develop and Pilot Test a Total Worker Health Team Curriculum for Home Care Workers
           During the first year of the project the investigators will develop and pilot test a
           Total Worker Health team curriculum with a single group of home care workers identified
           as leaders by the Service Employees International Union (SEIU Local 503). Pilot test
           participants will later serve as team leaders in the randomized controlled trial in Aim
           2. Curriculum materials will include educational workbooks, active home work
           assignments, and scripted meeting facilitation guides for team leaders. The curriculum
           will be designed to establish functioning Total Worker Health teams in 6 months using a
           half-day team building orientation followed by structured monthly educational and
           supportive team meetings. Study methods will be evaluated and revised based on pilot
           participants' feedback about the acceptability of the goals, procedures, and outcomes
           of intervention activities.

        2. Determine the Effectiveness of Total Worker Health Teams with a Randomized Controlled
           Trial The investigators will recruit a sample home care workers from the Portland and
           Eugene metro areas. This sample will then be organized into neighborhood clusters and
           randomly assigned to intervention and control conditions. Evaluation measures will be
           collected from all participants at pre-intervention (month 0), post-intervention (month
           6), and follow-up (month 12) time points. Intervention participants will complete the
           Total Worker Health curriculum while control participants receive usual treatment.
           Intervention effectiveness will be established at the 6-month time point through
           between group comparisons on changes in experienced community of practice, well-being,
           and prevention behaviors (diet, exercise, and safety). The investigators will also
           measure body composition and fitness, metabolic and heart disease biomarkers, job
           stress, social support, musculoskeletal symptoms, and illness/injuries.

        3. Measure the Integrity of Sustained Total Worker Health Team Meetings and Maintenance at
           Follow-Up. After each Total Worker Health team completes the intervention curriculum,
           they will be provided with funding and a structured guide to sustain regular team
           meetings for an additional 6 months. Researchers will observe and monitor team meetings
           during this follow-up period to measure participation level and adherence to the
           prescribed team meeting structure. The integrity scores for Total Worker Health team
           meetings and potential maintenance of between group intervention effects will be
           evaluated at the 12-month (follow up) time point.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in experienced community of practice at 6 and 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Survey measures: Experienced Community of Practice Scale (Cadiz, Sawyer &amp; Griffith, 2009).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in well-being at 6 and 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Survey measures: SF-12 version 2 (Ware et al., 2002), Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale (CES-D) (Bohannon et al., 2003), Loneliness (Hughes et al., 2008), Positive and Negative Affect (Watson et al., 1988).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in dietary behaviors at 6 and 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Survey measures: National Cancer Institute Fruit and Vegetable Screener (Thompson et al., 2002), High-Saturated Fat/High-Sugar Food Servings (Buxton et al., 2009).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in exercise behaviors at 6 and 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Survey measures: Exercise habits (Elliot et al., 2007).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in safety behaviors at 6 and 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Survey measures: Home Care Worker Task Demands Index, questions obtained from Belman et al., 2005.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in blood pressure at 6 and 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Direct measurement via Omron HEM-907 automatic blood pressure monitor.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in blood lipids at 6 and 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Direct measurement of total cholesterol, HDL cholesterol, LDL cholesterol, and triglycerides via Cholestech LDX Analyzer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in blood glucose at 6 and 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Direct measurement via Cholestech LDX Analyzer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in body weight at 6 and 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Direct measurement via Tanita TBF-310GS Bioelectric Impedance Analyzer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in body mass index (BMI) at 6 and 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Direct measurement of height via SECA 213 portable stadiometer. Direct measurement of weight via Tanita TBF-310GS Bioelectric Impedance Analyzer. Calculation of BMI using direct measurements of height and weight.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in percent body fat at 6 and 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Direct measurement via Tanita TBF-310GS Bioelectric Impedance Analyzer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in body measurements at 6 and 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Direct measurement of neck, waist, and hip circumference via Gulick II measuring tape. Calculation of waist hip ratio.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in stress at 6 and 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Survey measures: Stress In General (Stanton et al., 2001), Revised Social Readjustment Rating Scale (Holmes &amp; Rahe, 1967; Hobson et al., 1998; Scully et al., 2000), Interpersonal Conflict (Wright et al., 2014), Perceived Stress (Cohen et al., 1983).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in sleep and fatigue at 6 and 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Survey measures: items from the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (Buysse et al., 1989).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in social support at 6 and 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Survey measures: Social Support for Diet Behaviors (Sallis et al., 1987), Social Support for Exercise Behaviors (Sallis et al., 1987), Social Support Network (Toseland, 1990).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in musculoskeletal symptoms at 6 and 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Survey measures: Adapted Nordic Questionnaire for Musculoskeletal Symptoms (Dennerlein et al., 2012).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in illnesses and injuries at 6 and 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Survey measures: Self-reported lost time and first aid injuries, self-reported diagnoses of and treatment for co-morbid conditions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Wounds and Injuries</condition>
  <condition>Health Promotion</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention, conducted over a 12 month period, consists of monthly scripted, peer-led social support sessions covering health and safety topics.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual practices with regard to health and work conditions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intervention</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Currently employed as a publicly funded home care worker with a minimum of one
             consumer employer

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oregon Health and Science University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ohsu.edu/xd/research/centers-institutes/croet/oregon-healthy-workforce-center/projects/compass.cfm</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 11, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Oregon Health and Science University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ryan Olson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Scientist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Injury Prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Health Promotion</keyword>
  <keyword>Well being</keyword>
  <keyword>Safety</keyword>
  <keyword>Nutrition</keyword>
  <keyword>Physical Activity</keyword>
  <keyword>Sleep</keyword>
  <keyword>Stress</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
