<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="101005">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02142959</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RTA 408-C-1306</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02142959</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>RTA 408 Lotion in Patients at Risk for Radiation Dermatitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-blind, Vehicle-controlled, Parallel-group Phase 2 Study of the Efficacy, Safety, and Pharmacokinetics of RTA 408 Lotion in the Treatment of Patients at Risk for Radiation Dermatitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Reata Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>AbbVie</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Reata Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Radiation dermatitis is experienced by almost all patients (up to 95%) receiving radiation
      therapy for cancer.  Radiation dermatitis can be a serious condition because, in addition to
      its direct physical complications and the resulting impact on overall quality of life, it
      can also be a dose-limiting toxicity requiring changes to the prescribed course of radiation
      therapy. The most common strategy employed in an attempt to prevent or minimize radiation
      dermatitis involves moisturization of the irradiated area, use of a mild soap to keep the
      area clean, and minimizing exposure to potential mechanical irritants, such as scratching
      and rough clothing. However, this strategy has been shown to lack clinically significant
      efficacy.  Consequently, there is a clinical need for new treatments that are effective in
      protecting against radiotherapy-induced oxidative stress and the subsequent development of
      radiation dermatitis.

      Based on data from previous studies in animals and humans, Reata believes that RTA 408
      Lotion may effectively prevent and mitigate radiation dermatitis in oncology patients
      undergoing radiation therapy.

      This randomized, double-blind, vehicle-controlled, parallel-group trial will study the
      efficacy, tolerability and safety of two concentrations of RTA 408 Lotion (3% and 0.5%)
      versus vehicle in patients with breast cancer for whom radiation therapy is recommended.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Grading of skin changes following radiation therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>9 weeks (maximum of 13 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Grading of skin changes (using CTCAE grading scale) due to treatment with radiation therapy, following topical application of RTA 408 lotion or lotion vehicle</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Count of patients who experience a maximum radiation dermatitis grade of less than 2</measure>
    <time_frame>9 weeks (maximum of 13 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Count the number of patients who experience a maximum radiation dermatitis grade of less than 2 (based on CTCAE grading scale) due to treatment with radiation therapy, following topical application of RTA 408 lotion or lotion vehicle</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">177</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RTA 408 Lotion 0.5%</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>RTA 408 lotion 0.5% will be applied topically twice-daily, for up to 13 weeks, during the course of radiation therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RTA 408 Lotion 3%</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>RTA 408 lotion 3% will be applied topically twice-daily, for up to 13 weeks, during the course of radiation therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lotion vehicle/Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Lotion vehicle/placebo will be applied topically twice-daily, for up to 13 weeks, during the course of radiation therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RTA 408 Lotion 0.5%</intervention_name>
    <description>RTA 408 lotion 0.5% will be applied topically twice-daily, for up to 13 weeks, during the course of radiation therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>RTA 408 Lotion 0.5%</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RTA 408 Lotion 3%</intervention_name>
    <description>RTA 408 lotion 3% will be applied topically twice-daily, for up to 13 weeks, during the course of radiation therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>RTA 408 Lotion 3%</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lotion vehicle/Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Lotion vehicle manufactured to mimic RTA 408 lotion will be applied topically twice-daily, for up to 13 weeks, during the course of radiation therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lotion vehicle/Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult female patients (18 to 75 years of age, inclusive);

          2. Patients diagnosed with ductal carcinoma in situ or non-inflammatory breast
             adenocarcinoma who have been referred for post-operative radiotherapy and have had no
             prior radiation treatment to that breast;

          3. Patients planning to undergo 3D conformal radiation therapy to the whole breast (as
             part of breast-conservation therapy / lumpectomy) or chest wall (as part of
             post-mastectomy irradiation), with or without treatment of regional lymph nodes
             (i.e., axillary, supraclavicular, or internal mammary), using one of the following
             treatment schedules:

               1. 45 - 50.4 Gy in 1.8 Gy per day, in addition to 10-16 Gy boost

               2. 46 - 50 Gy in 2 Gy per day, in addition to 10-16 Gy boost;

          4. Patients who received breast-conservation therapy / lumpectomy must be receiving ≥
             107% of the total radiation dose (calculated from the total radiation dose including
             boost) to any portion of the breast, based on radiation inhomogeneity, and/or have a
             breast volume ≥ 1200 cc;

          5. Patients may also be receiving sequential, neoadjuvant or adjuvant, chemotherapy;

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with Stage T4 breast cancer;

          2. Patients with prior radiation therapy;

          3. Patients with type V or VI skin according to the Fitzpatrick scale;

          4. Patients with bilateral breast cancer;

          5. Patients receiving partial breast irradiation therapy;

          6. Patients with uncontrolled diabetes (HbA1c &gt; 11.0%, historical values within 6 months
             of screening are acceptable);

          7. Patients with collagen vascular disease or vasculitis;

          8. Patients with concurrent active malignancy other than adequately treated basal cell
             carcinoma of the skin or carcinoma in situ of the cervix;

          9. Patients with active bacterial, fungal or viral skin infections;

         10. Patients with known active hepatitis B or hepatitis C infection;

         11. Patients who intend to use any other topical cream, lotion or preparation applied to
             the radiation treatment area;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 19, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 16, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>RTA 408</keyword>
  <keyword>RTA 408 Lotion</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiation therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiation dermatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Oxidative stress</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Radiodermatitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
