<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="166558">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01997398</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12BN123</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01997398</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>DBS Under General Anesthesia: Comparison To The Standard Technique</brief_title>
  <official_title>DBS Under General Anesthesia Without Neurophysiology: Initial Experience and Comparison To The Standard Technique</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Joseph's Hospital and Medical Center, Phoenix</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Joseph's Hospital and Medical Center, Phoenix</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      There is a growing trend in functional neurosurgery toward direct anatomical targeting for
      deep brain stimulation (DBS).  This study describes a method and reports the initial
      experience placing DBS electrodes under general anesthesia without the use of microelectrode
      recordings (MER), using a portable head CT scanner to verify accuracy    intra-operatively.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Deep brain stimulation (DBS) is an established therapy for Parkinson's disease and tremor.
      The therapy was first introduced in the late 1980s, and was FDA approved in 1997.  Over
      100,000 patients have been treated with DBS, and the benefits have been confirmed through
      multicenter randomized controlled trials.

      Traditional DBS is performed with the patient awake. Parkinson's patients are required to be
      off their Parkinson's medicine during awake DBS, and single-unit cellular recordings are
      performed to map the intended target.  Electrophysiological mapping can require multiple
      brain penetrations.  The surgery can last 4-6 hours.  The surgeon uses a local anesthetic to
      numb the tissue where the incision is made, and mild sedatives are administered to ward off
      anxiety.   The prospect of being awake on the operating table for brain surgery concerns
      some patients, as does the requirement to be off medicine.

      There is growing interest in performing DBS under general anesthesia, whereby targets are
      selected anatomically (i.e., on MRI) rather than physiologically . So-called &quot;asleep DBS&quot; is
      performed with the patient under general anesthesia, and uses intraoperative CT imaging both
      to target and to verify accurate placement of DBS electrodes at the time of surgery.  Asleep
      DBS eliminates the need for the patient to be kept awake and off medicine.  The goal of
      Asleep DBS is to accurately place the electrodes at the target selected by the surgeon
      preoperatively, and this goal is accomplished through intraoperative imaging.
      Electrophysiological mapping is not performed.

      The Asleep DBS program at Barrow Neurological Institute / SJHMC started in March 2012; the
      second institution world-wide to adopt the asleep technique developed by Dr. Kim Burchiel.
      Other institutions have performed asleep DBS within an MRI magnet to visualize the placement
      of the electrode.  The &quot;Burchiel technique&quot; relies upon MRI-CT fusion algorithms to
      superimpose the leads, seen on CT, on the MRI which was used for planning.

      While asleep DBS improves the patient experience, it is incumbent upon us to demonstrate
      that the functional outcomes are equivalent to those reported for traditional &quot;awake&quot; DBS.
      Further, despite common use of MRI-CT fusion, which is available on our neuronavigation
      systems, the evidence supporting this modality comes from the 1990s, primarily from Gamma
      Knife literature.

      This study will include functional outcomes using established metrics for Parkinson's,
      capturing both motor function (Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale) and quality of life
      (Parkinson's Disease Questionnaire-39).  In addition, follow-up MRI imaging will allow us to
      verify that the true position of the DBS leads matches where we thought the leads were based
      on the intraoperative CT scan that was fused to the preoperative MRI.  In other words, there
      is an error in placement that we see at the time of surgery (if we our inaccuracy is over 2
      mm, we reposition the DBS lead).  There is also an inherent inaccuracy with CT-MRI fusion.
      If these inaccuracies are compounded such that where we think we are at the time of surgery
      is far from where we actually are (as seen on the follow-up MRI of the brain), then CT-MRI
      fusion is not reliable and should not be used to verify lead placement.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case-Only, Time Perspective: Retrospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional outcomes using established metrics for Parkinson's.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post-operatively</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Motor function: (Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale-3) and quality of life measures(Parkinson's Disease Questionnaire-39.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Verification of lead placement</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks post-operatively</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Follow-up MRI imaging will allows verification that the true position of the DBS leads match where it was thought the leads were based on the intraoperative CT scan that was fused to the preoperative MRI.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients will be selected by CPT codes corresponding to bilateral DBS electrode placement
        placed under general anesthesia with Leksell sterotactic navigation, portable CT and
        without the use of microelectrode recordings (MER).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient's who have undergone DBS surgery under general anesthesia without
             electrophysiology, utilizing a portable head CT scanner to verify accuracy
             intra-operatively.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient's who have undergone DBS surgery awake, without general anesthesia and with
             electrophysiology.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Francisco A Ponce, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>BARROW NEUROLOGICAL INSTITUTE / SJHMC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Joseph's Hospiatl &amp; Medical Center / Barrow Neurological Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85013</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 27, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Deep brain stimulation surgery under general anesthesia</keyword>
  <keyword>Deep brain stimulation target accuracy</keyword>
  <keyword>Deep brain stimulation for Parkinsons's disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Deep brain stimulation functional outcomes</keyword>
  <keyword>Deep brain stimulation quality of life outcomes</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
