<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="24926">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01727414</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ADDMedStudy</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>K23MH083881</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01727414</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Attention Deficit Disorder Medication Response Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Medication Response in Children With Predominately Inattentive Type ADHD</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates how children with Attention Deficit Disorder without Hyperactivity
      (ADD) respond to medication, and if their response is different from children who have
      problems with both hyperactivity and inattention. In order to do this, children ages 7-11
      whose primary difficulty is with attention problems and who have never been on behavioral or
      psychiatric medications are being recruited.  Once enrolled, children will try one week each
      of 3 different doses of methylphenidate, the most commonly prescribed Attention Deficit,
      Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) medication, as well as placebo.  Children will  be randomly
      assigned to one of six possible medication dose and placebo titration schedules, but the
      study doctor, family, and teacher will not know which dose (if any) children are receiving
      for a given week.  Each week, behavioral and side effect ratings will be completed by both
      the child's parent and teacher, and the family will meet with the study doctor for a
      physical examination and to discuss how each week went. Some children will also have
      neuropsychological testing to determine how methylphenidate influences their working memory,
      sustained attention, and ability to inhibit (stop) inappropriate responses.

      All data will be analyzed to decide which medication dose the child responded to best and
      further recommendations for treatment will be given. Ultimately, this study aims to improve
      understanding of how children with ADHD-Primarily Inattentive Type respond to stimulant
      medications by

        -  determining whether these children experience a diminished response to methylphenidate
           compared to children with both hyperactivity and inattention

        -  determining whether certain genetic and environmental factors play a role in this
           response.

      Findings from this study will be used to help streamline the identification of the most
      effective doses of medication for children with ADHD-Primarily Inattentive Type.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Robust data indicate that stimulant medications reduce ADHD symptoms and impairment, but it
      is unclear whether their efficacy generalizes across the ADHD subtypes. Although
      predominately inattentive type (PIT) is the most prevalent ADHD subtype in U.S.
      population-based studies, few studies have specifically examined response to stimulants in
      this subtype. Instead, medication guidelines for PIT have largely been extrapolated from
      studies enrolling all or mostly ADHD-combined type (CT). Thus, this application seeks to
      improve understanding of stimulant medication response and its predictors in children with
      PIT. We will evaluate participants' response to methylphenidate (MPH), the most widely
      prescribed stimulant, via a prospective, double-blind, placebo-controlled crossover trial
      with 3 dose conditions. Our first specific aim is to examine MPH medication and dose
      response in children with PIT (n=120) and CT (n=45) to test the hypotheses that participants
      with PIT have a diminished MPH response and derive less benefit from higher doses compared
      to those with CT. Since only one prior study has examined genetic predictors of MPH response
      variability within PIT-only samples, our second specific aim (exploratory) is to determine
      the potential role of genetic polymorphisms (e.g., those in DAT1, DRD4, NET, ADRA2A, COMT,
      SNAP25, CES1, GRM7, LPHN3) on MPH response in children with PIT (n=120), examining both
      symptom change with MPH and MPH dose response curves. If we identify significant differences
      in MPH response between the subtypes, our findings may guide clinical practice by suggesting
      more effective medication strategies (such as different dosing schedules) for children with
      PIT. In addition, this study may yield pharmacogenetic findings that, in the future, could
      enable physicians to tailor individual treatment plans for children with PIT, ameliorating
      the current prolonged and expensive practice of prescribing by trial and error.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Pharmacodynamics Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>ADHD symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 1, week 2, week 3, week 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessed via parent and teacher-completed Vanderbilt Rating Scales</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinician Global Impression rating</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 1, week 2, week 3, week 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sluggish Cognitive Tempo rating</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 1, week 2, week 3, week 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ADHD Impairment Ratings</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, wk 1, wk 2, wk 3, wk 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medication side effect ratings</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, wk 1, wk 2, wk 3, wk 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Biophysical parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, wk 1, wk 2, wk 3, wk 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>weight, heart rate, blood pressure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medication continuity and adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>one year after ending of medication trial</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Family satisfaction with medication trial</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1 month, 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropsychological test performance</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>math performance</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 1 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>direct behavioral observations</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 1 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">165</enrollment>
  <condition>ADHD - Inattentive Type</condition>
  <condition>ADHD - Combined Type</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Drug: OROS-Methylphenidate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Methylphenidate, capsule, 0mg, 18mg, 27, 36mg, or 54mg 1x/day for 7 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>OROS-Methylphenidate</intervention_name>
    <description>capsule; dosages - 18mg, 27mg, 36mg, 54 mg; frequency - each AM; duration - one week for each dose, with each child receiving 3 doses [children &lt; 25 kg receive 18mg, 27mg, 36mg; children &gt; or = to 25kg get 18mg, 36mg, 54mg]</description>
    <arm_group_label>Drug: OROS-Methylphenidate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>concerta</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>capsule, frequency - each AM, duration - 1 week</description>
    <arm_group_label>Drug: OROS-Methylphenidate</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Consent: The family must provide signature of informed consent by a parent or legal
             guardian.  Children must also assent to study participation.

          -  Age at Screening:7.0 years to 11.9 years, inclusive.

          -  Sex: Includes male and female children.

          -  ADHD Diagnostic Status: Meets DSM-IV criteria for ADHD, Predominantly Inattentive or
             Combined subtype with Clinical Global Impression-Severity rating corresponding to at
             least &quot;moderately ill.&quot;

          -  Cognitive Functioning-Intelligence Quotient (IQ) of greater than 80 as estimated by
             Vocabulary and Block Design subtests of the Wechsler Intelligence Scale for
             Children--4th  Edition, or an Intelligence Quotient (IQ) of 80 or greater when
             administered the  Full Scale Version of the Wechsler Intelligence Scale for
             Children—4th Edition.

          -  Absence of Learning Disability:On the abbreviated Wechsler Individual Achievement
             Test—2nd edition Reading and Math subtests, participants must score above 80.
             However, children may also be included if they receive a score of 75 or greater on
             the Word Reading and/or Math subtests, as long as this score is not a significant
             discrepancy from their full-scale IQ score (e.g., a difference of greater than one
             standard deviation or 15 points).

          -  School: Enrolled in a school setting rather than a home-school program.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Understanding Level: Participant and/or parent cannot understand or follow study
             instructions.

          -  Psychiatric Medications: Current or prior history of taking any medication for
             psychological or psychiatric problems.

          -  Behavioral Interventions: Current active participation in ADHD-related behavioral
             interventions or counseling.

          -  Exclusionary Psychiatric Conditions: Children with mania/hypomania and/or
             schizophrenia will be excluded.  The following comorbid diagnoses will not be
             excluded unless they are determined to be the primary cause of ADHD symptomatology
             (see below for description of this decision process): Post Traumatic Stress Disorder,
             Phobias and Anxiety Disorders, Obsessive Compulsive Disorder, Major Depression /
             Dysthymia, Eating Disorders, Elimination Disorders, Trichotillomania, Tic Disorder,
             Oppositional Defiant Disorder, Conduct Disorder.

          -  Organic Brain Injury: History of head trauma, neurological disorder, or other organic
             disorder affecting brain function.

          -  Cardiovascular Risk Factors: Children with a personal history or family history of
             cardiovascular risk factors will be excluded, or given the option of participating in
             the study after obtaining an EKG and a signed letter from a pediatric cardiologist
             verifying the safety of their participation in a trial of methylphenidate.  In this
             case, families will be responsible for the costs of EKG and cardiologist evaluation.
             If for any reason a family is unable to assume the cost of the EKG and cardiologist
             evaluations but still wishes for their child to participate, study staff will
             determine on a case-by-case basis whether the study budget allows the study to offer
             financial assistance to the families for these evaluations.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>11 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tanya E. Froehlich, MS, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Heather R. Matheson, B.A.</last_name>
    <phone>513-636-6632</phone>
    <email>heather.matheson@cchmc.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tanya E. Froehlich, MD, MS</last_name>
    <phone>513-636-1154</phone>
    <email>tanya.froehlich@cchmc.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Heather R Matheson, B.A.</last_name>
      <phone>513-636-6632</phone>
      <email>heather.matheson@cchmc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tanya E Froehlich, MD,MS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 15, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 1, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ADHD</keyword>
  <keyword>Inattention</keyword>
  <keyword>Methylphenidate</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacogenetics</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Attention Deficit Disorder with Hyperactivity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Methylphenidate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
