<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="83902">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01801449</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130086</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-AR-0086</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01801449</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rilonacept for Deficiency of the Interleukin-1 Receptor Antagonist (DIRA)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Open-Label Study of Rilonacept (Arcalyst) in the Deficiency of the Interleukin-1 Receptor Antagonist (DIRA)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Deficiency of the IL-1 receptor antagonist (DIRA) is a condition that causes repeated
      episodes of inflammation. People with DIRA can have rashes, fever, and joint pain. Most
      treatments for DIRA are intended to control the immune system to stop these inflammations.
      There are drugs that can treat DIRA, but they have to be given daily as injections.
      Researchers want to try another drug, rilonacept, as a treatment for DIRA. It needs to be
      given only once a week. Rilonacept will be given to individuals who are at least 3 months
      old and who have DIRA.

      Objectives:

      - To test the safety and effectiveness of rilonacept for children and adults with DIRA.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals at least 3 months old who have DIRA.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. Blood and urine
           samples will be collected. Other tests to study pain and movement will be given.
           Imaging studies such as bone density scans and x-rays may also be taken.

        -  Participants will have a minimum of four to five study visits over 12 months. Those who
           are on different anti-inflammatory drugs (such as anakinra) will stop taking them
           before beginning the study visits.

        -  Participants will have rilonacept injections weekly while on this study. The dose will
           be adjusted as needed to help treat the DIRA symptoms. Participants will keep a diary
           to monitor their symptoms and any side effects.

        -  Treatment with rilonacept will be given for 1 year. Participants will have study visits
           to monitor the treatment. They will provide blood samples and have other tests at these
           study visits.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Autoinflammatory diseases are illnesses characterized by episodes of inflammation that,
      unlike autoimmune disorders, lack the production of high titer autoantibodies or
      antigen-specific T cells. There is growing genetic and clinical evidence that specific
      cytokine pathways are dysregulated. Monogenic defects in the IL-1 pathway cause cryopyrin
      associated periodic syndromes (CAPS) and deficiency of the IL-1 receptor antagonist (DIRA),
      the latter is caused by mutations affecting the IL-1-receptor antagonist gene (IL1RN). Both
      disorders respond with complete resolution of the inflammatory response to treatment with
      the short acting IL-1 blocking agent anakinra. This exploratory study aims to examine the
      utility of the long acting IL-1 inhibitor rilonacept (rilonacept; Regeneron Pharmaceuticals,
      Inc.)

      This pilot study is designed to address: 1) the utility and dosage of rilonacept needed to
      achieve inflammatory remission in children with DIRA who have shown a response to treatment
      with anakinra [Kineret[registered]]; and 2) to evaluate the safety and pharmacokinetics in
      young children on rilonacept.

      Rilonacept is a recombinant fusion protein with picomolar affinity for IL-1 and a half-life
      of approximately 7.5 days in humans. It is approved by the Food and Drug Administration
      (FDA) for the treatment of adults and children 12 years of age and older with
      Cryopyrin-Associated Periodic Syndromes (CAPS), and was tested in the clinically milder
      forms of CAPS including Familial Cold Autoinflammatory Syndrome (FCAS) and Muckle-Wells
      Syndrome (MWS).

      In this study, clinical, and laboratory parameters will initially be measured at baseline
      following a withdrawal of anakinra for 24 hours. Subjects will receive a course of therapy
      with rilonacept that is predicted to induce inflammatory remission. Clinical and laboratory
      measures of inflammation will be assessed; rilonacept dose escalation will be implemented as
      necessary to achieve clinical and laboratory remission. Subjects will remain on study for 12
      months and primary end point will be evaluated at 6 months.

      Those subjects who complete the 1-year treatment period and maintain improved clinical and
      laboratory parameters compared to baseline values, may continue to receive study medication
      at their current dose. Principal investigator will help to obtain insurance coverage for
      rilonacept for their continued treatment, and will discuss with Regeneron Pharmaceuticals,
      Inc. for additional supplies of rilonacept for these subjects.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the ability of rilonacept administration to achieve/maintain inflammatory remission in patients with DIRA who have shown a response to treatment with Anakinra [Kineret].</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the ability of rilonacept to prevent new organ damage in patients with DIRA who have shown a response to treatment with Anakinra [Kineret], and in patients with DIRA treatment na(SqrRoot) ve.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the safety of rilonacept in subjects with DIRA</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the safety and pharmacokinetics in young children on Rilonacept.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate bone mineralization in patients with DIRA</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate health-related quality of life in children and adolescents with DIRA</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>DIRA</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rilonacept</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA

               1. Male or female pediatric and adult subjects with mutation positive IL1RN
                  indicating DIRA. For the first five patients enrolled, they must have been on a
                  stable dose of anakinra during the 2-week period prior to screening visit. If
                  the subject is on other medications such as NSAIDs, methotrexate and/or oral
                  steroids, it is a requirement that these doses have been stable during the
                  2-week period prior to screening visit.

               2. Subjects greater or equal to 3 months of age (however the first 5 patients
                  enrolled will be over 2 years of age). Subjects 3 months old or older will be
                  enrolled after SMC data review of the first 5 enrolled patients.

               3. Participation in NIH study #03-AR-0173 (   Studies of the Natural History,
                  Pathogenesis and Outcome of Autoinflammatory Diseases (NOMID/CAPS, DIRA, CRMO,
                  Still   s Disease, Behcet   s Disease, and other Undifferentiated
                  Autoinflammatory Diseases   )

               4. Subjects currently treated with anakinra may be enrolled in this study even
                  though their DIRA may be quiescent. For these subjects, a history of active DIRA
                  prior to treatment with anakinra will be sufficient. Subjects will not take
                  anakinra 24 hours before initiation of drug treatment. Treatment naive patients
                  will also be enrolled after SMC data review of the first 5 enrolled patients.

               5. Females of childbearing potential (young women who have had at least one
                  menstrual period regardless of age) must have a negative serum pregnancy test at
                  screening and a urine pregnancy test prior to administration of study
                  medication.

               6. Females of childbearing age and men able to father a child and who are sexually
                  active, who agree to use two forms of effective birth control, including
                  abstinence.

               7. Negative Purified Protein Derivative (PPD) test using 5 T.U. intradermal testing
                  or the QuantiFERON(SqrRoot)  - TB Gold test per the Centers for Disease Control
                  and Prevention (CDC) guidelines, and no evidence of active tuberculosis (TB) on
                  chest X-ray.

                  Subjects with latent TB (positive PPD or QuantiFERON - TB Gold test) currently
                  treated with adequate therapy for at least one month prior to first dose of
                  study medication may be included. Full prophylaxis regimens will be continued
                  while on the study.

                  Subjects who have had active TB in the past with documentation of adequate
                  treatment may be included with strict clinical and radiological follow-up as per
                  current guidelines.

                  The Infectious diseases service will be consulted regarding all patients with
                  evidence of TB infection (latent or active, current or history) prior to
                  enrollment, and as appropriate during the study.

                  Subjects who have been BCG-vaccinated will also be tested. Interpretation of PPD
                  and QuantiFERON - TB Gold test in BCG recipients will be the same as for
                  subjects who have not received BCG vaccine.

                  Guardian/parent able to understand, and complete study-related questionnaires.

                  Guardian/parent able and willing to give informed consent and abide with the
                  study procedures.

                  EXCLUSION CRITERIA

               1. Treatment receiving a live virus vaccine (such as the measles, mumps, and
                  rubella vaccine) during the 3 months prior to baseline visit. No live vaccines
                  will be allowed throughout the course of this study.

               2. Presence of active infections or a history of pulmonary TB infection without
                  documented adequate therapy. Subjects with current active TB, or recent close
                  exposure to an individual with active TB, are excluded from the study.
                  Exceptions include patients with latent TB treated with adequate therapy for at
                  least one month prior to the first dose of study medication, and patients with
                  history of TB with documentation of adequate treatment.

               3. Positive test for, or prior history of, HIV, or Hepatitis B or C.

               4. History of malignancy. Subjects deemed cured of superficial malignancies such as
                  cutaneous basal or squamous cell carcinomas, or in situ cervical cancer may be
                  enrolled.

               5. Known hypersensitivity to Chinese Hamster Ovary cell-derived biological or any
                  components of rilonacept.

               6. Presence of any additional rheumatic disease or significant systemic disease.
                  For example, major chronic infectious/ inflammatory/ immunologic disease (such
                  as inflammatory bowel disease, psoriatic arthritis, spondyloarthropathy, SLE in
                  addition to autoinflammatory disease).

               7. Presence of any of the following laboratory abnormalities at enrollment visit:

                  creatinine greater than 1.5xULN

                  WBC less than 3.0x103/mm3

                  ANC less than 800 cells/mL

                  platelet count less than 150,000 mm3

                  ALT or AST greater than 2.0x ULN.

               8. Lactating, breastfeeding or pregnant females.

               9. Enrollment in any other investigational treatment study or use of an
                  investigational agent, or has not yet completed at least 4 weeks or 5
                  half-lives, whichever is longer, since ending another investigational device or
                  drug trial.

              10. Subjects for whom there is concern about compliance with the protocol
                  procedures.

              11. Presence of other severe acute or chronic medical or psychiatric condition, or
                  significant laboratory abnormality requiring further investigation that may
                  cause undue risk for the subject   s safety, inhibit protocol participation, or
                  interfere with interpretation of study results, and in the judgment of the
                  Investigator would make the subject inappropriate for entry into this study.

              12. Subjects who have received a DMARDs (except methotrexate) and or TNFblocking
                  agent within 4 half-lives prior to study entry.

              13. Men able to father a child and who are sexually active, who do not agree to use
                  2 form of effective birth control, including abstinence during the duration of
                  the study an for at least 28 days following the last dose of rilonacept.

              14. Females of childbearing potential (woman greater than 12 or who have had at
                  least 1 menstrual period regardless of age) who are sexually active and who do
                  not agree to use 2 effective methods of birth control, including abstinence
                  during the duration of the study an for at least 28 days following the last dose
                  of rilonacept.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gina A Montealegre Sanchez, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nicole Plass, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-2237</phone>
    <email>plassn@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Gina A Montealegre Sanchez, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-5132</phone>
    <email>montealegrega@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-AR-0086.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Feldmann J, Prieur AM, Quartier P, Berquin P, Certain S, Cortis E, Teillac-Hamel D, Fischer A, de Saint Basile G. Chronic infantile neurological cutaneous and articular syndrome is caused by mutations in CIAS1, a gene highly expressed in polymorphonuclear cells and chondrocytes. Am J Hum Genet. 2002 Jul;71(1):198-203. Epub 2002 May 24.</citation>
    <PMID>12032915</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goldbach-Mansky R, Dailey NJ, Canna SW, Gelabert A, Jones J, Rubin BI, Kim HJ, Brewer C, Zalewski C, Wiggs E, Hill S, Turner ML, Karp BI, Aksentijevich I, Pucino F, Penzak SR, Haverkamp MH, Stein L, Adams BS, Moore TL, Fuhlbrigge RC, Shaham B, Jarvis JN, O'Neil K, Vehe RK, Beitz LO, Gardner G, Hannan WP, Warren RW, Horn W, Cole JL, Paul SM, Hawkins PN, Pham TH, Snyder C, Wesley RA, Hoffmann SC, Holland SM, Butman JA, Kastner DL. Neonatal-onset multisystem inflammatory disease responsive to interleukin-1beta inhibition. N Engl J Med. 2006 Aug 10;355(6):581-92.</citation>
    <PMID>16899778</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goldbach-Mansky R, Shroff SD, Wilson M, Snyder C, Plehn S, Barham B, Pham TH, Pucino F, Wesley RA, Papadopoulos JH, Weinstein SP, Mellis SJ, Kastner DL. A pilot study to evaluate the safety and efficacy of the long-acting interleukin-1 inhibitor rilonacept (interleukin-1 trap) in patients with familial cold autoinflammatory syndrome. Arthritis Rheum. 2008 Aug;58(8):2432-42.</citation>
    <PMID>18668591</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 1, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 27, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>DIRA</keyword>
  <keyword>Clinical Trial</keyword>
  <keyword>IL-1</keyword>
  <keyword>Autoinflammatory Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Rilonacept</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hereditary Autoinflammatory Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Interleukin 1 Receptor Antagonist Protein</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
