<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="25181">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02057614</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TD201 - CS01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02057614</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Topical Sirolimus for Plantar Keratoderma in Adults With Pachyonychia Congenita (PC)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Randomized, Double-Blind, Split-Body, Placebo-Controlled Evaluation of the Safety and Efficacy of Topical Sirolimus 1% (TD201) for Plantar Keratoderma in Adults With Pachyonychia Congenita</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>TransDerm, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pachyonychia Congenita Project</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to assess the safety of topical sirolimus (TD201) 1%
      for plantar keratoderma for the treatment of pachyonychia congenita. This study would also
      like to assess the potential of sirolimus (TD201) to improve the clinical severity of
      plantar keratoderma, including pain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sirolimus Serum levels</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>For the first 12 weeks of the study, sirolimus serum levels will be measured at monthly intervals (i.e., every 4 weeks) during the treatment phases of the study</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum Sirolimus Levels</measure>
    <time_frame>17-37 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>For the last two visits (weeks 17-37), sirolimus serum levels will be measured at monthly intervals during the treatment phases of the study</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Pachyonychia Congenita</condition>
  <condition>Plantar Keratoderma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Topical Sirolimus</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Topical Sirolimus</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Topical Sirolimus</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects must

               1. Be capable of understanding the purpose and risks of the study and sign a
                  written Informed Consent Form (ICF)

               2. Be male or female ≥ 16 years of age at the time of the screening visit

               3. Have a confirmed diagnosis of PC by genotyping (e.g., familial) and clinically
                  correlated painful keratoderma.

               4. Have roughly symmetrical calluses of similar severity on the plantar surface of
                  both feet

               5. Weigh at least 40 kg (88.2 lbs.)

               6. Have laboratory values within the range of normal

               7. Women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test on Day
                  -14 and a negative urine pregnancy test within 48 hours prior to subject's
                  assignment to study treatment at the baseline visit (Visit 1, Week 1, Day 1).
                  All female subjects (including those with tubal ligations) will be considered to
                  be of childbearing potential unless one or more of the following criteria are
                  met:

                    -  Over age  60

                    -  Amenorrheic for at least 2 years if age 45-60 years

                    -  Have had a hysterectomy and/or bilateral oophorectomy

               8. Subjects with reproductive potential and who are sexually active must agree to
                  use double-barrier contraception methods BEFORE beginning the study and for the
                  duration of the study (37 weeks) or for 12 weeks after the last dose if study
                  drug is discontinued prematurely

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A Subject with any of the following criteria is not eligible for inclusion in this
             study:

               1. Use of other investigational drugs within 30 days of the screening visit (for
                  dermatologic drugs see below) and/or has not recovered from any side effects of
                  prior investigational drugs or procedure in the affected area (e.g., a biopsy)

               2. Significant condition in the dermatologic treatment area such as trauma, which
                  could impair evaluation for the treatment of PC or nonhealing chronic wound,

               3. History of hypersensitivity to any of the study drugs or to drugs of similar
                  chemical classes or history of serious allergic reaction; known allergy to
                  sirolimus

               4. Prior history of grafting surgeries or other surgeries in the dermatologic
                  treatment area

               5. Prior history of liver disease

               6. Poorly controlled hyperlipidemia

               7. Pregnant or nursing (lactating) female, or a positive serum pregnancy test on
                  Day -14 and/or a positive urine pregnancy test within 48 hours of initiation of
                  treatment

               8. Active infection (i.e. bacterial, viral, parasitic or fungal) either
                  systemically or local near the site of treatment requiring chronic or prolonged
                  use of antimicrobial agents

               9. Known immunodeficiency including:

                    1. Hepatitis A

                    2. Hepatitis B

                    3. Hepatitis C

                    4. Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV)

              10. Serious known concurrent medical illness or infection, or any medical condition
                  that could potentially present a safety risk and/or prevent compliance with the
                  requirements of the protocol

              11. Any other severe, acute or chronic medical or psychiatric condition (including
                  current or history of substance abuse) or clinical laboratory abnormalities

              12. Current malignancy or a history of malignancy (within the previous 5 years)

              13. Myocardial infarction within 6 months prior to the baseline visit (Visit 1) or
                  history of cardiac dysrhythmia E2. Prior and Current Treatment

              14. Unable to be discontinued from drugs known to either be inducers or inhibitors
                  (moderate or strong) of cytochrome P450 isoenzymes

              15. Unable to be discontinued from drugs known to be strong or moderate
                  P-glycoprotein (P-gp) inhibitors within 7 days prior to the Screening Visit

              16. Use of topical therapies on the dermatologic treatment area within 6 weeks prior
                  to Screening visit (Day -14): pulsed dye laser, carbon dioxide laser, surgeries
                  within the treatment area, topical sirolimus, topical retinoids, topical
                  steroids or other topical prescription or over the counter medications

              17. Use of systemic drug therapies within 7 days prior to Screening Visit at Day
                  -14: e.g., cytotoxic drugs, immunomodulators or immunosuppressants, or
                  diltiazem, erythromycin, all azole antifungals, rifampin, nicardipine, verapamil
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joyce Teng, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>R Adeduntan</last_name>
      <phone>650-721-7163</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joyce Teng, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 6, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 29, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Nails, Malformed</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pachyonychia Congenita</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Sirolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
