<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="75519">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01854944</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>331-09-219</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01854944</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PET Trial to Assess the Receptor Occupancy of Brexpiprazole in Adult Subjects With Schizophrenia</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Otsuka Pharmaceutical Development &amp; Commercialization, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Otsuka Pharmaceutical Development &amp; Commercialization, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine how low and high does of brexpiprazole binds to
      certain receptors in the brain.  This will be determined by PET scans taken pre-dose and
      post-dose.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics/Dynamics Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>D2/D3 receptor occupancy</measure>
    <time_frame>4 hours post-last dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>-D2/D3 receptor occupancy (high and low doses)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>5-HT1A receptor occupancy</measure>
    <time_frame>4 hours post-last dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>-5-HT1A receptor occupancy (high dose only)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>5-HT2A receptor occupancy</measure>
    <time_frame>4 hours post-last dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>-5-HT2A receptor occupancy (high and low doses)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occupancy at SERT</measure>
    <time_frame>4 hours post-last dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>-Occupancy at SERT (high dose only)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the concentration-time curve during a dosing interval at steady-state</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed for the duration of treatment, an expected 10 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>AUC during a dosing interval at steady-state</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale, summary statistics of change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed at baseline, day 6 and discharge, an expected 12 day duration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The PANSS consists of 3 subscales containing a total of 30 symptom constructs.
- For each symptom construct, severity is rated on a 7-point scale, with a score of 1 indicating the absence of symptoms and a score of 7 indicating extremely severe symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum (peak) plasma Concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed for the duration of treatment, an expected 10 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>(Cmax)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent clearance of drug from plasma after extravascular administration</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed for the duration of treatment, an expected 10 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>CL/F; brexpiprazole only</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Maximum (peak) plasma concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed for the duration of treatment, an expected 10 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Abnormal Involuntary Movement Scale summary statistics of change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed at baseline, day 6 and discharge, an expected 12 day duration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The AIMS assessment consists of 10 items describing symptoms of dyskinesia that will be observed unobtrusively while the subject is at rest.
Facial and oral movements (items 1 through 4)
Extremity movements (items 5 and 6)
Trunk movements (item 7) will be observed
Each item will be rated on a 5-point scale, with a score of zero representing absence of symptoms (for item 10, no awareness), and a score of 4 indicating a severe condition (for item 10, awareness, severe distress)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Simpson-Angus Scale (SAS) summary statistics of change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed at baseline, day 6 and discharge, an expected 12 day duration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The SAS consists of a list of 10 symptoms of parkinsonism (gait, arm, dropping, shoulder shaking, elbow rigidity, wrist rigidity, head rotation, glabella tap, tremor, salivation, and akathisia).  Each item will be rated on a 5-point scale, with a score of 1 representing absences of symptoms, and a score of 5 representing a severe condition. The SAS Total Score is the sum of the scores for all 10 items.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Barnes Akathisia Rating Scale summary statistics of change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed at baseline, day 6 and discharge, an expected 12 day duration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The BARS consists of 4 items related to akathisia:
objective observation of akathisia by the investigator
subjective feelings of restlessness by the subject
subjective distress due to akathisia
global clinical assessment of akathisia.
The first 3 items will be rated on a 4-point scale, with a score of zero representing absence of symptoms and a score of 3 representing a severe condition. The global clinical evaluations will be made on a 6-point scale, with a score of zero representing absence of symptoms and a score of 5 representing severe akathisia. To complete this scale, subjects will be observed while they are seated and standing for a minimum of 2 minutes in each position. Symptoms observed in other situations (eg, while engaged in neutral conversations or engaged in activity on the ward) may also be rated. Subjective phenomena are to be elicited by direct questioning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impression-Severity scale, summary statistics of change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed at baseline, day 6 and discharge, an expected 12 day duration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess CGI-S, the rater or investigator will answer the following question:
&quot;Considering your total clinical experience with this particular population, how mentally ill is the subject at this time?&quot; Response choices include: 0 = not assessed; 1 = normal, not at all ill; 2 = borderline mentally ill; 3 = mildly ill; 4 = moderately ill; 5 = markedly ill; 6 = severely ill; and 7 = among the most extremely ill subjects.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impression-Improvement scale, summary statistics of change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed at baseline, day 6 and discharge, an expected 12 day duration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The rater or investigator will rate the subject's total improvement whether or not it is due entirely to drug treatment. Response choices include: 0 = not assessed,1 = very much improved, 2 = much improved, 3 = minimally improved, 4 = no change, 5 = minimally worse, 6 = much worse, and 7 = very much worse.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed at screening, baseline, day 6 and discharge, a duration of  13 to 56 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The C-SSRS captures the occurrence, severity, and frequency of suicide-related thoughts and behaviors during the assessment period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Brexpiprazole 1mg to 4mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Three cohorts of subjects will be evaluated:
- Cohorts 1 and 3 will receive high doses of brexpiprazole, and Cohort 2 will receive low doses of brexpiprazole.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Brexpiprazole 1mg to 4mg</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Brexpiprazole 1mg to 4mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Brexpiprazole</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  A diagnosis of Schizophrenia.

          -  Ability to provide written informed consent.

          -  Ability to understand the protocol and meet the protocol requirements.

          -  Must be in good physical health determined by ECG and  laboratory values, medical
             history and physical examinations.

          -  Has stable disease, defined as meeting all of the following criteria: A CGI-S score
             &lt;= 4 (moderately ill); A PANSS total score &lt;= 60; A score of &lt;= 4 (moderate) on any
             of the following PANSS items: (P7 (hostility); G8 (uncooperativeness)).

          -  Body mass index of 19 to 35 kg/m2

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Sexually active males and females of childbearing potential who are not practicing
             double-barrier birth control, or who will not remain abstinent, during the trial and
             for 30 days following the last dose of trial medication.  If employing birth control,
             2 of the following precautions must be used:  vasectomy, partner who uses hormonal
             contraception, tubal ligation, vaginal diaphragm, nonhormonal intrauterine device,
             condom, or sponge with spermicide.

          -  Females who are pregnant or lactating.  A negative serum pregnancy test must be
             confirmed prior to the first dose of trial medication for all female subjects.

          -  Subjects presenting with a first episode of schizophrenia based on the clinical
             judgment of the investigator.

          -  Subjects who have received continuous medication therapy to treat schizophrenia for
             less than 6 months prior to the drug-free interval.

          -  Subjects with schizophrenia who are considered resistant/refractory to antipsychotic
             treatment by history, who have a history of failure to clozapine, or who are
             responsive only to clozapine treatment.

          -  Subjects with a current DSM-IV-TR Axis I diagnosis other than schizophrenia including
             MDD, bipolar disorder, delirium, dementia, amnestic, or other cognitive disorders or
             subjects with borderline, paranoid, histrionic, schizotypal, schizoid, or antisocial
             personality disorder.

          -  Subjects who, in the opinion of the investigator, cannot be rated reliably on the
             battery of movement rating scales required by the protocol.

          -  Subjects with a significant risk of violent behavior, a significant risk of
             committing suicide based on history or investigator's judgment, or who have attempted
             suicide within 2 years of cohort assignment.

          -  Subjects with clinically significant tardive dyskinesia at enrollment.

          -  Subjects who experience clinical deterioration during the drug-free interval, such
             that they require prohibited rescue therapy, will not meet the trial criteria and
             will be replaced.

          -  Subjects who experienced an acute exacerbation requiring hospitalization within 3
             months prior to the Screening Visit or between the Screening and Baseline Visits.

          -  Subjects who experienced an acute exacerbation requiring change in antipsychotic
             medication (with reference to drug or dose) within the last 4 weeks prior to
             baseline.

          -  Subjects who have a history of myocardial infarction, hypertension, or diabetes or
             who have evidence of other medical conditions that would expose them to an undue risk
             of a significant AE or interfere with assessments of safety or efficacy during the
             course of the trial, including, but not limited to, hepatic, renal, respiratory,
             cardiovascular, endocrine, neurologic, hematologic, or immunologic disease.  The
             medical monitor must be contacted to discuss any such condition prior to cohort
             assignment.

          -  Subjects who have any of the following neurologic diagnoses, whether under treatment
             or not, whether stable or not:  migraine, epilepsy, Parkinson's disease, Alzheimer's
             disease, multiple sclerosis, residual of stroke, transient cerebral ischemic attacks,
             cerebral palsy, or any condition that requires intermittent or maintenance treatment
             or which is manifested by any abnormality on neurologic examination.  A subject with
             tardive dyskinesia or other nonclinically significant symptoms of EPS due solely to
             the current or prior use of antipsychotic medications is not excluded by this
             criterion.  Single-nerve peripheral palsies are also not excluded by this criterion:
             eg, Bell's palsy or radial-nerve palsy or fixed residuals from traumatic injury.

        History of or current hepatitis or acquired immunodeficiency syndrome or carriers of HBsAg
        and/or anti-HCV or HIV antibodies.

          -  Subjects with a history of thyroid pathology (unless the condition has been
             stabilized with medications for at least the past 3 months) and/or abnormal thyroid
             laboratory results.

          -  Subjects with a history of neuroleptic malignant syndrome.

          -  Subjects with a history of seizure disorder.

          -  Subjects who meet DSM-IV-TR criteria for substance dependence within 6 months prior
             to cohort assignment (excluding caffeine and nicotine), including alcohol and
             benzodiazepines, and/or a positive alcohol (breath or urine) test or a positive urine
             screen for drugs of abuse.  (In the case where a subject had a positive screen for
             stimulants and/or marijuana and was therefore excluded, the medical monitor should be
             contacted to determine if rescreening is an option.)

          -  Subjects who had any major surgery, any blood transfusion, or donated blood or plasma
             within 30 days prior to enrollment.

          -  The following laboratory test, vital sign, and ECG results are exclusionary:

               1. Platelets &lt;= 75,000/mm3

               2. Hemoglobin &lt;= 9 g/dL

               3. Neutrophils, absolute &lt;= 1000/mm3

               4. AST &gt; 2 times upper limit of normal

               5. ALT &gt; 2 times upper limit of normal

               6. Creatinine &gt;= 2 mg/dL

          -  Subjects with electrolytes outside of the normal range will not be enrolled in the
             trial without prior review and approval from the medical monitor.

          -  Subjects who have sitting (performed first) or supine blood pressure, after resting
             for &gt;= 3 minutes, higher than 140/90 mmHg or lower than 100/50 mmHg.  Upon standing
             from the supine position, subjects who have a fall in systolic blood pressure &gt;= 20
             mmHg or a fall in diastolic blood pressure &gt;= 10 mm Hg after 1 to 3 minutes in the
             standing position.  (Any repeated out-of-range values not deemed clinically
             significant need to be discussed with the medical monitor to determine eligibility.)

          -  Subjects who have a supine pulse rate, after resting for &gt;= 3 minutes, outside the
             range of 40 to 90 bpm.

          -  Subjects with any ECG abnormality at Screening, prior to dosing, will be excluded,
             including but not limited to, a PR interval &gt; 220 msec, QRS interval &gt; 110 msec, QTc
             &gt; 450 msec, QTcF &gt; 450 msec, QTcB &gt; 450 msec or the increase in QTcB is considered
             significant by the investigator, abnormal U waves, or other minor ST-T wave changes
             which are considered clinically significant.

          -  Prohibited concomitant medications/therapies used for the following time period prior
             to Day −1 and for the duration of the trial include:

          -  Antipsychotics

               1. Use of oral antipsychotics within 21 days prior to Day −1;

               2. Use of long-acting injectable antipsychotics within 6 months.

          -  Anxiolytics and Sleep Aids

             1) Regular use of benzodiazepines for 2 weeks (lorazepam [&lt;= 6 mg daily up to 48
             hours prior to PK and PD assessments] can be used as rescue therapy during the 21
             days prior to Day −1 and [&lt;= 4 mg daily up to 48 hours prior to PK and PD assessments
             or up to 24 hours prior to the completion of the EPS rating scales or C-SSRS] during
             the treatment period).

          -  Mood Stabilizers

             1) Use of lamotrigine within 14 days.

          -  Selective Serotonin Reuptake Inhibitors

               1. Use of Prozac within 28 days;

               2. Use of Paxil within 14 days;

               3. Use of Zoloft, Luvox, or Celexa within 7 days.

          -  Serotonin and Norepinephrine Reuptake Inhibitors

               1. Use of Effexor within 3 days;

               2. Use of duloxetine within 14 days.

          -  Other

               1. Use of Symbyax within 28 days;

               2. Use of CYP2D6 or CYP3A4 inhibitors or CYP3A4 inducers within 14 days;

               3. Use of electroconvulsive therapy within 2 months.

          -  Use and discontinuation of any other therapy (prescription medication, over-the
             counter, herbal medication, or vitamins) not listed above must be approved by the
             sponsor and the medical monitor.

          -  Subjects who received brexpiprazole in a prior clinical trial.

          -  Subjects who received any investigational agent in a clinical trial within 90 days
             prior to Screening.

          -  Consumption of alcohol and/or food and beverages containing methylxanthines,
             grapefruit, grapefruit juice, Seville oranges, or Seville orange juice within 72
             hours prior to dosing and for the duration of the trial.

          -  Subjects who are heavy smokers (ie, &gt; 21 cigarettes per day). Other

          -  Prisoners or subjects who are compulsorily detained (involuntarily incarcerated) for
             treatment of either a psychiatric or physical (eg, infectious disease) illness must
             not be enrolled into this trial.

          -  Subjects with a history of allergy to more than one class of medications.

          -  Any subject who, in the opinion of the investigator, should not participate in the
             trial.

          -  A history of difficulty in donating blood.

          -  Exposure to any substances known to stimulate hepatic microsomal enzymes within 30
             days prior to Screening through the end of the trial (eg, occupational exposure to
             pesticides, organic solvents).

          -  Additionally, subjects who meet the following imaging exclusion criteria will not be
             included in this trial:

               1. Subjects who suffer from claustrophobia.

               2. Subjects with MRI-incompatible implants and other contraindications for MRI,
                  such as pacemaker, artificial joints, nonremovable body piercings, tattoos
                  larger than 1 cm in diameter, metal fragments, claustrophobia, etc.

               3. Subjects who have received a diagnostic or therapeutic radiopharmaceutical
                  within 7 days prior to participation in this trial.

               4. Participation in other research trials involving ionizing radiation within 1
                  year of the PET scans that would cause the subject to exceed the yearly dose
                  limits for normal subjects.

               5. Subjects with history of IV drug use which would prevent venous access for PET
                  tracer injection.

               6. Severe motor problems that prevent the subject from lying still for PET and MRI.

               7. Subjects who complain of chronic pain (eg, as the result of rheumatoid
                  arthritis).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Elizabeth Hackett, RT(N)(CT)</last_name>
    <phone>212-543-1148</phone>
    <email>eeh2001@columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elizabeth Hackett, RT(N)(CT)</last_name>
      <phone>212-543-1148</phone>
      <email>eeh2001@columbia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ragy R Girgis, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 20, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 7, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
