<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="8394">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02104804</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>D1680C00010</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2014L00001</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02104804</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Saxagliptin Added to Insulin Monotherapy or to Insulin Combined With Metformin in Chinese Subjects With Type 2 Diabetes Who Have Inadequate Glycaemic Control</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multicenter, Randomized, Double-Blind, Phase 3b Trial to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Saxagliptin Added to Insulin Monotherapy or to Insulin in Combination With Metformin in Chinese Subjects in China With Type 2 Diabetes Who Have Inadequate Glycaemic Control on Insulin Alone or on Insulin in Combination With Metformin</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bristol-Myers Squibb</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AstraZeneca</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>China: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A Multicenter, Randomized, Double-Blind, Phase 3b Trial to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety
      of Saxagliptin Added to Insulin Monotherapy or to Insulin in Combination with Metformin in
      Chinese Subjects in China with Type 2 Diabetes Who Have Inadequate Glycaemic Control on
      Insulin Alone or on Insulin in Combination with Metformin
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Design: Randomized, prospective, double-blind, two-arm, parallel group, multi-center
      trial.

      Target Subject Population: Subjects aged ≥18 who have type 2 diabetes (HbA1c of ≥7.5% and
      ≤11.0% and FPG&lt;270 mg/dL (15 mmol/L)) on stable baseline therapy (insulin alone or insulin
      combined with metformin, with insulin at doses of ≥20 and ≤150 units per day total) for at
      least eight weeks at the time of screening. Insulin may be long-acting, intermediate-acting,
      or pre-mixed. 444 patients are planned to be randomized.

      Investigational Product, Dosage and Mode of administration: Active treatment will comprise
      Saxagliptin 5 mg tablets once daily.

      Comparator, Dosage and Mode of administration: Matching placebo tablets will be used as
      comparator.

      Duration of Treatment: The study is divided to a single blind placebo lead in period of 8
      weeks and a double-blind treatment phase of 24 weeks. Patients will be rescued based on high
      FPG values.

      Statistical Methods: The analysis of the primary endpoint of change from baseline to week 24
      of treatment in HbA1c will consist of an analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) model with
      treatment group and metformin use at enrolment as fixed effects and baseline HbA1c value as
      a covariate. The analysis will be performed on the Full analysis Set (FAS) consisting of
      randomised subjects who received at least 1 randomised investigational product dose and had
      at least 1 non-missing baseline and 1 post-baseline efficacy assessment. Within the
      framework of the ANCOVA model, point estimates and two-sided 95% confidence intervals (CI)
      for the mean change within each treatment group as well as for the difference in mean change
      between treatment groups will be calculated.

      The Per Protocol (PP) analysis set is a subset of the full analysis set and will consist of
      subjects who do not deviate from the terms of the protocol which may affect the study
      outcome significantly as specified in the pre-defined protocol deviation list prior to
      unblinding the study. All decisions to exclude subjects from the primary data set will be
      made prior to the unblinding of the study. The primary efficacy endpoint of change from
      baseline in HbA1c, demographics, and baseline diabetes related characteristics and all
      secondary efficacy endpoints are to be analyzed using the PP Data Set. The analyses of PPG
      AUC, 120 minute PPG, FPG and mean total daily dose of insulin will also be done on the FAS
      and use a similar ANCOVA model as described above. Subjects achieving a therapeutic
      glycaemic response (A1C &lt;7%) will be analyzed using a Fisher's exact test and will include
      exact 95% confidence intervals. The FPG analyses will utilize the mean of the latest two FPG
      values prior to randomization as the baseline value. The endpoint for the FPG analysis will
      be the mean of the week 20 and week 24 FPG values. All analyses (except the analysis of mean
      total daily dose of insulin) will utilize only observations at visits prior to rescue or
      where the subject's mean total daily dose of insulin has not increased by &gt;10% from
      baseline. If an observation at week 24 is missing or does not meet these criteria, the
      latest post-baseline value that does will be carried forward (LOCF). The analysis of mean
      total daily dose of insulin will utilize the latest, non-missing, post-baseline value
      regardless of rescue. Multiplicity for the primary and secondary endpoints will be
      controlled via a hierarchical testing procedure that utilizes the full alpha (0.05) for each
      test. The sequence of testing will be: 1. Change from baseline in HbA1c at Week 24. 2.
      Change from baseline in PPG AUC at Week 24.3. Change from baseline in 120 minute PPG at Week
      24. 4. Proportion of subjects achieving HbA1c &lt;7.0% at Week 24. 5. Change from baseline in
      FPG to the mean at Week 20 and Week 24. 6. Change from baseline in MTDDI at Week 24.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The change in glycosylated hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c) from baseline to Week 24 (prior to rescue/censoring)</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to week 24 (Prior to rescue/censoring)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary efficacy variable is the change in HbA1c from baseline to Week 24 (prior to rescue/censoring)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The change from baseline to Week 24 (prior to rescue/censoring) in the postprandial plasma glucose (PPG) area under the curve (AUC) from 0 to 180 minutes in response to a meal tolerance test</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to week 24 (Prior to rescue/censoring)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change from baseline in PPG AUC at Week 24 (prior to resuce/censoring)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The change from baseline to Week 24 (prior to rescue/censoring) in 120-minute postprandial plasma glucose (PPG) in response to a meal tolerance test</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to week 24 (Prior to rescue/censoring)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change from baseline in 120 minute PPG at Week 24 (prior to resuce/censoring)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of subjects achieving a therapeutic glycaemic response at Week 24 (prior to rescue/censoring) defined as HbA1C &lt;7%</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to week 24 (Prior to rescue/censoring)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of subjects achieving HbA1c &lt; 7% at Week 24 (prior to resuce/censoring)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The change from baseline to the mean of Weeks 20 and 24 (prior to rescue/censoring) in fasting plasma glucose (FPG)</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to Week 20 and Week 24 (prior to rescue/censoring)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in FPG from baseline to the mean of Week 20 and Week 24 (prior to rescue/censoring)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The change in mean total daily dose of insulin (MTDDI) from baseline to Week 24 (regardless of rescue/censoring)</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to week 24 (regardless of rescue/censoring)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in MTDDI from baseline to Week 24</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of AE and of marked abnormalities in clinical lab tests in all subjects</measure>
    <time_frame>From screening to Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The incidence of adverse events and of marked abnormalities in clinical laboratory tests in all subjects throughout the study</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">740</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Saxagliptin 5mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Saxagliptin 5mg, administered to subjects with Type 2 diabetes inadequately controlled with insulin alone or with insulin plus metformin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo administered to subjects with Type 2 diabetes inadequately controlled with insulin alone or with insulin plus metformin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saxagliptin 5mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Saxagliptin 5mg (plus stable insulin dose), given orally once daily (24 weeks); subjects stratified by use of stable metformin dose; flexible insulin dose (as needed for rescue).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Saxagliptin 5mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Insulin: intermediate-acting or basal or premixed ( include short- or rapid-acting insulin as one component). ≥20 unit/day, ≤150 units/day</other_name>
    <other_name>Metformin: Glucophage, 500-2500mg/day</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo for Saxagliptin</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo tablets (plus stable insulin dose), given orally once daily (24 weeks); subjects stratified by use of stable metformin dose; flexible insulin dose (as needed for rescue).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Insulin: intermediate-acting or basal or premixed ( include short- or rapid-acting insulin as one component). ≥20 unit/day, ≤150 units/day</other_name>
    <other_name>Metformin: Glucophage, 500-2500mg/day</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Provision of informed consent before participating in the study.

          2. Diagnosed with type 2 diabetes.

          3. Inadequate glycemic control (screening: HbA1c ≥7.5% and ≤11.0% and FPG&lt;270 mg/dL
             (15mmol/L). At Day -4 visit, HbA1c ≥7.5% and ≤10.5%. and FPG&lt;270 mg/dL (15mmol/L)).

          4. On a stable dose of insulin for 8 weeks or longer prior to screening.

          5. If taking metformin, subjects should have been taking the same daily dose for 8 weeks
             or longer prior to screening.

          6. Insulin type should be intermediate-acting or long-acting (basal) or premixed
             (premixed formulation may include short- or rapid-acting insulin as one component).

          7. Body mass index ≤45 kg/m^2.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Women of childbearing potential unable or unwilling to use acceptable birth control.

          2. Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding.

          3. Symptoms of poorly controlled diabetes. including but not limited to, marked polyuria
             and polydipsia with greater than 10% weight loss during the last three months prior
             to screening or other signs and symptoms.

          4. Significant cardiovascular history defined as: myocardial infarction, coronary
             angioplasty or bypass graft, valvular disease or repair, unstable clinical
             significant arrhythmia, unstable angina pectoris, transient ischemic attack, or
             cerebrovascular accident.

          5. Congestive heart failure

          6. Chronic or repeated intermittent corticosteroid treatment (subjects receiving stable
             doses of replacement corticosteroid (except dexamethasone) therapy may be enrolled).

          7. History of unstable or rapidly progressing renal disease.

          8. History of alcohol or drug abuse within the previous year.

          9. Unstable major psychiatric disorders.

         10. History of hemoglobinopathies

         11. Immunocompromised status

         12. Severe liver disease.

         13. In subjects treated with insulin alone a calculated creatinine clearance &lt;50 ml/min.
             In patients treated with insulin in combination with metformin a calculated
             creatinine clearance &lt;60 ml/min or serum creatinine &gt; 1.5 mg/dL in males or &gt;
             1.4mg/dL in females.

         14. Anemia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Linong Ji, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>People's Hospital of Peking Universty</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rupesh Jagadish</last_name>
    <phone>0086 21 6030 2724</phone>
    <email>ClinicalTrialTransparency@astrazeneca.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fuzhou</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guangzhou</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ha'er bin</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ha'er bing</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hefei</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nanchang</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nanjing</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>ShiJiazhuang</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shiyan</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wen Zhou</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wuhan</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Suspended</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Drucker DJ. Dipeptidyl peptidase-4 inhibition and the treatment of type 2 diabetes: preclinical biology and mechanisms of action. Diabetes Care. 2007 Jun;30(6):1335-43. Epub 2007 Mar 2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17337495</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cockcroft DW, Gault MH. Prediction of creatinine clearance from serum creatinine. Nephron. 1976;16(1):31-41.</citation>
    <PMID>1244564</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fonseca V, Schweizer A, Albrecht D, Baron MA, Chang I, Dejager S. Addition of vildagliptin to insulin improves glycaemic control in type 2 diabetes. Diabetologia. 2007 Jun;50(6):1148-55. Epub 2007 Mar 27.</citation>
    <PMID>17387446</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pan CY, Yang W, Tou C, Gause-Nilsson I, Zhao J. Efficacy and safety of saxagliptin in drug-naïve Asian patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus: a randomized controlled trial. Diabetes Metab Res Rev. 2012 Mar;28(3):268-75. doi: 10.1002/dmrr.1306.</citation>
    <PMID>22081481</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Vilsbøll T, Rosenstock J, Yki-Järvinen H, Cefalu WT, Chen Y, Luo E, Musser B, Andryuk PJ, Ling Y, Kaufman KD, Amatruda JM, Engel SS, Katz L. Efficacy and safety of sitagliptin when added to insulin therapy in patients with type 2 diabetes. Diabetes Obes Metab. 2010 Feb;12(2):167-77. doi: 10.1111/j.1463-1326.2009.01173.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20092585</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Yang W, Pan CY, Tou C, Zhao J, Gause-Nilsson I. Efficacy and safety of saxagliptin added to metformin in Asian people with type 2 diabetes mellitus: a randomized controlled trial. Diabetes Res Clin Pract. 2011 Nov;94(2):217-24. doi: 10.1016/j.diabres.2011.07.035. Epub 2011 Aug 26.</citation>
    <PMID>21871686</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 12, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 2, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus, Insulin, Dipeptidyl-Peptidase 4 Inhibitors, Metformin,saxagliptin,Endocrine System Diseases</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Saxagliptin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insulin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dipeptidyl-Peptidase IV Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
