<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="58752">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01965834</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UMIAMI-20110069</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01965834</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 2 Fenofibrate in Patients With Relapsed/Refractory Multiple Myeloma</brief_title>
  <official_title>PHASE II STUDY TO EVALUATE FENOFIBRATE THERAPY IN PATIENTS WITH RELAPSED/REFRACTORY MULTIPLE MYELOMA WHO HAVE FAILED AT LEAST TWO PRIOR THERAPIES</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Miami Sylvester Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Miami Sylvester Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Multiple myeloma cells are dependent on calcium (Ca2+) for their function.  Specifically,
      Ca2+ is required for the function of the endoplasmic reticulum in which proteins, including
      immunoglobulins, are folded prior to their release from the cell. Multiple myeloma cells
      secrete large concentrations of immunoglobulins continuously and as result depend on
      mitochondria activity to replenish the Ca2+ levels in the endoplasmic reticulum as was shown
      in vitro in our lab.  Fenofibrate has been shown to inhibit mitochondrial function resulting
      in inhibition of protein folding in the endoplasmic reticulum of MM cells that leads to the
      induction of a stress signal known as the unfolded protein response and subsequently
      apoptosis.  The effective anti-myeloma concentrations for fenofibrate are attainable in the
      clinical setting as they are in the same range as the effective concentrations for
      anti-hyperlipidemic effect.  The investigators propose to evaluate fenofibrate therapy in
      multiple myeloma patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Patients Achieving Response to Fenofibrate Therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine response rate (Strict Complete Response (sCR), Complete response (CR), Very Good Partial Response (VgPR), and Partial Response (PR) as defined in section 9.2) in multiple myeloma patients receiving oral fenofibrate therapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Subjects Experiencing Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate safety and tolerability of fenofibrate therapy in patients with multiple myeloma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Subjects Achieving Progression-Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fenofibrate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fenofibrate at 160 mg orally daily, if creatinine clearance &gt;= 50 mL/min, or Fenofibrate at 54 mg orally daily, if creatinine clearance &lt; 50 mL/min. Upon screening, registration and enrollment, all subjects will receive fenofibrate 160 mg orally daily for at least 2 months and may continue receiving study medication for as long as in the opinion of the investigator there is clinical benefit in doing so. Patients with calculated creatinine clearance &lt; 50 mL/min will receive a reduced dose of 54 mg orally daily.  Fenofibrate should be taken daily at around the same time of day.  Patients will receive a diary to document administration.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fenofibrate</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Fenofibrate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fenofibric acid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histologically or cytologically confirmed multiple myeloma.

          -  Patients must have measurable disease and therefore must have at least one of the
             following:

               -  Serum M-protein ≥1 gm/dL (&gt;=10 gm/L)

               -  Urine M-protein ≥200 mg/24 hr

               -  Serum FLC assay: involved FLC &gt;=10 mg/dL (&gt;= 100 mg/L) provided serum FLC ratio
                  is abnormal.

          -  Patient must have relapsed/refractory multiple myeloma after at least 2 prior
             treatment regimens as per the International Uniform Response Criteria for Multiple
             Myeloma

          -  Male or female &gt;= 18 years of age.

          -  Life expectancy of &gt;= 6 months.

          -  ECOG performance status &lt; 2.

          -  Normal organ and marrow function as defined below:

               -  Absolute Neutrophil Count (ANC) &gt; 1,000/mm3

               -  Platelets &gt;= 75,000/mm3

               -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 8 g/dL

               -  Calculated serum creatinine (calculated by Cockroft-Gault method) &gt;= 30 mL/min

               -  AST(SGOT)/ALT(SGPT) =&lt; 2.5 X ULN

               -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 X ULN

          -  Patient must be at least 2 weeks from prior chemotherapy, radiation therapy,
             biological therapy, immunotherapy, major surgery and any other investigational
             anti-cancer therapy prior to the first dose of study drug.

          -  Patient has recovered from toxicities (&lt; Grade 2) and/or complications from prior
             therapy.

          -  Patient is able to swallow capsules and is able to take or tolerate oral medications
             on a continuous basis.

          -  Female patients of childbearing potential must be willing to use 2 adequate barrier
             methods of contraception to prevent pregnancy or agrees to abstain from heterosexual
             intercourse for at least 1 month before dosing, and while women are on study and for
             up to 12 weeks after last dose of study drug.  Adequate contraceptive methods include
             intrauterine device, diaphragm with spermicide, cervical cap with spermicide, or
             female condom with spermicide.  Spermicides alone are not an acceptable method of
             contraception.

          -  Male patients agree to have female partners of childbearing potential use 2 adequate
             barrier methods of contraception as described in Section 3.1.10.

          -  Female patients of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test
             within 7 days prior to the first dose of study drug.

          -  Patient is available for periodic blood sampling, study related assessments and
             management at the treating institution for the duration of the study.

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent
             document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who only present with isolated plasmacytomas

          -  Inability to swallow oral medication.

          -  Prior allogeneic stem cell transplant (subject with prior autologous transplant is
             eligible).

          -  Patient has plans to undergo any type of stem cell transplantation (allogeneic or
             autologous) within 4 weeks of initiation of study therapy.

          -  Concurrent therapy with HMG-CoA Reductase Inhibitors.

          -  Patient with gallbladder disease or cholelithiasis.

          -  Patient has active liver disease, including biliary cirrhosis and unexplained liver
             function abnormalities.

          -  Patients receiving renal dialysis.

          -  History of hypersensitivity to fenofibrate or fenofibric acid, including sever skin
             rashes (e.g., Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis)

          -  Patients who would be receiving any other investigational agents while on study.

          -  Participation in any investigational drug study within 4 weeks preceding the start of
             study treatment.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements.

          -  Patient has systemic infection requiring treatment.

          -  Patient has acute diffuse infiltrative pulmonary disease or     pericardial disease.

          -  Subject is receiving corticosteroid therapy (&gt; 10 mg of prednisone or equivalent).

          -  Subject is a regular user or has a recent history (within the last year) of any
             illicit drugs, or substance abuse.

          -  Subject is pregnant or breast feeding, or expecting to conceive or father children
             within the projected duration of the study.

          -  Subject is known to be HIV positive.

          -  Subject has clinically active Hepatitis B or C

          -  History of prior malignancy except for cervical carcinoma in situ, non-melanoma skin
             cancer, adequately treated localized prostate cancer with PSA &lt; 0.1, or has undergone
             potentially curative therapy with no evidence of disease for five years, or who is
             deemed at low risk for recurrence by his/her treating physician.

          -  Patient with CNS metastases and/or carcinomatous meningitis.

          -  History of gastrointestinal disease that could potentially impact the ability of the
             patient to swallow and/or absorb study drug (i.e., gastrointestinal surgery,
             malabsorption syndrome, subjects requiring the use of feeding tube)

          -  History of gastrointestinal surgery or other procedures that might in the opinion of
             the investigator interfere with swallowing and/or absorption of the study drug.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Denise Pereria, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Miami Sylvester Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Miami Sylvester Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Denise Pereira, MD</last_name>
      <phone>305-243-9127</phone>
      <email>dpereira2@med.miai.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>University of Miami Sylvester Comprehensive Cancer Center</last_name>
      <phone>866-574-5124</phone>
      <email>sylvester@emergingmed.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Denise Pereira, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Theodore J Lampidis, Phd,</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mauricio Escobar, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joseph Rosenblatt, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Deborah Glick, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark Goodman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Byrnes, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James Hoffman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 23, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 15, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Multiple Myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>Fenofibrate</keyword>
  <keyword>Relapsed</keyword>
  <keyword>Refractory</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fenofibrate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fenofibric acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
