<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="26804">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01962415</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RIC for UBCT in NMD</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>PRO13100018</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01962415</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Reduced Intensity Conditioning in Patients Aged ≤30 With Non-Malignant Disorders Undergoing Cord Blood Transplantation</brief_title>
  <acronym>RIC UCBT NMD</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Reduced Intensity Conditioning in Patients ≤30 Years of Age With Non-Malignant Disorders Undergoing Umbilical Cord Blood Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pittsburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Umbilical cord blood transplant (UCBT) has been shown to be an effective treatment for a
      wide variety of non-malignant disorders (NMD) as well as malignant disorders also known as
      cancer. Before a patient can receive a UCBT, doctors need to reduce the chance that the
      patient's body will reject the cord blood cells. This is usually done by using chemotherapy
      or radiation therapy given to eradicate the patient's immune cells, which originate from
      stem cells in the bone marrow. If the therapy is is administered at or near at it's maximum
      tolerated dose, it is called myeloablative conditioning (MAC), referring to the fact that
      most MAC regimens ablate irreversibly most if not all stem cells residing in the bone
      marrow. While ultra high doses of chemotherapy is very effective for treating leukemia where
      there are cancerous stem cells, for those without cancer or leukemia this high/maximum
      intensity is not essential and poses lots of dangerous toxic side effects.

      In this research study, instead of using the standard myeloablative conditioning, the study
      doctor is using reduced-intensity conditioning (RIC), in which lower doses of chemotherapy
      will be used.  Although the lower doses may not eradicate every single stem cell in the bone
      marrow, nevertheless in the presented combination it still intends to eliminate already
      formed immune cells, paving the way to successful engraftment of donor cord blood cells.
      Engrafting cord blood cells can outcompete and reject the patients' few surviving stem
      cells. With reduced-intensity conditioning, the side effects on brain, heart, lung, liver,
      and other organ functions are usually less severe, and the patients can have a better
      long-term recovery. There is also realistic hope that after lower doses of chemotherapy many
      patients will avoid becoming sterile.

      The purpose of this study is to collect data from the patients undergoing reduced-intensity
      conditioning before UCBT, so that the study doctor can compare it to the standard
      myeloablative conditioning with the expectation that there will be full therapeutic benefits
      paired with better survival rate and improved quality of life following the reduced
      intensity approach compared to myeloablative regimen.

      Patients age 2 months to 30 years old who have a non-malignant disease that can be treated
      with an umbilical cord blood transplant will be considered for this study. A full list of
      eligibility criteria appears later in this record.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Umbilical cord blood (UCB) transplant following myeloablative conditioning (MAC) has been
      demonstrated to be safe and curative for a variety of malignant and non-malignant diseases
      (NMD), with unrelated UCB offering an alternative donor source for those patients without a
      related or unrelated bone marrow or peripheral blood stem cell source.  MAC carries a
      significant risk for transplant-related mortality (TRM), ranging from 20-30% in the first
      year following UCBT, and for long-term morbidity and mortality from effects on growth and
      fertility as well as risk for secondary malignancy.  RIC regimens with well below the
      maximum tolerated doses ( MTD) of chemotherapy  offer the potential for decreased morbidity
      and TRM which is attractive for patients with NMD.  Despite lower overall doses of
      chemotherapy we have demonstrated that cord blood cell engraftment can remain  stable at
      very high ( typically &gt;95%) levels for long-term and leading to full therapeutic benefits.
      In addition, RIC regimens may offer improved neurocognitive outcomes when compared to
      historical MAC regimens since it is based on less neurotoxic chemotherapy and possibly lower
      doses of steroids if there is lesser incidence and severity of GVHD that in combination
      could also lead to improved immune reconstitution following UCBT.

      Reduced-intensity conditioning (RIC) regimens rely on relatively high doses of
      immunosuppressive therapy, such as fludarabine (Flu) in combination with T-cell depleting
      antibodies (e.g. anti-thymocyte globulin [ATG] or alemtuzumab), in the setting of decreased
      myelosuppressive therapy, including lower dose alkylating agents (e.g. busulfan [Bu],
      cyclophosphamide [Cy], melphalan [Mel], thiotepa (TT).

      In this protocol, we will combine RIC with UCBT in eligible subjects, and collect data as
      described in the endpoints section.

      The subjects will be stratified according to type of primary disease and degree of immune
      competence each of the three strata will use a different amount of alemtuzumab prior to
      transplant.

      Male and female subjects aged 2 months to 30 years (inclusive) who meet all of the
      eligibility criteria will be considered for this study. Non-malignant disease populations
      amenable to stem cell treatment, listed in the eligibility section, will be considered
      appropriate for this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-transplant treatment-related mortality (TRM)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessment of post-transplant treatment-related mortality at day 100, day 180, and 1 year</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neurodevelopmental milestones</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluation of the pace of attaining neurodevelopmental milestones after reduced-intensity conditioning as compared to myeloablative conditioning historical controls from the target population</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune Reconstitution</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluation of the pace of immune reconstitution</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Severe opportunistic infections</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluation of the incidence of severe opportunistic infections</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>GVHD occurrence</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Description of the incidence of acute GVHD (II-IV) and chronic extensive GVHD</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Donor cell engraftment</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Determination of the feasibility of attaining robust donor cell engraftment (&gt;50% donor chimerism at 180 days) following reduced-intensity conditioning (RIC) regimens prior to UCBT in the target population</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Normal enzyme level</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Determination of the feasibility of attaining and sustaining normal enzyme levels in the target population</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neutrophil recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Determination of the pace of neutrophil recovery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Platelet recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Determination of the pace of platelet recovery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Grade 3-4 organ toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Description of the incidence of grade 3-4 organ toxicity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term complications</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluation of the long-term complications such as sterility, endocrinopathy, and growth failure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Late graft failure</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluation of the incidence of late graft failure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Primary Immunodeficiency Syndromes</condition>
  <condition>Congenital Bone Marrow Failure Syndromes</condition>
  <condition>Inherited Metabolic Disorders (IMD)</condition>
  <condition>Hereditary Anemias</condition>
  <condition>Patients With Sickle Disease Presenting Specific Symptoms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>STRATUM 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>STRATUM 1: Patients without immune deficiency and without recent history of CMV, adenovirus, RSV, Parainfluenza 3 infections. Patients with immune deficiency disorders but with an absolute lymphocyte count that is normal or near normal.
Patients in Stratum 1 will receive a full dose of alemtuzumab, and hydroxyurea, fludarabine, melphalan, and thiotepa.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>STRATUM 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>STRATUM 2: Patients with moderate lymphopenia, or patients without lymphopenia, nevertheless with recent history of CMV, adenovirus, RSV, Parainfluenza 3 infections.
Patients in Stratum 2 will receive a half dose of alemtuzumab, and hydroxyurea, fludarabine, melphalan, and thiotepa.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>STRATUM 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>STRATUM 3: Patients with severe lymphopenia
Patients in Stratum 3 will receive a test dose only of alemtuzumab, and hydroxyurea, fludarabine, melphalan, and thiotepa.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hydroxyurea</intervention_name>
    <description>Hydroxyurea will be given orally at a single daily dose of 30 mg/kg</description>
    <arm_group_label>STRATUM 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>STRATUM 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>STRATUM 3</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>hydroxycarbamide</other_name>
    <other_name>Hydrea</other_name>
    <other_name>Droxia</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Alemtuzumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Alemtuzumab will be given IV per current institutional guidelines.  A test dose will be given prior to conditioning.  The treatment dose of alemtuzumab will be given during conditioning based on the patients' assigned stratum.  Pre-medications for alemtuzumab include acetaminophen, diphenhydramine, and methylprednisolone on the day of alemtuzumab administration. Diphenhydramine, epinephrine, and methylprednisolone will be available at the bedside during administration of alemtuzumab.  If the patient has a fever &gt;38.5 C during or after alemtuzumab infusion, blood cultures will be drawn and antibiotic coverage will be added.</description>
    <arm_group_label>STRATUM 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>STRATUM 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>STRATUM 3</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Campath</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Fludarabine will be given IV at a dose of 30 mg/m2/dose (or 1 mg/kg/dose, whichever is lower) daily x5 doses</description>
    <arm_group_label>STRATUM 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>STRATUM 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>STRATUM 3</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fludara</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Melphalan</intervention_name>
    <description>Melphalan will be given IV at a dose of 70 mg/m2/dose daily x2 doses.</description>
    <arm_group_label>STRATUM 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>STRATUM 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>STRATUM 3</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Melphalan hydrochloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Alkeran</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Thiotepa</intervention_name>
    <description>Thiotepa will be given IV at a dose of 200 mg/m2 x1 dose.</description>
    <arm_group_label>STRATUM 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>STRATUM 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>STRATUM 3</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ThioTEPA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient must be 2 months to 30 years (inclusive) of age for all diagnoses.

          2. Patients must have a 4/6, 5/6 or 6/6 HLA matched related or unrelated UCB unit
             available that will deliver a pre-cryopreservation total nucleated cell dose of &gt; 3 x
             107 cells/kg.

          3. Patient must have adequate function of other organ systems as measured by:

               1. Creatinine ≤ 2.0 mg/dl and creatinine clearance ≥ 50 ml/min/1.73 m2.

               2. Hepatic transaminases (ALT/AST) ≤  4 x normal.

               3. Normal cardiac function by echocardiogram or radionuclide scan   (shortening
                  fraction &gt; 26% or ejection fraction &gt; 40% or &gt; 80% of normal value for age).

               4. Pulmonary function testing demonstrating CVC or FEV1/FVC of  &gt; 50% of predicted
                  for age and/or resting pulse oximeter ≥ 92% on room air or clearance by the
                  pediatric or adult pulmonologist.  For adult patients DLCO (corrected for
                  hemoglobin) should be &gt; 50% of predicted.

          4. Patient, parent, or legal guardian must have given written informed consent and/or
             assent according to FDA guidelines.

          5. Patients may not be pregnant or lactating and must have a current negative pregnancy
             test if pubertal and/or menstruating.

          6. Patients must have a minimum life expectancy of at least 6 months.

          7. Patients must be HIV negative.

          8. Patients must not have uncontrolled infections at the time of cytoreduction.

          9. Patients should have a non-malignant disorder amenable to treatment by stem cell
             transplantation, including but not limited to:

             A. Primary Immunodeficiency syndromes including but not limited to:

               -  Severe Combined Immune Deficiency (SCID) with NK cell activity

               -  Omenn Syndrome

               -  Bare Lymphocyte Syndrome (BLS)

               -  Combined Immune Deficiency (CID) syndromes

               -  Combined Variable Immune Deficiency (CVID) syndrome

               -  Wiskott-Aldrich Syndrome

               -  Leukocyte adhesion deficiency

               -  Chronic granulomatous disease (CGD)

               -  X-linked Hyper IgM (XHIM) syndrome

               -  IPEX syndrome

               -  Chediak -Higashi Syndrome

               -  Autoimmune Lymphoproliferative Syndrome (ALPS)

               -  Hemophagocytic Lymphohistiocytosis (HLH) syndromes

               -  Lymphocyte Signaling defects

               -  Other primary immune defects where hematopoietic stem cell transplantation may
                  be beneficial

             B. Congenital bone marrow failure syndromes including but not limited to:

               -  Dyskeratosis Congenita (DC)

               -  Congenital Amegakaryocytic Thrombocytopenia (CAMT)

               -  Osteopetrosis

             C. Inherited Metabolic Disorders (IMD) including but not limited to:

               -  Mucopolysaccharidoses o Hurler syndrome (MPS I) o Hunter syndrome (MPS II)

                  o Sanfilippo syndrome (MPS II)

               -  Leukodystrophies

                  o Krabbe Disease, also known as globoid cell leukodystrophy

                    -  Metachromatic leukodystrophy (MLD)

                    -  X-linked adrenoleukodystrophy (ALD)

               -  Other inherited metabolic disorders

                  o alpha mannosidosis

               -  Other inheritable metabolic diseases where hematopoietic stem cell
                  transplantation may be beneficial.

             D. Hereditary anemias

             • Thalassemia major

             • Sickle cell disease (SCD)

               -  Diamond Blackfan Anemia (DBA)

               -  other congenital transfusion dependent anemias

             Patients with sickle disease must have one or more of the following:

             • Overt or silent stroke

             • Pain crises ≥ 2 episodes per year for past year

             • One or more episodes of acute chest syndrome

             • Osteonecrosis involving ≥ 1 joints

             • Priapism

             Exclusion Criteria:

        1. UCB unit with a total nucleated cell count of &lt; 3 x 107/kg or &gt; 2 antigen  mismatching.

        2. Available HLA-matched related living donor unaffected with recipient's disease and able
        to donate without previous UCB donation.

        3. Allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant within the previous 6 months.

        4. Any active malignancy or MDS.

        5. Severe acquired aplastic anemia.

        7. Uncontrolled bacterial, viral or fungal infection (currently taking medication and with
        progression of clinical symptoms).

        8. Pregnancy or nursing mother.

        9. HIV positive

        10. Poorly controlled pulmonary hypertension.

        11. Any condition that precludes serial follow-up.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul Szabolcs, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paul Szabolcs, MD</last_name>
    <phone>412-692-5427</phone>
    <email>paul.szabolcs@chp.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mark Vander Lugt, MD</last_name>
    <phone>412-692-5427</phone>
    <email>mark.vanderlugt@chp.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Natalie Cercone, RN</last_name>
      <phone>412-692-5004</phone>
      <email>natalie.cercone@chp.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark Vander Lugt, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maria Escolar, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rakesh Goyal, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Randy Windreich, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michele Poe, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paul Szabolcs, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Xiaohua Chen, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 25, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 10, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Paul Szabolcs</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief, Division of Blood and Marrow Transplantation and Cellular Therapies</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Severe Combined Immune Deficiency (SCID) with NK cell activity</keyword>
  <keyword>Omenn Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Bare Lymphocyte Syndrome (BLS)</keyword>
  <keyword>Combined Immune Deficiency (CID) syndromes</keyword>
  <keyword>Combined Variable Immune Deficiency (CVID) syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Wiskott-Aldrich Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Leukocyte adhesion deficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic granulomatous disease (CGD)</keyword>
  <keyword>X-linked Hyper IgM (XHIM) syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>IPEX syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Chediak -Higashi Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Autoimmune Lymphoproliferative Syndrome (ALPS)</keyword>
  <keyword>Hemophagocytic Lymphohistiocytosis (HLH) syndromes</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphocyte Signaling defects</keyword>
  <keyword>Other primary immune defects where HSCT may be beneficial</keyword>
  <keyword>Dyskeratosis Congenita (DC)</keyword>
  <keyword>Congenital Amegakaryocytic Thrombocytopenia (CAMT)</keyword>
  <keyword>Osteopetrosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Mucopolysaccharidoses</keyword>
  <keyword>Hurler syndrome (MPS I)</keyword>
  <keyword>Hunter syndrome (MPS II)</keyword>
  <keyword>Sanfilippo syndrome (MPS II)</keyword>
  <keyword>Leukodystrophies</keyword>
  <keyword>Krabbe Disease, also known as globoid cell leukodystrophy</keyword>
  <keyword>Metachromatic leukodystrophy (MLD)</keyword>
  <keyword>X-linked adrenoleukodystrophy (ALD)</keyword>
  <keyword>Other inherited metabolic disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>alpha mannosidosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Other inheritable metabolic diseases where HSCT may be beneficial.</keyword>
  <keyword>Thalassemia major</keyword>
  <keyword>Sickle cell disease (SCD)</keyword>
  <keyword>Diamond Blackfan Anemia (DBA)</keyword>
  <keyword>other congenital transfusion dependent anemias</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunologic Deficiency Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancytopenia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemoglobinuria, Paroxysmal</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine monophosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alemtuzumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydroxyurea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Melphalan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thiotepa</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Campath 1G</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
