<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="80787">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02138747</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>178-MA-1001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02138747</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate Tolerability and Patient Preference Between Myrbetriq® and Detrol® LA in Subjects With Overactive Bladder (OAB)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Double-Blind, Randomized, Two-Period Crossover, Multi-Center Study to Evaluate the Tolerability and Patient Preference Between Myrbetriq® and Detrol® LA in Subjects With Overactive Bladder (OAB)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Astellas Pharma Global Development, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Astellas Pharma Inc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess tolerability of Myrbetriq compared to Detrol LA in
      the treatment of subjects with Overactive Bladder (OAB). This study will also assess patient
      preference, safety and tolerability of Myrbetriq and Detrol LA in subjects with symptoms of
      OAB as well as the impact of treatment on micturition frequency and incontinence episodes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will comprise of two double-blind treatment periods with a wash-out period in
      between. Subjects will receive a placebo during this time period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient tolerability assessed by the Tolerability Scale of the Overactive Bladder-satisfaction (OAB-S) questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of each treatment period (Week 8 and Week 18)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient preference from a 5-point scale</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of the second treatment period (Week 18)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The 5-point scale is composed of: strong preference for period 1, mild preference for period 1, no preference, mild preference for period 2, strong preference for period 2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Scales of the OAB-S questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of each treatment period (Week 8 and Week 18)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Impact on daily living with Overactive Bladder (OAB); OAB control; Satisfaction with control; Overall assessment of Patient's fulfillment of OAB medication expectations; Overall assessment of interruption of day-to-day life due to OAB; Overall satisfaction with OAB medication; Overall assessment of willingness to continue OAB medication; Overall assessment of improvement in day-to-day life due to OAB medication</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in number of incontinence episodes per 24 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to end of each treatment period (Week 8 and Week 18)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in number of micturitions per 24 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to end of each treatment period (Week 8 and Week 18)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">360</enrollment>
  <condition>Overactive Bladder (OAB)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Myrbetriq/Detrol LA sequence group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive Myrbetriq in the first treatment period then Detrol LA for the second treatment period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Detrol LA/Mybetriq sequence group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive Detrol LA in the first treatment period then Myrbetriq for the second treatment period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Myrbetriq/Myrbetriq sequence group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive Myrbetriq in both treatment periods.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Detrol LA/Detrol LA sequence group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive Detrol LA in both treatment periods.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Myrbetriq</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral</description>
    <arm_group_label>Myrbetriq/Detrol LA sequence group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Detrol LA/Mybetriq sequence group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Myrbetriq/Myrbetriq sequence group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>YM178,</other_name>
    <other_name>Mirabegron</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Detrol LA</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral</description>
    <arm_group_label>Myrbetriq/Detrol LA sequence group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Detrol LA/Mybetriq sequence group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Detrol LA/Detrol LA sequence group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>tolterodine ER</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject is willing and able to complete the micturition diary and questionnaires
             correctly.

          -  Subject has symptoms of OAB (urinary frequency and urgency with or without
             incontinence) for greater than or equal to 3 months prior to Screening.

          -  Subject must be treatment-naïve to pharmaceutical agents for OAB.

          -  Female subject must not donate ova starting at Screening and throughout the study
             period, and for 30 days after the final study drug administration.

          -  Male subject must not donate sperm starting at Screening and throughout the study
             period and for at least 30 days after final study drug administration.

          -  Subject agrees not to participate in another interventional study from the time of
             screening until the final study visit.

          -  Inclusion Criteria assessed at Visit 2 (Week 0) based on the 3-day micturition diary:

               -  Subject continues to meet all inclusion criteria of Visit 1.

               -  Subject must experience at least 3 episodes of urgency (grade 3 or 4) during the
                  3 day micturition diary.

               -  Subject must experience an average of greater than or equal to 8
                  micturitions/day on the 3 day micturition diary

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Female subject who is lactating or is intending to breastfeed during the study period
             and for 30 days after the final study visit.

          -  The subject has clinically significant bladder outlet obstruction (BOO) posing a risk
             of urinary retention.

          -  Subject has significant stress incontinence or mixed stress/urgency incontinence
             where stress is the predominant factor.

          -  Subject has evidence of Urinary Tract Infection (UTI) (urine culture greater than
             100,000 cfu/mL) as assessed at Screening (Visit 1).  The subject can be rescreened
             after successful treatment of the UTI (confirmed by a laboratory result of negative
             urine culture).

          -  Subject has a neurological cause for detrusor overactivity (e.g., neurogenic bladder,
             diabetic neuropathy or systemic or central neurological disease such as multiple
             sclerosis and Parkinson's disease).

          -  Subject has an indwelling catheter or practices intermittent self-catheterization.

          -  Subject has a chronic inflammatory condition such as interstitial cystitis, bladder
             stones, previous pelvic radiation therapy, or previous or current malignant disease
             of the pelvic organs (i.e., within the confines of the pelvis including the bladder
             and rectum in both sexes and the uterus, ovaries, and fallopian tubes in females); or
             of the lower gastrointestinal tract.

          -  Subject has uncontrolled narrow angle glaucoma, urinary or gastric retention, severe
             colitis ulcerosa, toxic megacolon, myasthenia gravis, polio or any other medical
             condition which makes the use of anticholinergics contraindicated.

          -  Subject has received intravesical injection in the past 12 months with botulinum
             toxin, resiniferatoxin, or capsaicin.

          -  Subject has received invasive treatment including electro-stimulation therapy.

          -  Subject is receiving a bladder training program or pelvic floor exercises which
             started or has changed less than 30 days prior to Screening.

          -  Subject has hepatic impairment defined as Child-Pugh Class A, B or C.

          -  Subject has severe renal impairment defined as creatinine clearance less than 30
             mL/min. A subject with End Stage Renal Disease or undergoing dialysis is also not a
             candidate for the study.

          -  Subject has severe uncontrolled hypertension, which is defined as a sitting systolic
             blood pressure greater than or equal 180 mmHg and/or diastolic blood pressure greater
             than or equal 110 mmHg.

          -  Subject has evidence of QT prolongation on electrocardiogram (ECG) defined as QTcF
             greater than 450 msec for males, QTcF greater than 470 msec for females or a known
             history of QT prolongation.

          -  Subject has a serum creatinine greater than 150 µmol/L, or aspartate aminotransferase
             (AST) or alanine aminotransferase (ALT) greater than 2x upper limit of normal (ULN),
             or γ-GT greater than 3x ULN and considered clinically significant.

          -  Subject has a hypersensitivity to any components of Myrbetriq (mirabegron), other
             β-AR agonists, tolterodine or other antimuscarinic agents, or any of the inactive
             ingredients.

          -  Subject has been treated with an experimental device within 30 days or received an
             investigational agent within 30 days prior to Screening.

          -  Subject has a concurrent malignancy or history of any malignancy (within the past 5
             years), except non-metastatic basal or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin that has
             been treated successfully.

          -  Subject with current history of alcohol and/or drug abuse.

          -  Subject is involved in the conduct of the study as an employee of the Astellas group,
             third party associated with the study, or the study site team.

          -  Exclusion Criteria assessed at Visit 2 (Week 0):

               -  Subject fulfills any exclusion criteria at Visit 1.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Astellas Scientific &amp; Medical Affairs, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Astellas Pharma Global Development</last_name>
    <phone>800-888-7704</phone>
    <phone_ext>5473</phone_ext>
    <email>clintrials.info@us.astellas.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 13, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Overactive bladder (OAB)</keyword>
  <keyword>Myrbetriq</keyword>
  <keyword>Detrol LA</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder, Overactive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Tolterodine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
