<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="131087">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01860677</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P-001567</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01860677</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cranial Electrotherapy Stimulation (CES) to Treat PTSD</brief_title>
  <acronym>CES-fMRI-PTSD</acronym>
  <official_title>Cranial Electrotherapy Stimulation (CES) to Treat PTSD: Identifying Metrics of Efficacy Using Brain Imaging</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mclean Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mending Minds Foundation, Ellen Ratner</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mclean Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Use of the Fischer Wallace Cranial Stimulator to relieve symptoms related to PTSD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The advent of an appreciation that alternative and complementary practices can have some
      beneficial effect on health has prompted the question of whether there are empirical
      measures of improvement that do not rely solely on subjective reports. The present study
      proposes to explore whether transcranial stimulation (or cranial electrotherapy stimulation;
      CES) using an FDA-approved device can alter brain function, mood and responses to cognitive
      tasks in patients diagnosed with Post Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD). Furthermore, the
      study will test whether such changes parallel clinical improvement in signs and symptoms.
      The dependent variables of interest will be magnetic resonance imaging (MRI).  Secondarily,
      we will assess the effects of CES on brain chemistry through the use of magnetic resonance
      spectroscopy procedures in normal, healthy control participants.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>BOLD fMRI and spectroscopy (neural activation patterns/brain function)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>For PTSD-diagnosed participants:  Three weeks of daily treatments (Monday-Friday) of CES will result in quantitative changes in neural activation patterns during task performance as measured by BOLD functional MRI. A secondary hypothesis is that these changes in brain function will parallel an improvement in mood which will be reflected in changes in resting state MRI scans.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinician-Administered PTSD Scale (CAPS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The CAPS is the gold standard in PTSD assessment. The CAPS is a 30-item structured interview that corresponds to the DSM-IV criteria for PTSD. The CAPS can be used to make a current (past month) or lifetime diagnosis of PTSD or to assesses symptoms over the past week. In addition to assessing the 17 PTSD symptoms, questions target the impact of symptoms on social and occupational functioning, improvement in symptoms since a previous CAPS administration, overall response validity, overall PTSD severity, and frequency and intensity of five associated symptoms (guilt over acts, survivor guilt, gaps in awareness, depersonalization, and derealization). For each item, standardized questions and probes are provided. As part of the trauma assessment (Criterion A), the Life Events Checklist (LEC) is used to identify traumatic stressors experienced. CAPS items are asked in reference to up to three traumatic stressors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Treatment of PTSD Symptoms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Fisher Wallace Cranial Electrostimulation device generates micro currents of electricity using a patented series of radio frequencies. The device has been designated by the FDA to be minimally invasive and has FDA approval to be used to reduce symptoms associated with anxiety, depression, pain and insomnia. The unit is locked at the factory to deliver a maximal output of 4 mA of current and has a timer that prevents it from staying on longer than 20 minutes. Current will be limited to a maximum of 2 mA.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants are outfitted with a device that is identical in appearance but does not deliver any current.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fisher Wallace Cranial Stimulator</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Active stimulation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Meets DSM-IV criteria for PTSD

          -  21 to 40 years old

          -  Otherwise physically healthy (normal physical exam, ECG, blood and urine chemistries)

          -  Female participants must use medically approved method of contraception.  If barrier
             method is used, they must agree to using two methods simultaneously (e.g., diaphragm
             and condom).

          -  If on antidepressant or antianxiety medication, must be on a stable prescription
             regimen with no intentions to change drugs or dose during the next 11 weeks.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Opiate maintenance (e.g., methadone or buprenorphine)

          -  Drug use (other than nicotine, alcohol, or marihuana) greater than 50 lifetime uses.

          -  Meets criteria for current drug abuse or dependence (other than nicotine, alcohol, or
             marihuana). Past abuse/dependence (greater than 3 years) is acceptable.

          -  Meets criteria for alcohol dependence. Past abuse/dependence (greater than 3 years)
             is acceptable.  They may meet criteria for alcohol abuse.

          -  Physical health problems

          -  History of significant cardiac problems

          -  History of seizures

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Persons with a demand-type cardiac pacemaker

          -  Persons receiving vagus nerve simulation

          -  Persons receiving deep brain stimulation

          -  Participants cannot have any conditions that are contraindicated for MRI
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Scott E Lukas, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>McLean Imaging Center, McLean Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>McLean Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Belmont</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02478</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Scott E Lukas, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>617-855-2767</phone>
      <email>slukas@mclean.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>David M Penetar, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>617-855-2913</phone>
      <email>dpenetar@mclean.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Scott E Lukas, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gilula MF, Barach PR. Cranial electrotherapy stimulation: a safe neuromedical treatment for anxiety, depression, or insomnia. South Med J. 2004 Dec;97(12):1269-70.</citation>
    <PMID>15646771</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 22, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 20, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mclean Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Scott Lukas</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, McLean Imaging Center</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PTSD</keyword>
  <keyword>cranial stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>fMRI (BOLD)</keyword>
  <keyword>spectroscopy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
