<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="161560">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02059395</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Mastery of BLS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02059395</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mastery Learning Versus Time-based Education: Skill Acquisition and Retention of Basic Life Support in Laypeople</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Canadian Institutes of Health Research</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      In cardiac arrest survival rates dramatically increase when bystanders are present and
      initiate Basic Life Support (BLS). However, even though serious efforts have been made,
      skill retention after a traditional time-based BLS course for laypeople remains suboptimal.
      In contrast, a mastery learning-based educational approach was shown to be efficacious and
      might be promising even for laypersons. Therefore the investigators aim to evaluate the
      impact of a mastery learning-based BLS course on skills retention of BLS in laypeople.

      Methods:

      Forty laypeople without previous BLS experiences will be randomized into the traditional
      time-based BLS course group (Control - TB group) or mastery learning-based group
      (Intervention - ML group).

      Both groups will receive BLS training consisting of 6 successive stations including
      diagnosis of cardiac arrest, chest compression, ventilation, one-rescuer BLS, two-rescuer
      BLS and AED use. In the ML group, subjects will deliberately practice and receive feedback
      at each station until a pre-set target level is reached. Subjects will be allowed to proceed
      to the next station only when they achieve the required target level of performance. In
      contrast,  participants of the TB group will be taught the same 6 stations in two hours,
      according to standard American Heart Association BLS criteria. All subjects will have an
      assessment of knowledge and skills immediately after teaching (immediate post-test) and at
      four months (retention post-test).

      Implications:

      Previous research has shown that mastery learning-based education improves learners'
      procedural skill performance. The investigators study will determine the impact of a mastery
      learning-based BLS course on skill retention in laypeople.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor)</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Skill Retention</measure>
    <time_frame>4 month after training</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Retention of basic life support skills are assessed 4 month after the initial training, rated according to the American Heart Association Heartsaver checklist. The difference between skill score between initial and  the retention test is defined as the primary outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Basic Life Support</condition>
  <condition>Cardiac Arrest</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Time based</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants follow the traditional Canadian Heart and Stroke Foundation Heartsaver Course</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mastery based</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants do follow the content of the Canadian Heart and Stroke Foundation Heartsaver Course content based on their own pace (timeframe)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mastery based learning</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants are allowed to follow the course content at their own speed</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mastery based</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Time based learning</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants follow the traditional Canadian Heart and Stroke Foundation Heartsaver Course according to the official course layout</description>
    <arm_group_label>Time based</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  University students in Ottawa

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Students of the Faculty of Medicine

          -  Previous Basic Life Support Training Certificate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sylvain Boet, MD</last_name>
    <phone>613-737-8187</phone>
    <email>sboet@toh.on.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Ottawa Skills and Simulation Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1Y 4E9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ashlee-Anne Pigford</last_name>
      <email>apigford@ohri.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 7, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Arrest</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
