<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="126034">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01865474</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DLBS1033-0212</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01865474</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety of DLBS1033 in Subjects With Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</brief_title>
  <official_title>DLBS1033 Therapy in Improving Hypercoagulation State in Subjects With Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dexa Medica Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dexa Medica Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Indonesia: National Agency of Drug and Food Control</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, double-blind, randomized, and controlled study. The investigational
      product, DLBS1033 at a dose of 490 mg thrice daily or placebo, will be given for an 8-week
      course of therapy.

      DLBS1033 effectively demonstrated fibrinolytic, fibrinogenolytic as well as antithrombotic
      activities. Hypercoagulation state with high fibrinogen level is usually found in diabetes
      mellitus patients.

      Therefore, the hypothesis of interest of this study is that DLBS1033 will reduce fibrinogen
      level of diabetes mellitus patients better than that of the Control Group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There will be 2 groups of treatment, each consisting of 68 subjects, with the treatment
      regimens as the following:

      Treatment I : DLBS1033 bioactive fraction tablet @ 490 mg, three times daily. Treatment II :
      Placebo tablet of DLBS1033, three times daily.

      Clinical examination to evaluate the efficacy of the investigational drug will be performed
      at baseline and every follow-up visit (at interval of 4 weeks) over the 8 weeks of study
      period. All subjects will be advised to follow such a lifestyle modification throughout the
      study period.

      All subjects will be under direct supervision of a medical doctor during the study period.

      During the study period, anti-diabetes treatment taken by study subjects should still be
      continued. Other treatment related to subjects' concomitant illnesses, such as hypertension,
      and/or dyslipidemia, is allowed during subjects' participation in the study.

      Other medication such as anti-platelets, fibrinolytic agents and anti-coagulants, or other
      treatment including herbals/alternatives which may affect haemostatic system, are not
      allowed to be used during the study period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fibrinogen level reduction</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Fibrinogen level reduction from baseline to the end of study (Week 8th)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of D-dimer</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change of D-dimer from baseline to every follow-up visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of von Willebrand Factor activity</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change of von Willebrand Factor activity from baseline to every follow-up visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hs-CRP level</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change of hs-CRP level from baseline to every follow-up visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of HbA1c</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change of HbA1c from baseline to end of study (Week 8th).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Electrocardiography (ECG)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Electrocardiography (ECG) from baseline to every follow-up visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Vital signs (blood pressure, pulse rate, respiration rate) from baseline to every follow-up visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Liver function</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Liver function (serum ALT, AST,γ-glutamyl transferase, alkaline phosphatase) at baseline and end of study (Week 8th)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Renal function</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Renal function (serum creatinine, BUN) at baseline and end of study (Week 8th)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prothrombin Time (PT)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Prothrombin time from baseline to every follow-up visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT)from baseline to every follow-up visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks and 8 weeks (during 8 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Adverse events (mainly: GI bleeding, and other bleeding events) from baseline to every follow-up visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of 11-dehydro-thromboxane-B2 level</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change of 11-dehydro-thromboxane-B2 level from baseline to every follow-up visit (as an indirect indicator to assess the effect of study treatment on TxA2)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">136</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>DLBS1033 bioactive fraction tablet 490 mg thrice daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment II</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo tablet of DLBS1033, thrice daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DLBS1033</intervention_name>
    <description>1 DLBS1033 tablet 490 mg thrice daily for 2 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment I</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Disolf</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo tablet of DLBS1033</intervention_name>
    <description>1 placebo tablet of DLBS1033 thrice daily for 2 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment II</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>placebo tablet of Disolf</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Signed informed consent before any trial related activities. Trial related activities
             are any procedure that would not have been performed during the normal management of
             the patient.

          -  Diagnosed as type 2 diabetes mellitus with A1c &gt; 7.0% at Screening.

          -  Men or women, between 25-65 years of age.

          -  Have been being treated with lifestyle intervention and/or any oral anti-diabetic
             agents and/or insulin.

          -  Adequate liver function: ALT and AST ≤ 2.5 times upper limit of normal.

          -  Adequate renal function: serum creatinine &lt; 2.0 times upper limit of normal.

          -  Able to take oral medication.

          -  Subjects or subjects' legally acceptable representatives are able and willing to
             record adverse events in a diary.

          -  Subjects or subjects' legally acceptable representatives have the ability to comply
             with the trial protocol, including instructions for taking trial medication and visit
             schedules.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. For females of childbearing potential: Pregnancy, breast-feeding, the intention of
             becoming pregnant.

               -  Patients must accept pregnancy tests during the trial if menstrual cycle is
                  missed.

               -  Fertile patients must use a reliable and effective contraceptive.

          2. The presence of electrocardiographic abnormality consisting of :

               -  Clinically significant cardiac arrhythmias, or

               -  Atrio-ventricular conduction block greater than first degree, or

               -  Severe ischemic ST-segment depression (≥ 2.0 mm), or

               -  ST-segment elevation in lead aVR of ≥ 1.0 mm, or

               -  Pathologic Q waves (with a duration of ≥ 0.04 sec; Q wave is defined as the
                  initial negative deflection of QRS complex on ECG), or

               -  Other significant ECG abnormalities necessitating medical or pharmacological
                  treatment.

          3. History of acute coronary syndrome (myocardial infarction, stroke, unstable angina
             pectoris), peripheral arterial diseases, venous thromboembolism or other
             cardiovascular events.

          4. History of other arteriosclerotic disease necessitating medical or pharmacological
             treatment.

          5. Severe hypertension (systolic blood pressure ≥ 180 mm Hg, diastolic ≥ 110 mm Hg).

          6. Treatment with antiplatelets or antithrombotic agents, including other oral
             lumbrokinase products within 14 days prior to Screening.

          7. Subjects with prior experience with DLBS1033.

          8. Subjects with high-risk of bleeding:

               -  Subjects with history of acquired or congenital bleeding disorder, coagulopathy,
                  or platelet disorder.

               -  Subjects with evidence of active pathological bleeding or history of bleeding
                  such as gastrointestinal or genitourinary unless the cause has been definitely
                  corrected.

               -  History or presence of intracranial bleeding or hemorrhagic retinopathy,
                  unstable angina, severe valvular disease, severe anemia, suspected or known
                  dissecting aneurysm, acute myocarditis or pericarditis, deep vein thrombosis,
                  severe aortic stenosis, severe hypertrophic obstructive cardiomyopathy.

          9. Presence of malignancies as observed clinically or by anamnesis.

         10. Subjects with any other disease state, including chronic or acute systemic
             infections, or uncontrolled illnesses, which judged by the investigator, could
             interfere with trial participation or trial evaluation.

         11. Subjects with known or suspected allergy to study medication or similar products.

         12. Subjects with concurrent herbal (alternative) medicines or food supplements suspected
             to have effect on the primary efficacy endpoint.

         13. Subjects enrolled in another experimental (interventional) protocol within the past
             30 days prior to Screening.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Asman Manaf, Prof. Dr. dr., SpPD-KEMD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, University of Andalas/ dr. M. Djamil Padang Hospital, Padang, Sumatera Barat, Indonesia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Asman Manaf, Prof. Dr. dr., SpPD-KEMD</last_name>
    <phone>+62811 663 426</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Internal Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, University of Andalas/ dr. M. Djamil Padang Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Padang</city>
        <state>Sumatera Barat</state>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Asman Manaf, Prof. Dr. dr., SpPD-KEMD</last_name>
      <phone>+62811 663 426</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Asman Manaf, Prof. Dr. dr., SpPD-KEMD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Irza Wahid, dr., SpPD-KHOM</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mukhyarjon, dr., M. Biomed</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Indonesia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 30, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 28, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>DLBS1033, Type 2 DM, fibrinolytic, hypercoagulation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
