<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="43618">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01994525</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>S-12-22</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01994525</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immunization Via Mosquito Bite With Radiation-attenuated Sporozoites</brief_title>
  <acronym>IMRAS</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase 1 Trial With Challenge to Assess the Safety and Biomarkers of Protection in Malaria-naïve Adults of Immunization Via Mosquito Bite With Radiation-Attenuated Plasmodium Falciparum Sporozoites (IMRAS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>U.S. Army Medical Research and Materiel Command</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Seattle Biomedical Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>U.S. Army Medical Research and Materiel Command</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is to assess the safety, tolerability, and biomarkers of protection in healthy
      malaria-naïve adults, who will receive bites from Anopheles stephensi mosquitoes either
      infected with Plasmodium falciparum Sporozoites (PfRAS) (true-immunization) or noninfected
      (mock-immunization).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1 open-labeled study. In addition to safety and tolerability of  Plasmodium
      falciparum Sporozoites (PfRAS), this study is a comprehensive, systems biology-based effort
      to identify and validate biomarkers of protection with PfRAS immunization, comparing
      sterility protected to nonprotected study subjects. The goal of the trial design is to
      achieve approximately 50% sterile protection in order to facilitate the identification of
      biomarkers and correlates of protection.

      Following true-immunization or mock-immunization, study subjects and nonimmunized
      infectivity controls will receive a challenge via the bites of 5 An stephensi mosquitoes
      carrying infectious P falciparum sporozoites within a controlled clinical environment
      (controlled human malaria infection, CHMI) to determine the level of sterile protection.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Solicited adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Occurrence of solicited adverse events (AE) from administration of study immunization (PfRAS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Unsolicited adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Occurrence of unsolicited adverse events (AEs) from administration of immunization (PfRAS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Laboratory adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Occurrence of laboratory AEs from administration of study immunization (PfRAS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serious adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Occurrence of serious adverse events (SAEs) from administration of immunization (PfRAS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Signs and symptoms related to malaria infection</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Occurrence of signs and symptoms related to malaria infection starting 7 days post-Controlled Human Malaria Infection (CHMI) (these will not be recorded as adverse events because they are expected as a result of malaria infection)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Parasitemia</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Development of parasitemia and time to parasitemia after malaria challenge</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Identify and validate immunological PBMC biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Compare Peripheral Blood Mononuclear Cell(s) (PBMC) read-outs between protected and nonprotected subjects and between immunized and mock-immunized subjects.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Identify and validate immunological serum biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Compare serum read-outs between protected and nonprotected subjects and between immunized and mock-immunized subjects.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Identify and validate whole blood immunological biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Compare whole blood read-outs between protected and nonprotected subjects and between immunized and mock-immunized subjects.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>7</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">52</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: PfRAS-infected</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>5 doses (immunizations) of approximately 200 infectious bites (200-400 bites total) from PfRAS-infected mosquitoes (true-immunization). The target dose is 960 infectious bites.
Challenge occurs 3 weeks after final immunization.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Noninfected</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo immunization. 5 doses of approximately 200 infectious bites (200-400 bites total) from irradiated uninfected mosquitoes (mock-immunization). The target dose is 960 infectious bites.
Challenge occurs 3 weeks after final immunization.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Nonimmunized</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>No protective intervention given.
Challenge occurs directly after screening.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: PfRAS-infected</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>3 to 7 doses (immunizations) of approximately 200 infectious bites (200-400 bites total) from PfRAS-infected mosquitoes (true-immunization). The target dose is dependent on protection results in cohort 1.
Challenge occurs 3 weeks after final immunization.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Noninfected</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo. 3 to 7 doses of approximately 200 infectious bites (200-400 bites total) from irradiated, uninfected mosquitoes (true-immunization). The target dose is dependent on protection results in cohort 1.
Challenge occurs 3 weeks after final immunization.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Nonimmunized</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>No protective intervention given.
Challenge occurs directly after screening.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hyperimmunity PfRAS-infected</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 1 sub-cohort
3 doses (immunizations) of approximately 200 infectious bites (200-400 bites total) from PfRAS-infected mosquitoes. The target dose is dependent on protection results in cohort 1. This arm will receive the first 3 immunizations of Cohort 2.
Challenge occurs 3 weeks after final immunization.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PfRAS</intervention_name>
    <description>Radiation-attenuated Plasmodium falciparum sporozoites (PfRAS) administered by the bite of infected Anopheles stephensi mosquitoes</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: PfRAS-infected</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: PfRAS-infected</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Hyperimmunity PfRAS-infected</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>True-immunization</other_name>
    <other_name>PfRAS infected Anopheles stephensi mosquitoes</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Administered by the bite of noninfected Anopheles stephensi mosquitoes</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Noninfected</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Noninfected</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Mock-immunization</other_name>
    <other_name>Noninfected Anopheles stephensi mosquites</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Challenge</intervention_name>
    <description>5 infectious Anopheles stephensi mosquito bites carrying infectious Plasmodium falciparum sporozoites within a controlled clinical environment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: PfRAS-infected</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Noninfected</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Nonimmunized</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: PfRAS-infected</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Noninfected</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Nonimmunized</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Hyperimmunity PfRAS-infected</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy adults (male or non-pregnant, non-breastfeeding female) 18-50 years of age
             (inclusive).

          -  Available and willing to participate for duration of study.

          -  Able and willing to provide written informed consent.

          -  Able to complete an Assessment of Understanding with a score of at least 70% correct.

          -  In good general health with no clinically significant health problems as established
             by medical history, physical exam and laboratory screening.

          -  Females of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test at screening
             and agree to not become pregnant or breastfeed for the duration of the study. She
             must be willing to use a reliable form of contraception during the study. Reliable
             forms of birth control include use of condoms, diaphragm or cervical cap, birth
             control pills, IUD or sperm killing products.

          -  Agree to refrain from blood donation (except as required in this study) for 3 years
             following P falciparum challenge.

          -  Agree not to travel to a malaria-endemic region during the study.

          -  Good peripheral venous access.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Positive Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV), Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), or
             Hepatitis C virus (HCV) serology.

          -  Positive sickle cell screening test, including evidence of sickle trait.

          -  Positive by CSP or AMA1 ELISpot assay or ELISA

          -  Anemia (below normal reference laboratory value of hemoglobin) on screening.

          -  Weight less than 110 pounds.

          -  Any history of malaria infection or travel to a malaria endemic region within 6
             months prior to first immunization.

          -  History of long-term residence (&gt; 5 years) in area known to have significant
             transmission of P falciparum [cumulative lifetime exposure].

          -  Use of systemic immunosuppressant pharmacotherapy (inhaled and topical steroids are
             allowed) within 60 days of scheduled leukapheresis or immunization.

          -  Current significant medical condition (cardiovascular, hepatic, renal, pulmonary, or
             hematological) or evidence of any other serious underlying medical condition
             identified by medical history, physical examination, or laboratory examination
             (includes bleeding disorders).

          -  Plan for surgery between enrollment and day 28 post-challenge.

          -  Receipt of immunoglobulin and/or any blood products within 90 days of scheduled
             leukapheresis or immunization.

          -  Evidence of increased cardiovascular disease risk (defined as &gt; 5%-10%, 5-year risk)
             as determined by the method of Gaziano (2008). Risk factors include sex, age (years),
             systolic blood pressure (mm Hg), smoking status, body mass index (BMI, kg/m2),
             reported diabetes status, and blood pressure.

          -  An abnormal electrocardiogram (ECG), defined as one showing pathologic Q waves and
             significant ST-T wave changes; left ventricular hypertrophy; any non-sinus rhythm
             excluding isolated premature atrial contractions; right or left bundle branch block;
             or advanced (secondary or tertiary) A-V heart block.

          -  History of a splenectomy.

          -  History of any other illness or condition which, in the investigator's judgment, may
             substantially increase the risk associated with the subject's participation in the
             protocol or compromise the scientific objectives. This may include psychiatric
             disorders (such as personality disorders, anxiety disorders, or schizophrenia) or
             behavioral tendencies (including active alcohol or drug abuse) discovered during the
             screening process that in the opinion of the investigator would make compliance with
             the protocol difficult.

          -  History of anaphylactic or other severe response to mosquito bites (history of local
             hypersensitivity reactions is allowed).

          -  History of retinal disease, visual field changes, psoriasis, porphyria, or known
             allergy to the anti-malarial chloroquine phosphate, which will be used to treat
             subjects developing malaria after CHMI.

          -  Participation in any study involving any investigational vaccine or drug within 90
             days prior to the screening visit, or plan to participate in another investigational
             vaccine/drug research during or within 1 month following participation in this study.

          -  Use or planned use of any drug with antimalarial activity that would coincide with
             immunization or challenge.

          -  Anticipated use of medications known to cause drug reactions with chloroquine or
             atovaquone-proguanil (Malarone) such as cimetidine, metoclopramide, antacids, and
             kaolin.

          -  Any other significant findings which, in the investigator's judgment, may
             substantially increase.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bradley Hickey, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Naval Medical Research Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bradley Hickey, MD</last_name>
    <phone>850-479-0751</phone>
    <email>Bradley.Hickey@med.navy.mil</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Judith Epstein, MD</last_name>
    <phone>301-252-9026</phone>
    <email>Judith.Epstein@med.navy.mil</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Naval Medical Research Center Clinical Trials Center (CTC)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20889</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bradley Hickey, MD</last_name>
      <phone>850-479-0751</phone>
      <email>Bradley.Hickey@med.navy.mil</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Judith Epstein, MD</last_name>
      <phone>301-295-8025</phone>
      <email>Judith.Epstein@med.navy.mil</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bradley Hickey, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Judith Epstein, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alexandra Singer, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cindy Tamminga, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 19, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 19, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
