<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="139722">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02128282</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>S4-13-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02128282</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of CX-4945 in Combination With Gemcitabine and Cisplatin for Frontline Treatment of Cholangiocarcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Study of CX-4945 in Combination With Gemcitabine and Cisplatin in the Frontline Treatment of Patients With Cholangiocarcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Senhwa Biosciences, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Senhwa Biosciences, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study considers the safety and tolerability of increasing doses of CX-4945 in
      combination with gemcitabine plus cisplatin to determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD),
      followed by a randomized study that compares antitumor activity in cholangiocarcinoma
      patients receiving the standard of care gemcitabine plus cisplatin versus CX-4945 at the
      combination MTD with gemcitabine plus cisplatin.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Protein kinase CK2 is a constitutively active serine/threonine kinase with a long history as
      a pro-survival, anti-apoptotic kinase.  Given the wide spread overexpression of CK2 in
      multiple cancers and its role in multiple non-oncogenic processes required to sustain the
      cancer phenotype, a selective inhibitor of CK2 is an attractive targeted approach to
      treating cancer.

      CX-4945 is a tetracyclic, small molecule carboxylate acid salt that exhibits potent and
      highly selective inhibition of CK2.  Protein kinase CK2 is also known to play an important
      role in the DNA damage repair mechanisms of cancer cells, and this study of CX-4945 in
      combination with gemcitabine plus cisplatin will determine if inhibition of CK2, in
      conjunction with the use of chemotherapy drugs, will result in improved clinical outcomes
      for patients with non-resectable cholangiocarcinoma.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD) of CX-4945 when used in combination with gemcitabine plus cisplatin</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to twenty-one (21) days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The Maximum Tolerated Dose of CX-4945 will be determined from safety observations during the first cycle, as the CX-4945 dose is escalated in cohorts of three patients in combination with standard gemcitabine plus cisplatin.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of the Objective Response Rate (ORR) between the test and the control arms using Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) v.1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization to date of progression or death from any cause up to 52 weeks.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Tumor measurements will be compared to baseline every six weeks, and the ORR will be determined using RECIST v. 1.1.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Cholangiocarcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CX-4945 and cisplatin plus gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CX-4945 capsules at the combination MTD on Days 0, 1 and 2, and Days 7, 8 and 9.
PLUS Cisplatin 25 mg/m.sq. by IV infusion on Days 1 and 8. PLUS Gemcitabine 1,000 mg/m.sq. by IV infusion on Days 1 and 8. On a 21 day cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cisplatin plus Gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cisplatin 25 mg/m.sq. by IV infusion on Days 1 and 8. PLUS Gemcitabine 1,000 mg/m.sq. by IV infusion on Days 1 and 8. On a 21 day cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CX-4945</intervention_name>
    <description>Capsules administered twice daily on Days 0, 1 and 2, and Days 7, 8 and 9 of each 21 day cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CX-4945 and cisplatin plus gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CX-4945</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cisplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>25 mg/m.sq. administered by IV infusion on Days 1 and 8 of a 21 day cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CX-4945 and cisplatin plus gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cisplatin plus Gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Platinol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gemcitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>1,000 mg/m.sq. administered by IV infusion on Days 1 and 8 of a 21 day cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CX-4945 and cisplatin plus gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cisplatin plus Gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Gemzar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of an unresectable liver mass consistent with cholangiocarcinoma, for which
             treatment with gemcitabine plus cisplatin is intended.

          -  For patients enrolled in the Dose Escalation Phase, one or more tumors measurable on
             radiograph or CT scan, or evaluable disease defined as non-measurable lesions per
             RECIST v. 1.1 (e.g., malignant ascites). All patients enrolled to the Randomized
             Study Phase must have measurable disease only.

          -  Laboratory data as specified below:

               -  Hematology: Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;1,500 cells/mm3, platelet count
                  &gt;100,000 cells/ mm.cu. and hemoglobin &gt; 9 g/dL

               -  Hepatic: bilirubin &lt;1.5 X Upper Limit of Normal (ULN); alkaline phosphatase
                  (ALP), alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &lt; 5.0
                  X ULN

               -  Renal: serum creatinine within normal limits (WNL), defined as within 25% of the
                  institution's stated reference range, or a calculated creatinine clearance &gt;45
                  mL/min/1.73 m. sq. for patients with abnormal, increased, creatinine levels.

               -  Coagulation: International Normalized Ratio (INR) &lt; 1.5 times normal, activated
                  Partial Thromboplastin Time (aPTT) &lt; 1.5 times normal. Patients receiving
                  therapeutic doses of anticoagulant therapy may be considered eligible for the
                  trial if INR and aPTT are within the acceptable therapeutic limits for the
                  institution.

          -  Estimated life expectancy of at least 3 months.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status 0 - 1.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A history of prior systemic treatment with gemcitabine or cisplatin. At least six
             months must have elapsed if gemcitabine or cisplatin was administered in an adjuvant
             treatment setting.

          -  Seizure disorders requiring anticonvulsant therapy.

          -  Known brain metastases (unless previously treated and well controlled for a period of
             at least 3 months).

          -  Major surgery other than diagnostic surgery, within 4 weeks prior to the first dose
             of test drug, minor surgery including diagnostic surgery within 2 weeks (14 days)
             excluding central IV port placements and needle aspirate/core biopsies. Radio
             frequency ablation or transcatheter arterial chemoembolization within 6 weeks prior
             to the first dose of test drug.

          -  Treatment with radiation therapy or surgery within one month prior to study entry.

          -  Treatment with chemotherapy or investigational drugs within 21 days prior to the
             screening visit. Acute toxicities from prior therapy must have resolved to Grade ≤ 1
             above baseline.

          -  Patients with a history of another malignancy within 3 years of the baseline visit.
             (Patients with cutaneous carcinomas or in-situ carcinomas will be considered for
             study entry on a case-by-case basis).

          -  Concurrent severe or uncontrolled medical disease (i.e., systemic infection,
             diabetes, hypertension, coronary artery disease, congestive heart failure).

          -  Active symptomatic fungal, bacterial and/or viral infection including active HIV or
             viral (A, B or C) hepatitis.

          -  Difficulty with swallowing or an active malabsorption syndrome.

          -  Chronic diarrhea (excess of 2-3 stools/day above normal frequency).

          -  Gastrointestinal diseases including gastritis, ulcerative colitis, Crohn's disease,
             or hemorrhagic coloproctitis.

          -  History of gastric or small bowel surgery involving any extent of gastric or small
             bowel resection.

          -  Clinically significant bleeding event within the last 3 months, unrelated to trauma,
             or underlying condition that would be expected to result in a bleeding diathesis.

          -  Patients who have exhibited allergic reactions to a similar structural compound or to
             a formulation component of CX-4945.

          -  Concomitant use either of warfarin and/or 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A
             (HMG-CoA) reductase inhibitors (statins).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mitesh Borad, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85259-5499</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mayo Clinic Clinical Trials Office</last_name>
      <phone>507-538-7623</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mitesh Borad, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 28, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cholangiocarcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Bile duct cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Biliary tract cancer</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cholangiocarcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Gemcitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
