<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="53560">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01787331</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CC#125513</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01787331</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase II Study of Itraconazole in Biochemical Relapse</brief_title>
  <official_title>Hedgehog Inhibition as a Non-Castrating Approach to Hormone Sensitive Prostate Cancer: A Phase II Study of Itraconazole in Biochemical Relapse</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Charles Ryan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is being done to test an investigational drug called itraconazole in the
      treatment of prostate cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase II, single arm study of itraconazole dosed at 300 mg PO BID in patients with
      noncastrate, non-metastatic, biochemically relapsed prostate cancer after prior definitive
      local therapy. Simon's two stage minimax design will be followed for accrual and include an
      interim test for lack of efficacy. There is a pre-specified stopping rule for safety after
      10 patients have been treated for a minimum of 8 weeks of protocol therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Patients Who Achieve Greater than 50% decline in Prostate Specific Antigen</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine whether the proportion of patients who achieve a ≥ 50% decline in serum PSA after 12 weeks of protocol therapy with itraconazole dosed at 300 mg BID is superior to a historical control based upon the observed PSA response proportion in prior studies of non-castrating systemic therapy in men with biochemically relapsed hormone sensitive prostate cancer. PSA progression will be defined as follows: (1) If no PSA decline is observed on therapy, PSA progression will be defined as an increase in serum PSA &gt; 50% above the baseline PSA, and an absolute increase of &gt; 2 ng/mL above baseline, confirmed by repeat measurement at least 2 weeks later (2) If PSA declines on therapy, PSA progression will be defined as an increase in serum PSA &gt; 50% above the nadir PSA on therapy, and an absolute increase &gt; 2 ng/mL above the nadir, confirmed by repeat measurement at least 2 weeks later.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of Median Time to PSA Progression</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the median time to PSA progression from the start of protocol therapy with itraconazole among men with biochemically relapsed prostate cancer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of Median Time to Clinical Progession</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the median time to clinical progression measured from the start of protocol therapy with itraconazole among men with biochemically relapsed prostate cancer. Clinical progression will be defined as the first occurrence of either the development of metastases or initiation of non-protocol therapy, and will exclude PSA-only progression. Clinical progression will be defined as the first occurrence of either the development of metastases or initiation of non-protocol therapy, and will exclude PSA-only progression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of Median Metastasis-Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the median metastasis-free survival measured from the start of protocol therapy in patients treated with itraconazole for biochemically relapsed prostate cancer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of Mean Percent Change Compared with pre-treatment in PSA doubling time</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the mean percent change from baseline after 12 weeks of protocol therapy compared with pre-treatment in PSA doubling time. The pre-treatment PSA doubling time will be determined based upon all PSA measurements obtained within 3 months prior to Day 1 of protocol therapy, with a minimum of three PSA measurements spaced at least 14 days apart.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Grade Toxicities Observed during Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To characterize the safety profile of itraconazole in the biochemically relapsed hormone sensitive prostate cancer population as graded by CTCAE version 4.03.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of the mean steady-state trough level of serum</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the mean steady-state itraconazole with its active metabolite (hydroxy-itraconazole) serum levels after 4 weeks of therapy with itraconazole.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Endocrine Parameters: Mean Percent Change in Serum Androgen Levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the mean percent change from baseline in serum androgen levels, including serum testosterone, DHEA-S, and androstenedione, after 4 and 12 weeks of protocol therapy with itraconazole.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Enodrine Parameters: Mean Percent Change in Additional Serume hormone levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the mean percent change from baseline in additional serum hormone levels, including adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH), aldosterone, deoxycorticosterone (DOC), 11-deoxycortisol, and cortisol after 4 and 12 weeks of protocol therapy with itraconazole.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Endocrine Parameters: Determination of Relationship between serum hormone levels and serum PSA decline</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine if there is a relationship between baseline and/or percent change in serum hormone levels and achieving a decline of &gt; 50% in serum PSA after 12 weeks of protocol therapy.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Hedgehog Pathway: Determination of Proportion of Patients who display down-regulation of Hedgehog pathway</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To  determine  the  proportion  of  patients  treated  with  itraconazole  who  display  a  down - regulation of the Hedgehog pathway, as assessed by measurement of GLI1 mRNA expression by qRT-PCR on serial skin biopsies obtained at baseline and after 4 weeks of protocol therapy. Down-regulation will be defined as a decline of any magnitude in GLI1 mRNA expression after 4 weeks of protocol therapy compared to baseline expression level.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Hedgehog Pathway: Determination of Relationship between down-regulation of Hedgehod pathway and PSA modulation</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine if there is a relationship between down-regulation of the Hedgehog pathway and PSA modulation, including proportion of patients achieving a decline of &gt; 50% in serum PSA as well as time to PSA progression.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Hedgehog Pathway: Evaluation of tissue for baseline Hedgehog pathway status</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate archived primary prostate cancer tissue (biopsy or prostatectomy specimen) for baseline Hedgehog pathway status, using both qRT-PCR-based mRNA expression analysis and protein-based immunohistochemical (IHC) analysis of key Hedgehog pathway components (GLI1, PCTH1, SMO) and Sonic hedgehog ligand.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Hedgehog Pathway: Determination of relationship between expression of components in Hedgehod pathway and PSA modulation</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine if there is a relationship between mRNA and IHC expression of components in the Hedgehog pathway in primary prostate cancer tissue and PSA modulation, including the proportion of patients achieving a decline of ≥ 50% in serum PSA as well as time to PSA progression.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Itraconazole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Taken at a dose of 300 mg by mouth twice daily (600 mg a day total).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Itraconazole</intervention_name>
    <description>Itraconazole is available as pink and blue capsules. Itraconazole should be taken with meals or within 30 minutes after a meal.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Itraconazole</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sporanox</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologic confirmation of adenocarcinoma of the prostate

          2. Biochemically relapsed disease with a rising PSA on at least two consecutive
             measurements at least two weeks apart after prior definitive local therapy (radical
             prostatectomy, external beam radiation, or brachytherapy) or combination of radical
             prostatectomy and radiotherapy (RT) with curative intent

          3. Prior primary or salvage radiation or not a candidate for salvage radiation due to
             patient preference or clinical assessment based upon disease characteristics and/or
             patient co-morbidities.

          4. Minimum PSA: If no prior androgen deprivation therapy (ADT) for biochemical relapse:

               -  1.0 ng/mL if prior radical prostatectomy with or without adjuvant/salvage
                  radiation therapy, confirmed by repeat measurement at least 2 weeks later, or

               -  Nadir + 2 ng/mL if prior RT alone without prior radical prostatectomy, confirmed
                  by repeat measurement at least 2 weeks later If prior ADT for biochemical
                  relapse:

               -  4.0 ng/mL or &gt; 2 ng/mL above nadir on prior cycle of ADT, whichever is higher,
                  confirmed by repeat measurement at least 2 weeks later

          5. No evidence of metastatic disease on imaging by whole body bone scan (technetium-99
             or Na-F PET bone scan) and cross-sectional imaging of the abdomen/pelvis (CT or MRI)
             within 6 weeks of Day 1 of protocol therapy

          6. Prior androgen deprivation therapy (ADT) with LHRH agonist and/or antagonist allowed
             for either (neo)adjuvant treatment with local therapy or for biochemical relapse

          7. Last effective dose of LHRH agonist/antagonist &quot;expired&quot; &gt; 3 months prior to study
             entry.

          8. For example, a patient receiving LHRH agonist injection every 3 months would be
             eligible provided their last injection was &gt; 6 months prior to Day 1 of protocol
             therapy. A patient receiving LHRH agonist injections every 4 months will be eligible
             provided last injection was &gt; 7 months prior to Day 1 of protocol therapy.

          9. Serum testosterone level: If no prior androgen deprivation therapy:

             - A single measurement greater than 150 ng/dL within 3 months of day 1 of protocol
             therapy If prior androgen deprivation therapy (either in adjuvant or biochemical
             relapse setting):

             The two most recent measurements of serum testosterone prior to Day 1 of protocol
             therapy must fulfill the following criteria:

               -  Both measurements are greater than 150 ng/dL.

               -  The two measurements are spaced at least 14 days apart.

               -  Both must be measured within 3 months of Day 1 of protocol therapy.

               -  There must not be an increase of &gt; 50 ng/dL between these two successive
                  measurements.

         10. PSA doubling time (PSADT) ≤ 15 months, calculated based upon all serum PSA
             measurements obtained within 3 months prior to Day 1 of protocol therapy, with a
             minimum of three PSA measurements spaced at least 14 days apart (see section 6). PSA
             values obtained when serum testosterone was known to be less than 150 ng/dL, prior to
             local therapy, or within three months of last dose of LHRH agonist/antagonist or
             antiandrogen will be excluded from the calculation of the PSADT. PSADT calculation to
             be carried out using the following website:
             http://nomograms.mskcc.org/Prostate/PsaDoublingTime.aspx

         11. Total bilirubin less than 1.5 times upper limit of normal (ULN), or less than 3 times
             ULN at study entry in a patient with documented Gilbert‟s disease.

         12. ALT and AST levels less than 1.5 times ULN at study entry

         13. Serum potassium greater than 3.5 mmol/L without oral supplementation

         14. No history of uncontrolled hypertension (blood pressure &gt; 160/100 mm Hg despite
             anti-hypertensive medication)

         15. ECOG performance status of 0 or 1

         16. Estimated life expectancy greater than 5 years

         17. Age greater than or equal to 18 years at time of study entry

         18. Ability to sign written informed consent

         19. Ability to swallow study drug whole as a capsule

         20. Primary prostate cancer tissue available for analysis is not required for inclusion
             onto this study but is strongly encouraged.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Castrate-resistant disease, as evidenced by either:

               -  Rising PSA on 2 consecutive measurements at least 2 weeks apart with concurrent
                  documented serum testosterone &lt; 50 ng/dL at the time of PSA measurement, or

               -  Rising PSA on 2 consecutive measurements at least 2 weeks apart measured within
                  3 months after last LHRH agonist/antagonist injection

          2. Prior bilateral orchiectomy

          3. Congestive heart failure of NYHA class III or higher severity at study entry

          4. History of chronic active hepatitis

          5. Grade 2 or higher peripheral neuropathy at the time of study entry

          6. Use of 5-alpha reductase antagonist (i.e. finasteride, dutasteride) or antiandrogen
             (i.e. flutamide, bicalutamide) within 6 weeks of Day 1 of protocol therapy

          7. Use of systemic steroids at an equivalent dose of prednisone 5 mg/day or higher
             within 6 weeks of Day 1 of protocol therapy

          8. Use of medications or herbal supplements which are known to potentially lower serum
             PSA within 6 weeks of Day 1 of protocol therapy

          9. Use of other medications that may potentially interact with itraconazole within 1
             week of study entry

         10. Use of other investigational agents within 6 weeks of Day 1 of protocol therapy

         11. Prior pathology consistent with small cell carcinoma or prostate cancer with
             predominantly neuroendocrine differentiation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Charles Ryan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paula Dutton</last_name>
    <phone>415-885-7871</phone>
    <email>walshp@medicine.ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Charles Ryan, MD</last_name>
    <phone>415-353-9279</phone>
    <email>ryanc@medicine.ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California San Francisco</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paula Dutton</last_name>
      <phone>415-885-7871</phone>
      <email>mailto:walshp@medicine.ucsf.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Charles Ryan, MD</last_name>
      <phone>415-353-9279</phone>
      <email>ryanc@medicine.ucsf.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Charles Ryan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 19, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 6, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Charles Ryan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Genitourinary cancer specialist, Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>biochemically relapsed</keyword>
  <keyword>hormone sensitive</keyword>
  <keyword>non-metastatic</keyword>
  <keyword>prostate cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>after prior definitive local therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>PSA</keyword>
  <keyword>Hedgehog-signaling pathway</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Itraconazole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydroxyitraconazole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
