<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="4754">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01766102</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-107</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01766102</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intra-operative Digital vs. Standard Mammography</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Comparison of Intra-Operative Digital Specimen Mammography to Standard Specimen Mammography</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A breast biopsy in the operating room may be needed in up to 15% of patients with an
      abnormality on mammogram. When an abnormality is present but there is no palpable mass, the
      abnormality must be localized with a wire before going to the operating room. This technique
      is also used when a breast cancer is present but there is no mass, in order to perform a
      targeted lumpectomy. Once the abnormality is surgically removed, the specimen with the wire
      is taken to the breast imaging department for a specimen x-ray to ensure that the targeted
      abnormality is present within the specimen. If the abnormality is close to the edge of the
      specimen, additional tissue is often removed.

      A newer method for evaluating the specimen is to perform imaging in the operating room.
      Portable digital mammography units are available for this purpose. The Biovision digital
      specimen mammography system is FDA-approved and currently in use in over 200 centers in the
      United States. Several studies have shown that intra-operative digital mammography is as
      accurate as standard specimen mammography and takes less time to perform. It may also
      decrease the chance of  having to go back to the operating room to take more breast tissue
      after lumpectomy because of cancer cells near teh margin(s) of the specimen on final
      pathology. Having to go back to the operating room to take more tissue is called a
      re-excision.

      The purpose of this study is to compare standard specimen mammography to intra-operative
      specimen mammography to quantify potential operating room time savings and to determine if
      the use of intra-operative specimen mammography decreases re-excision rates. We aim to see
      if intra-operative specimen mammography is more efficient and if it decreases re-excision
      rates.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Before the research starts patients will undergo some screening procedures to determine if
      patients are eligible to participate. This includes a medical history and an assessment of
      the patient's breast abnormality by mammogram and/or ultrasound and/or breast MRI. Patients
      will not need to undergo any extra procedures apart from those needed by the patient's
      surgeon to plan the patient's breast surgery. If the screening process shows that a patient
      is eligible to participate in this research study, the patient will be enrolled and the
      study will proceed on the day of surgery. If a patient does not meet the eligibility
      criteria the patient will not be able to participate in this research study.

      Patients will be assigned to one of two arms of this study on the day of your surgery.
      Because no one knows which of the breast specimen imaging options is best, patients will be
      &quot;randomized&quot; into one of the study groups: the Standard Specimen Mammography arm or, the
      Intra-operative Specimen Mammography arm. Randomization means that the patient is put into a
      group by chance. It is like flipping a coin. Neither the patient nor the surgeon will choose
      what group the patient will be in.

      If the patient is in the Standard Specimen Mammography arm, the patient's breast specimen
      (biopsy or lumpectomy) will be taken to the Breast Imaging department for a mammogram, which
      is the way breast specimens are typically imaged. If the patient is in the Intra-Operative
      Specimen Mammography arm, the patient's breast specimen will be imaged right in the
      operating room at the time of the surgery. The patient's images will also be linked to the
      Breast Imaging department, so the radiologist can confirm the surgeon's findings.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of Operative Time Savings</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To compare the overall operative time savings using intra-operative digital mammography compared with standard specimen mammography. This will be reported as minutes in the operating room.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of Radiographic and Pathologic Findings</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the rate of positive margin of a lumpectomy specimen based on final pathology for patients treated with intra-operative specimen radiograph compared with standard compression mammography. This will be report as a percent of patients in each arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intra-operative Mammography</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intra-operative Specimen Mammography</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Mammography</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard Specimen Mammography</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intra-operative Mammography</intervention_name>
    <description>The patient's breast specimen will be imagine in the operating room in an intra-operative imaging device - Biovision SN #30042</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intra-operative Mammography</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Biovision SN # 30042</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Mammography</intervention_name>
    <description>There is not an added device associated with this arm.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Mammography</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Newly diagnosed with a breast abnormality undergoing an excisional biopsy with wire
             localization or newly diagnosed with invasive breast cancer or ductal carcinoma
             undergoing a lumpectomy with wire localization

          -  Ability to understand and willingness to sign a written informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Recurrent breast cancer

          -  Palpable masses not requiring wire localization
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michelle Specht, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>MIchelle Specht, MD</last_name>
    <phone>617-726-0340</phone>
    <email>mspecht@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michelle Specht, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-726-0340</phone>
      <email>mspecht@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michelle Specht, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 9, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 8, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michelle Specht</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mammography</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
