<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="77166">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01815645</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2011/01469-7 (FAPESP)</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01815645</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Contingency Management Treatment for Crack Addiction - Study With Brazilian Population</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluating the Efficacy of Including Contingency Management to Standard Ambulatory Treatment for Crack Addiction - A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Federal University of São Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Federal University of São Paulo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Brazil: National Committee of Ethics in Research</authority>
    <authority>Brazil: Fundação de Amparo a Pesquisa do Estado de Sao Paulo</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Crack addiction has became a severe health problem in Brazil. Today, crack addiction is the
      primary cause for inpatient treatment (voluntary or not) for all illicit substances (losing
      only for alcohol addiction). A survey study conducted with children and adolescents
      currently living in the streets of 5 major cities of Brazil, point alarming results in which
      15% to 26% of all these children have smoked crack at least once in the last month.

      When compared to cocaine, crack users develop much faster diagnoses for crack dependence
      (mean of 5 month after first use), shows a more compulsive pattern of use, has higher
      probability of living or have lived in the streets, and of engaging in illegal activities.
      Consequently to this, mortality of crack addicts are 7 times higher than for the rest of the
      population.

      Despite all efforts being made for the development of effective pharmacological treatments
      for stimulant addiction (crack included), up to today, there is no robust evidence of
      efficacy of any pharmacological treatment. For that reason, the use of evidence based
      psychosocial interventions is so important for treating this population.

      Although today open treatment facilities in Brazil are more and more starting to use
      evidence based interventions such as motivational interviewing, cognitive behavior therapy,
      relapse prevention and coping skills, such treatments present very modest results when
      treating crack addiction. The biggest difficulties encountered when treating this population
      are maintaining patients in treatment, reducing crack use and achieving continued
      abstinence.

      A psychosocial treatment based in behavioral principals' named Contingency Management (CM)
      is widely applied in the USA.  Recent meta-analyses and review studies present robust
      evidence that, when applied alone or in adjunction with other psychosocial and
      pharmacological treatment, CM is the most effective treatment for what regards, treatment
      retention, reducing drug use and promoting continued abstinence.

      The purpose of this study is to evaluate if Contingence Management (CM) treatment can be
      affective on the treatment of crack addiction for Brazilian population seeking outpatient
      treatment.

      To accomplish this, 60 individuals (male and female from 18 to 65 years of age) seeking open
      treatment for crack addiction will be randomized to 2 treatment conditions (Standard
      treatment (ST) or ST plus CM).  Both treatments will last 12 weeks with 3 and 6-month
      follow-up. In both groups patients will be encourage to leave urine samples 3 times week.

      Hypotheses: Patients receiving ST+CM will stay longer in treatment, have more negative tests
      for cocaine/crack, and achieve longer periods of cocaine/crack abstinence when compared to
      patients receiving ST alone.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment retention</measure>
    <time_frame>measured during the 12 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Data on Treatment retention will be collected considering participants that complete 12 weeks of treatment and participants that abandons treatment during the 12 weeks of study.
Specific time of drop-out will also be considered.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>reduction of crack use</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>promotion of continued abstinence</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>continued abstinence will be measured by considering all participants that achieved at least 8 weeks of continued abstinence.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beck depression inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks of treatment, 3 and 6-month follow up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>beck anxiety inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks of treatment and 3-6 month follow up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ASSIST scores on crack and other substances</measure>
    <time_frame>12 week of treatment 3 and 6 month follow up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cocaine craving Questionnaire Bief scores</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks of treatment and 3-6 month follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Minnesota  Cocaine Craving Scale scores</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks of treatment, 3-6month follow ups</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>reduction of crack use</measure>
    <time_frame>at 3 and 6-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Cocaine Related Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard treatment plus Contingency Management</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard treatment plus Contingence Management</intervention_name>
    <description>12 weeks of the standard treatment offered by a open treatment service for drug addiction of the city of Sao Paulo (AME) plus Contingency Management</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard treatment plus Contingency Management</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>standard treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>12 weeks of standard treatment offered by AME (a open treatment service for drug addiction of the city of Sao Paulo)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Current diagnose of crack addiction (DSM IV)

          -  having used crack in the last month

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current psychotic disorder

          -  Diagnose of schizophrenia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ronaldo R Laranjeira, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>EPM/UNIFESP</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ambulatorio Medico de Especialidades (AME) da Vila Maria</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sao Paulo</city>
        <state>SP</state>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 16, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Federal University of São Paulo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>André de Queiroz Constantino Miguel</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Ph.D Studant</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cocaine related disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Contingency Management</keyword>
  <keyword>psychosocial treatment</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cocaine-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
