<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="87490">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02098551</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>...</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02098551</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Skin Testing With Recombinant Bet v 1 and Hypoallergenic Recombinant Bet v 1 Fragments</brief_title>
  <official_title>Skin Testing With Recombinant Bet v 1 and Hypoallergenic Recombinant Bet v 1 Fragments to Dissect the Contribution of IgE to Chronic Allergic Skin Inflammation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stefan Woehrl</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical University of Vienna</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of Vienna</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Austria: Ethikkommission</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Aim of this study is to use Bet v 1, the major allergen of birch pollen, to investigate the
      contribution of IgE- versus non-IgE-mediated mechanisms to chronic skin inflammation in
      atopic dermatitis patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this study non-IgE-reactive recombinant Bet v 1 fragments (F1: aa 1-74; F2: aa 75-160)
      and the fully IgE-reactive recombinant Bet v 1 (aa 1-160)will be used for skin prick testing
      and atopy patch testing in birch pollen allergic patients with birch pollen induced
      exacerbation of atopic dermatitis. For control purposes birch pollen allergic patients
      without birch pollen-induced atopic eczema, persons with allergies other than to birch and
      non-allergic people will be tested.

      The individuals will be subjected to in vivo skin prick and atopy patch testing with rBet v
      1, rBet v 1 fragment 1, rBet v 1 fragment 2 and an equimolar mix of the rBet v 1 fragments.
      In parallel, the IgE reactivity, and in vitro T cell proliferation, and cytokine production
      will be studied. Those analyses should help to determine the relevance of IgE mediated
      mechanisms to chronic skin inflammation and T cell proliferation in AD patients.

      A staining for the surface markers chemokine receptor (CCR4)+ and cutaneous lymphocyte
      antigen (CLA)+ which reportedly are enriched in inflamed skin will further allow to
      investigate whether patients with high numbers of T lymphocytes expressing CCR4 and CLA tend
      to exhibit stronger skin inflammation. Moreover, allergen-specific antibody and T cell
      responses will be analyzed 6-8 weeks after the epicutaneous allergen application.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case-Only, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To investigate if the use of recombinant Bet v 1 and the non-IgE-reactive recombinant hypoallergenic Bet v 1 fragments in APT can induce late phase skin reaction inflammation in atopic dermatitis patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The non-IgE-reactive recombinant Bet v 1 fragments (F1: aa 1-74; F2: aa 75-160) and the fully IgE-reactive recombinant Bet v 1 (aa 1-160) will be used for atopy patch testing in birch pollen allergic patients with birch pollen induced exacerbation of atopic dermatitis. The substances will be applied for 48 h using aluminium cups (Finn Chambers on Scanpor, Large, Epitest Ltd Oy) containing birch pollen extract, 160 μg of rBet v 1, rBet v 1 fragment 1, rBet v 1 fragment 2 or a mix containing 80 μg of each rBet v 1 fragment. After 48 h the patches will be removed and reactions will be read and photodocumented.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary objective is to analyze whether atopy patch testing (APT) can induce allergen-specific antibody and cellular immune responses.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Atopic Dermatitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Four (4)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Group 1: Birch pollen-related atopic dermatitis (AD)  (n=15) Group 2: Birch pollen allergic patients without AD  (n=5) Group 3: Allergic individuals without birch pollen allergy  (n=5) Group 4: Non-allergic individuals  (n=5)
Patients will be tested by SPT and APT:
SPT: Histamine, buffer, commercial birch pollen extract, rBet v 1, rBet v 1 fragment 1, rBet v 1 fragment 2, and equimolar rBet v 1 fragment mix (20 and 40 μg/ml) in duplets.
APT: birch pollen extract, rBet v 1, rBet v 1 fragment 1, rBet v 1 fragment 2, equimolar mix of rBet v 1 fragments (160 μg/application); negative control with vaseline</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SPT and APT</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients will be tested by skin prick testing (SPT: Histamine, buffer, commercial birch pollen extract, rBet v 1 (20 and 40 μg/ml), rBet v 1 fragment 1 (20 and 40 μg/ml), rBet v 1 fragment 2 (20 and 40 μg/ml), equimolar rBet v 1 fragment mix (20 and 40 μg/ml) in duplets.
Atopy patch testing (APT: birch pollen extract, rBet v 1:160 μg/application, rBet v 1 fragment 1: 160 μg/application, rBet v 1 fragment 2: 160 μg/ml, equimolar mix of rBet v 1 fragments: 160 μg/application; negative control with vaseline alone.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Four (4)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Different types of individuals will be recruited and divided in four groups. A total of 30
        allergic and non-allergic persons will be included in this study:

        patients with Birch pollen-related atopic dermatitis (AD), Birch pollen allergic patients
        without AD (group 2), allergic individuals without birch pollen allergy and non-allergic
        individuals.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age between 18 and 75 years

          2. They will be available to complete the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Severe general maladies

          2. Severe skin inflammation in the test area

          3. Risk of non-controllable general reaction

          4. Pregnancy and breast-feeding

          5. Autoimmune diseases, immune-defects including immuno-suppression,
             immune-complex-induced immunopathies

          6. Contra-indication for adrenaline

          7. Patients under long-term treatment with systemic corticosteroids immunosuppressive
             drugs, tranquilizers or psychoactive drugs

          8. Positive IgE reaction on hypoallergenic Bet v 1 derivatives

          9. The subject is currently participating in another clinical study in which the subject
             is or will be exposed to an investigational or a non-investigational drug.

         10. The subject is at risk of non-compliance with the study procedures/restrictions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rudolf Valenta, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Medical University of Vienna</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical University of Vienna</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <zip>1090</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 25, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 26, 2011</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical University of Vienna</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Stefan Woehrl</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Mag. Dr. Stefan Wöhrl</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>atopic dermatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>bet v 1</keyword>
  <keyword>bet v 1 fragments</keyword>
  <keyword>allergy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis, Atopic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
