<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="35241">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02032420</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STAR vs. ART</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02032420</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of the STAR Maneuver on UGRA Training</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double Blinded Randomized Controlled Trial on the Effects of Four Sequential Maneuvers on Ultrasound Guided Nerve Block Performance</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of New Mexico</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of New Mexico</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Volunteers will watch a training video demonstrating how to place a needle in the correct
      position while keeping it visible. Later the volunteers will be placed in front of a set up
      identical to the video, and asked to demonstrate how to direct an 80 mm echogenic Pajunk
      needle into 3 targets in a standardized homemade phantom a total of three times.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      After watching the training video, each volunteer will be placed in front of a set up
      identical to the video seen. Adjacent to this set up, a single fellowship trained regional
      anesthesiologist known as the assessor is situated with a screen that allows real time
      viewing of the ultrasound screen seen by the volunteer. The assessor is blinded to the
      assignment of the volunteer. Also, the assessor does not have any visualization of the
      volunteer. This prevents visualizing hand or body movement that may cause a bias. The same
      assessor is used for the whole study to provide consistent assessment of the task.

      The task involves the volunteer directing an 80 mm echogenic Pajunk needle into 3 targets in
      a standardized homemade phantom. The targets simulate the nerve roots commonly found in the
      interscalene block. Thus, they are arranged diagonally to simulate the nerve root position
      commonly seen. Also, they are arranged on a tilt relative to the flat surface of the phantom
      to simulate the direction the nerve travels. This is important as the tilt of the target
      requires the volunteer to tilt the probe so that their incidental ultrasound wave is
      perpendicular to the target for the brightest reflection to occur. This phenomenon is known
      as anisotropy. This increases the realism of the task that cannot be imitated by
      commercially available phantoms.

      There are 3 goals that the volunteer must fulfill in performing their task. Firstly, they
      must direct the needle to the 12 o'clock position of the 3 targets. Secondly, they must
      achieve maximal ultrasound image brightness of the 3 targets at all times. Thirdly, the
      entire needle must be visualized at all times.

      If the needle is not in the correct position, the assessor will verbally inform the
      volunteer to redirect it to the correct position. If the target images are not at their
      brightest, the assessor will verbally inform the volunteer not to manipulate the needle
      towards the target until the targets are at their brightest. Clinically, this functions to
      prevent the needle being inserted inside the nerve as the targets are not clearly seen.
      Thirdly, if the needle is visualized entirely, the volunteer will be told to stop
      manipulating the needle towards the target until the needle is fully visualized by
      manipulating the probe. A timer records the cumulative time the needle is not in full
      visualization. Clinically, this functions to prevent the needle being inserted into a nerve
      or structure that it should not.

      After all 3 targets have been completed, the volunteer repeats the task a total of 3 times.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time taken to return a needle back to direct visualization.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to one year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Needle-not-seen time</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to one year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of time the needle is not visualized during the task</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Needle-not-seen count</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to one year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of times the needle is not visualized during the task</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Task completion time</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after training</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Time taken to complete task</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Performer fatigue</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to one year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Self-reported trainee fatigue on a numerical rating scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">62</enrollment>
  <condition>Simulator-based Training of Ultrasound-guided Regional Anesthesia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>STAR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Introductory training by video depicting 4 sequential maneuvers for reacquisition of needle image in ultrasound: see, tilt, align, rotate.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ART</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Introductory training with a video depicting 3 probe position aspects for reacquisition of needle image by ultrasound: alignment, rotation, tilt.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>STAR</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>STAR</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ART</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>ART</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy volunteers

          -  Right handed

          -  Aged 18 to 55

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any person who has prior knowledge about ultrasound imaging or regional anesthesia

          -  Any person who has prior experience with laparoscopy or biopsy

          -  Any person who has problems with depth of field or simple hand eye co-ordination task
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicholas Lam</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of New Mexico</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of New Mexico Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <state>New Mexico</state>
        <zip>87106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 9, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of New Mexico</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nicholas Lam</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
