<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="112552">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01798966</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TF-1111</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01798966</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Twenty-four Hour Intraocular Pressure Patterns in Patients With Uncontrolled Thyroid Eye Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effects of Orbital Decompression Surgery on Intraocular Pressure Patterns in Patient With Thyroid Eye Disease Undergoing 24 Hour Continuous IOP Monitoring With the SENSIMED Triggerfish®</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sensimed AG</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, San Diego</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sensimed AG</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients with Thyroid Eye Disease (TED) often have enlarged extraocular muscles and higher
      orbital fat contents due to their disease process. The confined space of the orbit cannot
      hold the enlarged orbital contents creating a forward displacement and/or compression of the
      globe with a rise in intraocular pressure (IOP). Many of these patients undergo surgical
      decompression, a procedure that fractures orbital bones, in order to allow more space for
      the enlarged orbital contents to occupy. To date, there is no data that shows intraocular
      patterns over a 24-hour period in patients with mechanical compression on the globe as in
      TED. It is not know if the pattern of IOP is more consistent with normal IOP patterns,
      glaucomatous patterns, or perhaps completely different then either. The goal of this project
      is to investigate patterns of IOP in patients requiring orbital decompression because of
      orbital congestion. Changes in IOP during a 24-hour period will be studied with a
      contact-lens embedded sensor that provides continuous data. This device has previously been
      investigated and shown to be safe and well-tolerated. Monitoring the pattern in these
      patients will allow us to compare Thyroid TED patterns of IOP with those of normal and
      glaucomatous patients. Also, testing these patients before and after orbital decompression
      surgery will allow characterization of how intraocular pressure changes once the mechanical
      compression on the globe is relieved.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in IOP before and after orbital decompression surgery in patients with TED using the SENSIMED Triggerfish® 24-hour IOP monitoring contact lens</measure>
    <time_frame>within 24 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To investigate the difference in SENSIMED Triggerfish output during transition from wake to sleep states</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>IOP patterns</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The pattern of IOP in patients with TED will be compared with the pattern of IOP readings in normal subjects as well as glaucomatous patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events and Serious adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>4 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety will be evaluated throughout the duration of the study by collecting all adverse events</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Thyroid Eye Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SENSIMED Triggerfish</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SENSIMED Triggerfish</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>SENSIMED Triggerfish</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Contact lens sensor intented to continuously record IOP pattern for up to 24 hours</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject is able to comply with the study procedures

          -  18-80 years old

          -  Subjects diagnosed with Thyroid Eye Disease based on both endocrinology studies
             showing autoimmune dysfunction consistent with Graves' Disease as well as orbital
             imaging studies manifesting characteristics consistent with Thyroid Eye Disease.

          -  Ability to understand the character and individual consequences of the study

          -  Subject has consented to be in the trial

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with contraindications for wearing contact lenses

          -  Severe ocular surface disease

          -  Keratoconus or other corneal abnormality

          -  Severe ocular inflammation

          -  Full frame metal glasses during SENSIMED Triggerfish® monitoring

          -  Known hypersensitivity to silicone, plaster or ocular anesthesia (proparacaine)

          -  Simultaneous participation in other clinical studies

          -  Diagnosis of glaucoma
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Donald O Kikkawa, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Diego</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shiley Eye Center, University of California, San Diego</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Jolla</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92093-0496</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 5, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 21, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Eye Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thyroid Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Graves Ophthalmopathy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
