<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="79048">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02055846</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PPPR / IPC 2012-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02055846</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Analysis of the Mechanisms of Actions of Heat Shock Protein (Hsp27) Responsible of the Androgen-independent Evolution in Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Analysis of the Mechanisms of Actions of Hsp27 Responsible of the Androgen-independent Evolution in Prostate Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institut Paoli-Calmettes</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institut Paoli-Calmettes</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>France: Agence Nationale de Sécurité du Médicament et des produits de santé</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Prostate cancer (PC) represents one of the most common cancers in industrialized countries.
      Patients with localized disease may be treated with surgery or radiation, while androgen
      ablation is used as first-line therapy in patients with metastatic disease. While most
      patients initially respond well to this hormonal therapy, they most ultimately become
      unresponsive and recur within 2 years as androgen-independent prostate cancer (AIPC).
      Recently, docetaxel-based regimens have demonstrated improved survival in men with AIPC in
      two different, large, phase III studies. However, the median overall survival was prolonged
      for only 2 or 3 months. Androgen independent (AI) progression involves variable combinations
      of clonal selection, adaptive up-regulation of anti-apoptotic genes, ligand-independent
      androgen receptor (AR) activation, alternative growth factor pathways, and immune system
      escape. Additional therapeutic strategies targeting molecular mechanisms mediating
      resistance, combined with immunotherapy must be developed. One strategy to improve therapies
      in advanced PC involves targeting genes that are activated by androgen withdrawal, either to
      delay or prevent the emergence of the resistant AI phenotype. Recently, a
      scientist,identified Heat Shock Protein (Hsp27) as a highly over-expressed gene in AIPC.
      Hsp27 knockdown using antisens oligonucleotides (ASO) and small interfering RNA (siRNA)
      increased apoptotic rates and enhanced hormone- and chemo-therapy in PC. She developed and
      patented a 2nd generation ASO targeting Hsp27 that has been licensed (investigational drug
      called OGX-427) and clinical trials phase I/II is currently in process in PC. Despite
      OGX-427 efficiency, the functional role of stress induced Hsp27 in castration or
      chemotherapy-induced apoptosis remains undefined. The purpose of this study is to elucidate
      the pathways leading to Hsp27 action in androgen-independent prostate cancer  in order to 1/
      Increase the pharmacological safety of OGX-427 and 2/find new specific therapeutic targets
      and treatment strategy for androgen-independent prostate cancer .
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Level of Hsp27 protein</measure>
    <time_frame>within 24 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Mechanisms of action of Hsp27 protein to elucidate the pathways leading to Hsp27 action in androgen-independent prostate cancer (AIPC) by double hybrid Sos Recruitment System (SRS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Targets for OGX-427</measure>
    <time_frame>within 24 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Description of new specific therapeutic targets for androgen-independent prostate cancer and pharmacological safety of OGX-427</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Androgen-independent Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>prostate cancer</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Realisation of blood sample, urinary sample and tumor biopsy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Realisation of blood sample, urinary sample and tumor biopsy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>prostate cancer</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Prostate adenocarcinoma

          -  Patient &gt; 18 years old

          -  Patient affiliated to a social security system or benefiting from such a system

          -  Signed consent to participate

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient in emergency situation, major person being the object of a legal protective
             measure or unable to express its consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gwénaëlle GRAVIS, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institut Paoli-Calmettes</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dominique GENRE, MD</last_name>
    <phone>33 (0)4 91 22 37 78</phone>
    <email>bec@ipc.unicancer.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sandra COURNIER</last_name>
    <phone>33 (0)4 91 22 37 78</phone>
    <email>bec@ipc.unicancer.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gwénaëlle GRAVIS, MD</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille</city>
        <zip>13009</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gwénaëlle GRAVIS, MD</last_name>
      <phone>33 (0)4 91 22 37 78</phone>
      <email>bec@ipc.unicancer.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.institutpaolicalmettes.fr</url>
    <description>official web site of the sponsor</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 26, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Androgen-independent prostate cancer</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Androgens</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
