<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="40158">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01866423</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4P-13-1</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-01013</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>IISR-2012-M000668</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA014089</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01866423</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Orteronel in Treating Patients With Metastatic Hormone-Resistant Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 2 Trial of TAK-700 (Orteronel) Without Prednisone for Metastatic Castration-Resistant Prostate Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Southern California</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Southern California</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well orteronel works in treating patients with metastatic
      hormone-resistant prostate cancer. Orteronel may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking
      some of the enzymes needed for cell growth.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess the relationship between circulating tumor cell (CTC)-based androgen receptor
      (AR) expression level and &gt;=-50% prostate-specific antigen (PSA) decline following 12 weeks
      of therapy with TAK-700 (orteronel).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess changes in PSA and CTC levels and time to PSA progression (best response,
      decline at 12 weeks as continuous variable, etc.) with or without prior docetaxel-based
      treatment.

      II. To assess measurable disease response and time to radiographic disease progression for
      castration-resistant prostate cancer (CRPC) with or without prior docetaxel-based treatment.

      III. To explore relationships between endocrine and clinical responses.

      IV. To confirm the safety of TAK-700 administered without prednisone in patients with
      metastatic CRPC.

      OUTLINE: Patients receive orteronel orally (PO) twice daily (BID) on days 1-28. Courses
      repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AR protein expression levels in CTCs</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The two-sample t-test will be used. Once association between AR protein expression levels and response is established, graphical methods such as receiver-operator curves (ROC) or more quantitative methods such as the maximal chi-square method to determine whether there might be a cut-point with either great sensitivity or great specificity (or both) for identifying a cohort with either a high or low likelihood of PSA response.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PSA response, defined as occurrence of PSA decline to greater than or equal to 50% from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>At 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Standard descriptive methods will be used to summarize PSA. Values will be tabulated as outlined in the Prostate Cancer Working Group 2 (PCWG2) criteria and presented as Kaplan-Meier survival curves, as appropriate.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Best PSA response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Values will be tabulated as outlined in the PCWG2 criteria and presented as Kaplan-Meier survival curves, as appropriate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Absolute change in PSA</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Values will be tabulated as outlined in the PCWG2 criteria and presented as Kaplan-Meier survival curves, as appropriate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate using Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) version 1.1 and PCWG2 criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Response will be tabulated descriptively with 95% confidence intervals (CIs) and Kaplan-Meier survival curves, as appropriate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response using RECIST version 1.1 and PCWG2 criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Response will be tabulated descriptively with 95% CIs and Kaplan-Meier survival curves, as appropriate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events by NCI CTCAE version 4</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>All toxicities observed will be summarized with tables according to system, specific toxicity, grade, attribution, and time of onset.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Adenocarcinoma of the Prostate</condition>
  <condition>Hormone-resistant Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (orteronel)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive orteronel 300 mg PO BID on days 1-28. Courses repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>orteronel</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (orteronel)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TAK-700</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (orteronel)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of the prostate

          -  Voluntary written informed consent before performance of any study-related procedure
             not part of normal medical care, with the understanding that consent may be withdrawn
             by the subject at any time without prejudice to future medical care

          -  Patients, even if surgically sterilized (i.e., status post vasectomy), who agree to
             practice effective barrier contraception during the entire study treatment period and
             for 4 months after the last dose of study drug, or

          -  Agree to completely abstain from intercourse

          -  Serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) must be =&lt;
             2.5 x the upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x ULN

          -  Estimated creatinine clearance using the Cockcroft-Gault formula must be &gt; 40
             mL/minute

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1500/uL

          -  Platelet count &gt;= 100,000/uL

          -  Testosterone &lt; 50 ng/dL

          -  Screening calculated ejection fraction of &gt;= 50% by multiple gated acquisition (MUGA)
             scan or echocardiogram; metastatic progression on primary androgen-deprivation
             therapy (medical or surgical castration)

          -  Progression requiring a change in oncologic therapy defined by any of the following:

               -  Radiographic progression: appearance or increase in measurable lesions on
                  cross-sectional imaging or appearance of one or more new lesions on bone scan
                  * Rising PSA (&gt;= 2 ng/ml) which has risen on two occasions &gt;= 1 week apart

               -  Clinical progression evidenced by increased pain or other cancer-related
                  symptoms

          -  Patients should have recovered from prior oncologic therapies to a Common Terminology
             Criteria (CTC) grade =&lt; 1 except stable neuropathy or alopecia at National Cancer
             Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) grade =&lt; 2; if
             rapid clinical progression is documented by imaging, changes in PSA, or symptoms,
             then study treatment can begin &gt;= 2 weeks from prior therapy; otherwise, the
             following time periods between prior anti-cancer therapies and study treatment day 1
             will apply:

               -  &gt;= 3 weeks for prior cytotoxic therapies

               -  &gt;= 4 weeks for flutamide or nilutamide

               -  &gt;= 6 weeks for bicalutamide

               -  &gt;= 6 weeks since bone targeted radiopharmaceutical (e.g. samarium-153,
                  radium-223)

          -  Gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) agonists (leuprolide acetate, goserelin, etc.)
             or antagonists (degarelix, etc.) should be continued in patients without
             surgically-induced castrate androgen levels

          -  For chemotherapy naïve castration-resistant prostate cancer who are moderately
             symptomatic or who have hepatic metastasis: subjects must not be a candidate for
             docetaxel-based chemotherapy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of myocardial infarction, unstable symptomatic ischemic heart disease,
             ongoing arrhythmias of grade &gt; 2 (NCI CTCAE, version 4), thromboembolic events (e.g.,
             deep vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolism, or symptomatic cerebrovascular events), or
             any other cardiac condition (e.g. pericardial effusion, restrictive cardiomyopathy)
             within 6 months prior to first dose of study drug; chronic stable atrial fibrillation
             on stable anticoagulant therapy is allowed

          -  New York Heart Association class III or IV heart failure

          -  Electrocardiogram (ECG) abnormalities of:

               -  Q-wave infarction, unless identified 6 or more months prior to screening

               -  Corrected QT (QTc) interval &gt; 460 msec

          -  Patient has received other investigational drugs within 28 days before enrollment

          -  Diagnosed or treated for another malignancy within 2 years of enrollment, with the
             exception of complete resection of basal cell carcinoma or squamous cell carcinoma of
             the skin, an in situ malignancy

          -  Known hypersensitivity to compounds related to TAK-700 or to TAK-700 excipients

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension despite appropriate medical therapy (blood pressure [BP] of
             greater than 160 mmHg systolic and 90 mmHg diastolic at 2 separate measurements no
             more than 60 minutes apart during the screening visit); Note: patients may be
             rescreened after adjustment of antihypertensive medications

          -  Known active chronic hepatitis B or C, life-threatening illness unrelated to cancer,
             or any serious medical or psychiatric illness that could, in the investigator's
             opinion, potentially interfere with participation in this study

          -  Likely inability to comply with the protocol or cooperate fully with the investigator
             and site personnel

          -  Known gastrointestinal (GI) disease or GI procedure that could interfere with the GI
             absorption or tolerance of TAK-700, including difficulty swallowing tablets

          -  Prior treatment with &gt;= 3 lines of cytotoxic chemotherapy for metastatic prostate
             cancer

          -  Prior treatment with TAK-700
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mitchell Gross</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Southern California</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>USC Norris Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kristy Massopust</last_name>
      <phone>323-865-0843</phone>
      <email>kristy.massopust@med.usc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mitchell E. Gross</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 28, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
