<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="19981">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01868711</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>5768</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01868711</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Psychological Mindedness as a Predictor of Success in Cognitive Behavior Therapy for Depression</brief_title>
  <official_title>Psychological Mindedness as a Predictor of Success in CBT for Depressed Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York State Psychiatric Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York State Psychiatric Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Psychological mindedness(PM) is a meta cognitive process in which the person uses his
      cognitive and affective abilities to better understand his thoughts, feelings, and his
      behaviors as they interact with his internal experiences and his external experiences in the
      world, and dynamically modifies his behavior to move towards self self actualization, in a
      manner positive to himself and the world. We investigate whether assessment of PM can
      distinguish depressed patients who benefit from CBT. Moreover, there may be a relationship
      between PM and measures of brain function that also correlate with success in CBT.
      Therefore, we measure PM, neurophysiological measures (EEG and ERP's), and cognitive tests
      before and after CBT treatment of 70 adults with depression.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cognitive Behavior Therapy (CBT) was found to be the most effective psychotherapy for
      depression. Yet, it is effective only for 40% of the depressed people who receive this
      treatment. Until this day there is no method of predicting whom can be helped among
      depressed patients by CBT. In this study we examine whether level of psychological
      mindedness and other neurophysiological and cognitive variables can predict who may benefit
      from CBT among depressed patients. Subjects who are found to be clinically depressed are
      given 14 sessions of CBT.

      The screening procedure for this study includes a 20-30 minute telephone or in-person
      interview. Clinical staff members trained in diagnostic interviewing will conduct an initial
      phone interview to determine likely diagnostic suitability. If the subject is deemed
      preliminarily eligible for participation, meaning he or she is clinically depressed, they
      will then be invited for an in-person psychiatric evaluation conducted at the Depression
      Evaluation Services at New York State Psychiatric Institute.

      Upon arrival the subject will read the Depression Evaluation Services consent form for
      evaluation.Questions will be answered and the consent will be offered to read and sign,if
      agreeable. The evaluation will include a clinical interview, a structured clinical interview
      (the SCID-IV), collection of blood samples for routine medical tests, including thyroid
      function tests, and a urine sample [for urine analysis and toxicology screen].

      Important to note: subjects who enroll in the study need to not take any psychiatric
      medications or they must be on the same medications for 3 months and the same dose for 4
      weeks. During the psychotherapy, the patients will continue to see their own physician for
      medications. Medication management will NOT be within the province of this protocol. During
      the study there will be an ongoing consultation with the outside physician, particularly
      with regard to changes in medication and/or dosage. Should the MD or patient decide to make
      alternations in use of medication, this will not affect the patient's participation in
      psychotherapy or in this study.

      Subjects who were found to be eligible for the study will return within two weeks after the
      evaluation visit. An evaluator will rate the HRSD-17 and CGI-Severity.If they are still
      eligible, they will be asked to sign the study consent form, have the study explained,
      including its risks and possible benefits, as well as alternatives and its voluntary nature.
      Once they sign the consent form, patients will complete a battery of self-report instrument.
      Patients will be tested on EEG, ERP and cognitive tests the same day or another day based on
      their convenience. After that they will schedule their weekly CBT sessions with the study
      therapist. During 14 weeks they will be clinically monitored by Beck Depression Inventory at
      the beginning of every session and HRSD-17 every four weeks. They will complete study
      measures at week 8 and after the the 14 weeks sessions. They will be tested on EEG, ERP and
      cognitive tests after the 14 weeks of therapy.

      Study participants who do not remit (end treatment HDRS-17 &gt; 7) at the end of CBT trial will
      be offered medication for three months or will receive referral for alternative
      psychotherapy, per patient's preference.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Level of depression as measured by the Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>The change from baseline level of depression at post treatment level of depression, afer 14 sessions of CBT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Outcome measure of depression will be assessed as the change in depression between baseline (pre-treatment) and post treatment (after 14 sessions of CBT for depression).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Dysthymia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Behavior Therapy for Depression</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Depressed patients, age 18 to 70, will receive 14 individual manualized sessions of cognitive behavior therapy for depression, for a period of 14 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Behavior Therapy for Depression</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Behavior Therapy for Depression</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CBT</other_name>
    <other_name>Short term therapy</other_name>
    <other_name>Time limited therapy</other_name>
    <other_name>Manualized therapy</other_name>
    <other_name>Evidence based therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Behavior Therapy for Depression</intervention_name>
    <description>The CBT protocol represents incorporation and integration from several sources. These include (a) prior experience with the treatment of depression and (b) previously published cognitive therapy (CT) manuals published by Beck (1995). The present protocol encourages therapist flexibility in approach, yet during the treatment specific tools and methods of coping with depression are given to each patient. The patient will be psycho educated about symptoms of depression.  The patient will learn to use the following basic cognitive-behavioral techniques for the treatment of depression:
Constructing an 'Action Schedule', setting goals, doing 'Behavioral Experiments', and constructing a thought record, checking accuracy of thoughts, re framing thoughts when necessary and learn to engage in problem solving for particular situations.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Behavior Therapy for Depression</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CBT for Depression</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Males or females between the ages of 18 and 70 (inclusive).

          -  Primary DSM-IV-TR diagnosis of major depression, dysthymia or depressive disorder not
             otherwise specified (NOS).

          -  A negative urine toxicology, i.e., a urine specimen that does not test positive for
             use of drugs of abuse, or use of benzodiazepines.

          -  Ability to give informed consent.

          -  Fluent in English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have a &quot;lifetime&quot; history of Schizophrenia or other current psychotic
             disorder, Major Depressive Disorder with Psychotic or Catatonic features, Bipolar I
             Affective Disorder or Organic Mental Disease.

          -  DSM-IV substance abuse or dependence within the past 6 months (except nicotine or
             caffeine).

          -  Active suicidal or homicidal ideation, or judged to be at serious suicide risk.

          -  Any unstable medical or neurological condition.

          -  Presently receiving psychotherapy.

          -  Prior History of CBT for Depression treatment failure.

          -  Hearing loss greater than 30 dB hearing level or greater than 10 dB difference in
             hearing level between ears.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ronit Kishon, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>212 543 5312</phone>
    <email>rk159@columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jonathan W Stewart, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212 543 5745</phone>
    <email>jws6@columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York State Psychiatric Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ronit Kishon, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>212-543-5312</phone>
      <email>rk159@columbia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jonathan W Stewart, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212 543 5745</phone>
      <email>jws6@columbia.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ronit Kishon, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://depression-nyc.org</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 30, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 20, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Major Depressive Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Dysthymia</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive Behavior Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Psychological Mindedness</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dysthymic Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
