<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="141224">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01893983</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CRE 12-083</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CRE 12-083</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01893983</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Motivational Coaching to Enhance Mental Health Engagement in Rural Veterans</brief_title>
  <acronym>CREATE</acronym>
  <official_title>Motivational Coaching to Enhance Mental Health Engagement in Rural Veterans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate combat-related health problems among rural
      veterans. The research project also aims to test a new telephone-based approach for helping
      veterans who need treatment connect with the appropriate care. This study will help us to
      better understand the kinds of problems recently returned veterans experience. The study
      will also help us to find better ways to help veterans get the help they may need.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Project Background: One in five OEF/OIF/OND veterans resides in rural areas and primarily
      receives care from VA CBOCs. Compared to their urban counterparts, rural veterans experience
      a significantly greater MH burden and poorer outcomes. Nevertheless, less than 10% of
      OEF/OIF/OND veterans with a new PTSD diagnosis attend a minimum number of sessions required
      for evidence-based treatment, with rurality being one of the strongest predictors of poor
      engagement. Our pilot study in urban OEF/OIF/OND veterans demonstrated that telephone
      Motivational Interviewing (MI) delivered by research staff significantly improved MH
      treatment initiation and retention in care. However, we do not know whether telephone MI
      will have as strong an effect on MH treatment engagement when implemented by VA staff in
      CBOCs serving rural veterans.

      Project Objectives: As a part of the CeMOHR CREATE application to improve rural veterans'
      access to evidence-based mental healthcare (Fortney, PI), the overall goal of this project
      is to adapt, implement and test an MI-based coaching intervention to improve MH services
      engagement at CBOCs serving rural veterans.  The specific aims of this project are: (1)
      Conduct a developmental formative evaluation of perceived barriers to MH treatment
      engagement and adapt the MI-based treatment engagement intervention and implementation
      strategy to the needs of stakeholders; (2) Conduct a randomized multi-site pragmatic
      effectiveness trial comparing MH Referral alone with MH Referral plus MI-based coaching; and
      (3) Conduct an implementation-focused formative evaluation and use this information to make
      mid-course corrections to the implementation strategy based on stakeholder and key informant
      input.

      Methods: We will conduct the pragmatic effectiveness trial of the telephone motivational
      coaching intervention to determine whether, in comparison to MH Referral alone, telephone MI
      coaching improves MH treatment initiation and retention, the use of e-health MH resources,
      and perceived need and readiness for and access to MH treatment among rural veterans who use
      CBOCs (Aim 2).

      Impact: This research will help close the knowledge gap about barriers to care and
      preferences for MH services among rural veterans. In addition, information from this project
      will be used to develop implementation toolkits for MH treatment engagement interventions
      for rural veterans. Finally, this project will determine the effectiveness of a telephone
      Motivational Interviewing engagement intervention using e-health adjuncts, thereby filling a
      gap in the scientific literature about whether novel interventions can be used by VA staff
      in CBOCs to overcome rural-urban disparities in MH treatment engagement.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mental Health (MH) Treatment Engagement</measure>
    <time_frame>26 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Motivational Coaching (vs. Control) on MH treatment initiation.  This will be measured by self-report and by checking the subjects medical record.   We will adjust by clustering for CBOC and region as well as potential confounding by other covariates</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mental Health (MH) Treatment Retention</measure>
    <time_frame>26 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Motivational Coaching (vs. Control) on MH treatment retention.  This will be measured by self-report and by checking the subjects medical record.   We will adjust by clustering for CBOC and region as well as potential confounding by other covariates</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">280</enrollment>
  <condition>Mental Health</condition>
  <condition>Rural Health</condition>
  <condition>Veterans Health</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Motivational Coaching</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Telephone based Motivational Coaching sessions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Referral alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is the current standard of care</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Motivational Coaching</intervention_name>
    <description>Telephone-based Motivational Interviewing aimed at getting Veterans to engage or retain mental health treatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>Motivational Coaching</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  a veteran  over age 18, under the age 75.

          -  a resident of VISN 16 or 21 catchment areas receiving care at a CBOC with no plans to
             re-locate within 8 months of enrollment, and from baseline assessment:

          -  positive for 1 of the following disorders PTSD, depression, generalized anxiety
             disorder, panic disorder, high-risk drinking, and/or illicit substance use and

          -  moderately ambivalent (6 on the Readiness Ruler) about initiating or re-engaging in
             MH treatment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  hearing- impaired,

          -  no working telephone,

          -  veterans with self-reported (and/or CPRS-confirmed) diagnoses of psychosis or bipolar
             disorder, or active suicidality or homicidality, and from baseline assessment:

          -  currently or recently engaged (&lt;60 days of recruitment) in VA or non-VA MH treatment
             (will also confirm in CPRS if VA MH treatment).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen H. Seal, MD MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nicole McCamish, MA</last_name>
    <phone>(415) 221-4810</phone>
    <phone_ext>4284</phone_ext>
    <email>Nicole.McCamish@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Linda Abadjian, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(415) 221-4810</phone>
    <phone_ext>3975</phone_ext>
    <email>linda.abadjian1@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Central Arkansas VHS John L. McClellan Memorial Veterans Hospital, Little Rock, AR</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72205-5484</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Regina L Stanley, BA</last_name>
      <phone>501-257-1730</phone>
      <email>Regina.Stanley2@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>San Francisco</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94121</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nicole McCamish, MA</last_name>
      <phone>415-221-4810</phone>
      <phone_ext>4284</phone_ext>
      <email>Nicole.McCamish@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Linda Abadjian, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(415) 221-4810</phone>
      <phone_ext>3975</phone_ext>
      <email>linda.abadjian1@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karen H. Seal, MD MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.vetsreturnhome.com</url>
    <description>Click here for more information about this study: Motivational Coaching to Enhance Mental Health Engagement in Rural Veterans</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 11, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 21, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mental Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Veterans Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Rural</keyword>
  <keyword>Motivational Interviewing</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
