<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="143011">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02014584</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>200209</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02014584</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sexual Function in Men Receiving Dutasteride for Androgenetic Alopecia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Study of Sexual Function in Men Taking Dutasteride for the Treatment of Androgenetic Alopecia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Treatment of male pattern hair loss (MPHL) or androgenetic alopecia (AGA) with 5α-reductase
      inhibitor (5-ARIs) has been associated with sexual dysfunction including erectile
      dysfunction and loss of libido. This will be a multicenter, randomized, double-blind,
      placebo-controlled, parallel-group study to assess the impact of dutasteride treatment on
      sexual function as well as subject satisfaction with hair growth and quality of life in men
      with AGA. This study will consist of a Screening Visit, a 4-week Placebo Run-in Phase, a
      Treatment Phase of 24 weeks, and a subsequent Follow-up Visit after 4 weeks.  An extended
      6-month Follow-up Visit will be conducted for any individuals with a change in erectile
      function at the end of treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with a change in sexual function defined as a negative change from baseline in the IIEF-EF score of &gt;=4 units or a score of &lt;=25 on or before Week 24</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Weeks 4, 12 and 24.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>International Index of Erectile Function (IIEF) questionnaire is used to assess erectile function. It is a 15-item questionnaire with individual items assigned to five separate domains of sexual function (erectile function, orgasmic function, sexual desire, intercourse satisfaction, and overall satisfaction). Erectile function domain of the IIEF (IIEF-EF) includes Questions 1 through 5 and Question 15 (maximum score of 30).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with a negative change from baseline in the IIEF-EF score of &gt;=4 units or a score of &lt;=25 on or before Weeks 4 and 12 as well as the Follow-up Visit</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Weeks 4, 12 and 28.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>IIEF questionnaire is used to assess erectile function. It is a 15-item questionnaire with individual items assigned to five separate domains of sexual function (erectile function, orgasmic function, sexual desire, intercourse satisfaction, and overall satisfaction). IIEF-EF includes Questions 1 through 5 and Question 15 (maximum score of 30).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in total score of the IIEF at Weeks 4, 12, and 24 as well as the Follow-up Visit</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Weeks 4, 12, 24 and 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>IIEF questionnaire is used to assess erectile function. It is a 15-item questionnaire with individual items assigned to five separate domains of sexual function: Erectile function (Questions 1 through 5 and 15), Orgasmic function (Questions 9 and 10), Sexual desire (Questions 11 and 12), Intercourse satisfaction (Questions 6 through 8), and Overall satisfaction (Questions 13 and 14).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in the individual domain scores: erectile function, orgasmic function, sexual desire, intercourse satisfaction and overall sexual satisfaction, of the IIEF at Weeks 4, 12 and 24 as well as the Follow-up Visit</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Weeks 4, 12, 24 and 28.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>IIEF questionnaire is used to assess erectile function. It is a 15-item questionnaire with individual items assigned to five separate domains of sexual function: Erectile function (Questions 1 through 5 and 15), Orgasmic function (Questions 9 and 10), Sexual desire (Questions 11 and 12), Intercourse satisfaction (Questions 6 through 8), and Overall satisfaction (Questions 13 and 14).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in subject satisfaction with hair growth as assessed by the total score of the Hair Growth Satisfaction Scale (HGSS) at Weeks 12 and 24</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Weeks 12 and 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The HGSS will assess subject satisfaction with hair appearance and growth by scoring 5 questions on a 7-point scale ranging from very dissatisfied to very satisfied.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in the total score of the Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI) at Weeks 12 and 24</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Weeks 12 and 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The DLQI is a 10-item questionnaire designed to evaluate the effect of skin conditions (alopecia) on the subjects' quality of life. Each item is scored on a 4-point scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of adverse events related to sexual dysfunction</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months after the last dose of study medication</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Any adverse events related to sexual dysfunction will be carefully monitored during the study, and any such events ongoing at the end of treatment (Week 24) will be reassessed 6 months after the last dose of study medication (Extended Follow-up)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">700</enrollment>
  <condition>Alopecia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dutasteride Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive dutasteride 0.5 milligrams (mg) administered orally once daily for 24 Weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive placebo administered orally once daily for 24 Weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dutasteride</intervention_name>
    <description>Dutasteride will be supplied as soft gelatin capsules, containing 0.5 mg of dutasteride to be administered orally.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dutasteride Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Dutasteride matching placebo will be supplied as capsules to be administered orally.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject agrees to participate in the study and has signed and dated the informed
             consent form prior to the initiation of any study-related activities.

          -  Men 18 to 50 years old, inclusively

          -  AGA classified as Type III vertex, IV, or V (excluding Type IV anterior and Type V
             anterior) utilizing the Norwood-Hamilton classification

          -  Fluent and literate in local language with the ability to comprehend and record
             information on the International Index of Erectile Function, Hair Growth Satisfaction
             Scale, and Dermatology Life Quality Index questionnaires

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &lt;2x upper limit
             of normal (ULN); alkaline phosphatase and bilirubin &lt;=1.5xULN (isolated bilirubin
             &gt;1.5xULN is acceptable if bilirubin is fractionated and direct bilirubin is &lt;35%)

          -  Have been in a stable heterosexual relationship during the last 6 months prior to
             screening and expect to maintain that relationship throughout the study.

          -  Must be sexually active: a man is considered sexually active if he has engaged in
             sexual intercourse (at least once) during the 4 weeks prior to screening.

          -  Men with a female partner of childbearing potential must either agree to use
             effective contraception or have had a prior vasectomy. Contraception must be used
             from 2 weeks prior to administration of the first dose of study treatment until at
             least 5 half-lives for the drug (45 days) plus 3 months (i.e., a total of 4.5 months)
             to allow clearance of any altered sperm after the last dose of study treatment.

          -  Corrected QT interval (QTc) value &lt;450 milliseconds (msec) or &lt;480 msec for subjects
             with Bundle Branch Block, based on electrocardiogram (ECG) assessment at screening.
             Note: QTc is the QT interval corrected for heart rate according to either Bazett's
             formula (QTcB), Fridericia's formula (QTcF), or another method, machine or manual
             overread.

          -  Willing to comply with study requirements, including maintaining the same hair color
             throughout the study. Note: Subjects who use hair colorants/hair dyes may continue to
             do so.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current or pre-existing sexual dysfunction as determined by: History of erectile
             dysfunction defined as the consistent inability to achieve or maintain an erection
             sufficient to permit satisfactory sexual intercourse Score of &lt;=27 on the erectile
             function domain (IIEF-EF) of the IIEF at screening or at the baseline visit

          -  Evidence of hypogonadism defined by serum testosterone &lt;250 nanogram (ng)/decilitre
             (dL) at screening

          -  A clinically significant penile deformity in the opinion of the investigator

          -  A communicable skin or sexually transmitted disease, or any rash or lesions on the
             penis or in the surrounding area

          -  Serum prostate-specific antigen (PSA) &gt;2.0 ng/milliliter (mL) at screening

          -  Serum creatinine &gt;1.5xULN at screening

          -  Unstable liver disease (chronic stable hepatitis B and C are acceptable if the
             subject otherwise meets entry criteria)

          -  History of malignancy within the past 5 years, except basal cell or squamous cell
             carcinoma of the skin. Note: Subjects with suspicious ultrasound or digital rectal
             examination who have had a negative biopsy within the preceding 6 months and stable
             PSA are eligible for the study.

          -  History of prostate cancer before the age of 50 years in a first degree relative

          -  History of breast cancer or clinical breast examination suggestive of malignancy

          -  Active unstable thyroid disease, including subjects on therapy for either
             hyperthyroidism or hypothyroidism unless their dose of thyroid medication has been
             stable for at least 3 months and TSH is within the reference range

          -  Any unstable, serious co-existing medical condition(s) including, but not limited to,
             myocardial infarction, coronary bypass surgery, unstable angina, cardiac arrhythmias,
             clinically evident congestive heart failure, or cerebrovascular accident within 6
             months prior to screening; uncontrolled diabetes or peptic ulcer disease that is
             uncontrolled by medical management, and subjects who are known to be human
             immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positive (including subjects with acquired
             immunodeficiency syndrome [AIDS])

          -  History or current evidence of any serious and/or unstable pre-existing medical or
             psychiatric disorder, or other conditions that could, in the opinion of the
             investigator or the GlaxoSmithKline (GSK) medical monitor, interfere with the
             subject's safety, obtaining informed consent, or compliance with study procedures.
             Note: the investigator may consult with the GSK medical monitor if a condition could
             interfere with the subject's safety.

          -  Global scalp hair thinning, including occipital areas

          -  Scarring of the scalp, including prior hair transplant or scalp reduction, or any
             other condition or disease of the scalp or hair, including diseases of the hair shaft
             (e.g., tinea infection, non-androgenetic-cause of alopecia, psoriatic dermatitis or
             other psoriatic lesions, or uncontrolled seborrheic dermatitis)

          -  History of hair transplantation at any time to correct AGA or use of hair weaving
             within 6 months prior to screening

          -  History or evidence of hair loss other than AGA (e.g., due to an auto-immune,
             endocrine, mechanical or infectious process, or secondary to a scalp dermatological
             disorder)

          -  Use of any cosmetic product aimed at improving or correcting the signs of hair loss
             (e.g., scalp preparations with claims aiming at improved hair growth) within 2 weeks
             prior to screening

          -  Use of light or laser treatments on the scalp (e.g., light emitting diode [LED]
             lamps) within 3 months prior to screening

          -  Hypersensitivity to any 5-ARI or its components or excipients or drugs chemically
             related to the study treatment

          -  Use of dutasteride within 18 months prior to screening or use of finasteride within
             12 months prior to screening

          -  Previous use of systemic cytotoxic agents

          -  Use of glucocorticoids (inhaled glucocorticoids are allowed; topical corticosteroids
             are allowed provided that they are not used on the scalp) within 3 months prior to
             screening

          -  Use of the following during the 6 months prior to screening: Phosphodiesterase type 5
             (PDE5) inhibitors (e.g., sildenafil, tadalafil, vardenafil); Minoxidil (oral or
             topical); Carpronium chloride; Systemic drugs with anti-androgenic properties (e.g.,
             cyproterone acetate, spironolactone, ketoconazole, flutamide, and bicalutamide).
             Note: Use of ketoconazole shampoo on the scalp is prohibited during the study, but
             use before screening is not a reason for exclusion. Cimetidine is prohibited during
             the study, but use before screening is not a reason for exclusion; Topical or
             systemic estrogen or progesterone; Topical prostaglandin analogs on the scalp;
             Tamoxifen; Drugs potentially causing hypertrichosis (e.g., cyclosporine, diazoxide,
             phenytoin, psoralens); Drugs potentially causing hypertrichosis or telogen effluvium
             (e.g., valproic acid); Anabolic steroids; Lithium or phenothiazines.

          -  Participation in any investigational or marketed drug or device trial within 6 months
             prior to screening for this study. Note: Subject must not participate in any other
             drug or device trials during the course of this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
    <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 1, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>safety</keyword>
  <keyword>sexual function</keyword>
  <keyword>male pattern hair loss (MPHL)</keyword>
  <keyword>Androgenic alopecia (AGA)</keyword>
  <keyword>dutasteride</keyword>
  <keyword>satisfaction with hair growth</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Alopecia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alopecia Areata</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dutasteride</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
