<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="24932">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01740414</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>6021</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P50DA009236</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01740414</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Ibudilast on Oxycodone Self-administration in Opioid Abusers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Ibudilast (MN-166, Formerly AV411), a Glial Activation Inhibitor, on Oxycodone Self-administration in Opioid Abusers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York State Psychiatric Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>MediciNova</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York State Psychiatric Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Opioid drugs increase glial cell activation which may be related to the abuse liability of
      opioid drugs. Data supporting this hypothesis have demonstrated that glial cell attenuators
      decrease the positive rewarding aspect of opioids in laboratory animals. Ibudilast (MN-166,
      formerly AV411) is a compound that inhibits the activation of glia. Recent preclinical
      studies demonstrate that while ibudilast increases the analgesic effects of opioids, it
      decreases the rewarding effects of such drugs. It has also been shown that ibudilast
      suppresses morphine-induced release of dopamine, a primary neurotransmitter involved in the
      rewarding and reinforcing effects of abused drugs. Additionally, we recently found that
      ibudilast decreases subjective symptoms of opioid withdrawal in opioid dependent humans
      during detoxification.

      Therefore, the primary aim of this 6-7 week inpatient study is to investigate the ability of
      MN-166 to dose-dependently alter the reinforcing, analgesic, subjective, performance, and
      physiological effects of oxycodone, a commonly abused prescription opioid. A secondary aim
      is to verify the ability of the drug to decrease opioid withdrawal symptoms during the
      initial inpatient detoxification.

      This study will include two, 20-day phases. During Phase 1, participants will be detoxified,
      randomized to receive placebo or MN-166, and then be stabilized on the medication.
      Thereafter, participants will complete laboratory sessions. Subsequently, during Phase 2,
      participants will cross over to the other treatment arm, stabilize, and complete laboratory
      sessions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Opioid drugs increase glial cell activation and consequent cytokine release. These changes
      in glial cell activation may be related to the abuse liability of opioid drugs including
      heroin and prescription opioids. Data supporting this hypothesis have demonstrated that
      glial cell attenuators decrease the positive rewarding aspect of opioids in laboratory
      animals. Ibudilast (MN-166, formerly AV411) is a compound that inhibits the activation of
      glia and thereby inhibits the release of cytokines. Recent preclinical studies demonstrate
      that while ibudilast increases the analgesic effects of opioids, it decreases the rewarding
      effects of such drugs. It has also been shown that ibudilast suppresses morphine-induced
      release of dopamine, a primary neurotransmitter involved in the rewarding and reinforcing
      effects of abused drugs. Additionally, we recently found that ibudilast decreases subjective
      symptoms of opioid withdrawal in opioid dependent humans during detoxification.

      Therefore, the primary aim of this 6-7 week inpatient study is to investigate the ability of
      MN-166 to dose-dependently alter the reinforcing, analgesic, subjective, performance, and
      physiological effects of oxycodone, a commonly abused prescription opioid. A secondary aim
      is to verify the ability of the drug to decrease opioid withdrawal symptoms during the
      initial inpatient detoxification.

      This study will include two, 20-day phases. During Phase 1, participants will be detoxified,
      randomized to receive placebo or 50 mg MN-166 BID (po at 0800 and 2000 hr), and then
      stabilized on the medication. Thereafter, participants will complete laboratory sessions.
      Subsequently, during Phase 2, participants will cross over to the other treatment arm (Pbo
      to MN-166 or MN-166 to Pbo), stabilize, and complete laboratory sessions.

      Days 1-11 of Phase 1 will include a morphine taper and withdrawal assessment, while days
      12-20 of each phase will consist of 6 laboratory sessions (3 sample sessions and 3 choice
      sessions). During sample sessions, participants will receive one dose of oxycodone (0, 15,
      or 30 mg/70 kg, PO) that will be available during the choice session the following day. At
      least 72 hrs after the previous sample session, the second sample session will be completed,
      followed by a choice session the next day. And then at least 72 hrs after the second sample
      session, the third and final sample session will be completed, followed by the final choice
      session the next day. The analgesic, subjective, performance, and physiological effects of
      oxycodone will be measured. During the choice session, a drug versus money
      self-administration paradigm will be employed, and the progressive ratio that is completed
      for drug and/or money will be measured.

      We hypothesize that MN-166 will dose-dependently decrease oxycodone self-administration and
      positive subjective responses while increasing the analgesic effects of the drug. We further
      hypothesize that participants randomized to receive the active dose of MN-166 will exhibit
      fewer opioid withdrawal symptoms during and subsequent to the morphine taper than those
      assigned to placebo MN-166.

      A secondary additional objective is to collect exploratory information on potential
      predictors of prescription opioid self-administration including genetic polymorphisms,
      neurocognitive functioning, and response to stress. Blood samples will be collected to
      measure various genetic markers hypothesized to contribute to opioid drug effects (e.g.,
      OPRM1, OPRD1, OPRK1, PENK, PDYN, DRD2, CYP3A4, and CYP2D6 genes). Performance on
      neurocognitive tasks and physiological response to the Trier Social Stress Test will be
      assessed in all participants.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>pain intensity</measure>
    <time_frame>41 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Cold Pressure Test, Pain Intensity and Bothersome Scale, Cold Pressure Test Visual Analog Scale, Short-Form McGill Pain Questionnaire</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>positive subjective effects  to oxycodone</measure>
    <time_frame>41 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subjective Opiate Withdrawal Scale, Modified Clinical Global Impressions Scale, VAS Mood and Craving Scales, Clinical Opiate Withdrawal Scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>breakpoint values in progressive ratio drug self-administration procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>41 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>amount of drug versus money chosen in self administration task  (choice session)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>opioid withdrawal symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>41 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>opioid withdrawal signs assessed by pupil diameter photographs and questionnaires (Subjective/Clinical Opiate Withdrawal Scale), VAS Mood and Craving Scales, Modified Clinical Global Impressions Scale)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Opioid Abuse</condition>
  <condition>Opioid Dependence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MN-166 (formerly AV411)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>patient is receiving study drug (MN-166)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient is receiving placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MN-166 (formerly AV411)</intervention_name>
    <description>in one study arm, 50mg MN-166 BID are administered daily for 20 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>MN-166 (formerly AV411)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ibudilast</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>In the placebo arm, the patients receive placebo for 20 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults between the ages of 21 and 55

          -  Current opioid dependence according to DSM-IV criteria

          -  currently not seeking treatment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Female patients that are currently pregnant, or breastfeeding. Lack of effective
             birth control.

          -  Participants who have a positive history of neurological illness (including epilepsy)
             or those who have received anticonvulsant therapy during the past 5 years.

          -  Liver disease requiring medication or medical treatment, and/or aspartate or alanine
             aminotransferase levels greater than 3 times the upper limit of normal.

          -  Gastrointestinal or renal disease that would significantly impair absorption,
             metabolism or excretion of study drug, or require medication or medical treatment.

          -  Neurological or psychiatric disorders including psychosis, bipolar disorder, organic
             brain disease, any seizure history or other disorders that require treatment or that
             could make study compliance difficult.

          -  Positive tuberculosis (PPD) TB skin test, clinical history, and chest X-ray
             indicative of active tuberculosis. (Individuals with a positive PPD test and negative
             chest X-ray who are not symptomatic for tuberculosis, and do not require
             antituberculosis therapy will be eligible to participate. Participants will be asked
             if they ever tested positive for tuberculosis. If so, they will not be given a PPD
             and chest X-ray and clinical history will be used for evaluation purposes).

          -  Presence or positive history of severe medical illness or cardiovascular disease or
             heart abnormality, such as low hemoglobin (Hb &lt; 13 gm/dL in males, Hb &lt; 11 gm/dL in
             females) with evidence of acute or chronic blood loss, or BP &gt; 140/90.

          -  Participants on any current psychoactive prescription medications that may interfere
             with the study measures.

          -  Current physical dependence on any substance, other than opioids, nicotine or
             caffeine (ex., methadone, benzodiazepines, LAAM, marijuana, alcohol, etc.).

          -  Participants for whom detoxification is not &quot;clinically recommended&quot; such as those
             with a significant history of overdose following detoxification.

          -  Participation in an investigational drug study within the past 3 months.

          -  Hypersensitivity to any of the medications used in this study.

          -  Current (within the last 3 months) chronic pain.

          -  Platelet and white blood cell count that are not within the normal range (platelet =
             120 x103/μl -400 x103/μl; WBC= 3.5 x106/μl -10.8x106/μl).

          -  Use of Theophylline (PDE-3 inhibitor) or Roflumilast (PDE-4 inhibitor).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sandra D Comer, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, Columbia University and NYSPI</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sandra D Comer, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>646-774</phone>
    <phone_ext>6146</phone_ext>
    <email>comersa@nyspi.columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Maria Sullivan, MD</last_name>
    <phone>646-774</phone>
    <phone_ext>6152</phone_ext>
    <email>sulliva@nyspi.columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York State Psychiatric Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sandra D Comer, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>646-774-6146</phone>
      <phone_ext>6146</phone_ext>
      <email>comersa@nyspi.columbia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Maria Sullivan, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-774-6152</phone>
      <phone_ext>6152</phone_ext>
      <email>sulliva@nyspi.columbia.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sandra D Comer, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maria Sullivan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jermaine D Jones, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Verena E Metz, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 20, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 26, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>prescription opioid abuse</keyword>
  <keyword>pain</keyword>
  <keyword>opioid withdrawal</keyword>
  <keyword>oxycodone</keyword>
  <keyword>ibudilast</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Substance-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Opioid-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Oxycodone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Analgesics, Opioid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ibudilast</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
