<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="30285">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02128217</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ACTG A5327</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>UM1AI068636</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02128217</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sofosbuvir Plus Ribavirin For Acute Hepatitis C in HIV-infected Individuals (SWIFT-C)</brief_title>
  <acronym>SWIFT-C</acronym>
  <official_title>Sofosbuvir Plus Ribavirin Without Interferon For Treatment of Acute HCV in HIV-1 Infected Individuals (SWIFT-C)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AIDS Clinical Trials Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AIDS Clinical Trials Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      People who are recently infected with HCV have a great chance of being cured of the
      infection when they are treated with a combination of two drugs within the first 6 months of
      being infected. This study is being done to see if a new drug can replace one of the old
      drugs to provide a safer, more effective, and better tolerated treatment for new HCV
      infection. The name of this new drug is sofosbuvir (SOF), and it will replace
      pegylated-interferon alfa (PEG-IFN, a drug given as a weekly injection under the skin). SOF
      will be given in combination with ribavirin (RBV), a drug approved by the Food and Drug
      Administration (FDA).   All participants in this study will be monitored while on treatment
      at weeks 1, 2, 4, 8, and 12. All participants will be evaluated for a sustained virologic
      response (SVR) (undetectable HCV RNA levels) 1, 2, 4, and 8 (for the 8-week regimen) or 12
      (for the 12-week regimen) weeks after starting study treatment. After completing treatment,
      all participants will be evaluated for a SVR 2, 4, 8, 12, and 24 weeks after the end of
      treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>SVR12 defined as HCV RNA undetectable (&lt;LLOQ TND) of the assay at 12 weeks after date of last dose of study treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>At 12 weeks after date of last dose of study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The 12 week measurement will be the measurement obtained closest to 84 days (i.e. 12*7 days), within the window 79 to 112 days inclusive. If a subject has no HCV RNA measurement within this window, then the subject will be considered as having detectable HCV RNA at 12 weeks unless the preceding and subsequent HCV RNA measurements are both undetectable (&lt;LLOQ TND).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of a Grade ≥ 2 adverse event (AE: diagnosis, sign, symptom or laboratory abnormality), Serious AE according to ICH criteria, or treatment-limiting AE (ie, an AE reported as the reason for permanent discontinuation of study treatment)</measure>
    <time_frame>From initiation of study treatment to 28 days after last dose of study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Any event occurring after initiation of study treatment through to 28 days after date of last dose of study treatment will be included (except that an event that is ongoing at the same grade from before start of study treatment will be excluded).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HCV RNA undetectable during study treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 2, 4, 8 and, for the 12-week regimen, 12 weeks after starting study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>HCV RNA undetectable is defined as an HCV RNA measurement less than the assay lower limit of quantification, target not detected.  If there is no measurement at a scheduled time, then the subject will be considered as having detectable HCV RNA at that time, unless both the preceding and succeeding measurements are undetectable.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HCV RNA undetectable after end of study treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>2, 4, 8 and 24 weeks after last dose of study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>HCV RNA undetectable is defined as an HCV RNA measurement less than the assay lower limit of quantification, target not detected.  If there is no measurement at a scheduled time, then the subject will be considered as having detectable HCV RNA at that time, unless both the preceding and succeeding measurements are undetectable.  This outcome measure is generally referred to as SVR2, SVR4, SVR8 and SVR where SVR means sustained virologic response.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HCV virologic relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>From end of study treatment through to 24 weeks after end of study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>HCV RNA undetectable at end-of-treatment but HCV RNA quantifiable during follow-up with subsequent confirmation as quantifiable</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Development of SOF-associated resistance mutations</measure>
    <time_frame>Any time from start of study treatment to 24 weeks after end of study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The set of mutations to be considered will be defined at the time of analysis based on information from other studies available at that time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of each type of adverse event</measure>
    <time_frame>Any time from start of treatment to 24 weeks after end of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The adverse events to be considered are those used to define the safety primary outcome measure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in HIV-1 RNA from last measurement prior to start of study treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>4 and 12 weeks after start of study treatment (4 and 8 weeks after for the 8-week regimen</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>For subjects on ART at study entry, these will be categorized as changes from &lt;50 copies/mL to ≥50 copies/mL, or vice versa; for subjects not on ART at study entry, quantitative change in log10 HIV-1 RNA will be considered.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in CD4+ cell count from last measurement prior to start of study treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks after start of study treatment (8 weeks after for the 8-week regimen)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported adherence to SOF</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 2, 4, 8 and, for 12-week regimen only, 12 weeks after starting study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>whether or not a subject reports having taken all doses of SOF</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported adherence to RBV</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 2, 4, 8 and, for 12-week regimen only, 12 weeks after starting study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>whether or not a subject reports having taken all doses of RBV</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence as measured by SOF pill count</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 2, 4, 8 and, for 12-week regimen only, 12 weeks after starting study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of expected SOF doses taken</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence as measured by RBV pill count</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 2, 4, 8 and, for 12-week regimen only, 12 weeks after starting study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of expected RBV doses taken</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">44</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV-1 Infection</condition>
  <condition>Hepatitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: SOF+weight-based RBV for 12 wks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Follow-up will occur 24 weeks after the end of treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: SOF+weight-based RBV for 8 wks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 2 will open with the 12-week treatment duration, instead of 8 weeks if the sustained virologic suppression rate at 4 weeks after end of treatment  does not meet protocol-specified non-inferiority criteria. Follow-up will occur 24 weeks after the end of treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ribavirin</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive weight-based RBV orally, 2 times a day, every morning and every evening, with food.  Weight under 75 kg, 600 mg (3 tablets) morning and 400 mg (2 tablets) evening.  Weight over 75 kg, 600 mg (3 tablets) morning and 600 mg (3 tablets) evening.  The dose of RBV will be based on subject's weight at entry. Changes in weight after entry do not require a change in dose. Doses will only be changed for toxicity management.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: SOF+weight-based RBV for 12 wks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: SOF+weight-based RBV for 8 wks</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>RBV</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sofosbuvir</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive one 400 mg tablet of sofosbuvir orally every morning with food.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: SOF+weight-based RBV for 12 wks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: SOF+weight-based RBV for 8 wks</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SOF</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV-1 infection

          -  A documented confirmation of acute HCV infection within 6 months prior to A5327 entry
             or HCV reinfection as described in section 4.1.2 of the protocol.

          -  HCV RNA confirmed to be detectable &gt;12 weeks after first laboratory evidence of acute
             HCV and still within the &lt;24 week from first laboratory evidence of acute HCV
             infection window. First laboratory evidence of infection is defined as date of first
             elevated liver enzymes or date of first serologic evidence of HCV seroconversion
             and/or viremia (whichever occurs first).

          -  HIV-1 ARV therapy should fall into one of the following criteria:

               1. ARV untreated, for example due to (1) lack of indication per provider (CD4
                  T-cell count &gt;500 cells/mm3) or (2) decision by provider and subject to defer
                  ARV therapy during the study drug dosing period (8 or 12 weeks), or (3) elite
                  controller (CD4+ &gt;200 cells/mm3).

                  OR

               2. On a stable, protocol-approved (ddI, d4T, ZDV excluded), ARV regimen for &gt;8
                  weeks prior to screening with a CD4 T-cell count &gt;200 cells/mm3 and a documented
                  plasma HIV-1 RNA level &lt;50 copies/mL by any laboratory that has a Clinical
                  Laboratory Improvement Amendments (CLIA) certification or its equivalent ≥ 8
                  weeks preceding the A5327 screening visit. HIV-1 RNA levels should be within 1
                  year of the screening visit. Screening HIV-1 RNA must be &lt; 50 copies/mL as
                  measured by any local laboratory using an FDA-approved assay.

          -  Candidates must have the following laboratory parameters within 10-42 days prior to
             study entry:

               1. Hemoglobin ≥ 12 g/dL for male, ≥11 g/dL for female subjects

               2. International normalized ratio (INR) ≤1.5 x ULN unless subject has known
                  hemophilia or is stable on an anticoagulant regimen affecting INR

               3. Albumin ≥ 3 g/dL

               4. Creatinine clearance (CrCl) ≥ 60 mL/min, as calculated by the Cockcroft-Gault
                  equation (refer to section 6.3.5 for calculator utility link)

          -  Screening electrocardiogram (ECG) without clinically significant abnormalities as
             determined by the investigator.

          -  Female subjects of reproductive potential (defined as women who have not been
             post-menopausal for at least 24 consecutive months, ie, who have had menses within
             the preceding 24 months, or women who have not undergone surgical sterilization,
             specifically hysterectomy and/or bilateral oophorectomy or bilateral salpingectomy)
             must have a negative serum pregnancy test with a sensitivity of at least 25 mIU/mL
             performed during screening, within 48 hours prior to study entry.

          -  All subjects must agree not to participate in a conception process (eg, active
             attempt to become pregnant or to impregnate, sperm donation, in vitro fertilization).

        NOTE: Female candidates who are pregnant or breastfeeding are not eligible. A male
        candidate who has a pregnant female partner is not eligible for the study.

          -  When participating in sexual activity that could lead to pregnancy, all subjects must
             agree to use at least two reliable forms of contraceptive simultaneously while
             receiving protocol-specified medications, and for 6 months after stopping the
             medications. Such methods include:

               -  Condoms (male or female) with or without a spermicidal agent

               -  Diaphragm or cervical cap with spermicide

               -  Intrauterine device (IUD)

               -  Tubal ligation

               -  Hormone-based contraceptive (except those containing drospirenone)

          -  Subjects who are not of reproductive potential (women who have been post-menopausal
             for at least 24 consecutive months or have undergone hysterectomy and/or bilateral
             oophorectomy or salpingectomy or men who have documented azoospermia or undergone
             vasectomy) are eligible without requiring the use of contraceptives. Acceptable
             documentation of sterilization and menopause is specified as written or oral
             documentation communicated by clinician or clinician's staff of one of the following:

               -  Physician report/letter

               -  Operative report or other source documentation in the patient record (a
                  laboratory report of azoospermia is required to document successful vasectomy)

               -  Discharge summary

               -  Follicle stimulating hormone-release factor (FSH) measurement elevated into the
                  menopausal range as established by the reporting laboratory.

          -  Intention to comply with the dosing instructions for study drug administration and
             able to complete the study schedule of assessments.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Received investigational drug or device within 60 days prior to study entry.

          -  Prior exposure to a direct-acting antiviral (DAA) targeting the HCV NS5B polymerase.

        NOTE: DAAs include but are not limited to: mericitabine, ABT-333, ABT-072, BI-207127,
        BMS-791325, VX-222, tegobuvir, IDX719, setrobuvir, GS-9669, VX-135.

          -  Chronic liver disease of a non-HCV etiology (eg, hemochromatosis, Wilson's disease,
             α1 antitrypsin deficiency, primary sclerosing, cholangitis).

          -  Presence of active or acute AIDS-defining opportunistic infections within 30 days
             prior to study entry.

        NOTE:  A list of AIDS-defining opportunistic infections as defined by the CDC, can be
        found in Appendix B of the following document:
        http://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/preview/mmwrhtml/00018871.htm

          -  Active, serious infection (other than HIV-1 or HCV) requiring parenteral antibiotics,
             antivirals, or antifungals within 30 days prior to study entry.

          -  Infection with hepatitis B virus (HBV) defined as HBsAg positive.

          -  Evidence of acute hepatitis A infection defined as HAV IGM positive.

          -  History of clinically significant hemoglobinopathy (eg, sickle cell disease,
             thalassemia).

          -  Chronic use of systemically administered immunosuppressive agents (eg, prednisone
             equivalent &gt; 10 mg/day).

          -  History of solid organ transplantation.

          -  Current or prior history of clinical hepatic decompensation (eg, ascites,
             encephalopathy or variceal hemorrhage).

          -  History of a gastrointestinal disorder (or post operative condition) that could
             interfere with the absorption of the study drug.

          -  History of significant or symptomatic pulmonary disease, cardiac disease, or
             porphyria.

          -  History of difficulty with blood collection and/or poor venous access for the
             purposes of phlebotomy.

          -  History of clinically significant illness or any other major medical disorder that
             may interfere with subject treatment, assessment, or compliance with study
             requirements, which may include active drug or alcohol use or dependence.

          -  Use of any prohibited concomitant medications within 30 days prior to study entry.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to RBV, SOF, its metabolites, or formulation excipients or any
             other contraindication to the use of RBV or SOF.

          -  Currently receiving ZDV, ddI, or d4T.

          -  Acute HIV infection defined as the phase immediately following infection during which
             anti-HIV antibodies are undetectable.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Raymond T Chung, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susanna Naggie, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <link>
    <url>https://actgnetwork.org/</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 29, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ribavirin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
