<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="19829">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01665911</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-I-086</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01665911</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An in Situ Study on the Impact of Fluoride Dose and Concentration in Milk on Its Anti-caries Efficacy</brief_title>
  <official_title>An in Situ Study on the Impact of Fluoride Dose and Concentration in Milk on Its Anti-caries Efficacy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Frank Lippert</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Borrow Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Indiana University School of Dentistry</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study will be randomized, investigator-blind, observer-blind, laboratory analyst-blind
      and will utilize a 5-way cross-over study design with a primary objective to determine if a
      higher dose of fluoride in milk will provide a greater caries preventive effect.  Secondary
      objectives are to determine in a higher concentration of fluoride in milk will provide a
      greater caries preventive effect and if the caries preventive effect of fluoridated milk
      follows a dose-response pattern.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The evidence of milk fluoridation as a public health measure in caries prevention has been
      demonstrated in many clinical studies.  While these data are encouraging, the main focus now
      should be on the optimization of milk fluoride programs.  This protocol will concentrate on
      the parameters of fluoride dose and concentration utilizing an in situ model, the intra-oral
      caries test or model (ICT). The ICT is an established model which features the use of
      gauze-covered specimens to facilitate plaque growth and to simulate a caries-prone/plaque
      stagnation area. After subject has been consented and enrolled in the study per the
      inclusion/exclusion criteria, two to three days following a dental cleaning, two partially
      demineralized specimens will be placed in the buccal flange area of the subject's mandibular
      partial denture. During each of the five, three-week test periods, subjects will drink their
      assigned milk test product once per day for either five (100 ml milk) or ten (200 ml milk)
      timed minutes, wearing their mandibular partial dentures 24 hours a day during the test
      period. Fluoride free toothpaste will be used two to three days before and continuously
      during each treatment period. After each three-week test period, the two partially
      demineralized specimens will be removed from the subject's partial denture and analyzed
      using the surface microhardness test. Mineral content change (as percentage of surface
      microhardness recovery) in these artificially induced incipient enamel lesions will be the
      primary outcome variable. Each subject (n = 28) will serve as his or her own control.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>% Surface Microhardness (SMH) recovery score per each of five arms</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Three Weeks per each of five arms</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>SMH is used to assess changes in the mineral status of partially demineralized enamel specimens. The extent of remineralization will be calculated based on the following formula:
SMH recovery=(D-R)/(D-B)×100 where
B= indentation length of sound enamel specimen at baseline D= indentation length after in vitro demineralization R= indentation length after three week intra-oral exposure</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Caries</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>1.5 mg sodium fluoride in 100 ml milk</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>1.5 mg sodium fluoride in 200 ml milk</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>3 mg sodium fluoride in 100 ml milk</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>3 mg sodium fluoride in 200 ml milk</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>200 ml non-fluoridated milk-marketed</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>1.5 mg Sodium Fluoride in 100 ml milk</intervention_name>
    <description>Each subject will use this product during one of the five treatment periods in the crossover study design.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>sodium fluoride (PCCA Sodium Fluoride USP 51927-1038-00)</other_name>
    <other_name>Kroger Nonfat Dry Milk reconstituted with fluoride-free milk</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>1.5 mg sodium fluoride in 200 ml milk</intervention_name>
    <description>Each subject will use this product during one of the five treatment periods in the crossover study design.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>sodium fluoride (PCCA Sodium Fluoride USP 51927-1038-00)</other_name>
    <other_name>Kroger Nonfat Dry Milk reconstituted with fluoride-free milk</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>3 mg sodium fluoride in 100 ml milk</intervention_name>
    <description>Each subject will use this product during one of the five treatment periods in the crossover study design.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>sodium fluoride (PCCA Sodium Fluoride USP 51927-1038-00)</other_name>
    <other_name>Kroger Nonfat Dry Milk reconstituted with fluoride-free milk</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>3 mg sodium fluoride in 200 ml milk</intervention_name>
    <description>Each subject will use this product during one of the five treatment periods in the crossover study design</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 4</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>sodium fluoride (PCCA Sodium Fluoride USP 51927-1038-00)</other_name>
    <other_name>Kroger Nonfat Dry Milk reconstituted with fluoride-free milk</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Non-fluoridated milk, 200 ml</intervention_name>
    <description>Each subject will use this product during one of the five treatment periods in the crossover study design.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 5</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Kroger Nonfat Dry Milk</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  sign an informed consent, authorization for the release of health information for
             research and provide medical history information, including medications,  prior to
             their participation;

          -  be between 18 and 80 years old and in general good health;

          -  willingness to use a reliable form of contraception or abstaining during the course
             of the study (females of child-bearing potential only)

          -  wear a removable mandibular partial denture with sufficient room in one posterior
             buccal flange area to accommodate two enamel specimens (required dimensions 12×7 mm);

          -  be willing and capable of wearing their removable mandibular partial dentures 24
             hours a day for a total of five, three-week test periods;

          -  be in good dental health with no active caries or periodontal disease;

          -  agree to comply with all subjects' responsibilities as stated in the protocol (e.g.
             use of study products, attendance at appointments, etc.);

          -  have a salivary flow rate in the range of normal values (unstimulated whole saliva
             flow rate ≥ 0.2 ml/min; gum base stimulated whole saliva flow rate ≥ 0.8 ml/min).

          -  Be able to tolerate the taste and room temperature of the mixed milk product as
             demonstrated by drinking the milk at screening

        Exclusion Criteria:

        be pregnant, intending to become pregnant during the study period or breast feeding. A
        urine pregnancy test will be required at screening, the start of each treatment visit and
        the last study visit for all subjects of child-bearing potential to confirm the subject is
        not pregnant.

          -  have any medical condition that could be expected to interfere with the subject's
             safety during the study period;

          -  demonstrate an inability to comply with study procedures;

          -  have factors which could contraindicate their participation, such as any condition
             requiring the need for antibiotic premedication prior to a dental treatment, a
             condition requiring the need for long-term antibiotic use, blood thinning medications
             that prohibit the safe conduct of a dental cleaning* or previous use of the weight
             loss medications Fen Phen® or Redux®. (*Note: Subjects who are taking blood thinners
             in which written verification is obtained from their physician indicating their
             PT/INR levels (anti-coagulation blood levels) are at an acceptable level to avoid
             serious complications, such as bleeding during dental cleanings, may be accepted into
             the study at the discretion of the Investigator.)

          -  be currently taking or have ever taken a bisphosphonate drug (i.e. Fosamax®,
             Actonel®, Boniva®, Reclast®, or Zometa®) for treatment of osteoporosis.

          -  be lactose intolerant or have known allergy or intolerance to milk or milk products
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Frank Lippert, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Indiana University School of Dentistry</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Domenick Zero, DDS, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Indiana University School of Dentistry</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oral Health Research Institute, Indiana University School of Dentistry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 13, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 7, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Indiana University School of Dentistry</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Frank Lippert</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Research Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Caries</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fluorides</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sodium Fluoride</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Listerine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
