<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="168123">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01842399</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999913078</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-AG-N078</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01842399</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Resveratrol and Cardiovascular Health in the Elderly</brief_title>
  <official_title>Resveratrol and Cardiovascular Health in the Elderly: The Reache Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Resveratrol is a compound found in the skin of red grapes. It is being tested to see if it
      can have positive effects on human health. Lab studies show that it may help lower blood
      sugar, improve heart and blood vessel health, and prevent cancer. Researchers want to test
      different dose levels of Resveratrol to see what kind of effects it has on older overweight
      people. It will be tested in healthy volunteers at least 50 years of age.

      Objectives:

      - To test the effects of different dose levels of Resveratrol on heart and blood vessel
      health.

      Eligibility:

      - Healthy overweight nonsmoking volunteers at least 50 years of age.

      Design:

        -  This study will involve a screening visit and four study visits. Some of the study
           visits will involve overnight inpatient stays.

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. Blood and urine
           samples will be collected. They will be given a list of foods that they should avoid
           eating while on the study.

        -  Participants will be separated into three groups. Two groups will take different dose
           levels of the study drug. The third group will take a placebo.

        -  At the first study visit, participants will stay in the clinical center overnight for 2
           days of tests. They will provide blood and urine samples and have body scans to measure
           fat and muscle mass. They will also have exercise tests. A muscle biopsy will also be
           performed. At this visit, they will receive their dose of the study drug. They will
           continue to take this dose for as long as they are on the study.

        -  The second visit will be 16 weeks after the first one. It will take only 2 hours, and
           repeat most of the tests from the screening visit.

        -  The third visit will be 16 weeks later. It will involve an overnight stay. Most of the
           tests from the second visit will be repeated.

        -  The fourth and final visit will be 16 weeks later. It will involve an overnight stay.
           Most of the tests from the initial study visit (including the scans and the exercise
           tests) will be repeated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Resveratrol is found in the leaves and skin of grapes, in peanuts and in the roots of the
      plant polygonum cupsidatum. Although used since early years in Indian Ayurvedic and Chinese
      medicine, it came into prominence in the 1990   s as it was believed to be the major reason
      for the positive effect of wine on cardiovascular health and the French Paradox. Since then,
      studies have shown that resveratrol affects a number of key cellular pathways and molecular
      targets with a wide range of biological effects. Noted among these are its effects on the
      blood vessels, cancer, blood clotting, blood sugar control, muscle activity and
      inflammation. Resveratrol also may produce some of the same effects as decreased food
      intake, perhaps through its action on a molecule in the body called Sirtuin, which is
      important because this is one of the only approaches that has consistently demonstrated
      beneficial effects on the aging process.

      Resveratrol   s action and pharmacology has been extensively studied in test tubes, cells,
      and animals but is only now being explored fully in people. The animal studies include a
      recent NIA-conducted study in monkeys that demonstrated a reduction in the stiffness of
      blood vessel over several weeks. Phase 1 and 2 clinical studies in healthy human volunteers
      or in patients with type II diabetes mellitus have begun to identify possible roles for
      resveratrol as a nutritional supplement and the compound appears to have no harmful effects
      at doses up to 5 grams per day.

      We will perform a 12-month, Phase 1/2 trial of resVida (an oral preparation of resveratrol)
      in 90 overweight/obese people over the age of 50 (30 in each group). The primary endpoint
      will be vascular stiffness (as measured by Pulse Wave Velocity) and the secondary endpoint
      will be exercise capacity as measured by oxygen utilization (VO2max). Testing will be done
      on the levels of resveratrol in the blood with different doses of the compound. The study
      will also include measurements of changes in blood glucose levels, inflammation, and
      exercise capacity. These studies will provide necessary information for further testing of
      resVida as a compound that could promote healthy aging.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double-Blind, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Decreased rate of age associated arterial stiffening</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16, 32, 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in aerobic capacity, functional capacity, body composition, muscle energetics, inflammatory markers, glucose metabolism.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16, 32, 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Vascular Resistance</condition>
  <condition>Aging</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Antioxidants</condition>
  <condition>Aerobic Capacity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>2x/day orally</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>75 mg, 2x/day, orally</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>150 mg, 2x/day, orally</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Resveratrol</intervention_name>
    <description>Dietary Supplement</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>2x/day orally</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Male or Female, age 50 years or older, BMI 25-35.

        Females must be postmenopausal (no menses within 12 months).

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        BMI less than 25 or greater than 35.

        Diabetic subjects by history, Hemoglobin A1C greater than 6.5, or random serum glucose
        greater than 200 mg/dl.

        Renal dysfunction (GFR less than 60 mL/min).

        Medications:

        Cholesterol medications Atorvastatin(Lipitor) Rosuvastatin (Crestor), Simvastatin (Zocor),
        Gemfibrazole (Lopid), Niacin (Niacor), etc.

        Aspirin

        Anti-diabetic medications: Insulin, Metformin (Glucophage, Avandamet, Glibomet, etc),
        Rosiglitazone (Avandia), Exenatide (Byetta), Sitagliptin (Januvia), etc

        Anti-hypertensive medications Metoprolol (Lopressor), Carvedilol (Coreg), Nifedipine
        (Procardia, Adalat), Verapamil (Verelan,Calan, Covera), Lisinopril (Prinivil, Zestril),
        Captopril (Capoten), Losartan (Cozaar), Irbesartan (Avapro), etc.

        Testosterone and estrogen supplement

        Current glucocorticoid use, or up to 3 months ago (nasal, topical, ophthalmic, and inhaled
        use are not exclusionary)

        Vitamin supplements containing resveratrol

        Contraindications to MRI Study; e.g. metal implants, pacemaker, etc.

        Smoking nicotine presently or within the last 3 months.

        Known congestive heart failure now or in the past.

        Premenopausal women (menses within 12 months).

        Alcohol consumption more than 30 grams (equivalent to 2.5 glasses of wine) for men or 15
        grams for women (~1.5 glasses of wine) daily.

        Positive HIV or Hepatitis testing.

        Positive urine drug test.

        Positive urine pregnancy test.

        Receipt of any investigational products (e.g. drugs, supplements, dietary interventions)
        as part of a research study within 30 days of initial dose administration

        Unable to provided informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Luigi Ferrucci, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Vickie L Schaffner</last_name>
    <phone>(410) 350-7319</phone>
    <email>schaffnervl@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Luigi Ferrucci, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(410) 558-8110</phone>
    <email>ferruccilu@grc.nia.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Aging, Clinical Research Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wolff JL, Starfield B, Anderson G. Prevalence, expenditures, and complications of multiple chronic conditions in the elderly. Arch Intern Med. 2002 Nov 11;162(20):2269-76.</citation>
    <PMID>12418941</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Walston J, Hadley EC, Ferrucci L, Guralnik JM, Newman AB, Studenski SA, Ershler WB, Harris T, Fried LP. Research agenda for frailty in older adults: toward a better understanding of physiology and etiology: summary from the American Geriatrics Society/National Institute on Aging Research Conference on Frailty in Older Adults. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2006 Jun;54(6):991-1001. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16776798</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kirkland JL. The biology of senescence: potential for prevention of disease. Clin Geriatr Med. 2002 Aug;18(3):383-405. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12424865</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 27, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 25, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Vascular Stiffness</keyword>
  <keyword>Aging</keyword>
  <keyword>Resveratrol</keyword>
  <keyword>Aerobic Capacity</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Resveratrol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
