<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="156266">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01743092</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>153-2012</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01743092</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Testing Resources: Manual and Webinar Guided Treatment vs. Manual Guided Treatment</brief_title>
  <official_title>Meeting the Unique Treatment Needs of Female Gamblers: A Workbook and Webinar Effectiveness Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Research specific to women's gambling treatment needs is limited but suggests a critical
      need for women sensitive options and reduced barriers to access.  This pilot will test the
      effectiveness of a Tutorial Workbook (TW) both as a self-help tool and used in combination
      with a webinar.  Ontario women(n=48) over the age of 19, with gambling concerns, will be
      recruited through flyers, on-line and newspaper ads and randomly assigned to one of two
      groups: (a) TW or (b) TWW (TW plus Webinar).  All will complete questionnaires addressing
      gambling behaviours, personal history and mood states prior to and after the 12 week study.
      Groups (a) and (b) will also provide feedback on the TW's content and relevance. Group (b)
      will, in addition, provide feedback on the Webinar Group. TW and TWW will be valuable
      additions to current treatments, of special importance to reduce barriers for women.  The
      study will contribute to best practices in developing web-based treatments.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Most gambling specific research involves men yet findings are typically generalized to
      women, a shortcoming addressed in the literature. Women are underrepresented in treatment. A
      previous study (Boughton and Brewster, 2002) with 365 Ontario women not in treatment,
      explored barriers and treatment needs. Many respondents indicated that women-only groups and
      self-help materials would be of value. Using web-based resources to increase treatment
      options has merit in a growing technological age. This study will introduce two unique forms
      of treatment, a women friendly tutorial workbook developed specifically to address issues
      commonly underlying women's gambling and a webinar based group facilitated by a gambling
      clinician. Group support has been demonstrated to be highly beneficial for women in reducing
      isolation and shame. The research will assist in developing Best Practices in the problem
      gambling field, especially for women, a neglected and vulnerable group.

      There are two questions:

        1. First, to what extent is the Tutorial Workbook effective by itself as a treatment
           option in helping women make changes to their gambling.

        2. What extent is the addition of the webinar discussion group option an incremental
           benefit to the participant in helping women make changes to their gambling.

      Web based therapy has proven effective in the treatment of addiction and mental health
      issues but more research is needed to assess its efficacy for problem gambling. Self-help
      tools have been demonstrated as effective in reducing gambling but no women specific tools
      are available. Evidence of the effectiveness of the TW and TWW treatment options will reduce
      barriers for hard to serve populations of women and expand options for clinical programs to
      meet the needs of women unable to attend face to face programs. The TW attends to the unique
      issues and treatment/support needs of women with gambling concerns.

      Ultimately the TW materials, once fully developed, can be made available to the general
      public as an online tool, used to assist n providing telephone counselling, individually or
      in a group (Webinar) format or be made available as a self-help paper based utorial
      workbook.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Gambling Behaviours Questionnaire (unpublished)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The questionnaire asks the client about their involvement and spending on 16 different forms of gambling. The intended outcome would be reduced gambling behaviours</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Motivation to gamble (unpublished)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This is a three part questionnaire that asks the client about their motivation to gamble (Boughton, &amp; Brewster, 2002). Part 1 convers INCENTIVES TO GAMBLE, part 2 coverss URGES TO GAMBLE OR KEEP GAMBLING, and part three covers DRAWBACKS TO GAMBLING. The expected outcome would be reduced motivation to gamble. In particular a reduction in their feelings about incentives and urges to gamble and an increase in their awareness of drawbacks to gambling.
Boughton, R. &amp; Brewster, J. (2002). Voices of women who gamble in Ontario: A survey of women's gambling,, barriers to treatment and treatment service needs. Report to Ontario Ministry of Health and Long Term Care. Retrieved from http://www.gamblingresearch.org/download.sz/voicesofwomen%20Boughton%20(1).pdf
?docid=1524</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Pathological Gambling</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tutorial Workbook</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tutorial Workbook Group only receives a Tutorial Workbook Group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tutorial Workbook Group plus webinar</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tutorial Workbook Group plus webinar will receive in addition, a webinar as an additional resource.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Webinar</intervention_name>
    <description>Some clients will receive a webinar as part of their treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tutorial Workbook Group plus webinar</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>online discussion</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tutuorial workbook</intervention_name>
    <description>A work book about their addiciton</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tutorial Workbook</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Tutorial Workbook Group plus webinar</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  pathological gamblers

          -  not currently in formal gambling specific  treatment

          -  English proficiency (reading,  writing and speech)

          -  access to private computer and phone

          -  sufficient computer  skills to engage in webinar

          -  able to fully commit to time demands of weekly participation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  active psychosis

          -  unstable mood disorders

          -  emotion dysregulation

          -  extreme social anxiety

          -  cognitive challenges in reading

          -  not proficient in in English (reading,  writing and speech)

          -  suicidal behaviours

          -  current problems with drugs/ alcohol abuse
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nigel E Turner, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Roberta Boughton, MA</last_name>
    <phone>416-535-8501</phone>
    <phone_ext>3914</phone_ext>
    <email>Roberta.Boughton@camh.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Problem Gambling Treatment Service</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5S 2S1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Roberta Boughton, MA</last_name>
      <phone>(416)535-8501</phone>
      <phone_ext>33914</phone_ext>
      <email>Roberta.Boughton@camh.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Roberta Boughton, MA</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nigel E Turner, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.problemgambling.ca</url>
    <description>Website for the Problem Gambling Institute of Ontario and CAMH's problem gambling service</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 10, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 2, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nigel Turner</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Independent Scientist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pathological gambling</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>online counselling</keyword>
  <keyword>webinar</keyword>
  <keyword>workbook</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Gambling</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
