<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="21628">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01803412</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>115501</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01803412</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of the Safety, Tolerability and Efficacy of Long-term Administration of Drisapersen in United States (US) Subjects With Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label Extension Study of the Long-term Safety, Tolerability and Efficacy of Drisapersen (GSK2402968) in US Subjects With Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Prosensa Therapeutics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Prosensa Therapeutics</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase III, multicenter, open-label, uncontrolled extension study. The Purpose of
      this study is to evaluate the effects of long-term administration of drisapersen in US male
      subjects with Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy (DMD), who have previously participated in one of
      the following eligible studies of drisapersen: DMD114876, DMD114044 and DMD114349. This
      study does not have a minimum duration of participation. The study participation time of the
      subjects will vary depending on when they enter from one of the eligible studies, and will
      be permitted to continue the study until such a time that they withdraw based on
      protocol-defined criteria or GlaxoSmithKline (GSK) stops the study. Subjects will receive
      drisapersen 6 milligrams (mg)/kilogram (kg) as Subcutaneous (SC) injection(s) once a week
      (wk), continuously throughout their duration of participation. For subjects who cannot
      continue on 6 mg/kg/wk for safety and/or tolerability reasons, but who may benefit from
      drisapersen, an alternate intermittent dosing will be given as a regimen of 6 mg/kg/wk for 8
      weeks followed by 4 weeks off treatment. Subjects withdrawing from this study but who do not
      withdraw consent, will be followed up for safety and progress as clinically indicated, for
      at least 20 weeks after the last dose of study treatment, after which a follow-up telephone
      call will be conducted. If subjects withdraw, they will not be replaced.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence and severity of Adverse Events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>AEs will be assessed from Pre-baseline visit until 20 weeks after the subject has either completed the study or withdrawn from treatment early. AEs are any untoward medical occurrence in a patient or clinical investigation subject, temporally associated with the use of a medicinal product, whether or not considered related to the medicinal product</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Systolic and diastolic blood pressure measurements to assess the safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulse rate and respiratory rate measurements to assess the safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Body temperature measurements to assess the safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>12-Lead Electrocardiogram (ECG) measurements to assess the safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The following parameters will be assessed: heart rate, intervals, corrected QT (QTc) interval (Bazett). In addition, an assessment of abnormal morphology will be made</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Echocardiogram measurements to assess the safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The following parameters will be assessed:  Left ventricular end-diastolic/end-systolic wall thickness (septum, posterior wall), fractional shortening (SF) and ejection fraction (LVEF) will be derived from M-mode (from the parasternal long-axis or short-axis view) for quantitative measurements</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Laboratory tests to assess the safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Laboratory tests will include hematology, biochemistry and urinalysis parameters</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Muscle function assessment using 6-minute walking distance (6MWD) test</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subjects will be asked to walk, at their own preferred speed, up and down a fixed distance until they are told to stop after 6 minutes. The subjects are warned of the time and are told that they may stop earlier if they feel unable to continue. The total distance walked within 6 minutes (or until the subject stopped in case of early termination of the test) will be recorded in meters, as well as any falls.  Subjects who became non-ambulant in the prior study or who become non-ambulant during this study will not be able to perform this</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>North Star Ambulatory Assessment (NSAA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The NSAA is a functional scale devised from the Hammersmith Scale of Motor Ability specifically for use in ambulant children with DMD.  It consists of 17 activities graded 0 (unable to perform), 1 (performs with modifications), 2 (normal movement).  The scale assesses activities that are required for ambulatory activity and includes items that are rarely achieved in untreated DMD (jump, hop, raise head) as well as items that are known to progressively deteriorate over time (stand from a chair, walk)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulmonary function assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Non-invasive spirometry will be conducted to determine actual and percent values for Forced Vital Capacity (FVC) and Forced Expiratory Volume (FEV1)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of accidental falls during 6MWD</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of falls as well as the time of occurrence of each fall will be recorded for every subject</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to major disease milestones</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Major disease milestones are defined as those events that occurred since the last time they were assessed and include the following muscular dystrophy-related milestones: Achilles tendon contracture, hamstring contracture, lumbar lordosis, limb skeletal deformity, loss of ambulation, respiratory support during the day, respiratory support during sleep, scoliosis, use of leg braces, use of orthoses, use of special shoes, using Gower's maneuver or other milestone (to be specified)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Outcomes assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Two assessments will be completed to observe the changes in the ability of the subject to perform usual day-to-day activities during the study: 1. Physician Assessment of Daily Living -by the principal investigator, treating physician or suitable proxy who interacts with the subject/parent/caregiver at the corresponding clinic visit, and 2. Functional Outcomes Survey - by the family/caregivers who attends the scheduled clinic visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma concentration of drisapersen - continuous dosing regimen</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 0, 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24, 32, 40 and 48</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma concentration of drisapersen - intermittent dosing regimen</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 0, 7, 12, 19, 24, 31, 36 and 43</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">23</enrollment>
  <condition>Muscular Dystrophies</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Primary Continuous Dosing Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive drisapersen 6 mg/kg as SC injection(s) once a week, continuously throughout their duration of participation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Alternate Intermittent Dosing Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive drisapersen intermittently, as a regimen of 6 mg/kg as SC injection(s) once a week for 8 weeks followed by 4 weeks of no dosing, throughout their duration of participation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Drisapersen</intervention_name>
    <description>Drisapersen will be supplied as 3 mL (milliliter) vials containing 1 mL sterile solution of 200 mg/mL strength. Each subject will receive drisapersen 6 mg/kg administered SC once a week, either continuously or intermittently (for 8 weeks, followed by 4 weeks of no dosing) throughout their duration of participation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Alternate Intermittent Dosing Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Primary Continuous Dosing Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participation in an eligible drisapersen study as follows:

        (A) Prior DMD114876 subjects: Subjects who completed both the 24 week double-blind
        treatment and 24 week post-treatment phases in study DMD114876 OR Subjects who withdrew
        from the treatment portion of study DMD114876 due to meeting laboratory safety stopping
        criteria may be eligible to enrol in the extension study if: the laboratory parameters
        that led to stopping have resolved; the principal investigator (PI) considers the benefit
        of further treatment with drisapersen outweighs the risk to the individual subject; and
        following consultation with the Medical Monitor (B) Prior DMD114044 Subjects: US citizens
        who completed study DMD114044 in another country and who want to return to the US to
        participate in study DMD115501, upon agreement by a DMD115501 Investigator OR US citizens
        who participated in DMD114044 but who had to withdraw from the study due to meeting
        laboratory safety stopping criteria may be eligible to enrol in DMD115501 if: the
        laboratory parameters that led to stopping have resolved; the PI considers the benefit of
        further treatment with drisapersen outweighs the risk to the individual subject; and
        following consultation with the Medical Monitor and upon agreement by a DMD115501
        investigator (C) Prior DMD114349 Subjects: US citizens who participated in and completed
        study DMD114044 in another country and who entered into the ongoing open-label extension
        study DMD114349 in a country outside the US who wish to withdraw from DMD114349 and return
        to the US to participate in study DMD115501, upon agreement by a DMD115501 investigator.
        Subjects are required to withdraw from DMD114349 to participate in this study

          -  Continued use of glucocorticoids for a minimum of 60 days prior to study entry with a
             reasonable expectation that the subject will remain on steroids for the duration of
             the study. Changes to or cessation of glucocorticoids will be at the discretion of
             the PI in consultation with the subject/parent and the Medical Monitor

          -  Willing and able to comply with all protocol requirements and procedures (with the
             exception of those assessments requiring a subject to be ambulant, for those subjects
             who have lost ambulation)

          -  Able to give informed assent and/or consent in writing signed by the subject and/or
             parent(s)/legal guardian (according to local regulations)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject had a serious adverse experience or who met safety stopping criteria that
             remains unresolved from studies DMD115501, DMD114044, or DMD114349, which in the
             opinion of the investigator could have been attributable to study medication, and
             which is ongoing. Once resolved, subject may be eligible to enrol following PI
             consultation with the Medical Monitor

          -  Use of anticoagulants, antithrombotics or antiplatelet agents, or previous treatment
             with investigational drugs except for drisapersen, within 28 days of the first
             administration of study medication

          -  Current or anticipated participation in any other investigational clinical studies

          -  History of significant medical disorder which may confound the interpretation of
             either efficacy or safety data (e.g. current or history of renal or liver
             disease/impairment, history of inflammatory illness)

          -  Symptomatic cardiomyopathy. If subject has a left ventricular ejection fraction &lt;45%
             at Screening, the investigator should discuss inclusion of subject in the study with
             the medical monitor
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Prosensa Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Prosensa Therapeutics</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 28, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>GSK2402968</keyword>
  <keyword>open-label extension</keyword>
  <keyword>safety</keyword>
  <keyword>drisapersen</keyword>
  <keyword>Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy</keyword>
  <keyword>tolerability</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of Life</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Muscular Dystrophy, Duchenne</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Muscular Dystrophies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
