<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="104275">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01986361</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012-STR-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01986361</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Placebo-Controlled Onset-of-Action Study of Flurbiprofen Utilizing the Double-Stopwatch Method</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-Dose, Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Onset-of-Action Study Utilizing the Double-Stopwatch Method</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Reckitt Benckiser LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Reckitt Benckiser LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study's purpose is to demonstrate the onset of action, i.e., time to meaningful pain
      relief in patients with pharyngitis, of flurbiprofen 8.75 mg lozenge using the
      Double-Stopwatch Method (DSW).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Meaningful Pain Relief</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 hours post dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Time to meaningful pain relief is a patient-reported outcome (PRO) captured as part of the double stopwatch method.  Participants depress the second stop watch when they experience what they perceive as meaningful pain relief.  Instructions to participants are:  &quot;Stop the second stopwatch when the sore throat pain relief is meaningful to you. This does not mean you feel completely better, although you might, but when you feel relief of throat pain that is meaningful to you.&quot;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of First Perceived Pain Relief</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Time to first perceived pain relief is a patient-reported outcome (PRO) captured as part of the double stopwatch method. Participants depress the first stop watch when they experience any pain relief, termed &quot;perceived pain relief&quot;.  Instructions to participants are:  &quot;Stop the first stopwatch when you first feel any sore throat pain relief whatsoever. This does not mean you feel completely better, although you might, but when you first feel any relief of the throat pain you have now.&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of first perceived pain relief that is confirmed by meaningful pain relief</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of first indication of sore throat relief as measured by any reduction in the Sore Throat Scale (STS)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of first perceived pain reduction on the Sore Throat Scale (STS) which is followed by ≥ 20% pain reduction on the Sore Throat Pain Intensity Scale (STPIS)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction of sore throat as measured by Sore Throat Scale (STS) at individual time points.</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients with meaningful pain relief</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients with perceived pain relief</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weighted sum of differences on the Sore Throat Scale (STS) over 3 hours (SPID3)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Pharyngitis</condition>
  <condition>Sore Throat</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>flurbiprofen 8.75 mg lozenge</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A single flurbiprofen lozenge is sucked until fully dissolved.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo lozenge</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A single placebo lozenge is sucked until fully dissolved.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>flurbiprofen</intervention_name>
    <description>A single flurbiprofen 8.75 mg lozenge which also contains 1 mg of menthol in its vehicle base for flavour and taste purposes (blinding). Lozenge is sucked until dissolved, and not chewed, bit or swallowed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>flurbiprofen 8.75 mg lozenge</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>A single placebo lozenge which also contains 1 mg of menthol in its vehicle base for flavour and taste purposes (blinding). Lozenge is sucked until dissolved, and not chewed, bit or swallowed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo lozenge</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Primary diagnosis: pharyngitis confirmed by a Tonsillo-Pharyngitis Assessment ≥ 5

          -  Complaint of sore throat with an onset ≤ 4 days prior to randomization

          -  Have at least one symptom of upper respiratory tract infection (URTI) on the URTI
             Questionnaire (e.g., sore throat, runny nose, cough, fever)

          -  Have moderate or severe sore throat pain on the Throat Pain Scale

          -  Have a baseline Sore Throat Scale (STS) ≥ 6

          -  If the patient is a female of childbearing potential, she has been using effective
             contraception since the last date of menses and is not breast-feeding or lactating.
             She is also willing to take adequate contraceptive precautions through 24 hours after
             the completion of the study.

          -  If the patient is a female of childbearing potential, the patient must have a
             negative urine pregnancy test (UPT) result (indicating &quot;not pregnant&quot;) obtained on
             the day of scheduled randomization, prior to the designated time of randomization

          -  The patient is willing to remain at the study centre for 3 hours after receiving the
             dose of study medication

          -  During the 3-hour evaluation of the study medication lozenge at the site, the patient
             is willing to take &quot;nothing by mouth&quot; (e.g., no smoking, food, candy, lozenges,
             chewing gum, liquids).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known allergy and/or hypersensitivity to aspirin or other nonsteroidal
             anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), or any other inactive ingredients such as honey,
             lemon flavor, menthol, or sucrose.

          -  History of an upper gastrointestinal ulcer within the past 60 days, current
             clinically significant upper gastrointestinal complaints, or current regular use (≥ 3
             times in the previous week) of any medication for upper gastrointestinal symptoms,
             including antacids, H2 blockers, proton pump inhibitors or sucralfate

          -  History of any hepatic disease or renal dysfunction

          -  Other severe acute or chronic medical condition that may increase the risk associated
             with study participation or may interfere with the interpretation of study results
             and, in the judgment of the Investigator, would make the patient inappropriate for
             entry into this study.

          -  History of chronic analgesic use (≥ 3 times per week over the prior 4 weeks)

          -  Use of an antibiotic for an acute disease within the previous 24 hours before
             randomization. (Chronic antibiotic use, such as for acne, is acceptable.) Use of any
             quinolone antibiotic such as ciprofloxacin or nalidixic acid within the past week or
             concurrently is specifically prohibited.

          -  Use of mifepristone in the 12 days prior to the screening visit

          -  Use of inhaled therapy (e.g., inhaled steroids or β-agonists, such as Ventolin) on an
             acute basis for disease exacerbation in the week prior to the screening visit

          -  Use of any immediate release analgesic within 4 hours preceding administration of the
             study medication.

          -  Use of any sustained release analgesic within 12 hours preceding administration of
             the study medication.

          -  Use of any &quot;cold medication&quot; (i.e. decongestants, antihistamines, expectorants,
             antitussives) within 4 hours preceding administration of the dose of study
             medication.

          -  Use of any throat lozenge, throat spray, cough drop, or menthol-containing product
             within 2 hours preceding administration of the study medication

          -  Consumption of any caffeine-containing beverage (e.g., coffee, tea, hot chocolate,
             caffeinated soft drinks) within 5 minutes preceding administration of the study
             medication.

          -  Any evidence of mouth-breathing (which could worsen sore throat pain).

          -  Coughing that causes throat discomfort or any active physical disease (such as
             bronchopneumonia) which could compromise respiratory function and worsen a sore
             throat

          -  Unable in the opinion of the Investigator to comply fully with the study requirements
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Timothy Shea, BS</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Reckitt Benckiser LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Timothy J Shea, BS</last_name>
    <phone>973 404 2883</phone>
    <email>tim.shea@reckittbenckiser.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Connecticut - Student Health Services</name>
      <address>
        <city>Storrs</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06269-4011</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Arlene Kerlin, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 11, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 22, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pharyngitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Sore Throat</keyword>
  <keyword>acute upper respiratory tract infection (URTI)</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Pharyngitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Flurbiprofen</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
