<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="28530">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02054416</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PVB012013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02054416</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>External Compression Therapy for Secondary Prevention of Lower-Limb Loss and Cardiovascular Mortality</brief_title>
  <acronym>ArtAssist</acronym>
  <official_title>External Compression Therapy for Secondary Prevention of Lower-Limb Loss and Cardiovascular Mortality in Underserved Philadelphia Patient Population: A Randomized Controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Temple University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Temple University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this clinical research study the investigators will test the efficacy of an innovative,
      non-invasive methodology to reduce mortality and lower limb loss among high-risk
      medically-underserved patients with cardiovascular disease in North Philadelphia.

      Patients with cardiovascular disease and recent lower limb amputation will be treated with
      an intermittent compression device on the remaining lower limb to prevent dual amputation.

      The study hypothesis is that the study intervention will protect against further lower
      limb-loss/death and reduce cardiovascular mortality in these patients (one year effect
      against limb-loss/death).

      This study may result in better secondary prevention strategies for disadvantaged urban
      populations as well as the general population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Amputation free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Amputation of Lower Limb</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Art Assist Device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The ArtAssist© (model AA1000) device is made by ACI Medical located in San Marcos, CA (http://acimedical.com/) and is cleared per FDA under K942530.The study intervention will consist of one hour of IPC with the ArtAssist© device to the remaining leg, three times a day for a three month period. We will obtain the usage data from the device when the subject returns the device (the device has an internal device that stores the usage data) to evaluate subject compliance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sham devices look identical to the actual ArtAssist© devices, but provide low-pressure and differ only in number-coded tubing.  The study &quot;sham intervention&quot; will consist of one hour of IPC with the sham ArtAssist© device to the remaining leg, three times a day for a three month period. We will obtain the usage data from the device when the subject returns the device (the sham device has an internal device that stores the usage data) to evaluate subject compliance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ArtAssist© Device</intervention_name>
    <description>The study intervention will consist of one hour of IPC with the ArtAssist© device to the remaining leg, three times a day for a three month period. We will obtain the usage data from the device when the subject returns the device (the device has an internal device that stores the usage data) to evaluate subject compliance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Art Assist Device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Device</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>The ArtAssist© (model AA1000) device is made by ACI Medical located in San Marcos, CA (http://acimedical.com/) and is cleared per FDA under K942530.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and Female ages ≥ 21years old

          -  Able and willing to provide informed consent

          -  Status post amputation of lower limb

          -  IPC treatment can be initiated within 30 days post lower limb amputation

          -  Ankle-brachial index in the remaining extremity of less than 0.80, or toe-
                 brachial index less than 0 .60 (obtained within last 6 months)

          -  Patients must be able to sit and able to perform the compression  therapy
             independently

          -  Intact renal function or if patient has chronic kidney disease a pre study
             Creatinine will be obtained. If the patient has acute renal failure or is a dialysis
             patient he/she is eligible, but will be separately randomized and analyzed because
             Creatinine is linked to survival.

               -  Subjects status post healed minor (toe/metatarsal) amputations on treatment leg
                  will be included.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have no demonstrable peripheral artery disease by ankle-pressure and/or
             toe-pressure in the remaining limb (initial amputations were mostly precipitated by
             diabetic neuropathy, deformity, infection, or acute embolization.  Amputations
             resulting from the late effects of trauma, burns, frostbite, etc. are also excluded.

          -  Patients who are not able to consent due to their mental status, or who are not
             willing or able to perform the compression therapy in a sitting position

          -  Contracted nursing-home patients with index amputations resulting from largely
             pressure-related tissue-loss decubitus

          -  Patients with infected gangrene or osteomyelitis present in the contra-lateral
             extremity (which would need to be compressed) at the time of the index amputation

          -  Patients with active dry gangrene on the leg that is to be compressed

          -  Patients with congestive heart failure

          -  Patients in which a deep venous thrombosis or pulmonary embolism is suspected

          -  Patients who have undergone arterial compression therapy within 1 year prior to study

          -  Bilateral amputation of lower extremity

          -  Patients with an expected life-span less than 3 months

          -  Patients who require intensive care are not eligible, until they can be transferred
             to a regular nursing floor

          -  Patients in whom the remaining limb is non-functional, for example due to previous
             stroke
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul van Bemmelen, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paul van Bemmelen, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>215-707-3622</phone>
    <email>Paul.vanBemmelen@tuhs.temple.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Marian De Backer, RN, BSN</last_name>
    <phone>215-707-7143</phone>
    <email>marian.debacker@tuhs.temple.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Temple University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19140</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paul van Bemmelen, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>215-707-3622</phone>
      <email>paul.vanBemmelen@tuhs.temple.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Marian De Backer, RN, BSN</last_name>
      <phone>215-707-7143</phone>
      <email>marian.debacker@tuhs.temple.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 31, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Temple University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Paul van Bemmelen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>non-traumatic lower limb amputation</keyword>
  <keyword>AKA</keyword>
  <keyword>BKA</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
