<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="53759">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02056431</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CE-1304-7250</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02056431</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Balancing Treatment Outcomes and Medication Burden Among Patients With Symptomatic Diabetic Peripheral Neuropathy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Balancing Treatment Outcomes and Medication Burden Among Patients With Symptomatic Diabetic Peripheral Neuropathy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kaiser Permanente</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Patient Centered Outcome Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kaiser Permanente</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Painful diabetic peripheral neuropathy (DPN) affects more than 5.5 million people with
      diabetes. People with painful DPN have trouble sleeping, participating in social events, and
      conducting daily activities such as going to the store. Several prescription medications are
      available for the treatment of DPN symptoms, but none work perfectly and all have side
      effects that may be difficult for some patients.

      When patients report their symptoms and side effects to their doctor, they provide the
      doctor with important information to help them make adjustments to treatment that will help
      with symptoms and that the patient can tolerate in terms of side effects. In some cases,
      doctors may encourage patients to make these changes on their own at home based on their
      experience with therapy. However, patients may have a long time between visits to their
      doctor and may have trouble describing their symptoms to their doctor during a brief 10 to
      15 minute visit.

      This clinical trial explores the possibility of computerized telephone calls to patients
      (Interactive Voice Response, IVR, technology) to gather information about treatment
      experiences that can then be reported to the doctor or used to guide patients to make
      changes in how they take the medication. It addresses the following question: Can routinely
      asking patients about their experiences with medications and using that information to
      encourage clinically appropriate titration improve patient quality of life?

      The investigators hypothesize that systematic collection and feedback of information about
      DPN treatment preferences and experience from newly treated patients to their primary care
      physician will facilitate treatment changes that improve patient outcomes
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Among newly-treated Diabetic Peripheral Neuropathy (DPN) patients, the investigators will
      compare the systematic collection and feedback of information about patients' treatment
      experiences on changes in quality of life (intervention group) to newly treated DPN patients
      in usual care  who will receive generic educational messages by phone but no active data
      collection and feedback (comparator group).  The investigators have chosen usual care as the
      control to evaluate the potential for the intervention to enhance current practice.

      Aim 1: Refine and pilot test instruments for collecting the patient-reported data most
      important for guiding changes in treatment.

      Aim 2: Implement a seven-month cluster randomized  trial to improve quality of life among
      patients newly treated for DPN symptoms by collecting data on patient treatment experiences
      and facilitating evidence-based patient and provider-initiated treatment titration.

      Aim 3: Examine patient and physician initiated treatment changes as secondary outcomes in
      order to inform the development of this type of rapid feedback process for guiding decision
      making about initial treatment selection among patients with DPN.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Patient Quality of Life at 7 months</measure>
    <time_frame>7 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient and physician initiated changes in medication in the treatment regimen (e.g. discontinuation).</measure>
    <time_frame>7 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2124</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetic Peripheral Neuropathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Interactive Voice Response Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>1,062 participants will receive 3 interactive voice response calls (2nd, 4th, and 6th month post-treatment start date)  to collect information on medication use, side effects, rating of side effects, and pain symptoms to be fed back to their physicians.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Interactive Voice Response Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>1,062 participants will receive 3 non-interactive voice response calls (2nd, 4th, and 6th month post-treatment start date) containing general messages regarding diabetic education.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Interactive Voice Response Intervention Group</intervention_name>
    <description>1,062 participants will receive 3 interactive voice response calls (2nd, 4th, and 6th month post-treatment start date)  to collect information on medication use, side effects, rating of side effects, and pain symptoms to be fed back to their physicians.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Interactive Voice Response Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients newly prescribed medication to treat diabetic peripheral neuropathy
             symptoms.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with any evidence of use of diabetic peripheral neuropathy study
             medications.

          -  Patients with evidence of gestational diabetes (ICD-9: 648.8) due to variation in
             treatment and monitoring for women who are pregnant.

          -  Patients who simultaneously received a new diagnosis for depression or seizure
             conditions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alyce S. Adams, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kaiser Permanente Northern California</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rosa M. Hippler, MA</last_name>
    <phone>510-891-3721</phone>
    <email>Rosa.M.Hippler@kp.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 31, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Kaiser Permanente</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alyce Adams</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Research Scientist II</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Neuropathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient-Reported Outcomes</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Nervous System Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Demyelinating Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Polyneuropathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nerve Compression Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neurologic Manifestations</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neurotoxicity Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Neuropathies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
