<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="121108">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02024971</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>073-011</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>JapicCTI-132368</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02024971</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Special Drug Use Surveillance of Pioglitazone/Metformin Hydrochloride Combination Tablets Survey on Long-term Use for Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</brief_title>
  <official_title>Metact® Combination Tablets Special Drug Use Surveillance Survey on Long-term Use for Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Takeda</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Japan: Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate the safety and efficacy of long-term use of
      pioglitazone/metformin hydrochloride combination tablets in the routine clinical setting in
      patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus for whom therapy with pioglitazone hydrochlorie
      combined with metformin hydrochloride is considered suitable.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a special drug use surveillance (survey on long-term use) designed to investigate
      the safety and efficacy of long-term use of pioglitazone/metformin hydrochloride combination
      tablets (Metact Combination Tablets) in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus in the
      routine clinical setting.

      The following items will also be studied:

        1. The effects on safety and efficacy caused by changing the administration method of
           metformin hydrochloride associated with switching to Metact Combination Tablets

        2. The effects on compliance associated with switching to Metact Combination Tablets

        3. Safety and efficacy in patients who showed inadequate response to pioglitazone
           hydrochloride and were then switched to Metact Combination Tablets

      The planned sample size was 1000 participants. The usual adult dosage is one tablet of
      Metact administered orally once daily after breakfast (15 mg/500 mg or 30 mg/500 mg of
      pioglitazone/metformin hydrochloride).

      &lt;Precautions Related to Dosage and Administration&gt; Edema due to pioglitazone administration
      has been reported with comparative frequency in women. Therefore, it is preferable to be
      vigilant for edema and start Metact Combination Tablets at a dosage equivalent to 15 mg of
      pioglitazone once daily when administering the study drug to women.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of adverse drug reactions</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 12 months of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Frequency, severity, and time to onset of adverse drug reactions tabulated by each symptom. Adverse events are defined as any unfavorable and unintended signs, symptoms or diseases temporally associated with the use of a medicinal product reported from the first dose of study drug to the last dose of study drug. Among these, events which are considered possibly associated with a medicinal product are defined as adverse drug reactions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in glycosylated hemoglobin (HbA1c)</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 12 months of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Tabulation of the HbA1c test value and change at each test time point (test value at each test time point after baseline - test value at baseline).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in fasting blood glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 12 months of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Tabulation of fasting blood glucose test values and change at each test time point (test value at each test time point after baseline - test value at baseline).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in fasting insulin</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 12 months of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Tabulation of fasting insulin test values and change at each test time point (test value at each test time point after baseline - test value at baseline).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1103</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pioglitazone/metformin hydrochloride</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pioglitazone/metformin hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Pioglitazone/metformin hydrochloride combination tablets</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pioglitazone/metformin hydrochloride</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Metact Combination Tablets</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Type 2 diabetes mellitus
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus for whom a physician has concluded that
             therapy with pioglitazone hydrochloride combined with metaformin hydrochloride is
             suitable and for whom long-term treatment with Metact Combination Tablets is
             considered necessary.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients for whom pioglitazone hydrochloride and metformin hydrochloride are
             contraindicated.

               1. Patients with cardiac insufficiency or a history of cardiac insufficiency

               2. Patients with the following conditions (i) Patients with a history of lactic
                  acidosis (ii) Dialysis patients (including peritoneal dialysis) (iii) Patients
                  with cardiovascular conditions such as shock, cardiac insufficiency, myocardial
                  infarction, and pulmonary embolism; patients with severely impaired pulmonary
                  function; and patients with other conditions fostering susceptibility to
                  hypoxemia (iv) Patients with excessive alcohol consumption (v) Patients with
                  dehydration (vi) Patients with gastrointestinal disorders such as diarrhea and
                  vomiting (vii) Elderly patients

               3. Patients with renal impairment (including mild renal impairment)

               4. Patients with hepatic impairment

               5. Patients with severe ketosis, diabetic coma or pre-coma, or type I diabetes
                  mellitus

               6. Patients with severe infection, severe trauma, or pre- and post-operative
                  patients

               7. Patients who are malnourished, starved, debilitated, or have pituitary gland
                  insufficiency or adrenal gland insufficiency

               8. Patients with a history of hypersensitivity to the ingredients in Metact
                  Combination Tablets or biguanides

               9. Pregnant or potentially pregnant women
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Postmarketing Group Manager</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Takeda</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 29, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 29, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Drug therapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Pioglitazone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
