<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="41966">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02041624</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ORA-PES-05-WO</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02041624</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>International Registry on the Quality of Life of Patients With Grass-pollen-induced Allergic Rhinitis</brief_title>
  <acronym>ALTO</acronym>
  <official_title>An International Non-Interventional Registry on the Quality of Life of Patients With Grass-pollen-induced Allergic Rhinitis Treated With Oralair®.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stallergenes</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stallergenes</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Austria: Federal Office for Safety in Health Care</authority>
    <authority>Belgium: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>France: Comité consultatif sur le traitement de l'information en matière de recherche dans le domaine de la santé</authority>
    <authority>France: Conseil National de l'Ordre des Médecins</authority>
    <authority>France: The Commission nationale de l’informatique et des libertés</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Paul-Ehrlich-Institut</authority>
    <authority>Italy: The Italian Medicines Agency</authority>
    <authority>Netherlands: The Central Committee on Research Involving Human Subjects (CCMO)</authority>
    <authority>Russia: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Agencia Española de Medicamentos y Productos Sanitarios</authority>
    <authority>Switzerland: Ethikkommission</authority>
    <authority>Turkey: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the present study is to describe patient's perception of quality of life and
      effectiveness of ORALAIR® over a follow-up period up to 5 years, in real-life settings.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary objective:

      To describe the patient's perception of the impact of ORALAIR® on his/her health related
      generic and disease specific quality of life during the grasspollen season in real-life
      settings.

      Secondary objectives:

        -  To describe the patient's perceived effectiveness of ORALAIR® in allergic
           rhinoconjunctivitis management in terms of disease intensity, satisfaction and rescue
           medication

        -  To describe the patient adherence and compliance to ORALAIR® treatment

        -  To describe the socio-economic impact of ORALAIR®

      There will be two phases of data collection :

        1. st Phase: Screening visit (V0) During the 2014 grass-pollen season, investigators will
           consecutively include all patients meeting the selection criteria of the 1st Phase.
           Should the number of included patients be insufficient after the 2014 grass-pollen
           season, additional patients meeting the selection criteria of the 1st phase could be
           included in the 1st phase during the 2015 grass-pollen season. The 1st phase of the
           study is meant to collect data during the grass-pollen season in patients with allergic
           rhino-conjunctivitis and without any Allergen ImmunoTherapy treatment (AIT).

        2. nd Phase: Longitudinal Study

             -  Treatment-start visit (V1):

      Investigators will include in the 2nd Phase of the study all patients of the 1st phase
      starting a treatment with ORALAIR®, approximately 4 months before the 2015 grass-pollen
      season for patients included in the 1st phase during the 2014 grass-pollen season, and
      should the case arise, 4 months before the 2016 grass-pollen season for patients included in
      the 1st phase during the 2015 grass-pollen season. For every else patients of the 1st phase
      not included in the 2nd phase of the study, therefore not continuing the study, the
      investigator will record them in the Patient Log.

      - Follow-up visits: Patients will be followed-up, in accordance with the normal course of
      patient care. Follow-up visits are routinely performed approximately twice a year (depending
      upon each physician's current practice and local specificity of the country). Patients will
      remain in the study even if a visit is not performed, unless they have explicitly requested
      to be withdrawn from the study.

      - Additional visit-s: Should the patient come for a visit not considered in the visits
      hereby presented, the physician will complete an additional visit form of the e-CRF.

      - Direct patient follow-up: During the follow-up period, the patient (and/or, in the case of
      a minor, his/her parents or legally acceptable representatives) will receive 3 Patient
      Booklets sent by ProClinica™ by post mail at the beginning of each grasspollen season. The
      patient (and/or, in the case of a minor, his/her parents or legally acceptable
      representatives) will be asked to complete a Patient Booklet respectively at 2 weeks, 3
      weeks and 4 weeks after the beginning of the grasspollen season, and to send them back to
      Mapi after the last booklet is completed.

      As an observational study, the decision of subjects to take part in this study will not have
      any impact on the patient/investigator relation, nor influence the investigator's drug
      prescription or therapeutic management of the patient. Therefore the patient's reported
      outcomes will not be communicated to the investigators during the course of the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Ecologic or Community, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <target_duration>5 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Health related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>patients will be followed for the duration of the treatment, an expected average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary objective is to describe the patient's perception of the impact of ORALAIR® on his/her health related generic and disease specific quality of life during the grass-pollen season in real-life settings.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment Effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>patients will be followed for the duration of the treatment, an expected average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To describe the patient's perceived effectiveness of ORALAIR® in allergic rhino-conjunctivitis management in terms of disease intensity, satisfaction and rescue medication</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence and Compliance</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients will be followed for the duration of the treatment, an expected average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To describe the patient adherence and compliance to Oralair® treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Socio-economic impact</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients will be followed for the duration of the treatment, an expected average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A composite outcome measure consisting of composite values from the other secondary objectives to describe the socio-economic impact of ORALAIR®</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1500</enrollment>
  <condition>Allergic Rhinitis Due to Grass Pollens</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>allergic rhino-conjunctivitis</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patient with proven allergic rhino-conjunctivitis due to grass pollen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with allergic rhino-conjunctivitis are visiting their allergist during
        grass-pollen season when symptoms are strong. In accordance with the terms of the
        Marketing Authorization, ORALAIR® treatment has to be set-up &quot;at the right moment&quot; about 4
        months before the next grass-pollen season.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient of 5 years of age and older at the date of the screening visit

          -  Patient with proven allergic rhino-conjunctivitis due to grass pollen

          -  Patient eligible for a grass-pollen Allergen ImmunoTherapy (AIT)

          -  Patient who has not received any Allergen Immunotherapy Treatment over the last 2
             years

          -  Patient whose physician prescribed ORALAIR® independently of the study, before the
             beginning of the grass-pollen season

          -  Patient (and/or parents or legally acceptable representatives when applicable) with
             the cognitive and linguistic capacities necessary to complete questionnaires in the
             language of his country

          -  Patient (and/or parents or legally acceptable representatives when applicable) who
             agree to participate in the study and have read, understood, completed and signed the
             Informed Consent Form

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient participating in a clinical trial or in an epidemiological study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alain DIDIER, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hôpital Larrey, Toulouse, France</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bruno ROBIN, Pharm. D</last_name>
    <phone>+33155592000</phone>
    <phone_ext>2674</phone_ext>
    <email>brobin@stallergenes.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Antoine F. ABALLEA, Ph. D.</last_name>
    <phone>+33155592000</phone>
    <phone_ext>2884</phone_ext>
    <email>aaballea@stallergenes.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Laboratoire Stallergenes</name>
      <address>
        <city>Antony</city>
        <zip>92183</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.stallergenes.com/en.html</url>
    <description>Stallergenes Corporate website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 17, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 14, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>allergic</keyword>
  <keyword>rhinitis</keyword>
  <keyword>conjunctivitis</keyword>
  <keyword>grass pollen</keyword>
  <keyword>Allergen ImmunoTherapy (AIT)</keyword>
  <keyword>grass mix</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Rhinitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
