<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="82422">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02052648</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NLG2102</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02052648</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of IDO Inhibitor and Temozolomide for Adult Patients With Primary Malignant Brain Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Study of the Combination of Indoximod and Temozolomide for Adult Patients With Temozolomide-Refractory Primary Malignant Brain Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NewLink Genetics Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NewLink Genetics Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study, investigators will conduct a phase I/II trial in recurrent (temozolomide
      resistant) glioma patients. The overall goal of this study is to provide a foundation for
      future studies with indoximod tested in newly diagnosed glioblastoma patients with radiation
      and temozolomide, or in combination with vaccine therapies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to identify the safety profile and the recommended dose for phase 2
      study of the combination of indoximod (portion 1, phase 1b study). Investigators will then
      evaluate the tolerability and the preliminary activity in patients with recurrent GBM in
      three different situations:

        -  Combination of indoximod and temozolomide (bevacizumab-naive patients)

        -  Combination of indoximod and temozolomide with bevacizumab

        -  Combination of indoximod and temozolomide with stereotactic radiation. Ancillary
           studies will be conducted to assess the correlation between intra-tumoral IDO
           expression or serum biomarkers (immune monitoring) and treatment efficacy.

      If the current study shows an acceptable safety profile and suggests preliminary evidence of
      activity, this will provide the justification for subsequent randomized phase 2 studies in
      refractory glioblastoma multiforme (GBM).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2 Dosing</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Phase 1b component:
Primary objective is to determine the recommended Phase 2 dose of indoximod and temozolomide in combination for treatment of progressive high-grade glioma (including glioblastoma multiforme) or gliosarcoma.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Phase 1b component:
To determine the adverse event profile (event type, incidence severity, duration causality and treatment intervention) and identify regimen-limiting toxicities (RLT) of indoximod plus temozolomide in combination therapy.
Specifically, investigators define regimen-limiting toxicity (RLT) as a toxicity that delays the planned administration of the next cycle of the backbone chemotherapy. The goal of the trial will be to find the maximum dose of indoximod that does not induce RLT in more than 1/6 of patients treated with temozolomide.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Dose of Temozolomide Delivered Versus Historical Control</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To test the hypothesis that the addition of indoximod will not reduce the overall dose of temozolomide delivered or delay the timing of administration, compared to historical controls using T-test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Phase 1b component:
To determine the pharmacokinetic profile of indoximod in the setting of this treatment regimen. A thorough pharmacokinetic (PK) profile will be performed for each patient entered into the study through analysis of blood samples collected at protocol-defined time points.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Glioblastoma Multiforme</condition>
  <condition>Glioma</condition>
  <condition>Gliosarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Malignant Brain Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1b Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Phase 1B patients will receive Indoximod given in escalating doses. Initial dosing will be 600 mg BID by mouth with escalation planned to 1200 mg BID by mouth. The medication should be taken twice daily for 28 days each cycle.
Temozolomide will also be given by mouth at 150 mg/m^2 x 5 days at all dosing levels of indoximod. Each cycle is 28 days. Patients will continue until they experience disease progression or toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Indoximod</intervention_name>
    <description>Indoximod will be administered in escalating doses. Initial dosing will be 600 mg BID by mouth with escalation planned to 1200 mg BID by mouth
Indoximod in the form of 200 mg capsules will be given (3, 5, and 6 capsules depending on the escalated dose). Indoximod should be taken with water by mouth one hour before breakfast and one hour prior to dinner. The medication should be taken twice daily for 28 days each cycle. Patients will continue until they experience disease progression or toxicity.
If temozolomide is discontinued due to toxicity, patients may continue to receive indoximod alone.
Phase 2 Treatment Plan (Cohort 2):
This group of patients will receive fixed doses of indoximod determined in the phase 1 part, based on tolerability.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1b Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>1-methyl-D-tryptophan</other_name>
    <other_name>D-1MT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Temozolomide</intervention_name>
    <description>Phase 1 portion:
Temozolomide to be given by mouth at 150 mg/m^2 x 5 days at all dosing levels of indoximod. Each cycle is 28 days. Patients will continue until they experience disease progression or toxicity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1b Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Temodar</other_name>
    <other_name>Methazolastone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically proven intracranial glioblastoma multiforme (WHO grade IV glioma) or
             gliosarcoma. In addition, the Phase 1b cohort will include patients with progressive
             WHO grade III glioma. There must be imaging confirmation (with and without gadolinium
             contrast) of tumor progression or regrowth.

          -  Patients will be eligible if the original histology was lower grade glioma and a
             subsequent diagnosis of glioblastoma or gliosarcoma is made.

          -  Unequivocal radiographic evidence for tumor progression by MRI.

          -  Patients must have completed a course of radiation therapy and at least 2 adjuvant
             cycles of temozolomide for the phase 2 component.

          -  Prior temozolomide is not required for the phase 1 component; prior radiation is
             required for the phase 1 arm. It is suggested (but not required) that patients be at
             least 3 months post radiation to reduce the chances of pseudoprogression.

          -  Patients must be on a steroid dose less than 2 mg of dexamethasone daily (or
             equivalent), and this dose must not have increased for at least 14 days prior to
             obtaining the enrollment.

          -  ECOG performance status ≤1 or Karnofsky ≥70%.

          -  Age between 18 and 70

          -  Normal organ functions, which includes adequate: Bone marrow function as defined by
             the following laboratory values:

               -  Absolute Neutrophil Count (ANC) ≥ 1.0 x 10^9/L

               -  Platelets ≥ 100 x 10^9/L

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dL

          -  Renal function (creatinine level within normal institutional limit, or creatinine
             clearance ≥60 mL/min/1.73 m2 for patients with creatinine levels above institutional
             normal).

          -  Liver function (AST/ALT ≤2.5 X institutional upper limit of normal, Total bilirubin ≤
             1.5 times ULN, INR within 1.5 times ULN (or if receiving anticoagulant therapy an INR
             of ≤ 3.0 is allowed with concomitant increase in PT or an aPTT ≤ 2.5 × control).

          -  Must be 28 days from the administration of any investigational agent or prior
             cytotoxic therapy with the following exceptions:

             o Must be 14 days from administration of non-cytotoxic agents (e.g., bevacizumab
             (except COHORT 2b), interferon, tamoxifen, thalidomide, cis-retinoic acid, tyrosine
             kinase inhibitor, etc.).

          -  Patients with prior therapy that included interstitial brachytherapy, Gliadel wafer,
             or stereotactic radiosurgery must have confirmation of progressive disease, rather
             than radiation necrosis, by PET scanning, Thallium scanning, MRI spectroscopy, or
             surgical documentation.

          -  The effects of indoximod on the developing human fetus are unknown. For this reason
             and because indoximod may affect maternal immune tolerance of the fetus, sexually
             active women of child-bearing potential must agree to use two forms of contraception
             (hormonal and barrier method of birth control or abstinence) prior to study entry and
             for the duration of study participation. Use of contraception or abstinence should
             continue for a minimum of 1 month after completion of the study. Should a woman
             become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while participating in this study, she
             should discontinue the study drug and inform her treating physician immediately. Also
             men should be discouraged from fathering children while on treatment.

          -  Life expectancy greater than 6 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior invasive malignancy that is not the low-grade glioma, high-grade glioma,
             glioblastoma, or gliosarcoma (except non-melanomatous skin cancer or carcinoma in
             situ of the cervix) unless the patient has been disease free and off therapy for that
             disease for a minimum of 3 years.

          -  Patients on the phase 2 portion of the study may not have more than 2 prior regimens
             for recurrent disease for glioblastoma/gliosarcoma. Patients on the phase 1 portion
             of the study may not have had more than 3 prior regimens.

          -  Active systemic infection requiring treatment, including any HIV infection or
             toxoplasmosis.

          -  Systemic corticosteroid therapy &gt; 2 mg of dexamethasone daily (or equivalent) at
             study enrollment.

          -  Patients with significantly altered mental status that would prohibit the
             understanding or rendering of informed consent and compliance with the requirements
             of this protocol must have a legally authorized representative (LAR) willing to
             participate and support the patient throughout the trial. Affected patients without a
             LAR are excluded from participation.

          -  Other severe acute or chronic medical or psychiatric condition, or laboratory
             abnormality that may increase the risk associated with study participation or study
             drug administration, or may interfere with the interpretation of study results, and
             in the judgment of the investigator would make the patient inappropriate for entry
             into this study.

          -  Active or history of autoimmune disease

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study, where pregnancy is confirmed by a
             positive serum hCG laboratory test (&gt; 5 mIU/mL); breastfeeding should be
             discontinued.

          -  Patients with known autoimmune thyroid disease or positive anti-TPO antibodies
             (anti-Thyroid Peroxidase) at time of screening.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicholas Vahanian, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>NewLink Genetics Corporation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Georgia Regents University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Augusta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30912</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christine Sanchez, RN</last_name>
      <phone>706-721-0660</phone>
      <email>csanchez@gru.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Olivier Rixe, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 29, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>glioblastoma multiforme</keyword>
  <keyword>glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>gliosarcoma</keyword>
  <keyword>malignant brain tumor</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gliosarcoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Temozolomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dacarbazine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
