<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="21757">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01977612</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201304058</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01977612</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Randomized Clinical Trial of Skin Closure With Staples Versus Suture</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Controlled Phase IIB Trial Evaluating Wound Complication Rate After Skin Closure With Staples Versus Subcuticular Suture in Patients With BMI &gt;=30</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Women with gynecologic cancers are often obese and have other risk factors for
      post-operative wound separation. Data from obstetrics and orthopedic surgery literature have
      shown a decreased risk of wound separation and complications when the skin is closed with
      suture as compared to staples. Skin closure with either staples or suture is considered
      standard of care. Traditionally, most wounds have been closed with staples given their ease
      of use and quick application. In this randomized study the investigators plan to evaluate
      and compare the complication rate associated with both standard closures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators propose a randomized controlled trial to evaluate for a difference in
      wound complication rate between closure with sutures that are placed just below the skin
      level to hold the skin together and metal staples in obese women (BMI&gt;=30) undergoing
      gynecologic or gynecologic oncology via a midline skin incision for benign or cancer
      indications under the supervision of one of the full-time faculty members of the Division of
      Gynecologic Oncology at Washington University School of Medicine.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite of wound disruption or infection occurring within 4-8 weeks of the date of the primary surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>4-8 weeks post-surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of wound disruption within 4-8 weeks of the date of the primary surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>4-8 week post-surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of wound infection within 4-8 weeks of the date of the primary surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>4-8 weeks post-surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Purulent drainage, cellulitis, abscess, or a wound that requires drainage, debridement or antibiotics associated with a clinical diagnosis of infection.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Operative time</measure>
    <time_frame>During surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Time from skin incision to the end of skin closure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Analog pain score on postoperative days 3-4</measure>
    <time_frame>3-4 days post-op</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The highest pain score as recorded by nursing staff at a minimum of every 8 hours between 72-96 hours postoperatively.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cosmesis score</measure>
    <time_frame>4-8 weeks post-operative</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Score on a cosmesis survey as filled out by provider.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction score</measure>
    <time_frame>4-8 weeks post-operative</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients will be asked to rate the general appearance, location and comfort of the scar.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">162</enrollment>
  <condition>Wound Infection</condition>
  <condition>Wound Complication</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Staples</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients will undergo a surgical proceduure for treatment/diagnosis of their disease as part of standard care. They will be randomized pre-operatively to closure with either staples or sutures. In one arm the patients will have their skin closed with steel staples.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Suture</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients will undergo a surgical proceduure for treatment/diagnosis of their disease as part of standard care. They will be randomized pre-operatively to closure with either staples or sutures. In the second arm, patients will have their skin closed with subcuticular sutures.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Subcuticular suture</intervention_name>
    <description>Subcuticular suture will be used instead of staples in closing the skin of patients enrolled in one arm of this study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Suture</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Staple closure</intervention_name>
    <description>Staples will be used instead of sutures in closing the incision in one arm of the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Staples</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All women, &gt;=18 and &lt;= 85 years of age, undergoing surgery, via a midline laparotomy.

          -  Body mass index &gt;=30

          -  Benign or oncologic indications for surgery.

          -  Women of childbearing age will be required to have a negative human chorionic
             gonadotropin (HCG) test within seven days of surgery.

          -  Surgery will be supervised by one of the gynecologic oncology attendings at
             Washington University School of Medicine.

          -  Ability to understand and willingness to sign an IRB approved written informed
             consent document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding

          -  Pfannenstiel or transverse abdominal incision

          -  Concomitant panniculectomy or plastic surgery

          -  Women &lt;18 years of age

          -  History of prior abdominal or pelvic radiation

          -  Inability to sign an informed consent form prior to registration on study

          -  Inability to understand spoken or written English

          -  Prisoner

          -  Mental incapacity

          -  A history of allergic reactions attributed to either Monocryl suture or stainless
             steel staples.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Akiva Novetsky, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Akiva P Novetsky, MD, MS</last_name>
    <phone>314-362-3181</phone>
    <email>novetskya@wudosis.wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Lynne Lippmann</last_name>
    <phone>314-362-3181</phone>
    <email>lippmannl@wudosis.wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine and Barnes Jewish Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>St Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Akiva P Novetsky, MD, MS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perencevich EN, Sands KE, Cosgrove SE, Guadagnoli E, Meara E, Platt R. Health and economic impact of surgical site infections diagnosed after hospital discharge. Emerg Infect Dis. 2003 Feb;9(2):196-203.</citation>
    <PMID>12603990</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nugent EK, Hoff JT, Gao F, Massad LS, Case A, Zighelboim I, Mutch DG, Thaker PH. Wound complications after gynecologic cancer surgery. Gynecol Oncol. 2011 May 1;121(2):347-52. doi: 10.1016/j.ygyno.2011.01.026. Epub 2011 Feb 15.</citation>
    <PMID>21324517</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cardosi RJ, Drake J, Holmes S, Tebes SJ, Hoffman MS, Fiorica JV, Roberts WS, Grendys EC Jr. Subcutaneous management of vertical incisions with 3 or more centimeters of subcutaneous fat. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2006 Aug;195(2):607-14; discussion 614-6. Epub 2006 Jun 21.</citation>
    <PMID>16796988</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gallup DC, Gallup DG, Nolan TE, Smith RP, Messing MF, Kline KL. Use of a subcutaneous closed drainage system and antibiotics in obese gynecologic patients. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 1996 Aug;175(2):358-61; discussion 362.</citation>
    <PMID>8765253</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Soisson AP, Olt G, Soper JT, Berchuck A, Rodriguez G, Clarke-Pearson DL. Prevention of superficial wound separation with subcutaneous retention sutures. Gynecol Oncol. 1993 Dec;51(3):330-4.</citation>
    <PMID>8112641</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anthony T, Murray BW, Sum-Ping JT, Lenkovsky F, Vornik VD, Parker BJ, McFarlin JE, Hartless K, Huerta S. Evaluating an evidence-based bundle for preventing surgical site infection: a randomized trial. Arch Surg. 2011 Mar;146(3):263-9. doi: 10.1001/archsurg.2010.249. Epub 2010 Nov 15.</citation>
    <PMID>21079110</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Magann EF, Chauhan SP, Rodts-Palenik S, Bufkin L, Martin JN Jr, Morrison JC. Subcutaneous stitch closure versus subcutaneous drain to prevent wound disruption after cesarean delivery: a randomized clinical trial. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2002 Jun;186(6):1119-23.</citation>
    <PMID>12066083</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ramsey PS, White AM, Guinn DA, Lu GC, Ramin SM, Davies JK, Neely CL, Newby C, Fonseca L, Case AS, Kaslow RA, Kirby RS, Rouse DJ, Hauth JC. Subcutaneous tissue reapproximation, alone or in combination with drain, in obese women undergoing cesarean delivery. Obstet Gynecol. 2005 May;105(5 Pt 1):967-73.</citation>
    <PMID>15863532</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Figueroa D, Jauk VC, Szychowski JM, Garner R, Biggio JR, Andrews WW, Hauth J, Tita AT. Surgical staples compared with subcuticular suture for skin closure after cesarean delivery: a randomized controlled trial. Obstet Gynecol. 2013 Jan;121(1):33-8. doi: http://10.1097/AOG.0b013e31827a072c.</citation>
    <PMID>23262925</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frishman GN, Schwartz T, Hogan JW. Closure of Pfannenstiel skin incisions. Staples vs. subcuticular suture. J Reprod Med. 1997 Oct;42(10):627-30.</citation>
    <PMID>9350017</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cromi A, Ghezzi F, Gottardi A, Cherubino M, Uccella S, Valdatta L. Cosmetic outcomes of various skin closure methods following cesarean delivery: a randomized trial. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2010 Jul;203(1):36.e1-8. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2010.02.001. Epub 2010 Apr 24.</citation>
    <PMID>20417924</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Graaf IM, Oude Rengerink K, Wiersma IC, Donker ME, Mol BW, Pajkrt E. Techniques for wound closure at caesarean section: a randomized clinical trial. Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol. 2012 Nov;165(1):47-52. doi: 10.1016/j.ejogrb.2012.07.019. Epub 2012 Aug 19.</citation>
    <PMID>22910336</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rousseau JA, Girard K, Turcot-Lemay L, Thomas N. A randomized study comparing skin closure in cesarean sections: staples vs subcuticular sutures. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2009 Mar;200(3):265.e1-4.</citation>
    <PMID>19254586</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clay FS, Walsh CA, Walsh SR. Staples vs subcuticular sutures for skin closure at cesarean delivery: a metaanalysis of randomized controlled trials. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2011 May;204(5):378-83. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2010.11.018. Epub 2010 Dec 31.</citation>
    <PMID>21195384</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tuuli MG, Rampersad RM, Carbone JF, Stamilio D, Macones GA, Odibo AO. Staples compared with subcuticular suture for skin closure after cesarean delivery: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Obstet Gynecol. 2011 Mar;117(3):682-90. doi: 10.1097/AOG.0b013e31820ad61e. Review. Erratum in: Obstet Gynecol. 2011 Jun;117(6):1440.</citation>
    <PMID>21343772</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mackeen AD, Berghella V, Larsen ML. Techniques and materials for skin closure in caesarean section. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2012 Nov 14;11:CD003577. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD003577.pub3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23152219</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shetty AA, Kumar VS, Morgan-Hough C, Georgeu GA, James KD, Nicholl JE. Comparing wound complication rates following closure of hip wounds with metallic skin staples or subcuticular vicryl suture: a prospective randomised trial. J Orthop Surg (Hong Kong). 2004 Dec;12(2):191-3.</citation>
    <PMID>15621905</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haymer DS, Marsh JL. Germ line and somatic instability of a white mutation in Drosophila mauritiana due to a transposable genetic element. Dev Genet. 1986;6(4):281-91.</citation>
    <PMID>2840224</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fick JL, Novo RE, Kirchhof N. Comparison of gross and histologic tissue responses of skin incisions closed by use of absorbable subcuticular staples, cutaneous metal staples, and polyglactin 910 suture in pigs. Am J Vet Res. 2005 Nov;66(11):1975-84.</citation>
    <PMID>16334959</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Singer AJ, Arora B, Dagum A, Valentine S, Hollander JE. Development and validation of a novel scar evaluation scale. Plast Reconstr Surg. 2007 Dec;120(7):1892-7.</citation>
    <PMID>18090752</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 18, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 17, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Wound infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Wound separation</keyword>
  <keyword>Skin staples</keyword>
  <keyword>Subcuticular suture</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Wound Infection</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
