<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="70590">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02030041</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Simvavitd</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02030041</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Vitamin D Supplementation on Exercise Adaptations in Patients on Statin Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Vitamin D Supplementation on Exercise Adaptations in Patients on Statin Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Postgraduate Institute of Medical Education and Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Postgraduate Institute of Medical Education and Research</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>India: Indian Council of Medical Research</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The health benefits of exercise have been widely described, the most notable of which is an
      increase in cardiorespiratory fitness.Cardiorespiratory fitness has been identified as the
      strongest independent predictor of both all cause and cardiovascular disease mortality in
      nearly every population in which it has been examined.

      Statins, a class of hydroxymethylglutaryl-coenzyme A reductase inhibitors that lower
      low-density lipoprotein cholesterol, are commonly prescribed to patients with the metabolic
      syndrome. Statins are widely prescribed in combination with exercise to lower risk of
      cardiovascular disease morbidity and mortality. Every 1 millimole per liter reduction in LDL
      is associated with a 10-20% reduction in risk of cardiovascular events and all-cause
      mortality , while every 1 MET (3.5 milliters of oxygen per kilogram of body weight per
      minute) increase in fitness is associated with an 18% reduction in cardiovascular disease
      mortality  and an 11-50% reduction in all-cause mortality. Although the mechanisms are
      poorly understood, some statins have been shown to reduce skeletal muscle mitochondrial
      content and oxidative capacity in humans .

      The muscle is a special potential target for the vitamin D endocrine system. Myopathy is
      well recognized in patients with severe vitamin D deficiency. This myopathy can be rapidly
      and impressively corrected by the appropriate vitamin D therapy. The beneficial effect of
      vitamin D supplementation of severely deficient but otherwise healthy adults on muscle
      weakness, has been reported by improved mitochondrial function.

      Despite the potential public health implications, studies examining the benefits and risks
      of combining statins and exercise in humans are limited. Moreover, Vitamin D may play a role
      in statin mediated changes in exercise adaptations.This study is being done to look for
      effect of simvastatin on exercise mediated cardiorespiratory fitness and the effect of
      vitamin D supplementation in these settings.

       
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Metabolic syndrome is common in adult Asian Indians and was present in 41.1% of the study
      subjects in a study by Ramachandran et al in 2003. Among the total, only 8.6% were without
      any abnormality of the various components of metabolic syndrome. Therapeutic lifestyle
      changes, including exercise, are the first line of treatment for patients with the metabolic
      syndrome. The health benefits of exercise have been widely described, including an increase
      in cardiorespiratory fitness.Cardiorespiratory fitness has been identified as the strongest
      independent predictor of both all cause and cardiovascular disease mortality in nearly every
      population in which it has been examined Statins, a class of hydroxyl methyl
      glutaryl-coenzyme A reductase inhibitors  that lower low-density lipoprotein cholesterol,
      are commonly prescribed to patients with the metabolic syndrome or those with multiple
      cardiovascular disease risk factors when lifestyle changes fail to achieve LDL targets to
      reduce the risk of coronary heart disease morbidity and mortality.

      Statins are widely prescribed in combination with exercise to lower risk of cardiovascular
      disease morbidity and mortality. Every 1millimole per liter reduction in LDL is associated
      with a 10-20% reduction in risk of cardiovascular events and all-cause mortality3,4 , while
      every 1 MET (3.5 milliters of oxygen per kilogram of body weight per minute) increase in
      fitness is associated with an 18% reduction in cardiovascular disease mortality5 and an
      11-50% reduction in all-cause mortality. Some statins (simvastatin, atorvastatin,
      fluvastatin) have been shown to reduce skeletal muscle mitochondrial content and oxidative
      capacity in humans.

      Catherine et al examined the effects of simvastatin on changes in cardiorespiratory fitness
      and skeletal muscle mitochondrial content in response to aerobic exercise training.
      Sedentary overweight or obese adults with at least 2 metabolic syndrome risk factors
      (defined according to National Cholesterol Education Panel Adult Treatment Panel III
      criteria) were randomized to 12 weeks of aerobic exercise training or to exercise in
      combination with simvastatin (40 mg per day). The primary outcomes were cardiorespiratory
      fitness and skeletal muscle (vastus lateralis) mitochondrial content (citrate synthase
      enzyme activity). Thirty-seven participants (exercise plus statins; n=18; exercise only;
      n=19) completed the study. Cardiorespiratory fitness increased by 10% (P&lt;0.05) in response
      to exercise training alone, but was blunted by the addition of simvastatin resulting in only
      a 1.5% increase (P&lt;0.005 for group by time interaction). Similarly, skeletal muscle citrate
      synthase activity increased by 13% in the exercise only group (P &lt;0.05), but decreased by
      4.5% in the simvastatin plus exercise group (P&lt;0.05 for group by time interaction).

      Since vitamin D deficiency is common in the general population, and can be associated with
      reversible myalgias, Duell et al hypothesized that vitamin D deficiency may contribute to
      myopathic symptoms in some patients on statins.

      Sinha et al examined the effects of cholecalciferol therapy on skeletal mitochondrial
      oxidative function in vitamin D deficient subjects using 31P magnetic resonance
      spectroscopy. This longitudinal study assessed mitochondrial oxidative phosphorylation in
      the gastrosoleus compartment using phosphorus-31 magnetic resonance spectroscopy
      measurements of phosphocreatine recovery kinetics in 12 symptomatic, severely vitamin
      D-deficient subjects before and after treatment with cholecalciferol therapy to document
      serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D (25OHD) and bone profiles. Fifteen healthy controls also underwent
      31P-magnetic resonance spectroscopy and serum 25OHD assessment. The phosphocreatine recovery
      half-time (t1/2PCr) was significantly reduced after cholecalciferol therapy in the subjects
      indicating an improvement in maximal oxidative phosphorylation(34.44 ±8.18 sec to 27.84
      ±9.54 sec, P &lt;.001). This was associated with an improvement in mean serum 25OHD levels (8.8
      ±4.2 nmol/L to 113.8 ± 51.5 nmol/L, P &lt; .001). There was no difference in phosphate
      metabolites at rest. All patients reported an improvement in fatigue after cholecalciferol
      therapy.

      In recent years, there has been a growing movement to begin prescribing statins to low-risk
      patients and to all patients over the age of 50 for the primary prevention of cardiovascular
      disease making the case for statins to be used in primary prevention.Despite the potential
      public health implications, studies examining the benefits and risks of combining statins
      and exercise in humans are limited
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>exercise adaptations</measure>
    <time_frame>Twelve weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Thirty obese, vitamin D deficient ,dyslipidemic, type 2 diabetes patients will be recruited. Baseline mitochondrial function will be assessed by VO2max, P31 MR spectroscopy and muscle citrate synthase levels. Fifteen patients each will be given simvastatin and vitamin D or simvastatin and placebo. They will exercise for 12 weeks.Mitochondrial function will be reassessed by VO2max, P31MR spectroscopy  and muscle citrate synthase levels.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>[X]Statin Causing Adverse Effect in Therapeutic Use</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Simvastatin and vitaminD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fifteen participants will be vitamin D deficient with LDL &gt;100mg/dl This arm will receive simvastatin and vitaminD and will exercise for twelve weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Simvastatin and placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fifteen participants will be vitaminD deficient with LDL&gt;100mg.dl This arm will receive Simvastatin and placebo, and will exercise for twelve weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>vitaminD</intervention_name>
    <description>Vitamin D will be given to achieve normal serum levels</description>
    <arm_group_label>Simvastatin and vitaminD</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cholecalciferol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Simvastatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Simvastatin in a dose of 40 mg will be provided to the study participants</description>
    <arm_group_label>Simvastatin and vitaminD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Simvastatin and placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Statin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo will be provided in an arm with simvastatin</description>
    <arm_group_label>Simvastatin and placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Type 2 DM

          -  No significant microvascular complication

          -  Age between 25 and 50 yrs

          -  HbA1c&lt;7.5%

          -  LDL &gt;100mg/dl

          -  Overweight or obese (BMI 25 -39 kg/m2)

          -  Low physical activity(WHO-GPAQ)

          -  Euthyroid , Eugonadal

          -  Vitamin D deficient (&lt;20 ng/ml)

          -  Normal ECG

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Use of statins in past 3 months

          -  Use of Thiazolidinediones, GLP -1agonists, DPP -IV inhibitors,   Steroids, Orlistat
             or other medicines affecting lipid profile or body weight

          -  Smoking

          -  On Vitamin D supplementation

          -  Uncontrolled DM with HbA1c&gt;7.5

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension

          -  CAD and PVD in past 6 months

          -  Musculoskeletal problems resulting in inability to exercise

          -  Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anil Bhansali, DM</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>PGIMER, Chandigarh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Anil Bhansali, DM</last_name>
    <phone>01722756583</phone>
    <email>anilbhansaliendocrine@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ashu Rastogi, DM</last_name>
    <phone>01722756585</phone>
    <email>ashuendo@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>PGIMER</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chandigarh</city>
        <zip>160012</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anil Bhansali, DM</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 23, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Postgraduate Institute of Medical Education and Research</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ashu Rastogi</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Asst Professor, Department of Endocrinology, Postgraduate Institute of Medical Education and Research, Chandigarh</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>simvastatin</keyword>
  <keyword>exercise mediated cardiorespiratory fitness</keyword>
  <keyword>vitamin D supplementation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cholecalciferol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin D</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ergocalciferols</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Simvastatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydroxymethylglutaryl-CoA Reductase Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
