<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="117681">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01925469</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PFC-HSG-1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01925469</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Benzocaine Versus Placebo Spray for Pain Relief at Hysterosalpingogram</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial of Benzocaine Versus Placebo Spray for Pain Relief at Hysterosalpingogram</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: University of Pennsylvania IRB</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to assess the utility of benzocaine spray versus a placebo
      spray in alleviating pain during and after hysterosalpingogram (HSG).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hysterosalpingography (HSG) is a radiographic evaluation during which a radio-opaque medium
      is inserted through the cervical canal in order to define the size and shape of the uterine
      cavity and patency of the fallopian tubes. The utility of HSG is an integral part of the
      evaluation of infertile women for intrauterine pathology. In some cases, HSG can a painful
      procedure. Poor pain control can limit the quality of the study due to inability to complete
      the procedure in cases of extreme discomfort. There is little consensus regarding pain
      control during HSG, although a number of approaches have been studied.  Patients undergoing
      HSG are typically advised to premedicate with ibuprofen, which is consistent with the
      current standard of care. This study will assess pain control using a benzocaine spray (in
      addition to ibuprofen) in patients undergoing routine HSG at the Hospital of the University
      of Pennsylvania. All patients who present to the Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania
      for HSG will be eligible for the study. Benzocaine spray versus a placebo spray will be
      applied to a tenaculum (a surgical hooklike instrument used to grasp and hold the cervix).
      The tenaculum will then be applied to the cervix prior to HSG and pain relief will be
      assessed at 3 time intervals: 0, 5, and 30 minutes. The primary outcome is the mean
      difference in patients pain score and will be measured using the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS)
      which has been shown to be a valid and reliable scale.  The secondary outcome will assess
      patient satisfaction in each group using a validated patient satisfaction survey.  The study
      design will be prospective, randomized, placebo controlled, and double blinded.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pain score</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-procedure (Baseline) and procedure (Time 0)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary outcome is the difference in pain score using a validated visual analog scale before the procedure, which is designated as the pre-procedure (or baseline) pain score to the maximum pain during procedure (designated as time 0)  These two pain scores will be subtracted and the change in pain score will be reported.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>30 minutes post procedure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The patient's satisfaction will be assessed using a validated satisfaction scale 30 minutes post procedure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pain score from pre-procedure to 5 and 30 minutes post procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes and 30 minutes</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The patients pain scores will also be assessed at 5 and 30 minutes post procedure and the change in pain scores from baseline to these time points will be analyzed.  The pain scores will be subtracted to obtain the change in pain score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain Relief</condition>
  <condition>Analgesia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Benzocaine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Benzocaine spray (14%), an FDA approved drug, will be used to assess whether this provides additional pain relief at time of hysterosalpingogram.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Saline spray</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A saline placebo spray will be used in the placebo group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Benzocaine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Benzocaine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline spray</intervention_name>
    <description>A saline spray will be used in the placebo group</description>
    <arm_group_label>Saline spray</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All women who present to Penn Fertility Care over the age of 18 years old

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients under the age of 18

          -  Pregnant patients

          -  Patients with a history of hypersensitivity to benzocaine

          -  Patients with a history of asthma or bronchitis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Suleena K Kalra, MD, MSCE</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 22, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 6, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hysterosalpingogram</keyword>
  <keyword>HSG</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain relief</keyword>
  <keyword>Analgesia</keyword>
  <keyword>Benzocaine</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Benzocaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
