<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="115931">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01824368</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FEC-TH</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-000633-39</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01824368</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Extracorporeal Photopheresis in Liver Transplantation. Phase II Clinical Trial in Safety and Efficacy in Patients With Gradual Decrease of Immunosuppression.</brief_title>
  <acronym>FEC-TH</acronym>
  <official_title>FOTOAFERESIS EXTRACORPÓREA EN EL TRASPLANTE HEPÁTICO. ENSAYO CLINICO EN FASE II DE SEGURIDAD Y EFICACIA EN PACIENTES CON RETIRADA PROGRESIVA DE LA INMUNOSUPRESIÓN</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Red de Terapia Celular</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Spanish National Health System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Faculty of Medicine. University of Murcia.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital Virgen de la Arrixaca.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Health Service of Murcia.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fundación para la Formación e Investigación Sanitarias de la Región de Murcia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Red de Terapia Celular</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Spain: Spanish Agency of Medicines</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety of extracorporeal photopheresis in
      patients with long-standing liver transplantation subjected to a progressive reduction of
      immunosuppression by complications arising from its use.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>adverse event rate and rate of transplant rejection</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Liver Transplantation</condition>
  <condition>Immunosuppression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>People with liver transplantation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>People with liver transplantation over 2 years following treatment with immunosuppression including cyclosporine or tacrolimus.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Extracorporeal Photopheresis Procedure (FEC)</intervention_name>
    <description>The FEC will be held in the Cellex (Therakos), and authorized device in routine use in our unit for performing FEC in the treatment of graft-versus-host and cutaneous T-cell lymphoma. After performing a blood count, will connect the patient to Cellex through a central or peripheral.
1500 mL typically be processed peripheral blood mononuclear fraction obtained by apheresis process. Then be added Uvadex (8-metoxipsolareno, 0.017 mL / mL) to the mononuclear fraction bag and proceed to photoactivation with UVA radiation.
Finally the photoactivated product is again infuse the patient. It will monitor the final blood count to assess hemoglobin and platelets. The entire procedure is performed in a single step and closed mode, with Cellex.</description>
    <arm_group_label>People with liver transplantation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Have been receiving liver transplant two years ago.

          -  Be 18 years or older.

          -  Treatment with immunosuppression including cyclosporine or tacrolimus.

          -  Having a normal liver function in the last year

          -  Not have suffered acute rejection in the last year and have no chronic rejection

          -  Submit any significant side effects from medication immunosuppressive (hypertension,
             creatinine greater than 1.7 mgDl, diabetes, morbid obesity, osteoporosis,
             hyperlipidemia, severe hirsutism, neurotoxicity novo malignancy, etc.)

          -  Etiology of underlying disease: alcoholic cirrhosis with or without hepatocarcinoma,
             metabolic diseases, amyloidotic polyneuropathy family, biliary atresia, fulminant
             hepatitis non-A, non-B, non-C, cirrhosis cryptogenic and generally causes no viral or
             autoimmune.

          -  Patients offering sufficient guarantees of adherence to protocol

          -  Patients who give written informed consent for participate in the study.

          -  It is necessary that the patient meets all inclusion criteria.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Underlying disease of the autoimmune (primary sclerosing cholangitis, autoimmune
             cirrhosis, primary biliary cirrhosis) or epatocarcinoma about cirrhosis of viral or
             autoimmune.

          -  Patients with chronic rejection, or acute rejection in the last year.

          -  Patients with liver retransplantation.

          -  patients with history of hypersensitivity or idiosyncratic reactions to methoxsalen,
             psoralen the compounds or any of the excipients.

          -  patients with melanoma, cutaneous basal cell carcinoma or squamous cell coexistent.

          -  Patients with aphakia.

          -  Patients taking Oxoralen.

          -  Pregnant women or nursing mothers, or adults of childbearing age not using effective
             contraception.

          -  Participation in another clinical trial.

          -  Inability to understand informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Virgen de la Arrixaca</name>
      <address>
        <city>El Palmar</city>
        <state>Murcia</state>
        <zip>30120</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.red-tercel.com</url>
    <description>Red de Terapia Celular (TerCel)</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ffis.es</url>
    <description>Fundación para la Formación e Investigación Sanitarias Región de Murcia</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.murciasalud.es</url>
    <description>Servicio Murciano de Salud</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 26, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 1, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
