<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="21581">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01751412</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-346</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01751412</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Proton Radiation for Lymphoma Involving Mediastinum</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot Study Evaluating the Use of Proton Radiation for Treatment of Lymphoma Involving the Mediastinum</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research study is a Pilot Study. Pilot studies are conducted to see if it is practical
      to do this type of research on a larger scale in the future. The pilot part of this study is
      to assess the possibility of using proton radiation to treat lymphomas. Proton radiation is
      used for many other types of malignancies, but its use for the treatment of lymphoma has
      been limited. The treatment is still being studied as research doctors are trying to find
      out more about its use in the treatment of different types of lymphoma. Proton beam
      radiation therapy is an FDA approved radiation delivery system.

      Patients are being asked to participate in this research study if they have lymphoma in the
      center of their chest, near their heart. Conventional radiation therapy with photons is used
      as standard treatment for many patients with lymphoma. In this research study investigators
      are looking at another type of radiation called proton radiation, which is known to spare
      surrounding tissue and organs from radiation. Proton radiation delivers radiation to the
      area requiring radiation but delivers no dose beyond the region requiring treatment. This
      may reduce side effects that patients would normally experience with conventional radiation
      therapy or other means of delivering proton radiation therapy.

      In this research study, investigators are evaluating the effectiveness of using proton
      radiation delivered to reduce side effects associated with radiation treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      If a person agrees to participate in this research study, they will be asked to undergo some
      screening tests or procedures to confirm eligibility. Many of these tests and procedures are
      likely to be part of regular cancer care and may be done even if it turns out that a patient
      does not take part in the research study. If a patient has had some of these tests or
      procedures recently, they may or may not have to be repeated. These tests and procedures
      include: a medical history, performance status, physical examination, assessment of tumor,
      echocardiogram, electrocardiogram, pulmonary (lung) function tests and blood tests. If these
      tests show that a patient is eligible to participate in the research study, they will begin
      the study treatment. If a patient does not meet the eligibility criteria, they will not be
      able to participate in the research study.

      Proton radiation will be delivered daily for 2 to 5 weeks, depending on the dose prescribed
      by your physician. Treatment is delivered (Monday-Friday) for 5 days (no weekends or
      holidays). Each treatment will require that you lie on a table for 30 to 45 minutes.

      Participants will receive radiation therapy as an outpatient at Massachusetts General
      Hospital. During radiation therapy, they will have the following weekly assessments and
      procedures: physical exam, assess for any side effects, blood tests for cardiac markers.

      Study participants will be asked to return for a follow up visit 6-12 weeks after their last
      dose of radiation therapy. During this visit the following tests and procedures will be
      done: PET/CT scan, physical exam, assess for side effects and blood tests for cardiac
      markers.

      Participants will also be asked to return for a follow-up visit at 6 months, 12 months and
      annually for five years post radiation. Keeping in touch with study participants and
      checking on their condition helps investigators look at the long-term effects of the
      research study. At these visits, the following tests and procedures will be done: physical
      exam, assess for any side effects, ECG, ECHO, pulmonary tests, PET/CT scan, routine blood
      tests and blood tests for cardiac markers (at 6 months and 1 years only).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 0</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiation dose to normal tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess if the treatment plans for proton therapy show an improvement in radiation dose to normal heart and lung tissue compared to conventional 3D photon plans</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease specific outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate disease specific outcomes including progression free survival, local control and overall survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute toxicities</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess acute toxicities including pericarditis, pneumonitis, Lhermitte's, dermatitis, mucositis, esophagitis, leukopenia, xerostomia, and thrombocytopenia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Late toxicities</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate late toxicities including clinical and sub-clinical heart disease, pulmonary fibrosis, esophageal stricture, myelopathy, thyroid dysfunction and secondary cancers</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Proton Radiation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Delivered daily (Monday-Friday) for two to five weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Proton Radiation</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Proton Radiation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed Hodgkin lymphoma or non-Hodgkin lymphoma

          -  Must complete standard chemotherapy appropriate for the histologic subtype of
             lymphoma and be able to start radiation therapy within 3-6 weeks of completing
             chemotherapy

          -  Life expectancy of at least 12 months

          -  Must have achieved complete or partial response per PET-CT within 4 weeks of study
             entry following administration of chemotherapy

          -  Individuals with known history of HIV positivity must be on appropriate HAART therapy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding

          -  Prior therapeutic radiation therapy &gt; 200 cGy has been delivered to target volume

          -  Have not recovered from adverse events due to systemic agents administered more than
             4 weeks earlier

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness

          -  History of a different malignancy unless disease free for at least 2 years (cervical
             cancer in situ, basal or squamous cell carcinoma are acceptable)

          -  Receiving any other investigational agents
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen Winkfield, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karen Winkfield, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>6177244000</phone>
    <email>kwinkfield@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karen Winkfield, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>617-724-4000</phone>
      <email>kwinkfield@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karen Winkfield, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 20, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 14, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Karen Winkfield, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hodgkin</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Mediastinal</keyword>
  <keyword>Adult Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Pediatric Lymphoma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
