<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="40250">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01962623</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NA_00083893</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>K23MH090246</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01962623</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Interpersonal Psychotherapy for Youth With Severe Mood Dysregulation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Interpersonal Psychotherapy for Youth With Severe Mood Dysregulation- Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the feasibility and acceptability of utilizing an
      adapted form (i.e. IPT-SMD) of a psychosocial intervention, Interpersonal Psychotherapy for
      Depressed Adolescents, for youth with severe mood dysregulation (SMD).

      The investigators hypothesize that retention rates will be &gt;80%, satisfaction scores will
      average 6 (high) on a 7 point satisfaction scale, and that youth who receive the IPT-SMD
      intervention will have overall improvement in SMD symptoms.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This research is being done to learn more about how to help teenagers with a sad or angry
      mood, problems sleeping, distractibility, and emotional responses out of proportion to what
      would be expected in a situation. Together these symptoms are called Severe Mood
      Dysregulation (SMD). Currently, there is no standard treatment for teens that have SMD.
      These teens usually receive medication and some type of talk therapy. This research is being
      done to compare two types of talk therapy to see which is most effective in helping teens
      with SMD. Investigators will compare treatment as usual (TAU) with Interpersonal
      Psychotherapy for Youth with Severe Mood Dysregulation (IPT-SMD). Investigators do not know
      if TAU and IPT-SMD work just as well, or if one is better than the other. When this study is
      over, investigators hope there will be a better idea of how to study treatments for teens
      with SMD.

      For those participants who receive IPT-SMD, are prescribed an antipsychotic, and have
      significant improvement in symptoms, investigators will gradually taper the antipsychotic
      dose.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Retention rate</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To describe/assess feasibility of IPT-SMD, investigators will look at ease of recruitment and retention rate goal of at least 80%. Investigators will collect data on the number of subjects recruited, enrolled, and who followed the protocol for 24 weeks.  Investigators will comment on adherence to the overall study, as well as to specific treatment visits.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impressions Scale for SMD(CGI-SMD)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigators will utilize the Clinical Global Impressions Scale for Global Improvement (CGI-I) and Severity of Illness (CGI-S) to measure improvement in SMD symptoms and to assess the effectiveness of IPT-SMD on the severity of SMD symptoms in youth with SMD.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess the feasibility and acceptability of a 24-week psychosocial treatment intervention for youth with SMD, investigators will compare satisfaction questionnaires between treatment arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">44</enrollment>
  <condition>Severe Mood Dysregulation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as Usual (TAU)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants who are not randomly assigned to the IPT-SMD group will continue with treatment at usual, which is considered routine care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IPT-SMD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Weekly Interpersonal Therapy for SMD (IPT-SMD) sessions, which emphasizes building skills in managing relationships, helping with problem solving, strengthening communication skills and other skills.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IPT-SMD</intervention_name>
    <description>IPT-SMD is a modified form of Interpersonal Psychotherapy for Depressed Adolescents (IPT-A), which emphasizes building skills in managing relationships, helping with problem solving, and strengthening communication skills.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as Usual (TAU)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>IPT-SMD</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Interpersonal Psychotherapy for SMD</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and female subjects, ages 13 to 17 years, who meet criteria for severe mood
             dysregulation (SMD) as defined by NIMH criteria.

          -  Subject has an estimated IQ &gt;70 on the Kaufman Brief Intelligence Test (KBIT-2).

          -  Subjects will have continuously resided with a legal guardian who has known the
             adolescent well for at least one year before study entry and is legally able to sign
             the consent form.

          -  Children's Global Assessment Scale (CGAS) ≤ 60

          -  Participants must be on the same dose of any prescribed psychiatric medication for 4
             weeks prior to randomization.

          -  CGI-S (SMD) ≥ 4

          -  Participant and guardian must agree to have therapy sessions audiotaped for training
             purposes.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject poses a significant risk for dangerousness to self or others. Risk will be
             determined by clinical history, clinical diagnostic interview and KSADS-PL interview
             of parent and patient by clinician.

          -  Subject suffers from a concomitant medical or psychiatric comorbidity that makes this
             study protocol inadvisable (either the treatment is contraindicated or the disorder
             is not the primary focus of treatment).

          -  Subject meets DSM-IV criteria for current alcohol or substance dependence or current
             use (defined as the past 4 weeks).

          -  Primary caretaker does not speak English or is not capable of completing study
             measures.

          -  Pregnant females.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leslie Miller, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Leslie Miller, MD</last_name>
    <phone>410-550-9014</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University Bayview Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Leslie Miller, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 11, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 10, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Leslie Miller, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Severe Mood Dysregulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Mood Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Irritability</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
