<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="75744">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02153944</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>140114</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>14-M-0114</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02153944</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cognitive vs. Emotional Psychopharmacological Manipulations of Fear vs. Anxiety</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cognitive vs. Emotional Psycho-Pharmacological Manipulations of Fear vs. Anxiety</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Stress and anxiety can interfere with how well people perform tasks. But performing a task
      can sometimes lessen anxiety by distracting people from the stress. Researchers want to
      examine the interaction between attention and stress. They will use two drugs with different
      effects on stress and concentration.

      Objective:

      - To better understand how thinking and emotion affect anxiety and performance. Also, to
      study the effects of methylphenidate and propranolol on performance.

      Eligibility:

      - Adults age 18   50.

      Design:

        -  First, participants will be screened with a test in which they hear loud, sudden noises
           through headphones. Sticky pad electrodes will be placed on the skin under one eye.
           These electrodes will tell us how sensitive participants are to the noises.

        -  Second, participants will complete questionnaires about their mood, thinking, and
           anxiety. They will give a saliva sample. For this, a cotton swab will be placed in
           their mouth for 2 minutes.

        -  Third, participants will take a single dose of one of the study pills or a placebo.
           They will then look at words, shapes, and letters on a computer monitor. They will
           answer questions about what they remember. They may receive a shock or hear loud noises
           during the tests.

        -  For the shocks, small metal disk or sticky pad electrodes will be taped to a wrist or
           finger. For recording bodily responses, additional electrodes will be placed on the
           arms, body, and under each eye.

        -  Blood pressure and pulse will be measured during the tests. More saliva samples will be
           taken.

        -  At the end of the study, participants will answer questions about their reaction to the
           study testing and about any effects they noticed from the study pill.

        -  After the experiment, participants will be evaluated for effects of the study pill.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective:

      The overall aim of this protocol is to examine the effect of pharmacological manipulations
      of affective and cognitive processes on anxiety and task performance. Ultimately, the goal
      is 1) to provide insight into the relative influence of cognitive and affective states on
      anxiety, 2) generate theoretical models that can be applied to a better understanding of the
      interaction between cognition and emotion, 3) develop a better screening approach to
      candidate anxiolytics, and 4) help formulate novel therapeutic interventions for clinical
      anxiety.

      Excessive or inappropriately sustained anxiety and fear lead to the most common group of
      psychiatric disorders. A number of theoretical models have been proposed to understand the
      mechanisms engaged in these maladaptive behaviors. Most recent emphasis has focused on the
      synergistic contribution of cognitive and emotional processes. Our laboratory has been
      instrumental in delineating aspects of behavioral and neural processes that are associated
      with fear and anxiety, using psychophysiological and neuroimaging measures of fear and
      anxiety. Evidence shows that levels of anxiety modulate cognitive performance, such as
      working memory or perceptual discrimination, and that, conversely, cognitive engagement
      influences severity of experimentally induced anxiety. The exact contribution of emotional
      processes vs. cognitive processes to the experience of anxiety is not clear, similarly to
      the neural mechanisms underlying these interactions.

      In this protocol, we propose to manipulate pharmacologically separately cognitive and
      emotional processes to dissociate their contribution to fear/anxiety, while using
      state-of-the-art measures of anxiety derived from translational work. Indeed, we already
      developed integrative experimental models of fear and anxiety via the manipulation of
      predictable and unpredictable shock, respectively. We already employed successfully these
      models to measure anxiolytic and anxiogenic effects of various compounds such as alprazolam,
      citalopram, hydrocortisone, and oxytocin in healthy participants.

      We propose to start with a simple proof-of-concept study, using two pharmacological
      compounds in a double-blind randomized parallel design, each preferentially acting
      respectively on the cognitive (methylphenidate) or affective (propranolol) domain, and using
      a single cognitive process (working memory). Future work will expand to other compounds and
      cognitive processes, as well as vary the strategy to induce anxiety. Presently, anxiety will
      be induced using the threat of shock, while participants perform the task. We will examine
      whether 1) the reduction of induced-anxiety with propranolol improves cognitive performance,
      and 2) the facilitation of cognitive performance with methylphenidate reduces
      induced-anxiety. If these manipulations are successful, we will assess in a second step
      their neural correlates using functional neuroimaging.

      At this time, only the first behavioral/psychophysiological step of this proposal will be
      addressed.

      Study population:

      Medically and psychiatrically healthy adult males and females, aged 18 to 50 years.

      Design:

      The study is a double-blind cross-over design. Three groups of healthy participants will
      come for one experimental session. During this session, they will be asked to perform a
      working memory task under the threat of shock, i.e., while anticipating unpleasant electric
      shocks. Each group will receive one drug challenge, either placebo, propranolol (40 g) or
      methylphenidate (20 mg).

      Outcome measures:

      The primary outcome measures are the startle reflex and performance on the working memory
      task. Secondary measures include skin conductance, heart rate, and subjective measures of
      anxiety, as well as salivary measures of alpha-amylase, and cortisol.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double-Blind</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Will the reduction of induced-anxiety with propranolol improve cognitive performance.</measure>
    <time_frame>1year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Will the facilitation of cognitive performance with methylphenidate reduce induced-anxiety.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">69</enrollment>
  <condition>Anxiety Disorder</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Propanolol</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methylphenidate</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Ages 18-50

          -  Males and females

          -  Subjects give their own consent

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Previous exposure to Ritalin (MPH), or Inderal (PRO).

          -  Any significant medical or neurological problems (e.g. cardiovascular illness,
             respiratory illness, neurologic illness, seizure, etc.)

          -  Raynaud syndrome

          -  IQ &lt;  80

          -  Sinus bradycardia (P&lt; 60), or tachycardia (P&gt; 90)

          -  Significant ECG abnormality (i.e., greater than first-degree block etc.)

          -  Active broncho-spastic lung disease

          -  A history of visits to the emergency room because of asthma, or with recent history
             of asthma symptoms in the past year, which required medication treatment

          -  High or low blood pressure (SBP&gt; 140 or SBP&lt; 90; SDP&lt; 50 or SDP&gt; 90)

          -  A first-degree family history of mania, schizophrenia, or other psychoses based on
             verbal reports

          -  Significant past psychopathology (e.g., hospitalization for psychiatric disorders,
             recurrent depression, suicide attempt, psychoses)

          -  Current psychiatric disorders according to DSM-IV

          -  Past alcohol/drug dependence and alcohol/drug abuse in past one year or lifetime
             alcohol or drug dependence

          -  Current use of psychotropic medication

          -  Impaired hearing

          -  Pregnancy or positive pregnancy test

          -  Neurological syndrome of the wrist (e.g., carpal tunnel syndrome)

          -  Breastfeeding

          -  Significant lab abnormalities (i.e., CBC with differential, acute care and mineral
             panel, hepatic panel, thyroid panel)

          -  Positive urine toxicology screen

          -  You have been in another study with an experimental medication within the previous
             month

          -  Small startle reactivity (a change in EMG activity that is less than 3 times the
             baseline EMG activity)

          -  Glaucoma

          -  Current use of anti-acid medications
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Monique Ernst, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Monique Ernst, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-9355</phone>
    <email>ernstm@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2014-M-0114.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Airaksinen E, Larsson M, Forsell Y. Neuropsychological functions in anxiety disorders in population-based samples: evidence of episodic memory dysfunction. J Psychiatr Res. 2005 Mar;39(2):207-14. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>15589570</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ashare RL, Hawk LW Jr, Shiels K, Rhodes JD, Pelham WE Jr, Waxmonsky JG. Methylphenidate enhances prepulse inhibition during processing of task-relevant stimuli in attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder. Psychophysiology. 2010 Sep;47(5):838-45. doi: 10.1111/j.1469-8986.2010.01001.x. Epub 2010 Mar 10. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>20233343</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barrickman LL, Perry PJ, Allen AJ, Kuperman S, Arndt SV, Herrmann KJ, Schumacher E. Bupropion versus methylphenidate in the treatment of attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 1995 May;34(5):649-57. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>7775360</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 31, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 31, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Startle</keyword>
  <keyword>Induced-Threat</keyword>
  <keyword>Memory</keyword>
  <keyword>Stimulant</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive Interference</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Propranolol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylphenidate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
