<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="83862">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01759849</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CSL311</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01759849</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CSL311 and Cell Viability in Asthma</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of in Vitro CSL311 on the Function of Blood, Bone Marrow and Sputum Cells From Asthmatic Donors.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hamilton Health Sciences Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>CSL Limited</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hamilton Health Sciences Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To examine the effect of blocking signaling through the β-chain on viability, activation and
      differentiation of eosinophils and their progenitors collected from sputum, blood and bone
      marrow samples collected pre and post-allergen challenge from mild atopic asthmatic
      subjects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The experiments will use sputum samples induced from subjects with mild asthma, undergoing
      allergen inhalation challenges. In general, each sample will be composed of &gt;10% neutrophils
      and &gt;10% macrophages. Samples collected pre-allergen will have a low frequency of
      eosinophils and lymphocytes (&lt;1%), however the percentage of eosinophils will increase to
      approximately 12% following allergen challenges. The sputum samples will be processed in
      DPBS (without dithiothreitol), and the cell suspension will be adjusted to 1 million
      cells/ml in DMEM with penicillin and streptomycin. A cytospin will be made for differential
      cell counts. The mixed cell population at 5 million cells/ml will be incubated for 48 hours
      at 37 degrees Celcius ± β-chain MAb at a concentration of 100 mcg/ml. After 48 hours the
      cell culture medium will be removed for assay of cytokines and chemokines by ELISA. Cells
      will be resuspended in PBS and Binding Buffer (BD Pharmingen, Cat no. 556454),stained for
      assessments by flow cytometry, and analyzed in duplicate.

      Experiments will use blood (80 ml) and bone marrow aspirates (5ml) from atopic asthmatics
      taken pre and 24hr post allergen challenge. Methylcult micro-culture colonogenic assays will
      be performed to enumerate outgrowth of Eo/Baso-CFU and GM-CFU from CD34+ cells populations
      collected from the blood and bone marrow samples. Methylcult assays will be performed with
      CD34+ enriched cell populations in the presence of IL-5,IL-3 and GM-CSF +/- CSL311.
      Following 14 days culture, colonies will be enumerated.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sputum Collection</measure>
    <time_frame>7 hrs post allergen</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Three baseline sample collections will ensure sufficient numbers of cells are collected for proposed outcomes. Post allergen cells will be examined at time points when these populations are known to be at their highest frequency.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CSL311</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CSL 311 will determine the effects of a β-chain monoclonal antibody (MAb) on the function of cells naturally activated by in vivo allergen exposure, from donors with allergen-induced asthma</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CSL 311</intervention_name>
    <description>CSL311 is a humanized monoclonal antibody targeting the common beta chain receptor to IL-3, IL-5 and GM-CSF, which is present on select leukocytes including eosinophils.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CSL311</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and female volunteers 18 through 65 years of age.

          -  General good health

          -  Mild to moderate, stable, allergic asthma

          -  History of episodic wheeze and shortness of breath; FEV1 at baseline at least 70% of
             the predicted value

          -  Able to understand and give written informed consent and has signed a written
             informed consent form approved by the investigator's REB

          -  Positive methacholine challenge

          -  Positive skin-prick test to common aeroallergens (including cat, dust mite, grass,
             pollen)

          -  Positive allergen-induced airway bronchoconstriction (a fall in FEV1 of at least 20%
             from baseline)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A worsening of asthma or a respiratory tract infection within 6 weeks preceding study
             entry

          -  Use of corticosteroids, immunosuppressives, anticoagulants (warfarin or heparin)
             within 28 days prior to randomization into the study

          -  Use of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) within 48 hours of dosing or
             aspirin with 7 days of dosing

          -  Have chronic use of any other medication for treatment of allergic lung disease other
             than short- and intermediate-acting ß2-agonists or ipratropium bromide

          -  Use of caffeine-containing products or medications for 12 hours or alcohol or over
             the counter drugs including aspirin, cold and allergy medications for 48 hours or
             inhaled bronchodilators for 8 hours prior to methacholine and allergen challenges

          -  Use of tobacco products of any kind currently or within the previous 12 months, or
             smoking history &gt; 10 pack years.

          -  Lung disease other than mild to moderate allergic asthma

          -  Unwillingness or inability to comply with the study protocol for any other reason.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gail M Gauvreau, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hamilton Health Sciences Corporation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gail Gauvreau, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>605-525-9140</phone>
    <phone_ext>22791</phone_ext>
    <email>gauvreau@mcmaster.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>McMaster Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L8N 3Z5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gail M Gauvreau, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>905-525-9140</phone>
      <phone_ext>22791</phone_ext>
      <email>gauvreau@mcmaster.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gail M Gauvreau, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 9, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 17, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Asthma</keyword>
  <keyword>β-chain signaling</keyword>
  <keyword>allergen inhalation challenges</keyword>
  <keyword>sputum</keyword>
  <keyword>bone marrow aspirate</keyword>
  <keyword>blood collection</keyword>
  <keyword>-methacholine challenge</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
