<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="141092">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01709383</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DDCF 2012062</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01709383</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Using Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation (tDCS) to Improve Post-Stroke Aphasia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Can Enhancing Left Lateralization Using Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation Improve Recovery From Post-Stroke Aphasia?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Georgetown University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medstar Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Georgetown University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study tests whether weak electrical stimulation of the brain is effective in improving
      language or reading difficulties occurring after a brain injury or stroke.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study tests whether aphasia or alexia, language and reading disorders occurring after
      traumatic brain injury or stroke, can be improved using transcranial direct current
      stimulation (tDCS). tDCS is a non-invasive technique that applies a small amount of direct
      electrical current to the brain in order to temporarily alter brain processing.  Adults with
      aphasia/alexia resulting from stroke or traumatic brain injury will undergo baseline
      behavioral testing of various language and cognitive functions.  Subjects who are willing to
      undergo MRI evaluation will also be scanned.  They will then receive five days of either
      real or sham tDCS with standardized speech-language therapy, under a double-blind randomized
      placebo-controlled design.  Behavioral assessments, and MRIs for those participating in the
      MRI portion of the study, will be performed again at multiple time points after completing
      tDCS to assess for changes in these measures.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Western Aphasia Battery - Revised: Naming and Word Finding score</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to one day after treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This is a composite measure of verbal expression skills including tests of naming, verbal fluency, and sentence completion.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Western Aphasia Battery - Revised: Spontaneous Speech, Repetition, Auditory Verbal Comprehension and overall Aphasia Quotient</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately; 2 weeks post-treatment; 12 weeks post-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The above subtests will reflect the following: a composite measure of information content in conversational speech and picture description; a measure of word and sentence repetition; a composite measure of yes/no questions, auditory word recognition, and following sequential commands; and an overall aphasia severity score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Philadelphia Naming Test (PNT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately; 2 weeks post-treatment; 12 weeks post-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A test of picture naming using more common items than other picture naming tests, which reduces relationships between performance and premorbid education and socioeconomic status.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Boston Diagnostic Aphasia Examination (BDAE): Verbal agility subtest</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately; 2 weeks post-treatment; 12 weeks post-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A measure of annunciation to assess the impact of tDCS on slurring of speech and verbal apraxia.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective assessments including: Communicative Effectiveness Index, Stroke and Aphasia Quality of Life Scale, and Stroke Aphasic Depression Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately; 2 weeks post-treatment; 12 weeks post-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A set of questionnaires to be administered to subjects and immediate family members in order to assess the impact of language impairments on functional communication skills and overall quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive-Linguistic Quick Test (CLQT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately; 2 weeks post-treatment; 12 weeks post-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The following subtests from the CLQT will be administered: Symbol Cancellation, Story Retelling, Symbol Trails, Design Memory, Mazes,and Design Generation.  These scores will be used to calculate composite scores for the cognitive domains of attention, executive function, and visuospatial skills.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reading assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately; 2 weeks post-treatment; 12 weeks post-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A set of reading tasks designed to assess oral reading of real words and non-words at the single word level.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Motricity Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately; 2 weeks post-treatment; 12 weeks post-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>An assessment of upper extremity motor impairment, including: pinch grip, elbow flexion, and shoulder abduction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">112</enrollment>
  <condition>Aphasia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>The tDCS treatments will be applied bilaterally, with the anodal electrode placed on the left temple and the cathodal electrode placed on the right temple. The tDCS will be applied at the beginning of 60-minute speech-language treatment sessions for five days across a one-week period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham Stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>The sham tDCS will be applied at the beginning of 60-minute speech-language treatment sessions for five days across a one-week period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Stimulation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18 or older

          -  Aphasia due to left hemisphere stroke diagnosed by a physician or speech-language
             pathologist

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Skull defect at or near the site of tDCS delivery

          -  History of a significant stroke or traumatic brain injury other than the event that
             caused the aphasia

          -  History of other brain conditions that could impact interpretation of results (such
             as MS, brain tumor, encephalitis, premorbid dementia)

          -  Presence of implanted electrical or metallic devices in the head or body (except
             titanium; e.g. cochlear implants, implanted shunts with metal parts, deep brain
             stimulators, pacemakers, defibrillators)

          -  Presence of ferrous metal in the head (e.g. shrapnel)

          -  History of psychiatric disease requiring hospitalization, electroconvulsive therapy,
             or ongoing medication use (other than common SSRI or SNRI antidepressants)

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Severe comprehension deficits

        Additional Exclusion Criteria for the optional MRI portion of the study:

          -  Presence of metal in the body (except titanium)

          -  Claustrophobia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter Turkeltaub, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Georgetown University and MedStar National Rehabilitation Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alexa Desko</last_name>
    <phone>202-687-5205</phone>
    <email>ad655@georgetown.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MedStar National Rehabilitation Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Turkeltaub, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elizabeth Lacey, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Georgetown University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20057</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Turkeltaub, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elizabeth Lacey, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zaghi S, Acar M, Hultgren B, Boggio PS, Fregni F. Noninvasive brain stimulation with low-intensity electrical currents: putative mechanisms of action for direct and alternating current stimulation. Neuroscientist. 2010 Jun;16(3):285-307. doi: 10.1177/1073858409336227. Epub 2009 Dec 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20040569</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Schlaug G, Marchina S, Wan CY. The use of non-invasive brain stimulation techniques to facilitate recovery from post-stroke aphasia. Neuropsychol Rev. 2011 Sep;21(3):288-301. doi: 10.1007/s11065-011-9181-y. Epub 2011 Aug 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21842404</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fridriksson J, Richardson JD, Baker JM, Rorden C. Transcranial direct current stimulation improves naming reaction time in fluent aphasia: a double-blind, sham-controlled study. Stroke. 2011 Mar;42(3):819-21. doi: 10.1161/STROKEAHA.110.600288. Epub 2011 Jan 13.</citation>
    <PMID>21233468</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 9, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 28, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Aphasia</keyword>
  <keyword>Stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Neuroplasticity</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Aphasia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
