<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="74075">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02156843</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PYR-311</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2014-001641-24</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CSG-17</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>PYR-311 (PIONEER)</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02156843</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pyridorin in Diabetic Nephropathy</brief_title>
  <acronym>PIONEER</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase 3 Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Multi-Center Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of Pyridorin (Pyridoxamine Dihydrochloride) in Subjects With Nephropathy Due to Type 2 Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NephroGenex, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Collaborative Study Group (CSG)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medpace, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NephroGenex, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety and efficacy of oral Pyridorin 300 mg
      BID in reducing the rate of progression of nephropathy due to type 2 diabetes mellitus.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, multi-center Phase 3 study to
      evaluate the safety and efficacy of Pyridorin 300 mg BID (twice daily, every 12 hours) in
      subjects with nephropathy due to type 2 diabetes mellitus.  In this study, nephropathy is
      defined as a Serum Creatinine (SCr) &gt;= 1.3 mg/dL (115 umol/L) for female and &gt;=1.5 mg/dL
      (133 umol/L) for male subjects and a 24-hour urine collection protein/creatinine ration
      (PCR) &gt;=1200 mg/g (136 mg/mmol).  Subjects must have a baseline SCr &lt; 3.0 mg/dL (265 umol/L)
      and must be on previously established standard of care at screening.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to composite endpoint of &gt;=50% SCr increase from baseline or ESRD</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 42 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Time to the composite endpoint consisting of the earliest event amongst a SCr increase of 50% from baseline that occurs during follow-up; or End Stage Renal Disease.  ESRD is defined as the initiation of permanent dialysis, receiving a kidney transplant, or a SCr value &gt;= 6.0 mg/dL (528 umol/L) with a second SCr confirmation value &gt;=6.0 mg/dL (528 umol/L) obtained 4-6 weeks later.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to the composite endpoint &gt;=100% SCr increase or ESRD</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 42 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A SCr increase of &gt;=100% that occurs during follow-up; or ESRD</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in serum cystatin-C</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to Week 52 and from baseline to Week 104</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in urine protein/creatinine ratio (PCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to Week 52 and from baseline to Week 104</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in urinary transforming growth factor-beta (TGF-Beta) excretion</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to Week 52 and from baseline to Week 104</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in SCr</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to Week 52 and from baseline to Week 104</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">600</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetic Nephropathy</condition>
  <condition>Diabetic Kidney Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pyridorin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pyridorin (pyridoxamine dihydrochloride) 300 mg oral BID (twice daily, every 12 hours) Capsule</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo Oral Capsule taken BID (twice daily, every 12 hours)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pyridorin</intervention_name>
    <description>300 mg BID (twice daily, every 12 hours), oral capsule taken until end stage renal disease or death occurs, or the study is terminated by the sponsor.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pyridorin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pyridoxamine dihydrochloride</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo excipients without the active drug, oral capsule taken BID (twice daily, every 12 hours), until end stage renal disease or death occurs, or the study is terminated by the sponsor.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patients meeting all of the following criteria will be eligible to participate in the
        study:

          1. Patients who have given voluntary written informed consent to participate in this
             study prior to conducting Screening (Visit 1) procedures

          2. Patients 18 years of age or older with a diagnosis of type 2 diabetes

          3. Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) who agree to use appropriate birth control
             (double-barrier methods, hormonal contraceptives, or intrauterine device) for the
             duration of the study (women of childbearing potential is defined as all women who
             are not surgically sterile or are not at least 1 year post menopausal)  All women of
             childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test at Visit 1

          4. All men (unless surgically sterile, as defined below) who have sexual intercourse
             with a WOCBP must agree and commit to use a highly effective method of contraception
             for the duration of the study (defined as the time of the signing of the informed
             consent form through the conclusion of patient participation).  Highly effective
             methods of contraception include i. Male subjects agreeing that they and their female
             spouse/partners will use adequate contraception (2 forms of birth control, one of
             which must be barrier method) or be of non-childbearing potential

             ii. To be considered surgically sterilized, a male partner must have had a vasectomy
             at least 24 weeks before Visit 1

          5. At Visit 1, patients must have a history of overt diabetic nephropathy, as defined by
             the following

               -  A SCr measurement ≥1.3 mg/dL (115 umol/L) for females or ≥1.5 mg/dL (133 umol/L)
                  for males

               -  A 24-hour urine collection PCR ≥1200 mg/g (136 mg/mmol)

          6. Patients must have a SCr measurement &lt;3.0 mg/dL (265 umol/L)

          7. Patients must have an eGFR of  ≥20 mL/min/1.73m2, using the 4-variable Modification
             of Diet in Renal Disease equation in which eGFR = 175 x (SCr(mg/dL))-1.154 x
             (Age(years))-0.203 x (0.742 if female) x (1.212 if African American)

          8. Patient must have a second screening SCr measurement at Visit 1.1 or 1.1S taken 1
             week (± 2 days) after screening (Visit 1 or 1.1).  The value of the second screening
             SCr measurement must be &lt;3.0 mg/dL (265 umol/L) for both genders and within 25% of
             the first screening measurement

          9. Patients must be taking a single ACE-I or ARB at a constant dose for at least 26
             weeks prior to Visit 1, where the dose of the ACE-I or the ARB is considered
             appropriate for that patient and it is anticipated that the same dose can and will be
             maintained throughout the course of the study

         10. Patients taking any blood pressure medications in addition to an ACE-I or ARB,
             including diuretics, must be: (1) on a stable dose for 26 weeks prior to Visit 1 with
             a seated blood pressure of &lt;=150/90 mmHg; or (2) on a stable dose for 13 weeks prior
             to Visit 1 with a seated blood pressure of &lt;=140/90 mmHg

         11. Patients not taking any blood pressure medications other than an ACE-I or ARB must
             have a seated blood pressure &lt;=150/90 mmHg at Visit 1 and a seated blood pressure
             considered appropriate for the patient and one that can be sustained throughout the
             study

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patients are excluded from participation in the study if any of the following criteria
        apply

          1. Patients with type 1 diabetes

          2. Patients with a diagnosis of chronic kidney disease other than diabetic renal disease
             with or without hypertensive renal disease

          3. Patients receiving a renin inhibitor or an aldosterone antagonist or a combination of
             an ACE-I and an ARB within 26 weeks of Visit 1

          4. Patients with a history of solid organ transplantation

          5. Patients with a history of myocardial infarction, coronary re-vascularization
             procedures (including percutaneous transluminal coronary angioplasty), stroke, or
             transient ischemic attack within 30 days prior to Visit 1

          6. Patients with a diagnosis of New York Heart Association Class III or IV congestive
             heart failure at any time

          7. Patients with a history of being treated for neoplastic disease (except basal or
             squamous cell carcinoma of the skin) within 5 years prior to Visit 1

          8. Patients with any history of dialysis within 2 years prior to Visit 1

          9. Patients in whom dialysis or renal transplantation is anticipated by their physician
             within 1 year after Visit 1

         10. Patients who used SCr-altering drugs within 30 days prior to Visit 1

         11. Patients who require systemic immunosuppression therapy for &gt;2 weeks (except for
             inhalant steroids)

         12. Patients with clinically significant liver disease or transaminase (alanine
             aminotransferase and aspartate aminotransferase) levels &gt;2.5 × the upper limit of
             normal (ULN) measured at Visit 1.1 or Visit 1.1S

         13. Patients with bilirubin levels &gt;1.5 × ULN measured at Visit 1.1 or Visit 1.1S

         14. Patients with a history of allergic or other adverse response to vitamin B
             preparations

         15. Patients who require &gt;50 mg of vitamin B6 daily

         16. Patients who have an active history of dysphagia or swallowing disorders

         17. Patients with a history of hypersensitivity to Pyridorin or any of the excipients
             (non-active ingredients) in the Pyridorin formulation

         18. Patients who have taken pyridoxamine or any other investigational drug within 30 days
             prior to Visit 1, or have participated in a previous Pyridorin study or another
             interventional clinical study within 30 days prior to Visit 1

         19. Patients with an active history of drug or alcohol abuse

         20. Patients unlikely to comply with the study protocol (eg, an inability and
             unwillingness to participate in adequate training, an uncooperative attitude,
             inability to return for follow-up visits, or unlikelihood of completing the study)

         21. Women who are lactating, pregnant, or intend to become pregnant during the course of
             the study

         22. Patients who are investigational site staff members and their families or patients
             who are employees of the Sponsor or the Sponsor's designees and are directly involved
             in the conduct of the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Edmund J. Lewis, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>The Collaborative Study Group (CSG)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Julia B. Lewis, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>The Collaborative Study Group (CSG)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mohammed Sika, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>615-936-1179</phone>
    <email>CSG@vanderbilt.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Laura Craft, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>513-579-9911</phone>
    <phone_ext>2180</phone_ext>
    <email>L.Craft@medpace.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Collaborative Study Group (CSG)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60607</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Collaborative Study Group (CSG)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 28, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetic Kidney Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Nephropathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetic Nephropathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Kidney Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Type 2 Diabetes</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Nephropathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Pyridoxamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
