<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="78756">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01678846</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LSHTM_6183</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01678846</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Good Schools Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>GSS</acronym>
  <official_title>The Good Schools Study: Cluster Randomised Controlled Trial of a Program to Prevent Violence Against Children in Schools</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Raising Voices</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institute of Education, UK</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Makerere University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine</authority>
    <authority>Uganda: National Council for Science and Technology</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether use of the Good Schools Toolkit is
      effective in reducing violence against children in primary schools.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Violence against children has profound effects on both children's health and their ability
      to do well at school.  Fear, anxiety and injuries caused by violence may play a large role
      in both children's absenteeism and low educational achievement, and there is increasing
      interest from large bilateral donors in investigating this link in low income countries.
      The Good School Toolkit has been developed and refined for 6 years in Uganda by Raising
      Voices.  The toolkit takes a systemic approach, involving an entire school in a process of
      change to reduce violence and improve teaching techniques.  The Toolkit draws on the
      Transtheoretical Model and incorporates standard behaviour change techniques such as setting
      a goal and making an action plan, which are effective in modifying behaviour.  This study
      aims to determine whether use of the Good School Toolkit reduces children's experience of
      violence by school staff.  The investigators will also examine the effects of the Toolkit on
      children's educational outcomes, mental health and well-being.

      The investigators will conduct a cluster randomised controlled trial in 40 primary schools
      in Luwero District, Uganda.  More than 3500 children in Primary 5, 6 and 7 will be surveyed
      (aged about 11-16 years).  Half of the schools will receive the Toolkit, and other half will
      be put on a waiting list to receive the Toolkit at the end of the study.  The results from
      this evaluation will be used to brief policy-makers within the Ministry of Education and
      Sports involved in developing country-wide policy and practice around violence against
      children in schools.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>physical violence from school staff</measure>
    <time_frame>2-year follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>past week experience of any physical violence from school staff</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>child mental health</measure>
    <time_frame>2-year follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>score on the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>educational achievement</measure>
    <time_frame>2-year follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>scores on reading comprehension, spelling, mathematics tests</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>sexual violence from school staff</measure>
    <time_frame>2-year follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3500</enrollment>
  <condition>Physical Violence</condition>
  <condition>Educational Achievement</condition>
  <condition>Mental Health</condition>
  <condition>Sexual Violence</condition>
  <condition>Violence Against Children</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Good School Toolkit</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Schools in the intervention arm will receive the Good Schools Toolkit materials and implementation support.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Schools in this arm will receive the Good Schools Toolkit materials and some implementation support after the end of the trial.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Good School Toolkit</intervention_name>
    <description>The Toolkit uses a six step process to create a school wide intervention that engages teachers, students, administration, and parents to reflect on how they can promote quality of education in their school.  The Toolkit articulates complex ideas (what is a good learning environment, a good teacher, how to create positive discipline without using violence) through booklets, posters and school initiated learning processes.  Specific modules on alternative discipline techniques and how staff can use positive discipline are included in the Toolkit.  The intervention includes sessions on knowledge, attitudes and opportunities to practice new behavioural skills.  Work is led by teachers and students, and supported by visits from Raising Voices staff.  The Toolkit can be reviewed at (http://www.raisingvoices.org/children/good_school_toolkit.php).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Good School Toolkit</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        1. Inclusion Criteria:

               -  Schools

                    -  in Luwero District, Uganda

                    -  more than 40 students registered in Primary 5

               -  Participants

                    -  registered as a Primary 5, 6 or 7 pupil

                    -  any school staff member

          2. Exclusion Criteria:

               -  Schools

                  -- existing program related to prevention of violence against children or school
                  governance

               -  Participants -- not able to understand consent and study procedures
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen M Devries, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>LSHTM</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>District-wide</name>
      <address>
        <city>Multiple</city>
        <state>Luwero District</state>
        <country>Uganda</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Uganda</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 10, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 24, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>corporal punishment</keyword>
  <keyword>violence</keyword>
  <keyword>education</keyword>
  <keyword>depression</keyword>
  <keyword>anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>conduct disorder</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
