<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="43426">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01748825</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130032</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-C-0032</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01748825</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MK-1775 for Advanced Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of Single-agent MK-1775, a Wee1 Inhibitor, in Patients With Advanced Refractory Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - MK-1775 is a cancer treatment drug that acts against tumor cells. It appears to block a
      protein that affects other proteins inside the cell that can help the tumors grow. However,
      it has not been fully tested in humans. Researchers want to see if it is safe and effective
      against advanced solid tumors that have not responded to treatment.

      Objectives:

      - To see if MK-1775 is a safe and effective treatment for advanced solid tumors.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals at least 18 years of age who have advanced solid tumors that have not
      responded to treatment.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. Blood, urine,
           and tumor samples will be collected. Imaging studies will also be performed.

        -  Participants will take MK-1775 by mouth for 21-day cycles of treatment. They will have
           two doses on day 1, two doses on day 2, and one on day 3, with no treatment for the
           remaining days. Participants will keep a study diary to record their doses and any side
           effects.

        -  Some participants will have 2 weeks of MK-1775 for each cycle. They will repeat the
           dose schedule for days 1 through 3 on days 8 through 10.

        -  Treatment will be monitored with frequent blood tests and imaging studies. Additional
           blood and tumor samples may be collected.

        -  Treatment with MK-1775 will continue as long as the tumor does not grow and side
           effects are not severe.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

        -  Wee1 is a tyrosine kinase involved in the phosphorylation and inactivation of
           cyclindependent kinase 1 (CDK1/CDC2)-bound cyclin B, resulting in G2 cell cycle arrest
           in response to DNA damage to allow time for DNA repair. Recent preclinical data
           additionally implicates Wee1 in maintenance of genomic integrity during S phase.

        -  MK-1775 is a selective inhibitor of Wee1 kinase. Recent preclinical model data
           additionally show single agent anti-tumor activity in multiple cancer cell lines and
           tumor xenografts.

        -  Preliminary data show MK-1775 is tolerable at lower doses in combination with
           chemotherapeutic agents. We propose to demonstrate single-agent activity for MK-1775.

      PRIMARY OBJECTIVE:

        -  To establish the safety and tolerability of single-agent MK-1775 in patients with
           refractory solid tumors

        -  To determine the pharmacokinetics of MK-1775 in patients with refractory solid tumors

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

        -  To determine the effect of MK-1775 on markers of DNA damage and apoptosis in tumor
           tissue and circulating tumor cells

        -  To evaluate the antitumor activity of MK-1775 in patients with refractory solid tumors

      ELIGIBILITY:

        -  Patients must have histologically confirmed solid tumors for which all standard therapy
           known to prolong survival have failed, or for which standard therapies do not exist.

        -  No major surgery, radiation, or chemotherapy within 4 weeks prior to entering the study

        -  Adequate organ function

      Study Design:

        -  This study will follow a traditional 3+3 design.

        -  For dose level 1, MK-1775 will be administered orally for 5 doses each cycle. Starting
           at dose level 2 and onwards, MK-1775 will be administered orally for 5 doses for the
           first 2 weeks of each cycle . Each cycle is 21 days (   1 day for scheduling).

        -  Once MTD is established, 6 additional patients will be enrolled at the MTD to further
           evaluate that dose for PK and PD endpoints.

        -  A further expansion cohort of 6 additional patients with documented tumors harboring
           BRCA-1 or -2 mutations will lso be enrolled at the MTD to further explore the safety of
           the agent and obtain preliminary evidence of activity in this patient population.

        -  During the escalation phase, tumor biopsies will be optional and will be evaluated for
           pharmacodynamic (PD) studies for evidence of DNA damage, repair, and apoptosis (H2AX,
           pNbs1, ERCC1, and caspase 3). During the expansion phase, once MTD is reached,
           mandatory paired tumor biopsies will be pursued in the 6 additional patients enrolled
           at the MTD to further evaluate PD endpoints.

      &lt; TAB&gt;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the pharmacokinetics of MK-1775 in patients with refractory solid tumors</measure>
    <time_frame>January, 2014</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To establish the safety and tolerability of single-agent MK-1775 in patients with refractory solid tumors.</measure>
    <time_frame>January, 2014</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the effect of MK-1775 on MAKERS DNA damage and apoptosis</measure>
    <time_frame>January, 2014</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the antitumor activity of MK-1775 in patients with refractory solid tumors</measure>
    <time_frame>January, 2014</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MK-1775</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  ELIGIBILITY CRITERIA:

          -  Patients must have histologically confirmed solid tumors for which all standard
             therapy known to prolong survival have failed or for which standard therapies do not
             exist.

          -  Patients must have measurable disease or evaluable disease for the esclation phase;
             for the 6 additional patients enrolled at MTD for further evaluation of PK and PD
             endpoints, patients must have disease amenable to biopsy and be willing to undergo
             biopsy.  For the 6-patient BRCA-mutation expansion cohort, patients must have
             measurable disease; however, tumor biopsies are optional.

          -  Patients must have completed any chemotherapy, radiation therapy, surgery, or
             biologic therapy greater than or equal to 4 weeks prior to entering the study.
             Patients must be greater than or equal to 2 weeks since any prior administration of a
             study drug in an exploratory IND/Phase 0 study. Patients must have recovered to
             eligibility levels from prior toxicity or adverse events.

          -  Age greater than or equal to18 years of age.

          -  ECOG performance status less than or equal to 2 (Karnofsky &gt; 60%)

          -  Life expectancy of greater than 3 months.

          -  Patients must have normal organ and marrow function as defined below:

          -  leukocytes         greater than or equal to 3,000/mcL

          -  absolute             neutrophil count greater than or equal to 1,500/mcL

          -  platelets             greater than or equal to 100,000/mcL

          -  total bilirubin      less than or equal to 1.5 times institutional upper limit of
             normal

          -  AST(SGOT)/ALT(SGPT)  less than or equal to 3 times institutional upper limit of
             normal

          -  creatinine           less than or equal to 1.5 times institutional upper limit of
             normal

        OR

          -  creatinine clearance greater than or equal to 60 mL/min/1.73 m(2) for patients with
             creatinine levels above institutional normal.

          -  The effects of MK-1775 on the developing human fetus are unknown. For this reason and
             because molecular inhibitors of Wee1 kinase are known to be teratogenic, women of
             child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception (hormonal or
             barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry and for the
             duration of study participation. Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is
             pregnant while she or her partner is participating in this study, she should inform
             her treating physician immediately. Men treated or enrolled on this protocol must
             also agree to use adequate contraception prior to the study, for the duration of
             study participation, and 2 months after completion of MK-1775 administration.

          -  Because there is an unknown but potential risk for adverse events in nursing infants
             secondary to treatment of the mother with the study drugs, breastfeeding should be
             discontinued prior to the first of study drug and women should refrain from nursing
             throughout the treatment period and for 14 days following the last dose of study
             drug.

          -  Patients must be able to swallow whole tablets or capsules. Nasogastric or G-tube
             administration is not allowed. Any gastrointestinal disease which would impair
             ability to swallow, retain, or absorb drug is not allowed.

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent
             document.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Patients who are receiving any other investigational agents.

          -  Patients with known active brain metastases or carcinomatous meningitis are excluded
             from this clinical trial. Patients whose brain metastatic disease status has remained
             stable for greater than or equal to 4 weeks following treatment of brain metastases
             are eligible to participate at the discretion of the principal investigator.

          -  Eligibility of subjects receiving any medications or substances with the potential to
             affect the activity or pharmacokinetics of MK-1775 will be determined following
             review by the principal investigator.

          -  Patients receiving any medications or substances that are inhibitors or inducers of
             CYP3A4, or CYP3A4 substrates need to be reviewed by the principal investigator.
             Continuation of such medications will be at the discretion of the principal
             investigator. Concomitant use of aprepitant is prohibited.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements.

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study because the effects of the study drugs on
             the developing fetus are unknown.

          -  HIV positive patients on antiretroviral therapy are ineligible because of the
             potential for PK interactions.

        INCLUSION OF WOMEN AND MINORITIES:

        Both men and women of all races and ethnic groups are eligible for this trial.&lt; TAB&gt;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shivaani Kummar, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jennifer H Zlott</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 435-5664</phone>
    <email>zlottjh@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Shivaani Kummar, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 435-0517</phone>
    <email>kummars@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact National Cancer Institute Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>888-624-1937</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-C-0032.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Watanabe N, Broome M, Hunter T. Regulation of the human WEE1Hu CDK tyrosine 15-kinase during the cell cycle. EMBO J. 1995 May 1;14(9):1878-91.</citation>
    <PMID>7743995</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dai Y, Grant S. New insights into checkpoint kinase 1 in the DNA damage response signaling network. Clin Cancer Res. 2010 Jan 15;16(2):376-83. doi: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-09-1029. Epub 2010 Jan 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20068082</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jazayeri A, Falck J, Lukas C, Bartek J, Smith GC, Lukas J, Jackson SP. ATM- and cell cycle-dependent regulation of ATR in response to DNA double-strand breaks. Nat Cell Biol. 2006 Jan;8(1):37-45. Epub 2005 Dec 4.</citation>
    <PMID>16327781</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 11, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>MK-1775</keyword>
  <keyword>Refractory</keyword>
  <keyword>Solid Tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>Wee1 Inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Tyrosine Kinase</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
