<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="77354">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02065245</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20130646</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02065245</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>AllogeneiC Human Mesenchymal Stem Cells (hMSC) in Patients With Aging FRAilTy Via IntravenoUS Delivery.</brief_title>
  <acronym>CRATUS</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II, Randomized, Blinded and Placebo-controlled Trial to Evaluate the Safety and Potential Efficacy of Allogeneic Human Mesenchymal Stem Cell Infusion in Patients With Aging Frailty.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Miami</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The EMMES Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Miami</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Before initiating the full randomized study, a Pilot Safety Phase will be performed. The
      randomized portion of this trial will be conducted after a full review of the safety data
      from the Pilot Phase by the Data safety monitoring board.

      Following the Pilot Phase of fifteen (15) subjects, thirty (30) subjects are scheduled to
      undergo infusion and meeting all inclusion/exclusion criteria will be evaluate at baseline.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A Pilot Phase will be performed to test the safety of dose and volume escalation of cells
      administered via peripheral intravenous infusion.  The randomized portion of the study will
      be conducted after a full review of the safety data from the Pilot Phase by the data safety
      monitoring board.

      RANDOMIZATION STUDY

      This Phase I/II, randomized, blinded, placebo-controlled study is designed to evaluate the
      safety and tolerability of allogenic human mesenchymal stem cells in patients with Frailty
      and to explore potential efficacy over 4 weeks.

      Approximately fifteen (15) subjects will be enrolled in the pilot phase and thirty (30)
      subjects with Frailty will be enrolled for a total of forty-five (45) subjects.  Subjects
      will then be enrolled and randomized 1:1:1 to an active arm or placebo.  Additional subjects
      may be enrolled if deemed appropriate.

      Eligible subjects must have a diagnosis or symptoms of frailty as defined by the Canadian
      Study on Health &amp; Aging. Following informed consent before or at the screening visit, the
      diagnosis of FRAILTY will be confirmed by investigator review of medical history.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of any treatment emergent serious adverse events (TE-SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>One Month post infusion</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Incidence (at one month post infusion) of any treatment-emergent serious adverse events (TE-SAEs), defined as the composite of: death, non-fatal pulmonary embolism, stroke, hospitalization for worsening dyspnea and clinically significant laboratory test abnormalities.
Serum chemistry: sodium, potassium, chloride, bicarbonate, blood urea nitrogen, creatinine, glucose, calcium, phosphate, aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT), total bilirubin (fractionate if total &gt;1.5 times normal), alkaline phosphatase, γ-glutamyl transaminase (GGT), albumin,
Hematology (Complete blood count): hemoglobin, hematocrit, platelets, white blood cells (WBC), WBC differential</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in rate of decline of Frailty</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and 6 months.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>• Difference in rate of decline of Frailty defined as:
Reduced Activity
Slowing of Mobility
Weight Loss
Diminished handgrip strength
Exhaustion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in subject quality of life assessment(s):</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and 6 months.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>•	Difference in subject quality of life assessment(s):</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Death from any cause</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and 6 months.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Death from any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exercise change in ejection fraction.</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and 6 months.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Exercise change in ejection fraction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Inflammatory Markers.</measure>
    <time_frame>At Baseline and 6 months.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>• The following panel of inflammatory markers:  C-reactive protein (CRP), Interleukin-6, D-dimer, fibrinogen, complete blood count with differential, DNA, cytomegalovirus, and TNFα</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Aging Frailty</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group A (10 subjects) - Allogeneic human mesenchymal stem cells: 100 million cells/ml delivered via peripheral intravenous infusion.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group B (10 subjects) - Allogeneic human mesenchymal stem cells: 200 million cells/ml delivered via peripheral intravenous infusion.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group C (10 subjects) - Placebo delivered via peripheral intravenous infusion.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Allogeneic Human Mesenchymal Stem Cells (allo-hMSCs)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Group C</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Provide written informed consent.

          -  Subjects age greater than or equal to 60 and less than or qual to 95 years at the
             time of signing the Informed Consent Form.

          -  Show signs of frailty apart from a concomitant condition as assessed by the
             Investigator with a frailty score of 4 to 7 using the Clinical Frailty Scale

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Score of less than or equal to 24 on the Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE)

          -  Inability to perform any of the assessments required for endpoint analysis (report
             safety or tolerability concerns, perform pulmonary function tests, undergo blood
             draws, read and respond to questionnaires.

          -  Active listing (or expected future listing) for transplant of any organ.

          -  Clinically important abnormal screening laboratory values, including but not limited
             to: hemoglobin &lt;8 g/dl, white blood cell count &lt;3000/mm3, platelets&lt;80,000/mm3,
             international normalized ratio (INR) &gt; 1.5, aspartate transaminase, alanine
             transaminase, or alkaline phosphatase &gt; 3 times upper limit of normal, total
             bilirubin &gt; 1.5 mg/dl.

          -  Serious comorbid illness that, in the opinion of the investigator, may compromise the
             safety or compliance of the patient or preclude successful completion of the study.
             Including, but not limited to: HIV, advanced liver or renal failure, class III/IV
             congestive heart failure, myocardial infarction, unstable angina, or cardiac
             revascularization within the last six months, or  severe obstructive ventilatory
             defect.

          -  Any other condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, may compromise the
             safety or compliance of the patient or preclude successful completion of the study.

          -  Have known allergies to penicillin or streptomyocin. Be an organ transplant
             recipient.

          -  Have a clinical history of malignancy within 5 years (i.e., patients with prior
             malignancy must be disease free for 5 years), except curatively-treated basal cell
             carcinoma, squamous cell carcinoma, or cervical carcinoma.

          -  Have a non-pulmonary condition that limits lifespan to &lt; 1 year.

          -  Have a history of drug or alcohol abuse within the past 24 months.

          -  Be serum positive for HIV, hepatitis BsAg or Viremic hepatitis C.

          -  Be currently participating (or participated within the previous 30 days) in an
             investigational therapeutic or device trial.

          -  Be a female who is pregnant, nursing, or of childbearing potential while not
             practicing effective contraceptive methods. Female patients must undergo a blood or
             urine pregnancy test at screening and within 36 hours prior to injection.

          -  Female subjects must have an Follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) &lt; 25.8 IU/L

          -  Have hypersensitivity to dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>95 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joshua M Hare, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>ISCI / University of Miami Miller School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joshua M Hare, MD</last_name>
    <phone>305-243-5579</phone>
    <email>jhare@med.miami.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ISCI/University of Miami Miller School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joshua M Hare, MD</last_name>
      <phone>305-243-5579</phone>
      <email>jhare@med.miami.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Darcy L DiFede, RN, BSN</last_name>
      <phone>305-243-9106</phone>
      <email>ddifede@med.miami.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joshua M Hare, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pascal Goldschmidt, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://isci.med.miami.edu</url>
    <description>Interdisciplinary Stem Cell Institute at the University of Miami Miller School of Medicine</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 14, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Miami</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Joshua M Hare</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief Science Officer / ISCI Director / Senior Associate Dean</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Aging Frailty, Frailty, Cardiovascular</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
