<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="82275">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01875848</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PPO 13-184</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01875848</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Buprenorphine vs. Opioid Dose Escalation Among Patients With Chronic Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Buprenorphine vs. Opioid Dose Escalation Among Patients With Chronic Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study compares buprenorphine/naloxone to opioid dose escalation among patients with
      poorly controlled non-cancer pain on 60-100 mg daily morphine equivalent opioid dose.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Increasingly, Veterans are prescribed potent opioid analgesics for the treatment of chronic
      pain despite limited evidence for efficacy and increasing evidence of serious harms
      including addiction and non-fatal and fatal overdose. While guidelines recommend
      consideration of dose increase for patients not benefitting from opioid therapy, the rates
      of major harms are directly related to dose. Higher doses may also be more likely to
      precipitate opioid-induced hyperalgesia, a paradoxical increased pain response, in
      susceptible individuals. In summary, opioid dose increase, a currently accepted clinical
      response to poorly controlled pain, may offer little benefit and certainly increases risk,
      especially in patients already on moderate-high doses (60-100 mg daily morphine
      equivalents). Alternative treatment strategies to opioid dose escalation that lessen risk
      and possibly increase benefit are much needed.

      Switching to buprenorphine/naloxone (BUP/NX), a partial opioid agonist approved for use in
      the treatment of opioid abuse/dependence, may be a safe and effective alternative strategy
      to opioid dose escalation in the treatment of chronic pain. As a partial agonist, there is a
      ceiling to BUP/NX's respiratory depressant and other opioid-like effects, meaning it is less
      likely to cause addiction and overdose. Additionally, there are pre-clinical data to suggest
      BUP/NX is less likely to produce opioid-induced hyperalgesia and may even reverse it in
      patients switched from full agonist opioids. Case series have demonstrated improvements in
      pain, functional status and quality of life among patients switched from full agonist
      opioids to BUP/NX for chronic pain. Controlled trials are needed to establish BUP/NX's
      efficacy compared to opioid dose escalation in the treatment of poorly-controlled pain.

      The investigators propose a pilot 12-week, open label randomized trial of BUP/NX compared to
      opioid dose escalation among patients with poorly-controlled pain on the primary outcome of
      pain intensity. As patient acceptance of either opioid dose escalation or BUP/NX is unknown,
      the investigators' first objective is to assess willingness to enroll in a randomized trial
      and reasons for and against enrollment among eligible patients. The study will compare
      treatments on the primary outcome of pain intensity, measured using the 11-point pain
      numerical rating scale, and secondary outcomes of pain interference, using the Brief Pain
      Inventory functional interference subscale, medication adherence and patient global
      assessment of change. Mixed models will be employed in the analysis to accommodate potential
      unbalanced repeated measures with missing data. Effect size estimates will be used to
      generate sample size projections for a definitive trial. This line of research is a direct
      extension of the PI's HSR&amp;D-funded CDA-2 project developing a screening tool to identify low
      efficacy opioid use in primary care and also well-aligned with the Strategic Plan and
      Focused Area of Research of the Pain Research, Informatics, Medical comorbidities, and
      Education (PRIME) Center's proposal for a Center of Innovation (COIN) and its strategic
      objective to &quot;Promote access, continuity, and sustainability of safe and effective
      interventions for pain and pain-related disability.&quot;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Brief Pain Inventory, interference module</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>buprenorphine/naloxone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>induction onto buprenorphine/naloxone from opioid treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>opioid dose escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>increase of up to 25% of current opioid dose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>buprenorphine/naloxone</intervention_name>
    <description>partial opioid agonist</description>
    <arm_group_label>buprenorphine/naloxone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Suboxone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>opioid dose escalation</intervention_name>
    <description>up to 25% increase in patient's current opioid dose</description>
    <arm_group_label>opioid dose escalation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged 18 and older

          -  3 months of continuous opioid therapy for chronic pain;

          -  60-100 mg morphine equivalent daily opioid dose based on pharmacy records of standing
             and as needed opioids prescribed.

          -  28 (out of 70) on the 7-item Brief Pain Inventory (BPI) functional interference
             subscale at screening

          -  Numerical pain rating of 4 or greater (i.e., moderate pain or greater) at screening
             on the 11-point pain numerical rating scale (NRS)

          -  Females must (a) be using birth control pills or depo provera injections, or have an
             intrauterine device; or (b) be post-menopausal, or (c) have undergone surgically
             sterilization.

          -  Primary care provider's (PCP) assent for patient participation, ascertained via
             encrypted email or in-person query.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  DSM-IV defined substance use disorder, except nicotine dependence. Participants known
             to using marijuana, including those who are apparently legally authorized to use
             marijuana by non-VHA providers, will be excluded since opioid dose escalation in
             regular marijuana users is contraindicated.

          -  Opioid therapy for palliative care

          -  Participation in another investigational pharmaceutical trial within 30 days of
             screening

          -  Pregnancy or lactation

          -  Recently decompensated medical illness necessitating inpatient hospitalization (past
             30 days)

          -  Transaminases (aspartate aminotransferase/alanine aminotransferase) greater than five
             times the upper limit of normal within 90 days of assessment phase

          -  Not well-controlled psychiatric symptoms at the time of physician assessment,
             including suicidal ideation or untreated psychosis; or recently decompensated
             psychiatric illness necessitating inpatient hospitalization (past 30 days).

          -  Use of a moderate to strong CYP3A4 inhibitor
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William C Becker, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Connecticut Health Care System (West Haven)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Connecticut Health Care System (West Haven)</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06516</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 28, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pain management</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Buprenorphine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Analgesics, Opioid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Naloxone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
