<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="120944">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01806571</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MC1284</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-00469</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01806571</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Daunorubicin Hydrochloride, Cytarabine, and Nilotinib in Treating Patients With Newly Diagnosed Acute Myeloid Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Combination Daunorubicin and Cytarabine (Ara-c) and Nilotinib (Tasigna) (DATA) in Patients Newly Diagnosed With Acute Myeloid Leukemia and KIT Overexpression</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well giving daunorubicin hydrochloride, cytarabine, and
      nilotinib together works in treating patients newly diagnosed with acute myeloid leukemia.
      Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as, daunorubicin hydrochloride and cytarabine, work in
      different ways to stop the growth of cancer cell, either by killing the cells or by stopping
      them from dividing. Nilotinib may stop the growth of cancer cells by blocking some of the
      enzymes needed for cell growth. Giving daunorubicin hydrochloride together with cytarabine
      and nilotinib may kill more cancer cells
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the complete response rates of combination nilotinib, cytarabine, and
      daunorubicin (daunorubicin hydrochloride) in patients newly diagnosed with acute myeloid
      leukemia (AML) and Kit overexpression.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Determine the 2-year overall survival (OS) and disease-free survival (DFS) rates.

      II. Determine the complete response duration in patients treated with this regimen.

      III. Assess the safety and toxicity of this regimen based on National Cancer Institute (NCI)
      Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Assess the prognostic and predictive factors (Kit mutation/expression level, fms-related
      tyrosine kinase 3 [Flt3] mutation) for patients treated with this regimen.

      II. Assess the patterns of molecular response and relapse for Kit. III. Assess the effect on
      minimal residual disease (MRD) by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) or flow cytometry.

      OUTLINE:

      INDUCTION THERAPY: Patients receive daunorubicin hydrochloride intravenously (IV) over 10
      minutes on days 1-3, cytarabine IV continuously on days 1-7, and nilotinib orally (PO) twice
      daily (BID)on days 4-14. Patients achieving complete remission (CR) or complete remission
      with incomplete blood count recovery (CRi) proceed to consolidation therapy. Patients not
      achieving a decrease in bone marrow recovery or CR/CRi upon bone marrow recovery receive
      another course of induction therapy.

      CONSOLIDATION THERAPY: Patients receive cytarabine IV every 12 hours on days 1, 3, and 5,
      and nilotinib PO BID on days 4-14. Treatment repeats every 28 days for 4 courses in the
      absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients achieving CR or CRi
      proceed to maintenance therapy.

      MAINTENANCE THERAPY: Patients receive nilotinib PO BID on days 1-84. Treatment repeats every
      84 days for up to 8 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 6 months for up to 3
      years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of complete responses (CR or CRi) during induction therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The proportion of successes will be estimated by the number of successes divided by the total number of evaluable patients. Confidence intervals for the true success proportion will be calculated according to the approach of Duffy and Santner (Duffy D 1987).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From registration to death due to any cause, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The distribution of survival time will be estimated using the method of Kaplan-Meier (Kaplan E 1958).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>OS rate</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival time (DFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From registration to relapse or death due to any cause, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The distribution of DFS will be estimated using the method of Kaplan- Meier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>DFS rate</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of complete response</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date at which objective status is first noted to be CR or CRi to the earliest date relapse is documented, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The distribution of duration of complete response will be estimated using the method of Kaplan-Meier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability assessed by NCI CTCAE version 4.0 out to 3 years</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years after completion of study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The maximum grade for each type of adverse event will be recorded for each patient, and frequency tables will be reviewed to determine patterns. Additionally, the relationship of the adverse event(s) to the study treatment will be taken into consideration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">43</enrollment>
  <condition>Adult Acute Basophilic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Eosinophilic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Megakaryoblastic Leukemia (M7)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Minimally Differentiated Myeloid Leukemia (M0)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Monoblastic Leukemia (M5a)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Monocytic Leukemia (M5b)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloblastic Leukemia With Maturation (M2)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloblastic Leukemia Without Maturation (M1)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With 11q23 (MLL) Abnormalities</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With Del(5q)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With Inv(16)(p13;q22)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With t(16;16)(p13;q22)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With t(8;21)(q22;q22)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myelomonocytic Leukemia (M4)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Erythroleukemia (M6a)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Pure Erythroid Leukemia (M6b)</condition>
  <condition>Untreated Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (nilotinib, daunorubicin hydrochloride, cytarabine)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>INDUCTION THERAPY: Patients receive daunorubicin hydrochloride IV over 10 minutes on days 1-3, cytarabine IV continuously on days 1-7, and nilotinib PO BID on days 4-14. Patients achieving CR or CRi proceed to consolidation therapy. Patients not achieving a decrease in bone marrow recovery or CR/CRi upon bone marrow recovery receive another course of induction therapy.
CONSOLIDATION THERAPY: Patients receive cytarabine IV every 12 hours on days 1, 3, and 5, and nilotinib PO BID on days 4-14. Treatment repeats every 28 days for 4 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients achieving CR or CRi proceed to maintenance therapy.
MAINTENANCE THERAPY: Patients receive nilotinib PO BID on days 1-84. Treatment repeats every 84 days for up to 8 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>daunorubicin hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (nilotinib, daunorubicin hydrochloride, cytarabine)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cerubidin</other_name>
    <other_name>Cerubidine</other_name>
    <other_name>daunomycin hydrochloride</other_name>
    <other_name>daunorubicin</other_name>
    <other_name>RP-13057</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cytarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (nilotinib, daunorubicin hydrochloride, cytarabine)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ARA-C</other_name>
    <other_name>arabinofuranosylcytosine</other_name>
    <other_name>arabinosylcytosine</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytosar-U</other_name>
    <other_name>cytosine arabinoside</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>nilotinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (nilotinib, daunorubicin hydrochloride, cytarabine)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AMN 107</other_name>
    <other_name>Tasigna</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (nilotinib, daunorubicin hydrochloride, cytarabine)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (nilotinib, daunorubicin hydrochloride, cytarabine)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pharmacological studies</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Untreated, histological confirmed acute myeloid leukemia (AML) based on World Heath
             Organization (WHO) 2008 criteria with Kit expression (cluster of differentiation [CD]
             117) of myeloblasts &gt;= 20% by flow cytometry from bone marrow aspirate at diagnosis

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status (PS) 0, 1, or 2

          -  Magnesium within normal limits (WNL)

          -  Potassium WNL

          -  Phosphorus WNL

          -  Serum amylase =&lt; 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Serum lipase =&lt; 1.5 x ULN

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x ULN (does not apply to patients with isolated
             hyperbilirubinemia [e.g., Gilbert's disease], in that case direct bilirubin should be
             =&lt; 2 x ULN)

          -  Alkaline phosphatase =&lt; 3 x ULN

          -  Serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT) (aspartate aminotransferase [AST]) =&lt;
             3 x ULN

          -  Creatinine =&lt;1.5 x ULN

          -  Negative pregnancy test done =&lt; 7 days prior to registration, for women of
             childbearing potential only

          -  Provide informed written consent

          -  Willing to return to consenting Mayo Clinic (Mayo Clinic's campus in Rochester, Mayo
             Clinic's campus in Arizona, or Mayo Clinic's campus in Florida) institution for
             follow-up during the active monitoring phase of the study

          -  Willing to provide bone marrow aspirate and blood samples for correlative research
             purposes

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any of the following because this study involves investigational agent(s) whose
             genotoxic, mutagenic and teratogenic effects on the developing fetus and newborn are
             unknown

               -  Pregnant women

               -  Nursing women

               -  Men or women of childbearing potential who are unwilling to employ adequate
                  contraception throughout the study and for 3 months after completion of study
                  treatment

          -  Co-morbid systemic illnesses or other severe concurrent disease which, in the
             judgment of the investigator, would make the patient inappropriate for entry into
             this study or interfere significantly with the proper assessment of safety and
             toxicity of the prescribed regimens

          -  Immunocompromised patients (other than that related to the use of corticosteroids)
             including patients known to be human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positive

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements

          -  Receiving any other investigational agent which would be considered as a treatment
             for the primary neoplasm

          -  Other active malignancy =&lt; 3 years prior to registration; EXCEPTIONS: non-melanotic
             skin cancer or carcinoma-in-situ of the cervix

          -  Previous treatment with chemotherapy or any other tyrosine kinase inhibitor for a
             hematological disorder; Exceptions: patients with prior diagnosis of myelodysplastic
             syndrome (MDS) and/or treatment with hypomethylating agent (azacytidine or
             decitabine) are not excluded, prior hydroxyurea allowed

          -  Impaired cardiac function including any one of the following:

               -  Inability to monitor the QT interval on electrocardiogram (ECG)

               -  Congenital long QT syndrome or a known family history of long QT syndrome

               -  Clinically significant resting brachycardia (&lt; 50 beats per minute)

               -  QTc &gt; 450 msec on baseline ECG; if QTc &gt; 450 msec and electrolytes are not
                  within normal ranges, electrolytes should be corrected and then the patient
                  re-screened for QTc

               -  Myocardial infarction =&lt; 2 months prior to starting study

               -  Other clinically significant uncontrolled heart disease (e.g. unstable angina,
                  congestive heart failure or uncontrolled hypertension)

               -  History of or presence of clinically significant ventricular, atrial
                  tachyarrhythmias or ejection fraction cutoff

               -  Left ventricle ejection fraction &lt; 45%

               -  History of, congestive heart failure requiring use of ongoing maintenance
                  therapy for life-threatening ventricular arrhythmias

          -  Patients currently receiving treatment with strong cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4)
             inhibitors and treatment that cannot be either discontinued or switched to a
             different medication prior to starting study drug; patients receiving any medications
             or substances that are strong or moderate inhibitors of CYP3A4

               -  Use of the following strong or moderate inhibitors is prohibited &lt; 7 days prior
                  to registration

                    -  Strong inhibitors of CYP3A4/5 &gt; 5-fold increase in the plasma area under
                       the curve (AUC) values or more then 80% decrease in clearance

                         -  Boceprevir (Victrelis)

                         -  Clarithromycin (Biaxin, Biaxin XL)

                         -  Conivaptan (Vaprisol)

                         -  Grapefruit juice

                         -  Indinavir (Crixivan)

                         -  Itraconazole (Sporanox)

                         -  Ketoconazole (Nizoral)

                         -  Lopinavir/ritonavir (Kaletra)

                         -  Mibefradil

                         -  Nefazodone (Serzone)

                         -  Nelfinavir (Viracept)

                         -  Posaconazole (Noxafil)

                         -  Ritonavir (Novir, Kaletra)

                         -  Saquinivir (Fortovase, Invirase)

                         -  Telaprevir (Incivek)

                         -  Telithromycin (Ketek)

                         -  Voriconazole (Vfend)

                    -  Moderate inhibitors of CYP3A4/5 &gt; 2-fold in the plasma AUC values of
                       50-80%, decrease in clearance

                         -  Amprenavir (Agenerase)

                         -  Aprepitant (Emend)

                         -  Atazanavir (Reyataz)

                         -  Ciprofloxacin (Cipro)

                         -  Darunavir (Prezista)

                         -  Diltiazem (Cardizem, Cardizem CD, Cardizem LA, Cardizem SR, Cartia XT,
                            Dilacor XR, Diltia XT, Taztia XT, Tiazac)

                         -  Erythromycin (Erythrocin, E.E.S. , Ery-Tab, Eryc, EryPed, PCE

                         -  Fluconazole (Diflucan)

                         -  Fosamprenavir (Lexiva)

                         -  Imatinib (Gleevec)

                         -  Verapamil (Calan, Calan SR, Covera-HS, Isoptin SR, Verelan, Verelan
                            PM)

          -  Receiving any medications or substances that are inducers of CYP3A4; use of the
             following inducers are prohibited =&lt; 7 days prior to registration

               -  Strong inducers of CYP3A4/5 &gt; 80% decrease in AUC

                    -  Avasimibe

                    -  Carbamazepine (Carbatrol, Epitol, Equetro, Tegretol, Tegretol-XR)

                    -  Phenytoin (Dilantin, Phenytek)

                    -  Rifampin (Rifadin)

                    -  St. John's wort

               -  Moderate inducers of CYP3A4/5 50-80% decrease in AUC

                    -  Bosentan (Tracleer)

                    -  Efavirenz (Sustiva)

                    -  Etravirine (Intelence)

                    -  Modafinil (Provigil)

                    -  Nafcillin

                    -  Nevirapine (Viramune)

                    -  Phenobarbital (Luminal)

                    -  Rifabutin (Mycobutin)

                    -  Troglitazone

          -  Patients currently receiving treatment with any medications that have the potential
             to prolong the QT interval and the treatment cannot be either discontinued or
             switched to a different medication prior to starting study drug

          -  Impaired gastrointestinal (GI) function or GI disease that may significantly alter
             the absorption of study drug (e.g., ulcerative diseases, uncontrolled nausea,
             vomiting, diarrhea, malabsorption syndrome, small bowel resection or gastric bypass
             surgery)

          -  Acute or chronic pancreatic disease

          -  Known cytopathologically confirmed central nervous system (CNS) infiltration

          -  Acute or chronic liver disease or severe renal disease considered unrelated to the
             cancer

          -  History of significant congenital or acquired bleeding disorder unrelated to cancer

          -  Major surgery =&lt; 4 weeks prior to registration of the study or who have not recovered
             from prior surgery

          -  Treatment with other investigational agents =&lt; 14 days of registration

          -  Diagnosis of AML-M3 (or acute promyelocytic leukemia)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Aref Al-Kali, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Arizona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85259</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mayo Clinic Clinical Trials Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>507-538-7623</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Raoul Tibes, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mayo Clinic Clinical Trials Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>507-538-7623</phone>
      <email>alkali.aref@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Aref Al-Kali, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 30, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 25, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Aref Al-Kali</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Congenital Abnormalities</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Basophilic, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Eosinophilic, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Erythroblastic, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Megakaryoblastic, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Monocytic, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelomonocytic, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelomonocytic, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypereosinophilic Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cytarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Daunorubicin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
