<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="65544">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02032238</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CAVNAV-2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02032238</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Efficacy of Bevacizumab Combined With Navigated Laser in Patients With Clinically Significant Macula Edema</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>OD-OS GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>OD-OS GmbH</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this is study is to assess the efficacy of navigated laser treatment in
      reducing the number of anti-VEGF injections required to maintain visual gain obtained after
      Bevacizumab compared to Bevacizumab alone in patients with clinically significant macular
      edema (CSME).

      This will be prospective, active-controlled study using Bevacizumab (Genentech, South San
      Francisco CA) for intravitreal injections. Retinal photocoagulation will utilize the Navilas
      Laser System (OD-OS GmbH, Teltow, Germany), which is an approved indication for this device.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of eyes that received retreatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Clinically Significant Macular Edema</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Combination with navigated laser</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Combining photocoagulation and Anti-VEGF Injections in a pre-defined manner</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Monotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>patients receive Anti-VEGF Monotherapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Navigated laser</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard Anti-VEGF Injections will be combined with Navigated laser in a pre-defined manner</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combination with navigated laser</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anti-VEGF Injections</intervention_name>
    <description>Monotherapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combination with navigated laser</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Monotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  CSME and Diagnosis of diabetes mellitus

          -  Able and willing to provide informed consent prior to any study-related procedures

          -  Central foveal thickness &gt; 250 microns at baseline

          -  Best corrected visual acuity between 20/400 and 20/40

          -  Willing and able to comply with clinic visits and study-related procedures

          -  U.S. patients will be required to have a Health Insurance Portability and
             Accountability Act (HIPAA) authorization; in other countries, as applicable according
             to national laws

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  - Macular edema is considered to be due to a cause other than diabetic macular edema.

          -  An ocular condition is present such that, in the opinion of the investigator, visual
             acuity loss would not improve from resolution of macular edema (e.g., macular
             ischemia, vitreomacular traction, foveal atrophy, pigment abnormalities, dense
             subfoveal hard exudates, nonretinal condition).

          -  An ocular condition is present (other than diabetes) that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, might affect macular edema or alter visual acuity during the course of
             the study (e.g., vein occlusion, uveitis or other ocular inflammatory disease,
             neovascular glaucoma, etc.)

          -  Substantial cataract that, in the opinion of the investigator, is likely to be
             decreasing visual acuity by 3 lines or more (i.e., cataract would be reducing acuity
             to 20/40 or worse if eye was otherwise normal).

          -  History of treatment for diabetic macular edema at any time in the past 4 months
             (such as focal/grid macular photocoagulation, intravitreal or peribulbar
             corticosteroids, anti-VEGF drugs, or any other treatment).

          -  History of panretinal (scatter) photocoagulation (PRP) within 4 months prior to
             enrollment.

          -  History of major ocular surgery (including vitrectomy, cataract extraction, scleral
             buckle, any intraocular surgery, etc.) within prior 4 months or anticipated within
             the next 6 months following randomization. 13

          -  History of YAG capsulotomy performed within 2 months prior to randomization.

          -  Aphakia.

          -  Intraocular pressure &gt;= 25 mmHg.

          -  History of open-angle glaucoma (either primary open-angle glaucoma or other cause of
             open-angle glaucoma; note: history of angle-closure glaucoma is not an exclusion
             criterion).

          -  History of steroid-induced intraocular pressure (IOP) elevation that required
             IOP-lowering treatment.

          -  Exam evidence of external ocular infection, including conjunctivitis, chalazion, or
             significant blepharitis

          -  Significant renal disease, defined as a history of chronic renal failure requiring
             dialysis or kidney transplant.

          -  A condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, would preclude participation in
             the study (e.g., unstable medical status including blood pressure, cardiovascular
             disease, and glycemic control)

          -  Participation in an investigational trial within 30 days of randomization that
             involved treatment with any drug that has not received regulatory approval at the
             time of study entry

          -  Known allergy to any component of the study drug

          -  Blood pressure &gt; 180/110 (systolic above 180 OR diastolic above 110).

          -  Major surgery within 28 days prior to randomization or major surgery planned during
             the next 6 months.

          -  Myocardial infarction, other cardiac event requiring hospitalization, stroke,
             transient ischemic attack, or treatment for acute congestive heart failure within 4
             months prior to randomization.

          -  Systemic anti-vascular growth factor (anti-VEGF) or pro-VEGF treatment within 4
             months prior to randomization 14

          -  For women of child-bearing potential: pregnant or lactating or intending to become
             pregnant within the next 12 months.

          -  Subject is expecting to move out of the area of the clinical center to an area not
             covered by another clinical center during the first 12 months of the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ulrike Weber</last_name>
    <email>ulrike.weber@od-os.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Eye and Ear Infirmary</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10009</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Katy Tai</last_name>
      <email>KTai@NYEE.EDU</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 8, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 8, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Edema</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Macular Edema</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Bevacizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
