<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="58818">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02056834</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU-BIO-T-XX-004-04</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02056834</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>chronOS Inject in Proximal Tibial Fractures</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective, Multi-Center, Observational Study Evaluating the Augmentation With Calcium Phosphate Cement (chronOS Inject) for Bone Defect After Internal Fixation of Proximal Tibial Fractures</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Synthes GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Synthes GmbH</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>South Korea: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to observe the safety, the radiological and clinical
      outcomes of chronOS Inject after having been used as bone void filler in internal fixation
      of proximal tibial fractures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study was to observe the safety, the radiological and clinical
      outcomes of chronOS Inject after having been used as bone void filler in internal fixation
      of proximal tibial fractures. Secondary objectives were to assess the surgeon's satisfaction
      in using chronOS Inject and patient satisfaction post surgery.

      The study was planned to be a multi-center, prospective, observational study. Patients with
      proximal tibial fractures of type Schatzker I - VI, AO-Müller-Orthopaedic Trauma Association
      (AO-OTA) 41, AO-OTA 42 with bone defect were assessed for eligibility to enter the study.
      Patients eligible for the study were followed over time to twelve months after surgery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Union or non-union</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Fracture union is assessed by the investigators based on anteroposterior and lateral X-rays at all follow-up visits.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to union (in weeks)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Mean time to union is calculated based on the Kaplan-Meier estimator of the survivorship function.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Amount of articular subsidence</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evidence of articular subsidence of ≥2 mm is assessed by the investigators at each follow-up timepoint.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate and time of absorption of calcium phosphate cement</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Absorption rates are calculated from X-rays with the INFINITT program.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to ambulation after surgery (in weeks)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Weight bearing is indicated as partial or full at each follow up visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee range of motion (degrees of flexion, extension)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Total range of knee motion, extension and extension stability are assessed at each post-operative visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of complications/adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigators are asked to report all adverse events (AE) occurring in any clinical study patient. For reporting purposes, the event does not need to have a causal relationship with the device used in the study. An AE was defined as any unfavorable or unintended sign, symptom, or disease regardless of the relationship to the device. The investigator provides description, action taken and outcome of each adverse event, and classifies each event as to product relatedness and severity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiographic assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Radiographic results are indicated for depression, condylar widening and angulation (valgus/varus).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient's satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Satisfaction with treatment was assessed by the subject at all follow up visits, where subjects indicated their satisfaction with treatment on a 100-mm visual analog scale. A score of zero indicated no satisfaction, while a score of 100 indicated completely satisfied.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Surgeon's satisfaction with the product</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Satisfaction with product is assessed by the surgeon post-operatively, where surgeons indicated their satisfaction with treatment on a 100-mm visual analog scale. A score of zero indicated absolutely unacceptable, while a score of 100 indicated very satisfying.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Estimated blood loss during surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 (date of surgery)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Operation time</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 (date of surgery)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Time in hospital after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>From day 0 (date of surgery) to hospital discharge (up to 12 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Time to resume work partly or totally</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pain medication before and after surgery (type, amount, and duration)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Length of conservative therapy post-surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Closed Proximal Tibial Fracture Schatzker I - VI</condition>
  <condition>Closed Proximal Tibial Fracture AO-OTA 41</condition>
  <condition>Closed Proximal Tibial Fracture AO-OTA 42</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>chronOS Inject</arm_group_label>
    <description>Closed proximal tibial fractures of type Schatzker I - VI, AO-OTA 41, AO-OTA 42 with bone defect</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>chronOS Inject</intervention_name>
    <description>chronOS Inject is used as bone void filler in internal fixation of proximal tibial fractures</description>
    <arm_group_label>chronOS Inject</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with proximal tibial fractures of type Schatzter I - VI, AO-OTA 41, AO-OTA 42
        with bone defect are assessed for eligibility to enter the study. A computerized
        tomography is performed if necessary to confirm the fracture type and the amount of bone
        defect. Patients eligible for the study are followed over time to 12 months after surgery.

        A total of 30 patients who meet the inclusion/exclusion criteria are enrolled in the
        study, which is conducted at Kyungpook National University Hospital and Hanyang University
        Guri Hospital in the Republic of Korea.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with closed proximal tibial fractures defined by : Tibia plateau, Schatzker
             I - VI, AO-OTA 41, AO-OTA 42 with bone defect

          -  Skeletally mature adult 18 years or older, with close of growth plate at the time of
             surgery

          -  Psychosocially, mentally and physically able to fully comply with this protocol
             including adhering to scheduled visits, treatment plan, completing forms, and other
             study procedures

          -  Personally signed and dated informed consent document prior to any study-related
             procedures indicating that the patient has been informed of all pertinent aspects of
             the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Open fractures with severe soft tissue damage

          -  Proximal tibial fractures with tumor or osteomyelitis

          -  Any tibial anatomy or disease process that would interfere with deployment or
             performance of the device as defined by the surgeon

          -  Osteopenia or Osteoporosis: if dual energy x-ray absorptiometry (DEXA) is required,
             exclusion will be defined as a DEXA bone density measured T score &lt;=-1.0

          -  Known history of Paget's disease, osteomalacia, or any other metabolic bone disease

          -  Morbid obesity defined as a body mass index &gt;40 kg/m2 or weight more than 50 kg over
             ideal body weight

          -  Active malignancy. A patient with a history of any invasive malignancy (except
             non-melanoma skin cancer), unless treated with curative intent and there has been no
             clinical signs or symptoms of the malignancy &gt;5 years

          -  Known or documented history of communicable disease, including AIDS and HIV

          -  Active Hepatitis (receiving medical treatment within two years)

          -  Active systemic or local infection

          -  Active rheumatoid arthritis, non-controlled diabetes mellitus, or any other medical
             condition(s) that would represent a significant increase in surgical risk or
             interfere with normal healing

          -  Current or recent history (within last 2 years) of substance abuse (e.g.,
             recreational drugs, narcotics, or alcohol)

          -  Immunologically suppressed, or has received systemic steroids, excluding nasal
             steroids, at any dose daily for &gt;1 month within last 12 months

          -  Pregnant or planning to become pregnant during study period

          -  Involved in study of another investigational product that may affect outcome

          -  History of psychosocial disorders that could prevent accurate completion of self
             reporting assessment scales

          -  Patients who are incarcerated
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chang-Wug Oh, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kyungpook National University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kichul Park, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hanyang University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kyungpook National University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Daegu</city>
        <zip>700-721</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hanyang University Guri Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guri</city>
        <zip>471-701</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 5, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 31, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fractures, Bone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tibial Fractures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
