<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="26798">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01984515</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RRP 13-204</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>RRP 13-204</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01984515</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Increasing Engagement in Evidence-Based PTSD Therapy for Primary Care Veterans</brief_title>
  <official_title>Increasing Engagement in Evidence-Based PTSD Therapy for Primary Care Veterans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to implement an evidence-based Referral Management System that
      will address patient and system-level barriers to the uptake of evidence-based psychotherapy
      for PTSD by Veterans Affairs primary care patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Within the Veteran's Health Administration (VHA), primary care (PC) patients with PTSD have
      low rates of engagement in evidence-based psychotherapy (EBP) for PTSD.  Low engagement
      rates are due to a variety of patient-level (e.g., belief that treatment will not be
      helpful, stigma) and system-level barriers (e.g., lack of tracking of referral process,
      knowledge gaps on how to manage PTSD). We propose to conduct a pilot hybrid effectiveness-
      implementation study to implement an evidence-based Referral Management System (RMS) that
      will address patient and system-level barriers to the uptake of EBP for PTSD by VHA primary
      care patients.  RMS will address patient-level barriers with the delivery of a 1-session
      cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) intervention to identify and change treatment seeking
      beliefs that serve as an barrier to treatment engagement, including specific negative
      beliefs about EBP (e.g., talking about past trauma will be too difficult for me&quot;). This CBT
      intervention has been previously found to be effective for increasing treatment engagement
      with Veterans with PTSD. Depending on Veteran preference, it will be delivered by the PC-MHI
      provider within the PC clinic or a Behavioral Health Lab (BHL) care manager by phone.  RMS
      will be initiated by PACT staff and will address system-level barriers by having a BHL
      technician track the progress of RMS referrals and contact Veterans who have not followed
      thought on their chosen referral options. PACT staff will also be trained with simple
      scripts on how to address PTSD symptoms and make appropriate referrals based on VA/DoD
      Clinical Practice Guidelines for PTSD.  Our aims, implementation strategy, data collection,
      and analyses will be guided by established strategies.  The Consolidated Framework for
      Implementation Research (CFIR) will identify organization variables.  RE-AIM will
      investigate program uptake and patient/ system-level impact. An Implementation Mapping
      approach will guide our implementation strategy. We propose to conduct this study in 3
      phases.  Phase 1 includes interviews with PC and MH leadership about the relevance of CFIR
      constructs to RMS implementation and a meeting with PACT staff to train them on RMS and
      gather their input on how RMS should be adapted to their clinic.  A PC medical provider will
      serve as a clinical champion who is knowledgeable, communicative, and a leader in promoting
      RMS among his/her peers.  Phase 2 consists of implementing RMS for 6 months in one Syracuse
      PC clinic and then measuring RE-AIM outcomes.  Phase 3 involves meeting with PACT and MH
      Leadership and PACT staff to share a formal report of study results and gather information
      about potential barriers and facilitators to long-term maintenance and future expansion of
      RMS within the CFIR framework.  An expert national stakeholder panel will also be convened
      to guide development of a SDP that will investigate multi-VISN implementation.

      Our long-term aim of this line of research is to increase implementation of evidence-based
      psychotherapy for PTSD by getting more primary care patients with PTSD to engage in
      treatment.

      Our Specific Aims for this Rapid Response Project are to:

      1. Assess and improve the feasibility of implementing RMS in PC-MHI/PACT settings

      1A. Diagnose organizational and staff-level barriers and facilitators to implementing RMS.

      1B. Adapt RMS for the local context based on information gathered about barriers and
      facilitators.

      2. Evaluate initial impact of implementing RMS in PC-MHI/PACT settings.  Assess impact of
      RMS on RE-AIM measures of Reach, Efficacy/Effectiveness, Adoption, Implementation and
      Maintenance 3. Refine implementation strategy based on study findings for planned efforts to
      spread RMS to additional VISNs in a QUERI Phase 2 Service-Directed Project (SDP) to follow.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Engagement in evidence-based psychotherapy for PTSD</measure>
    <time_frame>From initiation of the Referral Management System to 6 months after initiation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Engagement will be assessed by how many patients attend at least 2 sessions of an evidence-based psychotherapy for PTSD and how many complete treatment.  Completion is defined as   8 sessions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PTSD Checklist-Specific</measure>
    <time_frame>Referral Management Initiation, 1 month post initiation, 3 months post initiation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PTSD symptoms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Health Questionnaire-9 Item</measure>
    <time_frame>Referral Management Initiation, 1 month post initiation, 3 months post initiation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Depressive Symptoms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Post-traumatic Stress Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Team Red Primary Care</arm_group_label>
    <description>Eligible patients will receive the Referral Management System in primary care</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Team Blue Primary Care</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patient will receive treatment as usual for PTSD in primary care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Referral Management System</intervention_name>
    <description>Referral Management System (RMS) will address patient-level barriers with the delivery of a 1-session cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) intervention to identify and change treatment seeking beliefs that serve as an barrier to treatment engagement, including specific negative beliefs about EBP (e.g., &quot;talking about past trauma will be too difficult for me&quot;).  RMS will address system-level barriers by tracking the progress of RMS referrals and contacting Veterans who have not followed thought on their chosen referral options. Primary Care staff will also be trained with simple scripts on how to address PTSD symptoms and make appropriate referrals based on VA/DoD Clinical Practice Guidelines for PTSD.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Team Red Primary Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Veterans primary care patients with PTSD
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Team Red primary care patients,

          -  have a score of at least 44 on PCL-S and

          -  able to give informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kyle Possemato, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Medical Center, Syracuse</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kyle Possemato, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(315) 425-4400</phone>
    <phone_ext>53551</phone_ext>
    <email>kyle.possemato@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Laura O Wray, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(716) 862-8598</phone>
    <email>Laura.Wray@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Medical Center, Syracuse</name>
      <address>
        <city>Syracuse</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>13210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kyle Possemato, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>315-425-4400</phone>
      <phone_ext>53551</phone_ext>
      <email>kyle.possemato@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Laura O Wray, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(716) 862-8598</phone>
      <email>Laura.Wray@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kyle Possemato, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 11, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 7, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Post-traumatic Stress Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Evidence-Based Psychotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment Engagement</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Implementation Science</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Traumatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
