<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="65281">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01686438</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IIR 11-296</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01686438</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Telemedicine Management of Chronic Insomnia</brief_title>
  <acronym>VIP</acronym>
  <official_title>Telemedicine Management of Veterans With PTSD and Chronic Insomnia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Insomnia is commonly present in Veterans with post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD).
      Treatment of insomnia with a specialized type of psychotherapy has been shown to be more
      effective than treatment with medications.  Unfortunately, few psychologists are trained to
      provide this treatment, limiting Veterans' access to care, especially those Veterans in
      remote and rural areas.  This project will evaluate the ability to deliver this
      psychotherapy to groups of Veterans by video teleconferencing.  Groups of Veterans with PTSD
      and chronic insomnia will receive the psychotherapy treatment either by meeting in-person
      with the psychologist or by the psychologist delivering the treatment by video
      teleconferencing.   Finding that video teleconferencing is a cost effective way to deliver
      this treatment could add an important new component to the care of Veterans with PTSD that
      provides an alternative to medications.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this project is to increase access to care of chronic insomnia for Veterans with
      posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD). While insomnia is one of the hyperarousal criteria for
      PTSD, it can have chronic, independent, negative effects on quality of life, and may
      exacerbate other symptoms of PTSD. Cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia (CBT-I) is
      highly efficacious and effective with long-term outcomes superior to those with
      pharmacotherapy. The lack of clinicians trained in CBT-I limits access to this treatment.
      Telemedicine could increase access to this specialized care, particularly for patients in
      rural and remote areas.

      The investigators will conduct a randomized, controlled trial in Veterans with PTSD and
      chronic insomnia to compare the clinical- and cost-effectiveness of CBT-I administered by
      video teleconferencing versus in-person delivery using a three-arm non-inferiority design.
      225 Veterans with PTSD and chronic insomnia receiving their primary care at community-based
      outpatient clinics (CBOC) will be randomized to receive one of the following group
      interventions at the CBOCs: 1) a manual based CBT-I program delivered via video
      teleconferencing, 2) the CBT-I program delivered in-person, and 3) in-person delivery of
      sleep hygiene education, a known non-active intervention. Daily sleep diaries will be
      completed during treatment using telephone interactive voice response to provide therapists
      with real-time, remote access to patient data. All treatment sessions will be audiotaped and
      reviewed by an independent rater for treatment fidelity. Participants will be assessed at
      baseline, 2 weeks following intervention, and every 3 months thereafter to the end of all
      data collection. Non-inferiority of clinical effectiveness will be expressed in terms of
      improvement in insomnia symptoms 6 months following completion of the intervention, as
      assessed by the Insomnia Severity Index (ISI). Detailed cost-effectiveness information will
      be collected over the entire observation period. A mixed-methods (qualitative and
      quantitative) formative evaluation will be conducted to examine differences between
      treatment groups in patient and provider perceptions and attitudes toward the two CBT-I
      interventions.

      Aim 1 (primary): To determine if Veterans with PTSD and chronic insomnia receiving CBT-I by
      video teleconferencing have an improvement in insomnia severity, as determined by change in
      ISI score, that is not clinically inferior to that in Veterans receiving in-person CBT-I.
      Improvements in ISI score will be compared between patients receiving CBT-I through video
      teleconferencing and through the in-person setting and between the CBT-I groups and a
      non-active control group.  Hypothesis 1: Six months following CBT-I treatment, the mean
      change in ISI score from baseline in Veterans receiving CBT-I by video teleconferencing will
      be no more than 1.67 smaller than the reference treatment, i.e., Veterans receiving
      in-person CBT-I. Since the expected mean difference in the active control group is -6.5,
      1.67 represents approximately 74% of retained efficacy for the test treatment. The observed
      lower bound will be used to determine the maximum reduction in efficacy consistent with the
      observed data.

      Aim 2 (secondary): To compare the differences in cost and quality-adjusted life years (QALY)
      between video teleconferencing and in-person delivery. Hypothesis 2a: Average total
      health-care delivery cost will be lower for Veterans receiving CBT-I by video
      teleconferencing compared to in-person encounter. Hypothesis 2b: The 90% upper limit of the
      cost per QALY ratio comparing video teleconferencing versus in-person encounter will be less
      than $100,000 (i.e., the investigators will have 90% confidence that it is good value for
      the cost).

      Aim 3 (secondary): To compare the effect of both modes of CBT-I delivery to sleep hygiene
      education on functional outcomes, sleep quality, and non-sleep-related PTSD severity.
      Functional outcomes will be assessed by the Short Form 12 (SF-12), and Work and Social
      Adjustment Scale. Sleep quality will be assessed by the sleep diary, wrist actigraphy, and
      Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI). Hypothesis 3a: At 6 months following CBT-I, Veterans
      who receive CBT-I by video teleconferencing or in-person delivery will have significantly
      greater improvements in functional outcomes and sleep quality compared to Veterans receiving
      the non-active intervention. Hypothesis 3b: Veterans receiving CBT-I (both groups) will have
      a significantly greater improvement in PTSD severity as assessed with the non-sleep items of
      the PTSD Checklist-Military (PCL-M).

      Aim 4 (exploratory): To conduct a mixed methods participant-oriented formative evaluation
      that will guide subsequent implementation of telemedicine delivery of CBT-I. Quantitative
      component: the investigators will track quantitative outcome measures across all 3 groups
      including attrition, therapeutic alliance (Working Alliance Inventory [WAI]), and treatment
      satisfaction and credibility (Charleston Psychiatric Outpatient Satisfaction Scale-VA
      [CPOSS-VA], and Treatment Credibility Scale). The investigators will estimate mean scores
      and simultaneous 95% confidence intervals to allow for inferential comparisons of WAI,
      CPOSS-VA, Treatment Credibility Scales, and attrition rates between all three treatment
      arms. Qualitative component: Through semi-structured individual interviews with providers
      and focus groups with patients from the two CBT-I intervention groups, the investigators
      will identify provider-level and patient-level perspectives, attitudes, and preferences
      regarding CBT-I delivered via video teleconferencing versus in-person, as well as barriers
      and facilitators to participation in either group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Insomnia Severity Index score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Wrist Actigraphy with sleep diary</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Objective measure of sleep pattern</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PTSD Checklist-Military (PCL-M)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measure of PTSD severity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SF-12</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>General quality of life assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Work and Social Adjustment Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subjective measure of sleep quality</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Working Alliance Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>2-8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Charleston Psychiatric Outpatient Satisfaction Scale-VA</measure>
    <time_frame>2-8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">225</enrollment>
  <condition>Sleep Initiation and Maintenance Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Post-Traumatic Stress Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CBT-I delivery by video teleconferencing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Groups of participants will receive a cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia program delivered by a trained psychologist using video teleconferencing.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>In-person CBT-I delivery</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Groups of participants will receive a cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia (CBT-I) program by meeting in-person with a trained psychologist.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia</intervention_name>
    <description>A behavioral modification program consisting of 6 clinic sessions focused on sleep hygiene, stimulus control, sleep restriction, and cognitive restructuring.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CBT-I delivery by video teleconferencing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>In-person CBT-I delivery</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CBT-I</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Veterans will have to meet the following inclusion criteria in order to be enrolled in
        this RCT:

          -  Men and women at least 18 years of age.

          -  Meet current DSM-IV-TR criteria for PTSD as determined by the Clinician Administered
             PTSD Scale (CAPS)

          -  Insomnia Severity Index score &gt; 14, the commonly used threshold for clinical
             insomnia, with self-reported duration of insomnia &gt;6 months.

          -  Ability to read and speak English (assessment instruments and therapy will be
             available only in English)

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Veterans will be excluded from participation if they meet any of the following exclusion
        criteria:

          -  Unable or unwilling to provide informed consent.

          -  Unwilling to participate in supervised group sessions at the community based
             outpatient clinic

          -  No telephone access or inability to return for follow-up testing.

          -  Individuals with an untreated sleep disorder [e.g., obstructive sleep apnea
             (apnea-hypopnea index   15 events/hr), periodic limb movement disorder (  10 leg
             movements/hr of sleep with arousals), central sleep apnea (  50% of apneas are
             central), Cheyne-Stokes respiration, obesity hypoventilation syndrome, and
             narcolepsy].

          -  A clinically unstable medical condition as defined by a new diagnosis or change in
             medical management in the previous 2 months.

          -  Evidence of substance dependence during the preceding twelve months. Evidence of &quot;at
             risk&quot; drinking behavior over the past month. Namely for men: more than 4 drinks on a
             given night, drinking on more than 3 nights a week, or more than 14 total drinks in a
             week; for women: more than 3 drinks in a given night, drinking on more than 3 nights
             a week, or more than 7 total drinks in a week.

          -  Individuals with bipolar disorder, delirium, dementia, amnestic disorder,
             schizophrenia and other psychotic disorders as determined by the SCID questionnaire.
             A concurrent anxiety disorder or depressive disorder diagnosis will be allowed.

          -  Individuals with prominent current suicidal or homicidal ideation. This will be
             assessed by the clinical psychologist administering the SCID and CAPS. In cases of
             prominent current suicidal or homicidal ideation appropriate safety measures will be
             taken. Following stabilization, Veterans who continue to be interested in
             participating in the study may be re-assessed.

          -  Unable to perform tests due to inability to communicate verbally, inability to read
             and write; less than a 5th grade reading level; visual, hearing or cognitive
             impairment (e.g., previous head injury).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Samuel T. Kuna, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Medical Center, Philadelphia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Samuel T Kuna, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(215) 823-5800</phone>
    <phone_ext>4400</phone_ext>
    <email>samuel.kuna@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Philip R Gehrman, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(215) 746-3578</phone>
    <email>philip.gehrman@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Medical Center, Philadelphia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Samuel T Kuna, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(215) 823-5800</phone>
      <phone_ext>4400</phone_ext>
      <email>samuel.kuna@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Philip R Gehrman, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(215) 746-3578</phone>
      <email>philip.gehrman@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jennifer Gala True, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Philip R. Gehrman, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Richard J. Ross, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Samuel T. Kuna, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 30, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 6, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cost effectiveness</keyword>
  <keyword>patient satisfaction</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Sleep Initiation and Maintenance Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Traumatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
