<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="115816">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01673568</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>123-SEROMA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01673568</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Abdominal Binder to Reduce Seroma Formation and Pain</brief_title>
  <acronym>SEROMA</acronym>
  <official_title>Postoperative Abdominal Binder in Reducing Seroma Formation and Pain After Ventral (Umbi/Epi) Hernia Repair.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hvidovre University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Copenhagen University Hospital at Herlev</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hvidovre University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Denmark: The Regional Committee on Biomedical Research Ethics</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Postoperative seroma formation is one of the most common complications after ventral hernia
      repair. Although some seromas may not have clinical impact, postoperative seroma formation
      often causes pain and discomfort and may even compromise wound healing. The use of
      postoperative abdominal binder is often recommended after ventral hernia repair to prevent
      seroma and diminish pain, but still with no scientific evidence. The primary aim of the
      present study is to investigate the effect of postoperative abdominal binders after
      laparoscopic ventral hernia repair on postoperative pain, discomfort and quality of life.
      Secondary, we register seroma formation.

      Method and material Randomized, controlled, multi-center, investigator-blinded study. 60
      patients (2X30 umbi/epi) are included, inclusion number is based on power calculations.
      Patients are randomized either to abdominal binder or no abdominal binder. The abdominal
      binder is worn from immediately after the operation and continuously for 7 days, night and
      day. Outcomes are based on patient self-reported registrations using Visual Analog Scales
      (VAS) and Carolina Comfort Scale (CCS), which is a validated, hernia-specific tool to
      estimate quality of life, pain and discomfort. Patients are followed-up for 30 days. For
      secondary outcome we use ultrasound to measure the volume of seroma formation. We use
      Mann-Witney, non-parametric statistics calculating the seroma formation and Friedmanns test
      for pain, discomfort and quality of life for the effect of time on inter- and intragroup
      differences during the study period. P &lt; 0.05 is considered significant.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Postoperative seroma formation is one of the most common complications after ventral hernia
      repair. Although some seromas may not have clinical impact postoperative seroma formation
      often causes pain and discomfort and may even compromise wound healing. Several
      interventional procedures have been investigated to reduce or avoid postoperative seroma
      formation such as removal of the hernia sac, VAC (vacuum-assisted closure) therapy, talcum
      application to the subcutaneous layer, suction etc., but results are conflicting and
      evidence is of poor quality. The use of postoperative abdominal binder is often recommended
      after ventral hernia repair to prevent seroma and diminish pain, but still with no
      scientific evidence. Randomized, controlled, multi-center, investigator-blinded study
      supplemented with blinded statistical analysis (see below). 60 patients (2 x 30, umbi/epi)
      Due to power calculations. An intention to treat analysis is done. . Patients are randomized
      either to abdominal binder or no abdominal binder. The abdominal binder is worn from
      immediately after the operation and continuously for 7 days, night and day. The belts are
      standard elastic belts (ostomy belts) from &quot;ETO garments©&quot; with standard height of 22 cm.
      and five different sizes in width (S, M, L, XL, XXL- depending on waist measure). A fitting
      will be done before the operation by waist measurement according to the recommendation from
      the company. Patients are followed-up for 30 days with clinical follow-up at day 7 and 30.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Investigator), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>pain</measure>
    <time_frame>1th postoperative day</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Outcome is based on patient self-reported registrations using Visual Analog Scales (VAS).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>seroma formation, fatigue, generel well-being, quality of life, movement limitations, and pain on day2,3,7 and 30.</measure>
    <time_frame>postoperative day 7</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Seroma formation measured on day 7 postoperatively with trans abdominal ultrasound scan (US). The method used in this study to estimate the volume of seroma is to measure the longitudinal section and cross section of the effusion and thereby calculating the volume.
Other outcomes are measured with VAS and Carolina Comfort scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">54</enrollment>
  <condition>Ventral Hernias</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>abdominal binder</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The abdominal binder is worn from immediately after the operation and continuously for 7 days, night and day. The belts are standard elastic belts (ostomy belts) from &quot;ETO garments©&quot; with standard height of 22 cm. and five different sizes in width (S, M, L, XL, XXL- depending on waist measure). A fitting will be done before the operation by waist measurement according to the recommendation from the company.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>no abdominal binder</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>no abdominal binder</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ETO garments</intervention_name>
    <description>patients wearing abdominal binder for 7 days postoperatively</description>
    <arm_group_label>abdominal binder</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>longuette</other_name>
    <other_name>ostomy belt</other_name>
    <other_name>trusses</other_name>
    <other_name>girdle</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Elective, primary and recurrent laparoscopic umbilical and epigastric hernia repair
             with mesh reinforcement

          -  Fascia defects 2-15 cm  measured preoperatively by the surgeon at the out-patient
             clinic for umbi/epi

          -  Elective, primary and recurrent laparoscopic trocar-site hernia

          -  Patients between 18-75 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Open ventral hernia repair

          -  Expected low compliance (language problems, dementia and abuse etc.)

          -  Fascia defects &gt;15 cm at the preoperative clinical examination.

          -  Acute operation

          -  Chronic pain syndrome

          -  Decompensated liver cirrhosis (Child-Pugh 3-4)

          -  Patients with a stoma

          -  If a secondary operation is performed during the hernia repair procedure
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thue Bisgaard, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital HVidovre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hvidovre Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hvidovre</city>
        <state>CPH</state>
        <zip>2650</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 23, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 4, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hvidovre University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mette Willaume Christoffersen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD. stud.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hernia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hernia, Ventral</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
