<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="166508">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01924598</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SC/13/0267</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01924598</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Study of Deep Brain Stimulation for Severe Anorexia Nervosa</brief_title>
  <official_title>Hungry for Reward :a Translational Study of Brain Processes Underpinning Anorexia Nervosa I: A Pilot Investigation of the Ethics, Practice and Neural Basis of Deep Brain Stimulation to the Nucleus Accumbens in Severe Intractible Anorexia Nervosa.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Councils UK</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Anorexia Nervosa (AN) has the highest mortality of any psychiatric disorder and a paucity of
      effective treatments. AN becomes intractable in around 20%, resulting in huge individual and
      healthcare costs. Exploration of underlying processes and novel treatment strategies is thus
      crucial. This is a pilot study of a novel translational approach to the investigation and
      treatment of severe AN. The aims are (1) to explore the safety, acceptability and
      feasibility of Deep Brain Stimulation (DBS) for AN (2) to map neural mechanisms underpinning
      aberrant reward and optimise DBS targets. The study will involve 3 consenting adults with
      full mental capacity, and will last 12 months. It incorporates an ethical substudy including
      assessment of capacity and informed consent. It combines complementary forms of cutting edge
      neuroimaging including DTI (diffusion tensor imaging), fMRI and MEG
      (magnetoencephalography). These will be complimentary in helping identify the best strategy
      for treating severe AN using DBS. Individuals with severe intractable AN will be eligible to
      take part. The study will be conducted in Oxford, United Kingdom at the John Radcliffe and
      Warneford Hospitals. The individuals will have preoperative ethical, neuroimaging and
      psychological assessments, then DBS to the Nucleus accumbens, followed by a 9 month followup
      period with 6-weekly joint neurosurgical psychiatric and psychological assessments and
      3-monthly MEG scans. The study will further our understanding of food reward processes in
      general and AN in particular indeed promises to provide important information which may
      revolutionize future treatments. The proposal builds upon a body of research investigating
      the role of aberrant reward processes in AN and exploits our complementary research
      experience in AN using experimental behavioural strategies (Park), fMRI (Harmer), MEG
      (Nobre) and DBS &amp; DTI (Aziz) to establish a powerful translational research strategy. The
      study is part of an MRC programme and linked with a separate casecontrol multimodal imaging
      study generating mutually informative data.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Our hypothesis, based on prior research, is that DBS to the nucleus accumbens will have
      beneficial neural and symptomatic effects in severe Anorexia Nervosa.

      As a pilot test of this hypothesis, and to evaluate acceptability and ethical issues we aim
      to initially study 3 patients.

      This pilot study may provide important clinical and scientific information to contribute to
      larger studies.

      DESIGN SUMMARY The design will consist of a case series of 3 patients with repeated
      measures. The individuals will be females aged 20-65 with at least 7 years history of severe
      treatment resistant AN, who are fully consenting and motivated to recover.

      The patients will be selected on the basis of specific suitability criteria. A small case
      series study design is needed as this is a novel and invasive strategy, and further
      information about acceptability, feasibility and neural processes involved is required to
      inform more extensive studies. This can optimally be obtained by initial detailed study of a
      small number of patients. As some heterogeneity of response is likely, as advised by our
      external reviewer Professor Walter Kaye, we are aiming to study 3 patients rather than a
      single patient pilot.

      The intervention will be bilateral deep brain stimulation targeted at the nucleus accumbens
      with stimulation at the ventral anterior limb of the internal capsule. Following DBS each
      patient will be followed up every 6 weeks for 9 months.

      First, after recruitment there will be a thorough preoperative examination of ethical issues
      including qualitative and semi structured interviews (MacCATCR (MacArthur Competence
      Assessment Tool for Clinical Research))to assess competence and informed consent will be
      completed by an independent researcher experienced in ethical issues in AN (Jacinta Tan).

      The study participants will then be have the initial research assessment and will be
      reviewed every 6 weeks in joint eating disorders psychiatry -neurosurgery clinics with a 6
      week pre-op observational phase followed by a post-op double blind crossover design with
      randomly assigned 6 week periods of active or sham stimulation, over a total 9 month
      follow-up period.

      6 weekly assessments will include :

        -  BMI

        -  Semi structured interviews : Eating Disorder Eating Disorder Examination (EDE)

        -  Yale Brown CornellEating Disorder Scale (YBCEDS)

        -  Observer rated comorbidity (SCID / Hamilton Depression rating scale)

        -  Computerized behavioural tasks: Food reward (Leeds-Oxford food preference task)
           reversal learning and habit formation tasks

        -  Self report schedules: EDE Questionnaire, functional impairment (CIA) , quality of life
           scale (WHOQUALBREF); starvation dependence scale, Beck Depression Inventory (BDI, Beck
           et al. 1961), the State Trait Anxiety Inventory (Spielberger, 1998), the
           Snaith-Hamilton pleasure scale (SHAPS, Snaith et al. 1995) and the Ruminative Response
           Scale for Eating Disorders (RRSED). Pre-operative imaging will involve fMRI , DTI and
           MEG. Post-operative imaging will involve MEG and DTI at 3, 6 and 9 months.

      DETAILS OF METHODOLOGY:

      Subjects selection and recruitment:

      A list of eligible patients, fulfilling inclusion and exclusion criteria will be made in
      discussion with NHS Oxfordshire Specialist Eating Disorder services clinicians. Patients
      will be ranked in order of suitability according to specific suitability criteria:

      i. Severity and intractablity of Anorexia Nervosa ii. Restrictive anorexia nervosa - without
      binging/purging iii. Absence of currently severe comorbid Obsessive Compulsive Disorder
      (OCD), depression or self-harm iv. Ideally on no, or minimal Psychotropic medication v. No
      recent history of compulsory treatment ( i.e. in the last year) vi. Has tried existing
      treatment options without success vii. Has never had periods of full remission viii.
      Intensity of desire to recover ix. Good intellectual function and education - well able to
      comprehend the facts of the intervention (e.g. healthcare background, university education)
      x. Poor social and occupational function, high levels of distress - not functioning well,
      having poor quality of life.

      The highest ranked patients will be asked if they consent to receiving information about the
      project. If they are interested they will be approached by Dr Park with information about
      the project, given an information sheet and the opportunity to discuss with family members.
      If they remain interested they be will be offered the opportunity to meet with Dr Park and
      Professor Aziz, for further information and to address questions , and involve their family
      if they wish. Following this they will be reviewed by Dr Park a week later and thus given a
      up to week to decide if they would like to participate. Consent to participate in the
      project will be taken by Dr Park and can be freely withdrawn at any point with no effect on
      their usual clinical care. Throughout the study the patients will receive supportive
      treatment as usual from the clinical team who will be independent from the research team,
      and it will be made clear they can opt out of the study at any point without having to give
      explanations.

      If the patient consents to participation they will have preoperative assessments in the
      University Research Department at the Warneford hospital:

      I: PREOPERATIVE PHASE: 1 month

        1. Initial assessment with the Research team.

             -  BMI: height and weight

             -  Semi structured interviews of Eating Disorder and comorbidity: EDE, SCID , Yale
                Brown Cornell Eating Disorder Scale (YBCEDS) ; Self-reported questionnaires as
                above indexing mood and quality of life

             -  Computerized behavioural tasks: Leeds Oxford food preference task, habit formation
                tasks

        2. Weekly Self report measures of symptoms done at home, weekly (5 minutes) using the
           'True Colours' Text messaging system pioneered at the University of Oxford Department
           of Psychiatry, adapted for Eating disorders by Dr Rebecca Park including the OXBREAD
           brief rating scale. http://oxtext.psych.ox.ac.uk/truecolours. This self report system
           will continue from entry to the study end.

        3. Preoperative phase. A: Capacity and ethical assessment

             -  Once a suitable patient is identified, and consented , Dr Jacinta Tan will
                interview the patient independently to do a full MacCATCR assessment plus in depth
                interview to explore the patient's experience of treatment, rationale for
                participation and motivations for taking part in research.

             -  The interview will also explore the ethical issues concerning this research from
                the participants' perspective

             -  The assessment is expected to take 2.5-3 hours and can be done in sections if the
                patient tires. It will be tape recorded and transcribed. Jacinta Tan will score
                the MacCATCR and an independent observer will also score the MacCATCR. Both will
                also provide global assessments of capacity to consent to research.

             -  Dr Tan will provide a detailed report of the interview and her assessment of
                ethical acceptability of participation for that individual. If she decides the
                patient is not suitable, the process will be repeated with the next individual on
                the list who agrees.

             -  In the interview before the surgery, Jacinta Tan will explore with the participant
                ethical issues that surround the research.

        4. Neuroimaging:

           Preoperatively each patient will have:

             -  a whole brain MRI scan including T1, T2, Inversion Recovery and DTI sequences and
                fMRI in resting state and task based using our food reward task: These scans will
                occur at the John Radcliffe Hospital , Oxford, duration 1 hour.

             -  a whole brain MEG scan- resting state and task based food reward task , which will
                be done at the Warneford Hospital, Oxford, duration 30 minutes.

        5. Medical optimisation: patients will have normalisation of electrolytes and ECG prior to
           being considered fit for the operation. They will need to be a BMI of&gt; 13

      II OPERATIVE PHASE: Month 2. The DBS operation will require a 4 day inpatient stay at the
      John Radcliffe Hospital On the day of surgery, the patient will be anaesthetised and the
      base ring fixed to the skull and a CT scan performed with a localiser fixed to the ring. The
      patient will then be transferred to theatre and the scalp cleansed. By fusing the structural
      MRI scan to the stereotactic CT scan the trajectory to implant electrodes into the nucleus
      accumbens bilaterally will be calculated. Then through bilateral scalp incisions and a twist
      drill skull perforation, deep brain electrodes will be passed to target bilaterally and
      fixed to the skull with titanium mini plates. The scalp will then be closed and a repeat
      stereotactic CT scan will be obtained to confirm electrode placement. Having done so, back
      in theatre the electrodes will be connected to extension cables that will then be passed
      subcutaneously down one side of the head, behind the ear to a subcutaneous pouch below the
      collar bone and connected to a rechargeable pacemaker and all the wounds closed.

      The day after surgery, the pacemaker will be turned on to ascertain any acute effects of
      stimulation. Having done so the patient will be discharged two days after implant to be
      assessed six weeks after implant when all wounds are healed and any acute effects of
      stimulation have worn off.

      III: POST OPERATIVE FOLL0WUP PHASE: Months 2-9 In the first post operative 6 weeks the
      stimulator will remain off. Following that there will be post-op blind crossover design with
      6 week periods of active or sham stimulation,over a total 9 month followup period. Patient
      and research assistant will remain blind to condition. Post operative assessments, aiming to
      track the neural and symptomatic change as a result of DBS will involve:

        1. Continuation of weekly self report rating scale of eating disorder, anxiety and
           depression involving the True Colours text messaging system started in phase I:
           http://oxtext.psych.ox.ac.uk/truecolours (5 minutes)

        2. 6-weekly reviews (2.5 hours) in the Department of Psychiatry  incorporating:

             -  Interview with the research assistant and DPhil student:

      BMI, Semi structured interviews including Eating Disorder Eating Disorders Examination
      (EDE), YaleBrownCornell Eating Disorder Scale (YBCEDS), and comorbid psychopathology (SCID).
      Behavioural paradigms: food reward (Oxford-Leeds food preference task, habit formation task;
      Self report schedules as in phase 1 assessing eating disorder symptoms, starvation
      dependence, functional impairment (CIA) and quality of life.

      • Joint Neurosurgery-Psychiatric reviews with Professor Aziz and Dr Park: During this review
      neurosurgical parameters such as the degree of stimulation, and psychiatric parameters such
      as experience of eating disorder and co-morbid psychiatric symptoms will be jointly
      assessed. Any necessary adjustments to stimulator intensity will then be programmed.

      Post-operative neuroimaging at 3, 6, and 9 months:

        -  DTI scan (fMRIB), John Radcliffe Hospital: 30 minutes

        -  MEG scan resting state and task based: food reward task based: (LO food preference task
           (Warneford Hospital) 30 minutes

           4. Optional Ethics sub-study: In a  single 2.5 hour session with each individual after
           surgery Dr Jacinta Tan will explore with the participant ethical issues that surround
           the research. Using a similar interview prior to the surgery, Dr Tan will elicit from
           the participant his/her experience of participation, his/her reflections on this, and
           also views in hindsight of the ethical issues surrounding the research.

        -  At the end of the study it will thus be possible to produce a detailed report of the
           ethics of the research, including the participant's perspective of the research
           experience
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events associated with surgery or stimulation</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months post operatively</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Eating Disorder pathology</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Global EDE Score</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Eating Disorder Pathology</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>BMI</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comorbid psychiatric symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>anxiety, depression, obsessionality</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Food Reward processing</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Ventral striatal response to hi vs low cal food pics as measured by fMRI</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Habit formation (adapted 'fabulous fruit task')</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Habit formation as indexed by persistence of response to devalued contingencies</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MEG 'Resting State Network'</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Neural changes pre-post DBS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>White matter integrity-DTI</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Food Reward processing</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Leeds-Oxford food preference task: ' implicit 'wanting' of low vs hi cal foods, as indexed by reaction times to hi vs low cal food pictures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Habit formation(noise avoidance task)</measure>
    <time_frame>9 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Habit formation as indexed by persistence of response to devalued stimuli</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3</enrollment>
  <condition>Severe Intractable Anorexia Nervosa</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Deep Brain Stimulation to nucleus accumbens/anterior limb of internal capsule</intervention_name>
    <description>6 week blocks of single blind periods of sham or active deep brain stimulation over 9 month post operative followup</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        1. Primary diagnosis: Anorexia Nervosa according to the DSMIV (Diagnostic and Statistical
        Manual of Mental Disorders Fourth Edition)criteria based on a psychiatric interview; 2.
        Illness duration of severe AN &gt; 7 years. 3. Disabling severity with substantial functional
        impairment 4. Female Gender and right handed 5. Treatment refractoriness, defined as lack
        of response to two or more typical modes of treatment, such as inpatient weight
        restoration, psychotherapy and psychopharmacology; 6. Severely underweight: BMI &gt;13 &lt;16 7.
        Age: 20-65 years old; 8. Written informed consent; 9. Able to fully understand the
        consequences of the procedure; 10. English speaking and able to answer the study questions
        fluently 11. Having the mental capacity to make provide informed consent to research
        participation.

        -

        Exclusion Criteria:1. Unstable physical condition (severe electrolyte disturbances,
        cardiac failure, other physical conditions due to underweight in which surgery/anaesthesia
        is contraindicated).

        2. Treatable underlying cause of anorexia/underweight. 3. Parkinson's disease, dementia,
        epilepsy. 4. History of schizophrenia/ psychosis, bipolar disorder. 5. Alcohol or
        substance abuse (including benzodiazepines) during the last 6 months.

        6. Current severe major depressive or Tic disorder. 7. Antisocial or Severe Borderline
        Personality Disorder. 8. Standard MRI scan exclusion criteria (pregnancy, pacemaker and
        metals contraindicated for MRI except for the DBS implantation and stimulator itself).

        9. Current Involuntary patient

        -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tipu Aziz, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Oxford</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rebecca Park, MD Phd</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Oxford</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rebecca Park, MD PhD MRCPSych</last_name>
    <email>rebecca.park@psych.ox.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tipu Aziz, MD FRCPsyc FMed Sci</last_name>
    <email>tipu.aziz@nds.ox.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oxford Health NHS foundation trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oxford</city>
        <state>Oxfordshire</state>
        <zip>OX37JX</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rebecca J Park, MDPhD</last_name>
      <email>rebecca.park@psych.ox.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jessica Scaife, PhD</last_name>
      <email>jessica.scaife@psych.ox.ac.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rebecca j Park, MDPhd</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.psych.ox.ac.uk/research/brain-eating-disorders</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 14, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 22, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Anorexia Nervosa</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment Development</keyword>
  <keyword>Capacity</keyword>
  <keyword>Neuroimaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Magnetoencephalography</keyword>
  <keyword>Diffusion Tensor Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>functional MRI</keyword>
  <keyword>Reward processing</keyword>
  <keyword>Habit formation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anorexia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anorexia Nervosa</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
