<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="107517">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01821963</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012-0977</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01821963</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Telaprevir Plus Standard of Care (SOC) in HCV Associated Hepatocellular Carcinoma (HCC)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Telaprevir in Combination With Standard of Care in Hepatitis C Genotype 1 Infection in Patients With Hepatocellular Carcinoma Awaiting Liver Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Vertex Pharmaceuticals Incorporated</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn if the antiviral combination of
      telaprevir, pegylated Interferon Alfa 2a (PegIFN alfa-2a) and ribavirin (RBV) can prevent
      the virus from coming back after the liver transplant.

      Telaprevir, PegIFN alfa-2a, and RBV are different antiviral drugs that work in combination
      at different stages of the HCV infection to stop the virus.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Drug Administration:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will take telaprevir 3 times
      a day.  You will take RVB by mouth 2 times a day.  You will receive PEGIFN alfa-2a by an
      injection under the skin 1 time a week.

      Study Visits:

      On the first day you take the study drug:

        -  You will have an eye exam performed by the study doctor.

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your vital signs (blood
           pressure, heart rate, temperature, and breathing rate).

        -  Blood (about 2 teaspoons) will be drawn for routine tests and to check for the
           hepatitis virus.

        -  You will be asked about any drugs you are taking or side effects you may be having.

      Every Week while you are on study:

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your vital signs.

        -  Blood (about 2 teaspoons) will be drawn for routine tests and to check for the
           hepatitis C virus.  If part of the blood sample is left over after the Hepatitis C
           testing, it will be stored in the laboratory as a back-up sample, in case the original
           samples get lost. This sample may also be used to check if the Hepatitis C virus has
           become resistant to the study drug. No extra blood will be drawn for this storage.

        -  You will be asked about any drugs you are taking or side effects you may be having.

        -  At Weeks 12, 24, 36, and 42, urine will be collected to check for infection and any
           other side effects to the drugs.

      If you can become pregnant, you will have a urine pregnancy test every 4 weeks

      Length of Treatment:

      You may continue receiving the antiviral therapy for up to 48 weeks, as long as the doctor
      thinks it is in your best interest.  You will no longer be able to take the study drug if
      the disease gets worse, if intolerable side effects occur, or if you are unable to follow
      study directions.

      Your participation on the study will be over after the follow-up visits.

      Follow-Up Visits:

      Beginning the day after you stop taking antiviral therapy (or the day of transplantation,
      whichever comes first), you will have up to 24 weeks of follow-up testing performed.  About
      4 and 20 weeks after your last dose:

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your vital signs.

        -  Blood (about 2 teaspoons) will be drawn for routine tests and to check for the
           hepatitis C virus.

        -  You will be asked about any side effects you may be having.

        -  At week 4 only, urine will be collected to check for infection and any other side
           effects to the drugs.

      This is an investigational study.  Telaprevir, PegIFN alfa-2a, and RBV are all FDA approved
      and commercially available for the treatment of  HCV infection. The use of these drugs in
      preventing the HCV infection is investigational.

      Up to 40 patients will take part in this study.  All will be enrolled at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Low Referral
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Undetectable Viral Load</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary endpoint is undetectable viral load at 12 weeks post-transplant (Post-transplant virological response - PTVR). In order to have undetectable HCV RNA viral load after transplant, patients need to have undetectable viral load before the liver transplant. Primary analysis for undetectable viral load at 12 weeks post-transplant response rate based on the modified intent-to-treat (ITT) population. The modified ITT population defined as those patients who have achieved an undetectable HCV-RNA level before the transplant. If patients drop out the study early due to severe toxicity or treatment failure including treatment-related death, they will be counted as non-responders when evaluating the response rate.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sustained Virological Response (SVR)</measure>
    <time_frame>60 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Sustained virological response (SVR) defined as a single undetectable HCV-RNA measurement 12 weeks after the 48-week treatment period for those still waiting for transplantation. The treatment duration will be summarized with descriptive statistics. Additional analyses based on evaluable patients also conducted regarding the PTVR response rate. The evaluable patients are defined as those patients who complete at least 16 weeks of treatment and have the 12 weeks post-transplant response measurement. The rate will also be computed stratified by the HCV treatment time (i.e., the 48-week HCV treatment versus less than 48 week HCV treatment) considering the different times under HCV. The SVR rate will be estimated, along with the exact 95% confident interval.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1</enrollment>
  <condition>Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pegylated Interferon Alfa 2a +  Ribavirin + Telaprevir</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Triple combination with Telaprevir, PegIFN alfa-2a and Ribavirin administered for 12 weeks, followed by dual therapy with PegIFN alfa-2a and Ribavirin. Dual therapy continued for 48 weeks of total duration of therapy, as standard of care treatment for cirrhotic patients, or until day of transplantation, whichever comes first. Starting doses for standard of care pegylated interferon (PegIFN) alfa-2a 180 mcg subcutaneously once weekly, for ribavirin (RBV) 1,000 mg orally daily (&lt; 75 kg) and 1,200 mg orally daily (≥ 75 kg), and for telaprevir 750 mg taken orally 3 times a day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pegylated Interferon Alfa 2a</intervention_name>
    <description>Starting dose: 180 mcg subcutaneously once weekly.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pegylated Interferon Alfa 2a +  Ribavirin + Telaprevir</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PegIFN</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ribavirin</intervention_name>
    <description>Starting dose: 1,000 mg by mouth daily.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pegylated Interferon Alfa 2a +  Ribavirin + Telaprevir</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Telaprevir</intervention_name>
    <description>Starting dose: 750 mg by mouth 3 times a day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pegylated Interferon Alfa 2a +  Ribavirin + Telaprevir</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Incivek</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Males or females aged ≥ 18 and ≤ 70 years

          2. Detectable Hepatitis C Virus ribonucleic acid (HCV-RNA) in serum

          3. HCV genotype 1 infection

          4. Child-Pugh-Turcotte (CPT) score &lt; 7 and Model for End-Stage Liver Disease (MELD)
             score &lt; 18

          5. PegIFN alfa-2a/RBV-naïve or previously treated patients (partial responders, null
             responders and relapsers)

          6. Hepatocellular carcinoma within transplant criteria in the United Network for Organ
             Sharing (UNOS) Region IV:

               1. Single lesion up to 6 cm, or

               2. Two or three lesions with largest no greater than 5 cm and the total tumor
                  diameter no greater than 9 cm

          7. Listed for liver transplantation

          8. Willingness to give written consent and agree to double contraception

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Decompensated cirrhosis

          2. Baseline platelet count less than 35,000/µL

          3. Baseline hemoglobin level less than 10 g/dL

          4. Baseline absolute neutrophil count less than 750/mm3

          5. Baseline creatinine clearance &lt; 50 mL per min.

          6. Women with a positive pregnancy test at baseline or men whose female partners are
             pregnant or are contemplating pregnancy

          7. Intolerance or contraindications to PegIFN alfa-2a/RBV use per standard treatment
             guidelines
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>69 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Harrys A. Torres, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas  MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 27, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatitis C Genotype 1 Infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatitis C virus</keyword>
  <keyword>HCV</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatocellular Carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>HCC</keyword>
  <keyword>Liver Transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>Pegylated Interferon Alfa 2a</keyword>
  <keyword>PegIFN alfa-2a</keyword>
  <keyword>Ribavirin</keyword>
  <keyword>RBV</keyword>
  <keyword>Telaprevir</keyword>
  <keyword>Incivek</keyword>
  <keyword>Antiviral drugs</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Interferon-alpha</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Interferon Alfa-2a</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Interferons</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ribavirin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peginterferon alfa-2a</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
