<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="151272">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01806389</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NA_00080884</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01806389</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Breastfeeding in Buprenorphine Maintained Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Lactation Among Buprenorphine Maintained Women: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Goals: The overarching goals for this proposed research are to provide pilot data for a
      study to inform the FDA regarding the safety of breastfeeding infants of mothers on
      buprenorphine maintenance and to develop guidelines for the practitioner treating
      buprenorphine maintained women who wish to breastfeed.

      Background: There is an increase in the prevalence of illicit opiate use among women of
      childbearing age. Recently, a large multisite study has suggested buprenorphine as an
      alternative to methadone for use in this population. As a consequence, buprenorphine is
      likely to be delivered to larger populations of pregnant and post-partum women. The
      population of prenatally opioid-exposed neonates is a particularly vulnerable population.
      Advances in neuroscience, molecular biology and epigenetics indicate that greater attention
      should be given to strategies that prevent, reduce, or mitigate the consequences of
      significant adversity on the developing brain. Breast milk and breastfeeding offer
      significant health and other benefits that are particularly salient for this group. Today,
      there is a near complete lack of information regarding the safety of buprenorphine
      maintenance and lactation, making it unlikely that providers will endorse or mothers will
      adopt this practice.

      Methods: Five pregnant buprenorphine maintained breastfeeding women and their neonates will
      be enrolled. Subjects will selected by buprenorphine maintenance in the postpartum period
      and enrollment in a parent protocol and by decision to breast feed their infants. Subject
      will provide breast milk at times of peak maternal buprenorphine levels on days 2, 3, 4, 14
      and 30 after delivery to determine buprenorphine and norbuprenorphine concentrations.
      Subjects will also provide plasma at times of peak buprenorphine levels for determination of
      buprenorphine and norbuprenorphine concentrations on the same days. Concentrations of
      buprenorphine and norbuprenorphine in the plasma of infants will be determined on
      approximately day 14 of life. The relationship between maternal dose, maternal and infant
      plasma concentrations, and breast milk concentrations of buprenorphine and norbuprenorphine
      will be determined, and ingestible infant dose calculated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study would recruit participants from a funded trial evaluating fetal neurobehavior and
      maternal physiology among a population of opioid dependent and buprenorphine maintained
      pregnant women. Those women electing to breastfeed will be approached for participation in
      this study at 36 weeks of gestation.

      Study Procedures Study participants will have urine toxicology testing for the following
      drug classes/cut off values: cocaine/300 ng/mL; methamphetamines/1000ng/mL;
      methadone/300ng/mL; MDMA/500 ng/mL; MOP/300 ng/mL; oxycodone/100 ng/mL; PCP/25 ng/mL;
      benzodiazepines/300ng/mL; buprenorphine/10 ng/mL; marijuana/50ng/mL weekly as part of study
      procedures in addition to weekly random urine toxicology screening provided at CAP for the
      study period of 36 weeks until delivery. To ensure that participants are not using illicit
      substances or abusing licit substances and are candidates for the institution and
      continuation of breastfeeding, subjects will continue to provide urine toxicology testing as
      above for the period of time from delivery to day 30 postpartum. Subjects noted to be doing
      so will be discharged from the protocol and referred to their substance abuse treatment
      counselor for appropriate consequences.

      Data collection protocol: Upon delivery, the nursing staff at the hospital of delivery will
      contact study staff for initiation of study procedures. Women will have plasma and breast
      milk samples obtained by study personnel on days 2, 3, 4, 14 and 30 at times of peak (2 ½
      hours after sublingual dosing) maternal buprenorphine levels. Infant weight will be
      collected on these days. Days of data collection will be determined by the, 2nd, 3rd, 4th 24
      hour periods after birth of the infant.  The 14th, and 30th day data collections will occur
      on the weekday nearest the 24 hour period on those days. Infant NICU Network Neurobehavioral
      Scale scores on days 3, 14 and 30 and infant NAS scores as below are collected as part of
      the parent protocol and data abstracted for this protocol.

      Maternal plasma: Using 3mL vacutainer green-top collection tubes, 3 cc of blood will be
      collected via venupuncture by one of two study RNs, one responsible for inpatient specimen
      collection (i.e. while the mother and infant are hospitalized after delivery) and one
      responsible for outpatient specimen collection (after hospital discharge). Blood samples
      will be collected on ice and within two hours, cold centrifuged to harvest the plasma.
      Plasma will be stored in polypropylene tubes and stored at -20°C. Plasma will be collected
      at times of peak maternal buprenorphine levels on days 2, 3, 4, 14 (approximately) and 30
      (approximately) after infant delivery.

      Breast milk: Breast milk samples will be collected after the infant has completed feeding
      from the same breast via electric pump and consist of approximately 5 cc of breast milk at
      time of peak maternal buprenorphine levels on days 2,3,4, 14 and 30 after infant delivery.
      Breast milk will be stored at -20°C within two hours of collection.

      Analysis of breast milk and plasma samples: Plasma and breast milk samples will be analyzed
      by the Chemistry and Drug Metabolism Section of the Intramural Research Program of the
      National Institute on Drug Abuse, National Institutes of Health in Baltimore, Maryland under
      the direction of Dr. Marilyn A. Huestis.

      Infant plasma: 1cc of infant blood will be taken by heel stick on the weekday nearest day 14
      of life. The 14 day blood sample will be coincident with a routine infant blood test (PKU
      testing) when possible. Blood samples will be collected on ice and within two hours, cold
      centrifuged to remove plasma. Plasma will be stored in polypropylene tubes and stored at
      -20°C until analysis.

      Other infant data: Infant weight will be obtained at each data collection point (i.e. days
      2,3,4, 14 and 30).

      Other maternal data: Maternal compliance to drug treatment will be abstracted from daily
      treatment records. Poor compliance to treatment will be determined on an individual basis
      via discussion with the subject's counselor, but in general compliance will be determined by
      attendance to daily therapy at CAP with no unexcused or unexplained absence from treatment
      in the 30 days subsequent to delivery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in maternal plasma concentrations of buprenorphine</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 2,3,4,14 and 30 after delivery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Maternal plasma will be obtained at the time of peak buprenorphine levels on days 2,3,4,14 and 30</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in maternal breast milk concentrations of buprenorphine</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 2,3,4,14 and 30 after delivery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Breast milk will be obtained on these days at the time of peak plasma levels of buprenoprhine</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Infant plasma concentrations of buprenorphine</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14 of life</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Infant plasma will be obtaqined on day 14 of life</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Opioid Dependency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Buprenorphine</arm_group_label>
    <description>Buprenorphine maintained women at delivery of their infant</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Maternal urine, plasma and breast milk INnfant plasma
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Five buprenorphine maintained women who deliver and infant and desire to breastfeed
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 18-41 years

          2. Opioid dependent per DSMIVR criteria, buprenorphine maintained, enrolled in parent
             study.

          3. Delivery at 37 weeks of gestation or later

          4. Breast feeding in the first month of life

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Concurrent Axis I diagnosis, or the presence of a serious psychiatric illness that
             would preclude informed consent

          2. Major congenital malformation or minor congenital malformation that would impair the
             infant's ability to feed (i.e. Pierre-Robin syndrome, cleft palate)

          3. Delivery at an outside institution unaffiliated with this protocol

          4. Failure to leave specimens as per protocol

          5. Infant medical complications that impair the ability to feed after delivery (i.e.
             respiratory concerns such as meconium aspiration, perinatal asphyxia, etc. These will
             be individually determined on a case-by-case basis)

          6. Any detected maternal medical condition making lactation inadvisable, i.e. newly
             diagnosed HIV infection or requirement for medication not compatible with
             breastfeeding.

          7. Infants with other medical conditions that would make study participation impossible,
             i.e. nonviable neonates, neonates with uncertain viability.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>41 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lauren M Jansson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 12, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 20, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lauren M. Jansson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Pediatrics Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast milk</keyword>
  <keyword>Breastfeeding</keyword>
  <keyword>Lactation</keyword>
  <keyword>Buprenorphine</keyword>
  <keyword>Opioid</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Buprenorphine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
