<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="67005">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01738139</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012-0784</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-00030</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01738139</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ipilimumab and Imatinib Mesylate in Advanced Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Trial of Ipilimumab (Immunotherapy) and Imatinib Mesylate (c-Kit Inhibitor) in Patients With Advanced Malignancies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to find the highest tolerable dose of the
      combination of ipilimumab and imatinib that can be given to patients with advanced cancer.
      The safety of this drug combination will also be studied.

      Ipilimumab is designed to increase the immune system's ability to fight cancer.

      Imatinib is designed to bind to certain proteins on the tumor cells, which may prevent the
      cells from growing.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Groups:

      Dose Escalation Group:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will be assigned to a dose
      level of your study drug combination based on when you joined this study.  Up to 4 dose
      levels of the study drug combination will be tested.  Up to 6 participants will be enrolled
      at each dose level.  The first group of participants will receive the lowest dose level.
      Each new group will receive a higher dose than the group before it, if no intolerable side
      effects were seen.  This will continue until the highest tolerable dose of the study drug
      combination is found.

      Dose Expansion Group:

      After the highest tolerable dose level of the study drug combination is found, up to 20
      additional participants will be enrolled in the dose expansion group. Patients with
      metastatic gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GIST), melanoma, or tumors with original tumor
      biopsies testing positive for KIT mutations (a cancer biomarker) will be eligible to enroll
      and will receive the highest dose of the study drug combination that was tolerated in the
      dose escalation group.

      Study Drug Administration:

      If you are in the Dose Escalation Group, the first study cycle is 35 days.  Each cycle after
      that is 21 days.

      If you are in the Dose Expansion Group, all study cycles are 21 days.

      If you are in the Dose Escalation Group, you will start taking imatinib by mouth 1 time each
      day for 14 days before you receive ipilimumab.  On Day 15 of each cycle, you will receive a
      single dose of ipilimumab by vein over 90 minutes.  You will continue to take imatinib by
      mouth 1 time each day.

      If you are in the Dose Expansion Group, you will receive ipilimumab by vein over 90 minutes
      on Day 15 of each cycle.  You will also take imatinib by mouth 1 time each day of each
      cycle.

      Study Visits:

      One (1) time each week during Cycle 1:

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your weight and vital signs.

        -  You will be asked about any drugs you may be taking and any side effects you may be
           having.

        -  Blood (about 1 tablespoon) will be collected for routine tests.

        -  Urine will be collected for routine tests (only during the first week of Cycle 1).

      Every 3 weeks during Cycles 2 and beyond:

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your weight and vital signs.

        -  Blood (about 1 tablespoon) and urine will be collected for routine tests.

      Starting after Cycle 2:

        -  You will have a CT or MRI scan after every 2 cycles to check the status of the disease.

        -  If you are able to become pregnant, you will have a blood (about 1 teaspoon) or urine
           pregnancy test.

      Length of Study:

      You may continue taking the study drugs for as long as the doctor thinks it is in your best
      interest.  You will no longer be able to take the study drugs if the disease gets worse, if
      intolerable side effects occur, or if you are unable to follow study directions.

      This is an investigational study.  Ipilimumab is FDA approved and commercially available for
      the treatment of unresectable or metastatic melanoma.  Imatinib is FDA approved and
      commercially available for the treatment of advanced or metastatic gastrointestinal stromal
      tumor (GIST).

      The combination of ipilimumab and imatinib is currently being used for research purposes
      only.

      Up to 96 participants will take part in this study.  All will be enrolled at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD) of Ipilimumab and Imatinib Mesylate</measure>
    <time_frame>56 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) defined as highest dose level with less than 2 patients with dose limiting toxicity (DLT) out of at least six patients in the cohort.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">96</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Cancers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ipilimumab + Imatinib Mesylate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The dose escalation portion of this study will consist of an initial daily oral administration of imatinib mesylate 400 mg alone for 14 days. A single Ipilimumab treatment 1 mg/kg given on day 15 will be added to daily imatinib mesylate therapy. Dose escalation group first study cycle is 35 days.  Each cycle after that is 21 days. This study has an expansion cohort using the MTD determined by the dose escalation study to treat patients with KITconfirmed GIST, melanoma, and uncategorized solid tumors. Both studies will consist of a screening visit and continuous 21-day treatment cycles. Cycles will be repeated every 21 days for 4 cycles until disease progression or development of intolerable toxicities, and a post-treatment visit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ipilimumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Dose Escalation Group Starting Dose: 1 mg/kg by vein on day 15. The first study cycle is 35 days.  Each cycle after that is 21 days.
Dose Expansion Group Starting Dose:  MTD from Dose Escalation Group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ipilimumab + Imatinib Mesylate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Yervoy</other_name>
    <other_name>BMS-734016</other_name>
    <other_name>MDX010</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Imatinib Mesylate</intervention_name>
    <description>Dose Escalation Group Starting Dose: 400 mg by mouth once per day for 35 days. The first study cycle is 35 days. Each cycle after that is 21 days.
Dose Expansion Group Starting Dose: MTD from Dose Escalation Group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ipilimumab + Imatinib Mesylate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Imatinib</other_name>
    <other_name>Gleevec</other_name>
    <other_name>STI 571</other_name>
    <other_name>NSC-716051</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. For dose escalation study, patients must have histological confirmation of solid
             tumors that is metastatic or unresectable. For expansion cohorts, patients must have
             metastatic or unresectable GIST, melanoma, or uncategorized tumors that are positive
             for c-KIT mutations. KIT positive tumors will be confirmed in original biopsied
             tumors and biopsied tumors acquired during this study. This analysis will be done by
             CLIA approved mutational analysis which will likely include isolation of genomic DNA
             from tumor, polymerase chain reaction (PCR) amplification of exons of interest of
             c-KIT gene, bidirectional sequencing of PCR amplicons, and computational analysis of
             sequences to determine mutation presence or absence.

          2. Patients who have completed previous therapies 4-weeks prior to (or within 5 drug
             half lives) enrollment on study. Radiation therapy wash out period will be 2 weeks.
             This includes an exception of patients with metastatic GIST tumors who are taking
             maintenance imatinib mesylate therapy. These patients are allowed to remain on
             imatinib mesylate therapy up to enrollment in this study.

          3. Age &gt; or = 15 years

          4. ECOG performance status &lt; 2 (Karnofsky &gt; 60%).

          5. Patients must have normal organ and marrow function as defined below: leukocytes &gt;
             3,000/mcL; absolute neutrophil count &gt;1,500/mcL; platelets &gt; 100,000/mcL, total
             bilirubin &lt; or = 2.0 mg/dL. (Does NOT apply to patients with Gilbert's Syndrome);
             AST(SGOT)/ALT(SGPT) &lt; 2.5 X institutional upper limit of normal (patients with liver
             involvement will be allowed &lt; or = 5.0 X institutional upper normal limit) serum
             creatinine &lt; 2.0 mg/dL

          6. Patients MUST have recovered from all treatment related toxicities to Grade 1 NCI
             CTCAE (v 4.0) in severity

          7. Patients must be willing and able to review, understand, and provide written consent
             before starting therapy

          8. Patients with histologically proven intracranial glioblastoma, gliosarcoma or
             anaplastic astrocytoma will be eligible. Patients must have shown unequivocal
             radiographic evidence for tumor progression by MRI scan. A scan should be performed
             within 14 days prior to registration and on a steroid dose that has been stable for
             at least 5 days. If the steroid dose is increased between the date of imaging and
             registration, a new baseline MRI is required.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Autoimmune disease: Patients with a history of inflammatory bowel disease (including
             Crohn's disease and ulcerative colitis) and autoimmune disorders such as rheumatoid
             arthritis, systemic progressive sclerosis [scleroderma], Systemic Lupus Erythematosus
             or autoimmune vasculitis [e.g., Wegener's Granulomatosis] are excluded from this
             study.

          2. History of acute diverticulitis, intra-abdominal abscess, GI obstruction, abdominal
             carcinomatosis or other known risk factors for bowel perforation.

          3. Any underlying medical or psychiatric condition, which in the opinion of the
             Investigator, will make the administration of study drug hazardous or obscure the
             interpretation of Adverse Events (AEs): e.g. a condition associated with frequent
             diarrhea or chronic skin conditions, recent surgery or colonic biopsy from which the
             patient has not recovered, or partial endocrine organ deficiencies.

          4. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, history of congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements.

          5. Known HIV, Hepatitis B, or Hepatitis C.

          6. Any non-oncology vaccine therapy used for prevention of infectious diseases (for up
             to one month prior to or after any dose of ipilimumab).

          7. Concomitant therapy with any of the following: IL-2, interferon or other non-study
             immunotherapy regimens; cytotoxic chemotherapy; immunosuppressive agents; other
             investigational therapies; or chronic use of systemic corticosteroids (used in the
             management of cancer or non-cancer-related illnesses).

          8. Patients who do not agree to practice appropriate birth control methods while on
             therapy.

          9. Pregnant women are excluded from this study. Women of child-bearing potential and men
             must agree to use contraception prior to study entry and for the duration of study
             participation. Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while
             participating in this study, she should inform her treating physician.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David S. Hong, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David S. Hong, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-563-1930</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 28, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Advanced Cancers</keyword>
  <keyword>Advanced Malignancies</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic</keyword>
  <keyword>Unresectable</keyword>
  <keyword>Ipilimumab</keyword>
  <keyword>Yervoy</keyword>
  <keyword>BMS-734016</keyword>
  <keyword>MDX010</keyword>
  <keyword>Imatinib Mesylate</keyword>
  <keyword>Imatinib</keyword>
  <keyword>Gleevec</keyword>
  <keyword>STI 571</keyword>
  <keyword>NSC-716051</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Imatinib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
