<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="127731">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01883375</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H2013:024</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01883375</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dignity Talk: Helping Palliative Care Patients and Families Have Important Conversations</brief_title>
  <acronym>DTalk</acronym>
  <official_title>Dignity Talk: a Novel Palliative Care Intervention for Patients and Their Families</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Manitoba</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research  (CIHR)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Manitoba</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Ethics Review Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Dying patients and their families face many challenges near the end-of-life. Not only do
      patients often experience physical distress, but they also have feelings of loss of dignity,
      isolation, and uncertainty. Family members also face many challenges. They bear witness to
      the suffering of loved ones, and they face uncertainty, loss, and at times a mounting sense
      of helplessness.

      The purpose of this study is to introduce and evaluate a new intervention called Dignity
      Talk, meant to enhance end-of-life experience for both patients and their families. Dignity
      Talk is based on a set of questions by which terminally ill patients and their family
      members can engage in meaningful conversations with each other. It is intended to lessen
      feelings of loss and helplessness and enhance feelings of connectedness by facilitating
      conversations that tap into a sense of meaning and purpose, sharing of memories, wishes,
      hopes, and giving guidance to those who will soon be left behind.

      In Phase 1, 20 patients and family members will help finalize the method and Dignity Talk
      question framework (is it easy to understand, do the investigators have the right questions,
      and is the wording sensitive). In Phase 2 of the study the investigators will ask 100
      patient-family pairs for feedback about Dignity Talk: what influence it had on their
      palliative care experience, whether it works well, and whether this intervention should
      become a regular part of palliative care. The investigators will also ask for feedback from
      health-care providers in both phases. Four to six months after the death of their loved one,
      the investigators will contact the family member to ask their thoughts about Dignity Talk,
      how it shaped their experience of their grief and bereavement.

      The investigators expect that the study will show that Dignity Talk can be an effective,
      highly accessible palliative care intervention, which will enhance the end-of-life
      experience for palliative patients and the families who support them.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Family communication connectedness Index</measure>
    <time_frame>31 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>31 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Palliative Care</condition>
  <condition>Family</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dignity Talk dyad completers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dignity Talk non-completers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dignity Talk</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient and family member participants will be given the Dignity Talk  framework questions and asked to use them in conversation with each other. Research nurse will return twice (at 2-4 days and 4-6 days) to address participant issues/concerns. If at the end of 10 days, one or more Dignity Talk items have been discussed and participants confirm they have covered all items wish to discuss, patient and family member will be seen to be &quot;completers&quot;. 4-6 months after the death of patient, family members will be contacted in order to collect data pertaining to their bereavement experiences and distress. Will also be asked to complete evaluative feedback on Dignity Talk.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dignity Talk dyad completers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient and family member participants will be given the Dignity Talk framework questions and asked to use them in conversation with each other. Research nurse will return twice (at 2-4 days and 4-6 days) to address participant issues/concerns. If at the end of 10 days, participants have not completed Dignity Talk, patient and family member will be seen to be &quot;non-completers&quot;. 4-6 months after the death of patient, family members will be contacted in order to collect data pertaining to their bereavement experiences and distress.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dignity Talk non-completers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        For Patient:

          -  Patient being cared for on in-patient palliative care unit whose life expectancy is 6
             months or less

          -  18 years of age or older

          -  able to provide informed oral and written consent

          -  cognitive capacity (based on clinical consensus)

        For Family Member:

          -  Family member who the patient identifies they would be comfortable talking with about
             Dignity Talk question framework

          -  Family member who is 18 years of age or older

          -  Family member who is able to provide oral and written consent

          -  Family member who has cognitive capacity to participate in meaningful conversation
             (based on research staff decision)

        For Healthcare Provider:

          -  Employed one of the participating sites

          -  in a discipline directly involved in clinical care (physician, nursing, social work,
             spiritual care, allied healthcare, etc.)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  not meeting the above inclusion criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Katherine A Cullihall, RN BN</last_name>
    <phone>204-787-4924</phone>
    <email>katherine.cullihall@cancercare.mb.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Boniface Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winnipeg</city>
        <state>Manitoba</state>
        <zip>R3E 0V9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lorie Forbes, MN</last_name>
      <phone>(204) 258-1044</phone>
      <email>lforbes@sbgh.mb.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Harvey M Chochinov, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Riverview Health Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winnipeg</city>
        <state>Manitoba</state>
        <zip>R3L 2P4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John B Bond, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(204) 478-6215</phone>
      <email>jbond@rhc.mb.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Harvey M Chochinov, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 18, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 11, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Palliative Care</keyword>
  <keyword>Family</keyword>
  <keyword>adaptation, psychological</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
