<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="92267">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01703754</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ATI001-201</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01703754</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Adenoviral Vector Monotherapy or Combination With Chemotherapy Study in Subjects With Recurrent/Metastatic Breast Cancer and Accessible/Visible Lesions</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Randomized, Open Label Study of Ad-RTS-hIL-12 Monotherapy or Combination With Palifosfamide-Tris in Subjects With Recurrent/Metastatic Breast Cancer and Accessible Lesions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ziopharm</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ziopharm</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Phase II, randomized, safety and efficacy study in recurrent/metastatic breast cancer with
      accessible lesions.

      Primary End point is rate of Progression Free Survival (PFS) at the 16 week treatment time
      point. Hypothesis: Adenoviral vector (Ad-RTS-hIL-12) alone and in combination with
      chemotherapy (palifosfamide-tris) is safe and efficacious.

      2 Part study:

        -  Part One: Safety run-in for Ad-RTS-hIL-12 alone arm (A) and palifosfamide-tris alone
           arm (B). This is followed by a combination therapy (Ad-RTS-hIL-12 + palifosfamide-tris)
           safety run-in arm (C).

        -  Part Two: Efficacy evaluation of study treatment arms (A) and (C).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of study drug therapy based on type and rate of adverse events occurring in the treatment population</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 24 weeks-Beginning from the time a patient signs the informed consent to the Follow up Tumor Assessment visit</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>16-week PFS rate, calculated as the number of subjects who had not progressed or died prior to 16 weeks from the date of their first dose, divided by the number of subjects in the study arm.</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks, starting at the date the first dose of study drug is administered</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (ORR) by modified RECIST v1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 24 weeks- From first study drug dose to Follow-Up Tumor Assessment Visit</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of subjects achieving a confirmed PR or CR according to modified RECIST v1.1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Benefit rate: proportion of subjects with CR, PR, or SD by modified RECIST v1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimate PFS by modified RECIST v1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 24 weeks, beginning at the first study drug administratrion and ending at the Follow up Tumor Assessment visit</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate Pharmacodynamic tumor markers in tumor tissue samples that may correlate with objective tumor response and/or clinical outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 24 weeks, starting with first study drug administrationa and ending at the Follow up Tumor Assessment visit</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">68</enrollment>
  <condition>Recurrent/Metastatic Breast Cancer With Accessible Lesions</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ad-RTS-hIL-12</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Experimental study drug monotherapy arm (A), Part 1 and 2 of protocol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Palifosfamide-tris</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study drug monotherapy arm (B), Part 1 of protocol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ad-RTS-hIL-12 and palifosfamide-tris</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study drug combination arm (C), in Part 1 and Part 2 of protocol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ad-RTS-hIL-12</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral activator ligand with adenoviral vector injection of cancer lesions</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ad-RTS-hIL-12</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ad-RTS-hIL-12 and palifosfamide-tris</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Palifosfamide-tris</intervention_name>
    <description>Small molecule chemotherapy, IV administration</description>
    <arm_group_label>Palifosfamide-tris</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ad-RTS-hIL-12 and palifosfamide-tris</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  To be enrolled in the trial, each subject must satisfy all of the following inclusion
             criteria:

               1. Males or females of all races ≥ 18 years of age, who have provided written
                  informed consent prior to completing any study specific procedure.

               2. Histologically or cytologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of the breast, either
                  locally recurrent or metastatic disease with injectable lesions, for which no
                  proven effective therapy exists. Locally recurrent disease must not be amenable
                  to surgical resection or radiation with curative intent.

               3. Subject has failed or progressed on at least 1 prior systemic chemotherapy
                  regimen ± biologic/experimental therapy (if first-line therapy, failure or
                  progression during or within the first 30 days).

               4. Resolution of all chemotherapy or radiation-related toxicities to Grade 1
                  severity or lower, except for stable sensory neuropathy ≤ Grade 2 and alopecia.

               5. A minimum of 2 lesion(s) assessed by imaging using modified RECIST v1.1, 1 NOT
                  to be injected AND at least 1 injectable lesion(s)(may use
                  radiographically-guided injection of lesions if available at site)

               6. ECOG performance status 0, 1, 2

               7. Male and female subjects must agree to use a highly reliable method of birth
                  control (expected failure rate less than 5% per year) from the screening visit
                  through 28 days after the last dose of study drug. Women of childbearing
                  potential (perimenopausal women must be amenorrheic for at least 12 months to be
                  considered of non-childbearing potential) must have a negative pregnancy test at
                  screening.

               8. Adequate bone marrow reserve as indicated by:

                    1. ANC &gt; 1500/μL (without use of growth factors within 7 days)

                    2. ALC &gt; 700/μL (without use of growth factors within 7 days)

                    3. Platelet count &gt; 100,000/mm3 (without transfusion in prior 7 days)

                    4. Hemoglobin &gt; 9.0 g/dL (without transfusion in prior 7 days)

               9. Adequate renal function as evidenced  by estimated glomerular filtration rate
                  (eGFR) using the Modification of Diet in Renal Disease (MDRD) equation:  eGFR ≥
                  60 mL/min/1.73 m2

              10. Adequate liver function as evidenced by the following:

                    1. Bilirubin ≤ 1.5 times the upper limits of normal (ULN)

                    2. Alanine aminotransferase (ALT), and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) ≤
                       2.5×ULN, in the case of liver metastases ≤ 5×ULN

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects will be excluded from enrolling in the trial if they meet any of the
             following exclusion criteria:

               1. Subjects with HER2/neu-positive immunohistochemistry 3+ or fluorescence in situ
                  hybridization-amplified breast tumors who are eligible for, but who have not
                  received HER2-targeted therapy (eg, trastuzumab)

               2. Concomitant anti-cancer therapies (eg, endocrine therapy for breast cancer)

               3. Prior therapies discontinuation periods:

                    1. Radiation within 3 weeks of enrollment

                    2. Chemotherapy within 4 weeks of enrollment

                    3. Nitrosoureas within 6 weeks of enrollment

                    4. Biologic therapy and/or immunomodulatory therapy (eg, G-CSF/GM-CSF,
                       interferons or interleukins, growth hormone, IVIG, retinoic acid) within 6
                       weeks of enrollment

                    5. Prior therapy with immune checkpoint inhibitors (eg, anti-CTLA4 antibodies,
                       anti-PD1 antibodies) within 12 weeks of enrollment

                    6. No washout period is required for endocrine therapy

               4. Radiation therapy encompassing &gt;25% of bone marrow

               5. History of bone marrow or stem cell transplantation

               6. Any congenital or acquired condition leading to an inability to generate an
                  immune response, including concomitant immunosuppressive therapy

               7. Immunosuppressive therapy:

                    1. Systemic immunosuppressive drugs including corticosteroids (prednisone
                       equivalent &gt;10 mg/day http://www.medcalc.com/steroid.html) within 8 weeks

                    2. Immune suppression/requiring immunosuppressive drugs including subjects
                       with organ allografts requiring any immunosuppression

                    3. Active autoimmune disease requiring the equivalent of  &gt;10 mg/day of
                       prednisone

               8. Major surgery within 4 weeks of study treatment, or major surgery planned for
                  duration of study participation

               9. History of prior malignancy, unless the prior malignancy was diagnosed and
                  definitively treated ≥5 years previously with no subsequent evidence of
                  recurrence NOTE: This does not apply to previous breast cancer, carcinoma in
                  situ of the cervix, inactive melanoma or non-melanoma skin cancer, or Grade 1
                  papillary bladder cancer

              10. Subjects with brain or subdural metastases are not eligible, unless local
                  therapy completed and corticosteroids discontinued for this indication for ≥4
                  weeks before starting study treatment. Any signs (eg, radiologic) and/or
                  symptoms of brain metastases must be stable for ≥4 weeks before starting study
                  treatment; radiographic stability should be determined by comparing a
                  contrast-enhanced computed tomography or magnetic resonance imaging brain scan
                  performed during screening to a prior scan performed at least 4 weeks earlier.

                  NOTE: Screening for brain lesions by CT or MRI is not required for all potential
                  subjects; however, if there are any neurological signs or symptoms consistent
                  with brain metastases, then a brain CT or MRI should be performed as clinically
                  indicated.

              11. Any medications that induce, inhibit or are substrates of CYP450 3A4 within 7
                  days prior to the first dose of study drug

              12. Subjects with meningeal carcinomatosis

              13. Known significant hypersensitivity to study drugs or excipients

              14. History of malabsorption syndrome or other condition that would interfere with
                  enteral absorption

              15. International Normalized Ratio (INR) and activated partial thromboplastin time
                  [PTT] &lt;1.5 x ULN, if not therapeutically anticoagulated. Subjects who are being
                  therapeutically anticoagulated with an agent such as Coumadin (warfarin sodium)
                  or subcutaneous heparin may be included provided there is no prior evidence of
                  underlying abnormality in coagulation parameters, screening test results are in
                  appropriate therapeutic range, and anticoagulation regimen is stable and closely
                  monitored

              16. New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class II or greater congestive heart failure
                  OR active ventricular arrhythmia requiring medication

              17. Any other unstable or clinically significant concurrent medical condition (eg,
                  infection requiring systemic anti-infective agents) that would, in the opinion
                  of the investigator, jeopardize the safety of a subject and/or their compliance
                  with the protocol

              18. Localized infection at site of injectable lesion(s)requiring antiinfective
                  therapy within 2 weeks of the first dose of study drug. NOTE: Appropriate
                  confirmatory testing (eg, punch biopsy with bacterial counts)must be performed
                  to rule out the presence of infection if ambiguous, or clinical signs of
                  infection are evident
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sadia Saleem</last_name>
    <phone>617-778-0863</phone>
    <email>ssaleem@ziopharm.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Gina Weber</last_name>
    <phone>617-259-2262</phone>
    <email>gweber@ziopharm.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32207</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Billings</city>
        <state>Montana</state>
        <zip>59101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Middletown</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45042</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Greenville</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29605</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Germantown</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38138</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Spokane</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>99218</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 13, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 29, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Genetically Modified Organism</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Recurrent Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Palifosfamide</keyword>
  <keyword>INXN1001</keyword>
  <keyword>INXN2001</keyword>
  <keyword>Adenoviral vector</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ifosfamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Isophosphamide mustard</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
