<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="112785">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02100566</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RWJ 71476</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02100566</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Behavioral Economics for Advance Care Options</brief_title>
  <acronym>BEACON</acronym>
  <official_title>Behavioral Economics for Advance Care OptioNs</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Genesys Regional Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Genesys Regional Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      People with life-limiting illness often receive more aggressive healthcare than desired
      including costly procedures that provide little medical benefit.  Advance Directives (AD)
      can reduce this effect but various factors limit their adoption.

      A randomized trial will target home health care (HHC) patients with a serious, life limiting
      illness to test if the behavioral economics principles of endowment (possessing something)
      and focusing (featuring something important to you) can motivate AD completion. We will
      investigate if offering patients an AD by default, in combination with framing the rationale
      for AD completion (emphasizing patient control or caregiver burden) improves AD completion
      and family conversation compared to a no-intervention group. The study hypothesis is to
      determine if rates of AD completion and family conversations will be highest among patients
      receiving the intervention focused on reduced caregiver burden; and if the two intervention
      groups will have higher rates of both than the control group.

      We suspect that a small change in how patient information is framed (endowment and focusing
      used in tandem) will potentially leverage large increases in AD completion and that
      targeting HHC patients allows AD discussions early in the disease trajectory when they can
      participate in care decisions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary research question: Does offering patients an Advance Directive (AD) document (by
      default), in combination with framing the rationale for AD completion (emphasizing either:
      A. patient control; or B. reduction in caregiver burden) improve AD completion as compared
      to a no-intervention control group?

      Study Design: The project will conduct a 3-group randomized trial in which ADs are provided
      to Home Health Care (HHC) patients by default in the two treatment groups. When discussing
      the benefits of AD completion, intervention group A nurses will focus on ADs' potential to
      promote patients' control over the care they receive. In intervention group B, nurses will
      focus on the potential for AD completion to reduce caregiver burden. In the control group,
      patients will receive ADs only if they actively request them (as in standard practice).
      Specially trained nurses will be responsible for conducting the intervention. Training of
      RNs will consist of didactic and experiential learning on applying endowment and focusing
      effect scripts in a consistent manner that are true to the behavioral economic principles.
      Intervention will occur on the second home visit during which the patient will be presented
      with one of three options by the RN depending on their random assignment. Patients in both
      intervention groups will be given an AD by default.  Patients who elect to complete an AD
      can have this completed with Home Healthcare (HHC) RN during the home visit or during a
      separate visit by a HHC social worker who is trained in Advance Care Planning (ACP).

      Methodology

      Home Visit #1 - Patient Eligibility:

      The home health RN who visits patients, will complete the &quot;Selection of Patient Form&quot; to
      determine eligibility for participation in the study (see subjects/sample below).  Patients
      who are determined to be eligible for the study, will be asked if they are willing to
      participate in the study and asked to sign a consent form .

      Home Visit #2-#4 (depending on condition of patient) - Intervention:

      Patient is assigned into one of the three intervention groups and is provided one of three
      packets  (packet includes script , copy of &quot;Your Health, Your Choice: My Advance Directive&quot;,
      and self-addressed stamped envelope). The home health RN on the this visit will provide the
      designated script regarding advance directives (see &quot;Scripts for Intervention Groups&quot;).  The
      intervention will occur when reviewing the &quot;Patient Information for Home Health Care&quot; under
      the &quot;Medical Decision Making&quot; topic.   Four possible outcomes can occur following this
      visit: A) patient indicates desire to complete AD at home visit #2; B) patient indicates
      desire to complete AD with Nurse or Social Worker as separate visit; C) patient elects to
      complete AD on their own, or D) patient declines to complete AD. A). If patient indicates
      desire to complete AD at home when script presented: the AD document will be reviewed and
      the patient will be helped to complete the document.

      Subjects/Sample: Home, Health and Hospice patients who reside in the County will be
      randomized to one of three groups. Eligibility will be determined at the first home visit.
      Inclusion criteria are adult patients, 50 years and older, who have a serious, life-limiting
      illness and require home health care (see below). Eligible patients will be identified and
      selected concurrently from new intakes to Reverence home care.

      Inclusion Criteria:

      A subject will be eligible for study participation if he/she meets the both 1 &amp; 2 criteria:

      1.1 Age  50 years and older 2.0  Subject must have one or more of the following serious life
      limiting illness that requires home health care (as determined from review of medical
      records and clinical judgment) 2.1. Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) or any
      respiratory (pulmonary) disease that requires home oxygen use (e.g. interstitial lung
      disease, sleep-disordered breathing), 2.2. End Stage Renal Disease 2.3. Peripheral vascular
      disease (PVD) 2.4. NYHA Class III or IV Heart Failure (HF) Class III:  Marked limitation in
      activity due to symptoms, even during less-than-ordinary activity, e.g. walking short
      distances (20-100 m).  Comfortable only at rest.

      Class IV: Severe limitations. Experiences symptoms even while at rest. Mostly bedbound
      patients.

      2.5. Cancer as a discharge diagnosis (any type)     Type: 2.6. Neuromuscular/movement
      disorders: Myasthenia gravis, ALS, Parkinson's, and Multiple sclerosis

      Exclusion Criteria:

      A subject will not be eligible for study participation if he/she meets any of the following
      criteria

      3.1. Patient cannot sign legal documents such as consent or AD (Impaired decision-making
      capacity) 3.2. Previously specified written AD 3.3. Home health nurse would not conduct the
      home visit (open visits such as physical therapy only) 3.4. Patients referred for Palliative
      Care (where home health nurse would not conduct the home visit and patient might receive
      additional AD intervention).

      3.5  Patient previously enrolled in this study.

      Data Management and Statistical Analysis:

      Sample Size- Calculated on the primary outcome of AD completion rate, we used an estimated
      baseline completion of 10% for the control group. A two-tailed test for comparing completion
      rates between a default option and the standard, as well as, comparing the two framing
      interventions will require a total of 350 participants (125 in each intervention and 100 in
      the control). This achieves a minimum of 88% power to detect a 15% absolute difference
      between the groups at alpha of 0.05 and accounts for a 5% attrition rate. The hypothesis
      that AD completion rates differ by at least 15% between two groups within each arm (default
      option compared to control; autonomy framing compared to caregiver burden framing) will be
      analyzed using Chi-square analysis.

      Expected Outcomes of the Study:

      It is hypothesized that offering patients an AD document (by default), in combination with
      framing the rationale for AD completion (emphasizing either: A. patient control; or B.
      reduction in caregiver burden) will improve AD completion as compared to a no-intervention
      control group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Advance directive document completion</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of advance directive documents completed within one month of enrollment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Advance Directive document completion</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of advance directive documents completed within one year of enrollment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Advance directive communication</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of patients who discuss advance directives with their family or care giver within one year of enrollment.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">350</enrollment>
  <condition>End of Life Care</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral Counseling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Provide an advance directive document to patients along with counseling that either focuses on care giver burden or on patient autonomy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard AD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The topic of advance directives (AD) is introduced but patient receives an AD document only upon request.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Counseling (Care giver burden focus)</intervention_name>
    <description>An advance directive (AD) document is provided to the patient along with counseling that focuses on care giver burden as the reason for adoption of the AD.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral Counseling</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Focusing effect</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Counseling (patient autonomy focus)</intervention_name>
    <description>An advance directive (AD) document is provided to the patient along with counseling that focuses on patient autonomy (control) as the reason for adoption of the AD.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral Counseling</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Focusing effect</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  50 years or older

          -  One or more of the following:

          -  Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease

          -  End stge renal disease

          -  Peripheral vascular disease

          -  NYHA class II or V heart failure

          -  Cancer

          -  Neuromuscular / movement disorder

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient referred to palliative care

          -  Patient has advance directive

          -  Patient has impaired decision making ability

          -  Patient previously enrolled in this study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark A Vogel, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Genesys Regional Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mark A Vogel, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>810-605-4616</phone>
    <email>mvogel@genesys.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kimberly R Barber, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>810-606-7724</phone>
    <email>kbarber@genesys.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Reverence Home Health Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grand Blanc</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48439</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mark Vogel, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>810-605-4616</phone>
      <email>mvogel@genesys.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kimberly Barber, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>810-606-7724</phone>
      <email>kbarber@genesys.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark Vogel, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 27, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 27, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Genesys Regional Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mark Vogel, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Behavioral Medicine Director</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Advance Directive</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
