<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="33537">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01993719</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>140022</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>14-C-0022</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01993719</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase II Prospective Randomized Study of Cell Transfer Therapy for Metastatic Melanoma Using Tumor Infiltrating Lymphocytes Plus IL-2 Comparing Two Different Chemotherapy Preparative Regimens</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Prospective Randomized Study of Cell Transfer Therapy for Metastatic Melanoma Using Tumor Infiltrating Lymphocytes Plus IL-2 Comparing Two Different Chemotherapy Preparative Regimens</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Adoptive cell therapy (ACT) using autologous tumor infiltrating lymphocytes can mediate
           the regression of bulky metastatic melanoma when administered along with high-dose
           aldesleukin (IL-2) following a non-myeloablative lymphodepleting chemotherapy
           preparative regimen consisting of cyclophosphamide and fludarabine.

        -  In a series of consecutive trials using this chemotherapy preparative regimen alone or
           with 2 Gy or 12 Gy total body irradiation (TBI) objective response rates using RECIST
           criteria were 49%, 52%, and 72%, respectively. Of the 20 complete regressions seen in
           this trial, 19 are on-going at 70 to 114 months.

        -  The chemotherapy alone preparative regimen required in-patient treatment and was
           associated with significant neutropenia and thrombocytopenia requiring multiple
           transfusions and treatment for febrile neutropenia.

        -  We would thus now like to evaluate ACT with TIL comparing the standard cyclophosphamide
           and fludarabine regimen with a reduced preparative regimen (300 mg/m(2)
           cyclophosphamide qd times 3 and fludarabine (30 mg/m2 qd times 3) that is associated
           with less neutropenia and thrombocytopenia and can be administered as an outpatient.

      Objectives:

        -  To determine, in a prospective randomized trial, whether patients receiving TIL plus a
           lower dose chemotherapy preparative regimen followed by aldesleukin are able to attain
           a response rate equivalent to TIL plus our standard chemotherapy regimen followed by
           aldesleukin.

        -  To assess bone marrow toxicity of the two regimens to determine the duration and
           severity of anemia, neutropenia and/or thrombocytopenia.

        -  Platelet and red cell transfusion requirement and progression free survival and overall
           survival will be evaluated as secondary endpoints.

      Eligibility:

        -  Age greater than or equal to 18 and less than or equal to 66 years

        -  Evaluable metastatic melanoma

        -  Metastatic melanoma lesion suitable for surgical resection for the preparation of TIL

        -  No contraindications to high-dose aldesleukin administration

        -  No concurrent major medical illnesses or any form of immunodeficiency

      Design:

        -  Patients with metastatic melanoma will have lesions resected and after TIL growth is
           established, patients will be prospectively randomized to receive ACT with TIL plus
           aldesleukin comparing two different chemotherapy preparative regimens.

        -  Up to 120 patients may be enrolled over 4-5 years.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Adoptive cell therapy (ACT) using autologous tumor infiltrating lymphocytes can mediate
           the regression of bulky metastatic melanoma when administered along with high-dose
           aldesleukin (IL-2) following a non-myeloablative lymphodepleting chemotherapy
           preparative regimen consisting of cyclophosphamide and fludarabine.

        -  In a series of consecutive trials using this chemotherapy preparative regimen alone or
           with 2 Gy or 12 Gy total body irradiation (TBI) objective response rates using RECIST
           criteria were 49%, 52%, and 72%, respectively. Of the 20 complete regressions seen in
           this trial, 19 are on-going at 70 to 114 months.

        -  The chemotherapy alone preparative regimen required in-patient treatment and was
           associated with significant neutropenia and thrombocytopenia requiring multiple
           transfusions and treatment for febrile neutropenia.

        -  We would thus now like to evaluate ACT with TIL comparing the standard cyclophosphamide
           and fludarabine regimen with a reduced preparative regimen (300 mg/m(2)
           cyclophosphamide qd times 3 and fludarabine (30 mg/m2 qd times 3) that is associated
           with less neutropenia and thrombocytopenia and can be administered as an outpatient.

      Objectives:

        -  To determine, in a prospective randomized trial, whether patients receiving TIL plus a
           lower dose chemotherapy preparative regimen followed by aldesleukin are able to attain
           a response rate equivalent to TIL plus our standard chemotherapy regimen followed by
           aldesleukin.

        -  To assess bone marrow toxicity of the two regimens to determine the duration and
           severity of anemia, neutropenia and/or thrombocytopenia.

        -  Platelet and red cell transfusion requirement and progression free survival and overall
           survival will be evaluated as secondary endpoints.

      Eligibility:

        -  Age greater than or equal to 18 and less than or equal to 66 years

        -  Evaluable metastatic melanoma

        -  Metastatic melanoma lesion suitable for surgical resection for the preparation of TIL

        -  No contraindications to high-dose aldesleukin administration

        -  No concurrent major medical illnesses or any form of immunodeficiency

      Design:

        -  Patients with metastatic melanoma will have lesions resected and after TIL growth is
           established, patients will be prospectively randomized to receive ACT with TIL plus
           aldesleukin comparing two different chemotherapy preparative regimens.

        -  Up to 120 patients may be enrolled over 4-5 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine whether patients receiving TIL plus a lower dose chemotherapy preparative regimen followed by aldesleukin are able to attain a response rate equivalent to TIL plus our standard chemotherapy regimen followed by aldesleukin.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the relative platelet and red cell transfusion requirements on the two arms</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard dose chemotherapy + Young TIL + Aldesleukin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Low dose chemotherapy + Young TIL + Aldesleukin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aldesleukin</intervention_name>
    <description>720,000 IU/kg IV over 15 minute every eight hours (+/- 1 hour) for up to 5 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>(standard dose) 25 mg/m(2)/day IVPB daily over 15-30 minutes for 5 days vs (low dose) 30mg/m2 IV over 30 minutes x 3 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide</intervention_name>
    <description>(standard dose) 60 mg/kg/day over 1 hour for 2 days IV vs (low dose) 300mg/m2 IV over 1 hour x 3 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Young Tumor Infiltrating Lymphocytes (young TIL)</intervention_name>
    <description>Autologous young TIL infusion will be administered intravenously over 20 to 30 minutes (minimum 1 X 10(9) and up to a maximum of 2 X 10(11) lymphocytes).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Measurable metastatic melanoma with at least one lesion that is resectable for TIL
             generation.

          2. Confirmation of diagnosis of metastatic melanoma by the Laboratory of Pathology of
             NCI.

          3. 3 or fewer brain metastases. Note: If lesions are symptomatic or greater than or
             equal to 1 cm each, these lesions must have been treated and stable for 3 months for
             the patient to be eligible.

          4. Greater than or equal to 18 years of age and less than or equal to 66 years of age.

          5. Able to understand and sign the Informed Consent Document

          6. Clinical performance status of ECOG 0 or 1.

          7. Life expectancy of greater than three months.

          8. Patients of both genders must be willing to practice birth control from the time of
             enrollment on this study and for up to four months after receiving the preparative
             regimen.

          9. Serology:

               -  Seronegative for HIV antibody. (The experimental treatment being evaluated in
                  this protocol depends on an intact immune system. Patients who are HIV
                  seropositive can have decreased immune-competence and thus are less responsive
                  to the experimental treatment and more susceptible to its toxicities.)

               -  Seronegative for hepatitis B antigen, and seronegative for hepatitis C antibody.
                  If hepatitis C antibody test is positive, then patient must be tested for the
                  presence of antigen by RT-PCR and be HCV RNA negative.

         10. Women of child-bearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test because of the
             potentially dangerous effects of the preparative chemotherapy on the fetus.

         11. Hematology:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count greater than 1000/mm(3) without the support of
                  filgrastim

               -  WBC greater than or equal to 3000/mm(3)

               -  Platelet count greater than or equal to 100,000/mm(3)

               -  Hemoglobin &gt;  8.0 g/dl

         12. Chemistry:

               -  Serum ALT/AST less than or equal to 2.5 times the upper limit of normal

               -  Serum Creatinine less than or equal to 1.6 mg/dl

               -  Total bilirubin less than or equal to 1.5 mg/dl, except in patients with Gilbert
                    s Syndrome who must have a total bilirubin less than 3.0 mg/dl.

         13. More than four weeks must have elapsed since any prior systemic therapy at the time
             the patient receives the preparative regimen, and patients    toxicities must have
             recovered to a grade 1 or less (except for toxicities such as alopecia or vitiligo).
             Patients must have progressive disease after prior treatment.

             Note: Patients may have undergone minor surgical procedures within the past 3 weeks,
             as long as all toxicities have recovered to grade 1 or less.

         14. Six weeks must have elapsed from the time of any antibody therapy that could affect
             an anti cancer immune response, including anti-CTLA4 antibody therapy, so at the time
             the patient receives the preparative regimen to allow antibody levels to decline.
             Note: Patients who have previously received ipilimumab and have documented GI
             toxicity must have a colonoscopy with normal colonic biopsies.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Women of child-bearing potential who are pregnant or breastfeeding because of the
             potentially dangerous effects of the treatment on the fetus or infant.

          2. Any form of primary immunodeficiency (such as Severe Combined Immunodeficiency
             Disease).

          3. Concurrent opportunistic infections (The experimental treatment being evaluated in
             this protocol depends on an intact immune system. Patients who have decreased immune
             competence may be less responsive to the experimental treatment and more susceptible
             to its toxicities).

          4. Active systemic infections, coagulation disorders or other active major medical
             illnesses of the cardiovascular, respiratory or immune system, as evidenced by a
             positive stress thallium or comparable test, myocardial infarction, cardiac
             arrhythmias, obstructive or restrictive pulmonary disease.

          5. Concurrent systemic steroid therapy.

          6. History of severe immediate hypersensitivity reaction to any of the agents used in
             this study.

          7. History of coronary revascularization or ischemic symptoms.

          8. Documented LVEF of less than or equal to 45%, testing is required in patients with:

               -  Age greater than or equal to 60 years old

               -  Clinically significant atrial and or ventricular arrhythmias including but not
                  limited to: atrial fibrillation, ventricular tachycardia, second or third degree
                  heart block.

          9. Documented FEV1 less than or equal to 60% predicted tested in patients with:

               -  A prolonged history of cigarette smoking (20 pk/year of smoking within the past
                  2 years).

               -  Symptoms of respiratory dysfunction
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>66 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven A Rosenberg, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Linda Williams, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(866) 820-4505</phone>
    <email>linda_williams@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Steven A Rosenberg, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-4164</phone>
    <email>sar@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact NCI/Surgery Branch Recruitment Center</last_name>
      <phone>866-820-4505</phone>
      <email>ncisbirc@mail.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2014-C-0022.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jemal A, Siegel R, Ward E, Murray T, Xu J, Thun MJ. Cancer statistics, 2007. CA Cancer J Clin. 2007 Jan-Feb;57(1):43-66.</citation>
    <PMID>17237035</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Atkins MB, Lotze MT, Dutcher JP, Fisher RI, Weiss G, Margolin K, Abrams J, Sznol M, Parkinson D, Hawkins M, Paradise C, Kunkel L, Rosenberg SA. High-dose recombinant interleukin 2 therapy for patients with metastatic melanoma: analysis of 270 patients treated between 1985 and 1993. J Clin Oncol. 1999 Jul;17(7):2105-16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10561265</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gogas HJ, Kirkwood JM, Sondak VK. Chemotherapy for metastatic melanoma: time for a change? Cancer. 2007 Feb 1;109(3):455-64. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17200963</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 22, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Metastatic</keyword>
  <keyword>Melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Adoptive Cell Therapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine monophosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aldesleukin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
