<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="11780">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02128906</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UPCI 13-056</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02128906</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Radiotherapy With Cisplatin vs. Docetaxel-cetuximab in HNSCC: ERCC1 Biomarker Enrichment and Interaction Design</brief_title>
  <acronym>UPCI 13-056</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Phase II Study of Definitive Radiotherapy With Concurrent Cisplatin vs. Docetaxel-cetuximab in Locally Advanced Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma: an ERCC1 Biomarker Enrichment and Interaction Design</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pittsburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Data and Safety Monitoring Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn which chemotherapy combination may be
      more effective in treating locally advanced head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC).
      The side effects of these combinations will also be studied.

      This study treatment consists of intensity-modulated radiation therapy (IMRT) and concurrent
      chemotherapy. For study chemotherapy, patients will be randomized between cisplatin or the
      combination of docetaxel and cetuximab. Subjects will be stratified depending on HPV status
      and the presence of ERCC-1 [4F9] in the tumor prior to randomization.  The study will
      evaluate cisplatin vs. docetaxel-cetuximab in the overall population, and test which
      radiation and chemotherapy combination works best in relationship to how much ERCC-1 [4F9]
      is expressed in a tumor.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the efficacy of radiotherapy with concurrent docetaxel-cetuximab vs. cisplatin in patients with locally advanced HNSCC and increased tumoral ERCC1 expression, as measured by time to progression (TTP)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the efficacy of radiotherapy with concurrent docetaxel-cetuximab vs. cisplatin in patients with PULA HNSCC and decreased/normal tumoral ERCC1 expression, as measured by TTP</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the efficacy of radiotherapy with concurrent docetaxel-cetuximab vs. cisplatin in all patients irrespective of ERCC1 status, as measured by TTP</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prospectively validate the candidate cutpoint for decreased/normal vs. increased ERCC1 [4F9] expression in patients treated with cisplatin-IMRT</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prospectively investigate two sets of radiologic interpretive criteria, including RECIST 1.1 and integrated PET/CT, for the designation of complete response (CR), and to compare the ability of the two CR classifications to accurately predict 2-year TTP.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Oropharynx, Larynx, or Hypopharynx</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cisplatin-IMRT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cisplatin 40 mg/m2 weekly x 7; IMRT: once daily, M-F, 7 weeks (70 Gy)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Docetaxel-Cetuximab-IMRT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Docetaxel 15 mg/m2 weekly x 7; Cetuximab 400 mg/m2 load, one week prior to IMRT; Cetuximab 250 mg/m2 weekly x 7; IMRT: once daily, M-F, 7 weeks (70 Gy)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cisplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Cisplatin 40 mg/m2 weekly x 7</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cisplatin-IMRT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IMRT</intervention_name>
    <description>IMRT: once daily, M-F, 7 weeks (70 Gy)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cisplatin-IMRT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Docetaxel-Cetuximab-IMRT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Docetaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Docetaxel 15 mg/m2 weekly x 7</description>
    <arm_group_label>Docetaxel-Cetuximab-IMRT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cetuximab</intervention_name>
    <description>Cetuximab 400 mg/m2 load, one week prior to IMRT Cetuximab 250 mg/m2 weekly x 7</description>
    <arm_group_label>Docetaxel-Cetuximab-IMRT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pathologically confirmed squamous cell carcinoma, undifferentiated carcinoma, or
             poorly differentiated carcinoma of the oropharynx, larynx, or hypopharynx with no
             evidence of distant metastasis.  Biopsy sampling of primary tumor with pathology
             report documenting diagnostic tissue type is required.

          -  Patients must have stage III, IVa or IVb disease as determined by imaging studies and
             complete head and neck exam.  Staging evaluation should be in accordance with the
             American Joint Committee on Cancer Staging Manual, 7th edition.

          -  Patients with oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma may have p16(+) or p16(-)
             disease; in these patients, p16 status must be known prior to randomization.
             Assessment of p16 status may occur locally or centrally.  Note: The definition of
             p16(+) disease is diffuse nuclear and cytoplasmic staining in ≥ 70% of tumor cells.

          -  Patients must be untreated with curative-intent surgery for current diagnosis of
             Stage III, IVa, or IVb disease.  Diagnostic biopsy of primary tumor and/or nodal
             sites is permitted.

          -  Diagnostic simple tonsillectomy is permitted, provided patient has RECIST-measurable
             residual tumor and/or nodal disease.

          -  Patients with a second HNSCC primary tumor are eligible for this study, provided more
             than 2 years have elapsed since the first diagnosis of HNSCC, the original tumor was
             managed with surgery only (no adjuvant chemotherapy/radiotherapy), and has not
             recurred.

          -  Patients with simultaneous primaries or bilateral tumors are excluded, with the
             exception of patients with bilateral tonsil cancers or patients with T1-2, N0, M0
             resected differentiated thyroid carcinoma, who are eligible.

          -  No prior systemic treatment (chemotherapy or biologic/molecular targeted therapy) or
             radiation treatment for head and neck cancer.

          -  Patients may have received chemotherapy or radiation for a previous, curatively
             treated non-HNSCC malignancy, provided at least 2 years have elapsed.

          -  Patients must be untreated with radiation above the clavicles.

          -  Patients with a history of curatively-treated non-HNSCC malignancy must be
             disease-free for at least 2 years except for carcinoma-in-situ of cervix,
             non-melanomatous skin cancer, or T1-2, N0, M0 resected differentiated thyroid
             carcinoma.

          -  Diagnostic primary tumor tissue must be available for ERCC1 staining

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status 0-1 (See Appendix 8)

          -  Age ≥ 18

          -  Patients must have measurable disease according to RECIST 1.1

          -  Patients must have the following laboratory values measured within 14 days of
             registration:

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt; 1500/mm3

          -  Hemoglobin (Hb) &gt; 8.0 g/dL

          -  Platelet count (PLT) &gt; 100,000/mm3

          -  Creatinine clearance ≥ 45 ml/min determined by 24-hour collection or estimated by the
             Cockraft-Gault formula:

        Calculated Creatinine Clearance = [(140-age) X (actual body weight in kg) X (0.85 if
        female)]/(72 X serum creatinine)

          -  Serum bilirubin &lt; 2 mg/dL

          -  AST (aspartate aminotransferase) and ALT (alanine aminotransferase) &lt; 3 times upper
             limit of normal (ULN)

          -  The following assessments are required within 14 days prior to registration: Na, K,
             Cl, glucose, Ca, Mg, and albumin.  The following metabolic values will exclude
             patients from study enrollment:

          -  Serum calcium (ionized or adjusted for albumin) &lt; 7 mg/dl (1.75 mmol/L) or &gt; 12.5
             mg/dl (&gt; 3.1 mmol/L) despite intervention to normalize levels

          -  Magnesium &lt; 0.9 mg/dl (&lt; 0.4 mmol/L) or &gt; 3 mg/dl (&gt; 1.23 mmol/L) despite
             intervention to normalize levels

          -  Potassium &lt; 3.5 mmol/L or &gt; 6 mmol/L despite intervention to normalize levels

          -  Sodium &lt; 130 mmol/L or &gt; 155 mmol/L despite intervention to normalize levels Note:
             Patients with an initial magnesium &lt; 0.5 mmol/L (1.2 mg/dl) may receive corrective
             magnesium supplementation but should continue to receive either prophylactic weekly
             infusion of magnesium and/or oral magnesium supplementation (eg, magnesium oxide) at
             the investigator's discretion.

          -  No prior severe infusion reaction to a monoclonal antibody

          -  Written informed consent must be obtained from all patients prior to beginning
             therapy. Patients should have the ability to understand and the willingness to sign a
             written informed consent document.

          -  Informed consent must be obtained from all patients prior to beginning therapy,
             including consent for mandatory tissue submission for ERCC1 staining (and p16
             staining if not locally conducted). Patients should have the ability to understand
             and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document.

          -  No unstable angina or myocardial infarction within the prior 6 months; no symptomatic
             congestive heart failure; no serious cardiac arrhythmia requiring medication; no
             cerebrovascular ischemia or stroke within the past 6 months.

          -  No uncontrolled intercurrent illness including active infection, uncontrolled
             diabetes, uncontrolled hypertension, or uncontrolled psychiatric illness which in the
             investigator's opinion would limit compliance with study requirements or compromise
             patient safety.

          -  Women must not be pregnant or breast feeding because chemotherapy and/or cetuximab
             may be harmful to the fetus or the nursing infant. Pregnant women are excluded from
             this study because chemotherapy and/or cetuximab have the potential for teratogenic
             or abortifacient effects.

          -  Women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
             (hormonal or barrier method of birth control) prior to study entry and for the
             duration of study participation. Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is
             pregnant while in this study, she should inform her treating physician immediately.
             All females of childbearing potential must have a blood test or urine study within 14
             days of registration to rule out pregnancy.

          -  HIV-positive patients receiving combination anti-retroviral therapy are excluded from
             the study because of possible drug interactions with study drugs.  Appropriate
             studies will be undertaken in patients receiving combination anti-retroviral therapy
             when indicated.  Note: HIV testing is not required for entry into this protocol.

          -  Patients may not be receiving any other anti-neoplastic investigational agents.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Julie Bauman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Barb Schwabenbauer, RN</last_name>
    <phone>412-623-6793</phone>
    <email>panianba@upmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Barb Schwabenbauer, RN</last_name>
      <phone>412-623-6793</phone>
      <email>panianba@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 29, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Julie E. Bauman, MD, MPH</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ERCC1</keyword>
  <keyword>squamous cell carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>oropharynx</keyword>
  <keyword>larynx</keyword>
  <keyword>hypopharynx</keyword>
  <keyword>p16</keyword>
  <keyword>radiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>docetaxel</keyword>
  <keyword>cetuximab</keyword>
  <keyword>cisplatin</keyword>
  <keyword>EGFR</keyword>
  <keyword>Biomarker</keyword>
  <keyword>efficacy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oropharyngeal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cetuximab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
