<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="88915">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01722552</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R34DA032423 - 01A1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01722552</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>China Adherence Through Technology Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>CATS</acronym>
  <official_title>China Adherence Through Technology Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Boston University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>FHI 360</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Guangxi Center for Disease Control and Prevention</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Dimagi Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Boston University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>China: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The CATS project is designed to increase understanding of interventions that are feasible
      and effective in helping injection drug users (IDU) or other patients at high risk of poor
      medication adherence who are HIV-positive to maintain a high ART adherence. The study will
      involve: assessing the feasibility and acceptability of using real-time feedback, a wireless
      technology-updated adaptation of an approach the investigators found to be feasible and
      effective in China, to promote ART adherence among Chinese patients, including IDU;
      generating preliminary effectiveness data of real-time feedback on adherence, CD4 count, and
      HIV viral load; and identifying the factors that explain how real-time feedback influences
      intervention success or failure.

      The specific aims of the study are:

      SA1: Determine the feasibility and acceptability of using real-time feedback, a wireless
      technology-updated adaptation of an approach we found to be feasible and effective in China,
      to promote ART adherence among Chinese patients. The investigators will conduct a pilot RCT
      of the real-time feedback intervention among Chinese patients in order to assess its
      feasibility and acceptability in this population.

      SA2: Generate preliminary effectiveness data of real-time feedback on adherence, CD4 count,
      and HIV viral load. The RCT will allow the researchers to generate rigorous estimates of
      effect sizes on these important endpoints.

      SA3: Describe the factors that explain how real-time feedback influences intervention
      success or failure. The investigators will use a quantitative-qualitative mixed-methods
      research approach to explore how the intervention influences the experience of adherence
      support in this patient population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators will implement CATS over 2.5 years by implementing a randomized controlled
      trial to assess real-time feedback, an intervention that utilizes wireless technology via an
      electronic pill container device ('Wisepill'), and investigating the mechanisms by which the
      intervention operates using quantitative and qualitative research methods. 120 patients will
      be enrolled in a HIV clinic in Nanning, capital of Guangxi province, a border province with
      high rates of HIV and IDU. Enrolled patients will be randomized to intervention vs.
      comparison group for the 6-month intervention. The study will follow all patients for an
      additional 3 months to determine sustainability of intervention impact. In addition to
      adherence and clinical data, quantitative and qualitative data will be collected using
      survey instruments, focus groups, and in-depth interviews. Analysis of these data will
      enable achievement of the specific aims and contribute to the scientific evidence base on
      effective approaches to promoting ART adherence among IDU and other patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in proportion of subjects who achieve &gt;/= 95% adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at 6 months after start of intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subjects will participate in the 6-month real-time feedback intervention. Comparison patients will continue to be monitored by Wisepill, but they will remain blinded to the adherence information generated by the Wisepill devices, as will their care providers.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects who achieve &gt;/= 95% cumulative adherence over entire 6 months of intervention period</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subjects will participate in the 6-month real-time feedback intervention. Comparison patients will continue to be monitored by Wisepill, but they will remain blinded to the adherence information generated by the Wisepill devices, as will their care providers.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Medication Adherence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>adherence feedback</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention subjects will receive personalized cell phone reminder messages whenever they fail to take a dose within 30 minutes of dose time (as indicated by lack of a Wisepill opening). They will then participate in monthly interactive counseling sessions using summaries of their previous month's behavior. Patients whose mean adherence in the previous month was &lt;95% will be required to have a counseling session, while those with higher adherence will be given the option to have a counseling session.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>adherence feedback</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>adherence feedback</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who are 18 years of age and above, currently on ART or about to begin ART at
             the Guangxi CDC clinic, deemed at risk for poor adherence either by patients or
             medical staff, own a cell phone, and provide written consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Persons who do not speak Mandarin Chinese or who have mental health issues such that
             they cannot provide written informed consent will not be allowed to participate.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lora Sabin, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Boston University Center for Global Health and Development</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boston University Center for Global Health and Development</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02118</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Guangxi CDC ART Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nanning</city>
        <state>Guangxi</state>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 3, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Boston University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lora Sabin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>AIDS</keyword>
  <keyword>antiretroviral therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>adherence</keyword>
  <keyword>China</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
