<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="79127">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02157246</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OCTO_043</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02157246</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>RHYTHM-I: Investigating Hypoxia in Rectal Tumours</brief_title>
  <acronym>RHYTHM-I</acronym>
  <official_title>RHYTHM-I: Modulation of Radiotherapy According to HYpoxia: Exploiting Changes in the Tumour Microenvironment to Improve Outcome in Rectal Cancer.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A low level of oxygen in cancer cells makes them less likely to respond to chemotherapy and
      radiotherapy treatments. There is interest in using new drugs that improve the level of
      oxygen in tumours. Another approach would be to increase the radiotherapy dose to tumours
      with low oxygen levels.

      Before we can do this for patients with rectal cancer, we need to develop a reliable way of
      identifying areas of low oxygen within the rectal tumour. This will make us able to tell
      which patients may be suitable for such a change in their treatment.

      Traditionally, the level of oxygen in tumours is measured by inserting a needle into the
      tumour and measuring it directly. This is not possible in rectal cancer. This study has been
      designed to identify the best alternative method. We would like to do a blood test, take a
      sample of cancer tissue and some detailed scans (18F-fluoromisonidazole (F-MISO) positron
      emission tomography, perfusion computed tomography, dynamic contrast enhanced magnetic
      resonance imaging and velocity selective arterial spin labeling MRI). The results of these
      tests will be compared to decide which gives us the most comprehensive and reliable
      information.

      Patients in Group A go straight to surgery. By looking for markers of low oxygen levels on
      the tumour that has been removed, we will be able to find out which of the study tests
      performed before the tumour was removed is the best. By repeating the scans we will be able
      to see how reliable they are and how much they change on a day to day basis. We think that
      tumours that still have low levels of oxygen after 8 to 10 doses of radiotherapy are the
      least likely to respond to treatment.

      Group B will have scans before radiotherapy treatment and after 8 to 10 doses of
      radiotherapy to see if we can identify the patients that have persistent low levels of
      oxygen.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 0</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Group A FMISO-PET derived hypoxic volumes</measure>
    <time_frame>At surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Validation of FMISO-PET as a measure of hypoxia in rectal cancer.
FMISO-PET derived hypoxic volumes will be compared to reconstructed volumes from the immunohistochemistry of PIMO, CAIX and HIF on whole mount histology of the resected tumour.
The spatial distribution of FMISO uptake on PET images will be compared with PIMO, CAIX and HIF immunohistochemistry distributions in the resected tumour.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Group B Percentage change in FMISO-PET SUVmax and uptake volume</measure>
    <time_frame>Day -7 to -2 and day 10-12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Quantifying the percentage change in FMISO SUVmax and uptake volume between the two FMISO-PET scans after 8-10 fractions of CRT.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hypoxia gene microarray read outs from biopsies</measure>
    <time_frame>Day -7 to -2 (Group A &amp; B) and day 10-12 (Group B)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Group A: To assess whether the FMISO-PET defined hypoxia correlates with a validated hypoxia metagene profile.
Group B: To compare baseline hypoxia measures and changes in FMISO-PET and hypoxia gene microarray readouts with pathological response.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FMISO-PET SUVmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Day -7 to -2 (Group A &amp; B) and 10-12 (Group B only)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Group A: Assess inter-individual variability in FMISO uptake and intra-individual reproducibility of FMISO-PET in rectal cancer.
Group B: Determine percentage change in FMISO-PET SUVmax after 8-10 fractions of CRT. Determine correlation of baseline and day 10-12 FMISO-PET SUVmax with pathological response.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>pCT derived blood flow parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Day -7 to -2 (Group A &amp; B) and day 10-12 (Group B)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Group A: Assess inter-individual variability in pCT derived blood flow parameters and intra-individual reproducibility of pCT in rectal cancer. Assessment of the utility of pCT derived AIF in the processing of dynamic FMISO-PET scans.
Group B: Quantitative changes in pCT derived blood flow parameters after 8-10 fractions of CRT.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Blood sample</measure>
    <time_frame>Day -7 to -2 and day 10-12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood samples will be taken at each imaging time point for investigational work to identify potential circulating hypoxia biomarkers.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Group A VS-ASL MRI</measure>
    <time_frame>Day -7</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Examine to ability to determine outcome measures of perfusion and oxygen consumption using VS-ASL MRI scanning.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypoxia in Rectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A, pimonidazole, no CRT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Biomarker for hypoxia, F-MISO scan</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B, CRT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>F-MISO scan</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pimonidazole</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Group A, pimonidazole, no CRT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>F-MISO scan</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Group A, pimonidazole, no CRT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B, CRT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria (Group A):

          1. T2-3 N0 histologically proven adenocarcinoma of the rectum with MRI confirmation that
             the circumferential resection margin is not involved or threatened and agreement from
             the local multi-disciplinary team (MDT) that the tumour is operable and does not
             require pre-operative CRT.

          2. The rectal cancer on MRI and/or CT measures at least 2 cm by 2 cm.

          3. The patient is medically fit for operative resection of the tumour.

          4. Male or female, Age at least 18 years.

          5. ECOG performance score of 0-2 and be capable of co-operating with protocol.

          6. Written (signed and dated) informed consent.

          7. Haematological and biochemical indices within the ranges shown below:

               1. Haemoglobin (Hb) ≥12.0 g/dL

               2. Platelet count ≥ 100 x 109/L

               3. PT 10-14 seconds

               4. Renal function:

        Serum Creatinine &lt;120 mmol/L OR Calculated GFR &gt;50 ml/min

        Inclusion Criteria (Group B):

          1. Histologically confirmed invasive adenocarcinoma of the rectum

          2. Pelvic MRI defined disease:

             a. Mesorectal fascia (MRF) involved or breached i. Includes involvement of adjacent
             organ b. Mesorectal fascia threatened (tumour ≤ 1mm from MRF). This includes i.
             Primary tumour ≤ 1mm from MRF ii. Extramural vascular invasion ≤ 1mm from MRF iii.
             Tumour deposit with irregular border and mixed signal intensity ≤ 1mm from MRF c. Low
             tumours at/below the level of the levators where: i. Tumour ≤ 1mm from levator on two
             imaging planes ii. Tumour through full thickness of muscularis propria or beyond at
             level of puborectalis sling or below iii. Tumour involving the intersphincteric plane
             iv. Tumour involving the external anal sphincter

          3. Patient is considered likely to be fit for surgical resection following CRT

          4. Patient has been considered to be medically fit to receive CRT by their treating
             oncologist

          5. Male or female, Age at least 18 years.

          6. ECOG performance score of 0-2.

          7. The patient is willing and able to give informed consent and to comply with the
             protocol for the duration of the study.

          8. Haematological and biochemical indices within the ranges shown below:

               1. Haemoglobin (Hb) ≥12.0 g/dL

               2. Platelet count ≥ 100 x 109/L

               3. PT 10-14 seconds

               4. Renal function:

        Serum Creatinine &lt;120 mmol/L OR Calculated GFR &gt;50 ml/min

        Exclusion Criteria (Group A):

          1. Unequivocal evidence of metastatic disease.  Patients with equivocal lesions will be
             determined as eligible on consensus of the MDT.

          2. Previous pelvic radiotherapy.

          3. Pregnant or breast-feeding women, or women of childbearing potential unless effective
             methods of contraception are used.

          4. Treatment with any other investigational agent, or participation in another
             interventional clinical trial within 28 days prior to enrolment.

          5. Currently taking anti-coagulants

          6. Patients who for any reason are unable to undergo MRI and/or CT scans as per local
             guidelines e.g. if they are fitted with a pacemaker, have metal fragments in or
             around the eye, cannot tolerate the scan for any reason or are allergic to contrast
             agents.

          7. Patients who are known to be serologically positive for Hepatitis B, Hepatitis C or
             HIV.

        Exclusion Criteria (Group B):

          1. Previous pelvic radiotherapy (including brachytherapy)

          2. Unequivocal evidence of metastatic disease.  Patients with equivocal lesions will be
             determined as eligible on consensus of the MDT.

          3. Pregnant or breast-feeding women, or women of childbearing potential unless effective
             methods of contraception are used.

          4. Currently taking anti-coagulants

          5. Gastrointestinal disorder which would interfere with oral therapy and its
             bioavailability

          6. Treatment with any other investigational agent, or participation in another clinical
             trial within 28 days prior to enrolment.

          7. Other psychological, social or medical condition, physical examination finding or a
             laboratory abnormality that the Investigator considers would make the patient a poor
             trial candidate or could interfere with protocol compliance or the interpretation of
             trial results.

          8. Patients who for any reason are unable to undergo MRI and/or CT scans as per local
             guidelines e.g. they are fitted with a pacemaker, have metal fragments in or around
             the eye, cannot tolerate the scan for any reason or are allergic to contrast agents.

          9. Patients who are known to be serologically positive for Hepatitis B, Hepatitis C or
             HIV.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tim Maughan</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Oxford</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Naomi McGregor</last_name>
    <phone>+44 1865 227192</phone>
    <email>rhythm@octo-oxford.org.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Claire Brooks</last_name>
    <phone>+44 1865 227161</phone>
    <email>claire.brooks@oncology.ox.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oxford University Hospitals NHS Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oxford</city>
        <zip>OX3 7LE</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maughan</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.octo-oxford.org.uk</url>
    <description>Click here for more information</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 10, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hypoxia</keyword>
  <keyword>rectal cancer</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Rectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anoxia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Pimonidazole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluoromisonidazole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
