<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="124345">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01856673</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HA-UV-JHU-2013-001</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1138-4894</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01856673</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Two Community-based Mental Health Interventions Afrocolombian Victims of Violence</brief_title>
  <acronym>AFROTRAUMACO</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Two Mental Health Interventions, Based on the Community, for the Afro-Colombian Population Victims of Violence</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidad del Valle, Colombia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Heartland Alliance for Human Needs and Human Rights</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>United States Agency for International Development (USAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidad del Valle, Colombia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Colombia: Ministry of Health and Social Protection</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a community prevention randomized trial with three parallel groups: two
      intervention groups and one control group in each city.

      The aim of the trial is to evaluate the impact of two community interventions on mental
      health designed to decrease symptoms of depression, anxiety, and post-traumatic stress
      disorders in Afro-Colombians victims of violence in two Colombian cities: Buenaventura and
      Quibdó.

      Adult persons (equal or more than 18 years old) belonging to Afro-Colombian communities in
      both cities will participate in the enter survey. The subjects will be selected based on the
      severity of symptoms and level of dysfunction identified using the instruments of this
      research; i.e. those obtaining an score equal or higher than 49.

      The fieldwork and the interventions will be conducted by people belonging to the community;
      they are called Mental Health Community Workers (MHCW). After six weeks of formal training,
      they will be able to perform the interventions: 1) Component-based Intervention (CBI) and 2)
      Community Therapy Group Intervention (CTI) for those people affected by violence and
      displacement that were pre-selected according to the baseline instrument.

      The MHCW will be under the constant supervision by psychologists of the project, and under
      weekly supervision by a group of experts of Johns Hopkins University, the Heartland Alliance
      and the CISALVA Institute by means of phone calls or Skype. Selected subjects will be
      randomly allocated to any study branch: CBI, CTI or the waiting control group.

      The study subjects will follow their allocated treatment, or waiting control, during 8 to 12
      weeks; then they will be re-assessed using the project instrument.

      The study outcome is the differences in instrument scores between the follow-up and the
      baseline.

      Control subjects will be assessed by the project psychologist after the follow-up, and they
      will receive treatment when necessary.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Colombian armed conflict primarily affects rural communities, and it has caused
      thousands of deaths and displacement of large number of people from rural areas toward the
      two most important cities in Pacific coast region: Buenaventura in Valle del Cauca province
      and Quibdó in Chocó province.

      This project will assess a treatment with cognitive-behavioral therapy approach to reduce
      mental symptoms triggered by violence and will develop mechanisms for a sustainable supply
      of mental health services in the region.

      Adult Afrocolombian persons who have responded to the study survey but present symptoms of
      severe mental illness like schizophrenic, psychotic, suicidal attempters, and those who can
      potentially harm others, or who require specialized treatment will not be included in the
      study.

      They will be referred to a project psychologist who will determine whether they require
      psychiatric treatment, in which case, they will be referred to health institutions through
      social workers who will ensure treatment is given. Finally, anyone who is related with the
      MHCW will be considered as exclusion.

      For the CBI arm, new clients will be enrolled as long as treatment place becomes available
      (i.e., as long as previous clients completed the treatment), thus to keep the providers
      (MHCW) running at full capacity. These new clients will be chosen from those randomly
      allocated to receive CBI. On completion of treatment, they will be reassessed within fifteen
      (15) days after completing the treatment.

      Similarly, for the CTI arm new groups will be formed as long as place becomes available
      (i.e, as long as previous groups finished), thus to keep providers running at full capacity.
      Group members will be chosen from those randomly allocated to receive CTI, selecting enough
      persons at each time to fill up a group before a group begins. All group members will be
      reassessed within fifteen (15) days after finishing the CTI.

      Those allocated to the control group will undergo a waiting period similar to the period
      between the initial and final assessments of those receiving CBI or CTI. This period could
      be 3 months, but it could be longer if there are treatment delays. At the end of this time,
      the participants will be reassessed.

      For controls, after they are reassessed, they will be evaluated and receive professional
      attention by psychologists to decide what is the best intervention that we can offer to the
      clients in both cities.

      The anticipated results will be the reduction in symptoms of anxiety, depression and
      post-traumatic stress disorders in 20 points among subjects in intervention groups (CBI or
      CTI) compared with those in the control group.

      Also, an adherence of 70% is expected, and to generate strategies for the promotion and
      prevention in mental health for Afro-Colombian victims of violence and displacement.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Investigator), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Score Difference in symptoms of anxiety, depression and post-traumatic stress disorders.</measure>
    <time_frame>Within the fifteen (15) days after finishing the intervention, either Component-Based Intervention (CBI) or Community Therapy group Intervention (CTI). In the control group, 12 weeks after the baseline assessment.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Difference in scores of symptoms of anxiety, depression and post-traumatic stress disorders between the subject's baseline and the final assessments according to the study instrument.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">432</enrollment>
  <condition>Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <condition>Violence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ARM 1: Component-Based Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Component-Based Intervention (CBI) only</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ARM 2: Community Therapy Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Community Therapy Intervention (CTI) only</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ARM 3: Standby group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standby group without intervention, but under monthly monitoring.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Component-Based Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>It was developed for treating symptoms related to violent trauma, i.e. symptoms of depression, anxiety and distress, among victimized population by violence and torture in Colombia. The most relevant components for treatment of these 3 problematic issues were identified from literature review and panel of experts. Descriptions and schemes have been developed in order to guarantee facility of use by community counselors who have little background in mental health skills. These counselors, who will be called Mental Health Community Workers (MHCW), will receive training in this technique before beginning of interventions. Application of this technique will be supervised constantly by mental health professionals (psychologist or social worker) from the project team.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ARM 1: Component-Based Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CBI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Community Therapy Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>It consists on teaching skills to people in the community to provide mental health therapy. Therapy will be performed by MHCW under constant supervision of mental health professionals (psychologists or social workers). Sessions will begin with a series of introductory activities that motivates participants to propose different problems that they would like to solve in the group. A participant proposed a problem and he/she will be asked to talk about it. MHCW and/or psychologist will support individuals if anyone needs help to solve a psychological crisis. At the end of this narration, participants will be asked about who has had a similar situation, and how they solved it. In this way, proposed solutions will be collected by the MHCW. Finally, session closes with a motivating activity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ARM 2: Community Therapy Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CTI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standby group</intervention_name>
    <description>Standby group: they will be assessed at baseline with the initial survey and they will wait between 10 and 12 weeks; then an exit assessment will be performed with the study instrument. After the exit survey, control group participants will have an appointment with a professional psychologist to determine whether they require a mental health treatment. Those with such necessity will receive treatment in the ACOPLE center by professional psychologists or they will be referred to other health care level according to the type of psychopathology (e.g., psychosis) or its severity. Also, participants in the control group will be monitoring monthly by phone calls and if they have any psychological problem, they will be assessed in the ACOPLE center.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ARM 3: Standby group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults (18 years of age or older) Afro-Colombian victims of violence and torture who
             have expressed sadness, suffering psychological trauma caused by violence and when
             the situation was known by the leaders of AFRODES or the community leaders contacted
             by the research team.

          -  Persons with a total symptomatic value greater than or equal to 49 points in the
             study instrument, with the presence of trauma from violence, and a loss of
             functionality score greater than zero.

          -  Individuals who signed the informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  People of ethnicities other than Afro-Colombian.

          -  Children under 18 years old.

          -  Persons who present symptoms of severe mental illness such as schizophrenia,
             psychotic episodes, suicidal attempters, and those who potentially could harm others.

          -  Anyone who is related with the counselors (CMHW).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>María Isabel Gutiérrez Martínez, MD, MSc, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>CISALVA Institute of Universidad del Valle, Colombia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrés Fandiño Losada, MD, MSc, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CISALVA Institute of Universidad del Valle, Colombia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Francisco Javier Bonilla Escobar, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CISALVA Institute of Universidad del Valle, Colombia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Diana Milena Martínez Buitrago, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CISALVA Institute of Universidad del Valle, Colombia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Julián Santaella, VMD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CISALVA Institute of Universidad del Valle, Colombia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>María Isabel Gutiérrez Martínez, MD, MSc, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+57-2-5577206</phone>
    <phone_ext>103</phone_ext>
    <email>maria.gutierrez@correounivalle.edu.co</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Andrés Fandiño Losada, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>+57-2-5577206</phone>
    <phone_ext>103</phone_ext>
    <email>carlos.fandino@correounivalle.edu.co</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro ACOPLE de Quibdó</name>
      <address>
        <city>Quibdó</city>
        <state>Chocó</state>
        <country>Colombia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Diego Fernando Rodríguez, Psychologist</last_name>
      <phone>+57-3187123672</phone>
      <email>drodriguez@heartlandalliance.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Francisco Javier Bonilla Escobar, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+57-3017829015</phone>
      <email>fjbonillaescobar@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Francisco Javier Bonilla Escobar, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Diana Milena Martínez Buitrago, MD, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro ACOPLE de Buenaventura</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buenaventura</city>
        <state>Valle del Cauca</state>
        <country>Colombia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sandra Canaval, Psychologist</last_name>
      <phone>+57-3186964801</phone>
      <email>scanaval@heartlandalliance.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Francisco Javier Escobar Bonilla, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+57-3017829015</phone>
      <email>fjbonillaescobar@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Diana Milena Martínez Buitrago, MD, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Francisco Javier Bonilla Escobar, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Colombia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cisalva.univalle.edu.co</url>
    <description>Research Center: CISALVA Institute of Universidad del Valle, Colombia</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://heartlandalliance.org</url>
    <description>Sponsor: Heartland Alliance for Human Needs and Human Rights</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://uvsalud.univalle.edu.co</url>
    <description>Institutional Review Board</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sjölund BH, Kastrup M, Montgomery E, Persson AL. Rehabilitating torture survivors. J Rehabil Med. 2009 Sep;41(9):689-96. doi: 10.2340/16501977-0426.</citation>
    <PMID>19774300</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bisson J, Andrew M. Psychological treatment of post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD). Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2007 Jul 18;(3):CD003388. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17636720</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kinzie JD. Psychotherapy for massively traumatized refugees: the therapist variable. Am J Psychother. 2001;55(4):475-90.</citation>
    <PMID>11824215</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 14, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 14, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidad del Valle, Colombia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Maria Isabel Gutiérrez Martínez</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mental Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Displacement</keyword>
  <keyword>Torture</keyword>
  <keyword>Violence</keyword>
  <keyword>Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>Community-based intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Community prevention trial</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Traumatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
