<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="42024">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02119624</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>140094</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>14-AA-0094</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02119624</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neural Substrates of Approach-Avoidance Conflict</brief_title>
  <official_title>Neural Substrate of Approach Avoidance in Alcoholism</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - People who are dependent on alcohol drink even when they know something bad might happen.
      Researchers want to learn more about why they do this.

      Objectives:

      - To study brain response when a person plays a game in different threat conditions.

      Eligibility:

        -  Healthy right-handed adult heavy drinkers age 21   60

        -  Healthy right-handed adult light drinkers age 21   60

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with medical history, physical exam, and blood and urine
           tests. They will have an EKG and psychiatric interview.

        -  Participants will have one or two clinic visits.

        -  Participants will be asked about their alcohol drinking.

        -  They will choose a snack and alcoholic beverage that they must drink in 5 minutes.
           After their breath alcohol content (BrAC) is zero, they will play a game in the MRI
           scanner.

        -  The scanner is a metal cylinder that takes pictures of the brain. Participants lie on a
           table that slides in and out of the cylinder. They will be in it for about 90 minutes,
           lying still for up to 20 minutes.

        -  During the MRI, participants will play a simple computer game to earn food or drink
           points under different threats of electric shock. Points can be exchanged for food or
           alcohol after the game. Sometimes, participants will receive a mild electric shock
           through a metal disk on the wrist. Electric shocks will only happen if the participant
           tries to earn a reward point.

        -  After the MRI, participants use their points for another drink and snack. They will
           stay at the clinic until their BrAC is low, usually within 3 hours. Participants cannot
           drive themselves home.

        -  Participants will have a follow-up phone call the next day.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective: Continued drug seeking despite knowledge of adverse consequences is a hallmark of
      addiction. To model this behavior, we will refine the parameters of a modified Monetary
      Incentive Delay (MID) task that will allow us to investigate neural substrates of
      approach-avoidance conflict resolution. We will then use this task to investigate functional
      magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) brain activation during pursuit of reward in heavy and
      light drinkers.

      Study Population: Healthy non-treatment-seeking heavy drinkers and healthy light drinkers
      aged 21 to 60.

      Design: The study will require 1 to 2 visits. Subjects will play a modified MID task called
      Reward Incentive Delay with Shock (RIDS) to measure motivation to earn cue reward points in
      conditions that are signaled to be safe or associated with a threat. After playing the RIDS
      task subjects will be able to self-administer alcohol and/or food based on the reward points
      earned during the task.

      Outcome measures: The outcome measures are differences in behavioral task performance and in
      blood oxygenation dependent level (BOLD) signal measured using standard fMRI techniques and
      analyzed using AFNI software.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>These include behavioral and imaging data, which will help to determine differences between heavy drinking and light drinking participants on bases of their behavioral and functional imaging data (e.g., BOLD signal).</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Alcoholism</condition>
  <condition>fMRI</condition>
  <condition>Rewarding Mediating System</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  Inclusion criteria (Light Drinkers):

               1. In good health as determined by medical history, physical exam, ECG, and lab
                  tests;

               2. Between 21 and 60 years of age;

               3. Currently consuming between 1 and 10 drinks per week for females and 1 and 14
                  drinks per week for males;

               4. Right handed.

        Exclusion criteria (Light Drinkers):

          1. Have liver function tests (AST, ALT, GGT, ALP) 3-times the upper limit of normal
             (ULN); or have Total Bilirubin above 1.5 ULN and Albumin below 3.5 g/dl;

          2. Have fulfilled DSM-IV-TR criteria for alcohol or other substance dependence
             (excluding nicotine) at any time;

          3. Report having received any medication to treat a psychiatric disorder within the past
             year, have a past or present diagnosis of a psychotic or bipolar disorder, or have
             ever had a head injury requiring hospitalization;

          4. Weigh over 330 pounds;

          5. Are pregnant, as determined by a positive pregnancy test, or breast feeding;

          6. Report to have a &quot;facial flushing&quot; response to the consumption of alcohol

          7. Have ferromagnetic objects in their bodies which might be adversely affected by MRI
             including implanted pacemakers, medication pumps, aneurysm clips; metallic prostheses
             (including metal pins and rods, heart valves or cochlear implants, shrapnel
             fragments, permanent eye liner or small metal fragments in the eye that welders and
             other metal works may have     any doubt about presence of these objects will result
             in exclusion from this study), or if candidates are uncomfortable in small closed
             spaces (have claustrophobia), or cannot lie comfortably on their back for up to one
             hour;

          8. Medical illnesses (such as diabetes or hypertension) or neurological illnesses
             (carpal tunnel syndrome; migraine headaches; seizure disorders) likely to interfere
             with the study;

          9. Endorse more than 3 symptoms on the Yale Food Addiction Scale;

         10. Have colorblindness.

        Inclusion criteria (Heavy Drinkers):

          1. In good health as determined by medical history, physical exam, ECG, and lab tests;

          2. Between 21 and 60 years of age;

          3. Currently consuming 15+ drinks for females and 20+ drinks for males;

          4. Right-handed;

          5. Not regularly abstinent for more than 3 days per week, but have abstained from
             alcohol for 3 consecutive days without experiencing withdrawal symptoms;

          6. Able to provide a plausible history that they can abstain from alcohol without
             significant withdrawal symptoms when coming to the clinic. In addition, participants
             will be asked to quantify their worst withdrawal symptoms using the Clinical
             Institute Withdrawal Assessment (CIWA) Instrument. Participants who score 8 or above
             will not be enrolled in the protocol;

          7. Not seeking treatment for their alcohol consumption.

        Exclusion criteria (Heavy Drinkers):

        All exclusion criteria for Light Drinkers except the following:

        Have fulfilled DSM-IV criteria for any substance dependence (excluding alcohol or
        nicotine) at any time.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Reza Momenan, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Erica Grodin</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-5630</phone>
    <email>grodin@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Reza Momenan, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-6972</phone>
    <email>rezam@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2014-AA-0094.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adolphs R, Tranel D, Damasio H, Damasio AR. Fear and the human amygdala. J Neurosci. 1995 Sep;15(9):5879-91.</citation>
    <PMID>7666173</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alvarez RP, Biggs A, Chen G, Pine DS, Grillon C. Contextual fear conditioning in humans: cortical-hippocampal and amygdala contributions. J Neurosci. 2008 Jun 11;28(24):6211-9. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1246-08.2008.</citation>
    <PMID>18550763</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aupperle RL, Paulus MP. Neural systems underlying approach and avoidance in anxiety disorders. Dialogues Clin Neurosci. 2010;12(4):517-31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21319496</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 30, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 17, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neural Networks</keyword>
  <keyword>Alcoholism</keyword>
  <keyword>fMRI</keyword>
  <keyword>Reward</keyword>
  <keyword>Addiction</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Alcoholism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
