<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="45287">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01994226</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>149/11</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01994226</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Colchicine Or Naproxen Treatment for ACute gouT</brief_title>
  <acronym>CONTACT</acronym>
  <official_title>Multi-centre, Open-label, Active-comparator, Pragmatic Clinical Trial of Low-dose Colchicine Versus Naproxen in Patients With Acute Gout.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Keele University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Keele University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Gout is the most common cause of inflamed joints affecting 1.4% of adults in the UK. Most
      patients are treated entirely in general practice yet primary care management is frequently
      suboptimal. Acute attacks of gout are excruciatingly painful and require urgent drug
      treatment to reduce inflammation, most commonly with antiinflammatory drugs(NSAIDs) or
      colchicine. In primary care, NSAIDs are most commonly used but can cause serious side
      effects such as stomach ulcers and heart disease, particularly in the elderly. Patients
      frequently require repeat prescriptions for recurrent attacks of acute gout increasing the
      risk of drug-related side-effects. Low-dose colchicine is popular amongst rheumatologists as
      it is effective and well tolerated. However, general practitioners (GPs) prescribe
      colchicine infrequently, probably because in the past the recommendation was for high doses
      to be prescribed which commonly caused severe diarrhoea. Recently, prescribing
      recommendations for colchicine have changed, advocating a lower dose regime.

      Currently there is no evidence regarding whether NSAIDs or low-dose colchicine is the best
      treatment for acute gout. This trial will be the first direct comparison of the
      effectiveness and side effects of a NSAID (naproxen) and low-dose colchicine to treat acute
      gout in primary care. Naproxen will be used in this trial because it has been shown to be as
      effective as oral prednisolone for the treatment of acute gout, is safer than other commonly
      used NSAIDs such as diclofenac and indomethacin, and is inexpensive.

      Patients consulting their GP with an acute attack of gout in up to 100 general practices
      will be invited to participate. Treatment success will be assessed by comparing pain
      reduction between the two drugs. The trial will also monitor side effects, quality of life,
      and cost effectiveness.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pain intensity</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 0-7, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Gout</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low-dose colchicine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>500 mcg every eight hours for four days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Naproxen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single initial dose of 750 mg followed by 250 mg every eight hours for up to seven days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Low-dose colchicine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Low-dose colchicine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Naproxen</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Naproxen</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults aged 18 years and over

          -  Consultation with GP, primary care out-of-hours service or walk-in-centre

          -  Current attack of acute gout (first attack or recurrent).

          -  Patient has capacity and willingness to give consent and complete the trial
             paperwork

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known unstable medical conditions (such as ischaemic heart disease, impaired liver
             function)

          -  Known stage 4/5 kidney disease (eGFR/creatinine clearance &lt;30ml/min)

          -  Recent surgery or gastrointestinal bleed

          -  History of gastric ulcer

          -  Current anticoagulant use

          -  Allergy to aspirin/NSAID

          -  Previous inability to tolerate naproxen or low-dose colchicine

          -  Other contraindication to either study drug in accordance with the Summary of Product
             Characteristics (SPC)

          -  Prescription of naproxen or colchicine in the previous 24 hours

          -  Pregnant or lactating females

          -  Potentially vulnerable

          -  Previous participation in the CONTACT trial during a previous acute attack of gout.

          -  Involvement in another clinical trial of an investigational medicinal product in the
             last 90 days or any other research within the last 30 days
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Liz Hartshorne</last_name>
    <phone>01782 734859</phone>
    <email>nstccg.keelecontact@nhs.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 19, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 19, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Gout</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Naproxen</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colchicine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
