<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="158139">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01993693</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ZetrOZ-3</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01993693</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Wearable Therapeutic Ultrasound Study for Knee Osteoarthritis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Wearable Therapeutic Ultrasound Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>ZetrOZ, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>State University of New York - Upstate Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>ZetrOZ, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Unites States: State University of New York Upstate Medical University Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the ability of a wearable therapeutic ultrasound
      device to reduce pain and increase mobility for subjects with knee osteoarthritis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Up to 50 million people in the U.S. suffer from some form of chronic pain, and 60% of these
      Americans are under 65 and have limited mobility because of knee or hip Osteoarthritis (OA).
       Pharmaceuticals currently dominate the treatment options due to widespread insurance
      coverage and convenience.  However, there are a myriad of public health problems associated
      with analgesic use, including costs, untoward side effects, and addiction potential with
      opioid analgesics.

      Ultrasound therapy for pain and healing has been approved by the U.S. FDA and has been in
      use around the globe for the last 60 years. Traditionally, ultrasound-mediated pain
      treatment has been delivered in clinics and has been limited to short and confined periods
      of 5-15 min at acoustic intensities from 1-4 W/cm2 over a course of weeks to months. Over
      the past decade, research has increasingly focused on lower-intensity therapeutic ultrasound
      (30-1000 mW/cm2) delivered over extended 1-8 hr periods. Recent animal studies using
      low-intensity therapeutic ultrasound (LITUS) have demonstrated successful inflammation
      reduction, reduced cartilage degeneration, and tendon and fracture healing. It is believed
      that using a lower-intensity ultrasonic treatment regimen over extended treatment periods
      works with the body's natural healing process and minimizes acoustic insult as compared with
      traditional, higher intensity treatments. This study proposes to evaluate clinically the
      first wearable low intensity ultrasound system for noninvasive treatment of arthritis pain.
      This technology has the potential to measurably increase the quality of life for millions of
      people who suffer from osteoarthritis pain by providing a safe, effective, and easy-to-use
      treatment.

      The pilot study will test the versatile ultrasound therapy system in a clinical study that
      will enroll up to 60 patients with mobility-impairing knee OA. The goal of the study  is to
      establish statistically significant data that daily 4 hour LITUS treatment decreases
      participant pain (Visual Analog Scale [VAS]) and improves patient mobility (measured by an
      accelerometer worn by each participant) over placebo devices.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Pain will be recorded twice a day, immediately before application of the device and then immediately after the 4 hour treatment.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Pain will be recorded using the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mobility</measure>
    <time_frame>Mobility will be recorded logged every 5 minutes, up to 24 hours a day, by the actigraph that the subject is wearing on their wrist.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Mobility will be measured using an actigraph that will be worn on the subject's wrist 24 hours a day.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Knee Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ultrasonic Diathermy Device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Therapeutic ultrasound used daily.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Ultrasonic Diathermy Device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sham device that does not deliver ultrasound</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ultrasonic Diathermy Device</intervention_name>
    <description>The Ultrasonic Diathermy Device provides low intensity therapeutic ultrasound to musculoskeletal tissues and joints for the purpose of pain relief, relief of muscle spasm, treatment of joint contraction, and local increase of circulation. The device is FDA-cleared for up to 4 hours of continuous use per treatment. It is a stationary hands-free device.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ultrasonic Diathermy Device</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>sam</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Individual will be included if they:

          1. Have physician-diagnosed mild to moderate knee OA (OARSI atlas grades 1-2) based on
             fixed-flexion x-ray radiological findings for osteophytes and joint space narrowing
             within the past 12 months,

          2. are between 35-65 years of age

          3. report a frequent pain score between 4-7 (range: 0-10) during the week preceding
             enrollment

          4. report mobility limitations because of their knee pain

          5. are currently not taking any prescription pain medication other than nonsteroidal
             antiinflammatory drugs (NSAIDs).  All pain medication taken during the study should
             be documented.

          6. are willing not to use any cream, gel, or topical solution during the administration
             of treatment other than the approved ultrasound gel provided to the subject at the
             initiation of the study

          7. are deemed appropriate by their physician to participate.

        Individuals will be excluded if they:

          1. cannot successfully demonstrate the ability to put on and take off the device

          2. are cognitively impaired

          3. have bone-on-bone crepitus

          4. have severe OA or patients with little to no cartilage on the knee

          5. have knee replacement or other surgical intervention

          6. take variable prescription medication

          7. are non-ambulatory

          8. participated in a clinical trial for an investigational drug and/or agent within 30
             days prior to screening

          9. are currently taking neuropathic medications (ie: Neurontin, Lyrica or Topamax)
             and/or antidepressants (ie: Amitriptyline).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Timothy A. Damron, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>SUNY Upstate Orthopedics</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Vanessa Levine</last_name>
    <phone>(973)727-1951</phone>
    <email>vlevine@zetroz.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Upstate Orthopedics</name>
      <address>
        <city>East Syracuse</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>13057</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tina Craig, CCRP</last_name>
      <phone>315-464-8618</phone>
      <email>tcraig@upstate.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Vanessa Levine, MS</last_name>
      <phone>(973)727-1951</phone>
      <email>vlevine@zetroz.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Timothy Damron, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>George Lewis, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 24, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>knee</keyword>
  <keyword>pain</keyword>
  <keyword>osteoarthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>ultrasound</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
