<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="164804">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01889797</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PrE0401</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>BO25454</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01889797</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase II Randomized Trial Comparing GA101 and Rituximab in Untreated Low Tumor Burden Indolent Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <acronym>PrE0401</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase II Randomized Trial Comparing GA101 (Obinutuzumab) and Rituximab in Patients With Previously Untreated Low Tumor Burden Indolent Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>PrECOG, LLC.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genentech</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>PrECOG, LLC.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients with previously untreated low tumor burden indolent Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma (NHL)
      will receive either rituximab or GA101 weekly for 4 weeks followed by re-staging to
      determine response.

      Rituximab, an anti-CD20 chimeric antibody, was approved by the United States Food and Drug
      Administration in 1998 for the treatment of patients with relapsed low-grade B-cell
      lymphomas. Clinically, four weekly doses of rituximab have proven to be well tolerated and
      effective in previously untreated as well as relapsed patients with low-grade lymphoma.

      GA101 is an anti-CD20 humanized and glyco-engineered monoclonal antibody. GA101 has been
      shown to have increased antibody-dependent cellular cytotoxicity (ADCC) and direct
      cell-death induction compared to Rituximab. It is possible that GA101 may have greater
      efficacy than rituximab.

      PrE0401 Sub-Study Evaluation of Corrected QT (QTc) Interval and Pharmacokinetic Parameters
      in Patients Participating in GA101 (Obinutuzumab)

      Approximately twenty-five patients randomized to GA101 may participate in the sub-study.
      Electrocardiograms and blood samples will be obtained.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      According to the American Cancer Society, it is estimated that approximately 70,800
      individuals will be diagnosed with non-Hodgkin's lymphoma (NHL) and over 18,990 men and
      women will die of the disease in 2014. The survival rates for patients with indolent NHL
      remained unchanged from the 1950s through the early 1990s, but recent evidence suggests that
      outcomes are improving. Indolent NHL is a particular challenge because it is an incurable
      disease requiring multiple treatments; yet relatively long survivals elevate the importance
      of quality of life associated with treatment.

      Agents such as rituximab are active in patients with a low burden of disease and result in
      high response rates and durable remissions for most patients. However, the optimal
      therapeutic approach to patients with low-grade lymphoma with a low disease burden is
      controversial as conventional chemotherapy also results in high rates of response.
      Regardless of whether patients receive immunotherapy, chemotherapy, or a combination
      thereof, they unfortunately exhibit a continuing pattern of disease relapse and the median
      survival for newly diagnosed patients is between 7-10 years.

      Rituximab and GA101 both target the CD20 antigen. The CD20 antigen is located on the surface
      of normal and malignant B-cell lymphocytes. An attractive feature of this target is that
      CD20 is not on hematopoietic stem cells, nor is it expressed in any great extent on other
      normal body tissues.

      Studies in vitro have shown that rituximab predominantly induces antibody dependent cellular
      cytotoxicity (ADCC), but also binds complement and directly induces apoptosis in lymphoma
      cells.

      GA101 shows increased ADCC related to an improved binding of the GA101 to the different
      allotypes expressed by natural killer cells and monocytes. It also has increased direct
      cell-death related to an elbow hinge amino acid exchange and Type II binding of the CD20
      epitope. The safety of GA101 in NHL so far appears to be similar to that observed with
      rituximab in patients with NHL, except for a higher incidence of infusion-related reactions.

      Depletion of malignant B-cells using anti-CD20 monoclonal antibodies has an acceptable
      safety profile, particularly in patients with low-grade B-cell lymphomas with a low disease
      burden. To determine whether treatment with GA101 results in better outcomes than that seen
      with rituximab and to determine which anti-CD20 antibody to utilize in future studies, we
      will conduct a randomized Phase II trial of rituximab and GA101 in patients with previously
      untreated low-grade lymphoma. Patients will receive either rituximab or GA101 weekly for 4
      weeks followed by re-staging. The endpoints of the study will be the Complete Response (CR),
      Overall Response Rate (ORR), time to next treatment, progression free survival (PFS), and
      safety of each treatment arm.

      PrE0401 Sub-Study Evaluation of Corrected QT (QTc) Interval and Pharmacokinetic Parameters
      in Patients Participating in GA101 (Obinutuzumab)

      Patients randomized to GA101 and who consent to the sub-study will have electrocardiograms
      obtained pre and post Week 1 and Week 4 to investigate the effect of GA101 on QTc interval.
      Pharmacokinetic blood samples will also be done to evaluate serum concentrations of GA101 at
      the same time-points.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete Response (CR) Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Re-staging (week 12, 13 or 14) and during follow-up if physician feels patient is subsequently in CR for up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Positron Emission Tomography (PET)-documented CR rates after induction therapy (weekly treatment x 4 weeks with GA101 or rituximab)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PET Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Re-staging (week 12, 13 or 14)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PET response rate [PET-documented CR + Partial Response (PR)] based on PET scan results.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Re-staging (week 12, 13 or 14)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall response rate (CR + PR by Cheson criteria) at re-staging (including bone marrow biopsy if CR suspected) by PET and Neck, Chest, Abdomen and Pelvic Computed Tomography (CT) scan.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Next Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 3 months for 2 years, then every 6 months for up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Next treatment is defined as any monoclonal antibody treatment, immunological therapy (such as vaccines), chemotherapy, radiotherapy, or radioimmunotherapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 3 months for 2 years, then every 6 months for up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>CT scan every 6 months until progression. Compare PFS in each treatment arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Weekly x 4 weeks and Re-Staging (week 12, 13 or 14)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Adverse event rates, exposure and laboratory data by treatment arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cytokine Profile</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Re-Staging (week 12, 13 or 14)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Descriptive statistics of changes, such as malignant B-cells, will be reported.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Bank Biospecimens for Retrospective Examination</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Re-Staging (week 12, 13 or 14)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To bank biospecimens for retrospective examination of FcGammaR (FcRIIIA) polymorphisms and correlation with responses to antibody therapy and GA101.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Bank Biospecimens for Future Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Re-Staging (week 12, 13 or 14)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To bank biospecimens for future assessment of biomarkers of prognosis and/or response.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Indolent Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: Rituximab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Rituximab 375 mg/m² IV weekly for 4 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: GA101</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>GA101 1,000 mg IV weekly for 4 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Arm A: Rituximab</intervention_name>
    <description>Rituximab 375 mg/m² IV x 4 weekly doses.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: Rituximab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IDEC-C2B8</other_name>
    <other_name>Chimeric anti-CD20 monoclonal antibody</other_name>
    <other_name>Rituxan</other_name>
    <other_name>NSC# 687451</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Arm B: GA101</intervention_name>
    <description>GA101 1,000 mg (flat dose) IV x 4 weekly doses.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: GA101</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Obinutuzumab</other_name>
    <other_name>RO5072759</other_name>
    <other_name>huMAB&lt;CD20&gt;</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Registration: Patients having both diffuse and follicular architectural elements will be
        considered eligible if the histology is predominantly follicular (≥ 50% of the
        cross-sectional area), and there is no evidence of transformation to a large cell
        histology.

          -  Biopsy-proven diagnosis of Grade 1 or 2 follicular non-Hodgkin's lymphoma with no
             evidence of transformation to large cell histology.

          -  Meet criteria for Low Tumor Burden:

               -  No nodal or extra nodal mass ≥ 7 centimeter (cm)

               -  &lt;3 nodal masses &gt;3 cm in diameter

               -  No systemic symptoms or B symptoms

               -  No splenomegaly &gt;16 cm by CT scan

               -  No risk of compression of a vital organ.

               -  No leukemic phase with &gt;5000/mm³ circulating lymphocytes.

          -  No cytopenias defined as:

               -  Platelets &lt;100,000/mm³

               -  Hemoglobin (Hgb) &lt;10 g/dL

               -  Absolute Neutrophil Count (ANC) &lt;1500/mm³

          -  Must have Stage III or Stage IV disease.

          -  Baseline measurements/evaluations obtained within 6 weeks of registration. Patient
             must have at least one objective measurable disease parameter.

          -  Age ≥ 18 years.

          -  Eastern Oncology Cooperative Group Performance Status 0-1.

          -  Must not have received investigational agents within 30 days of registration.

          -  Signed Institutional Review Board (IRB)-approved informed consent.

          -  Willing to provide blood samples for research purposes.

          -  Women must not be pregnant or breastfeeding.

          -  Women of childbearing potential and sexually active males must use an accepted and
             effective method of contraception.

          -  No prior chemotherapy, radiotherapy or immunotherapy for lymphoma.

          -  No prior treatment with cytotoxic drugs or rituximab for a previous cancer or another
             condition (e.g. rheumatoid arthritis) or prior use of an anti-CD20 antibody.

          -  No prior use of any monoclonal antibody within 3 months of randomization.

          -  No history of severe allergic/anaphylactic reactions to humanized/murine monoclonal
             antibodies or known sensitivity/allergy to murine products.

          -  No history of prior malignancy except for adequately treated basal cell or squamous
             cell skin cancer, in situ cervical cancer, or other cancer for which the patient has
             been disease-free for at least 2 years and did not require treatment with cytotoxic
             drugs or rituximab.

          -  No major surgery within 4 weeks prior to randomization, other than for diagnosis.

          -  Must be Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) negative.

          -  Have adequate organ function without growth factor and/or transfusion support within
             ≤ 2 weeks prior to registration:

               -  ANC ≥ 1500/mm³

               -  Hgb ≥ 10 g/dL

               -  Platelets ≥ 100,000/mm³

               -  Serum Creatinine ≤ 2x Upper Limit Normal (ULN)

               -  Total Bilirubin ≤ 2x ULN

               -  AST (aspartate aminotransferase)/ALT (alanine aminotransferase) ≤ 5x ULN

               -  PTT (Partial Thromboplastin Time) or aPTT (activated Partial Thromboplastin
                  Time) &gt;1.5x the ULN in the absence of a lupus anticoagulant

               -  INR (International Normalized Ratio) &gt;1.5x the ULN in the absence of therapeutic
                  anticoagulation

          -  No active, uncontrolled infections (afebrile for ≥ 48 hours off antibiotics).

          -  Must not receive immunization with attenuated live vaccines within 28 days prior to
             registration or during the study period.

          -  Must be tested for hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) and total hepatitis B core
             antibody (anti-HBc) within 2 weeks of registration. Patients who are chronic carriers
             of HBsAg and anti-HBc are excluded.

          -  Must be tested for hepatitis C antibody within 2 week of registration. If this test
             is positive, patients are excluded unless a hepatitis C virus ribonucleic acid (HCV
             RNA) is negative.

          -  No evidence of significant, uncontrolled concomitant diseases that could affect
             compliance with the protocol or interpretation of results, including significant
             cardiovascular disease (i.e., severe arrhythmia, myocardial infarction within the
             previous 6 months, unstable arrhythmias, or unstable angina) or pulmonary disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen Ansell, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic in Minnesota</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kelly Walker, RN</last_name>
    <phone>215-789-3634</phone>
    <email>kwalker@precogllc.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of South Alabama</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mobile</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>36604</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pamela Francisco</last_name>
      <phone>251-445-9870</phone>
      <email>pfrancisco@health.southalabama.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Thomas Butler, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic-Arizona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85259</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Daniel Johnson</last_name>
      <phone>480-301-6685</phone>
      <email>johnson.daniel6@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Craig Reeder, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Marin Cancer Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>Greenbrae</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94904</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jaime Chang</last_name>
      <phone>415-925-5040</phone>
      <email>jchang@marinspecialtycare.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jennifer Lucas, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Joseph's/Candler Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Savannah</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>31405</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stephanie Smith</last_name>
      <phone>912-819-5723</phone>
      <email>smiths1@sjchs.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark Taylor, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Decatur Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Decatur</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>62526</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laura Boyd</last_name>
      <phone>217-876-4763</phone>
      <email>LBOYD@dmhhs.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James Wade, III, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Carle Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Urbana</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>61801</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Leslie Schenck</last_name>
      <phone>217-326-0399</phone>
      <email>leslie.schenck@carle.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Wenqing Zhang, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bobbie Frye</last_name>
      <phone>317-274-2992</phone>
      <email>fryeba@iupui.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jose Azar, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Siouxland Hematology Oncology Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sioux City</city>
        <state>Iowa</state>
        <zip>51101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tom Hoopingarner</last_name>
      <phone>712-252-9326</phone>
      <email>shoaresearch@shoa-research.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Donald Wender, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Greater Baltimore Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21204</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Brendan Costello</last_name>
      <phone>443-849-3122</phone>
      <email>bcostello@gbmc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gary Cohen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Joseph Mercy Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shannon Porter</last_name>
      <phone>734-712-2704</phone>
      <email>porters@trinity-health.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christopher Reynolds, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Melissa Plagge</last_name>
      <phone>507-266-3784</phone>
      <email>plagge.melissa@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephen Ansell, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Metro MN CCOP</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis Park</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55416</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Betsy Wagner, RN</last_name>
      <phone>952-993-1555</phone>
      <email>elizabeth.wagner@parknicollet.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Audrey Haas, RN</last_name>
      <phone>952-993-1518</phone>
      <email>Audrey.haas@parknicollet.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joseph Leach, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Missouri Valley Cancer Consortium</name>
      <address>
        <city>Omaha</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Erin Smith</last_name>
      <phone>402-991-8070</phone>
      <phone_ext>201</phone_ext>
      <email>esmith@mvcc.cc</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gamini Soori, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Montefiore Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10467</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jessica Yu</last_name>
      <phone>718-405-8545</phone>
      <email>jeyu@montefiore.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Noah Kornblum, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aultman Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Canton</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Janet Moore, RN</last_name>
      <phone>330-363-1250</phone>
      <email>jmoore@aultman.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James Schmotzer, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Toledo Community Oncology Program</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toledo</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43617</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jessica Ciesler</last_name>
      <phone>419-843-6147</phone>
      <phone_ext>221</phone_ext>
      <email>jciesler@tcop.info</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rex Mowat, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Geisinger Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Danville</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>17822</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Heather Albertson</last_name>
      <phone>570-214-9501</phone>
      <email>halbertson@geisinger.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Edward Gorak, DO</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Reading Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Reading</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anita Wilhelm, RN</last_name>
      <phone>484-628-5232</phone>
      <email>anita.wilhelm@readinghealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Terrence Cescon, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Susquehanna Health Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Williamsport</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>17701</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Susan Miller, RN, OCN</last_name>
      <phone>570-326-8892</phone>
      <email>smiller@susquehannahealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Warren Robinson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gundersen Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Crosse</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>54601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chris Meyer</last_name>
      <phone>608-775-2837</phone>
      <email>cmmeyer2@gundersenhealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Farnen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dean Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53717</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dana Jass, RN</last_name>
      <phone>608-410-2773</phone>
      <email>dana.jass@deancare.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amit Sanyal, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ProHealth Care, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Waukesha</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53188</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chanda Miller</last_name>
      <phone>262-928-5539</phone>
      <email>chanda.miller@phci.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Timothy Wassenaar, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aurora Health Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wauwatosa</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53266</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jan DeBartolo, RN</last_name>
      <phone>414-778-4345</phone>
      <email>Jan.DeBartolo@aurora.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Carol Tutino, RN</last_name>
      <phone>414-649-5526</phone>
      <email>carol.tutino@aurora.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Thompson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hainsworth JD, Litchy S, Burris HA 3rd, Scullin DC Jr, Corso SW, Yardley DA, Morrissey L, Greco FA. Rituximab as first-line and maintenance therapy for patients with indolent non-hodgkin's lymphoma. J Clin Oncol. 2002 Oct 15;20(20):4261-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12377971</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beers SA, Chan CH, French RR, Cragg MS, Glennie MJ. CD20 as a target for therapeutic type I and II monoclonal antibodies. Semin Hematol. 2010 Apr;47(2):107-14. doi: 10.1053/j.seminhematol.2010.01.001. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20350657</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mössner E, Brünker P, Moser S, Püntener U, Schmidt C, Herter S, Grau R, Gerdes C, Nopora A, van Puijenbroek E, Ferrara C, Sondermann P, Jäger C, Strein P, Fertig G, Friess T, Schüll C, Bauer S, Dal Porto J, Del Nagro C, Dabbagh K, Dyer MJ, Poppema S, Klein C, Umaña P. Increasing the efficacy of CD20 antibody therapy through the engineering of a new type II anti-CD20 antibody with enhanced direct and immune effector cell-mediated B-cell cytotoxicity. Blood. 2010 Jun 3;115(22):4393-402. doi: 10.1182/blood-2009-06-225979. Epub 2010 Mar 1.</citation>
    <PMID>20194898</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Salles GA, et al. Efficacy and Safety of Obinutuzumab (GA101) Monotherapy in Relapsed/Refractory Indolent Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma: Results from a Phase I/II Study (BO20999) American Society of Hematology Annual meeting 2011 Abstract 268.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 26, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Untreated Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Low Tumor Burden Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>NHL</keyword>
  <keyword>Indolent</keyword>
  <keyword>Rituximab</keyword>
  <keyword>Rituxan</keyword>
  <keyword>GA101</keyword>
  <keyword>Obinutuzumab</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
