<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="149653">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01884688</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013-05</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01884688</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Autologous Expanded Natural Killer Cell Therapy for Asymptomatic Multiple Myeloma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Autologous Expanded Natural Killer Cell Therapy for Asymptomatic Multiple Myeloma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Arkansas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Arkansas</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the safety and in vivo persistence and expansion
      of autologous and expansion of autologous, ex vivo expanded-natural killer(ENK) cells.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To determine whether significant in vivo expansion of auto-ENK cells occurs, defined as a &gt;
      4 fold increase in absolute cluster of differentiation 3(CD3)-cluster of differentiation 56
      (CD56+) NK cell count/blood 7 days after infusion over the pre-study baseline level and the
      safety of the ENK cell therapy in research participants with high-risk asymptomatic multiple
      myeloma (AMM) defined as gene expression profile (GEP) 70 gene score&gt;-0.26.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Increase in ENK (Expanded Natural Killer Cells) cells after participants receive treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the significance in expansion of auto-ENK cells defined as a &gt;4 fold increase in absolute CD3-CD56+ NK cell count/blood 7 days after infusion over the pre-study baseline level and the safety of the ENK cell therapy in research participants with high-risk asymptomatic multiple myeloma defined as gene expression profile 70 gene score</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of time between when a asymptomatic patient becomes symptomatic</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine if ENK cell therapy in high-risk asymptomatic multiple myeloma delays or prevents progression to multiple myeloma.  Time to progression will be compared to case matched historical controls.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Asymptomatic Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ENK Cell Infusion</intervention_name>
    <description>Day 0(1 dose) ENK Cell Infusion Day 0 to + 12 (13 doses) Aldesleukin (IL2), 3x10 IU</description>
    <other_name>Auto-ENK Cell Therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The study population will be participants with AMM being seen at Myeloma Institute
             for Research and Therapy (MIRT), and under continuing followup with standard clinical
             care testing .

          -  Participants must have a diagnosis of AMM as defined in Staging Criteria (Section
             3.0) and GEP-70 score &gt;-0.26.

          -  Participant (male or female) from any race or ethnicity must be at least 18 years of
             age and not older than 75 years of age at the time of registration.

          -  Participants must have a performance status of 0 - 2 by Zubrod criteria

          -  Participants must have signed an Institutional Review Board (IRB)-approved informed
             consent and Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) authorization
             form.

          -  Must be fit to undergo leukapheresis for ENK cell generation as determined by PI.

          -  Must be a suitable candidate for insertion of apheresis catheter. Participants with
             unusual anatomy or vascular anomalies preventing insertion of apheresis catheter will
             not qualify.

          -  Patients must have previous test results indicating adequate pulmonary function
             studies (PFT) &gt; 50% of predicted on mechanical aspects (FEV1, forced vital
             capacity(FVC), etc) and diffusion capacity (DLCO) &gt; 50% of predicted.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must not have received prior treatment for their disease. Prior use of
             bisphosphonates is permitted.

          -  No other prior malignancy is allowed except for the following: adequately treated
             basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer, in situ cervical cancer, adequately treated
             Stage I or II cancer from which the patient is currently in complete remission, or
             any other cancer from which the patient has been disease-free for 2 years.

          -  May not have history of poorly-controlled hypertension, diabetes mellitus, or any
             other serious medical illness or psychiatric illness that could potentially interfere
             with the completion of treatment according to this protocol or could be considered to
             be an exclusion criterion deemed by the PI.

          -  Pregnant or nursing women may not participate. Women of childbearing potential must
             have a negative pregnancy test documented within 10 to 14 days of enrollment.
             Women/men of reproductive potential may not participate unless they have either
             agreed to practice true abstinence, when this is in line with the preferred and usual
             lifestyle of the participant. (Periodic abstinence [eg,calendar, ovulation,
             symptothermal, post-ovulation methods] and withdrawal are not acceptable methods of
             contraception.) OR begin TWO reliable methods of birth control: 1 highly effective
             method and 1 additional effective method AT THE SAME TIME, at least 28 days before
             starting study treatment through 30 days after the last dose of study treatment.

          -  Serologic evaluation will be used to assess exposure to syphilis, West Nile Virus,
             Chagas, cytomegalovirus (CMV), Immunoglobulin G (IgG), hepatitis B, and C, HIV I and
             II,  and human t cell lymphoma virus (HTLV) I/II.  Participants may not be hepatitis
             B or C (+) unless positive due to previous vaccination or positive but has received
             therapy and is negative for hepatitis B or C by rapid test polymerase chain reaction
             (RT-PCR). An HIV-I/II(+) and HTLV-1/II (+) participant will be rejected on medical
             grounds.  Participants serologically positive for syphilis, West Nile Virus, Chagas,
             CMV, are only excluded if they are being treated for active infection.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Frits Van Rhee, M.D., Phd</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Arkansas</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nathan Petty</last_name>
    <phone>501-526-6990</phone>
    <phone_ext>2435</phone_ext>
    <email>pettynathanm@uams.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Arkansas for Medical Science</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nathan Petty</last_name>
      <phone>888-693-5662</phone>
      <email>mirt@uams.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Susann Szmania</last_name>
      <phone>501-686-8435</phone>
      <email>szmaniasusannm@uams.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Aziz Bakhous, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bart Barlogie, MD, Phd</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jameel Muzaffar, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Monica Grazziutti, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Senu Apewokin, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Shebli Atrash, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michele Fox, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Donald Johann Jr., MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christopher Heuck, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vyjayanthi Ganga, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maurizio Zangari, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Aasiya Matin, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yogesh Jethava, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rashid Khan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 8, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 10, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Asymptomatic Multiple Myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>Auto-ENK Cell Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural Killer Cells</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
