<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="53774">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02069431</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>801-2013</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>AG028740</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02069431</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Oxytocin Aging Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Oxytocin on Physical and Cognitive Functioning in the Elders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The life expectancy of older Americans continues to increase, with persons aged &gt; 65 years
      representing the fastest growing segment of the US population (Manton et al., 1995). While
      prolongation of life remains an important public health goal, a goal of even greater
      significance is that extended life should involve preservation of the capacity to live
      independently and to function well physically, cognitively, and socioemotionally (Katz et
      al., 1983). Therefore, identification of proven interventions to maintaining functioning
      across these domains and prevent disability is a major public health challenge (Branch et
      al., 1991). Greater physical and cognitive independence in older adults has been shown to
      crucially influence social integration in old age (Cornwell &amp; Waite, 2009), resulting in
      significant increase in quality of life and reduction of risk for morbidity and mortality,
      social stress, anxiety, and depressive symptoms (Bassuk et al., 1999; Seeman, 1996). A
      promising candidate to promote functional levels across physical, cognitive, and
      socioemotional domains is the neuropeptide oxytocin (OT) (Barraza et al., 2013; Bartz et
      al., 2011; Feifel et al., 2012; Meyer-Lindenberg et al., 2011; Szeto et al., 2012).
      Combining neuroendocrine with behavioral approaches (e.g., performance-based measures of
      physical and cognitive function), the proposed multidisciplinary research therefore sets out
      to clarify the extent to which intranasal administration of OT over a period of 4 weeks can
      reduce inflammation and improve physical and cognitive function in older men. Constituting a
      complementary piece to the IRB approved currently ongoing Faces Study (IRB # 39-2013), this
      project will also allow examination of interactions between OT's effect on physical health,
      cognition, and socioemotional function.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Overview: This study has the following parts:

        -  Initial screening visit

        -  2 baseline study visits

        -  4-week treatment phase

        -  2 study visits after treatment

        -  Follow-up phone contact

      All study visits will be conducted at the Institute on Aging or the McKnight Brain Institute
      at the University of Florida. The treatment phase will take place in your home.

      You will be assigned by chance, much like the flip of a coin, to receive either the oxytocin
      or the placebo. The placebo is a substance, like salt water, that looks like and is given in
      the same way as the oxytocin but contains no oxytocin. Neither you nor the research
      assistant will know which type of dose you are getting. This information is coded and
      securely stored away until the data is analyzed. This is called a &quot;blind study&quot; for that
      reason, but that information is available if it is needed.

      Screening Visit: Together with the information obtained in the phone pre-screening that the
      investigators have already conducted, the main purpose of the screening visit is to find out
      if you are eligible to participate in the study.

        -  The investigators will ask you questions about your health condition and recent
           activities and the investigators will review your current and past medical health as
           well as your education and living situation.

        -  You will then have a short physical exam by a licensed physician including measurement
           of your blood pressure and pulse (called vital signs or &quot;vitals&quot;) and a brief
           consultation to go over your medical review. This will not be a clinical doctor visit
           for routine medical care, but a visit to confirm that you are eligible and it is safe
           for you to participate in the research study.

        -  A blood draw (~30milileters (mL) or ~2 tablespoons (tbs)) and urine collection (~2mL or
           ~0.14 tbs) will follow. Result of blood or/and urine testing may indicate that you
           should not participate in the study (e.g., certain blood tests' results could be out of
           normal range). The blood test will also be used to determine the level of oxytocin
           occurring normally in your blood and to determine level of inflammation in your body.
           If any incidental or clinically significant findings occur, we will inform you of this
           and give you a copy of the lab results. We will also encourage you to see your primary
           care physician.

        -  Some of the blood and a saliva sample (~2mL or ~ 0.14 tbs) that you will be asked to
           provide will help to find out how the activity of your genes may impact how you perform
           on some tests. All samples will be stored in a locked space at the Institute on Aging.

      Baseline Visit 1: In the first baseline study visit you will be asked to participate in the
      following:

        -  We will ask you to participate in a series of tests and answer questionnaires related
           to physical, auditory (hearing), and your social and emotional functioning. Some of
           these tests will be administered on paper, some on the computer, and some in person.

        -  Physical Test Battery

        -  You will be asked to walk at your usual pace for a distance of 13 feet (4 meters) two
           (2) separate times

        -  You will be asked to stand from a sitting position, without using your arms. If you are
           able to perform this task, you will be asked to stand up from and sit down on a chair
           five (5) times as fast as you can.

        -  You will be asked to maintain your balance while standing in three different positions,
           1) with your feet together, 2) with the heel of one foot beside the big toe of the
           other foot, and 3) the heel of one foot in front of and touching the toes of the other
           foot.

        -  You will be asked to walk a distance of 400 meters (1/4 mile) at your preferred pace.

        -  You will be asked to perform upper- and lower-body muscle strength and endurance
           assessment

        -  You will be asked to respond to various questionnaires related to your physical health.

        -  Auditory Test Battery

        -  You will be asked to complete tasks that ask you to listen and attend to desired
           stimuli in the presence of a competing message or noise.

        -  Socioemotional Test Battery

        -  You will be asked to complete questionnaires to measure your social and emotional
           health, which will include questions to measure your current mood, your general level
           of trust, your level of loneliness, and your drive to identify emotions and thoughts in
           others and to respond to these with an appropriate emotion. These questions will also
           measure your selflessness and concern for the well-being of others, your emotional
           attention and clarity, your anxiety level and your personality.

      Baseline Visit 2: In the second baseline study visit you will be asked to participate in the
      following:

        -  At the beginning of this visit, we will ensure that you are eligible and safe to
           participate in the scanning session that day.

        -  We will ask you to participate in a series of tests and respond to questionnaires
           related to your memory and your thought process. Some of these tests will be
           administered on paper and some on the computer.

        -  Cognitive Test Battery

        -  You will be asked to complete tasks that ask you to attend to, respond to, or remember
           various stimuli on the computer screen.

        -  You will then practice the tasks that you will work on while in the magnetic resonance
           imaging (MRI) scanner. The tasks will involve viewing geometrical shapes, faces, and
           images of objects and scenes. You will receive detailed information and have a chance
           to ask any questions that you may have about the tasks or about the MRI procedure
           before you go into the scanner.

        -  At this point, you will be shuttled to the McKnight Brain Institute, and get settled
           into the MRI scanner, all with the assistance of the trained researcher.

        -  While you are resting comfortably in the scanner, we will ask you to work on the tasks
           mentioned above and while you do the MRI machine will produce images of your brain, as
           well as scan your brain at rest. You will be in the scanner for less than 60 minutes.

      Treatment Phase: In the 4-week treatment phase you will be asked to engage in the following:

        -  You will self-administer either oxytocin or a placebo into your nose by using a nasal
           spray bottle. The spray will be administered twice a day over 4 weeks. We will give you
           guidance about how to administer the spray and will ask you to keep a log book of your
           oxytocin/placebo administration.

        -  In addition, during the treatment phase we will ask you to fill in a short diary about
           social activities you engaged in during your day as well as emotions you experienced.

        -  In Week 1 and 4 of your treatment, we will fit you with a device (i.e., bio-harness)
           that allows us to measure physiological functions of your body such as your heart rate
           and your breathing rate, for over a period of 24 hours while you engage in your daily
           activities. You will be asked to wear it on a typical day, representative of your
           normal daily activity. The 24-hour period will be one in which you are not traveling
           out of town. We will visit you in your home to fit you with and take off the
           bio-harness. The bio-harness will be comfortably fitted with a chest strap around your
           upper body. It generally will not affect the clothes you can wear, it is water
           resistant, and you will be able to purse the large majority of your daily activities in
           the usual manner.

        -  During the treatment phase, we will call you once a week to ask you whether you
           experience any drug side effects or any problem with your health.

      Post-Treatment Visit 1: In the first post-treatment study visit you will be asked to
      participate in the following:

        -  We will ask you questions about your health condition and recent activities.

        -  You will again be physically examined (including vitals) by a licensed physician.

        -  Another blood draw (~15mL or ~1 tbs) will be conducted to determine the level of
           oxytocin after the treatment phase and to determine level of inflammation in your body.
           Urine (~2mL or ~0.14 tbs) will be collected again to ensure that no adverse changes
           have occurred during the treatment phase. The samples will be stored in a locked space
           at the Institute on Aging.

        -  We will again ask you to participate in a series of tests and respond to questionnaires
           related to physical, auditory (hearing), and your social and emotional functioning.
           These measures will be very similar to the ones you did before the treatment phase.

      Post-Treatment Visit 2: In the post-treatment study visit you will be asked to participate
      in the following:

        -  At the beginning of this visit, we will ensure that you are eligible and safe to
           participate in the scanning session that day.

        -  We will ask you to participate in a series of tests and respond to questionnaires
           related to your memory and your thought process. These measures will be very similar to
           the ones you did before the treatment phase.

        -  You will then practice the tasks that you will work on while in the magnetic resonance
           imaging (MRI) scanner. The tasks involve viewing geometrical shapes, faces, and images
           of objects and scenes. You will receive detailed information and have a chance to ask
           any questions that you may have about the tasks or about the MRI procedure before you
           go into the scanner.

        -  At this point, you will be shuttled to the McKnight Brain Institute, and get settled
           into the MRI scanner, all with the assistance of the trained researcher.

        -  While you are resting comfortably in the scanner, we will ask you to work on the tasks
           mentioned above and while you do the MRI machine will produce images of your brain, as
           well as scan your brain at rest. You will be in the scanner for less than 60 minutes.

        -  Upon completion of the study, we will tell you about the general goals of the study and
           answer any questions that you may have.

           1-Week Follow-Up Phone Call: In the follow-up phone call you will be asked to
           participate in the following:

        -  We will call you about one week after your last study visit to inquire whether you
           experienced any drug side effects or any health problems.

      If you participate in this research study, as mentioned above, we will collect blood,
      saliva, and urine samples in separate containers for laboratory tests. The samples will be
      stored in a locked space at the Institute on Aging and at the Department of Psychology at
      the University of Florida. We will use the samples to measure levels of hormones such as
      oxytocin and their effects on your thought process and behavior in the study. And we will
      use the genetic material (DNA, RNA, and protein) to look at how the activity of your genes
      may impact your thought process and behavior.

      The genetic material we obtain from the samples will be stored until the end of the study.
      By temporarily storing the genetic material, we will be able to examine the importance of
      different oxytocin genes as well as other genes that are not yet known as being involved in
      how people think and behave.

      When there is no longer sufficient amounts of blood, saliva, and urine samples collected
      from you for analysis, or samples  become degraded, or you request in writing that we
      destroy it, any remaining genetic material will be destroyed. The genetic material will only
      be accessible to the research staff and will be labeled only by an identification number,
      not your name. The University of Florida will not sell the samples and will not use the DNA
      for cloning.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The use of intranasal oxytocin (OT) will reduce inflammatory biomarkers  in older men after the 4 week treatment (post intervention).</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The use of intranasal OT will reduce inflammatory biomarkers (IL-6, tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α, TNF-sR1, TNF-sR2, CRP) measured in blood samples.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The use of intranasal OT will improve objective and subjective physical function (gait, balance, fatigue, etc.) in older men after the 4 week treatment (post intervention).</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The use of intranasal OT will improve socioemotional function (face processing, emotion processing, etc.) in older men after the 4 week treatment (post intervention).</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The use of intranasal OT will improve auditory and cognitive function (executive functioning, attention, memory, etc.) in older men after the 4 week treatment (post intervention).</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Inflammation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intranasal Oxytocin spray</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intranasal OT (24 IUs) self-administration will take place twice a day over a 28-day period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intranasal Placebo spray</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>placebo (containing all of the inert ingredients except for the oxytocin) self-administration will take place twice a day over a 28-day period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intranasal Oxytocin spray</intervention_name>
    <description>Intranasal OT (24 IUs) self-administration will take place twice a day over a 28-day period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intranasal Oxytocin spray</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intranasal Placebo spray</intervention_name>
    <description>placebo (containing all of the inert ingredients except for the oxytocin) self-administration will take place twice a day over a 28-day period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intranasal Placebo spray</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  males aged 60 years or older

          -  Caucasian

          -  right-handed

          -  generally healthy physically and cognitively

          -  blood pressure &lt; 160/90 mm Hg

          -  willing and able to give informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  participants will be extensively screened for study eligibility aligning with study
             and safety requirements related to drug application and Magnetic Resonance Imaging
             (MRI)/Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy (MRS)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Natlie Ebner, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Natalie Ebner, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>352-273-2141</phone>
    <email>natalie.ebner@ufl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Megan S Lorow, BS, CCRC</last_name>
    <phone>352-294-5090</phone>
    <email>mlorow@ufl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UF Institute on Aging Clinical and Translational Research Building</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Natalie Ebner, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>352-273-2141</phone>
      <email>natlie.ebner@ufl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Megan S Lorow, BS, CCRC</last_name>
      <phone>352-294-5090</phone>
      <email>mlorow@ufl.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Natalie Ebner, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ronald Cohen, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephen Anton, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Todd Manini, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christiaan Leeuwenburgh, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bhanuprasad Sandesara, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 19, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 10, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>inflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>physical function</keyword>
  <keyword>cognitive function</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Oxytocin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
