<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="60307">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01793935</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SMRI #: 12T-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01793935</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Withania Somnifera: an Immunomodulator and Anti-inflammatory Agent for Schizophrenia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Sensoril® (Ashwagandha), an Immunomodulator and Anti-inflammatory Agent for Schizophrenia: A Parallel Group, Randomized Double Blind, and Placebo Controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pittsburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: University of Pittsburgh IRB</authority>
    <authority>United States: University of Pittsburgh, Research Conduct and Compliance Office</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Stanley Medical Research Institute</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Withania somnifera (WSE; Ashwagandha in Ayurveda) extracts have been used as an adaptogen or
      to build resistance to stress or diseases in indigenous medical systems in India for
      centuries. Modern scientific data for WSE indicate several bioactive molecules
      (withanolides, withanosides, indosides, withaferin-A, others) with significant
      immunomodulatory, anti-inflammatory and stress reducing properties.

      This study will examine whether a standardized extract of Withania Somnifera (WSE;
      Sensoril®) will improve total, positive, negative symptoms, and stress in patients with
      schizophrenia.  The study will examine whether WSE reduces PANSS positive and negative
      symptoms and stress scores in subjects, and whether these improvements are mediated by
      changes in inflammatory immune indices.  An additional aim will determine if patients
      receiving WSE will have fewer adjustments to their psychotropic medications that those
      assigned to placebo. The study will examine whether WSE will re-balance Th1/Th2 ratios
      (cytokine measures) and mediate a reduction of elevated hs-CRP levels.  It is hypothesized
      that those subjects whose Th1/Th2 ratios normalize will likely have a greater magnitude of
      clinical improvement versus those subjects whose immune ratios remain unbalanced.

      The proposal is a 12-week, double-blind, placebo-controlled RCT of WSE added to
      antipsychotic medications in 60 patients with schizophrenia with an exacerbation of
      symptoms.  If efficacy is affirmed, this low cost extract could be studied further, and used
      quite readily across low, middle and high income countries.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary aim is to determine whether a standardized extract of Withania somnifera will
      reduce psychopathology scores (PANSS total) and stress scores(PSS total) in persons with
      schizophrenia?

      The study will also determine whether WSE reduces measures of positive and negative symptoms
      of schizophrenia (PANSS subscale scores)?

      Another primary aim will be to determine if changes in antipsychotic and/or other
      psychotropic medications (lithium, anticonvulsants, antidepressants, anxiolytic agents or
      hypnotics) (examples: dosage escalation or reductions or switch or stoppage) will favor the
      group receiving the standardized Withania somnifera extract versus those receiving placebo.
      Even though we expect changes in antipsychotic medications to occur when patients experience
      an exacerbation of psychotic symptoms (or other psychiatric symptoms), we hypothesize that
      those receiving the standardized Withania somnifera extract will experience fewer medication
      adjustments then those assigned to placebo.

      A secondary aim is to determine whether WSE will rebalance TH1/TH2 ratios (cytokine
      measures) and mediate a reduction of elevated hs-CRP levels? The study will assess whether
      those subjects whose TH1/TH2 ratios normalize have a greater magnitude of clinical
      improvement vs. those subjects whose immune ratios remain unbalanced. Similarly, the study
      will assess whether reduction of hsCRP levels correlate with improvements in PANSS total and
      subscale scores or the PSS total scores.

      Eighty patients with DSM IV TR (or if instituted by the study initiation: DSM V)
      schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder will be screened and 60 eligible patients will be
      enrolled in a 12 week placebo controlled double blind study.  Subjects who have experienced
      an exacerbation of positive symptoms (delusions, hallucinations, etc).  Subjects receiving
      medications that affect the immune-inflammatory system will be excluded and those receiving
      antibiotics, antiviral or anti-parasitic medications will be excluded.

      Base line laboratory and EKG examination will be carried out to establish eligibility for
      study participation.  In addition specific laboratory analyses of immune markers namely
      interleukin-2, interferon gamma, interleukin-4, interleukin 6 and high sensitivity
      C-Reactive Protein will be carried out.

      Sixty patients will be randomly assigned to receive either WSE or matching placebo starting
      with 1 capsule of 250 mg strength twice a day (total daily dose = 500 mg) for the first week
      which will be increased to 2 capsules of 250 mg twice daily (total daily dose = 1000 mg) for
      a total treatment period of 12 weeks.  An assessment of psychopathology (PANSS) and stress
      will be carried out at each scheduled visit.  Assessments of safety including vital signs
      and treatment emergent adverse events will also be carried out at each visit.
      Immune-inflammatory markers will be re-assessed at the final visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline in Total PANSS score, Positive and Negative symptom subscores at 12 weeks or end of study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) measures symptom severity in patients with psychotic illnesses. It yields a total score as well as subscores for Positive symptoms and Negative symptoms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived Stress Scale (PSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline in Perceived Stress Scale score at 12 weeks or end of study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Perceived Stress Scale (PSS) measures the degree to which situations in one's life are appraised as stressful.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impression Scale (CGI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline in Clinical Global Impression Scale score at 12 weeks or end of study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Clinical Global Impression Scale (CGI) for Severity and Change subscales is an assessment of clinical impression of the severity of illness and the change in severity of symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune Markers</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from Baseline in Immune markers at 12 weeks or end of study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in the following immune markers IL-2, IFN-У, IL-4, IL-6 and hs-CRP will be assessed to examine if they mediate improvements (or lack thereof) in PANSS total and subscale scores, or in the PSS scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Vital Signs</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline in Vital Signs at 12 weeks or end of study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Clinically significant changes in vital signs, examples: blood pressure, pulse, will be assessed for &quot;normal&quot; or &quot;abnormal&quot; following randomization to 12 weeks or end of study</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Numbers of Participants with Treatment Emergent Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Randomization visit in the Number of Participants with Adverse Events at 12 weeks or end of study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Numbers of Participants with Treatment Emergent Adverse Events as a measurement of safety and tolerability.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Laboratory Analytes</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline in Laboratory Analytes at 12 weeks or end of study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in laboratory analytes will be classified as &quot;normal&quot; or &quot;abnormal&quot; (example: white blood cell counts)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <condition>Schizoaffective Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sensoril®</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sensoril® is a proprietary extract of Withania Somnifera</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sensoril®</intervention_name>
    <description>Sensoril® is a proprietary extract of Withania Somnifera. Each Sensoril® capsules will contain 250 mg of standardized extract of Withania Somnifera</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sensoril®</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ashwagandha</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Each Placebo capsule comprises inert ingredients; microcrystalline cellulose NF 102, croscarmellose Sodium NF, silicon Dioxide, Fumed NF (Cab-0-sil), magnesium sterate, NF matched in appearance and fill weight to Sensoril® capsules. Moreover, based on past experience, we will expose the placebo capsules to covered sachets containing Sensoril, so that the smell permeates the placebo capsules which then smell like the Sensoril capsules.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>&quot;Sugar Pill&quot;</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult males or females (≥ 18 years, to 75 years)

          2. DSM IV TR diagnosis of schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder (If officially
             instituted by study initiation: DSM V diagnoses will be used).

          3. Ability to provide informed written consent

          4. PANSS total score ≥ 60, positive symptom cluster, (delusions, conceptual
             disorganization, hallucinatory behavior, excitement, grandiosity,
             suspiciousness/persecution, hostility and unusual thought content with at least 2
             items scoring ≥ 4, or one of these items scoring ≥ 5, on a scale ranging from 1 =
             absent to 7 = extreme

          5. Current symptom exacerbation ≥ 2 weeks, but ≤ 1 year

          6. Receiving anti-psychotic medications for ≥ 4 weeks

          7. For women of child bearing age, a negative pregnancy test at screening.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Testing positive for illicit substances (marijuana or alcohol use will be assessed on
             a case by case basis, caffeine and nicotine are excepted)

          2. Receiving pharmacological treatment for addictions (naltrexone, suboxone,
             acamprosate, others) will be reviewed on a case by case basis

          3. Seriously unstable medical illnesses

          4. Pregnant or breast feeding women

          5. Known allergy or history of serious adverse event with WSE

          6. Subjects who may require imminent hospitalization (examples: suicidal or aggressive
             behavior)

          7. Currently receiving antibiotics, anti-viral, or anti-parasitic medications

          8. Currently receiving immunosuppressive medications (e.g. corticosteroids, chemotherapy
             or transplantation or HIV/AIDs associated drugs).

          9. Currently receiving NSAIDs or Aspirin (&gt;81 mg/day) on a daily basis or PRN use &gt;
             2x/week (in the last 4 weeks).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>KN Roy Chengappa, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>KN Roy Chengappa, MD</last_name>
    <phone>412-246-5006</phone>
    <email>chengappakn@upmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Patricia Schlicht, BSN, MA</last_name>
    <phone>412-246-5258</phone>
    <email>schlpx@upmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Western Psychiatric Institute &amp; Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Patricia Schlicht, BSN, MA</last_name>
      <phone>412-246-5258</phone>
      <email>schlpx@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jaspreet S Brar, MBBS, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>412-246-6604</phone>
      <email>brarjs@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>KN Roy Chengappa, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jaspreet S Brar, MBBS, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jessica Gannon, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 27, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>K.N. Roy Chengappa</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Psychiatry</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Schizophrenia</keyword>
  <keyword>Sensoril</keyword>
  <keyword>Withania Somnifera extract</keyword>
  <keyword>Total/ Positive / Negative Symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>Stress</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunomodulation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Psychotic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Adjuvants, Immunologic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunologic Factors</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anti-Inflammatory Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
