<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="156432">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01951092</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Lifespan Dev Grant Rana-2012</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01951092</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>mHealth Intervention Supporting HIV Treatment Adherence and Retention</brief_title>
  <official_title>mHealth Intervention Supporting HIV Treatment Adherence and Retention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Miriam Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Miriam Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: The Miriam Hospital Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: mHealth study Data Safety Monitoring Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Despite advances in antiretroviral treatment (ART) over the past 10 years, the incidence of
      HIV in the United States remains stagnant with over 50,000 new cases annually. HIV-infected
      individuals inconsistently engaged with care are less likely to receive ART which is
      associated with correspondingly adverse clinical outcomes in the long term and increased
      risk of transmission. Mobile health (mHealth) strategies including cell phone and text
      messaging have shown success in the developing world for medication adherence, yet mHealth
      interventions have not been developed to improve retention in HIV care. This strategy needs
      to be tested to demonstrate feasibility, acceptability and preliminary effectiveness in
      supporting HIV treatment adherence in Rhode Island.

      The Miriam Hospital Immunology Center is an urban HIV-clinic that provides comprehensive
      primary and specialty care for over 1400 HIV-infected patients. It is the largest HIV clinic
      in Rhode Island with patients also referred from eastern Connecticut and southern
      Massachusetts. In 2010, there were 165 new patients in clinic, 70 of whom were diagnosed
      within 1 year of entering care.   In this environment, we propose a pilot study with the
      following specific aims:

      Specific Aim 1: To pilot a bidirectional mHealth intervention among individuals at high risk
      of loss to follow-up, including those with a recent HIV diagnosis or those re-engaging in
      HIV care. HIV-infected persons (n=30) with a recent diagnosis or re-engaging in care at the
      Immunology Center at TMH will be recruited to participate in a bidirectional mHealth
      intervention that delivers automated, regularly scheduled appointment and medication
      adherence reminders in an individualized format, and also allows individuals to request
      motivational enhancement and problem-solving support to address barriers to care.

      Specific Aim 2: To assess the impact and acceptability of the pilot intervention through
      qualitative interviews. All participants will also be invited to complete individual
      in-depth interviews which will assess acceptability and effectiveness of the pilot mHealth
      intervention, such as content and frequency of automatic messages, for retention and
      medication adherence for HIV-infected individuals in RI.

      The results of this study will provide preliminary data to inform an R21 or R34 application
      to determine efficacy of an mHealth intervention among HIV-infected persons at high-risk for
      loss to follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility and Acceptability of Intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A qualitative interview is completed at the end of the 6 month intervention where participants are queried on aspects of the texting intervention including: frequency of messaging, content of messaging, comfort with confidentiality with messaging, interactions between clinic staff as a result of messaging, and ideas on how to incorporate messaging clinic-wide.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Exploratory end point of PVL &lt;200 copies at the end of the study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">32</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <condition>Adherence</condition>
  <condition>mHealth</condition>
  <condition>Retention</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single Arm intervention study</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All subjects receive text messages for: 1)  medication reminders; 2) appointment reminders; 3) a text message addressing barriers (e.g., reminders to attend AA meetings). Each subject will undergo baseline assessments, choose personalized messages at that time. Subsequently monthly phone calls with study coordinator regarding frequency/changing messages, and then month 3 assessment, and month 6 (final assessment) with option for qualitative interview.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Text messaging</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Single Arm intervention study</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV infected

          -  age &gt;/= 18

          -  patient at The Miriam Hospital Immunology Center

          -  has cell phone that can send and receive text messages

          -  English speaking only

        Exclusion Criteria:

        -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Miriam Hospital Immunology Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02906</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 23, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The Miriam Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Aadia Rana</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>mHealth</keyword>
  <keyword>adherence</keyword>
  <keyword>retention</keyword>
  <keyword>texting</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
