<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="159869">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02044094</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RB-US-13-0002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02044094</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Multiple Dose Study of Blockade of Opioid Effects of Subcutaneous Injections of Buprenorphine in Participants With Opioid Use Disorder</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multiple-Dose Study of Blockade of Subjective Opioid Effects, Plasma Levels, and Safety of Subcutaneous Injections of Depot Buprenorphine (RBP-6000) in Subjects With Opioid Use Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Reckitt Benckiser Pharmaceuticals Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Reckitt Benckiser Pharmaceuticals Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multiple-dose study in non-treatment seeking male and female subjects with
      moderate to severe opioid use disorder who meet criteria from the Diagnostic and Statistical
      Manual of Mental Disorders, 5th Edition (DSM-5) to evaluate the effectiveness of RBP-6000 to
      block exogenous opioids.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A study of RBP-6000 300 mg administered via subcutaneous depot injections using the ATRIGEL
      Delivery System to determine whether there is a difference in the average score of
      subjective-effects questionnaires completed by study participants (using a visual analog
      scale (VAS)) after administering 6 mg or 18 mg hydromorphone compared to 0 mg hydromorphone
      (placebo) as an opioid blockade test (challenge).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Opioid Blockade Following Administration of 0, 6, or 18 mg Intramuscular (IM) Hydromorphone As Measured Using the Subjective Opioid Effects Rating for the Question &quot;Do you like the drug?&quot; Visual Analog Scale (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1-12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reinforcing Effects Of the Daily Randomized Hydromorphone Challenge as Measured by the Mean Hydromorphone Break Point Value</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1-12 (during each 3-day challenge)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The hydromorphone break point value is the ratio of the highest number of choices for hydromorphone to the highest number of choices for money when participants make the choice of working for the amount of hydromorphone dosed earlier that day or for money.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between plasma concentration and predicted mu opioid receptor occupancy of buprenorphine and both the blockade of the subjective effects of hydromorphone post injection of buprenorphine 300 mg (RBP-6000)</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1-12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Summary of Participants with Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 to Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between the opioid blockade subjective effect when participants are asked &quot;Do you feel any drug effect?&quot; and simulated mu opioid receptor occupancy</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1-12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Observed plasma levels of buprenorphine are used to predict the mu opioid receptor occupancy using an established maximal effect [Emax] model published by Greenwald [Greenwald et al, 2007].</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between the opioid blockade subjective effect when participants are asked &quot;Does the drug have any good effects?&quot;  and simulated mu opioid receptor occupancy</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1-12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Observed plasma levels of buprenorphine are used to predict the mu opioid receptor occupancy using an established maximal effect [Emax] model published by Greenwald [Greenwald et al, 2007].</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between the opioid blockade subjective effect when participants are asked &quot;Do you like the drug?&quot;  and simulated mu opioid receptor occupancy</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1-12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Observed plasma levels of buprenorphine are used to predict the mu opioid receptor occupancy using an established maximal effect [Emax] model published by Greenwald [Greenwald et al, 2007].</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between the opioid blockade subjective effect when participants are asked &quot;Do you feel sedated?&quot;  and simulated mu opioid receptor occupancy</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1-12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Observed plasma levels of buprenorphine are used to predict the mu opioid receptor occupancy using an established maximal effect [Emax] model published by Greenwald [Greenwald et al, 2007].</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between the opioid blockade subjective effect when participants are asked &quot;How high are you right now?&quot;  and simulated mu opioid receptor occupancy</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1-12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Observed plasma levels of buprenorphine are used to predict the mu opioid receptor occupancy using an established maximal effect [Emax] model published by Greenwald [Greenwald et al, 2007].</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between the opioid blockade subjective effect when participants are asked &quot;Does the drug have any bad effects?&quot;  and simulated mu opioid receptor occupancy</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1-12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Observed plasma levels of buprenorphine are used to predict the mu opioid receptor occupancy using an established maximal effect [Emax] model published by Greenwald [Greenwald et al, 2007].</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Opioid Use Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>depot buprenorphine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>300-mg buprenorphine (RBP-6000) administered as a single subcutaneous injection on Days 1 and 29.  RBP-6000 effectiveness is 'challenged' on three consecutive days each week of the 12 week treatment period by participants taking hydromorphone at 0 mg (placebo), 6 mg and 18 mg doses assigned in randomized order and then completing study assessments.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Buprenorphine</intervention_name>
    <description>A depot of buprenorphine 300 mg delivered using the ATRIGEL® Delivery System on study days 1 and 29.  As the depot degrades, buprenorphine is released into the systemic circulation at a consistent rate over an approximately 28-day period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>depot buprenorphine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>RBP-6000</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>buprenorphine and naloxone</intervention_name>
    <description>Buprenorphine and naloxone (SUBOXONE® sublingual film) is given to participants on days -14 to day -1 (the SUBOXONE Film stabilization period) as soon as they start to experience withdrawal symptoms.  SUBOXONE is initially administered several times daily until the stable dose of between 8 mg and 24 mg daily is established.</description>
    <arm_group_label>depot buprenorphine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SUBOXONE®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>hydromorphone</intervention_name>
    <description>Hydromorphone challenges are administered during the screening period (days -17 to -15), during the SUBOXONE film stabilization period (days -3 to -1), and weekly during the 12-week treatment period after administration of RBP-6000.  Each challenge consists of 3 days during which participants are administered 0 mg (placebo), 6 mg and 18 mg hydromorphone via intramuscular injection daily in varying blinded sequences.
Hydromorphone can also be earned during the Reinforcing effects tasks and up to the same randomized dose received in the hydromorphone challenge that morning can be earned (or money can be chosen).</description>
    <arm_group_label>depot buprenorphine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>dihydromorphinone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo for hydromorphone administered  via intramuscular injection during each challenge.</description>
    <arm_group_label>depot buprenorphine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>0.45% normal saline</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Meet Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 5th Edition (DSM-5)
             criteria for moderate or severe opioid use disorder at screening and are not seeking
             opioid use disorder treatment

          -  Body mass index of &gt;= 18.0 to &lt;= 33.0 kg/m^2

          -  Females - women of childbearing potential (defined as all women who are not
             surgically sterile or postmenopausal for at least 1 year prior to informed consent)
             must have negative pregnancy test prior to enrollment and must agree to use a
             medically acceptable means of contraception from screening through at least 3 months
             after the last dose of study drug

          -  Male subjects with female partners of child-bearing potential must agree to use
             medically acceptable contraception from screening through at least 3 months after the
             last dose of study drug

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with any current diagnosis requiring chronic opioid treatment

          -  Subjects who currently meet the criteria for diagnosis of moderate or severe
             substance use disorder by DSM-5 criteria for any substances other than opioids,
             caffeine, or nicotine.

          -  Subjects who have abused or used buprenorphine within 14 days prior to informed
             consent.

        Other protocol-defined criteria may apply.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Clinical Development Manager</last_name>
    <phone>804-379-1090</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vince &amp; Associates Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Overland Park</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66212</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 24, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 21, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Opioid dependent</keyword>
  <keyword>Buprenorphine</keyword>
  <keyword>Suboxone Film</keyword>
  <keyword>Opioid blockade</keyword>
  <keyword>Hydromorphone challenge</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Buprenorphine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydromorphone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Analgesics, Opioid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Naloxone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
