<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="166584">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02022098</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Debio 1143-201</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02022098</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Debio 1143-201 Dose-finding and Efficacy Phase I/II Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Randomized Study to Determine the Maximum Tolerated Dose, Safety, Pharmacokinetics and Antitumor Activity of Debio 1143 Combined With Concurrent Chemo-Radiation Therapy in Patients With Locally Advanced Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Head and Neck.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Debiopharm International SA</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Debiopharm International SA</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>France: Agence Nationale de Sécurité du Médicament (ANSM)</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Phase I study (dose escalation) To determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of Debio 1143
      in combination with concurrent CRT in patients with LA-SCCHN.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of Debio 1143 in combination with concurrent CRT in patients with LA-SCCHN.</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety profile of Debio 1143 in combination with concurrent CRT</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-tumour activity of the recommended dose of Debio 1143 in combination with concurrent CRT in the study population</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>PK of Debio 1143 and cisplatin when administered in combination with radiation therapy, and explore the potential for drug-drug interactions of Debio 1143 in combination with cisplatin</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Pharmacokinetic parameters (Cmax, AUC,  tmax,CL/F, Vss/F, ) of Debio 1143 alone and in combination withcisplatin and radiotherapy.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic biomarkers of Debio 1143 activity in combination with concurrent CRT</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>cIAP1 in PBMCs serum cytokeratin 18, IL-8, MCP-1 and TNF-alpha</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Head and Neck</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Debio1143</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Debio1143</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cisplatine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Debio1143</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiotherapy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Debio1143</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Willing and able to sign a written informed consent;

          2. Male or female ≥18 ≤75 years of age.

          3. Histologically confirmed diagnosis of previously untreated LA-SCCHN (Stage III, IVa
             and IVb according to the American Joint Committee on Cancer Staging System) of one or
             more of the following sites: oral cavity, oropharynx, hypopharynx and larynx;

          4. Tumour HPV negative status for oropharynx cancer patients, determined by p16 IHC;

          5. Positive smoking history (&gt; 10 packs/year);

          6. Availability of pre-treatment tumour sample (optional for Phase I; mandatory for
             Phase II [10-20 tumour slides]);

          7. Measurable disease by the RECIST 1.1 criteria;

          8. Negative medical history of Hepatitis B and Hepatitis C;

          9. Women of child-bearing potential:

               1. Negative serum pregnancy test at screening;

               2. Agreement to use appropriate contraception methods from study entry to 6 months
                  after the last day of treatment. Agreement to use contraception methods from her
                  male partner.

         10. Male patients agree to use contraception methods from study entry to 6 months after
             the last day of treatment;

         11. ECOG performance status 0 or 1

         12. Subjects must have adequate haematological, renal and hepatic function; calculated
             creatinine clearance ≥ 60 mL/min as determined by the modified method of Cockcroft
             and Gault or by the EDTA method, absolute neutrophil count

             ≥1 500/μL, platelets ≥100 000/μL, haemoglobin ≥ 10 g/dL, aspartate (AST) and alanine
             transaminase (ALT) less than 3 times the upper limit of the normal range (ULN), total
             bilirubin ≤ 2.0 mg/dL, serum albumin &gt;35 g/L.

         13. QTcF interval ≤ 450 ms

         14. Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) within the institutional normal ranges as
             measured by echocardiogram (ECHO) or multigated acquisition (MUGA) scan;

         15. No prior treatment with IAP inhibitors.

         16. No use or requirement for use of aspirin or aspirin containing products with &gt; 100 mg
             of aspirin per day;

         17. No history of gastrointestinal bleeding within 1 year;

         18. No active rheumatoid arthritis, active inflammatory bowel disease, chronic
             infections, or any other disease or condition associated with chronic inflammation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Nasopharyngeal, paranasal sinuses, nasal cavity tumours or thyroid cancers;

          2. Squamous cell cancer involving cervical neck nodes but from unknown primary site;

          3. Metastatic disease;

          4. Any prior or current treatment for invasive head and neck cancer of any kind. This
             will include but is not limited to: prior tyrosine kinase inhibitors, prior
             neoadjuvant therapy, prior surgical resection, or use of any investigational agent;

          5. Weight loss of &gt;10% during the last month;

          6. Not compensated liver cirrhosis (Child-Pugh class C);

          7. Gastro-intestinal disorders that could affect drug absorption (including, but not
             limited to, major abdominal surgery, significant bowel obstruction, ulcerative
             colitis, Crohn's disease);

          8. Impaired bone turnover (serum C-terminal telopeptide [CTX] &lt;300 pg/mL);1

          9. Concurrent treatment with any other systemic anti-cancer therapy that is not
             specified as part of the protocol regimen;

         10. Concomitant treatment with any drug on the prohibited medication list (provided
             separately);

         11. Subjects with known history of uncontrolled or symptomatic angina, arrhythmias, or
             congestive heart failure;

         12. History of another malignancy within the last 5 years, with the exception of
             completely resected basal or squamous cell skin cancer, or successfully treated
             insitu carcinoma. History of non-invasive lesion or in-situ carcinoma, including in
             the head and neck region that was successfully treated with surgery, photodynamic or
             laser, will be permitted;

         13. Peripheral neuropathy ≥ grade 2;

         14. Clinical hearing loss (to be confirmed by audiogram in doubtful cases);

         15. If female, pregnant or lactating;

         16. History of allergic reactions to appropriate antiemetics (e.g. 5-HT3 antagonists) to
             be administered with chemotherapy;

         17. The investigator considers the subject unfit for the study as a result of the medical
             interview, physical examinations, or screening investigations.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jean Bourhis, Pr</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>CHUV, Lausanne</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Claudio Zanna, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+41 21 321 01 11</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jerôme Douchain</last_name>
    <phone>+41 21 321 01 11</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Curie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75248</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Claudius Regaud</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulouse</city>
        <zip>31052</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Gustave Roussy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Villejuif</city>
        <zip>94000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Vaudois (CHUV)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lausanne</city>
        <zip>1011</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.debiopharm.com</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 20, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 13, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
