<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="70442">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01814241</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-0900</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01AI068074</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01814241</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mechanisms of Desensitization During Peanut Oral Immunotherapy</brief_title>
  <acronym>PnOIT4</acronym>
  <official_title>Mechanisms of Desensitization During Peanut Oral Immunotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to attempt to understand how desensitization works in peanut
      allergic children who are undergoing oral immunotherapy (OIT) to peanut. We want to identify
      the early changes in the desensitization process the immune cells undergo to become
      desensitized to the peanut protein.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Peanut allergic children will undergo an oral food challenge (OFC) to 1 gm peanut protein in
      order to accomplish two objectives: (1)to confirm the diagnosis of peanut allergy, and (2)
      to measure the amount of peanut protein it takes to cause an allergic reaction. Each subject
      will then undergo a modified rush phase in which the subject receives 6 doses of peanut
      protein in one day. The build-up phase begins afterward in which the subject's dose of
      peanut protein is increased every 2 weeks for 36 weeks. After the final build-up dose, the
      subject consumes that dose for 2 weeks after which he or she returns to the food allergy
      center for the second food challenge. If the subject successfully consumes this food
      challenge without symptoms, the daily dosing of peanut protein will be stopped and the
      subject will then undergo a third food challenge. If the subject successfully consumes the
      peanut protein during that challenge, he or she will return for a fourth food challenge to
      peanut.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects who develop desensitization</measure>
    <time_frame>40 to 44 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The percentage of peanut allergic subjects who develop desensitization as defined by being able to consume 5000mg of peanut protein during a double blind food challenge after completing a build-up phase of peanut OIT.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects who maintain desensitization once OIT is stopped</measure>
    <time_frame>1 to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The percentage of subjects who maintain desensitization once the OIT is withdrawn at 1, 2, 3, and 4 week intervals.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Immune system changes in whole blood</measure>
    <time_frame>44 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The investigation of mechanistic changes that occur in the immune system during set time points throughout the study. Mechanistic changes to be addressed include whole blood basophil activation to peanut proteins measured as percentage of CD63+ basophils.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the measurement of the skin prick test (SPT) to peanut</measure>
    <time_frame>44 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The investigation of mechanistic changes that occur in the immune system during set time points throughout the study as evidenced by the decreased size of the SPT to peanut.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease in Peanut specific immunoglobin E (IgE)</measure>
    <time_frame>44 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Immune system changes as evidenced by decreasing peanut-specific immunoglobin E (IgE) measured in kU/L over the time on peanut oral immunotherapy</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Increase in immunoglobin G4 (IgG4) to peanut</measure>
    <time_frame>44 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Immune system changes as evidenced by increasing peanut-specific immunoglobin G4 (IgG4) measured in kU/L over the time on peanut oral immunotherapy</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Food Hypersensitivity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Peanut Protein</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Peanut protein of varying amounts</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Peanut protein</intervention_name>
    <description>Subject will take varying amounts of peanut protein starting with a small amount and building up over time to larger amounts.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Peanut Protein</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 4 to up to 12 years of age of any gender, race, or ethnicity.

          -  Minimum weight 16 kg at the time of enrollment.

          -  Physician diagnosis of peanut allergy OR convincing clinical history of an allergic
             reaction to peanut.

          -  Detectable serum peanut -specific IgE level (CAP-FEIA ≥ 0.35 kU/L) and a positive SPT
             (wheal ≥ 3mm on skin prick test to peanut extract compared to a negative control.)

          -  Allergic reaction to ≤ 1 gm peanut protein during a blinded oral challenge test
             conducted at screening (e.g., a double-blinded, placebo-controlled food challenge
             [DBPCFC]).

          -  Written informed consent from parent/guardian.

          -  Written assent from subject if applicable

          -  Consumption of oat-containing product within 90 days prior to enrollment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of allergic reaction to peanut consistent with severe anaphylaxis (defined as
             hypotension/shock; or neurologic impairment).

          -  Chronic disease other than asthma, atopic dermatitis, rhinitis requiring therapy;
             e.g., heart disease or diabetes.

          -  Active eosinophilic gastrointestinal disease in the past 2 years

          -  Participation in any interventional study for the treatment of food allergy in the 6
             months prior to visit -1

          -  Inhalant allergen immunotherapy that has not yet reached maintenance dosing.

          -  Asthma defined as moderate or severe persistent by National Asthma Education and
             Prevention Program Expert Panel Guidelines (e.g. asthma that requires more than
             fluticasone 440 mcg or its equivalent daily for adequate control).

          -  Inability to discontinue antihistamines for skin testing, OFC and the initial dose
             escalation.

          -  Use of omalizumab or other non-traditional forms of allergen immunotherapy (e.g.,
             oral or sublingual) in the 12 months prior to visit -1.

          -  Any systemic therapy which in the judgment of the investigator could be
             immunomodulatory (e.g. rituximab) in the 12 months prior to visit -1, Systemic
             corticosteroid therapy of up to a total of three weeks is allowed.

          -  Use of investigational drug in 90 days prior to visit -1.

          -  Plan to use any investigational drug during the study period.

          -  The presence of any medical condition that the investigator deems incompatible with
             participation in the trial.

          -  Inability to speak English.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wesley Burks, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UNC Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brian Vickery, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UNC Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Edwin Kim, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UNC Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UNC Chapel Hill</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 15, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Wesley Burks, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Peanut allergy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Food Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
