<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="30281">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02134717</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>U01HL112711</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02134717</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of CCR5 Inhibition on Sarcoidosis Immunophenotypes</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Interventional Study of the Effect of CCR5 Inhibition With Maraviroc on Immune Cells in the the Lung and in Peripheral Blood of Patients With Sarcoidosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pittsburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study hypothesizes that inhibition of the receptor CCR5 by maraviroc will diminish
      inflammation in patients with sarcoidosis. Subjects with active sarcoidosis will first
      undergo bronchoscopy with bronchoalveolar lavage to recover lung immune cells for baseline
      analysis. They will then receive the drug maraviroc for 6 weeks duration.  They will then
      undergo a repeat bronchoscopy with bronchoalveolar lavage to recover lung immune cells for
      analysis following maraviroc treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators hypothesize that inhibition of CCR5 by maraviroc may have a beneficial
      immunomodulatory effect on the granulomatous inflammation of pulmonary sarcoidosis. The
      specific aim of this proposal is the investigate the effect of CCR5 inhibition on the
      trafficking of mononuclear cells to the lung, skin, peripheral blood in subjects with active
      sarcoidosis exposed to the CCR5 inhibitor, maraviroc. A second aim will be to isolate by
      cell sorting CD4+CCR5+ T cells for amplified gene expression profiling before and after CCR5
      inhibition, experiments the investigators believe will elucidate genes associated with
      downstream activation and inhibition of CCR5 receptor function.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total cell count and differentials in blood and bronchoalveolar lavage fluid pre- and post maraviroc</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>General indicators of inflammation following CCR5 inhibition in blood and bronchoalveolar lavage</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mononuclear cell activation and T-cell differentiation</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MNC activation and T-cell differentiation before and after CCR5 inhibition</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CCRS expression among these immune effector cells</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>CCRS expression among these immune effector cells before and after CCR5 inhibition</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Sarcoidosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>sarcoidosis stage II</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All subjects with active stage II sarcoidosis with or without skin disease will receive the drug maraviroc 300mg to be taken orally twice a day for 6 weeks duration.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>all subjects will receive maraviroc 300mg orally twice a day for 6 weeks</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>sarcoidosis stage II</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>maraviroc</other_name>
    <other_name>selzentry</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bronchoscopy with bronchoalveolar lavage</intervention_name>
    <description>Bronchoscopy employs a flexible instrument that is inserted into the trachea and proximal airways after topical anesthesia.  Bronchoalveolar lavage involves the instillation of saline solution through the bronchoscope into the airways followed by recovery under suction to collects lung fluid containing cells and proteins.</description>
    <arm_group_label>sarcoidosis stage II</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>venipunctures</intervention_name>
    <description>Venipuntures will be performed at study entry, after two weeks, and at the end of the study to collect blood for research studies and safety laboratories.</description>
    <arm_group_label>sarcoidosis stage II</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Skin biopsy</intervention_name>
    <description>For subjects with sarcoidosis skin lesions, an optional skin biopsy specimen may be collected for research studies.</description>
    <arm_group_label>sarcoidosis stage II</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologically proven sarcoidosis from any site (noncaseating granulomas without
             other causes).

          2. Diagnosis of active sarcoidosis (Sec. 5.5.4.t) clinical stage II by CXR.

          3. FVC &gt;4S% and DLCO &gt;50% of predicted values.

          4. Evidence of active sarcoidosis (see criteria above)

          5. Able and willing to complete all study procedures (e.g., bronchoscopy, post-drug
             surveillance)

          6. Age: 18+ years old (prevalence greatest in young adults; pediatric maraviroc safety
             not established).

          7. Not on immunosuppression for sarcoidosis at the time of recruitment, (e.g., steroids,
             TNF-a blockade)

          8. Liver function (transaminases, bilirubin), coagulation (INR, PTT, platelet count),
             BUN, creatinine, and WBC within normal limits.

          9. If female: negative pregnancy test, agreement to use reliable contraception if of
             childbearing potential 30 days prior and for 30 days after study completion (drug
             safety during pregnancy not established).

         10. Negative HIV and HBsAg tests

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Diagnosis of infection based upon clinical evaluation and/or microbial testing.

          2. The diagnosis of any disease involving the heart, lungs, liver (HVC), kidney,
             hematologic, endocrine, or Gl systems which, in the judgment of the PI, would pose an
             undue risk to the subject if they participated in this study. This includes but is
             not limited to diabetes, uncontrolled hypertension, liver disease (HVC), or history
             of malignancy.

          3. Medications that will either inhibit or induce CYP3A4 (including St John's Wort)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kevin F Gibson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>DorothyP. and Richard P. SImmons Center for Interstitial Lung Disease at the University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Steve Bruno, BA</last_name>
    <phone>412-605-1550</phone>
    <email>brunos@upmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Morgan Kirkpatrick, BA</last_name>
    <phone>412-692-2151</phone>
    <email>kirkpatrickml@upmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dorothy P. and Richard P. Simmons center for Interstitial lung Disease at the University of Pittsburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kevin MD</last_name>
      <phone>412-624-7225</phone>
      <email>gibsonkf@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://simmonscenterild.upmc.edu</url>
    <description>DorothyP. and Richard P. Simmons Center for Interstitial Lung Disease</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 30, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>sarcoidosis</keyword>
  <keyword>CCR5 inhibition</keyword>
  <keyword>maraviroc</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcoidosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
