<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="10000">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01997905</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CP2011-2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01997905</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Stroke Feasibility Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Feasibility Clinical Investigation of a Minimally Invasive Surgically Deployed AtriCure AtriClip Left Atrial Appendage Exclusion System for Stroke Prophylaxis in Patients With Non-Valvular Atrial Fibrillation and in Whom Long Term Oral Anticoagulation Therapy is Medically Contraindicated</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AtriCure, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AtriCure, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a feasibility study to assess the safety and efficacy of the AtriCure AtriClip when
      placed via Minimally Invasive Surgical Deployment to the Left Atrial Appendage.  The purpose
      is for evaluation of Stroke Prevention in Patients with Non-Valvular Atrial Fibrillation who
      are unable to take Oral Anticoagulants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serious Adverse Events within 30 Days Post-Index  Procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days post-index procedure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary safety endpoint consists of the following serious adverse events within 30 days post-index procedure (unless otherwise noted), as adjudicated by Independent Physician Adjudicator:
Serious Injury to the cardiac structure or other body structure deemed to be related to the delivery or placement of the Clip
Cardiac-Related Death, Myocardial Infarction, or Ischemic Stroke
Major bleeding (defined as requiring re-operation and/or transfusion (&gt; 2 U packed red blood cells (PRBC)) within any 24 hour period during the first 2 days post-index procedure or at any time point if attributed to the device/index procedure).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite Left Atrial Appendage Placement and Exclusion success</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediate to 3-months post-index procedure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Primary Efficacy endpoint is a success/failure endpoint with success requiring all of the following:
Patient Technical Success: The ability to successfully implant an AtriClip device at the LAA in a patient.
Intra-Procedural Complete Exclusion of the LAA:  The complete exclusion of the LAA defined by lack of fluid communication (&lt;3 mm residual communication with LAA and &lt;10 mm residual pocket) between the LA and LAA, assessed intra-procedurally by TEE.
3 Month Follow-Up Complete Exclusion of the LAA:  The complete exclusion of the LAA defined by lack of fluid communication (&lt;3 mm residual communication with LAA and &lt; 10mm residual pocket) between the LA and LAA at &gt;=3 month TEE or CTA evaluation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Stroke and Non-CNS systemic embolism</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months and 6 months post-index procedure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The secondary efficacy endpoints will be a composite of the following events within 3 months and 6 months post-index procedure:
Stroke (ischemic )
Non-CNS (Central Nervous System) systemic embolism.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serious Device or Procedure Related Adverse Event Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month and 6 month post-index procedure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall Serious Device or Procedure Related Adverse Event Rate: Incidence of all serious device or procedure related adverse events observed through the 3 month and 6 month follow-up assessments as adjudicated by Independent Physician Adjudicator.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Serious Adverse Event Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month and 6 month Post Index Procedure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall Serious Adverse Event Rate: Incidence of all serious adverse events, regardless of attribution, observed through the 3 month and 6 month follow-up assessments, as adjudicated by Independent Physician Adjudicator.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Adverse Event Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month and 6 month post-index procedure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall Adverse Event Rate: Incidence of all device and procedure related adverse events and any neurological related AEs, regardless of attribution, observed through the 3 month and 6 month follow-up assessments, as adjudicated by Independent Physician Adjudicator.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <condition>AFib</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AtriClip LAA Exclusion Device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>AtriClip delivered via minimally invasive surgical procedure</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AtriClip LAA Exclusion Device</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>AtriClip LAA Exclusion Device</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LAAØ</other_name>
    <other_name>PRO1</other_name>
    <other_name>AtriClip™ LAA Exclusion System</other_name>
    <other_name>AtriClip™ LAA Exclusion System w/ preloaded Gillinov-Cosgrove™ Clip</other_name>
    <other_name>AtriClip LAA Exclusion System and Delivery System (LAAØ)</other_name>
    <other_name>AtriClip LAA Exclusion System and Delivery System (PRO1)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient is ≥ 18 years and ≤ 80 years of age.

          2. Patient has electrocardiographically confirmed non-valvular atrial fibrillation
             (paroxysmal, persistent, or longstanding persistent AF).

          3. CHADS2 or CHA2DS2VASc score ≥2.

          4. Patient has medical contraindication to long term anticoagulant therapy (OAC),
             defined as one or more of the following:

               -  history of intracranial bleeding (e.g. due to amyloid angiopathy or other
                  condition) which renders patient unsafe for OAC;

               -  history of  gastrointestinal, genitourinary, or respiratory tract bleeding due
                  to permanent condition which renders patient unsafe for OAC;

               -  HAS-BLED Score ≥ 3.

          5. Patient is considered an acceptable surgical candidate, including use of general
             anesthesia.

          6. Female patients must be of non-child bearing potential, or have a negative pregnancy
             test within 7 days prior to index procedure.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Stroke within 30 days, or TIA within 3 days, respectively, prior to index procedure.

          2. Documented medical history of any penetrating trauma to thorax, or blunt trauma to
             thorax which resulted in a left pneumothorax or left hemothorax.

          3. Myocardial infarction within 60 days prior to index procedure.

          4. NYHA Class IV heart failure.

          5. Ejection fraction &lt; 40% (based on baseline transthoracic echocardiography (TTE)).

          6. Prior attempted obliteration of left atrial appendage (percutaneous or open cardiac
             surgery).

          7. Previous catheter ablation with perforation or complication.

          8. Prior open cardiac surgery, or percutaneous coronary intervention with associated
             unintended cardiac perforation, or pericardial adhesions are suspected.

          9. History of pericarditis or pericardiocentesis.

         10. Active infection, septicemia, or fever of unknown origin.

         11. Concomitant elective surgical procedure (in addition to AtriClip placement) at the
             time of index procedure.

         12. Planned atrial arrhythmia ablation procedure within six months following index
             procedure.

         13. Underlying structural heart disease requiring planned surgical treatment within six
             months following the index procedure.

         14. Cardiac or thoracic surgical procedure within the thirty days prior to index
             procedure.

         15. Anticoagulation therapy for other medical condition (i.e. deep vein thrombosis) is
             required.

         16. Patient unable to discontinue thienopyridines (e.g. clopidogrel) or non-ASA
             antiplatelet agents 4 days pre-operatively and abstain for at least 2 days
             post-operatively.

         17. Renal Failure as defined by creatinine &gt; 2.0 mg/dl (&gt; 152.5 umol/L) and/or need for
             dialysis.

         18. Known carotid artery diameter stenosis greater than 80%.

         19. Patient has symptomatic or high-grade carotid disease (&gt;70% bilaterally).

         20. Patient unable or unwilling to undergo transesophageal echocardiography (TEE).

         21. Presence of thrombus in the left atrium or LAA, as determined by baseline TTE or
             Computed Tomography Angiogram (CTA).

         22. Documented history of thrombophilic disorder, with diagnosis established via previous
             objective testing (e.g. familial screening for thrombophilia).

         23. Moderate to Severe Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (FEV1 or VC&lt;70% predicted)
             or intolerant of single lung ventilation.

         24. History of Hypercoagulopathy

         25. Body Mass Index (BMI) &gt; 35.

         26. Other medical illness or comorbidity that may cause non-compliance with the protocol,
             confound data interpretation (e.g. severe dementia), or limited life expectancy (i.e.
             &lt; 3 months).

         27. Enrolled in another investigational device or drug study at the time of enrollment
             and during the course of the study.

         28. Psychiatric disorder which in the judgment of the investigator could interfere with
             informed consent, completion of tests, therapy, or follow-up.

         29. Patient is pregnant or intends to become pregnant within 6 months post-index
             procedure.

        Intraoperative Exclusion Criteria

          1. Left atrial appendage width &lt; 29mm or &gt; 50mm, based on TEE imaging.

          2. Presence of thrombus in the left atrium or LAA based on TEE imaging.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Basel Ramlawi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Methodist Hospital Houston</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shana Zink</last_name>
    <phone>513-755-4562</phone>
    <email>szink@atricure.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mercy Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Saqib Masroor</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Franciscan St. Francis Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marc Gerdisch</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Good Samaritan Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Smith</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Houston Methodist Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Basel Ramlawi</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sentara Heart Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Norfolk</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jonathan Philpott</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aspirus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wausau</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John Johnkoski</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 22, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 21, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Left Atrial Appendage</keyword>
  <keyword>LAA</keyword>
  <keyword>Atrial Fibrillation</keyword>
  <keyword>AFib</keyword>
  <keyword>AF</keyword>
  <keyword>Stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>TIA</keyword>
  <keyword>contraindication to oral anticoagulation therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Arrhythmias, Cardiac</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
