<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="72137">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01838642</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130108</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-C-0108</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01838642</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ponatinib for Advanced Medullary Thyroid Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Ponatinib in Advanced or Metastatic Medullary Thyroid Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Medullary thyroid cancer (MTC) represents 5% of thyroid cancers and presents as a
           hereditary (25% of cases) or sporadic (75% of cases) neuroendocrine malignancy.

        -  MTC arises from the parafollicular C-cells of the thyroid.

        -  Germline mutations in the RET proto-oncogene occur in virtually all of hereditary MTC
           cases, and somatic RET mutations occur in 50% of sporadic cases.

        -  Drugs targeting RET kinase such as vandetanib and cabozantinib have shown efficacy in
           the treatment of advanced or metastatic MTC, however, more effective RET inhibitors are
           needed for previously untreated patients as well as patients who have become refractory
           to other molecular targeted therapeutics (MTTs).

        -  Ponatinib, a drug that is FDA approved as a therapy for chronic myelogenous leukemia

      (CML) and Philadelphia chromosome-positive acute lymphoblastic leukemia (Ph+ ALL), is a
      potent inhibitor of RET kinase.

      Primary Objective:

      -To determine the objective overall response rate (complete response [CR] + partial response

      [PR] by RECIST) to ponatinib in the treatment of patients with advanced or metastatic MTC
      previously treated with cabozantinib and vandetanib who: 1) have tumors with RET mutations
      and 2) have tumors without RET mutations.

      Eligibility:

        -  Patients must have histologically confirmed, unresectable, locally advanced or
           metastatic MTC, with measurable disease by RECIST criteria.

        -  Patients must have disease amenable to biopsy and be willing to undergo biopsy for
           molecular analysis, and also have adequate archival material from their thyroidectomy
           or from a tumor biopsy obtained prior to beginning any systemic therapy.

        -  Patients must have failed or been intolerant to prior treatment with both cabozantinib
           and vandetanib.

        -  The last dose of prior systemic therapy must be more than 28 days prior to the first
           dose of ponatinib

        -  Radiation therapy is permitted if the last treatment was received more than 28 days
           prior to the first dose of ponatinib.

      Design:

        -  Open label phase II trial with 2 treatment groups:

        -  RET mutation positive MTC, previously treated with vandetanib and cabozantinib

        -  RET mutation negative MTC, previously treated with vandetanib and cabozantinib

        -  Patients will receive ponatinib 30 mg orally daily until disease progression or until
           the development of intolerable side effects.

        -  Tumor response will be assessed by RECIST 1.1 criteria at 8 weeks and then every 12
           weeks thereafter. After one year on study, tumor response will be assessed every 16
           weeks.

        -  Patients will have a biopsy of their MTC for molecular analysis prior to initiating
           treatment with ponatinib. Patients will also have a biopsy of their MTC at the time of
           tumor progression, should that occur.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Medullary thyroid cancer (MTC) represents 5% of thyroid cancers and presents as a
           hereditary (25% of cases) or sporadic (75% of cases) neuroendocrine malignancy.

        -  MTC arises from the parafollicular C-cells of the thyroid.

        -  Germline mutations in the RET proto-oncogene occur in virtually all of hereditary MTC
           cases, and somatic RET mutations occur in 50% of sporadic cases.

        -  Drugs targeting RET kinase such as vandetanib and cabozantinib have shown efficacy in
           the treatment of advanced or metastatic MTC, however, more effective RET inhibitors are
           needed for previously untreated patients as well as patients who have become refractory
           to other molecular targeted therapeutics (MTTs).

        -  Ponatinib, a drug that is FDA approved as a therapy for chronic myelogenous leukemia

      (CML) and Philadelphia chromosome-positive acute lymphoblastic leukemia (Ph+ ALL), is a
      potent inhibitor of RET kinase.

      Primary Objective:

      -To determine the objective overall response rate (complete response [CR] + partial response
      [PR] by RECIST) to ponatinib in the treatment of patients with advanced or metastatic MTC
      previously treated cabozantinib and vandetanib who: 1) have tumors with RET mutations and 2)
      have tumors without RET mutations.

      Eligibility:

        -  Patients must have histologically confirmed, unresectable, locally advanced or
           metastatic MTC, with measurable disease by RECIST criteria.

        -  Patients must have disease amenable to biopsy and be willing to undergo biopsy for
           molecular analysis, and also have adequate archival material from their thyroidectomy
           or from a tumor biopsy obtained prior to beginning any systemic therapy.

        -  Patients must have failed or been intolerant to prior treatment with both cabozantinib
           and vandetanib.

        -  The last dose of prior systemic therapy must be more than 28 days prior to the first
           dose of ponatinib.

        -  Radiation therapy is permitted if the last treatment was received more than 28 days
           prior to the first dose of ponatinib.

      Design:

        -  Open label phase II trial with 2 treatment groups:

        -  RET mutation positive MTC, previously treated with vandetanib and cabozantinib

        -  RET mutation negative MTC, previously treated with vandetanib and cabozantinib

        -  Patients will receive ponatinib 30 mg orally daily until disease progression or until
           the development of intolerable side effects.

        -  Tumor response will be assessed by RECIST 1.1 criteria at 8 weeks and then every 12
           weeks thereafter. After one year on study, tumor response will be assessed every 16
           weeks.

        -  Patients will have a biopsy of their MTC for molecular analysis prior to initiating
           treatment with ponatinib. Patients will also have a biopsy of their MTC at the time of
           tumor progression, should that occur.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the objective overall response rate (complete response [CR] + partial response [PR] by RECIST) to ponatinib</measure>
    <time_frame>24-36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>24-36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity and safety</measure>
    <time_frame>24-36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate tumor markers and other correlative parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>24-36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">31</enrollment>
  <condition>Thyroid Neoplasms</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ponatinib</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Diagnosis of localized or metastatic unresectable MTC. The histological diagnosis of
             MTC must be confirmed on review of submitted tumor tissue by the Laboratory of
             Pathology in the National Cancer Institute

          -  Measurable disease, defined as at least one lesion that can be accurately measured in
             at least one dimension (longest diameter to be recorded for non-nodal lesions and
             short axis for nodal lesions) as greater than or equal to 20 mm with conventional
             techniques or as greater than or equal to 10 mm with spiral CT scan.

          -  Disease amenable to biopsy and agree to undergo biopsy for molecular analysis

          -  The last dose of previous therapy targeting RET kinase must be given at least 4 weeks
             prior to the first dose of ponatinib.

          -  Previous treatment with cytotoxic chemotherapy, immunotherapy, or radiotherapy are
             permitted, if the last dose was given at least 4 weeks prior to the first dose of
             ponatinib

          -  Patient must have failed (progressed on or been intolerant of) prior treatment with
             cabozantinib and vandetanib.

          -  Age greater than or equal to 18 years old

          -  ECOG performance status less than or equal to 2

          -  Normal organ and marrow function as defined below:

               -  Leukocytes greater than or equal to microL

               -  Absolute neutrophil count 1,500/microL

               -  Platelet count greater than or equal to 100,000 microL

               -  Total bilirubin &lt; 1.5 times ULN

               -  AST(SGOT)/ALT(SGPT) &lt; 2.5 times institutional ULN or &lt;  5 times ULN if liver
                  involvement

               -  Prothrombin Time &lt; 1.5 times ULN

               -  Creatinine &lt; 1.5 times ULN

               -  Lipase less than or equal to 1.5 times ULN

          -  Negative pregnancy test for women of childbearing potential. The effects of ponatinib
             on the developing human fetus are unknown. For this reason, women of childbearing
             potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception (hormonal or barrier
             method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry and for the duration of
             study participation. Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while
             she or her partner is participating in this study, she should inform her treating
             physician immediately.

          -  Normal QT interval corrected (Fridericia) (QTcF) on screening ECG evaluation, defined
             as QTcF of less than or equal to 450 ms in males or less than or equal to 470 ms in
             females.

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document
             and follow the guidelines of the clinical protocol including visits to NCI, Bethesda,
             Maryland for treatment and follow up visits.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Patients who are receiving any other investigational agent.

          -  Patients with brain metastases or spinal cord compression unless they completed
             radiation therapy greater than or equal to 4 weeks prior to the first dose of
             ponatinib and are stable without steroids or anti-convulsant therapy for greater than
             or equal to 10 days.

          -  Medications that are known to be associated with Torsades de Pointes.

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension (systolic blood pressure &gt;  150 or diastolic blood pressure
             &gt;  100

          -  Significant or active cardiovascular disease, specifically including but not
             restricted to:

               -  History of myocardial infarction

               -  History of atrial or ventricular arrhythmia

               -  Unstable angina within 6 months prior to first dose of ponatinib

               -  History of congestive heart failure

               -  Left ventricular ejection fraction fraction (LVEF) less than lower limit of
                  normal

               -  History of peripheral arterial occlusive disease

               -  History of cerebrovascular accident or transient ischemic attack

               -  Venous thromboembolism including deep venous thrombosis or pulmonary embolism
                  within 6 months prior to enrollment

          -  A history of pancreatitis or alcohol abuse

          -  Uncontrolled hypertriglyceridemia (&gt; 450 mg/dL)

          -  Major surgery (with the exception of minor surgical procedures, such as catheter
             placement or tumor biopsy) within 28 days prior to the first dose of ponatinib

          -  Ongoing or active infection including known history of human immunodeficiency virus
             [HIV], hepatitis B virus [HBV], or hepatitis C [HCV]. Testing for these viruses is
             not required in the absence of a history of infection.

          -  Suffer from any condition or illness that, in the opinion of the investigator, would
             compromise patient safety or interfere with the evaluation of the safety of the study
             drug

          -  Evidence of a bleeding diathesis that cannot be corrected with standard therapy or
             factor replacement

          -  Presence of another primary malignancy within the past 2 years (except for
             nonmelanoma skin cancer or cervical cancer in situ. Prior prostate cancer is also
             permitted if PSA is now undetectable.)

          -  Pregnant or lactating
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ann W Gramza, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Candice M Cottle-Delisle, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-4395</phone>
    <email>cottlec@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ann W Gramza, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 827-4989</phone>
    <email>gramzaaw@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kaitlyn Chambers</last_name>
      <phone>301-402-4395</phone>
      <email>kaitlyn.chambers@nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Roxanne Merkel</last_name>
      <phone>(301) 402-4395</phone>
      <email>merkelre@mail.nih.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-C-0108.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lakhani VT, You YN, Wells SA. The multiple endocrine neoplasia syndromes. Annu Rev Med. 2007;58:253-65. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17037976</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Modigliani E, Cohen R, Campos JM, Conte-Devolx B, Maes B, Boneu A, Schlumberger M, Bigorgne JC, Dumontier P, Leclerc L, Corcuff B, Guilhem I. Prognostic factors for survival and for biochemical cure in medullary thyroid carcinoma: results in 899 patients. The GETC Study Group. Groupe d'étude des tumeurs à calcitonine. Clin Endocrinol (Oxf). 1998 Mar;48(3):265-73.</citation>
    <PMID>9578814</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moley JF, DeBenedetti MK. Patterns of nodal metastases in palpable medullary thyroid carcinoma: recommendations for extent of node dissection. Ann Surg. 1999 Jun;229(6):880-7; discussion 887-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10363903</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 20, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Monoclonal Antibody</keyword>
  <keyword>AP24534</keyword>
  <keyword>RET Mutation Positive</keyword>
  <keyword>RET Mutation Negative</keyword>
  <keyword>RET Inhibitor</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thyroid Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thyroid Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
