<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="109186">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01806064</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>105RC101</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01806064</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase 1B Dose-escalation Study of TRC105 in Combination With Axitinib in Patients With Advanced Renal Cell Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A PHASE 1B DOSE-ESCALTION STUDY OF TRC105 IN COMBINATION WITH AXITINIB IN PATIENTS WITH ADVANCED RENAL CELL CARCINOMA</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tracon Pharmaceuticals Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tracon Pharmaceuticals Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate safety and tolerability and determine a recommended phase 2 dose for TRC105 when
      added to standard dose axitinib in patients with advanced renal cell carcinoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Axitinib is an oral inhibitor of multiple receptor tyrosine kinases including vascular
      endothelial growth factor receptor VEGFR-1, VEGFR-2, and VEGFR-3 at therapeutic plasma
      concentrations.  These receptors are implicated in pathologic angiogenesis, tumor growth,
      and cancer progression.  Axitinib is approved for the treatment of advanced renal cell
      carcinoma, following progression on one prior systemic therapy. TRC105 is an antibody to
      CD105, an important angiogenic target on vascular endothelial cells that is distinct from
      VEGFR. TRC105 inhibits angiogenesis, tumor growth and metastases in preclinical models and
      complements the activity of bevacizumab and multi-kinase inhibitors that target VEGFR. In a
      phase 1 study of advanced solid tumors,TRC105 therapy caused a global reduction in
      angiogenic biomarkers and reduced tumor burden at doses that were well-tolerated. By
      targeting a non-VEGF pathway that is upregulated following VEGF inhibition, TRC105 has the
      potential to complement VEGF inhibitors and could represent a major advance in cancer
      therapy. TRC105 potentiates bevacizumab and VEGFR tyrosine kinases (VEGFR TKI) in
      preclinical models. In a phase 1b study, the combination of TRC105 and bevacizumab produced
      radiographic reductions in tumor volume in bevacizumab refractory patients. Together, the
      use of TRC105 with axitinib may result in more effective angiogenesis inhibition and
      improved clinical efficacy over that seen with axitinib alone.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine Maximum Tolerated Dose of TRC105 in Combination with Axitinib</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety and dose limiting toxicity will be assessed by dose cohort.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TRC105 Pharmacokinetic Concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Plasma TRC105 concentrations will be measured at specified timepoints.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Renal Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TRC105 and Axitinib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TRC105 and Axitinib</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>TRC105 and Axitinib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Chimeric Antibody (TRC105) to CD105</other_name>
    <other_name>INLYTA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologically confirmed advanced renal cell carcinoma that has progressed following
             treatment with at least one multi-targeted tyrosine kinase inhibitor that targets the
             VEGF receptor (e.g., sunitinib, pazopanib, sorafenib, tivozanib). Prior
             immunotherapy, bevacizumab or mTOR inhibitor treatment is allowed. Patients who
             experienced &gt; grade 3 toxicity on prior VEGF or VEGF receptor treatment are excluded
             unless the toxicity resolved to grade 1 following medical intervention and continued
             VEGF or VEGF receptor treatment.

          2. No history of other carcinoma within the last five years, and/or where the risk of
             recurrence is known to be under 5%

          3. Measurable disease by RECIST criteria

          4. Age of 18 years or older

          5. ECOG performance status ≤ 1

          6. Resolution of all acute adverse events resulting from prior cancer therapies to NCI
             CTCAE grade ≤ 1 or baseline (except alopecia)

          7. Willingness and ability to consent for self to participate in study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Prior treatment with TRC105

          2. Current treatment on another therapeutic clinical trial

          3. Receipt of a small molecule anticancer agent, including an investigational anticancer
             small molecule, within 14 days of starting study treatment

          4. Receipt of a large molecule anticancer agent (e.g., antibody), including an
             investigational anticancer antibody, within 28 days of starting study treatment

          5. Prior surgery (including open biopsy) within 28 days of starting the study treatment
             or the anticipated need for a major surgical procedure within the next six months

          6. Prior radiation therapy within 28 days of starting the study treatment, except
             radiation therapy for bone metastases is permitted up to 14 days of starting
             treatment

          7. Minor surgical procedures such as fine needle aspiration, Mediport placement or core
             biopsy within 7 days of study treatment

          8. Uncontrolled chronic hypertension defined as systolic &gt; 150 or diastolic &gt; 90 despite
             optimal therapy (initiation or adjustment of BP medication prior to study entry is
             allowed provided that the average of 3 BP readings at a visit prior to enrollment is
             &lt; 140/90 mm Hg)

          9. Symptomatic ascites or pericardial or pleural effusion

         10. History of brain involvement with cancer, spinal cord compression, or carcinomatous
             meningitis, or new evidence of brain or leptomeningeal disease.  Patients with
             radiated or resected lesions are permitted, provided the lesions are fully treated
             and inactive, patients are asymptomatic, and no steroids have been administered for
             at least 30 days.

         11. Angina, MI, symptomatic congestive heart failure, cerebrovascular accident, transient
             ischemic attack, arterial embolism, pulmonary embolism, Venous thrombosis, including
             pulmonary embolism and deep venous thrombosis (unless adequately anticoagulated
             without warfarin for more than two weeks), PTCA or CABG within the past 6 months

         12. Active bleeding or pathologic condition that carries a high risk of bleeding (e.g.
             hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia).  Patients who have been uneventfully
             anti-coagulated with low molecular weight heparin are eligible.

         13. Thrombolytic use (except to maintain i.v. catheters) within 10 days prior to first
             day of study therapy

         14. Cardiac dysrhythmias of NCI CTCAE grade ≥ 2 within the last 28 days

         15. Known active viral or nonviral hepatitis or cirrhosis

         16. History of hemorrhage or hemoptysis (&gt; ½ teaspoon bright red blood) within 6 months
             of starting study treatment

         17. Pregnancy or breastfeeding.  Female patients must be surgically sterile (i.e.:
             hysterectomy) or be postmenopausal, or must agree to use effective contraception
             during the study and for 3 months following last dose of TRC105.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Manoj Jivani</last_name>
    <email>mjivani@traconpharma.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Bonne Adams</last_name>
    <email>badams@traconpharma.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alabama at Birmingham</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sharon R Barkley</last_name>
      <phone>205-975-2008</phone>
      <email>sbarkley@uab.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Guru P. Sonpavde, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90048</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nancy Moldawer</last_name>
      <email>Nancy.Moldawer@cshs.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Edwin Posadas, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carol Gurski</last_name>
      <email>cgurski@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>M. Dror Michaelson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Meghara Walsh</last_name>
      <email>MWALSH10@PARTNERS.ORG</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Toni K. Choueiri, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David McDermott, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 5, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 26, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>TRC105</keyword>
  <keyword>CD105</keyword>
  <keyword>RCC</keyword>
  <keyword>Renal Cell Carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Axitinib</keyword>
  <keyword>INLYTA</keyword>
  <keyword>Advanced Renal Cell Carcinoma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
