<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="122509">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01661972</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00037688</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01661972</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase I/II Study of Capecitabine Plus Aflibercept to Treat Metastatic Colorectal Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>X-TRAP</acronym>
  <official_title>X-TRAP: Phase I/II Study of Capecitabine Plus Aflibercept in Metastatic Colorectal Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>John Strickler, M.D.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sanofi</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Primary Phase I objectives are to determine the recommended phase II dose for the
      capecitabine and aflibercept doublet combination; and to describe any dose limiting and
      non-dose limiting toxicities. The Phase II Primary objective is to determine progression
      free survival associated with this regimen. The Phase II secondary objectives are to
      determine response rate associated with this regimen; to determine overall survival
      associated with this regimen; and to explore any correlation of clinical outcome with
      baseline and on treatment changes in blood-based angiogenesis biomarkers.

      This open-label, non-randomized phase I/II trial is designed to assess the safety,
      tolerability and RPTD of capecitabine plus aflibercept in adult subjects with metastatic
      colorectal cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recommended Phase II dose (RPTD) for the capecitabine and aflibercept doublet combination</measure>
    <time_frame>RPTD for the study will be determined at the completion of Phase I; up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Phase 1 of this study will be the dose escalation component to determine safety and the RPTD for the capecitabine plus aflibercept combination. Dose escalation will begin with cohort 1 and continue as described in the protocol.  RPTD is determined by the dose limiting and non-dose limiting toxicities (Primary obj 2 for Phase I)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival associated with the regimen</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months progression free</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary objective of Phase II is to describe any signs of clinical activity, including response rate and progression free survival in patients with metastatic colorectal cancer.  For the purpose of sample size determination, a patient will be considered to have been successfully treated if the patient remained progression-free 2 months after the administration of the experimental treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of best response</measure>
    <time_frame>approximately every 9 weeks and/or restaging</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Response is assessed at restaging, approximately every 9 weeks.  For response, the frequency of best response (CR+PR) to the treatment will be tabulated and its 95% confidence intervals will be computed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Subjects will be followed until death which is estimated to be on average 6 months - 1 year after coming off protocol therapy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall survival associated with this regimen will be assessed. Subjects will be followed until death which is estimated to be on average 6 months - 1 year after coming off protocol therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Capecitabine and Aflibercept</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Capecitabine and aflibercept</intervention_name>
    <description>A standard 3+3 dose escalation format will be used. Since each agent is well tolerated as monotherapy and in combination with other chemotherapy regimens, we will start at capecitabine 850mg/m2 to be given days 1-14 and off days 15-21. The dose will then be escalated to 1000mg/m2, given on the same schedule. The dose of aflibercept will be held constant at 6 mg/kg, given intravenously every 3 weeks. Both agents will be administered on a 21-day cycle. Once the RPTD of the doublet combination has been identified, an additional 50 subjects with metastatic colorectal cancer will be added to a single-arm, Phase II portion for expanded safety, response and biomarker data.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Capecitabine and Aflibercept</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. For the phase I portion, patients must have histologically and/or cytologically
             confirmed malignant solid tumor that is refractory to standard therapies.

             For the phase II portion, patients must have histologically and/or cytologically
             confirmed metastatic colorectal carcinoma that has progressed on, is intolerant of,
             or is inappropriate for all standard therapies. Subjects must have been treated with
             a fluoropyrimidine (e.g., 5-fluorouracil or capecitabine), oxaliplatin, irinotecan
             and bevacizumab or have contraindication to such treatment. Prior epithelial growth
             factor receptor (EGFR)-targeting agent (or contraindication to these drugs) is
             required for subjects with K-Ras wildtype tumors

          2. Measurable disease by RECIST 1.1 criteria (see Appendix 1). Previously irradiated
             sites can be included if there is documented progression of disease in that site.

          3. Age 18 years and older.

          4. KPS &gt; 70% (see Appendix 2)

          5. Life expectancy &gt; 3 months.

          6. Adequate organ and marrow function as defined below:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt; 1.5 x 109/L

               -  Platelet count &gt; 100 x 109/L

               -  Hemoglobin &gt; 9 g/dl

               -  Total bilirubin  &lt; 1.5 x ULN

               -  AST (SGOT)/ALT (SGPT) &lt; 2.5 x ULN (or &lt;5 x ULN if liver metastases)

               -  Creatinine clearance ≥50 mls/min by Cockcroft-Gault

               -  Urine Protein/Creatinine ratio  &lt; 1 (or protein &lt; 1+ on urinalysis or
                  24hour urine protein &lt; 1gram/24 hours)

          7. Previous radiotherapy for palliation of recurrent disease is allowed if &gt;4 weeks have
             elapsed since completion of therapy.

          8. Ability to take oral medications.

          9. Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent
             document.

         10. Women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test within 7
             days from day 1 of study drug; both men and women must be willing to use two methods
             of contraception, one of them being a barrier method during the study and for 6
             months after last study drug administration.

         11. Signed informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients currently receiving anticancer therapies or who have received anticancer
             therapies within 4 weeks from day 1 of study drug (including investigational agents,
             chemotherapy, radiation therapy, antibody based therapy, etc.)

          2. History of severe hypersensitivity reactions/anaphylaxis attributed to humanized
             and/or chimeric monoclonal antibodies or other such proteins.

          3. History of significant intolerance to capecitabine or 5FU (ie. Grade 4 toxicity
             related to one of these agents; grade 3-4 toxicity related to other concurrently
             administered agents is not an exclusion).

          4. History of abdominal fistula or gastrointestinal perforation at any point within 6
             months prior to day 1 of study drug, unless surgically repaired.

          5. Active peptic ulcer disease, inflammatory bowel disease (e.g. ulcerative colitis,
             Crohn's disease), diverticular disease or other gastrointestinal conditions with
             increased risk of perforation or gastrointestinal bleeding.

          6. Active bleeding diathesis or history of any major bleeding, CNS bleeding, or
             significant hemoptysis within 6 months of enrollment.

          7. Anticoagulation with warfarin (anticoagulation with low molecular weight heparin is
             not an exclusion).

          8. History of arterial thromboembolic events or symptomatic pulmonary embolism within 6
             months of study enrollment.

          9. Poorly controlled hypertension [defined as systolic blood pressure (SBP of &gt;150 mmHg
             or diastolic blood pressure (DBP) of &gt;90 mmHg]

         10. Patients who have had a major surgery or significant traumatic injury within 4 weeks
             from day 1 of study drug.

         11. History of active brain metastases or carcinomatous meningitis (treated metastases
             are permitted, provided the patient is asymptomatic and off steroids for 28 days).

         12. Female patients who are pregnant or breast feeding, or adults of reproductive
             potential who are not using effective birth control methods. Two acceptable forms of
             contraceptives must be continued throughout the trial by either sex. Hormonal
             contraceptives are not acceptable as a sole method of contraception.  (Women of
             childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test within 7 days prior
             to day 1 of study drug).

         13. Any active infection, intercurrent illness, severe acute or chronic medical or
             psychiatric  condition or laboratory abnormality that may increase the risk
             associated with study participation or study drug administration, or may interfere
             with the interpretation of study results, and in the judgment of the investigator
             would make the patient inappropriate for entry into this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Strickler, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Brant Hamel, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>919-668-1861</phone>
    <email>brant.hamel@duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Anthony Amara, MSW</last_name>
    <phone>919-668-1861</phone>
    <email>anthony.amara@duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke Cancer Center, Duke University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Strickler, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virginia Oncology Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Norfolk</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23502</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Z Chang, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.dukecancerinstitute.org/research/clinical-trials/trials_for_adult_category/1500</url>
    <description>Duke Cancer Institute Research programs: Gastrointestinal Cancers - Colorectal cancers and cancers of the stomach, esophagus and other digestive organs</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 17, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 31, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Duke University Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>John Strickler, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>colorectal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>all solid tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>metastatic</keyword>
  <keyword>refractory</keyword>
  <keyword>advanced solid tumors</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Capecitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluorouracil</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
