<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="6374">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01663103</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-0586</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01663103</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Interleukin-1 Trap to Treat Vascular Dysfunction in Chronic Kidney Disease (CKD)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Interleukin-1 Trap to Treat Vascular Dysfunction in Chronic Kidney Disease (CKD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Risk of cardiovascular diseases (CVD) is significantly elevated in patients with chronic
      kidney disease (CKD); however, this increased risk is only partially explained by
      traditional cardiovascular risk factors.  Patients with CKD exhibit chronic inflammation, a
      key mechanism contributing to vascular dysfunction (i.e., large elastic artery stiffening
      and endothelial dysfunction).  Inhibiting inflammation improves vascular dysfunction in
      other populations characterized by chronic inflammation.  However, it is currently unknown
      if reducing inflammation with an interleukin-1 (IL-1) blocker enhances vascular function in
      CKD patients.  Aim 1 will assess the efficacy of IL-1 blocking with rilonacept for treating
      vascular dysfunction in patients with stage III or IV CKD (estimated glomerular filtration
      rate 15-60 mL/min/1.73 m2).  Aim 2 will determine if blocking IL-1 with rilonacept also
      reduces inflammation and oxidative stress.  These studies could shift clinical practice
      guidelines by establishing a novel therapy for reducing CVD risk in CKD patients not
      requiring chronic hemodialysis.      
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in flow-mediated dilation (FMD)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after start of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in FMD after 3 months of treatment with rilonacept will be compared to change in the placebo group.  Change in FMD will also be assessed at intermediate time points of 1 and 2 months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in aortic pulse-wave velocity (aPWV)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after start of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in aPWV after 3 months of treatment with rilonacept will be compared to change in the placebo group.  Change in aPWV will also be assessed at intermediate time points of 1 and 2 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in contribution of oxidative stress to FMD</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after start of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>FMD will be assessed following acute infusion of ascorbic acid compared to saline.  The improvement in FMD with ascorbic acid reflects the degree of oxidative stress contributing to impairment in FMD.  Assessment of these outcomes will also be made at intermediate time points of 1 and 2 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in contribution of oxidative stress to aPWV</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>aPWV will be assessed following acute infusion of ascorbic acid compared to saline.  The improvement in aPWV with ascorbic acid reflects the degree of oxidative stress contributing to increase in arterial stiffness.  Assessment of these outcomes will also be made at intermediate time points of 1 and 2 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in circulating oxidative stress</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after start of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in Oxidized low-density lipoprotein (oxLDL), glutathione peroxidase (GPX) and total antioxidant status (TAS) after 3 months of rilonacept vs. placebo will be assessed as circulating markers of oxidative stress.  Assessment of these outcomes will also be made at intermediate time points of 1 and 2 months.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in circulating inflammatory markers</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after start of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in high-sensitivity C-reactive protein (hsCRP), interleukin-1β (IL-1β), interleukin-1 receptor antagonist (IL-1Ra), interleukin-6 (IL-6) and interleukin-10 (IL-10) after 3 months of rilonacept vs. placebo will be assessed as circulating markers of inflammation.  Assessment of these outcomes will also be made at intermediate time points of 1 and 2 months.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in vascular oxidative stress</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after start of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Vascular endothelial cells will be collected and assessed for changes in protein expression of the following markers of oxidative stress: nitrotyrosine, NADPH p47phox and copper-zinc superoxide dismutase (CuZnSOD) after 3 months of rilonacept vs. placebo.  Assessment of these outcomes will also be made at intermediate timepoints of 1 and 2 months.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in vascular inflammation</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after start of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Vascular endothelial cells will be collected and assessed for changes in protein expression of the following markers of inflammation: IL-1β, IL-1Ra, nuclear factor k B (NFkB),  IL-6 and IL-10 after 3 months of rilonacept vs. placebo.  Assessment of these outcomes will also be made at intermediate timepoints of 1 and 2 months.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in vascular endothelial nitric oxide synthase (eNOS) expression</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after start of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Vascular endothelial cells will be collected and assessed for changes in protein expression of eNOS and eNOS phosphorylated at Ser 1177 after 3 months of treatment with rilonacept vs. placebo.  Assessment of these outcomes will also be made at intermediate timepoints of 1 and 2 months.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">38</enrollment>
  <condition>Renal Insufficiency, Chronic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rilonacept</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>12 weeks of treatment with rilonacept (subcutaneous injection with a loading dose of 320 mg, followed by 160 mg/wk)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Twelve weeks of treatment with placebo (subcutaneous injection of normal saline with a loading dose of 320 mg, followed by 160 mg/wk)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rilonacept</intervention_name>
    <description>12 weeks of treatment with rilonacept (subcutaneous injection with a loading dose of 320 mg, followed by 160 mg/wk)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rilonacept</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Arcalyst</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18-80 years

          -  CKD stage III or IV (eGFR with the 4-variable Modified Diet Renal Disease (MDRD)
             prediction equation: 15-60 mL/min/1.73m2; stable renal function in the past 3 months)

          -  An elevated high sensitivity C-reactive protein (hs-CRP) of &gt; 2.0 mg/L and &lt;30 mg/L
             on at least 2 consecutive weekly determinations

          -  Urine protein excretion &lt; 5.0 g/24h estimated by a spot urine protein/creatinine
             ratio

          -  Ability to provide informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with advanced CKD requiring chronic dialysis

          -  Active infection (chronic or acute (within 3 months) or antibiotic therapy (w/in 1
             mo); history of recurrent infection

          -  Significant co-morbid conditions that lead the investigator to conclude that life
             expectancy is less than 1 year

          -  Expected to undergo living related transplant in next 6 months

          -  History of severe congestive heart failure (i.e., EF &lt; 35%)

          -  Hospitalization in the past month

          -  Severe arthritis, lupus, inflammatory bowel disease, asthma or other disease(s) or
             medical condition(s) that, in the opinion of the investigator, could interfere with
             hsCRP or immune function

          -  Immunosuppressant agents such as cyclosporine, tacrolimus, azathioprine, etanercept,
             infliximab, adalimumab, anakinra or long-term oral glucocorticoids taken in past 12
             months

          -  Known malignancy

          -  HIV, active, chronic hepatitis B as evidenced by HBsAg positive and HBsAb negative,
             or hepatitis C positive

          -  Woman who are pregnant, nursing or planning to become pregnant

          -  Body mass index (BMI) &gt;40 kg/m2

          -  Warfarin use (or other cytochrome P (CYP)450 substrates with a narrow therapeutic
             index) [ok if do not participate in endothelial cell collection]

          -  Taking medication(s) that interact with agents administered during experimental
             sessions (e.g., sildenafil interacts with nitroglycerin)

          -  Currently receiving or planning to receive live or inactivated vaccines

          -  Alcohol dependence or abuse

          -  Subjects at risk for tuberculosis (TB). Specifically, subjects with:

          -  Current clinical, radiographic or laboratory evidence of active TB at screening or
             latent TB that has not been previously treated

          -  A history of active TB within the last 3 years even if it was treated.

          -  A history of active TB greater than 3 years ago unless there is documentation that
             the prior anti-TB treatment was appropriate in duration and type.

          -  Therapy for latent TB which has not been completed as per local guidelines.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kristen L Jablonski Nowak, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado Denver Anschutz Medical Campus</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Heather Farmer, B.A.</last_name>
    <phone>303-724-7791</phone>
    <email>Heather.Farmer@ucdenver.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Clinical and Translational Research Center (CTRC) Outpatient Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Heather Farmer, B.A,</last_name>
      <phone>303-724-7791</phone>
      <email>Heather.Farmer@ucdenver.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kristen L Jablonski Nowak, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 20, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 7, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Interleukin-1</keyword>
  <keyword>Endothelium, Vascular</keyword>
  <keyword>Vascular Stiffness</keyword>
  <keyword>Oxidative Stress</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>Endothelial cells</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
