<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="93927">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01698255</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P30 MH085943-05</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>11108011880</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01698255</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Psychotherapy for Late Life Depression</brief_title>
  <acronym>ENGAGE-II</acronym>
  <official_title>Psychotherapy for Late Life Depression</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized pilot study will test the feasibility of a behavioral intervention for late
      life depression.  Enrolled participants will receive 9 weeks of a specialized form of
      psychotherapy we call &quot;ENGAGE&quot; or standard of care psychotherapy.  ENGAGE is a stepped care
      psychotherapy based on what is currently known about older adults' response to depression
      interventions.  Stepped care is a model of treatment that starts with the minimum effective
      therapeutic techniques first, and then based on how well people respond to treatment,
      additional therapeutic techniques are added until individuals recover from their depression.
       The treatment components of ENGAGE were selected to match the most common problems seen in
      older adults with depression.  They include instructing the participant in basic problem
      solving techniques and encouraging re-engagement in rewarding activities.

      Participants will be depressed, older adult clients of Westchester Jewish Community Services
      or outpatient research subjects recruited by the Cornell Institute of Geriatric Psychiatry.
      In addition to receiving therapy, study participants will also undergo research assessments
      at the beginning of the study and then at weeks 6 and 9.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To compare the effectiveness of the ENGAGE intervention in reducing depressive symptoms with that of the standard of care psychotherapy.  We will assess severity of depression at Baseline. 6 weeks and 3 months using the Hamilton Depression Rating Scale as the primary measure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ENGAGE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ENGAGE is a stepped care psychotherapy based on what is known about how older adults respond to depression interventions.  Stepped care is a model of treatment that starts with the minimum effective therapeutic techniques first, and then based on how well people respond to treatment, additional therapeutic techniques are added until people are recovered from their depression.  The steps of ENGAGE are:
basic social and physical engagement, which has been found to be a very effective depression strategy for most older adults;
the addition of strategies to address clinical features of depression interfering with treatment engagement, namely affect regulation, pessimism, and disorganization.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care Psychotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The comparison group for this study will be the current standard of care psychotherapy offered by Westchester Jewish Community Services (WJCS) therapists.  This type of psychotherapy is often supportive or eclectic in nature.  Therapists will focus on helping the subject to express feelings and focus on strengths and abilities in working through current difficulties and transitions.  Therapists assigned to provide standard psychotherapy to eligible participants will receive training and supervision from WJCS staff consistent with agency practice.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ENGAGE</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>ENGAGE</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard of Care Psychotherapy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care Psychotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria (WJCS Participants):

          -  Current client of Westchester Jewish Community Services;

          -  Age 60 years or older;

          -  Diagnosis of depression as determined by WJCS therapists;

          -  Command of English sufficient to participate in talking therapy;

        Inclusion Criteria (Cornell Participants):

          -  Age 60 years or older;

          -  Depression as determined by a Patient Health Questionnaire-9 score of 6 or higher
             (with at least one item being &quot;depressed mood&quot; or &quot;loss of interest/pleasure&quot;);

          -  Command of English sufficient to participate in talking therapy;

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Dementia: Mini Mental State Exam score below 24 or clinical diagnosis of dementia by
             Diagnostic and Statistical Manual IV;

          -  High suicide risk, i.e. intent or plan to attempt suicide in near future;

          -  History of psychiatric diagnoses other than major depressive disorder or generalized
             anxiety disorder (including bi-polar depression, psychotic depression,
             schizoaffective disorders).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Patrick J Raue, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>914-997-8384</phone>
    <email>praue@med.cornell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Westchester Jewish Community Services</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hartsdale</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10530</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Patrick J Raue, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>914-997-8684</phone>
      <email>praue@med.cornell.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>George S Alexopoulos, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Weill Cornell Medical College</name>
      <address>
        <city>White Plains</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10605</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Patrick J Raue, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>914-997-8684</phone>
      <email>praue@med.cornell.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>George S Alexopoulos, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 12, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 2, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Geriatrics</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
