<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="20020">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01901211</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-423</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01901211</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Physical and Social Benefits of Multi-Player Interactive Computer Play Games in Youth With Cerebral Palsy</brief_title>
  <official_title>CP Fit 'n' Fun Project: Physical and Social Benefits of Multi-Player Interactive Computer Play Games in Youth With Cerebral Palsy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Holland Bloorview Kids Rehabilitation Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Queen's University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council, Canada</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Holland Bloorview Kids Rehabilitation Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Ethics Review Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      As children with cerebral palsy (CP) become teenagers, they experience a decrease in their
      physical function and mobility. Decreased mobility leads to increased social isolation for
      the teens and impacts negatively on their quality of life. This loss of function is
      multifactorial, but poor physical fitness and muscle weakness secondary to disuse are
      significant contributors. Exercise video games are a novel approach to engage youth in
      physical exercise and social interaction with their peers. The objective of this study is to
      evaluate  the impact of an exercise video gaming intervention to improve physical fitness
      and social wellbeing. Our over-arching research questions are whether &quot;exergames&quot; can
      provide health benefits (improved physical fitness) and improved social wellbeing in youth
      with CP.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary objectives of this study are to evaluate the impact of exergaming on
      cardiovascular fitness and social wellbeing related to friends/peers in youths with CP. The
      secondary objectives of the study will be to evaluate the impact of the exergaming
      intervention on additional components of physical fitness including anaerobic fitness, and
      muscle strength. In addition, the effect of the exergaming intervention on overall
      health-related quality of life (HRQL), self-esteem and motor participation will also be
      measured. Finally, the effectiveness of a technique for balancing performance in multiplayer
      exergames will be evaluated. The objectives will be investigated using a randomized
      crossover study design.Outcomes will be measured a total of four times: at study entry and
      after the first ten-week period (either comparison or intervention), at the end of a
      six-week washout period, then again after second period (either intervention or comparison).
      Outcomes will be assessed by physiotherapists and research staff members who will be blinded
      to the condition of the participants.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the 7.5 meter Shuttle Run Test for Gross Motor Function Classification Scale (GMFCS) level III (SRT-III)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (1-week pre-study arm 1), 11-weeks (post study arm 1), 17-weeks (post washout period), 28-weeks (post study arm 2)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The 7.5m Shuttle Run test (SRT-III) is a maximal, running-based, field test that can assess cardiovascular fitness in children with CP GMFCS level III. In the tests, markers are placed 7.5m apart in a square formation. Participants walk from marker to marker according to progressively faster auditory cues from a music device.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Social Wellbeing Domain of the KINDL-R Quality of Life Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (1-week pre-study arm 1), 11-weeks (post study arm 1), 17-weeks (post washout period), 28-weeks (post study arm 2)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Wellbeing Related to Friends/Peers domain of the KINDL-R is a four-item subscale focusing on time spent with friends, being perceived as a success with friends, getting along with friends and whether or not they felt different from peers over the past week. Individual items are scored on a five-point Likert scale and the subscale can be scored in isolation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Handheld dynamometry measures of knee flexors and knee extensors</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (1-week pre-study arm 1), 11-weeks (post study arm 1), 17-weeks (post washout period), 28-weeks (post study arm 2)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Handheld dynamometry will be used to measure muscle strength for the quadriceps muscles and the hamstrings at 90˚ of knee flexion in both legs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The 30-second Wingate Cycle Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (1-week pre-study arm 1), 11-weeks (post study arm 1), 17-weeks (post washout period), 28-weeks (post study arm 2)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The 30-second Wingate Cycle Test is a measure of anaerobic power, a key component of physical fitness. The cycle test is performed when a participant uses a cycle ergometer and pedals as hard as they can for 30-seconds against a constant braking force.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anthropometric measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (1-week pre-study arm 1), 11-weeks (post study arm 1), 17-weeks (post washout period), 28-weeks (post study arm 2)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Anthropometric measurements of waist circumference, triceps and subscapular skinfold thickness, height and weight will be used to assess body composition as indicators of physical fitness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total Score of the KINDL-R Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (1-week pre-study arm 1), 11-weeks (post study arm 1), 17-weeks (post washout period), 28-weeks (post study arm 2)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The total score of the 24-item KINDL-R questionnaire will measure the participants' health-related quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Self-Worth Domain of the KINDL-R Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (1-week pre-study arm 1), 11-weeks (post study arm 1), 17-weeks (post washout period), 28-weeks (post study arm 2)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The 4-item Self-worth Domain of the KINDL-R will be used as an indicator of self-esteem.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gaming data</measure>
    <time_frame>10-weeks of the exergaming intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Gaming data will be collected as measures of effectiveness of the games' balancing techniques, engagement and adherence. The games will be instrumented to automatically collect usage data including: time and frequency of play; amount of time within HR zones; pedaling cadence information; minigames played; and location of the player's avatar in the virtual world.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>StepWatch Activity Monitors</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (1-week pre-study arm 1), 11-weeks (post study arm 1), 17-weeks (post washout period), 28-weeks (post study arm 2)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>StepWatch Activity Monitors will be used to measure activity levels and motor participation. The StepWatch is a two-plane accelerometer that is worn around the ankle in a knit cuff. The StepWatch measures ambulatory activity (i.e. total daily step count) and acts as an indicator of motor participation in the community.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">11</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebral Palsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exergaming</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this arm, the participants will participate in the exergaming intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Comparison Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this arm of the study, participants will engage in their typical physical activity routines for the ten week duration. Participants will receive a call from the RA each week. The RA will ask the child to report on all the physical and social activities that they engaged in for that week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exergaming Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The exergaming system will be installed into the participants' homes. Players will pedal the exergame bike in order to move their game avatar. Headsets allow players to communicate with each other in real-time. Participants will  play the games 3 to 5 times per week, during scheduled game times. Players will wear a heart rate (HR) monitor and will achieve game benefits for reaching their target HR. They will be asked to exercise in a target HR zone of 40-65%HR reserve. Each week, participants will receive a call from a research assistant (RA), who will provide feedback on their exercise progress and a HR goal for each week. The RA will also record physical and social activities engaged in and any difficulties like leg pain or technical issues.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exergaming</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of CP and GMFCS level III

          -  Between 9 and 18 years of age inclusive

          -  Ability to operate a handheld videogame controller

          -  High-speed internet in the home

          -  Able to commit for the entire study duration

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Orthopedic surgery in the preceding six months

          -  Exercise-induced asthma

          -  Any underlying heart condition

          -  Seizure disorder

          -  Visual, auditory or cognitive disabilities that will interfere with game play
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>9 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>19 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Darcy Fehlings, MD, MSc, FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Holland Bloorview Kids Rehabilitation Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>T.C. Nicholas Graham, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Queen's University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Holland Bloorview Kids Rehabilitation Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M4G1R8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 11, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 11, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cerebral palsy</keyword>
  <keyword>Interactive computer play</keyword>
  <keyword>Multi-player gaming</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Palsy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paralysis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
