<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="11599">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01894906</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RMTI-SFP-8</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01894906</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Quantitative Mass Transfer of SFP-iron From Dialysate to Blood in CKD-HD Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Controlled, Randomized Study to Assess the Quantitative Mass Transfer of Iron From SFP-containing Hemodialysate Under Varying Conditions of Blood and Dialysate Flow Rates, Dialyzer Membrane Types and Dialysate Bicarbonate Concentrations in CKD-HD Patients.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rockwell Medical Technologies, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rockwell Medical Technologies, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the quantity of iron derived from SFP that is
      transferred from the dialysate to patients during a single dialysis session.  The effects of
      various conditions which may affect the transfer of iron such as blood and dialysate flow
      rate, changes in bicarbonate delivery, dialyzer membrane type and the effect of reuse will
      also be investigated.  The absorption and removal of iron from the blood will also be
      investigated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      -  A total of 12 subjects on standard 3X/week hemodialysis will be studied in 2 groups (6
           subjects per group)

        -  2 primary dialyzer membranes will be studied.:

             -  Polyamide Membrane (Gambro Polyflux series: 17R and 21R)

             -  Cellulose Triacetate (Baxter CT series: CT-190)

        -  Each 1-week treatment cycle will include 3 haemodialysis (HD) sessions per subject,
           including 2 study treatment-HD sessions and 1 non-treatment-HD session per subject.
           Treatment-HD sessions will be conducted midweek and end-of-week (i.e. Dialysis days 3
           and 5 of each week with a 1 day interdialytic interval) to avoid excessive fluid shifts
           due to the increased UF needed during the non-treatment HD session (conducted at
           beginning of the week; HD day 1).

        -  Within each group, each subject will be randomized to 1 of 6 treatment sequences.  The
           treatments to be investigated are: Control; new dialyzer, reused dialyzer, low blood
           flow/dialysate flow, Low bicarbonate concentration and a different synthetic dialyzer
           membrane (PAES)

        -  Blood for a complete serum iron profile over time will be obtained during the new
           dialyzer (SFP/standard bicarbonate/new dialyzer/ high Qb and Qd) for all subjects.
           This will necessitate approximately a 24-hour inpatient confinement to obtain blood at
           specified time intervals after dialysis is completed.  Blood for a partial iron profile
           will be collected during the dialysis sessions at all other dialysis sessions.

        -  Each of the 6 enrolled subjects per dialyzer membrane type will be assigned to a
           different sequence of treatments to help ensure that the treatment sequence does not
           affect the analysis (Note: the first dialysis sessions of each of the 3 study weeks,
           i.e. HD1, HD4 and HD7, are non-study related sessions during which no study procedures
           are performed except for adverse event collection.

        -  Patients should not be receiving any of the following medications from screening
           through the end of the study:

             -  Oral iron preparations, including multivitamin supplements containing iron

             -  Intravenous iron preparations

        -  Doses of ESA's should not be changed from screening to the end of the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Bio-availability Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Net iron delivery from SFP dialysate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Iron concentration in timed dialysate collections will be analyzed.  Expended dialysate over the intervals of 0.5, 1, 2 ,3 and 4 hours will be collected and measured.  Aliquots will be analyzed for iron content.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Iron delivery under different conditions.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The analyses of other Treatments will be performed on total data from both dialyzer membrane groups.  Equivalence of net iron delivery will be assessed using standard bioequivalence criteria. The geometric mean ratio of net iron delivery for each treatment relative to reference treatment will be calculated along with the associated 90% confidence intervals of the geometric mean ratio.  The 90% CIs of the geometric mean ratio for net iron delivery in Treatments C-F will be evaluated to determine if they fall within the standard bioequivalence bounds (80-125%)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of serum iron and exploratory modeling</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The serum total iron, Transferrin Bound Iron (TBI) and Non-transferrin Bound Iron (NTBI) pharmacokinetic parameters (baseline corrected and total) will be listed and summarized for each membrane group and overall. The serum total iron, TBI, NTBI UIBC and TIBC concentrations for all treatments will be presented and summarized at each collected time point. The iron delivery via the dialyzer will be presented and summarized at each collected time point. All serum iron concentrations may be used to develop an exploratory model for effects of treatments on serum iron.  Baseline and control corrected iron parameters may be used to refine the model as appropriate.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Kidney Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each subject will receive one control treatment and 5 treatments with SFP added to dialysate.  The 5 SFP treatments will encompass 5 different conditions which may impact the intradialytic transfer of iron to the subject:  new dialyzer, reused dialyzer, low blood/dialysate flow rate, low machine delivered bicarbonate concentration, and a different synthetic dialysis membrane (PAES).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Soluble Ferric Pyrophosphate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group/ cohort designation: Cellulose dialysis membrane (CT-190)/ Polyamide membrane. Each subject will receive one control treatment and 5 treatments with SFP added to dialysate.  The 5 SFP treatments will encompass 5 different conditions which may impact the intradialytic transfer of iron to the subject:  new dialyzer, reused dialyzer, low blood/dialysate flow rate, low machine delivered bicarbonate concentration, and a different synthetic dialysis membrane (PAES).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Soluble Ferric Pyrophosphate</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Soluble Ferric Pyrophosphate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SFP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult subject ≥ 18 years of age undergoing chronic hemodialysis for chronic kidney
             disease (CKD) for at least 3 months, expected to remain on hemodialysis and be able
             to complete the study.

          2. Screening Hgb ≥ 9.5 g/dL.

          3. Screening transferrin saturation % (TSAT) ≥ 15% to ≤ 45%.

          4. Screening serum ferritin ≥ 200 to ≤ 1200 µg/L.

          5. Subject's standard dialyzer membrane is one of the 2 types, i.e. Baxter CT-190 or
             Gambro 17R or 21R.

          6. The subject uses a reprocessed dialyzer for standard HD treatments.

          7. Prescribed dialysis 3X/week.

          8. Minimally adequate measured dialysis dose defined as URR (urea reduction ratio) ≥
             65%, or single-pool Kt/V (dialyzer clearance of urea multiplied by dialysis time,
             divided by patient's total body water) ≥ 1.2, or KIDt/V (online dialyzer clearance
             measured using ionic dialysance multiplied by dialysis time, divided by patients
             total body water) ≥ 1.2.

          9. Stable dialyzer blood flow rate that is generally ≥ 350 mL/min and acceptable to the
             Investigator.

         10. Stable dialysate flow rate that is generally ≥ 600 mL/min and acceptable to the
             Investigator.

         11. Vascular access for dialysis that will be used upon enrollment with stable function
             in the judgment of the Investigator.

         12. Female subjects must be either amenorrheic for ≥ 1 year or agree to not become
             pregnant by continuous use of an effective birth control method acceptable to the
             Investigator for the duration of their participation in the study.

         13. Must be willing and able to provide written informed consent directly or through
             their authorized representative.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject has a living kidney donor identified or living-donor kidney transplant
             scheduled during study participation. (Note:  Patients awaiting deceased-donor
             transplant need not be excluded.)

          2. Vascular access for hemodialysis is a femoral catheter.

          3. Known active bleeding from any site other than AV fistula or graft (e.g.,
             gastrointestinal, hemorrhoidal, nasal, pulmonary, etc.).

          4. Scheduled surgery during the study.

          5. RBC or whole blood transfusion within 4 weeks prior to Screening.

          6. Hospitalization in the month prior to Screening (except for vascular access surgery)
             that, in the opinion of the Investigator, confers a significant risk of
             hospitalization during the course of this study.

          7. Evidence of current malignancy involving a site other than skin (except any melanoma,
             which renders the patient non-eligible).

          8. History of drug or alcohol abuse within the last 6 months.

          9. Regularly requiring hemodialysis more than three times per week.

         10. Noncompliance with dialysis regimen in the opinion of the Investigator.

         11. Pregnancy or intention to become pregnant before completing all study drug treatment.

         12. Known ongoing inflammatory disorder (other than CKD), such as systemic lupus
             erythematosus, rheumatoid arthritis, or other collagen-vascular disease undergoing a
             disease flare.

         13. Any current febrile illness (e.g., oral temperature &gt; 100.4°F, 38°C).  (The patient
             may subsequently become eligible at least 1 week after resolution of the illness).

         14. Known active bacterial, tuberculosis, fungal, viral, or parasitic infection requiring
             anti-microbial therapy or anticipated to require anti-microbial therapy during the
             patient's participation in this study.

         15. Occult tuberculosis requiring prophylactic treatment with anti-tubercular drug(s)
             that overlaps with the patient's participation in this study.

         16. Known positive status for hepatitis B surface antigen (hepatitis B testing is not
             required as part of this protocol).

         17. Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection (HIV testing is not required as
             part of this protocol).

         18. Cirrhosis of the liver based on histological criteria or clinical criteria (i.e.,
             presence of ascites, esophageal varices, multiple spider nevi, or history of hepatic
             encephalopathy).

         19. Active hepatitis with ALT and/or AST levels consistently greater than twice the upper
             limit of normal at any time during the two months prior to enrollment.

         20. Participation in a study of an investigational drug or device within 30 days prior to
             randomization in this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Raymond D Pratt, MC FACP</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Rockwell Medical Inc</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55404</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 8, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 27, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Soluble Ferric Pyrophosphate,</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetics,</keyword>
  <keyword>Iron, Mass Transfer,</keyword>
  <keyword>Hemodialysis</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic therapy;</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Iron</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
