<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="104156">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01822561</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEEC-10722</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01822561</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Eplerenone for Central Serous Chorioretinopathy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Eplerenone for Central Serous Chorioretinopathy: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tufts Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tufts Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      -  The goal of the study is to examine the short-term effects and safety of a systemic
           anti-aldosterone medication, eplerenone, in a small group of patients with central
           serous chorioretinopathy (CSCR).

        -  There is currently no standard treatment or therapy for either acute or chronic CSCR, a
           potentially debilitating eye disease.

        -  There is evidence in both animals and humans that high blood serum corticosteroid
           levels can cause or worsen CSCR or findings similar to CSCR in the choroid and retina

        -  Eplerenone, a mineralocorticoid receptor antagonist, has been shown to be of visual and
           anatomic benefit in a small series of 4 patients with chronic CSCR, suggesting that
           decreasing mineralocorticoid action in the eye may improve signs and symptoms of CSCR

        -  The investigators' aim is to evaluate a standardized dose of eplerenone in a controlled
           prospective fashion for both acute and chronic CSCR.

        -  The study consists of taking a standard dose of eplerenone, 50mg once daily, for 1
           month

        -  Over the course of the month, patients will be monitored for side effects, as well as
           visual and anatomical response to the medication
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      -  The investigators hypothesize that aldosterone inhibition with eplerenone will decrease
           choroidal vessel vasodilation, focal leakage, and choroidal thickness in patients with
           both acute and chronic CSCR, leading to resolution of subretinal fluid and ultimately
           an improvement in symptoms.

        -  Resolution of sub-retinal fluid will be the primary outcome, which can be precisely
           measured using optical coherence tomography (OCT)

        -  Secondary outcomes will include: Change in macular thickness measured with OCT,  in
           central macular circle thickness on OCT, change in visual acuity, change in dye leakage
           characteristics on fluorescein angiography, change in OCT characteristics of the fellow
           eye, and safety and tolerability characteristics

        -  In acute CSCR, subretinal fluid often resolves on its own, but it often takes several
           months (the literature shows that ~20% of patients have complete resolution of
           sub-retinal fluid on OCT 1 month after presentation)

        -  Chronic CSCR is defined as persistent fluid on OCT after 3 months of symptom onset, or
           recurrence of signs and symptoms within 1 year after the prior episode

        -  In this study, the investigators will not make a distinction between acute and chronic
           CSCR

        -  Eplerenone, a generic medication, is a potassium sparing diuretic, which is FDA
           approved to treat heart failure as well as high blood pressure, but is not FDA approved
           for treatment of central serous chorioretinopathy.

        -  The most important side effect of eplerenone is elevation of serum potassium and
           decrease of blood pressure

        -  Patients will therefore be screened with routine blood tests as suggested by the
           package insert of the medication, and serum potassium and blood pressure will be
           monitored routinely as directed by the medication package insert

        -  Study visits will be performed at therapy initiation, 1 week, 2 weeks, and 4 weeks
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Resolution of Sub-retinal Fluid</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 month after treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Optical coherence tomography (OCT) is an imaging technique capable of extremely high resolution (~5-7 microns) imaging of the macula, and is able to detect the presence and amount of subretinal fluid present, the key anatomic abnormality in Central Serous Chorioretinopathy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in macular thickness</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 month after treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Automated software to calculate the thickness of the macula is standard on commercial OCT devices.  Macular thickness before and after treatment will be assessed and compared.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Best Corrected Visual Acuity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 month after treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Visual acuity will be measured with standard ETDRS eye charts, with manifest refraction at the initiation and conclusion of treatment.  Although an important measure, this was not chosen as the primary outcome measure, as some patients with central serous chorioretinopathy may have a normal visual acuity when properly refracted (refraction can change with elevation of the macula by sub-retinal fluid)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in choroidal thickness, both eyes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 month after treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Choroidal thickness can be measured using OCT, and is known to be affected in patients with central serous chorioretinopathy.  OCT characteristics may be affected in the fellow eye.  Thickness of the choroid under the fovea will be manually calculated in both the study eye and the fellow eye.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and Tolerability Characteristics</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 month after treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Eplerenone can cause elevation of serum potassium, cholesterol, and LFT's, as well as decrease the blood pressure.  After initial screening, serum potassium and creatinine will be evaluated at 1 and 4 weeks after baseline. Additional serum tests of electrolytes, liver function tests, uric acid, and a fasting cholesterol panel will be obtained before treatment and 4 weeks after baseline.  Adverse and Serious Adverse Events will be recorded and reported to the Institutional Review Board.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Central Serous Chorioretinopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Eplerenone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients in this study will receive Eplerenone 50mg once daily for 4 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Eplerenone 50mg</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients will receive the same dose of eplerenone.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Eplerenone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Inspra (Pfizer)</other_name>
    <other_name>Eplerenone (Generic)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 18 or over

          2. Ability to give written informed consent

          3. Presence of sub-retinal fluid under the fovea as seen on OCT

          4. Diagnosis of Acute or Chronic CSCR:

               -  Acute CSCR: First presentation to eye clinic with visual symptoms, including
                  decreased vision or visual distortion, and the characteristic appearance of CSCR
                  on examination, fluorescein angiography, and OCT.

               -  Chronic CSCR: Previous diagnosis of CSCR, persistent subretinal fluid on OCT for
                  more than 3 months after initial presentation to the eye clinic, and &lt;50%
                  reduction in fluid thickness on OCT after 3 months.  Patients who have had
                  previous treatment for CSCR may be included.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Age less than 18

          2. Persons with impaired decision-making ability.

          3. Women who are known to be pregnant or are actively trying to conceive.

          4. Additional eye disease affecting the macula or posterior retina.

          5. At screening, serum potassium concentration ≥5.0 mEq/L , a serum creatinine
             concentration &gt;2 mg/dL in men and &gt;1.8 mg/dL in women, or a creatinine clearance &lt;50
             mL/min, and during concomitant administration of potassium supplements,
             potassium-sparing diuretics, and/or potent CYP3A4 inhibitors (amifostine,
             cyclosporine, fluconazole, itraconazole, ketoconazole, mifepristone, posaconazole,
             potassium salts, Rituximab, tacrolimus or voriconazole).

          6. Patients with type 2 diabetes will be screened for microalbuminuria with a
             urinalysis. If microalbuminuria is present, these patients will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New England Eye Center / Tufts Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andre J Witkin, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-646-7950</phone>
      <email>awitkin@tuftsmedicalcenter.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Julie Burt</last_name>
      <phone>617-636-0747</phone>
      <email>jburt@tuftsmedicalcenter.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andre J Witkin, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jay S Duker, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elias Reichel, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Caroline R Baumal, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Adam R Rogers, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nadia K Waheed, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Roger Goldberg, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marissa Weber, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jordana Fein, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhao M, Célérier I, Bousquet E, Jeanny JC, Jonet L, Savoldelli M, Offret O, Curan A, Farman N, Jaisser F, Behar-Cohen F. Mineralocorticoid receptor is involved in rat and human ocular chorioretinopathy. J Clin Invest. 2012 Jul 2;122(7):2672-9. doi: 10.1172/JCI61427. Epub 2012 Jun 11.</citation>
    <PMID>22684104</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gemenetzi M, De Salvo G, Lotery AJ. Central serous chorioretinopathy: an update on pathogenesis and treatment. Eye (Lond). 2010 Dec;24(12):1743-56. doi: 10.1038/eye.2010.130. Epub 2010 Oct 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20930852</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bouzas EA, Karadimas P, Pournaras CJ. Central serous chorioretinopathy and glucocorticoids. Surv Ophthalmol. 2002 Sep-Oct;47(5):431-48. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12431693</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chan WM, Lai TY, Lai RY, Liu DT, Lam DS. Half-dose verteporfin photodynamic therapy for acute central serous chorioretinopathy: one-year results of a randomized controlled trial. Ophthalmology. 2008 Oct;115(10):1756-65. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2008.04.014. Epub 2008 Jun 5.</citation>
    <PMID>18538401</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Imamura Y, Fujiwara T, Margolis R, Spaide RF. Enhanced depth imaging optical coherence tomography of the choroid in central serous chorioretinopathy. Retina. 2009 Nov-Dec;29(10):1469-73.</citation>
    <PMID>19898183</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reibaldi M, Cardascia N, Longo A, Furino C, Avitabile T, Faro S, Sanfilippo M, Russo A, Uva MG, Munno F, Cannemi V, Zagari M, Boscia F. Standard-fluence versus low-fluence photodynamic therapy in chronic central serous chorioretinopathy: a nonrandomized clinical trial. Am J Ophthalmol. 2010 Feb;149(2):307-315.e2. doi: 10.1016/j.ajo.2009.08.026. Epub 2009 Nov 6.</citation>
    <PMID>19896635</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Robertson DM, Ilstrup D. Direct, indirect, and sham laser photocoagulation in the management of central serous chorioretinopathy. Am J Ophthalmol. 1983 Apr;95(4):457-66.</citation>
    <PMID>6682293</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nielsen JS, Jampol LM. Oral mifepristone for chronic central serous chorioretinopathy. Retina. 2011 Oct;31(9):1928-36. doi: 10.1097/IAE.0b013e31821c3ef6.</citation>
    <PMID>21878843</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Forooghian F, Meleth AD, Cukras C, Chew EY, Wong WT, Meyerle CB. Finasteride for chronic central serous chorioretinopathy. Retina. 2011 Apr;31(4):766-71. doi: 10.1097/IAE.0b013e3181f04a35.</citation>
    <PMID>21273946</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weinberger MH, Roniker B, Krause SL, Weiss RJ. Eplerenone, a selective aldosterone blocker, in mild-to-moderate hypertension. Am J Hypertens. 2002 Aug;15(8):709-16.</citation>
    <PMID>12160194</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pitt B, Remme W, Zannad F, Neaton J, Martinez F, Roniker B, Bittman R, Hurley S, Kleiman J, Gatlin M; Eplerenone Post-Acute Myocardial Infarction Heart Failure Efficacy and Survival Study Investigators. Eplerenone, a selective aldosterone blocker, in patients with left ventricular dysfunction after myocardial infarction. N Engl J Med. 2003 Apr 3;348(14):1309-21. Epub 2003 Mar 31. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2003 May 29;348(22):2271.</citation>
    <PMID>12668699</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fujimoto H, Gomi F, Wakabayashi T, Sawa M, Tsujikawa M, Tano Y. Morphologic changes in acute central serous chorioretinopathy evaluated by fourier-domain optical coherence tomography. Ophthalmology. 2008 Sep;115(9):1494-500, 1500.e1-2. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2008.01.021. Epub 2008 Apr 18.</citation>
    <PMID>18394706</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 10, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 25, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Central Serous Chorioretinopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Eplerenone</keyword>
  <keyword>Optical Coherence Tomography</keyword>
  <keyword>Enhanced Depth Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Subretinal Fluid</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Central Serous Chorioretinopathy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Eplerenone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Spironolactone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
