<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="156564">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02082392</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>#6652</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02082392</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Developing New Clinical Management Strategies</brief_title>
  <official_title>Developing New Clinical Management Strategies for Antidepressant Treatments</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York State Psychiatric Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York State Psychiatric Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to develop new methods of administering antidepressant medications
      that will result in improved drug/placebo separation in randomized controlled trials (RCTs)
      for Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) and enhanced medication response in open clinical
      treatment. The highly intensive, weekly visit schedule followed in most antidepressant RCTs
      radically differs from how antidepressant medications are prescribed in standard clinical
      practice and is believed to be a major reason why the majority of studies submitted to the
      Food and Drug Administration (FDA) fail to show a significant difference between medication
      and placebo. Moreover, a &quot;one size fits all&quot; approach to psychopharmacologic management
      (i.e., weekly visits for all patients) does not take into account differences between
      patients that may predispose some individuals to respond positively to frequent follow-up
      visits, while others may respond negatively or not at all. Clinic visits comprise multiple
      components that may be therapeutic for depression, including activating patients' behavior,
      exposing them to medical procedures, permitting social interactions with research staff, and
      providing supportive meetings with clinicians. Two independent meta-analyses have associated
      more frequent study visits with increased antidepressant and placebo response as well as
      decreased separation between medication and placebo. Despite the high costs and potential
      disadvantages of weekly follow-up visits for patients receiving antidepressant medication,
      this clinical management strategy has not been studied prospectively to date. It is unknown
      whether weekly follow-up visits are needed to ensure treatment compliance and patient safety
      in clinical trials and to what degree contacts with clinicians influence medication and
      placebo response.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study utilizes a 2 x 2, double-blind, acute, prospective design randomizing adult
      outpatients with MDD to &quot;Research Frequency Management&quot; (RFM, weekly study visits) vs.
      &quot;Community Frequency Management&quot; (CFM, every 4 weeks study visits) and antidepressant
      medication vs.placebo. Specifying visit frequency as the independent variable in this study
      has the distinct advantages of being easily operationalized for research purposes avoiding a
      priori assumptions about which components of study visits influence antidepressant and
      placebo response (i.e., behavioral activation vs. doctor-patient relationship vs. medical
      procedures). Close monitoring of all subjects will be assured by telephone evaluations of
      individuals randomized to CFM at intervals between monthly visits, and additional study
      contacts will be scheduled as necessary to maintain patient safety (all extra-protocol
      contacts will be recorded and included as a variable in outcome analyses). Additionally,
      subjects will be characterized extensively on clinical, demographic, and psychological
      measures to pilot the study assessment battery and search for predictor variables
      influencing the effects of contact frequency on medication and placebo response.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>8 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>scale for depressive symptoms administered by trained rater. The HRSD is the standard measure of depression severity for clinical trials of antidepressants and was chosen as the primary outcome measure over other depression rating scales to ensure compatibility of study results with our meta-analyses and ongoing studies of expectancy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hamilton Anxiety Rating Scale (HARS) 14-item scale</measure>
    <time_frame>8 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Scale for anxiety symptoms administered by trained rater. The HARS is a standard measure of anxiety severity in pharmacotherapy studies that has been shown to have acceptable reliability and validity in studies of depressed patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CGI Severity and Improvement</measure>
    <time_frame>8 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>scales developed to measure the clinician's view of subjects' global functioning before and after initiating a study medication. The CGI correlates well with other standard outcome measures for depression (e.g., HRSD), is sensitive to change in antidepressant trials, and offers clinically understandable anchor points.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment Emergent Symptom Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>8 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>rating scale for physical symptoms reported during the study. This is a standard means of recording drug-related adverse effects that will allow us to assess whether contact frequency is associated with differences in side effects among study subjects.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>California Pharmacotherapy Alliance Scale (CALPAS)—Clinician Version</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>24 item Likert scale rating the clinician's assessment of the therapeutic alliance, particularly about medication issues, with the patient. This scale is superior to other therapeutic alliance scales because it is focused on drug treatment and does not contain items specific to psychotherapy. Prior studies using the CALPAS reported an association between therapeutic alliance and outcome, and some studies found alliance mediated the effect of expectancy on depression outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blind assessment—Clinician Version</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Rates clinician's guess as to the identity of study medication and the confidence in that guess. This assessment is necessary to document the effectiveness of the study's methods of treatment allocation concealment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quick Inventory of Depressive Symptoms—Self Report (QIDS-SR) 16 item scale</measure>
    <time_frame>8 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>rating scale for depressive symptoms based on DSM criteria. A self-report measure for depressive symptoms is valuable in this study, because it is less susceptible to clinician and rater bias. The QIDS-SR has been increasingly used in antidepressant studies (e.g., STAR*D) due to its equivalent weightings for each symptom item, clearly understandable anchor points, and inclusion of all DSM criteria for depression</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment Credibility and Expectancy Scale (CES)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>8 item scale in which subjects rate their impression of the credibility of the treatment and how they estimate their expectation of improvement. The CES is the most widely used measure of expectancy and has demonstrated good psychometric properties in multiple studies. For this study, the primary measure of expectancy will be item 4: &quot;By the end of the treatment period, how much improvement in your depressive symptoms do you think will occur?&quot; (0-100%).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Client Satisfaction Questionnaire 8 (CSQ 8)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>self-administered scale with items rating respondents' satisfaction with mental health services they are receiving on a 4 point Likert scale. Use of the CSQ 8 will allow us to determine whether CFM and RFM are associated with differences in participant satisfaction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cornell Treatment Preference Index</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>scale used in mental health studies to document the type and strength of patients' treatment preferences. We will use a modified version in this study asking subjects &quot;Based on your experience and how you feel right now, which of the visit frequencies in this study would be your first choice?&quot; The strength of this preference will be measured on a 5-point Likert scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Revised Life Orientation Test (LOT-R)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>scale developed to assess individual differences in generalized optimism versus pessimism. Degree of optimism on this scale has been correlated with the magnitude of placebo response observed in studies of placebo analgesia, and we will determine whether LOT-R scores moderate effects of therapeutic contact.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Schedule for Adaptive and Nonadaptive Personality (SNAP)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>this questionnaire is a widely used assessment tool for personality disorders that we will also use to identify predictors of response to varying visit frequency.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>California Pharmacotherapy Alliance Scale (CALPAS)—Patient Version</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>24 item Likert scale rating the patient's assessment of the therapeutic alliance, particularly about medication issues, with the clinician. This scale is superior to other therapeutic alliance scales because it is focused on drug treatment and does not contain items specific to psychotherapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blind assessment—Patient Version</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>rates subject's guess as to the identity of study medication and the confidence in that guess. This assessment is necessary to document the effectiveness of the study's methods of treatment allocation concealment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Clinical Frequency Management</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study visits monthly (Week 0, 4, and 8), with phone visits every other week (Week 2 and 6).  Double-blind, placebo-controlled treatment with escitalopram 10mg/day, raised to 20mg/day, if non-responders at week 4.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Research Frequency Management</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Weekly study visits, treatment with double-blind, placebo controlled escitalopram 10 mg/day, raised to 20mg/day at week 4 if non-responders.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Escitalopram</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Clinical Frequency Management</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Research Frequency Management</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lexapro</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1. men and women aged 18-60 years

          -  2. diagnosis with Diagnostic and Statistical Manual (DSM) IV Major Depressive
             Disorder (MDD)

          -  3. 24-item Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression (HRSD) score greater than or equal to
             18

          -  4. capable of providing informed consent and complying with study procedures

          -  5. using appropriate contraceptive method if woman of child-bearing age

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1.  Current comorbid Axis I DSM IV disorder other than Nicotine Dependence,
             Adjustment Disorder, or Anxiety Disorder

          -  2.  diagnosis of substance abuse or dependence (excluding Nicotine Dependence) within
             the past 12 months

          -  3. present or past history of psychosis, psychotic disorder, mania, or bipolar
             disorder

          -  4. baseline HRSD score &gt; 28 or HRSD suicide item &gt; 2

          -  5. history of allergic or adverse reaction to escitalopram, or non-response to
             adequate trial of escitalopram (at least 4 weeks at dose of 20mg) during the current
             episode

          -  6. current treatment with psychotherapy, antidepressants, antipsychotics, or mood
             stabilizers

          -  7. CGI-Severity score of 7 at baseline

          -  8. acute, severe, or unstable medical illness 8. Clinical
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bret Rutherford, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>New York State Psychiatric Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York State Psychiatric Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jane Tandler</last_name>
      <phone>646-774-6852</phone>
      <email>tandler@nyspi.columbia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bret Rutherford, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 6, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 6, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dexetimide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Citalopram</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
