<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="111040">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02028065</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>8616-101</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-004640-37</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02028065</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Incidence of Hypersensitivity After Administration of Sugammadex in Healthy Participants (MK-8616-101)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Parallel Group Study to Evaluate the Incidence of Hypersensitivity After Repeated Single Dose Administration of Sugammadex (MK-8616) in Healthy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess the potential for hypersensitivity symptoms upon
      repeat exposure to sugammadex. Healthy participants will be randomized to one of three
      treatment arms: sugammadex 4 mg/kg, sugammadex 16 mg/kg or placebo. During each of Treatment
      Periods 1, 2 and 3, each participant will receive a single intravenous (IV) bolus injection
      of their randomized treatment while confined to the study center. In each Period,
      participants will remain at the study center until completion of the 24-hour post dose
      assessments. An approximately 5-week washout will be required between treatment periods.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with adjudicated symptoms of hypersensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 28 days after last dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with adjudicated anaphylaxis</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 28 days after last dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">375</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypersensitivity</condition>
  <condition>Anaphylaxis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sugammadex 4 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single IV dose of sugammadex 4 mg/kg during each of Treatment Periods 1, 2 and 3 with an approximately 5-week washout between periods</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sugammadex 16 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single IV dose of sugammadex 16 mg/kg during each of Treatment Periods 1, 2 and 3 with an approximately 5-week washout between periods</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single IV administration of placebo during each of Treatment Periods 1, 2 and 3 with an approximately 5-week washout between periods</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sugammadex</intervention_name>
    <description>Sugammadex 4 mg/kg or 16 mg/kg administered as a single IV bolus over 10 seconds</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sugammadex 4 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sugammadex 16 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo administered as a single IV bolus over 10 seconds</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or non-pregnant and non-breast feeding female

          -  Females of childbearing potential must have a serum β-human chorionic gonadotropin
             (β-hCG) level consistent with non-pregnant state and agree to use (and/or have their
             partner use) two acceptable methods of birth control beginning at screening,
             throughout the trial (including washout intervals between treatment periods) and
             until after the post-study follow-up visit

          -  Females not of childbearing potential must be either a) postmenopausal (have not had
             a menstrual period for at least 1 year and have a follicle stimulating hormone [FSH]
             value in the postmenopausal range) or b) surgically sterile (i.e., have had
             hysterectomy, oophorectomy or tubal ligation)

          -  In good health based on medical history, laboratory tests and other assessments

          -  Body Mass Index (BMI) ≥19 and ≤32 kg/m^2

          -  Non-smoker or smokes ≤10 cigarettes/day or equivalent (2 pipes/day, 1 cigar/day) and
             agrees not to smoke while confined at the study center

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Mentally or legally incapacitated, has significant emotional problems at the time of
             screening visit or expected during the conduct of the trial or has a history of
             clinically significant psychiatric disorder of the last 5 years

          -  History of clinically significant endocrine, gastrointestinal, cardiovascular,
             hematological, hepatic, immunological, renal, respiratory, genitourinary or major
             neurological abnormalities or diseases

          -  History of cancer (malignancy)

          -  History of significant multiple and/or severe allergies (e.g., food, drug, latex
             allergy), or has had an anaphylactic reaction or significant intolerability to
             prescription or non-prescription drugs or food

          -  Positive for hepatitis B surface antigen, hepatitis C antibodies or human
             immunodeficiency virus (HIV)

          -  Has had major surgery and/or donated or lost 1 unit of blood (approximately 500 mL)
             within 4 weeks prior to screening

          -  Has participated in another investigational trial within 4 weeks prior to screening

          -  Is unable to refrain from or anticipates the use of any medication, including
             prescription and non-prescription drugs or herbal remedies beginning approximately 2
             weeks prior to administration of the initial dose of trial drug, throughout the trial
             (including washout intervals between treatment periods), until the post-study
             follow-up visit

          -  Has received subcutaneous or sublingual immunotherapy within the past 1 year

          -  Consumes &gt;3 glasses of alcoholic beverages per day

          -  Consumes excessive amounts, defined as &gt;6 servings of coffee, tea, cola, energy
             drinks, or other caffeinated beverages per day

          -  Currently a regular user (including &quot;recreational use&quot;) of any illicit drugs or has a
             history of drug (including alcohol) abuse within approximately 12 months

          -  Has a recollection of previously receiving sugammadex, Bridion™, SCH 900616, ORG
             25969, or MK-8616

          -  History of chronic urticaria or angioedema

          -  Is or has an immediate family member (spouse or children) who is a member of
             investigational site or sponsor staff directly involved with this trial
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 5, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 3, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>reversal of neuromuscular blockade</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anaphylaxis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
