<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="36760">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01828021</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CP-MGAH22-02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01828021</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 2 Study of the Monoclonal Antibody MGAH22(Margetuximab)in Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Advanced Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single Arm, Open-Label, Phase 2 Study of MGAH22 (Fc-optimized Chimeric Anti-HER2 Monoclonal Antibody) in Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Advanced Breast Cancer Whose Tumors Express HER2 at the 2+ Level by Immunohistochemistry and Lack Evidence of HER2 Gene Amplification by FISH</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>MacroGenics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>MacroGenics</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine if MGAH22 is effective in the treatment of certain
      patients with relapsed or refractory advanced breast cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In the pivotal study that established that Herceptin® was highly effective when added to
      standard chemotherapy in the front-line treatment of women with HER2 positive metastatic
      breast cancer, benefit appeared to accrue to those patients whose tumors expressed the HER2
      oncoprotein at the 3+ level by immunohistochemistry (IHC) or those patients whose tumors
      demonstrated evidence of HER2 gene amplification by fluorescence in situ hybridization
      (FISH) testing. Similarly, when Herceptin® was used as a single therapy in women with
      metastatic breast cancer that had progressed following cytotoxic chemotherapy, 3+
      overexpression of HER2, but not 2+ expression, was associated with response to treatment.
      These and other studies have led to the recommendation that Herceptin® should be
      administered to patients with breast cancer whose tumors exhibit 3+ overexpression or gene
      amplification. This study will evaluate whether treatment of patients with tumors that would
      not be expected to respond to Herceptin® therapy, namely those that lack HER2 gene
      amplification and express the oncoprotein at the 2+ level by IHC, may benefit from the use
      of the anti-HER2 monoclonal antibody, MGAH22. If 5 or more responses are seen in 41
      evaluable patients, then further clinical development of MGAH22 will be justified.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 2, Day 22</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Response based on Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1 criteria based on Cycle 2, Day 22 computed tomography (CT) scans. This study will employ a Simon two-stage optimum design in which an initial cohort of 21 patients will be treated with MGAH22. If two or more responses (partial or complete response) are seen at the first tumor re-evaluation on day 22 of Cycle 2, the study will be expanded to include up to 41 patients (20 additional patients in Cohort 2, the second stage of the study) in order to determine whether further development of the drug is warranted (5 or more responses in 41 evaluable patients).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Following Cycle 2 Day 22 of first 21 patients and following Cycle 2 Day 22 of all 41 patients</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Response rate is the proportion of patients achieving a best response of complete response or partial response when such responses are confirmed at least 28 days after initial observation of response.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Response</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until the date of first documented progression, assessed up to 100 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Duration of response is defined as the number of days from initial response to date of disease progression or death. A patient's response duration will be censored if at the time of study completion or study withdrawal, response is ongoing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Day 1 to date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 100 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Progression-free survival (PFS) is defined as the number of days from the date of study enrollment (Study Day 1) to the date of disease progression, death, study completion or study withdrawal, whichever occurs first.  A patient's PFS will be censored if at the time of study completion or study withdrawal, disease progression or death has not occurred.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Day 1 to date of death from any cause assessed up to 100 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall survival (OS) is defined as the number of days from the date of study enrollment  (Study Day 1) to the date of death (by any cause) or last observation, whichever occurs first.  A patient's OS will be censored if at the time of study completion or study withdrawal, the patient remains alive.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>Time of consent to 28 days after last MGAH22 administration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Adverse events (AEs), serious adverse events (SAEs), Electrocardiogram (ECG) monitoring, monitoring for development of anti-drug antibodies</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">41</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MGAH22</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Anti-HER2 monoclonal antibody</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Margetuximab</intervention_name>
    <description>Anti-HER2 monoclonal antibody</description>
    <arm_group_label>MGAH22</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MGAH22</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically or cytologically confirmed invasive carcinoma of the breast

          -  Evidence of progression of disease during or following at least two prior systemic
             therapies for advanced (unresectable locoregional or metastatic) disease

          -  Evidence of HER2 oncoprotein expression at the 2+ level by central laboratory

          -  Evidence of lack of HER2 oncogene amplification as determined by FISH testing by
             central laboratory

          -  Performance Status of 0 or 1

          -  Life expectancy at least 6 months

          -  Measurable disease (by RECIST 1.1)

          -  Acceptable laboratory parameters and organ reserve

          -  Baseline left ventricular ejection fraction &gt;50%

          -  Anti-cancer therapy must be completed and any associated toxicities resolved to
             &lt;=Grade 1 levels or baseline levels and at least 2 weeks must have elapsed before
             enrollment. Treatment with monoclonal antibodies must be completed at least 28 days
             before entry.  Must have completed immunosuppressive medications or vaccinations
             before enrollment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Major surgery or trauma within 4 weeks

          -  Known hypersensitivity to murine or recombinant proteins, polysorbate 80, or any
             excipient contained in the MGAH22 drug formulation

          -  Second primary malignancy that has not been in remission for more than 3 years

          -  History of active viral, bacterial, or systemic fungal infection requiring parenteral
             treatment within 14 days

          -  History within 3 months of deep vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolism, or stroke

          -  Symptomatic or untreated central nervous system (CNS) metastatic disease Patients
             with previously treated CNS metastatic disease which has been stable for at least 56
             days are eligible

          -  Requirement for concurrent steroids &gt; 10 mg/day of oral prednisone or the equivalent,
             except steroid inhaler, nasal spray, or ophthalmic solution

          -  Serious medical condition that would impair the ability to receive or tolerate
             MGAH22; dementia or altered mental status that would preclude provision of informed
             consent

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension, heart disease including history of congestive heart
             failure, history of myocardial infarction, angina pectoris requiring medication,
             clinically significant valvular heart disease, high risk arrhythmias, or disease
             corresponding to New York Heart Association class III or IV.

          -  Significant pulmonary compromise
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark D. Pegram, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stanford J. Stewart, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>MacroGenics</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Seila Liv</last_name>
    <phone>(650) 624-2662</phone>
    <email>livs@macrogenics.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California San Francisco</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hope S Rugo, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark Pegram, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Florida Cancer Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Plantation</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33324</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elizabeth Tan-Chiu, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kathy Miller, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tufts Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John K Erban, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tennessee Oncology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Denise A Yardley, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nordstrom JL, Gorlatov S, Zhang W, Yang Y, Huang L, Burke S, Li H, Ciccarone V, Zhang T, Stavenhagen J, Koenig S, Stewart SJ, Moore PA, Johnson S, Bonvini E. Anti-tumor activity and toxicokinetics analysis of MGAH22, an anti-HER2 monoclonal antibody with enhanced Fcγ receptor binding properties. Breast Cancer Res. 2011;13(6):R123. doi: 10.1186/bcr3069. Epub 2011 Nov 30.</citation>
    <PMID>22129105</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 27, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 26, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HER2 2+</keyword>
  <keyword>FISH non-amplified</keyword>
  <keyword>Relapsed</keyword>
  <keyword>Refractory</keyword>
  <keyword>Advanced</keyword>
  <keyword>Margetuximab</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Trastuzumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
