<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="166665">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02124798</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>200339</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02124798</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase 2B Open-Label, Single-Arm, Repeat-Dose Study to Evaluate the Reliability of an Autoinjector</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label Single-Arm Study to Evaluate the Reliability of an Autoinjector That Administers Belimumab Subcutaneously in Subjects With Systemic Lupus Erythematosus (SLE)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to assess the suitability of the autoinjector for
      self-administration of belimumab by subjects with SLE in real-life conditions. The study
      will assess the use of the autoinjector inside the clinic setting and outside the clinic
      setting. The study will also assess the safety and tolerability of belimumab administered
      subcutaneously (SC) via the autoinjector. Subjects will self-administer belimumab SC into
      the thigh or abdomen using the autoinjector device for 8 weekly doses. Subjects will return
      for a follow-up visit 4 weeks after the last SC dose of belimumab. All injections will be
      assessed by the investigators for success based on direct observation and/or the subject
      diary. A total of 118 subjects (treated with at least one dose of study drug) are planned to
      be enrolled in this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects successfully able to self-administer their observed first and second doses in Weeks 1 and 2</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess the suitability of the autoinjector for self-administration of belimumab by subjects with SLE</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects successfully able to self-administer their observed doses in Weeks 4 and 8</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess the use of the autoinjector inside the clinic setting</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects successfully able to self-administer their doses outside the clinic setting in Weeks 3, 5, 6, and 7</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess the use of the autoinjector outside the clinic setting</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">118</enrollment>
  <condition>Systemic Lupus Erythematosus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will self-administer belimumab SC into thigh or abdomen using the autoinjector device for 8 weekly doses; 4 of the doses will be administered under observation in the clinic and 4 of the doses will be administered outside the clinic and without observation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Belimumab autoinjector</intervention_name>
    <description>Single use, disposable autoinjector assembled with the prefilled syringe containing the drug product belimumab with unit dose strength of 200mg/mL and 1 mL will be given as a once weekly SC dose</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female aged at least 18 years at the time of signing the informed consent.

          -  Have a clinical diagnosis of SLE according to the American College of Rheumatology
             (ACR) criteria.

          -  Active, autoantibody positive SLE, defined as the presence of anti nuclear antibody
             (ANA) or anti-double strand deoxyribonucleic acid (dsDNA) antibodies (at screening or
             historically).

          -  Are on a SLE treatment regimen including intravenous (IV) belimumab every 28 days for
             at least three 28-day cycles.  Day 0 (i.e., day of first dose of study agent) should
             be scheduled about 2 weeks after the last dose IV dose of belimumab but may be
             scheduled 1 week and up to 4 weeks after the last IV dose.

          -  A female subject is eligible to participate if she is of: Non-childbearing potential
             defined as pre-menopausal females with a documented tubal ligation or hysterectomy
             (for this definition, &quot;documented&quot; refers to the outcome of the
             investigator's/designee's review of the subject's medical history for study
             eligibility, as obtained via a verbal interview with the subject or from the
             subject's medical records); or postmenopausal defined as 12 months of spontaneous
             amenorrhea (in questionable cases a blood sample with simultaneous follicle
             stimulating hormone [FSH] &gt;40 milli international unit/milliliter [MIU/mL] and
             estradiol &lt;40 picogram/mL [&lt;147 picomoles/Liter] is confirmatory). (Females on
             hormone replacement therapy [HRT] and whose menopausal status is in doubt will be
             required to use one of the contraception methods if they wish to continue their HRT
             during the study. Otherwise, they must discontinue HRT to allow confirmation of
             post-menopausal status prior to study enrollment. For most forms of HRT, at least 2 4
             weeks will elapse between the cessation of therapy and the blood draw; this interval
             depends on the type and dosage of HRT. Following confirmation of their
             post-menopausal status, they can resume use of HRT during the study without use of a
             contraceptive method.); Child-bearing potential with negative pregnancy test as
             determined by serum human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) test at screening and urine
             hCG test prior to dosing; Agrees to use one of the contraception methods for 2 weeks
             prior to the day of dosing to sufficiently minimize the risk of pregnancy at that
             point.  Female subjects must agree to use contraception until Day 112; OR has only
             same-sex partners, when this is her preferred and usual lifestyle

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &lt;2x upper limit of normal (ULN), alkaline phosphatase
             and bilirubin &lt;=1.5xULN (isolated bilirubin &gt;1.5xULN is acceptable if bilirubin is
             fractionated and direct bilirubin &lt;35%).

          -  Capable of giving written informed consent, which includes compliance with the
             requirements and restrictions listed in the consent form.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Have previously participated in a study of SC belimumab.

          -  Have received a live vaccine within 30 days of Day 0 or anticipate receipt of a live
             vaccine during the study or within 120 days after the last injection of study drug.

          -  Have received a non-biologic investigational agent within 60 days of Day 0.

          -  Have severe active central nervous system (CNS) lupus (including seizures, psychosis,
             organic brain syndrome, cerebrovascular accident (CVA), cerebritis or CNS vasculitis
             requiring therapeutic intervention within 60 days of Day 0.

          -  Have clinical evidence of significant unstable or uncontrolled acute or chronic
             diseases not due to SLE (i.e., cardiovascular, pulmonary, hematologic,
             gastrointestinal, hepatic, renal, neurological, malignancy, or infectious diseases)
             which, in the opinion of the principal investigator, could confound the results of
             the study or put the subject at undue risk.

          -  Have a planned surgical procedure

          -  History of any other medical disease (e.g., cardiopulmonary), laboratory abnormality,
             that, in the opinion of the investigator, makes the subject unsuitable for the study.

          -  Have required management of acute or chronic infections, as follows: Currently on any
             suppressive therapy for a chronic infection (such as tuberculosis, pneumocystis,
             cytomegalovirus, herpes simplex virus, herpes zoster, and atypical mycobacteria);
             Hospitalization for treatment of infection within 60 days of Day 0; Use of parenteral
             (IV or intramascular [IM]) antibiotics (antibacterials, antivirals, anti-fungals, or
             anti-parasitic agents) within 60 days of Day 0.

          -  History of or a positive test for human immuno virus (HIV) at Screening.

          -  A positive Hepatitis B surface antigen or Hepatitis B core antibody, or positive
             Hepatitis C antibody result within 3 months of Screening or positive at Screening.

          -  Have an Immunoglobulin A (IgA) deficiency (IgA level &lt;10 milligrams/deciliter).

          -  Have a Grade 3 or greater laboratory abnormality based on the Adverse Event Severity
             Grading except for the following that are allowed: Stable Grade 3 prothrombin time
             (PT) secondary to warfarin treatment; Stable Grade 3 partial thromboplastin time
             (PTT) due to lupus anticoagulant and not related to liver disease or anti-coagulant
             therapy; Stable Grade 3/4 proteinuria (&lt;=6 grams/24 hour equivalent by spot urine
             protein to creatinine ratio allowed); Stable Grade 3 hypoalbuminemia due to lupus
             nephritis, and not related to liver disease or malnutrition; Stable Grade 3 gamma
             glutamyl transferase (GGT) elevation due to lupus hepatitis, and not related to
             alcoholic liver disease, uncontrolled diabetes, or viral hepatitis. If present, any
             abnormalities in the ALT and/or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) must be&lt;= Grade 2;
             Stable Grade 3 neutropenia or stable Grade 3 white blood cell count. Note: All Grade
             3 or greater laboratory abnormalities will be flagged in the laboratory report.
             Therefore the above exceptions will be determined by the Investigator and Medical
             Monitor.

          -  Have a history of an anaphylactic reaction to parenteral administration of contrast
             agents, human or murine proteins, or monoclonal antibodies

          -  Have evidence of serious suicide risk including any history of suicidal behavior in
             the last 6 months, or who in the investigator's opinion, pose a significant suicide
             risk

          -  Have current drug or alcohol abuse or dependence, or a history of drug or alcohol
             abuse or dependence within 364 days prior to Day 0

          -  Are unable to administer study agent by SC injection.

          -  In the opinion of the investigator, any subject who is unable to read and/or would
             not be able to complete a patient diary.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
    <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lansing</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48917</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 22, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 24, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Subcutaneous</keyword>
  <keyword>Autoinjector</keyword>
  <keyword>Belimumab</keyword>
  <keyword>Real-Life Use Study</keyword>
  <keyword>Reliability</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Lupus Erythematosus, Systemic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
