<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="159813">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01933594</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A5315</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>11892</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>ACTG 5315</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01933594</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluating the Safety and Efficacy of Single-Dose Romidepsin in Combination With Antiretroviral Therapy in HIV-Infected Adults With Suppressed Viral Load</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Study of Single Dose Romidepsin in HIV-Infected Adults With Suppressed Viremia on Antiretroviral Therapy to Assess Safety, Tolerability, and Activation of HIV-1 Expression</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Antiretroviral therapy (ART) can reduce HIV to very low levels in the blood, but it cannot
      cure HIV infection because a small amount of virus remains in cells as a hidden (latent)
      form. The purpose of this study is to identify single doses of the drug romidepsin (RMD)
      that are safe and well tolerated, and that induce HIV-1 expression in HIV-1-infected adults
      who are on either efavirenz (EFV)-, raltegravir (RAL)-, or dolutegravir (DTG)-based ART
      regimens.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A major challenge in eradicating HIV-1 infection is the persistence of virus in long-lived
      cells, such as latently infected memory CD4 T cells. One approach for eliminating the HIV-1
      reservoir is to activate viral replication in these latently infected CD4 T cells by
      targeting cellular mechanisms that repress proviral transcription. Histone deacetylase
      inhibitors (HDACis), such as RMD, induce HIV-1 expression by increasing acetylation and
      facilitating transcriptional activation of HIV-1. RMD administered in combination with ART
      may serve as an important component of a strategy to eradicate the HIV-1 latent reservoir.
      The purpose of this study is to identify single doses of RMD that are safe and well
      tolerated, and that induce HIV-1 expression in HIV-1-infected adults who are on either EFV-,
      RAL-, or DTG-based ART regimens.

      Participants will be randomly assigned to either the RMD or the placebo arm of one of three
      cohorts. The three cohorts will differ in the dose of RMD given. Participants will be
      enrolled into Cohort 1 first; if the dose given to Cohort 1 is well tolerated and no safety
      concerns are noted, Cohort 2 will be enrolled. If the dose given to Cohort 2 is well
      tolerated and no safety concerns are noted, Cohort 3 will be enrolled.

      This study will last for 28 or 56 days; some participants will attend study visits only
      through Day 28, and some will return for a study visit on Day 56. Whether a participant
      continues to Day 56 depends on his or her HIV-1 RNA level at the Day 7 visit or whether the
      participant experiences a Grade 3 or higher adverse event (AE).

      At the screening visit, participants will give a medical history and will undergo a physical
      exam; blood and urine samples will be collected. At the entry visit, RMD or placebo will be
      administered as an intravenous (IV) infusion over 4 hours. An electrocardiogram (ECG) will
      be administered before, immediately after, and 14 days after infusion. Participants will
      undergo pharmacokinetic (PK) sampling which will require that blood be drawn before the
      infusion; during the infusion; 4, 6, 12, 24, and 48 hours after the infusion; and on Days 7,
      14, and 28. Some participants may also have blood drawn at a Day 56 visit. If participants
      agree, their blood samples may be stored for future research.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of Grade 3 or higher adverse events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through 28 days after the administration of RMD or placebo</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Including signs/symptoms, lab toxicities, and /or clinical events that is probably, possibly, or definitely related to study treatment (as judged by the core team, blinded to treatment arm)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in plasma HIV-1 RNA levels from baseline (average of pre-entry and entry values) as detected by single copy assay</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through 48 hours (average) after the administration of RMD or placebo</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cell-associated HIV-1 RNA levels in resting CD4 T cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through 24 hours after the administration of RMD or placebo</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in plasma HIV-1 RNA levels as detected by single copy assay</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through 28 days after the administration of RMD and placebo</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cell-associated HIV-1 RNA levels in resting CD4 T cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through 14 days after the administration of RMD or placebo</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in cell-associated HIV-1 RNA levels in total CD4 T cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through 28 days after the administration of RMD or placebo</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in histone acetylation in total CD4 T cells by flow cytometry</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through 14 days after the administration of RMD or placebo</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in total HIV-1 DNA and 2-long terminal repeat (LTR) circles in resting or total CD4 T cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through 28 days after the administration of RMD or placebo</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters (area under the curve [AUC], maximum concentration [Cmax], and minimum concentration [Cmin]) for RMD and co-administered antiretroviral drugs (EFV, DTG, or RAL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through 24 hours after the administration of RMD or placebo</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number/percent of participants with HIV-1 RNA levels greater than or equal to 200 copies</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through 7 days after the administration of RMD or placebo</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All reported Grade 2 through 4 AEs</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through 28 or 56 days after the administration of RMD or placebo</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Whether this is measured through 28 or 56 days after the administration of RMD or placebo depends on when the participant's last study visit is.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1-Arm 1A (RMD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in Cohort 1, Arm 1A will receive RMD intravenously (IV) over 4 hours (beginning at Hour 0) at the Day 1 study visit. Dose of RMD will be 0.5 mg/m^2, with total dose based on the participant's body surface area (BSA), which is determined by participant's height and weight.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1-Arm 1B (Placebo for RMD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in Cohort 1, Arm 1B will receive 0.9% sodium chloride for injection IV over 4 hours (beginning at Hour 0) at the Day 1 study visit. Dose of sodium chloride for injection placebo will be 0.5 mg/m^2, with total dose based on the participant's BSA, which will be determined by weight and height.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2-Arm 2A (RMD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in Cohort 2, Arm 2A will receive RMD IV over 4 hours (beginning at Hour 0) at the Day 1 study visit. Dose of RMD will be 2 mg/m^2, with total dose based on the participant's BSA, which is determined by participant's height and weight.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2-Arm 2B (Placebo for RMD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in Cohort 2, Arm 2B will receive 0.9% sodium chloride for injection IV over 4 hours (beginning at Hour 0) at the Day 1 study visit. Dose of sodium chloride for injection placebo will be 2 mg/m^2, with total dose based on the participant's BSA, which will be determined by weight and height.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3-Arm 3A (RMD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in Cohort 3, Arm 3A will receive RMD IV over 4 hours (beginning at Hour 0) at the Day 1 study visit. Dose of RMD will be 5 mg/m^2, with total dose based on the participant's BSA, which is determined by participant's height and weight.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3-Arm 3B (Placebo for RMD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in Cohort 3, Arm 3B will receive 0.9% sodium chloride for injection  IV over 4 hours (beginning at Hour 0) at the Day 1 study visit. Dose of sodium chloride for injection placebo will be 5 mg/m^2, with total dose based on the participant's BSA, which will be determined by weight and height.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Romidepsin</intervention_name>
    <description>RMD will be administered over 4 hours via an intravenous (IV) catheter placed into a peripheral vein.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1-Arm 1A (RMD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2-Arm 2A (RMD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3-Arm 3A (RMD)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>RMD</other_name>
    <other_name>Istodax</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo for RMD: 0.9% sodium chloride for injection</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo for RMD will be administered over 4 hours via an IV catheter placed into a peripheral vein.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1-Arm 1B (Placebo for RMD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2-Arm 2B (Placebo for RMD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3-Arm 3B (Placebo for RMD)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>0.9% NaCl</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV-1 infection, documented by any licensed rapid HIV test or HIV enzyme or
             chemiluminescence immunoassay (E/CIA) test kit at any time prior to study entry and
             confirmed by a licensed Western blot or a second antibody test by a method other than
             the initial rapid HIV and/or E/CIA, or by HIV-1 antigen or plasma HIV-1 RNA. More
             information on this criterion is available in the protocol.

          -  Receiving a raltegravir-, dolutegravir-, efavirenz-based Department of Health and
             Human Services (DHHS)-recommended antiretroviral therapy (ART) regimen for at least
             90 days prior to study entry (i.e., regimens in the DHHS' &quot;not recommended category&quot;
             are not allowed) with no intention to change for the duration of the study. More
             information on this criterion is available in the protocol.

          -  Documentation of at least two historical HIV-1 RNA measurements less than 50
             copies/mL while on ART obtained by standard ultrasensitive assay. Documentation of
             the first measurement must be from a result obtained between 365 days and 91 days,
             inclusive, prior to study entry. Documentation of the second measurement must be from
             a result obtained between 730 days and 366 days, inclusive, prior to study entry. In
             addition, there must be no HIV-1 RNA values greater than or equal to 50 copies/mL for
             at least 365 days prior to study entry.

          -  CD4 cell count equal to or greater than 300 cells/mm^3 obtained within 90 to 50 days
             prior to study entry at any United States laboratory that has a Clinical Laboratory
             Improvement Amendment (CLIA) certification or its equivalent

          -  HIV-1 RNA level of fewer than 50 copies/mL obtained by standard ultrasensitive assay
             within 90 to 50 days prior to study entry

          -  HIV-1 RNA level of 0.4 copies/mL or greater obtained by single copy assay (SCA)
             within 90 to 50 days prior to study entry. This result must be available prior to the
             pre-entry visit.

          -  The following laboratory values obtained within 21 to 0 days prior to study entry by
             any US laboratory that has a CLIA certification or its equivalent.

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) equal to or greater than 1,500 cells/mm^3

               -  Hemoglobin equal to or greater than 12.0 g/dL for men and greater than 11.0 g/dL
                  for women

               -  Platelet count equal to or greater than 120,000/mm^3

          -  The following laboratory values obtained within 21 to 7 days prior to study entry by
             any United States laboratory that has a CLIA certification or its equivalent:

               -  Creatinine clearance (CrCl) equal to or greater than 60 mL/min. More information
                  on this criterion is available in the protocol.

               -  Potassium and magnesium within normal limits.More information on this criterion
                  is available in the protocol.

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase
                  [SGOT]) less than 2.0 times the upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamic-pyruvic transaminase [SGPT]) less
                  than 2.0 times ULN

               -  Alkaline phosphatase less than 2.0 times ULN

               -  Total bilirubin less than 2.5 times ULN

          -  Hepatitis C virus (HCV) antibody negative result within 90 to 50 days prior to study
             entry or, if the HCV antibody result is positive, a negative HCV RNA result obtained
             within 90 to 50 days prior to study entry

          -  Negative hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) result obtained within 90 to 50 days
             prior to study entry

          -  For females of reproductive potential, negative serum or urine pregnancy test (urine
             pregnancy test with a sensitivity of less than or equal to 25 mIU/mL) at the
             screening visit, pre-entry visit within 21 to 7 days prior to study entry, and at
             entry prior to romidepsin infusion, by any United States laboratory that has a CLIA
             certification or its equivalent. Reproductive potential is defined as: girls who have
             reached menarche, women who have had menses within the past 12 months and who do not
             have a follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) greater than 40 IU/L, women who have had
             menses within the past 24 consecutive months if an FSH measurement is not available,
             or women who have not undergone surgical sterilization (e.g., hysterectomy, bilateral
             oophorectomy, or bilateral salpingectomy). More information on this criterion is
             available in the protocol.

          -  Female participants of reproductive potential must refrain from participating in
             active attempts to become pregnant, and, if participating in sexual activity that
             could lead to pregnancy, must agree to use at least two reliable forms of
             contraception that are non-estrogen based. All participants of reproductive potential
             must be instructed to use contraceptives for 6 months/180 days after completing RMD
             or placebo infusion. Acceptable forms of contraception include: condoms (male or
             female) with or without spermicidal agent; diaphragm or cervical cap with spermicide;
             non-hormonal or progestin-only containing intrauterine device (IUD) (e.g., Mirena,
             Implanon, Nuva Ring); tubal ligation; or non-estrogen containing formulations of
             hormonal birth control drugs, given by pills, shots, or placed on or under the skin,
             for at least 90 days prior to study entry. More information on this criterion is
             available in the protocol.

          -  Karnofsky performance score of at least 80 within 21 to 7 days prior to study entry

          -  Ability and willingness to provide written informed consent

          -  Site investigator anticipates that a fully active alternative ART regimen could be
             constructed in the event of virologic failure on the current ART regimen

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of or current malignancy requiring cytotoxic therapy

          -  Bacterial, fungal, or viral infection (other than HIV) requiring systemic therapy
             within 30 days prior to entry

          -  History of or current cytomegalovirus (CMV) end organ disease (e.g., retinitis)

          -  History of or current AIDS-related syndromes or symptoms that pose a perceived
             excessive risk for study drug-related morbidity, as determined by the site
             investigator

          -  Chronic, acute, or recurrent infections that are current and serious in the opinion
             of the site investigator and for which the participant has not completed at least 14
             consecutive days of therapy within 30 days prior to study entry and/or is not
             clinically stable

          -  Active autoimmune disorders including but not limited to: inflammatory bowel
             diseases, scleroderma, severe psoriasis as determined by the site investigator,
             systemic lupus erythematosus, rheumatoid arthritis, and optic neuritis

          -  History of seizure disorders

          -  History of anticonvulsant use within 60 days prior to study entry

          -  History of myocardial infarction (MI) within 6 months prior to study entry, history
             of QTc prolongation (defined as electrocardiogram [ECG] with QTc intervals greater
             than 450 ms) at any time prior to study entry, New York Heart Association (NYHA)
             class III or IV heart failure at any time prior to study entry, or family history of
             prolonged QTc syndrome

          -  Breastfeeding

          -  Use of immunomodulators (e.g., interleukins, interferons, cyclosporine), HIV vaccine,
             systemic cytotoxic chemotherapy, or investigational therapy within 60 days prior to
             study entry. More information on this criterion is available in the protocol.

          -  Any vaccination within 30 days prior to entry or intent to receive an elective
             vaccination (e.g., flu shot, hepatitis A vaccine, or hepatitis B vaccine) during the
             course of the study.

          -  Intent to use cytokines (e.g., interleukin 2 [IL-2] or interleukin 12 [IL-12]) during
             the course of the study. Prior administration of cytokines is not an exclusion
             criterion; however, at least 60 days between the most recent cycle of any cytokine
             and study entry is required.

          -  Within 60 days prior to study entry, use of systemic azole antifungals (voriconazole,
             itraconazole, ketoconazole); dexamethasone; macrolide antibiotics (azithromycin,
             clarithromycin, erythromycin); ARVs that are inhibitors of, or are metabolized by,
             cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) (atazanavir, ritonavir, nelfinavir, indinavir,
             saquinavir, darunavir, lopinavir, rilpivirine, maraviroc); cobicistat; warfarin;
             nefazodone; rifamycins (rifabutin, rifampin, rifapentine); St. John's Wort;
             carbamazepine; phenytoin; phenobarbital; amiodarone; dofetilide; pimozide;
             procainamide; quinidine; sotalol; and birth control products containing estrogen;
             drugs that are p-glycoprotein inhibitors; and drugs that prolong the QTc interval
             with a risk of Torsades de Pointes. More information on this criterion is available
             in the protocol.

          -  Known allergy, sensitivity, or any hypersensitivity to components of RMD or its
             formulation

          -  Use of histone deacetylase inhibitors (e.g., vorinostat, valproic acid) at any time
             prior to study entry

          -  Active illicit drug or alcohol use or dependence that, in the opinion of the site
             investigator, would interfere with adherence to study requirements

          -  Acute or serious illness requiring systemic treatment and/or hospitalization that is
             not resolved within 30 days prior to entry

          -  Psychosocial conditions that would prevent study compliance and follow-up, as
             determined by the site investigator

          -  Documented opportunistic infections within 60 days prior to entry

          -  Known history of poor peripheral venous access
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Mellors, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Deborah McMahon, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alabama CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karen Savage, R.N., B.S.N.</last_name>
      <phone>205-975-7925</phone>
      <email>kgsavage@uab.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA CARE Center CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90035</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Arezou S. Akha</last_name>
      <phone>310-557-3798</phone>
      <email>asadighi@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ucsf Hiv/Aids Crs</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jay Dwyer</last_name>
      <phone>415-476-4082</phone>
      <phone_ext>353</phone_ext>
      <email>jdwyer@php.ucsf.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Hospital CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mary Graham Ray, R.N., M.S.N.</last_name>
      <phone>303-724-0712</phone>
      <email>graham.ray@ucdenver.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital CRS (MGH CRS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Theresa Flynn, R.N., M.S.N., A.N.P.</last_name>
      <phone>617-724-0072</phone>
      <email>tflynn@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham and Women's Hospital Therapeutics Clinical Research Site (BWH TCRS) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cheryl E. Keenan</last_name>
      <phone>617-732-5635</phone>
      <email>ckeenan2@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Rochester Adult HIV Therapeutic Strategies Network CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Emily L. Cosimano, B.S.N.</last_name>
      <phone>585-276-5903</phone>
      <email>Emily_Cosimano@urmc.rochester.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chapel Hill CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Susan Pedersen</last_name>
      <phone>919-966-6713</phone>
      <email>spederse@med.unc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Case CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jane Baum, R.N.</last_name>
      <phone>216-844-2546</phone>
      <email>jb@clevelandactu.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kathy Watson, B.S.N.</last_name>
      <phone>614-293-5856</phone>
      <email>kathy.watson@osumc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Penn Therapeutics, CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joseph Quinn, R.N.</last_name>
      <phone>215-349-8093</phone>
      <email>joseph.quinn@uphs.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carol Oriss, R.N.</last_name>
      <phone>412-383-1434</phone>
      <email>orissca@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt Therapeutics (VT) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37204</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Deborah Sutherland, R.N., B.S.N., C.C.R.P.</last_name>
      <phone>615-936-8516</phone>
      <email>deborah.sutherland@vanderbilt.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Washington AIDS CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98104-9929</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christine Jonsson</last_name>
      <phone>206-744-8886</phone>
      <email>cjonsson@u.washington.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ylisastigui L, Archin NM, Lehrman G, Bosch RJ, Margolis DM. Coaxing HIV-1 from resting CD4 T cells: histone deacetylase inhibition allows latent viral expression. AIDS. 2004 May 21;18(8):1101-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15166525</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klimek VM, Fircanis S, Maslak P, Guernah I, Baum M, Wu N, Panageas K, Wright JJ, Pandolfi PP, Nimer SD. Tolerability, pharmacodynamics, and pharmacokinetics studies of depsipeptide (romidepsin) in patients with acute myelogenous leukemia or advanced myelodysplastic syndromes. Clin Cancer Res. 2008 Feb 1;14(3):826-32.</citation>
    <PMID>18245545</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 28, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Romidepsin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
