<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="127940">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02129075</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2014-00898</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2014-00898</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CITN-07-FLT3L</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CITN-07-FLT3L</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U01CA154967</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02129075</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CDX-1401 and Poly-ICLC Vaccine Therapy With or Without CDX-301in Treating Patients With Stage IIB-IV Melanoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II, Open-Label, Multicenter, Randomized Study of CDX-1401, a Dendritic Cell Targeting NY-ESO-1 Vaccine, in Patients With Malignant Melanoma Pre-treated With Recombinant CDX-301, a Recombinant Human Flt3 Ligand</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized phase II trial studies how well DEC-205/NY-ESO-1 fusion protein CDX-1401
      (CDX-1401) and neoantigen-based melanoma-poly-ICLC vaccine (poly-ICLC) vaccine therapy work
      when given with or without recombinant flt3 ligand (CDX-301) in treating patients with stage
      IIB-IV melanoma. The cancer vaccine CDX-1401 attaches to a protein that is made in tumor
      cells. The vaccine helps the body recognize the tumor to fight the cancer. The CDX-301
      vaccine may help the body make more of the tumor fighting cells, known as dendritic cells.
      The poly-ICLC vaccine stimulates the immune system and may help these dendritic cells mature
      so that they can recognize the tumor. It is not yet know whether CDX-1401 and poly-ICLC will
      work better with or without CDX-301 in treating melanoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine whether the immune response to cancer/testis antigen 1B (NY-ESO-1) elicited
      by vaccination with CDX-1401 (anti-DEC205-NY-ESO-1 fusion protein vaccine) plus
      poly-cytidylic with poly-lysine (poly-ICLC) is substantially increased by prior expansion in
      the number of circulating dendritic cells (DC) by therapy with CDX-301 (fms-related tyrosine
      kinase 3 ligand [Flt3L]) (recombinant flt3 ligand).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess the effect of the vaccine regimen on immune responses to other ongoing and
      nascent antitumor response antigens associated with melanoma (e.g., preferentially expressed
      antigen in melanoma [PRAME], melanoma antigen family A, 3 [MAGE-A3], tumor protein p53
      [p53], and premelanosome protein [gp100]) as well as memory viral responses (influenza A)
      and chronic viral responses (cytomegalovirus [CMV], Epstein-Barr virus [EBV]).

      II. To assess the effect of the vaccine regimen on the frequency and phenotypic character of
      peripheral blood mononuclear cell (PBMC) subsets including DCs, monocyte populations, T
      cells, and natural killer (NK) cells.

      III. To assess the safety, tolerability, and clinical efficacy of the vaccine regimens.

      OUTLINE: Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 treatment arms.

      ARM I: Patients receive recombinant flt3 ligand subcutaneously (SC) on days -7 to -1, 1-3,
      and 22-28 of course 1 and on days 1-3 of course 2 only; DEC-205/NY-ESO-1 fusion protein
      CDX-1401 SC or intradermally (ID) on day 1; and poly-ICLC SC on day 1.

      ARM II: Patients receive DEC-205/NY-ESO-1 fusion protein CDX-1401and poly-ICLC as in Arm I.

      In both arms, treatment repeats every 28 days for 4 courses in the absence of disease
      progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 4 and 12 weeks and then
      annually thereafter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune T-cell response to NY-ESO-1</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 weeks after final vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Response rates will be analyzed by tabulating the frequency of positive response for each assay by antigen and treatment arm at each time point for which an assessment is performed. Response rates will be presented with their corresponding 95% confidence interval estimates calculated using the score test method. Fisher's exact tests will be used to compare the response rates of the 2 treatments, with a significant difference declared if the 1-sided P value is =&lt; 0.10.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune responses to other ongoing and nascent antitumor response antigens as well as memory and chronic viral responses</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 weeks after final vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency and phenotypic character of PBMC subsets including DCs, monocyte populations, T cells, and NK cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 weeks after final vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>T cell infiltrates and NY-ESO-1 expression in pre-treatment tissue using immunohistochemistry</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>CDX-301 serum level pharmacokinetic assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (day -7) and day 22 of course 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Ciliary Body and Choroid Melanoma, Medium/Large Size</condition>
  <condition>Ciliary Body and Choroid Melanoma, Small Size</condition>
  <condition>Extraocular Extension Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Iris Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Carcinoma of Unknown Primary</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Intraocular Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Mucosal Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIB Intraocular Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIB Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIC Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIA Intraocular Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIA Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Intraocular Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Intraocular Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Intraocular Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (CDX-301, CDX-1401, and poly-ICLC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive recombinant flt3 ligand SC on days -7 to -1, 1-3, and 22-28 of course 1 and on days 1-3 of course 2 only; DEC-205/NY-ESO-1 fusion protein CDX-1401 SC or ID on day 1; and poly-ICLC SC on day 1. Treatment repeats every 28 days for 4 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (CDX-1401 and poly-ICLC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive DEC-205/NY-ESO-1 fusion protein CDX-1401and poly-ICLC as in Arm I. Treatment repeats every 28 days for 4 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>recombinant flt3 ligand</intervention_name>
    <description>Given SC</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (CDX-301, CDX-1401, and poly-ICLC)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CDX-301</other_name>
    <other_name>flt3 ligand</other_name>
    <other_name>Mobista</other_name>
    <other_name>rFlt3L</other_name>
    <other_name>rhuFlt3L</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DEC-205/NY-ESO-1 fusion protein CDX-1401</intervention_name>
    <description>Given SC or ID</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (CDX-301, CDX-1401, and poly-ICLC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (CDX-1401 and poly-ICLC)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CDX-1401</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>neoantigen-based melanoma-poly-ICLC vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given SC</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (CDX-301, CDX-1401, and poly-ICLC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (CDX-1401 and poly-ICLC)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NeoVax melanoma vaccine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (CDX-301, CDX-1401, and poly-ICLC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (CDX-1401 and poly-ICLC)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (CDX-301, CDX-1401, and poly-ICLC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (CDX-1401 and poly-ICLC)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pharmacological studies</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with fully resected stage IIb through IV melanoma, with melanoma validated
             by histology or cytology, who have NOT received prior therapy

               -  Patients may have had primary cutaneous, mucosal, or ocular melanoma or
                  metastasis from an unknown primary site.

               -  Tissue should be submitted for evaluation of NY-ESO-1 expression and T-cell
                  infiltrates; however, availability of tissue and/or positivity for NY-ESO-1 is
                  not mandatory

          -  Prior therapy requirements:

               -  Prior radiation, chemotherapy or biologics NOT allowed

          -  Not currently receiving any anticancer therapy

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance score of 0-1

          -  Life expectancy of at least 6 months

          -  Leukocytes &gt;= 3,000/mcL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1,000/mcL

          -  Platelets &gt;= 75,000/mcL

          -  Hemoglobin &gt; 9 g/dL

          -  Total bilirubin &lt; 1.5 x institutional upper limit of normal (bilirubin &lt; 3 x
             institutional upper limit of normal for Gilbert's syndrome)

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase
             [SGOT])/alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT])
             =&lt; 2.5 x institutional upper limit of normal

          -  Creatinine &lt; 1.5 x institutional upper limit of normal OR creatinine clearance &gt;= 60
             mL/min/1.73 m2 for patients with creatinine levels above institutional normal

          -  The first three patients enrolled in the Flt3L arm of the study cannot be human
             immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-positive; after that, HIV-positive patients with
             adequate immune function as evidenced by stable cluster of differentiation (CD)4
             counts &gt;= 350/mm3 are allowed to participate if the following criteria are met:

               -  Maintained on stable antiretroviral therapy with no significant drug
                  interactions, and

               -  No recent history of acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS) indicator
                  conditions (&gt; 2 years from enrolling in trial), and

               -  Physician providing patient's care for HIV must also approve of patient entering
                  the study

          -  Both men and women of all races and ethnic groups are eligible for this trial

          -  Females of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test within 7 days
             before the initiation of protocol therapy

               -  Women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate
                  contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control or abstinence) before
                  study entry and for the duration of study participation; should a woman become
                  pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while she or her partner is participating in
                  this study, she should inform her treating physician immediately; men treated or
                  enrolled on this protocol must also agree to use adequate contraception before
                  the study, for the duration of study participation, and 4 months after
                  completion of CDX-1401 or CDX-301 administration

               -  NOTE: Subjects are considered not of child bearing potential if they are
                  surgically sterile, they have undergone a hysterectomy, bilateral tubal
                  ligation, or bilateral oophorectomy, or they are postmenopausal; menopause is
                  the age associated with complete cessation of menstrual cycles, menses, and
                  implies the loss of reproductive potential; by a practical definition, it
                  assumes menopause after 1 year without menses with an appropriate clinical
                  profile at the appropriate age

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have had cytotoxic chemotherapy, radiotherapy, interferon (IFN), or
             ipilimumab before entering the study

          -  Immunosuppressive therapy within 30 days prior to initiation of protocol therapy

          -  Steroid therapy, or steroid therapy with more than 7 consecutive days of steroids
             within the prior 4 weeks

               -  The use of prednisone or equivalent &lt; 0.125 mg/kg/day (absolute maximum of 10
                  mg/day) as replacement therapy is permitted

               -  Inhaled or topical corticosteroids are permitted

          -  Patients who are receiving any other investigational agents

          -  Current or history of systemic autoimmune disease requiring systemic therapy

               -  NOTE: The following will not be exclusionary:

                    -  The presence of laboratory evidence of autoimmune disease (e.g., positive
                       ANA titer) without associated symptoms

                    -  Clinical evidence of vitiligo

                    -  Other forms of depigmenting illness

          -  Cardiovascular disease that meets one of the following: congestive heart failure (New
             York Heart Association class III or IV), active angina pectoris, or recent myocardial
             infarction (within the last 6 months)

          -  Cirrhosis or chronic hepatitis C virus positivity or chronic hepatitis B infection

               -  NOTE: A positive hepatitis B serology indicative of previous immunization (i.e.,
                  hepatitis B surface antibody [HBsAb]-positive and hepatitis B core antibody
                  [HBcAb]-negative), or a fully resolved acute hepatitis B virus infection is not
                  an exclusion criterion

          -  Known history of immunodeficiency disorder other than HIV-positive status

          -  Extensive active brain disease including symptomatic brain metastases or presence of
             leptomeningeal disease

               -  NOTE: Patients with brain metastasis, after definitive therapy with surgery or
                  stereotactic radiation and stable off steroids for &gt;= 4 weeks, are eligible

          -  Other invasive cancers that are clinically active

          -  Pregnancy or nursing or unwilling to take adequate birth control during therapy

               -  NOTE: Breastfeeding should be discontinued

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to CDX-1401 or CDX-301 or poly-ICLC

          -  Prior organ allograft or allogeneic transplantation, if the transplanted tissue is
             still in place

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements

          -  Medical or psychiatric illness that would, in the opinion of the investigator,
             preclude participation in the study or the ability of patients to provide informed
             consent for themselves

          -  History of pulmonary disease such as emphysema or chronic obstructive pulmonary
             disease (COPD) (forced expiratory volume in one second [FEV1] &lt; 60% of predicted for
             height and age); pulmonary function tests (PFTs) are required in patients with
             prolonged smoking history or symptoms of respiratory dysfunction

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study; breastfeeding should be discontinued if
             the mother is treated with CDX-1401 or CDX-301 and poly-ICLC

          -  Patients should not receive additional investigational agents or anti-cancer
             therapies, unless progression of disease warrants discontinuation of study treatment
             and commencement of alternate therapies

               -  NOTE: Efforts should be made to maintain stable doses of concomitant medications
                  during the course of treatment with CDX-301; initiation of any new medication
                  (excluding oral contraceptives) during the course of the study is discouraged
                  and should only be done for a medically indicated adverse event or new condition

          -  Vaccinations other than those given as part of this research study are prohibited
             throughout the duration of study participation

               -  NOTE: Influenza vaccination is permitted during the flu season; the preferred
                  time is 7 to 14 days after CDX-1401 administration

          -  Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents and concomitant systemic corticosteroids are
             to be avoided; if used, doses of steroids should be the minimum necessary for
             appropriate clinical management; the use of topical steroids should be reserved for
             severe administration site reactions only; acetaminophen and/antihistamines may be
             used as prophylactic therapy if needed for patients who develop clinically
             significant local or systemic reactions following study drug administration
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nina Bhardwaj</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cancer Immunotherapy Trials Network</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dartmouth Hitchcock Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lebanon</city>
        <state>New Hampshire</state>
        <zip>03756</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marc S. Ernstoff</last_name>
      <phone>603-650-5534</phone>
      <email>marc.s.ernstoff@hitchcock.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marc S. Ernstoff</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jedd D. Wolchok</last_name>
      <phone>646-888-2395</phone>
      <email>wolchokj@mskcc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jedd D. Wolchok</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Sinai Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nina Bhardwaj</last_name>
      <phone>212-824-8427</phone>
      <email>Nina.Bhardwaj@mssm.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nina Bhardwaj</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 30, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uveal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Unknown Primary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Poly ICLC</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Flt3 ligand protein</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
