<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="8196">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01850004</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CA180-406</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012‐001421‐27</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01850004</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Open-Label Study Evaluating Dasatinib Therapy Discontinuation in Patients With Chronic Phase Chronic Myeloid Leukemia With Stable Complete Molecular Response</brief_title>
  <acronym>DASFREE</acronym>
  <official_title>Open-Label Single Arm Phase 2 Study Evaluating Dasatinib Therapy Discontinuation In Patients With Chronic Phase Chronic Myeloid Leukemia (CP-CML) With Stable Complete Molecular Response (CMR) DASFREE</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bristol-Myers Squibb</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bristol-Myers Squibb</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>European Union: European Medicines Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study purpose is to test the hypothesis that Chronic Phase Chronic Myeloid Leukemia
      (CP-CML) patients with stable Complete Molecular Response (CMR)who discontinue Dasatinib
      treatment are able to maintain a sustained remission in the long-term, with undetectable or
      minimally detectable BCR-ABL residual disease
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary Purpose: Protocol designed to evaluate remission of disease after treatment
      discontinuation.  Treatment re-started if relapse occurs
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MMR rate at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>At 12 months after Dasatinib discontinuation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Major Molecular Response (MMR) rate at 12 months is the proportion of subjects who maintain MMR at 12 months after Dasatinib discontinuation without re-starting Dasatinib treatment in the enrolled subjects in the study</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Event-free survival (EFS) after Dasatinib discontinuation</measure>
    <time_frame>At 12 months after Dasatinib discontinuation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>EFS is defined as survival with no molecular relapse, including no loss of MMR</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relapse-free survival (RFS) after Dasatinib discontinuation</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6, 18, 24 months and every 6 months thereafter up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Relapse is defined as any of the following events while a subject is on study: the loss of MMR, Complete Cytogenetic Response (CCyR), Complete Hematologic Response (CHR) or progression to advanced/blastic phase. RFS is defined as the time from Dasatinib treatment discontinuation to the date of relapse</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of BCR-ABL kinetics for subjects who experience loss of Complete Molecular Response (CMR) but not MMR</measure>
    <time_frame>Monthly in the first year and every 3 months thereafter up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of BCR-ABL kinetics in subjects in CMR or less with measurable levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Monthly in the first year and every 3 months thereafter up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of transformation to AP/BC</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years or death date</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Accelerated Phase (AP) is defined as Blasts in Peripheral Blood (PB) or Bone Marrow (BM) 15-29%; Blast+promyelocytes ≥30% with blasts &lt; 30% or Additional Chromosomal Abnormalities (ACA) in Ph+ cells (clonal progression), or basophils in blood ≥ 20% or platelets &lt;100 x 10(9)/L unrelated to therapy
Blastic Phase or Crisis (BP/BC) is defined as Blasts in PB or BM ≥30%, or extramedullary blast cell involvement (with the exception of spleen and liver)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years or death date</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Progression-free survival (PFS) is defined as overall survival plus the additional events progression to accelerated phase or blast crisis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of transformation to OS</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years or death date</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall survival (OS) is defined as the time between first dose date and death date</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">74</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Phase Chronic Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dasatinib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dasatinib 20, 50, 80, 100 and 140 mg tablets by mouth, once daily, up to 60 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dasatinib</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Dasatinib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sprycel</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        For more information regarding BMS clinical trial participation, please visit
        www.BMSStudyConnect.com

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Signed Written Informed Consent

             a. Patients must be informed of the investigational nature of this study and of
             alternative standard therapeutic options and must provide written informed consent

          -  Target Population

               1. Men and women diagnosed with CP-CML, on treatment with Dasatinib for a minimum
                  of 2 years at the time of enrollment and in Dasatinib -induced complete
                  molecular remission (defined as ≤ 0.0032% or ≥ 4.5 log reduction of BCR-ABL
                  transcript as determined by local standards) ongoing for at least 1 year prior
                  to study entry

                    -  Patients are eligible for the screening assessment from the central lab if
                       they have been in stable Dasatinib induced CMR for a minimum of nine
                       months, documented by at least three assessments, conducted 2.5 - 6.5
                       months apart, at a local lab. The first screening assessment conducted at
                       the central lab will be repeated after three months, if the first
                       assessment confirms CMR (MR 4.5). Patients are eligible for enrollment if
                       both assessments from the central lab confirm ≤ 0.0032% International Scale
                       (IS) or 4.5 log reduction of BCR-ABL transcript as determined by local
                       standards (MR4.5)

               2. Patients with CP CML treated with Dasatinib as first line treatment or patients
                  with CP CML receiving Dasatinib in second-line treatment after a Tyrosine-kinase
                  inhibitor (TKI)-based therapy

               3. Eastern Co-Operative Group (ECOG) Performance Status (PS) of 0-1

               4. Life expectancy of &gt; 1 year

               5. Adequate renal function defined as serum creatinine ≤ 3.0 times the
                  institutional ULN

               6. Adequate hepatic function defined as: total bilirubin ≤ 2.0 times the
                  institutional ULN; alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase
                  (AST) ≤ 2.5 times the institutional upper limit of normal (ULN)

               7. Serum Na, K, Mg, and total serum Ca or ionized Ca levels must be greater than or
                  equal to the institutional lower limit of normal. Patients with low K, Mg
                  levels, total serum Ca and/or ionized Ca must be replete to allow for protocol
                  entry

               8. Subject Re-enrollment: This study does not permit the re-enrollment of a subject
                  that has discontinued the study as a pre-treatment failure

          -  Age and Reproductive Status

               1. Men and women, ages ≥18

               2. Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) must have a negative serum or urine
                  pregnancy test [minimum sensitivity 25 IU/L or equivalent units of Human
                  Chorionic Gonadotropin (HCG)] within 24 hours prior to the restart of study drug

               3. Women must not be breastfeeding

               4. WOCBP must agree to follow instructions for method(s) of contraception at the
                  restart of treatment with study drug (Dasatinib) and for the duration treatment
                  plus 30 days (duration of ovulatory cycle) for a total of 30 days post-treatment
                  completion

               5. Men who are sexually active with WOCBP must agree to follow instructions for
                  method(s) of contraception for 90 days after study entry (withdrawal of
                  Dasatinib), at restart of study drug (Dasatinib) and for the duration of
                  treatment with study drug (Dasatinib) plus 90 days (duration of sperm turnover)
                  for a total of 90 days post-treatment completion

        Investigators shall counsel WOCBP and male subjects who are sexually active with WOCBP on
        the importance of pregnancy prevention and the implications of an unexpected pregnancy.
        Investigators shall advise WOCBP and male subjects who are sexually active with WOCBP on
        the use of highly effective methods of contraception. Highly effective methods of
        contraception have a failure rate of &lt; 1% per year when used consistently and correctly

        At a minimum, subjects must agree to the use of two methods of contraception, with one
        method being highly effective and the other method being either highly effective or less
        effective as listed below:

        Highly effective methods of contraception:

          -  Male condoms with spermicide

          -  Hormonal methods of contraception including combined oral contraceptive pills,
             vaginal ring, injectables, implants, and intrauterine devices (IUDs) such as Mirena®
             by WOCBP subject or male subject's WOCBP partner.

          -  Nonhormonal IUDs, such as ParaGard®

          -  Tubal ligation

          -  Vasectomy

          -  Complete Abstinence*

        (*Complete abstinence is defined as complete avoidance of heterosexual intercourse and is
        an acceptable form of contraception for all study drugs. Subjects who choose complete
        abstinence are not required to use a second method of contraception, but female subjects
        must continue to have pregnancy tests. Acceptable alternate methods of highly effective
        contraception must be used in the event that the subject chooses to forego complete
        abstinence)

        Less effective methods of contraception:

          -  Diaphragm with spermicide

          -  Cervical cap with spermicide

          -  Vaginal sponge

          -  Male Condom without spermicide*

          -  Progestin only pills by WOCBP subject or male subject's WOCBP partner

          -  Female Condom*

        (*A male and female condom must not be used together)

        f. Azoospermic males and WOCBP who are continuously not heterosexually active are exempt
        from contraceptive requirements. However WOCBP must still undergo pregnancy testing as
        described in these sections

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Target Disease Exceptions

               1. Subjects with more than one CML treatment before Dasatinib

               2. Patients who have not achieved a 1-log reduction in BCR-ABL transcript levels
                  compared with baseline as determined by local standards or &gt; 10% IS
                  [International Standard]) documented at 3.0-6.5 months since the initial start
                  of Dasatinib therapy (first or second line)

               3. Patients who have previously undergone hematopoietic stem cell transplantation
                  (SCT) or who are scheduled for SCT

               4. Any prior treatment with interferon

               5. Previous diagnosis of CML accelerated phase or blast crisis

          -  Medical History and Concurrent Diseases

               1. Prior or concurrent malignancy, except the following:

                    -  Curatively treated basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer

                    -  Cervical carcinoma in situ

                    -  Adequately treated Stage I or II cancer from which the subject is currently
                       in complete remission

                    -  Any other cancer from which the subject has been disease free for 3 years

               2. A serious uncontrolled medical disorder or active infection that would impair
                  the ability of the subject to receive protocol therapy

               3. Uncontrolled or significant cardiovascular disease, including any of the
                  following:

                    -  Congestive cardiac failure (NYHA &gt; 2) within 3 months

                    -  Diagnosed or suspected congenital long QT syndrome

                    -  Any history of significant ventricular arrhythmias for example ventricular
                       tachycardia (BT), ventricular fibrillation (VF), and Torsade de Points
                       (TdP)

                    -  Prolonged QT Interval Corrected (QTc) interval on pre-entry
                       electrocardiogram (&gt; 450 msec)

                    -  Any history of second- or third-degree heart block (may be eligible if the
                       subject currently has a pacemaker)

                    -  Unstable angina within 3 months that belongs to the spectrum of clinical
                       presentation of Acute Coronary Syndrome (ACS)

                    -  Prior myocardial infarction within 6 months

                    -  Uncontrolled hypertension: inability to maintain blood pressure below the
                       upper limit of 140/90 mmHg

               4. Pulmonary arterial hypertension

               5. Subjects with pericardial effusion of any grade at study entry are excluded.
                  Subjects with small, clinically insignificant pleural effusion at the time of
                  study entry are allowed

               6. History of significant bleeding disorder unrelated to CML, including

                    -  Diagnosed congenital bleeding disorders (e.g., von Willebrand's disease)

                    -  Diagnosed acquired bleeding disorder within one year (e.g., acquired
                       anti-factor VIII antibodies)

          -  Physical and Laboratory Test Findings

             a. Patients with a high Sokol or Hasford risk score at initial CML diagnosis

          -  Allergies and Adverse Drug Reaction

             a. Subjects with known hypersensitivity to excipients of Dasatinib tablets (Tablet
             core:lactose monohydrate, microcrystalline cellulose, croscarmellose sodium;
             hydroxypropyl cellulose, magnesium stearate; Film-coating: hypromellose titanium
             dioxide macrogol 400)

          -  Sex and Reproductive Status

               1. Patients who are pregnant or breastfeeding or likely to become pregnant

               2. Men whose partner is unwilling or unable to avoid pregnancy

          -  Other Exclusion Criteria

               1. Patients with a history of non-compliance to CML treatment and monitoring
                  requirements

               2. Prisoners or subjects who are involuntarily incarcerated

               3. Subjects who are compulsorily detained for treatment of either a psychiatric or
                  physical (eg, infectious disease) illness
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bristol-Myers Squibb</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Bristol-Myers Squibb</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Recruiting sites have contact information. Please contact the sites directly. If there is no contact information, please email:</last_name>
    <email>Clinical.Trials@bms.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>First line of the email MUST contain NCT# and Site #.</last_name>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City Of Hope Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Duarte</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Snyder, Site 0006</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Local Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site 0001</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern Medical Faculty Foundation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jessica Altman, Site 0013</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hackensack University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hackensack</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stefan Faderl, Site 0024</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Local Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75246</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site 0011</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University Of Texas Md Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jorge E Cortes, Site 0023</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Local Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 2M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site 0005</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Local Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>Helsinki</city>
        <zip>00290</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site 0004</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Local Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris Cedex 10</city>
        <zip>75475</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site 0012</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Local Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pessac</city>
        <zip>33604</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site 0003</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Local Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vandoeuvre les Nancy</city>
        <zip>54511</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site 0002</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Local Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aachen</city>
        <zip>52074</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site 0026</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Local Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>13353</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site 0020</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Local Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mannheim</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site 0021</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Local Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rostock</city>
        <zip>18055</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site 0019</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Local Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ulm</city>
        <zip>89081</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site 0022</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Local Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orbassano</city>
        <state>Torino</state>
        <zip>10043</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site 0015</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Local Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>Catania</city>
        <zip>95124</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site 0025</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Local Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>Firenze</city>
        <zip>50134</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site 0017</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Local Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <zip>00161</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site 0016</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Local Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <zip>00144</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site 0018</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Local Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>Las Palmas de Gran Canaria</city>
        <zip>35010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site 0009</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Local Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28034</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site 0010</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Local Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>Malaga</city>
        <zip>29010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site 0008</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Local Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oviedo</city>
        <zip>33006</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site 0014</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>Finland</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://ctr.bms.com/ctd/start.do</url>
    <description>BMS Clinical Trial Information</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.bms.com/studyconnect/Pages/home.aspx</url>
    <description>BMS clinical trial educational resource</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.bms.com/clinical_trials/Pages/Investigator_Inquiry_form.aspx</url>
    <description>Investigator Inquiry form</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.fda.gov/MEDWATCH/safety.htm</url>
    <description>FDA Safety Alerts and Recalls</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 27, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 8, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelogenous, Chronic, BCR-ABL Positive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Chronic-Phase</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dasatinib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
