<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="63922">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02094937</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201135</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02094937</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Compare the Efficacy and Safety of Fluticasone Furoate (FF) 100 mcg Once Daily With Fluticasone Propionate (FP) 250 mcg Twice Daily (BD) and FP 100 mcg BD in Well-controlled Asthmatic Japanese Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>201135 : A Randomised, Double-blind, Multicenter, Parallel-group Study to Compare the Efficacy and Safety of Fluticasone Furoate (FF) 100 mcg Once Daily With Fluticasone Propionate (FP) 250 mcg Twice Daily (BD) and FP 100 mcg BD in Well-controlled Asthmatic Subjects Stepped Down From a Maintenance Therapy With RELVAR® Inhaler (FF/VI) 100/25 mcg Once-daily in Japanese Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Japan: Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare (MHLW) and Pharmaceuticals and Medical Devices Agency (PMDA)</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary aim of this study is to clarify the position of FF and FF/Vilanterol (VI) 100/25
      micrograms (mcg) compared with existing therapies by assessing FF dosage equivalent to low
      to middle-dose inhaled corticosteroids (ICS). The study is divided into Run-in period,
      Period 1 (open-label treatment), Period 2 (double blind treatment) and Follow-up. Subjects
      with well controlled asthma after completing a run-in period of 4 weeks will be switched
      from middle-dose ICS/long acting beta 2 agonist (LABA) equivalent dose to once-daily FF/VI
      100/25 mcg for an 8 weeks treatment period (Period 1). After this, subjects will be
      randomized in a 1:1:1 ratio to receive either FP 250 mcg twice daily, FP 100 mcg twice daily
      or FF 100 mcg once daily in a 12 week double blind treatment period (Period 2). There will
      be a 1 week Follow-up Period following completion of the double-blind treatment period, or
      early withdrawal from the study.  Overall , the total duration of subject's participation in
      the study will be for 25 weeks. RELVAR is a registered trademark of the GSK group of
      companies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to withdrawal due to poorly -controlled (requires step-up) asthma during Period-2</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8 to Week 20</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Poorly-controlled asthma is defined as 3 or more of the following: day-time symptom score of &gt;=1 on more than 2 days; 2 or more days of rescue salbutamol use; morning peak expiratory flow (PEF) of &lt;80% of the best effort value on one or more days; a best pre-bronchodilator forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1) of &lt;80% of the predicted normal value at any visit; night-time symptom score of &gt;=1. Also, subject with asthma worsening or exacerbations will be considered as poorly-controlled.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with well-controlled asthma at the end of Period-2</measure>
    <time_frame>20 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Well-controlled asthma is defined as 2 or more of the following when assessed weekly: day-time symptom score of &gt;=1 on no more than 1 day; no more than 1day of rescue salbutamol use; morning PEF of &gt;=80% of the best effort value every day. And no night time awakenings, asthma worsening or exacerbations when assessed daily. Also, a best pre-bronchodilator FEV1 of &gt;=80% of the predicted normal value at any visit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in clinic visit trough FEV1 at the end of Period-2</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 20</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Electronic spirometry will be used to measure trough FEV1. Baseline value will be the pre-dose value at randomization.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in daily morning and evening peak expiratory flow (PEF) averaged during Period-2</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8 to Week 20</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PEF will be measured each morning and evening prior to study medication and any rescue salbutamol inhalation aerosol use using an electronic peak flow meter. Baseline will be the mean of the daily values in one week prior to randomization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in the percentage of symptom-free 24-hour periods during Period-2</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8 to Week 20</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subjects who will be symptom free for 24-hours will be assessed. Baseline will be the mean of the daily values in one week prior to randomization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in the percentage of rescue-free 24-hour periods during Period-2</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8 to Week 20</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The time span during which the subjects will not have to take any rescue medication (medication intended to relieve symptoms immediately) will be considered as a rescue free period. Baseline will be the mean of the daily values in one week prior to randomization.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in Asthma Control Test (ACT) score during Period-2</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8 to Week 20</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>ACT is a 5 question test with various responses rating frequency of asthma events over 4-week period. The questions are designed to be self-completed by the subject. Baseline value will be the pre-dose value at randomization.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with ACT score &gt;=20 at the end of the Period-2</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 20</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The proportion of subjects with ACT score &gt;=20 at the end of the Period-2 will be analyzed using a logistic regression model including terms for baseline, gender, age and treatment group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">360</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1 FF/VI 100/25 mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive Fluticasone Furoate/Vilanterol 100/25 mcg once-daily via a dry powder inhaler for 8 weeks in the open-label treatment period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2 FF 100 mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive Fluticasone Propionate matching placebo twice-daily (morning and evening) and Fluticasone Furoate 100 mcg once daily in the evening, via a dry powder inhaler for 12 weeks in the double-blind treatment period</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3 FP 250 mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive Fluticasone Propionate 250 mcg twice-daily (morning and evening) and Fluticasone Furoate matching placebo once daily in the evening, via a dry powder inhaler for 12 weeks in the double-blind treatment period</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 4 FP 100 mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive Fluticasone Propionate 100 mcg twice-daily (morning and evening) and Fluticasone Furoate matching placebo once daily in the evening, via a dry powder inhaler for 12 weeks in the double-blind treatment period</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluticasone Furoate/Vilanterol</intervention_name>
    <description>FF/VI 100mg/25 mcg is available as a dry white powder to be given once daily in the evening via dry powder inhaler</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1 FF/VI 100/25 mcg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluticasone Furoate 100 mcg</intervention_name>
    <description>FF 100 mcg is available as a dry white powder to be given once daily in the evening via dry powder inhaler</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2 FF 100 mcg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluticasone Propionate 250 mcg</intervention_name>
    <description>FP 250 mcg is available as a dry white powder to be given twice daily (morning and evening) via dry powder inhaler</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3 FP 250 mcg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluticasone Propionate 100 mcg</intervention_name>
    <description>FP 100 mcg is available as a dry white powder to be given twice daily (morning and evening) via dry powder inhaler</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 4 FP 100 mcg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluticasone Furoate Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo of Fluticasone Furoate will be given once daily in the evening via dry powder inhaler</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 4 FP 100 mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3 FP 250 mcg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluticasone Propionate Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo of Fluticasone Propionate will be given twice daily (morning and evening) via dry powder inhaler</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2 FF 100 mcg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Informed consent: Subjects must give their signed and dated written informed consent
             to participate.

          -  Type of Subject: Outpatients 18 years of age or older at Visit 1. Subjects must have
             a diagnosis of asthma as defined by the National Institutes of Health at least 1 year
             prior to Visit 1.

          -  Gender: Male or Eligible Female, defined as non-childbearing potential or
             childbearing potential using an acceptable method of birth control consistently and
             correctly, as defined by the following: Male partner who is sterile prior to the
             female subject's entry into the study and is the sole sexual partner for that female
             subject; Oral contraceptive (either combined estrogen/progestin); Any intrauterine
             device (IUD) with a documented failure rate of less than 1% per year; Double barrier
             method - spermacide plus a mechanical barrier (e.g., spermacide plus a male condom or
             a spermacide and female diaphragm); Females of childbearing potential who are not
             sexually active must commit to complete abstinence from intercourse throughout the
             clinical trial and for a period after the trial to account for elimination of the
             drug (minimum of six days); Female subjects should not be enrolled if they are
             pregnant, lactating or plan to become pregnant during the time of study
             participation. A serum pregnancy test is required for females of childbearing
             potential at the initial screening visit (Visit 1) and Visit 11 or Early Withdrawal.
             In addition a urine pregnancy test will be performed on all females of childbearing
             potential at Visit 2, Visit 5 and Visit 12.

          -  Severity of Disease: A best pre-bronchodilator FEV1 of &gt;=80% of the predicted normal
             value at the screening visit (Visit 1). Predicted values will be based upon National
             Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES) III. As subjects are Asian, the
             Asian adjustment will be used.

          -  Stable Asthma: Subjects must have stable asthma, as judged by the Investigator. This
             includes no change in asthma medication for at least 8 weeks prior to Visit 1 and an
             ACT score of &gt;=20 at Visit 1.

          -  Current Anti-Asthma Therapy: All subjects must be using the middle-dose ICS/LABA
             which is equivalent to twice-daily combination of fluticasone propionate and
             salmeterol 250 mcg for at least 12 weeks prior to the registration visit. In
             addition, the prescription of the middle-dose ICS/LABA shouldn't be changed at least
             8 weeks prior to Visit 1.

          -  Short-Acting Beta2-Agonists (SABA): All subjects must be able to use salbutamol
             aerosol inhaler which will be provided as a rescue medication at Visit 1 during the
             study as needed. Subjects must be able to avoid using salbutamol for at least 6 hours
             prior to study visits.

          -  12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG): Evidence of significant normality in the 12-lead ECG
             performed at Visit 1, as judged by the investigator Selected specific ECG findings
             that are not considered to be significant and will not exclude the subject from study
             participation include, but are not limited to, the following: T interval corrected
             for heart rate (QTc) &lt;450 milliseconds (msec) or QTc &lt;480 msec for patients with
             bundle branch block. The QTc is the QT interval corrected for heart rate according to
             Fridericia's formula (QTcF), machine overread. The QTc should be based on single or
             averaged QTc values of triplicate electrocardiograms (ECGs) obtained over a brief
             recording period. If there are any clinically significant abnormalities including but
             not limited to a T interval for heart rate (QT) prolonged, confirm with two
             additional ECGs taken.

        Other inclusion criteria at Visit 2 and Visit 5:

          -  Subjects whose asthma meets the criterion of &quot;well-controlled&quot; (as defined in the
             protocol), and in the Investigators judgement it is acceptable for subject to &quot;switch
             (Visit 2)&quot; and &quot;step-down (Visit 5)&quot; in one week prior to Visit 2 or Visit 5.

          -  Compliance rate of the middle-dose ICS/LABA which is equivalent to twice-daily
             combination of fluticasone propionate and salmeterol 250 mcg (Visit1- Visit 2) and
             FF/VI 100/25 mcg (Visit 2 - Visit5) should be achieved &gt;=80%

          -  Compliance with completion of both morning and evening eDairy data fulfils &gt;=5days in
             one week prior to Visit 2 and Visit 5.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of Life-threatening asthma: Defined for this protocol as an asthma episode
             that required intubation and/or was associated with hypercapnia, respiratory arrest
             or hypoxic seizures within the last 10 years.

          -  Respiratory Infection: Culture-documented or suspected bacterial or viral infection
             of the upper or lower respiratory tract, sinus or middle ear that is not resolved
             within 8 weeks of Visit 1 and led to a change in asthma management or, in the opinion
             of the Investigator, is expected to affect the subject's asthma status or the
             subject's ability to participate in the study.

          -  Asthma Exacerbation: Any asthma exacerbation requiring systemic corticosteroids or
             injection within 12 weeks of Visit 1 or that resulted in overnight hospitalization
             requiring additional treatment for asthma within 6 months prior to Visit 1.

          -  Concurrent Respiratory Disease: A subject must not have current evidence of
             pneumonia, pneumothorax, atelectasis, pulmonary fibrotic disease, bronchopulmonary
             dysplasia, chronic bronchitis, emphysema, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, or
             other respiratory abnormalities other than asthma.

          -  Other Concurrent Diseases/Abnormalities: A subject must not have any clinically
             significant, uncontrolled condition or disease state that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, would put the safety of the subject at risk through study participation
             or would confound the interpretation of the efficacy results if the condition/disease
             exacerbated during the study. The list of additional excluded conditions/diseases
             includes, but is not limited to the following: congestive heart failure, known aortic
             aneurysm, clinically significant coronary heart disease, clinically significant
             cardiac arrhythmia, stroke within 3 months of Visit 1, uncontrolled hypertension (two
             or more measurements with systolic BP &gt;160 millimeters of mercury (mmHg), or
             diastolic BP &gt;100mmHg), recent or poorly controlled peptic ulcer, haematologic,
             hepatic, or renal disease, immunologic compromise, current malignancy (history of
             malignancy is acceptable only if subject has been in remission for one year prior to
             Visit 1 (remission = no current evidence of malignancy and no treatment for the
             malignancy in the 12 months prior to Visit 1)), tuberculosis (current or untreated)
             [Subjects with a history of tuberculosis infection who have completed an appropriate
             course of antituberculous treatment may be suitable for study entry provided that
             there is no clinical suspicion of active or recurrent disease], Cushing's disease,
             Addison's disease, uncontrolled diabetes mellitus, uncontrolled thyroid disorder,
             recent history of drug or alcohol abuse

          -  Oropharyngeal Examination: A subject will not be eligible for the run-in if he/she
             has clinical visual evidence of candidiasis at Visit 1.

          -  Investigational Medications: A subject must not have used any investigational drug
             within 30 days prior to Visit 1 or within five half-lives (t1/2) of the prior
             investigational study (whichever is longer of the two).

          -  Allergies: Drug Allergy: Any adverse reaction including immediate or delayed
             hypersensitivity to any beta2-agonist, sympathomimetic drug, or any intranasal,
             inhaled, or systemic corticosteroid therapy.  Known or suspected sensitivity to the
             constituents of the investigational product (i.e., lactose or magnesium stearate);
             Milk Protein Allergy: History of severe milk protein allergy.

          -  Concomitant Medication: Administration of prescription or over the counter medication
             that would significantly affect the course of asthma, or interact with study drug,
             such as: anticonvulsants (barbiturates, hydantoins, carbamazepine); polycyclic
             antidepressants; beta-adrenergic blocking agents; phenothiazines and monoamine
             oxidase (MAO) inhibitors; Immunosuppressive Medications: A subject must not be using
             or require use of immunosuppressive medications during the study.

        Note: Immunotherapy for the treatment of allergies is allowed during the study provided it
        was initiated at least 4 weeks prior to Visit 1 and subjects remain in the maintenance
        phase for the duration of the study; Cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) inhibitors: Subjects who
        have received a potent CYP3A4 inhibitor within 4 weeks of Visit 1 (e.g.,Clarithromycin,
        atazanavir, indinavir, itraconazole, ketoconazole, nefazadone, nelfinavir; ritonavir;
        saquinavir; telithromycin, troleandomycin, voriconazole, mibefradil, cyclosporine, etc).

          -  Compliance: A subject will not be eligible if he/she or his/her parent or legal
             guardian has any infirmity, disability, disease, or geographical location which seems
             likely (in the opinion of the Investigator) to impair compliance with any aspect of
             this study protocol, including visit schedule and completion of eDiaries and a paper
             medical conditions diary.

          -  Tobacco Use: Current smoker or a smoking history of 10 pack years (e.g., 20
             cigarettes/day for 10 years). A subject may not have used inhaled tobacco products
             within the past 3 months (i.e., cigarettes, cigars or pipe tobacco).

          -  Affiliation with Investigator's Site: A subject will not be eligible for this study
             if he/she is an immediate family member of the participating Investigator,
             sub-Investigator, study coordinator, or employee of the participating Investigator.

        Other exclusion criteria at Visit 2 and Visit 5:

          -  Evidence of clinically significant abnormal laboratory tests during Visit 1which are
             still abnormal upon repeat analysis and are not believed to be due to disease(s)
             present. Each Investigator will use his/her own discretion in determining the
             clinical significance of the abnormality.

          -  Changes in asthma medication (excluding salbutamol inhalation aerosol provided at
             Visit 1).

          -  Occurrence of a culture-documented or suspected bacterial or viral infection of the
             upper or lower respiratory tract, sinus or middle ear during the run-in and the
             open-label treatment period that led to a change in asthma management or, in the
             opinion of the Investigator, is expected to affect the subject's asthma status or the
             subject's ability to participate in the study.

          -  Any asthma exacerbation requiring systemic corticosteroids or injection or that
             resulted in overnight hospitalization requiring additional treatment for asthma.
             Clinical visual evidence of oral candidiasis at Visit 2 and Visit 5.

          -  Positive urine pregnancy test for all females of childbearing potential at Visit 2
             and Visit 5

          -  Subjects that the investigator decides that it is impossible for subject to do
             &quot;switch (Visit 2)&quot; and &quot;step-down (Visit 5)&quot;.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
    <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aomori</city>
        <zip>036-8545</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fukuoka</city>
        <zip>811-1394</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fukuoka</city>
        <zip>802-0052</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fukuoka</city>
        <zip>816-0813</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gifu</city>
        <zip>509-6134</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hiroshima</city>
        <zip>732-0052</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kagawa</city>
        <zip>761-8073</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kanagawa</city>
        <zip>252-0143</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kanagawa</city>
        <zip>239-0821</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kochi</city>
        <zip>780-0901</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kyoto</city>
        <zip>612-0026</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oita</city>
        <zip>870-0921</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Osaka</city>
        <zip>560-0005</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tokyo</city>
        <zip>103-0027</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tokyo</city>
        <zip>145-0063</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tokyo</city>
        <zip>191-0031</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 20, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>fluticasone propionate</keyword>
  <keyword>step-down regimen</keyword>
  <keyword>well-controlled subjects</keyword>
  <keyword>adults</keyword>
  <keyword>switching regimen</keyword>
  <keyword>asthma</keyword>
  <keyword>fluticasone furoate</keyword>
  <keyword>fluticasone furoate/Vilanterol</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fluticasone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
