<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="31959">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02138318</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GA12/10210</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02138318</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>High Definition Versus Chromoendoscopy for Dysplasia Detection in Ulcerative Colitis (UC)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Controlled Trial of High Definition White Light Endoscopy Versus Chromoendoscopy for Dysplasia Detection in Ulcerative Colitis Surveillance</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Leeds Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Leeds Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>UK: Health Research Authority</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients with ulcerative colitis (UC) have an increased risk for colorectal cancer (CRC)
      compared to the general population. Regular screening by colonoscopy is an internationally
      recommended cancer prevention strategy. Random sampling of the mucosa throughout the colon
      has been the mainstay of conventional surveillance practice to detect abnormalities, known
      as dysplasia which can progress to CRC. This requires multiple biopsies, to be taken and
      processed, a practice which is is tedious, expensive, time consuming and has a low pickup
      rate. Dysplasia in UC is typically flat and patchy and can be easily overlooked with
      standard conventional white light colonoscopy (WLC).

      Detection can be improved by the application of dyes which highlight more subtle
      abnormalities. This practice, known as chromoendoscopy (CE) is better than WLC at dysplasia
      detection but more time consuming for the patient and cannot guarantee that the whole colon
      is covered. CE has only been compared in clinical trials with standard definition endoscopy
      rather than the recently available high definition endoscopes with better resolution and
      picture. High definition (HD) endoscopy uses a high definition onitor and a high resolution
      CCD (charge coupled device) providing much better images than standard video endoscopy. HD
      colonoscopy promises therefore to provide an alternative to CE in UC surveillance without
      the need for the extra time and experience required for dye spraying for both endoscopists
      and nursing staff.

      The investigators plan to do a randomized trial to assess HD colonoscopy alone compared to
      chromoendoscopy (with HD colonoscopies) for dysplasia detection during surveillance for
      ulcerative colitis. There have been no trials comparing these two modalities and the
      investigators hope to provide evidence that the additional benefit of CE over HD colonoscopy
      would be marginal and therefore CE would be reserved for procedures using standard
      definition scopes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>number of lesions</measure>
    <time_frame>Once annually at routine clinical assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of lesions with at least low grade dysplasia detected by targeted biopsy to be compared between the two groups by chisquared test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">152</enrollment>
  <condition>Ulcerative Colitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>chromoendoscopy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High definition (HD) endoscopy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High definition (HD) endoscopy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>High definition (HD) endoscopy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>chromoendoscopy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>chromoendoscopy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with longstanding (more than 10 years), extensive (extending proximal to the
             splenic flexure) colitis attending for surveillance colonoscopy.

          -  Patients over 18 years of age

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Unwilling or unable to give informed consent

          -  Severe active colitis (as assessed by the endoscopist)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dr Venkat Subramanian</last_name>
    <email>Venkat.Subramanian@leedsth.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Leeds Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leeds</city>
        <state>West Yorkshire</state>
        <zip>LS1 3EX</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dr Venkat Subramanian</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dr Venkat Subramanian</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 1, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Colitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colitis, Ulcerative</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
