<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="144730">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02049385</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>140041</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>14-M-0041</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02049385</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Determine if Enhancing Glutamate Transporter Function Produces Antidepressant Effects in People With Major Depressive Disorder</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pathophysiological Study to Determine if Enhancing Glutamate Transporter Function Produces Antidepressant Effects in Patients With Major Depressive Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Depressed people appear to have problems regulating levels of a brain chemical called
      glutamate    than people who are not depressed. The drug diazoxide may help regulate
      glutamate levels in people with depression. Researchers want to know if it can rapidly
      improve depression symptoms. This would help many people with depression, because most
      medications take a long time to work.

      Objectives:

      - To see if diazoxide can quickly improve depressive symptoms in people with
      treatment-resistant major depressive disorder (MDD).

      Eligibility:

      - Adults 18 to 65 years old with MDD, who are currently depressed without psychotic
      features.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be hospitalized for the entire study, 11   13 weeks. They may be
           allowed short leaves. Participants will be interviewed many times during the study.
           They will also fill out questionnaires.

        -  Phase I will last about 4 weeks.

      &lt; TAB&gt; - Participants will be screened with lab tests, and psychiatric and medical history
      and exams.

      &lt; TAB&gt;  - Participants will slowly go off current medications. They will be drug-free for 2
      weeks.

        -  Phase II will last about 8 to 9 weeks.

        -  Participants will be monitored, answer questions, and give blood samples. They will
           drink a glucose drink, give saliva samples, and have scans of their brains taken.

        -  Participants will take the study drug daily by mouth for one 3-week session.

        -  They will take a placebo daily by mouth for the other 3-week session.

        -  There will be a drug-free period of 14 to 21 days between sessions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective:

      To date, available pharmacological treatments for major depressive disorder (MDD) have
      proven to be only modestly effective during the acute phase. We have been systematically
      testing different glutamatergic modulators in patients with mood disorders in order to
      develop improved therapeutics. A recent report found that the (beta)-lactam antibiotic
      ceftriaxone increased glutamate uptake by increasing GLT1(EAAT2) function, and had
      antidepressant-like effects in animal models. Using the learned helpless model of depression
      we developed outbred lines, defined a new anatomy of helplessness, and determined that
      synaptic loss due to excess extracellular glutamate appears to be involved in the
      pathophysiology of helplessness; these animals show a 40% decrease in EAAT2 astrocytic
      transporter expression. Together, these data suggest that astrocytic glutamate reuptake
      systems may be central in the pathophysiology and treatment of depression, and that agents
      that directly increase astrocytic glutamate uptake may represent a novel class of
      antidepressants.

      With this protocol, we propose to test a specific, new mechanism that uses diazoxide to
      chronically increase the expression of the glutamate transporter EAAT2, resulting in removal
      of glutamate from the synaptic cleft. Diazoxide enhances glutamate uptake in glia by
      activating ATP-sensitive potassium (KATP) channels.  We expect that this effect will reduce
      excessive glutamate transmission and be associated with acute antidepressant effects. The
      model presented here is a clinically testable one. If successful, it may lead to the
      development of a group of novel pharmacological treatments for major depression.

      Study Population:

      24 individuals with treatment-resistant major depressive disorder.

      Design:

      Male and female patients, ages 18 to 65 years, with a diagnosis of MDD, currently in an
      episode of major depression, will be recruited for this study. This study will consist of
      the double-blind crossover administration of either diazoxide (200-400 mg/day given orally)
      or placebo. The study will assess the efficacy of 3 weeks of a glutamate transporter
      enhancer (diazoxide, 200-400 mg/day given orally) compared with placebo in improving overall
      depressive symptomatology in patients with treatment-resistant MDD. Other aims of the study
      include: 1) determining whether changes in brain neurochemicals (glutamate) correlate with
      antidepressant response (decrease in Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) total
      scores) to diazoxide in patients with treatment-resistant MDD, and 2) examine other
      biomarkers of response.

      Outcome Measures:

      Primary: MADRS total score. Secondary outcome measures: Proportion of subjects achieving
      remission (MADRS less than or equal to 10) and response (less than or equal to 50% reduction
      from baseline in MADRS total score); change from baseline in Beck Depression Inventory
      (BDI), Hamilton Anxiety Rating Scale (HAM-A), Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (HDRS),
      Visual Analog Scale (VAS), and the Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS) total
      scores.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double-Blind, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MADRS total score</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects achieving remission (MADRS less than/equal to 10) &amp; amp;  response (MADRS more than/equal to 50%) change from baseline in Beck Depression Inventory, Hamilton Anxiety Rating Scale, &amp; amp;  Hamilton Depression Rating...</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Diazoxide</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               -  18 to 65 years of age.

               -  Women of child bearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test and
                  confirmed (by the investigator) use of 2 effective methods of contraception (see
                  below).

               -  Each subject must be capable of understanding all required tests and
                  examinations and sign an informed consent document.

               -  Subjects must fulfill DSM-IV criteria for MDD, single episode or recurrent
                  without psychotic features, based on clinical assessment and confirmed by a
                  structured diagnostic interview (SCID-P). Subjects must be experiencing a
                  current major depressive episode of at least 4 weeks duration.

               -  Subjects must have an initial score of at least 20 on the MADRS at screening and
                  at baseline of study phase I.

               -  Subjects must have a current or past history of lack of response to two adequate
                  antidepressant trials (may be from the same chemical class) operationally
                  defined using the modified-Antidepressant Treatment History Form (ATHF).

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Current psychotic features or a diagnosis of schizophrenia or any other psychotic
             disorder as defined in the DSM-IV.

          -  Subjects with a history of DSM-IV drug or alcohol dependency or abuse (except for
             caffeine or nicotine dependence) within the preceding 3 months.

          -  Head injury that results in loss of consciousness exceeding 5 minutes (for the
             imaging component of the study).

          -  Subjects with a DSM IV Axis II diagnosis of borderline or antisocial personality
             disorder.

          -  Pregnant or nursing women or women of child bearing potential not using 2 medically
             accepted means of contraception (to include oral, injectible, or implant birth
             control, condom, diaphragm with spermicide, intrauterine devices (IUD), tubal
             ligation, abstinence or partner with vasectomy).

          -  Serious, unstable illnesses including hepatic, renal, gastroenterologic, respiratory,
             cardiovascular (including ischemic heart disease), endocrinologic, neurologic,
             immunologic, or hematologic disease.

          -  Subjects with hyperthyroidism or clinical hypothyroidism.

          -  Subjects with one or more seizures without a clear and resolved etiology.

          -  Clinically significant abnormal laboratory tests (including blood glucose).

          -  Diabetes

          -  Fasting plasma glucose concentration &gt; 120 mg/dl

          -  Upright blood pressure &lt; 60mmHg on three occasions 30 minutes apart (based on
             scheduled research measurements).

          -  Treatment with a reversible MAOI within 4 weeks of study phase II.

          -  Treatment with fluoxetine within 5 weeks of study phase II.

          -  Treatment with any other disallowed concomitant medication 14 days before
             randomization.

          -  Treatment with clozapine or ECT within 1 month of randomization.

          -  Lifetime history of deep brain stimulation.

          -  Subjects who, in the investigator   s judgment, pose a current serious suicidal or
             homicidal risk.

          -  Positive HIV test

          -  Contraindications to MRI   (metal in body, claustrophobia, etc)

        No structured psychotherapy will be permitted during the study.

        Definition of treatment-resistance

        All subjects are required to have previously failed two adequate antidepressant trials
        (may be from the same chemical class). Adequacy of antidepressant trials will be
        determined with the modified ATHF.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carlos A Zarate, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yamila Carmona</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-9348</phone>
    <email>carmonay@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Carlos A Zarate, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-0861</phone>
    <email>zaratec@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2014-M-0041.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aitken RC. Measurement of feelings using visual analogue scales. Proc R Soc Med. 1969 Oct;62(10):989-93. Review. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>4899510</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Akhondzadeh S, Mojtahedzadeh V, Mirsepassi GR, Moin M, Amini-Nooshabadi H, Kamalipour A. Diazoxide in the treatment of schizophrenia: novel application of potassium channel openers in the treatment of schizophrenia. J Clin Pharm Ther. 2002 Dec;27(6):453-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12472985</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Altamura CA, Mauri MC, Ferrara A, Moro AR, D'Andrea G, Zamberlan F. Plasma and platelet excitatory amino acids in psychiatric disorders. Am J Psychiatry. 1993 Nov;150(11):1731-3.</citation>
    <PMID>8214185</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 28, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Glutamate</keyword>
  <keyword>Pathophysiology</keyword>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antidepressive Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diazoxide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
