<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="66989">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01710839</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12246</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01710839</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Targeted Laser With Lucentis 0.5mg Verses L Lucentis 0.5mg Monotherapy for Ischemic Central Vein, Hemi Retinal Vein Occlusion and Branch Retinal Vein Occlusion</brief_title>
  <acronym>WAVE</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase IV Open Label Trial of the Safety, Tolerability and Efficacy of 0.5mg Ranibizumab Intravitreal Injections Combined With Wide Field Angiography Guided Panretinal Photocoagulation vs. 0.5mg Ranibizumab Intravitreal Injection Monotherapy in Subjects With Ischemic Central Retinal Vein Occlusion, BRVO, HRVO Who Incompletely Respond to at Least 2 Consecutive Intravitreal Injections in the Past 4 Months.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Charles C Wykoff, PhD, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genentech</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Greater Houston Retina Research</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To see if Lucentis 0.5mg combined with Targeted Pan Retinal photocoagulation will decrease
      the total number of intravitreal injections in a year for ischemic central retinal vein
      occlusion, compared to standard of care
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The WAVE trial is a phase IV, open label, 12-month trial of intravitreal ranibizumab 0.5 mg
      in patients  with ischemic CRVO who have been previously treated with ranibizumab or any
      other anti-VEGF intravitreal injection therapy, who are incomplete responders to 2 or more
      consecutive intravitreal anti-VEGF injections in the past 4 months.

      Cohort 1 patients previously treated Patients will receive 6 doses of ranibizumab 0.5 mg,
      followed by PRN     intravitreal injection of ranibizumab 0.5 mg based on pre-defined
      retreatment criteria for up to 11 total injections Wide field angiography guided peripheral
      targeted-retinal photocoagulation (TRP), will be divided into 2 sessions if needed, one at
      the 2 weeks post injection visit and another later at M4/V8, if repeat wide field angiogram
      indicates areas not sufficiently treated in the first TRP session

      Cohort 2 patients, previously treated patients will receive 6 doses of ranibizumab 0.5 mg,
      followed by PRN intravitreal injection of ranibizumab 0.5 mg based on pre-defined
      retreatment criteria for up to 11 total injections
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total number of intravitreal injections in a 12 month period</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assess the number of intravitreal injections over 12 months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Acuity</measure>
    <time_frame>12 month period</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluate the mean change from baseline in ETDRS BCVA at 12 months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Retinal Ischemia</measure>
    <time_frame>12 month period</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Quantify change in area of perfused and ischemic retina.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Foveal Avascular Zone</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assess change in foveal avascular zone area and largest diameter, measured during the early phase of the angiogram</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Incidence and severity of adverse events (ocular and non-ocular).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neovascularization of the Iris, Optic Nerve and Elsewhere</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percent of patients that develop neovascularization of the iris, optic nerve and/or elsewhere.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Central Foveal Outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Mean change in Central Foveal Volume on High Resolution OCT.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Aqueous VEG F Levels</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>VEGF, other cytokines and ranibizumab levels in aqueous and serum samples at randomization and at the exit or early termination visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Field</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Goldman Visual Field changes at 6 and 12 months from baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Ischemic Central Retinal Vein Occlusion, Hemi Retinal Vein Occlusion, Branch Retinal Vein Occlusion</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Targeted Pan Retinal laser combined with 0.5mg ranibizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>previously treated with at least 2 consecutive or more intravitreal injections of any anti-VEGF agent with persistent macular edema will receive 6 loading doses of 0.5 mg ranibizumab followed by PRN treatment with ranibizumab 0.5 mg; after receiving the first loading dose of ranibizumab, the subject will have peripheral targeted-retinal photocoagulation (TRP) based on 200° wide field angiography. After the first session of TRP, subjects will have a repeat wide field angiogram at M4/V8 and possibly a second TRP session if peripheral non-perfusion or poor-perfusion persist. The 200°wide field angiography will indicate areas of peripheral ischemia which will be selectively treated, preserving areas of more perfused retina.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ranibizumab 0.5mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>previously treated with at least 2 consecutive or more intravitreal injections of any anti-VEGF agent with persistent macular edema will receive 6 loading doses followed by PRN monthly treatment with ranibizumab 0.5 mg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>0.5mg Ranibizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>intravitreal injections</description>
    <arm_group_label>Targeted Pan Retinal laser combined with 0.5mg ranibizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ranibizumab 0.5mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lucentis</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Targeted Pan Retinal Photocoagulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Targeted Pan Retinal Photocoagulation based on wide field angiography</description>
    <arm_group_label>Targeted Pan Retinal laser combined with 0.5mg ranibizumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PRP</other_name>
    <other_name>Pan Retinal Photocoagulation</other_name>
    <other_name>TRP</other_name>
    <other_name>Pan Laser</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with Ischemic Central Retinal Vein Occlusion with at least 2 consecutive
             monthly intravitreal injections of anti-VEGF medications with presence   of
             persistent edema in the past 4 months

          -  Visual acuity between 20/25 and 20/800, ETDRS visual acuity

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  IOP over 30 mm Hg

          -  Any previous retinal laser photocoagulation to the study eye

          -  Previous intravitreal injection in the study eye of any corticosteroid treatment

          -  Inability to assess iris or angle neovascularization (corneal opacity precluding
             gonioscopy)

          -  Significant cardiovascular disease or cancer that would prevent follow-up visits or
             completion of the 12 month study

          -  Significant diabetic retinopathy in the fellow eye (diabetic macular edema,
             proliferative diabetic retinopathy, or high-risk non-proliferative diabetic
             retinopathy)

          -  Pregnancy (positive pregnancy test)

          -  Concurrent disease in the study eye that could compromise visual acuity or require
             medical or surgical intervention during the study period

          -  Aphakia or absence of the posterior capsule in the study eye

          -  Previous violation of the posterior capsule is also excluded unless it occurred as a
             result of YAG laser posterior capsulotomy in association with prior, posterior
             chamber intraocular lens implantation

          -  History of idiopathic or autoimmune uveitis in either eye

          -  Structural damage to the center of the macula in the study eye prior to CRVO likely
             to preclude improvement in visual acuity following the resolution of macular edema,
             including atrophy of the retinal pigment epithelium, subretinal fibrosis, laser
             scar(s)

          -  Vitreomacular traction or clinically significant epiretinal membrane in the study eye
             evident biomicroscopically or by OCT (vitreomacular attachment OK)

          -  Ocular inflammation (including trace or above) in the study eye Systemic Conditions

          -  Uncontrolled Blood pressure: defined as systolic pressure &gt; 180mmHg and/or diastolic
             pressure of 110 mm Hg (sitting) during the screening period

          -  Uncontrolled diabetes mellitus

          -  Renal failure requiring dialysis or renal transplant

          -  Pregnancy (positive pregnancy test) or lactation

          -  Premenopausal women not using adequate contraception. The following are considered
             effective means of contraception:  surgical sterilization or use of oral
             contraceptives, barrier contraception with either a condom or diaphragm in
             conjunction with spermicidal gel, an IUD, or contraceptive hormone implant or patch.

          -  Any other condition that the investigator believes would pose a significant hazard to
             the subject if the investigational therapy were initiated

          -  Participation in another simultaneous medical investigation or trial

          -  History of other disease, metabolic dysfunction, physical examination finding, or
             other findings giving reasonable suspicion of a disease or condition that
             contraindicates the use an investigational drug, might affect interpretation of the
             results of the study, or render the subject at high risk from treatment complications
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Charles C Wykoff, PhD, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Retina Consultants of Houston</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Charles C Wykoff, PhD, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-524-3434</phone>
    <email>ccwmd@houstonretina.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Karri L Schuetzle</last_name>
    <phone>713-524-3434</phone>
    <email>karri.schuetzle@houstonretina.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Retina Consultants of Houston/The Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karri L Schuetzle</last_name>
      <phone>713-524-3434</phone>
      <email>karri.schuetzle@houstonretina.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Leslie K Kao, BS</last_name>
      <phone>713-524-3434</phone>
      <email>leslie.kao@houstonretina.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David M Brown, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Matthew S Benz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Charles C Wykoff, PhD, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tien P Wong, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rosa Y Kim, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amy C Schefler, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James C Major, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Richard H Fish, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eric Chen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Greater Houston Retina Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>The Woodlands</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77384</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karri Schuetzle</last_name>
      <phone>713-524-3434</phone>
      <email>Karri.Schuetzle@houstonretina.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Melisa Bocanegra</last_name>
      <phone>713-524-3434</phone>
      <email>melisa.bocanegra@houstonretina.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Charles C Wykoff, PhD, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Retina Consultants of Houston</name>
      <address>
        <city>The Woodlands</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77384</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karri L Schuetzle</last_name>
      <phone>713-394-7534</phone>
      <email>karri.schuetzle@houstonretina.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David M Brown, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tien P Wong, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Matthew S Benz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James C Major, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Richard H Fish, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Charles C Wykoff, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eric Chen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rosa Y Kim, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amy C Schefler, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Armaly MF. Ocular pressure and visual fields. A ten-year follow-up study. Arch Ophthalmol. 1969 Jan;81(1):25-40.</citation>
    <PMID>5763217</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boyd SR, Zachary I, Chakravarthy U, Allen GJ, Wisdom GB, Cree IA, Martin JF, Hykin PG. Correlation of increased vascular endothelial growth factor with neovascularization and permeability in ischemic central vein occlusion. Arch Ophthalmol. 2002 Dec;120(12):1644-50.</citation>
    <PMID>12470137</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brown David M, Campochiaro Peter A, Singh Rishi P, Li Zhengrong, Gray Sarah , Saroj Namrata, Rundle Amy Chen, Rubio Roman G, Murahashi Wendy Yee Ranibizumab for Macular Edema following Central Retinal Vein Occlusion, Six month Primary End Point Results of a Phase III study. Ophthalmology 2010;117: 1124-1133</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Campochiaro, Peter A, Brown David M, Awh, Carl C, Young Lee, Gray Sarah , Saroj Namrata, Murahashi Wendy Yee, Rubio Roman G, Sustained Benefits from Ranibizumab for Macular Edema following Central Retinal Vein Occlusion : Twelve Monrth Outcomes of a Phase III Study. Ophthalmology 2011; 118:2041-2049</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>A randomized clinical trial of early panretinal photocoagulation for ischemic central vein occlusion. The Central Vein Occlusion Study Group N report. Ophthalmology. 1995 Oct;102(10):1434-44.</citation>
    <PMID>9097789</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Natural history and clinical management of central retinal vein occlusion. The Central Vein Occlusion Study Group. Arch Ophthalmol. 1997 Apr;115(4):486-91. Erratum in: Arch Ophthalmol 1997 Oct;115(10):1275.</citation>
    <PMID>9109757</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Christen WG, Glynn RJ, Manson JE, Ajani UA, Buring JE. A prospective study of cigarette smoking and risk of age-related macular degeneration in men. JAMA. 1996 Oct 9;276(14):1147-51.</citation>
    <PMID>8827967</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Conn G, Bayne ML, Soderman DD, Kwok PW, Sullivan KA, Palisi TM, Hope DA, Thomas KA. Amino acid and cDNA sequences of a vascular endothelial cell mitogen that is homologous to platelet-derived growth factor. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1990 Apr;87(7):2628-32.</citation>
    <PMID>2320579</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Connolly DT, Heuvelman DM, Nelson R, Olander JV, Eppley BL, Delfino JJ, Siegel NR, Leimgruber RM, Feder J. Tumor vascular permeability factor stimulates endothelial cell growth and angiogenesis. J Clin Invest. 1989 Nov;84(5):1470-8.</citation>
    <PMID>2478587</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Connolly DT, Olander JV, Heuvelman D, Nelson R, Monsell R, Siegel N, Haymore BL, Leimgruber R, Feder J. Human vascular permeability factor. Isolation from U937 cells. J Biol Chem. 1989 Nov 25;264(33):20017-24.</citation>
    <PMID>2584205</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Vries C, Escobedo JA, Ueno H, Houck K, Ferrara N, Williams LT. The fms-like tyrosine kinase, a receptor for vascular endothelial growth factor. Science. 1992 Feb 21;255(5047):989-91.</citation>
    <PMID>1312256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hayreh SS, Klugman MR, Podhajsky P, Kolder HE. Electroretinography in central retinal vein occlusion. Correlation of electroretinographic changes with pupillary abnormalities. Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol. 1989;227(6):549-61.</citation>
    <PMID>2483144</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 17, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Greater Houston Retina Research</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Charles C Wykoff, PhD, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Deputy Director of Research</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CRVO</keyword>
  <keyword>BRVO</keyword>
  <keyword>HRVO</keyword>
  <keyword>Macular edema</keyword>
  <keyword>vein occlusion</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Retinal Vein Occlusion</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
