<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="36639">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01670721</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AFLIBL06266</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-000048-89</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1128-9325</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01670721</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Colorectal Cancer Metastatic</brief_title>
  <acronym>AFEQT</acronym>
  <official_title>A Multicenter, Single Arm, Open Label Clinical Trial Evaluating Safety and Health Related Quality of Life of Aflibercept in Combination With Irinotecan/5FU Chemotherapy (FOLFIRI) in Patients With Metastatic Colorectal Cancer (mCRC) Previously Treated With an Oxaliplatin-Containing Regimen</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sanofi</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Regeneron Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sanofi</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>France: Institutional Ethical Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objective:

      To evaluate the safety of aflibercept in patients with metastatic Colorectal Cancer (mCRC)
      treated with irinotecan/5FU combination (FOLFIRI) after failure of an oxaliplatin-based
      regimen (patients similar to those evaluated in the VELOUR trial) according to side effects
      prevention and management guidelines.

      Secondary Objective:

      To document the Health-Related Quality of Life (HRQL) of aflibercept in this patient
      population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Each patient will be treated until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, death,
      Investigator's decision or patient's refusal for further treatment (whichever come first).
      Patients will be followed-up during treatment and for at least 30 days after its last study
      treatment (either aflibercept or FOLFIRI) administration, up to a maximum of 6 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants reporting Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>up to a maximum of 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Related Quality of Life (HRQL) assessed by using changes from baseline in score derived from the 2 HRQL&quot;questionnaires&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer Metastatic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Aflibercept</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>One (1) hour intravenous infusion on Day 1 followed by FOLFIRI (irinotecan, 5-Fluorouracil and leucovorin) administered as follows:
dI-leucovorin infusion over 2 hour on Day 1
Irinotecan: infusion over 90-minute infusion, on Day 1,  followed by bolus 5-FU and 5-FU continuous infusion over 46 hours infusion OR as individualized by physician's clinical judgment.
Treatment cycle to be administered every 2 weeks. Study treatment (aflibercept and FOLFIRI) has to be discontinued upon documentation of disease progression.
If FOLFIRI is permanently discontinued, then aflibercept should be continued until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity or patient's refusal of further treatment.
If aflibercept is permanently discontinued, then FOLFIRI can be continued until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity or patient's refusal of further treatment.
The end of treatment will be the date of the last treatment administration, either aflibercept or FOLFIRI whichever comes last</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AFLIBERCEPT AVE0005</intervention_name>
    <description>Pharmaceutical form:Concentrate for solution for infusion Route of administration: Intravenous</description>
    <arm_group_label>Aflibercept</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>irinotecan</intervention_name>
    <description>Pharmaceutical form:Concentrate for solution for infusion Route of administration: Intravenous</description>
    <arm_group_label>Aflibercept</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fluorouracil</intervention_name>
    <description>Pharmaceutical form:Concentrate for solution for infusion Route of administration: Intravenous</description>
    <arm_group_label>Aflibercept</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Leucovorin</intervention_name>
    <description>Pharmaceutical form:Concentrate for solution for infusion Route of administration: Intravenous</description>
    <arm_group_label>Aflibercept</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Histologically or cytologically proven adenocarcinoma of the colon or rectum

          -  Metastatic disease

          -  Age ≥18 years

          -  ECOG PS 0-1

          -  One and only one prior chemotherapeutic regimen for metastatic disease. This prior
             chemotherapy must be an oxaliplatin containing regimen. Patients must have progressed
             during or following the last administration of the oxaliplatin based chemotherapy.
             Patients relapsing within 6 months of completion of oxaliplatin adjuvant chemotherapy
             are also eligible.

          -  Patients must be affiliated to a Social Security System.

        Exclusion criteria:

        Related to Methodology

          -  Prior therapy with irinotecan oAbsolute neutrophil counts (ANC) &lt; 1.5 x 109/L
             oPlatelet count &lt; 100 x 109/L oHemoglobin &lt; 9.0 g/dL oTotal bilirubin &gt;1.5 x ULN
             oTransaminases &gt;3 x ULN (unless liver metastasis are present, 5 x ULN in that case)
             oAlkaline phosphatase &gt;3 x ULN (unless liver metastasis are present, 5 x ULN in that
             case)

          -  Less than 4 weeks elapsed from prior radiotherapy or prior chemotherapy or major
             surgery to the time of inclusion or until the surgical wound is fully healed
             whichever came later (48 hours in case of minor surgical procedure or until wound
             full healing observed).

          -  Treatment with any investigational drug within 30 days prior to inclusion.

          -  Adverse events (with exception of alopecia, peripheral sensory neuropathy and those
             listed in specific exclusion criteria) from any prior anti cancer therapy of grade &gt;1
              [NCI CTCAE] v.4.0) at the time of inclusion.

          -  History of brain metastases, uncontrolled spinal cord compression, or carcinomatous
             meningitis or new evidence of brain or leptomeningeal disease.

          -  Other prior malignancy. Basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer, carcinoma in situ of
             the cervix or any other cancer from which the patient has been disease free for &gt; 5
             years are allowed.

          -  Any of the following within 6 months prior to inclusion: myocardial infarction,
             severe/unstable angina pectoris, coronary/peripheral artery bypass graft, NYHA class
             III or IV congestive heart failure, stroke or transient ischemic attack.

          -  Any of the following within 3 months prior to inclusion: Grade 3-4 gastrointestinal
             bleeding/hemorrhage, treatment resistant peptic ulcer disease, erosive oesophagitis
             or gastritis, infectious or inflammatory bowel disease, diverticulitis, pulmonary
             embolism or other uncontrolled thromboembolic event.

          -  Occurrence of deep vein thrombosis within 4 weeks, prior to inclusion.

          -  Known AIDS-related illnesses or known HIV disease requiring antiretroviral treatment.

          -  Any severe acute or chronic medical condition, which could impair the ability of the
             patient to participate to the study or to interfere with interpretation of study
             results.

          -  Pregnant or breast-feeding women. Positive pregnancy test for women of reproductive
             potential.

          -  Patient with reproductive potential (female and male) who do not agree to use a
             method of contraception during the study treatment period and for at least 6 months
             following completion of study treatment. The definition of effective method will be
             left to the investigator's judgment.

        Related to Aflibercept:

          -  Urine protein-creatinine ratio (UPCR) &gt;1 on morning spot urinalysis or proteinuria &gt;
             500 mg/24-h.

          -  Serum creatinine &gt; 1.5 x ULN . If creatinine 1.0-1.5 x ULN, creatinine clearance,
             calculated according to Cockroft-Gault formula, &lt; 60 ml/min will exclude the patient.

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension (blood pressure &gt; 140/90 mmHg or systolic blood pressure
             &gt;160 mmHg when diastolic blood pressure &lt; 90 mmHg, on at least 2 repeated
             determinations on separate days, or upon clinical judgement within 3 months prior to
             study inclusion.

          -  Patients on anticoagulant therapy with unstable dose of warfarin and/or having an
             out-of-therapeutic range INR (&gt;3) within the 4 weeks prior to inclusion.

          -  Evidence of clinically significant bleeding diathesis or underlying coagulopathy
             (e.g. INR&gt;1.5 without vitamine K antagonist therapy), non-healing wound.

        Related to FOLFIRI

          -  Known DHPD deficiency

          -  Predisposing colonic or small bowel disorders in which the symptoms were uncontrolled
             as indicated by baseline of &gt; 3 loose stools daily.

          -  Prior history of chronic enteropathy, inflammatory enteropathy, chronic diarrhea,
             unresolved bowel obstruction/sub-obstruction, more than hemicolectomy, extensive
             small intestine resection with chronic diarrhea.

          -  History of anaphylaxis or known intolerance to atropine sulphate or loperamide or
             appropriate antiemetics to be administered in conjunction with FOLFIRI

          -  Treatment with concomitant anticonvulsivant agents that are CYP3A4 inducers
             (phenytoin, phenobarbital, carbamazepine), unless discontinued &gt;7 days.

          -  Patients with known Gilbert's syndrome.

        The above information is not intended to contain all considerations relevant to a
        patient's potential participation in a clinical trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Clinical Sciences &amp; Operations</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Sanofi</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Trial Transparency Team</last_name>
    <email>Contact-US@sanofi-aventis.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Administrative office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 15, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 13, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fluorouracil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Irinotecan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leucovorin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levoleucovorin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
