<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="164982">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02114697</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00059784</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02114697</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Atherosclerosis in High Risk Population Groups: An Assessment by Magnetic Resonance Imaging</brief_title>
  <official_title>Atherosclerosis in High Risk Population Groups: An Assessment by Magnetic Resonance Imaging</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cardiovascular disease (CVD) and cancer are the leading causes of suffering and death
      amongst the American population. While an ever-increasing number of cancer survivors have a
      favorable outcome due to advances in cancer treatment; cancer survivors remain at high risk
      of developing CVD at an early age. There is scant information available on the pathogenic
      process that contributes to cardiovascular threat amongst cancer survivors and little is
      known about the interventions, which may interrupt or decrease the risk of CVD in this
      population. Importantly, early-subclinical markers may substantially precede clinical
      markers.

      The investigators are a collaborative team of basic and clinical scientists with
      complimentary strengths and would like to propose a research study. The goal of this study
      is correlation between metabolomics (in blood) and atherosclerosis in carotid arteries
      (measured via MRI) in asymptomatic cancer survivors. The overlapping and interacting
      components of the proposed study will create a system to classify CVD risk phenotype in
      terms of metabolic outlines and predictive models that integrate the metabolic patterns,
      pathways, and functional networks. This makes it feasible to discover metabolomic signatures
      of 'high' and 'low' CVD risk in a relatively healthy population with/without subclinical
      vascular disease.

      By establishing a bio-repository, this data can be used for answering additional innovative
      research questions now and in future. We expect use of metabolomics technology to support
      affordable disease surveillance and forecasting models in a manner similar to the one used
      by National Weather Service to predict the timing, occurrence, path and intensity of
      hurricanes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this project is to accurately determine the constituents and
      characteristics of atherosclerotic plaques in carotid arteries by magnetic resonance imaging
      (MRI) techniques in cancer survivors; at different data intervals: before and after
      administration of treatment (medical and life style modification) and then correlate
      contrast agent dynamics with serum markers of inflammation and other tests of cardiac or
      vascular dysfunction, where available.

      The proposed study involves 100 asymptomatic patients who received prior chest or head and
      neck radiation therapy (HNXRT) as part of cancer treatment. MRI data (direct assessment of
      atherosclerosis) would be correlated with indirect measures of atherosclerosis (blood
      surrogate markers &amp; metabolomics).

      The investigators intend to conduct an initial baseline MRI, blood tests (to correlate with
      surrogate markers of inflammation) and other tests whenever available of cardiac or vascular
      dysfunction. This cohort will be followed up with medication and/or life style modification
      regimen for a period of initially18 months and subsequently at 36 months. A repeat of all
      baseline studies (MRI and blood tests) would be performed as part of the 18 and 36-month
      follow-up. The plaque characteristics found at MRI will be correlated with results of blood
      tests (baseline, 18 and 36 months) and changes in one or both will be the expected end point
      of the study.

      Introduction: Radiation therapy (XRT) is critical for the treatment of many benign and
      malignant neoplasms. It is well established that cancer survivors who have undergone XRT
      exhibit a long-term survival rate that significantly lags behind age and gender-matched
      population controls (7-11). Several scientific studies and publications have demonstrated
      that, of all etiologies of non-cancer mortality, cardiovascular disease (CVD) remains the
      most significant cause of morbidity and mortality in cancer survivors (7-11). Until recently
      radiation vasculopathy has attracted little research attention, because patients would often
      succumb to their malignancy before the vascular conditions manifested clinically (8). This
      is no longer the rule as more patients are now &quot;outliving&quot; their malignancies and are
      presenting with the long-term sequelae of cancer treatments (9). Sequelae and manifestations
      of accelerated atherosclerosis have been identified in the vasculature of almost every organ
      system (12-15). Atherosclerotic plaques that are susceptible to rupture, termed &quot;vulnerable&quot;
      or &quot;unstable&quot; consist of a large necrotic core made substantially of lipids and cell debris
      and a thin, collagen-poor fibrous cap (3, 16-18).

      Another characteristic of unstable plaques is that they contain numerous inflammatory cells.
      It has been documented that inflamed plaque and those with a large lipid core and thin
      fibrous cap are more likely to progress and cause clinical events than those without these
      features (19-21). Inflammation plays a major role in the onset, progression and
      destabilization of arterial plaque (22-27). Therefore imaging the vasculature for both its
      inflammatory state and presence of type of disease is very important (28-30). The potential
      of magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) to characterize arterial plaques has been extensively
      studied (1, 31-33). MRI due to its ability of tissue characterization, superior resolution,
      lack of radiation, non invasiveness is an ideal modality for in vivo study of arterial
      plaques.

      Aims: The purpose of this study is to assess carotid artery MRI plaque characteristics in
      100 asymptomatic cancer survivors with history of chest, head and neck radiotherapy (HNXRT).
      Another objective is to analyze plaque changes in the same group after initiation of
      treatment for 18 and 36 months.

      The following specific aims (A), research questions (RQ) and hypotheses (H) will be
      addressed.

      A 1: To characterize the plaque constituents including fibrous cap (FC), lipid core and
      hemorrhage within the carotid plaque by MRI. RQ 1a: What are the predominant plaque
      constituents?. RQ 1b: Is there a predominance of complex and vulnerable plaque features in
      the neck arterial vasculature of cancer survivors?. H 1: We hypothesize that there is a
      predominance of vulnerable plaque in carotid arterial vasculature of HNXRT patients due to
      the phenomenon of radiation vasculopathy.

      A 2: Determine the correlation between plaque inflammation (direct measure by MRI) with
      serum markers of inflammation through blood tests (hsCRP, LpPLA2, IL-6) and metabolomics. RQ
      2: Is there any correlation between the direct and surrogate markers of inflammation?. H 2:
      We hypothesize that there is a predictable correlation between the direct and surrogate
      measures of inflammation.

      A 3: To assess the longitudinal change in the artery plaque characteristics (inflammation
      and morphology) with treatment. RQ 3: Is there a predictable relationship between
      inflammation (pattern of enhancement-/contrast kinetics) and vulnerable features within a
      plaque?. H 3: We hypothesize that changes in plaque characteristics pre and post treatment
      would correlate with contrast agent dynamics over time.

      A 4: To determine the efficacy of comprehensive treatment (life style modification + statin)
      versus (life style modification + placebo). RQ 4: Is one regimen better than the other in
      cancer survivors with subclinical atherosclerosis? H 4: We hypothesize that comprehensive
      treatment (life style modification + statin) would have better inflammation control and
      favorable plaque modification than life style modification alone as measured by parameters
      in (A2 &amp; A3).

      Research Strategy:

      Subjects: The investigators intend to recruit 100 asymptomatic cancer survivors who had
      prior history of chest, head and neck radiotherapy (HNXRT). These patients of The Winship
      Cancer Institute who are being invited to return to The Survivorship Clinic as part of
      longterm routine follow-up. The research will be coordinated through the Emory School of
      Medicine, Department of Radiology in partnership with The Winship Cancer Institute,
      Survivorship Clinic, Department of Cardiology and The Stroke Center. All the aspects of
      clinical and research assessment and follow-up will be provided within The Emory Healthcare
      System.

      Variables and Measures: Blood will be drawn for testing in the MRI Research Laboratory at
      EMORY by a research nurse. The blood specimens will be drawn immediately before each MRI
      examination to measure laboratory testing of serum markers of inflammation (hsCRP, LpPLA2,
      IL-6) and metabolomics. Creatinine will be measured to calculate eGFR. In addition, the
      Framingham Risk Assessment Tool for General Cardiovascular Disease (FRAT) will be employed
      to determine the 10-year risk prediction for general cardiovascular events using the
      assessed values of age; history of diabetes, smoking, and hypertension; systolic blood
      pressure.

      Examination Plan Overview: All study participants will be given IRB approved informed
      consent. Those who decide to take part and give consent for the study would be enrolled in
      the research study. The investigators would be taking snap shots with MRI at three data
      points and monitor treatment effects. A baseline MRI will be performed to assess arterial
      atherosclerotic constituents and blood tests to have a baseline. Once the initial MRI and
      blood tests have been performed, and in the case where subclinical disease is present i.e.
      elevated blood markers or arterial plaque on MRI. HNXRT cancer survivor patients with
      abnormal tests will be started on treatment, which includes life style modification and-/-or
      lipid lowering medication. Patients with positive tests would be divided into two groups;
      one group will receive life style modification + statin therapy and the second group will
      receive life style modification alone. A repeat MRI and blood tests (2nd study) will be
      performed at 18 months after initiation of such treatment to assess changes in plaque
      morphology and enhancement characteristics. A final set of MRI and blood tests will be
      performed at 36 months after initiation of such treatment to assess changes in plaque
      morphology and enhancement characteristics. MRI findings of baseline, 18 months and 36
      months would be correlated with blood markers of inflammation.

      Treatment and Clinical Follow-Up: Patients enrolled in the &quot;Accelerated Atherosclerosis in
      High Risk Population Groups: An Assessment by Magnetic Resonance Imaging&quot; study will be
      evaluated in the cardiology clinic by Khusrow Niazi, MD, FACC, FSCAI who is the Director of
      Peripheral Vascular Intervention at Emory University and treats patients with carotid artery
      disease. All these patients will be randomized based on the last digit of their medical
      record number. If the last digit will be an even number they will then be given a statin,
      which they will take and will also be instructed about regular exercise by Emory HeartWiseSM
      Risk Reduction. Program. Patients will be made aware of the side effects of statins and
      about the procedures to report these side effects. Patients with the last digit being an odd
      number will ONLY be advised about exercise by Emory HeartWiseSM Risk Reduction Program.
      These patients will have regular visits and patients on a statin will be followed up and
      evaluated for any adverse effects of the medication and for compliance. Additionally these
      patients will get routine clinical follow-up in the oncology (The Winship Cancer Institute
      Clinics) and cardiology clinics (Emory Hospital) as part of the ongoing routine clinical
      care.

      After initial/baseline MRI, our recruited research subjects that demonstrate increased blood
      markers and/or atherosclerosis on MRI would be subjected to life style modification ±
      medical (statin) therapy. Department of Cardiology would prescribe and monitor statin
      therapy: Rosuva (20 mg once a day) with target LDL goal &lt; 70; non-HDL goal &lt; 100 and Aspirin
      (81 mg once a day). The rational for using rosuva 20 mg is because this dosage has already
      been successfully used in JUPITER Trial (35). The follow-up by Cardiology department would
      comprise educating the patients on life style modification and also how to monitor and
      report any adverse drug affects which if expected would be further assessed with laboratory
      testing with LFT's and CBC. Any patients who suffer clinical side effects of treatment as
      part of our research would be taken off our study. They would however continue routine
      clinical follow-up in 'The Survivorship and Cardiology clinics'.

      Life style modification will be tailored, implemented and followed up by Emory HeartWiseSM
      Risk Reduction Program. This Program will use several analytical tools including
      questionnaire (BOMC, Rose, FRAT, CHD Knowledge Test). These analytical tools, laboratory as
      well as imaging tests will help EmoryHeartWise Risk Reduction Program devise the best life
      style modification and exercise strategy for our patients.

      Emory HeartWiseSM Risk Reduction Program

      Joint Proposal WCI/Preventive Cardiology- Emory HeartWiseSM Risk Reduction:

      Lifestyle Modifications in our high-risk patients with Subclinical Atherosclerosis 12 week/3
      months; 3 x/week, total 36 visits Recommend 6 Minute Walk Test (MWT) on Telemetry for each
      Patient: functional screen

      Evaluation:

        1. A 6 Minute walk test on telemetry - screening tool for function and
           cardiovascular/hemodynamic response.

        2. PHQ-9 (Patient Health Questionnaire) depression questionnaire

        3. Risk stratification - ACSM (American College of Sports Medicine) guidelines

      Exercise components:

        1. Create exercise prescription based on ACSM guidelines and results of 6 MWT.

        2. Orientation: safety principles of exercise, waist hip circumference; BMI (Body Mass
           Index); risk factor identification.

        3. Brief meeting with Registered Dietitian (RD) for review of food intake/diary.

        4. 1x/month 10 -15 minute meeting with RD for review of food intake and plan.

        5. Minimum of 3x/week exercise program - based on FITT (frequency, intensity, time, and
           type) principles.

        6. Individualized exercise prescription created and progressed by staff; tracked on flow
           sheets; monitor blood pressure; if diabetes - Blood Glucose (BG) pre/post/during if
           necessary.

      The Healthy Exercise for Lymphoma Patients (HELP) trial was a randomized controlled trial
      looking at the benefits of 12 weeks supervised exercise program for cancer survivors
      compared to usual care (36). Improvements in health-related fitness and quality of life were
      maintained at the 6-month clinical follow up. The same model of secondary prevention through
      supervised, graded exercise as well as identifying and intervening with education and active
      participation in risk factor modification is being proposed to help high-risk patients
      identified with subclinical atherosclerosis.

      The premise of inclusion of exercise regimen in our study is that regular, moderate levels
      of exercise have been shown to be beneficial at lowering blood pressure, total cholesterol,
      low-density lipoprotein, triglycerides, increasing high density lipoprotein, metabolic
      syndrome, insulin sensitivity, and all-cause mortality (37). Intensive lifestyle
      modification through education, support, and supervised exercise are the core components
      directed at risk factor reduction (38).

      MRI Examination:

      Pre-MRI screening and informed consent: Upon arrival at the MRI Research Center, a trained
      MRI technologist will screen each study participant for metal objects and implants that may
      be hazardous in the MRI environment. The subject will be given a copy of the informed
      consent form. The PI or the co-investigator will be responsible for ensuring that the
      subject fully understands the procedure, for answering any questions the subject may have
      and for obtaining written informed consent. The technologist will then guide the subject to
      the MRI scanner room.

      Imaging protocol: All scans will be performed on a 3.0T MRI scanning system using 4-channel
      dedicated coil. A fast gradient echo 3-plane localizer will be performed to locate the major
      artery and its bifurcations.  The location and extent of the lesion will be ascertained or
      verified from the 3D-TOF angiographic images. The site of imaging will be selected to
      coincide with the location of a selected known lesion.

      Baseline, Intermediate and Final MRI: Each subject will undergo similar scan protocol at
      baseline, intermediate and final MRI. Anatomical landmarks will be used to match images
      (baseline, intermediate and final) in the same patient from the three time points spread
      over an intervals of 18 months. These landmarks include arterial bifurcations, vertebrae,
      proximity of other vessels and patterns of fat and muscle. Since the slice volume would be
      planned centered at the area of interest for all the studies (initial and repeat); the exact
      Z-location of each slice would be known and reproducible for acquisition and comparative
      measurements.

      Project Timeline: The equipment and resources are currently in place to begin patient
      examinations immediately upon receiving funding. We anticipate the recruitment of all 100
      patients from the existing pool of patients at the Emory Clinics (Survivorship Clinic)
      within the 12 months of funding. The time from baseline MRI and initial follow-up MRI study
      will be 18 months which would give us time to observe therapy related changes in the plaque
      morphology and observe correlation between plaque morphology and inflammatory markers in the
      serum. The last set of follow up MRI and blood tests at 36 months would serve as the end
      point for final analyses of the long term effects of the instituted treatment regimen. Thus,
      if the co-investigators responsible for statistical models receive the complete data 6
      months after the end of the studies, it is expected to take another 6 months to complete the
      entire work. So realistically the project should be completed in 48 months.

      Adverse Event Reporting: We do not expect any serious physical adverse events from this
      research study. Participating in this study involves very few/minimal risks. Study staff
      will work with patients to minimize any stress or discomfort with the study procedures. The
      study involves a blood draw, which may cause slight bruising or pain at the site where the
      blood is drawn. In addition, bleeding, dizziness, fainting or feeling lightheaded, nausea,
      hematoma or infection may occur because of drawing your blood. The blood will be drawn from
      expert/trained staff so this will be less likely to happen.

      We do not expect any serious physical adverse events from MRI examinations. Due to recent
      concerns related to the use of gadolinium-based contrast agents in patients with renal
      dysfunction and risk of nephrogenic systemic fibrosis (NSF), serum creatinine levels will be
      measured from blood drawn before each MRI examination (49). Patients with normal renal
      function values will be administered contrast and this approach virtually eliminates any
      possibility of NSF. Statin treatment might cause some side effects in few individuals which
      would be closely monitored by symptoms and followed by blood tests; if any side effects
      occur, the medication would be immediately stopped; patients would be taken off the study
      protocol and they would continue their routine follow up in The Survivorship and Cardiology
      clinics. Subjects will be provided with telephone numbers of the PI, co-investigators and
      the Emory University IRB. Any adverse events will be appropriately documented and reported
      through the Department of Radiology Safety Committee.

      Data and Safety Monitoring Plan (DSMP): There might be a minimal risk due to breach in
      confidentiality of the patient information, which we plan to overcome by keeping all
      personal facts and data private and confidential, and will use it strictly for research
      purposes. In order to maintain confidentiality, we will use a participant number rather than
      patient names on study records where we can. All patient records will be identified by an
      individual code number and the record of subject identifiers and corresponding reference
      codes will be stored in a locked cabinet in the protected and monitored research office
      building. All the results will be presented and published as group data. Agencies such as
      the Food and Drug Administration and the Emory University Human Investigations Committee
      have the right to review these records. We will keep the records private to the extent
      allowed by law. We will do this even if outside review occurs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression of cardiovascular disease confirmed by MRI of carotid arteries</measure>
    <time_frame>3 MRI examinations: At recruitment, at 18 months and at 36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Plaque features including plaque volume and complexity will act as surrogate measures for progression of cardiovascular disease.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Atherosclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise plus placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Recommended exercise regimen and placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rosuvastatin 20 mg, Aspirin 81 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Rosuvastatin (20 mg once a day) orally, for 3 years Aspirin (81 mg once a day) orally, for 3 years</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rosuvastatin 20 mg, Aspirin 81 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Rosuvastatin 20 mg, Aspirin 81 mg: both drugs to be administered orally, once a day, for the duration of the trial (to be discontinued on account of unacceptable adverse effects)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rosuvastatin 20 mg, Aspirin 81 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Crestor 20mg, Aspirin 81 mg</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 22 and above with prior head and neck or chest irradiation

          -  Six months or more post head and neck irradiation

          -  Documented subclinical cardiovascular disease (inflammatory markers in the serum)

          -  Pre-existing plaques [detected by ultrasound, CT or MRI]

          -  Asymptomatic major arterial stenosis

          -  Not being considered for arterial surgery or endovascular treatment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Recurrence of cancer (with or without treatment)

          -  Planned surgical or endovascular intervention for revascularization of carotid
             arteries at the time of enrollment

          -  Renal failure

          -  eGFR &lt; 45 (calculation based on serum creatinine levels, race, age and gender)

          -  Medically unstable or hematologic, renal, or hepatic dysfunction

          -  Non-atherosclerotic arterial stenosis (dissection)

          -  Presence of stents or external clips that can cause artifacts impairing accurate
             interpretation of MRI data

          -  Contraindications to MRI: cardiac pacemaker, metal implants, metal in eyes, pregnant
             or nursing women, claustrophobia, allergy to MRI contrast

          -  Physical or mental impairment that would limit the patient's ability to comply with
             the medical instructions or study procedures.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>22 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>FAISAL KHOSA, MD, FRCPC, FFRRCSI</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Khusrow Niazi, MD, FACC, FSCAI</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ota H, Yu W, Underhill HR, Oikawa M, Dong L, Zhao X, Polissar NL, Neradilek B, Gao T, Zhang Z, Yan Z, Guo M, Zhang Z, Hatsukami TS, Yuan C. Hemorrhage and large lipid-rich necrotic cores are independently associated with thin or ruptured fibrous caps: an in vivo 3T MRI study. Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol. 2009 Oct;29(10):1696-701. doi: 10.1161/ATVBAHA.109.192179. Epub 2009 Jul 16.</citation>
    <PMID>19608971</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Virmani R, Burke AP, Kolodgie FD, Farb A. Vulnerable plaque: the pathology of unstable coronary lesions. J Interv Cardiol. 2002 Dec;15(6):439-46. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12476646</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yeh JM, Nekhlyudov L, Goldie SJ, Mertens AC, Diller L. A model-based estimate of cumulative excess mortality in survivors of childhood cancer. Ann Intern Med. 2010 Apr 6;152(7):409-17, W131-8. doi: 10.7326/0003-4819-152-7-201004060-00005.</citation>
    <PMID>20368646</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dorresteijn LD, Kappelle AC, Boogerd W, Klokman WJ, Balm AJ, Keus RB, van Leeuwen FE, Bartelink H. Increased risk of ischemic stroke after radiotherapy on the neck in patients younger than 60 years. J Clin Oncol. 2002 Jan 1;20(1):282-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11773180</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jordan LC, Duffner PK. Early-onset stroke and cerebrovascular disease in adult survivors of childhood cancer. Neurology. 2009 Dec 1;73(22):1816-7. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0b013e3181c33b10. Epub 2009 Oct 21.</citation>
    <PMID>19846829</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Diller L, Chow EJ, Gurney JG, Hudson MM, Kadin-Lottick NS, Kawashima TI, Leisenring WM, Meacham LR, Mertens AC, Mulrooney DA, Oeffinger KC, Packer RJ, Robison LL, Sklar CA. Chronic disease in the Childhood Cancer Survivor Study cohort: a review of published findings. J Clin Oncol. 2009 May 10;27(14):2339-55. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2008.21.1953. Epub 2009 Apr 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19364955</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mertens AC, Yasui Y, Neglia JP, Potter JD, Nesbit ME Jr, Ruccione K, Smithson WA, Robison LL. Late mortality experience in five-year survivors of childhood and adolescent cancer: the Childhood Cancer Survivor Study. J Clin Oncol. 2001 Jul 1;19(13):3163-72.</citation>
    <PMID>11432882</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haynes JC, Machtay M, Weber RS, Weinstein GS, Chalian AA, Rosenthal DI. Relative risk of stroke in head and neck carcinoma patients treated with external cervical irradiation. Laryngoscope. 2002 Oct;112(10):1883-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12368635</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bowers DC, Liu Y, Leisenring W, McNeil E, Stovall M, Gurney JG, Robison LL, Packer RJ, Oeffinger KC. Late-occurring stroke among long-term survivors of childhood leukemia and brain tumors: a report from the Childhood Cancer Survivor Study. J Clin Oncol. 2006 Nov 20;24(33):5277-82. Epub 2006 Nov 6.</citation>
    <PMID>17088567</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moser EC, Noordijk EM, van Leeuwen FE, le Cessie S, Baars JW, Thomas J, Carde P, Meerwaldt JH, van Glabbeke M, Kluin-Nelemans HC. Long-term risk of cardiovascular disease after treatment for aggressive non-Hodgkin lymphoma. Blood. 2006 Apr 1;107(7):2912-9. Epub 2005 Dec 8.</citation>
    <PMID>16339404</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steele SR, Martin MJ, Mullenix PS, Crawford JV, Cuadrado DS, Andersen CA. Focused high-risk population screening for carotid arterial stenosis after radiation therapy for head and neck cancer. Am J Surg. 2004 May;187(5):594-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15135672</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Casscells W, Naghavi M, Willerson JT. Vulnerable atherosclerotic plaque: a multifocal disease. Circulation. 2003 Apr 29;107(16):2072-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12719287</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hatsukami TS, Ross R, Polissar NL, Yuan C. Visualization of fibrous cap thickness and rupture in human atherosclerotic carotid plaque in vivo with high-resolution magnetic resonance imaging. Circulation. 2000 Aug 29;102(9):959-64.</citation>
    <PMID>10961958</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>MacNeill BD, Lowe HC, Takano M, Fuster V, Jang IK. Intravascular modalities for detection of vulnerable plaque: current status. Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol. 2003 Aug 1;23(8):1333-42. Epub 2003 Jun 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12805071</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Crisby M, Nordin-Fredriksson G, Shah PK, Yano J, Zhu J, Nilsson J. Pravastatin treatment increases collagen content and decreases lipid content, inflammation, metalloproteinases, and cell death in human carotid plaques: implications for plaque stabilization. Circulation. 2001 Feb 20;103(7):926-33.</citation>
    <PMID>11181465</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Davies MJ. Stability and instability: two faces of coronary atherosclerosis. The Paul Dudley White Lecture 1995. Circulation. 1996 Oct 15;94(8):2013-20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8873680</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kolodgie FD, Virmani R, Burke AP, Farb A, Weber DK, Kutys R, Finn AV, Gold HK. Pathologic assessment of the vulnerable human coronary plaque. Heart. 2004 Dec;90(12):1385-91. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15547008</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hansson GK. Inflammation, atherosclerosis, and coronary artery disease. N Engl J Med. 2005 Apr 21;352(16):1685-95. Review. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>15843671</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Krams R, Segers D, Mousavi Gourabi B, Maat W, Cheng C, van Pelt C, van Damme LC, de Feyter P, van der Steen T, de Korte CL, Serruys PW. Inflammation and atherosclerosis: mechanisms underlying vulnerable plaque. J Interv Cardiol. 2003 Apr;16(2):107-13.</citation>
    <PMID>12768913</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Libby P. Inflammation in atherosclerosis. Nature. 2002 Dec 19-26;420(6917):868-74. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12490960</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hansson GK, Robertson AK, Söderberg-Nauclér C. Inflammation and atherosclerosis. Annu Rev Pathol. 2006;1:297-329. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18039117</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Libby P, Ridker PM, Maseri A. Inflammation and atherosclerosis. Circulation. 2002 Mar 5;105(9):1135-43. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11877368</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stone GW, Maehara A, Lansky AJ, de Bruyne B, Cristea E, Mintz GS, Mehran R, McPherson J, Farhat N, Marso SP, Parise H, Templin B, White R, Zhang Z, Serruys PW; PROSPECT Investigators. A prospective natural-history study of coronary atherosclerosis. N Engl J Med. 2011 Jan 20;364(3):226-35. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1002358. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2011 Nov 24;365(21):2040.</citation>
    <PMID>21247313</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bengel FM. Vascular FDG uptake: further steps toward clinical acceptance. J Nucl Cardiol. 2008 Mar-Apr;15(2):154-6. doi: 10.1016/j.nuclcard.2008.01.010.</citation>
    <PMID>18371583</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Croce K, Libby P. Intertwining of thrombosis and inflammation in atherosclerosis. Curr Opin Hematol. 2007 Jan;14(1):55-61. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17133101</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Silvera SS, Aidi HE, Rudd JH, Mani V, Yang L, Farkouh M, Fuster V, Fayad ZA. Multimodality imaging of atherosclerotic plaque activity and composition using FDG-PET/CT and MRI in carotid and femoral arteries. Atherosclerosis. 2009 Nov;207(1):139-43. Epub 2009 Apr 24.</citation>
    <PMID>19467659</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fayad ZA, Fuster V. Characterization of atherosclerotic plaques by magnetic resonance imaging. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2000 May;902:173-86. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10865837</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mitsumori LM, Hatsukami TS, Ferguson MS, Kerwin WS, Cai J, Yuan C. In vivo accuracy of multisequence MR imaging for identifying unstable fibrous caps in advanced human carotid plaques. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2003 Apr;17(4):410-20.</citation>
    <PMID>12655579</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yuan C, Mitsumori LM, Beach KW, Maravilla KR. Carotid atherosclerotic plaque: noninvasive MR characterization and identification of vulnerable lesions. Radiology. 2001 Nov;221(2):285-99. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11687667</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ridker PM, Danielson E, Fonseca FA, Genest J, Gotto AM Jr, Kastelein JJ, Koenig W, Libby P, Lorenzatti AJ, MacFadyen JG, Nordestgaard BG, Shepherd J, Willerson JT, Glynn RJ; JUPITER Study Group. Rosuvastatin to prevent vascular events in men and women with elevated C-reactive protein. N Engl J Med. 2008 Nov 20;359(21):2195-207. Epub 2008 Nov 9.</citation>
    <PMID>18997196</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Courneya KS, Stevinson C, McNeely ML, Sellar CM, Friedenreich CM, Peddle-McIntyre CJ, Chua N, Reiman T. Effects of supervised exercise on motivational outcomes and longer-term behavior. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2012 Mar;44(3):542-9.</citation>
    <PMID>21814149</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ahmed HM, Blaha MJ, Nasir K, Rivera JJ, Blumenthal RS. Effects of physical activity on cardiovascular disease. Am J Cardiol. 2012 Jan 15;109(2):288-95. doi: 10.1016/j.amjcard.2011.08.042. Epub 2011 Oct 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22011559</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Williams MA, Ades PA, Hamm LF, Keteyian SJ, LaFontaine TP, Roitman JL, Squires RW. Clinical evidence for a health benefit from cardiac rehabilitation: an update. Am Heart J. 2006 Nov;152(5):835-41. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17070142</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pannu N, Tonelli M. Strategies to reduce the risk of contrast nephropathy: an evidence-based approach. Curr Opin Nephrol Hypertens. 2006 May;15(3):285-90. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16609296</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 22, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 10, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Emory University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Faisal Khosa</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cancer survivorship, cardiovascular disease, stroke, TIA</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Aspirin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rosuvastatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
