<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="43571">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01946425</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GRC51</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1120-1262</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01946425</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Immunogenicity Among Healthy Children Receiving Fluzone® Quadrivalent Influenza Virus Vaccine</brief_title>
  <official_title>Safety and Immunogenicity Among Healthy Children Receiving Fluzone® Quadrivalent Influenza Virus Vaccine (2013-2014 Formulation)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sanofi Pasteur, a Sanofi Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sanofi</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to evaluate the safety and immunogenicity of Fluzone® Quadrivalent
      vaccine in participants aged 6 months to &lt; 9 years at enrollment, divided into 2 age strata
      (6 months to &lt; 36 months and 3 years to &lt; 9 years)

      Primary Objective:

        -  To describe the safety of the 2013-2014 formulation of Fluzone Quadrivalent vaccine,
           administered in a 1- or 2-dose schedule, in accordance with Advisory Committee on
           Immunization Practices' (ACIP) recommendations, in children 6 months to &lt; 9 years of
           age.

      Observational Objectives:

        -  To describe the immunogenicity of the 2013-2014 formulation of Fluzone Quadrivalent
           vaccine, administered in a 1- or 2-dose schedule in accordance with ACIP
           recommendations, in children 6 months to &lt; 9 years of age.

        -  To submit sera from subjects to the Center for Biologics Evaluation and Research (CBER)
           for further analysis by the World Health Organization (WHO), the Centers for Disease
           Control and Prevention (CDC), and the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) to support
           formulation recommendations for subsequent influenza vaccines.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Participants will be assigned to the appropriate age group (6 months to &lt; 36 months of age
      or 3 years to &lt; 9 years of age) based on the subject's age at the time of enrollment.

      Solicited adverse event (AE) information will be collected for 7 days after each
      vaccination, unsolicited AE information will be collected from Visit 1 to Visit 2, or to
      Visit 3 for those subjects receiving 2 doses. Serious adverse event information will be
      collected from Visit 1 to Visit 2 or Visit 3, as appropriate.

      Immunogenicity will be evaluated in all subjects prior to vaccination on Day 0 (Visit 1) and
      at Day 28 after the final vaccination using the hemagglutination inhibition technique. For
      each influenza vaccine strain, pre- and post-vaccination geometric mean titers will be
      calculated.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants reporting solicited injection site and systemic events and unsolicited adverse events following vaccination with Fluzone Quadrivalent vaccine.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 up to Day 28 post vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants 6 Months to &lt; 36 Months of Age Solicited injection site reactions: Tenderness, Redness, and Swelling; Solicited systemic reactions: Fever (Temperature), Vomiting, Abnormal crying, Drowsiness, Loss of appetite, and Irritability. Participants 3 Years to &lt; 9 Years of Age: Solicited injection site reactions: Pain, Redness, and Swelling; Solicited systemic reactions: Fever (Temperature), Headache, Malaise, Myalgia. Unsolicited adverse events, including serious adverse events will also be collected for all participants.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geometric mean titers of antibodies to vaccine antigens following vaccination with Fluzone Quadrivalent vaccine</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 and Day 28 after final vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Immunogenicity will be evaluated prior to vaccination and at 28 days after vaccination using the hemagglutination inhibition (HAI) technique. For each influenza vaccine strain, pre and post vaccination geometric mean titers (GMTs) and seroprotection and seroconversion will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Seroprotection and seroconversion to vaccine antigens following vaccination with Fluzone® Quadrivalent vaccine</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28 after final vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Seroprotection is defined as: A titer ≥ 40 (l/dil) at pre vaccination and at Day 28 after the final vaccination. Seroconversion is defined as: Either a pre vaccination titer &lt; 10 (1/dil) and a post vaccination titer ≥ 40 (1/dil), or a pre vaccination titer ≥ 10 (1/dil) and a ≥ 4 fold increase in post vaccination titer at Day 28 after the final vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants at 6 months to &lt; 36 months age at enrollment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants at 3 years to &lt; 9  age at enrollment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluzone® Quadrivalent Influenza Virus Vaccine, No Preservative</intervention_name>
    <description>0.25 mL, Intramuscular (Pediatric Dose, 2013-2014 formulation)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fluzone® Quadrivalent, No Preservative</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluzone® Quadrivalent Influenza Virus Vaccine, No Preservative</intervention_name>
    <description>0.5 mL, Intramuscular (2013-2014 formulation )</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fluzone® Quadrivalent, No Preservative</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject is 6 months to &lt; 9 years of age on the day of first study vaccination (study
             product administration)

          -  Subject and parent/legally acceptable representative are willing and able to attend
             scheduled visits and to comply with the study procedures during the entire duration
             of the study

          -  Assent form has been signed and dated by subjects 7 to &lt; 9 years of age, and informed
             consent form has been signed and dated by parent(s) or another legally acceptable
             representative

          -  For subjects 6 months to &lt; 12 months of age, born at full term of pregnancy (≥ 37
             weeks) and with a birth weight ≥ 2.5 kg (5.5 lbs.) Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known systemic hypersensitivity to eggs, chicken proteins, or any of the vaccine
             components, or a history of a life-threatening reaction to Fluzone Quadrivalent
             vaccine or to a vaccine containing any of the same substances (the complete list of
             vaccine components is included in the Prescribing Information)

          -  History of serious adverse reaction to any influenza vaccine

          -  Receipt of any vaccine within 30 days before  receiving study vaccine, or plans to
             receive another vaccine before Visit 2 for subjects receiving 1 dose of influenza
             vaccine or Visit 3 for subjects receiving 2 doses of influenza vaccine

          -  Participation in another interventional clinical trial investigating a vaccine, drug,
             medical device, or medical procedure in the 30 days preceding the first study
             vaccination or during the course of the study unless no intervention for the other
             study occurred within the 30 days prior to the first study vaccination and none are
             planned before the subject would complete safety surveillance for the present study

          -  Prior vaccination with any formulation of 2013-2014 influenza vaccine

          -  Bleeding disorder or receipt of anticoagulants in the 3 weeks preceding inclusion,
             which may be a contraindication for intramuscular (IM) vaccination, at the discretion
             of the Investigator

          -  Thrombocytopenia, which may be a contraindication for IM vaccination, at the
             discretion of the Investigator

          -  Any condition that in the opinion of the Investigator would pose a health risk to the
             subject if enrolled or could interfere with the evaluation of the vaccine

          -  Personal history of Guillain-Barré syndrome

          -  Known or suspected congenital or acquired immunodeficiency; or receipt of
             immunosuppressive therapy such as anti-cancer chemotherapy or radiation therapy
             within the preceding 6 months; or long-term systemic corticosteroid therapy
             (prednisone or equivalent for more than 2 consecutive weeks within the past 3 months)

          -  Personal history of clinically significant developmental delay (at the discretion of
             the Investigator), neurologic disorder, or seizure disorder

          -  Chronic illness that, in the opinion of the Investigator, is at a stage where it
             might interfere with trial conduct or completion

          -  Known seropositivity for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis B, or
             hepatitis C

          -  Moderate or severe acute illness/infection (according to Investigator judgment) on
             the day of vaccination or febrile illness (temperature ≥ 100.4°F]). A prospective
             subject should not be included in the study until the condition has resolved or the
             febrile event has subsided

          -  Receipt of immune globulins, blood, or blood-derived products in the past 3 months

          -  Identified as a natural or adopted child of the Investigator or an employee with
             direct involvement in the proposed study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>8 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Sanofi Pasteur Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Bardstown</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40040</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84121</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.sanofipasteur.com</url>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.sanofi.com</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 24, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 16, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Influenza</keyword>
  <keyword>Influenza virus vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>Fluzone® Quadrivalent Influenza Virus Vaccine (No Preservative)</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
