<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="99102">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01855958</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11-0013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01855958</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Motor Cortex Plasticity and the Effect of Deep Intramuscular Needling Stimulation Therapy (DIMST) in Osteoarthritis Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Primary Motor Cortex Plasticity and the Bottom up Effect of Deep Intramuscular Needling Stimulation Therapy (DIMST)in Osteoarthritis Chronic Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital de Clinicas de Porto Alegre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Associação Fundo de Incentivo à Pesquisa</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital de Clinicas de Porto Alegre</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Brazil: Associação Fundo de Incentivo à Pesquisa</authority>
    <authority>Brazil: National Committee of Ethics in Research</authority>
    <authority>Brazil: National Health Surveillance Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to evaluate the cortical excitability in pain of knee
      osteoarthritis (OA), as well as the effect of one session of a kind of electroacupuncture
      (deep needling intramuscular stimulation therapy - DIMST) in this pain and the cortical
      excitability after  the intervention.

      The hypothesis is that cortical excitability is altered in this condition, confirming the
      findings already described in other chronic pain conditions. The investigators also believe
      that a session DIMST can reduce pain and alter cortical excitability, restoring its previous
      activity will occur from chronic pain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recent developments in the treatment of chronic pain have shown that the primary motor
      cortex (M1) is an effective target for neural brain stimulation techniques, such as
      transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS). Due to these promising initial results, the
      plasticity of M1 has also been investigated as a potential marker for chronic pain. TMS
      studies using single or paired pulse shown changes in M1 plasticity in neuropathic pain and
      fibromyalgia pain compared to healthy subjects. Thus, there is a decrease in the inhibitory
      activity of chronic pain that can take a state as shown uninhibited by measuring TMS indexed
      intracortical inhibition (ICI) and cortical silent period (CSP). Based on these experimental
      data and clinical studies have been focused on the effects of neuromodulation techniques in
      M1 excitability. The techniques used to stimulate the peripheral nervous system was
      investigated using different approaches. The DIMST is a therapy applied to treat peripheral
      chronic syndromes that may have central components such as myofascial pain. During DIMST,
      the needles are applied to the spinal segment associated with nerve roots dermatome
      corresponding to the pathology. This treatment can also be effective in the treatment of
      diseases that have major peripheral components such as OA. OA is a major cause of suffering
      and disability in the elderly, having an inflammatory component, such as a factor that
      contributes to the symptoms and progression of the disease. There is evidence that OA could
      lead to sensitization central and segmental, but these effects on M1 plasticity and other
      central components are not completely known.

      Therefore, researchers proposed to evaluate the plasticity of M1 in this chronic pain
      condition and also the effect of bottom-up DIMST in pain and cortical excitability.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the pressure pain threshold (PPT) after the intervention.</measure>
    <time_frame>All research was conducted in one day. The PPT was assessed before and within an hour after one single intervention session.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The subject was instructed to verbally report the perception of pain onset. The PPT was assessed using an electronic algometer (J Tech Medical Industries, USA). The device had a 1-cm2 hard-rubber probe, which was applied over structures at L1- L5 dermatome at the knee. The average values of PPT in kgf/cm2 for three successive readings taken at intervals of 3-5 min were used as the outcomes.The investigators also measured PPT during cold water immersion, evaluated the degree to which pain perception is modulated by conditional pain modulation (CPM) following the presentation of an initial heterotopic noxious stimulus. Subjects immersed their left hands into cold water (zero to 1°C) for 1 minute. During the last 30 seconds of cold-water immersion, the PPT procedure was administered over structures at L1- L5 dermatome at the knee. The temperature was held constant across during the experiment for each subject.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in motor evoked potential (MEP) after the intervention.</measure>
    <time_frame>Evaluation performed before and within an hour after an intervention session, in the same day.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Cortical excitability was assessed using a transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) device (MagPro X100)and a figure-of-8 coil centered over the left motor cortex (M1). Subjects were seated in a comfortable reclining chair with their arms and hands lying relaxed on the armrests. The investigators measured the resting motor threshold (rMT) of the right first dorsal interosseous (FDI) muscle. The MEPs was recorded by surface electromyography (EMG) using Ag-AgCl cup electrodes in a belly tendon montage.
Resting motor threshold (rMT)was deﬁned as the stimulus intensity at which peak-to-peak MEP amplitude of 50 µV was obtained in at least 5 of 10 consecutive trials.
MEP was deﬁned as approximately 130% of the rMT or the stimulus intensity at which peak-to-peak MEP amplitude of at least 1 mV was obtained in 10 consecutive trials.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modify cortical excitability with the intervention.</measure>
    <time_frame>To evaluate in one day the cortical excitability before and within an hour after intervention by intracortical inhibition (ICI), intracortical facilitation (ICF) and silent period (CSP).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>ICI was evaluated using inter-stimuli intervals (ISIs) of 2 ms with paired-pulse stimulation. The subthreshold stimulus was set at 80% of rMT, and the suprathreshold test stimulus was set at 130% of rMT.
ICF was evaluated using an ISI of 12 ms with paired-pulse and similar parameters for the conditioning and test stimuli. After a randomized protocol, thirty trials were assessed using a 2ms interval, a 12ms interval and test-only trials. The resulting MEP amplitude was converted into the mean amplitude, and paired-pulse parameters were expressed as the amount of inhibition or facilitation (ICI or ICF = conditioned MEP/ unconditioned MEP).
To determine the CSP subjects were instructed to squeeze the dynamometer using their fingers at 20% of maximal force when a single pulse stimulus (130% rMT) was applied.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change the pain intensity.</measure>
    <time_frame>To evaluate the intensity of pain by VAS within twenty four hours before and within one hour after the intervention.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The intensity of pain was measured by a 10-cm VAS. VAS scores ranged from no pain (zero) to the worst possible pain possible (10 cm). The pain score on VAS during the last 24 hours was used to classify the subjects into two groups: (1) absence of pain or mild pain (scores equal to or lower than 4 cm) and (2) moderate, intense, or worst possible pain (scores higher than 4 cm).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate pain intensity, functional capacity and rigidity in knee OA.</measure>
    <time_frame>In the baseline.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Brazilian version of the Western Ontario and McMaster Universities (WOMAC) osteoarthritis index was used, it has been proven valid and reliable for people with knee and hip osteoarthritis.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">26</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis, Knee.</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Pain.</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DIMST</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The investigators used acupuncture needles with guide tubes (Suzhou Huanqiu Acupuncture Medical Appliance Co. Ltd., 218, China) that were 40 mm in length and 0.25 mm in diameter. The needling in DIMST was applied using an electro acupuncture device (Cosmotron, São Paulo, Brazil) in the dermatomes corresponding to the nerve roots involved in the knee (L1, L2, L3, L4, L5, S1, and S2). DIMST using was administered maintaining a distance from the spinous process line of 2 cm. The anatomic sites of peripheral DIMST were the muscles vastus medialis, rectus femoris, vastus lateralis, tibialis anterioris; and the pes anserinus bursae. All subjects received one 30min session using a frequency of 2 Hz.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo-sham</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The investigators used the same electro acupuncture device (Cosmotron, Sao Paulo, Brazil), which was previously set to prevent the current to pass through the electrodes. Subjects were informed that it would be a stimulus of low intensity and high frequency that they probably would not have any sense of it. The electrodes were placed on the same points where the active stimulation was applied while the nerve stimulation unit was left in front of the subject, for 30 minutes. This positioning ensured that the intermittent diode simulating the electrical stimulus was visible and audible.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DIMST</intervention_name>
    <description>The investigators used electro acupuncture of 2 Hz during 30 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo-sham</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Paraspinal electro acupuncture.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo-sham</intervention_name>
    <description>Electro acupuncture with rubber electrodes, without current passing.</description>
    <arm_group_label>DIMST</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Electrostimulation with rubber electrodes.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women with over 18 years old, with chronic pain because of primary osteoarthritis of
             the knee.

          -  Pain stable for at least three months. Score greater than or equal to 3 cm (0 cm =
             &quot;no pain&quot; and &quot;worst possible pain&quot; = 10cm) on VAS for pain perception at baseline.

          -  No contraindications to electro acupuncture or transcranial magnetic stimulation.

          -  Naive in acupuncture treatment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinically significant or unstable disorder, medical or psychiatric.

          -  Presence of neurological or rheumatic comorbidity.

          -  Pregnancy.

          -  Having performed surgery in the knee to be treated in the last 6 months, or be
             planning surgery for the next semester.

          -  Having performed with corticosteroid infiltration in the last six weeks or are using
             this.

          -  Having performed with hyaluronic acid infiltration.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wolnei Caumo, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maria L Tarragó, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital de Clínicas de Porto Alegre.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Porto Alegre</city>
        <state>Rio Grande do Sul</state>
        <zip>90035903</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lefaucheur JP, Drouot X, Ménard-Lefaucheur I, Keravel Y, Nguyen JP. Motor cortex rTMS restores defective intracortical inhibition in chronic neuropathic pain. Neurology. 2006 Nov 14;67(9):1568-74.</citation>
    <PMID>17101886</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zunhammer M, Eichhammer P, Franz J, Hajak G, Busch V. Effects of acupuncture needle penetration on motor system excitability. Neurophysiol Clin. 2012 Jun;42(4):225-30. doi: 10.1016/j.neucli.2012.02.134. Epub 2012 Mar 6.</citation>
    <PMID>22632870</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lo YL, Cui SL. Acupuncture and the modulation of cortical excitability. Neuroreport. 2003 Jul 1;14(9):1229-31.</citation>
    <PMID>12824765</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Imamura M, Imamura ST, Kaziyama HH, Targino RA, Hsing WT, de Souza LP, Cutait MM, Fregni F, Camanho GL. Impact of nervous system hyperalgesia on pain, disability, and quality of life in patients with knee osteoarthritis: a controlled analysis. Arthritis Rheum. 2008 Oct 15;59(10):1424-31.</citation>
    <PMID>18821657</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schwenkreis P, Scherens A, Rönnau AK, Höffken O, Tegenthoff M, Maier C. Cortical disinhibition occurs in chronic neuropathic, but not in chronic nociceptive pain. BMC Neurosci. 2010 Jun 11;11:73. doi: 10.1186/1471-2202-11-73.</citation>
    <PMID>20540759</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laste G, Caumo W, Adachi LN, Rozisky JR, de Macedo IC, Filho PR, Partata WA, Fregni F, Torres IL. After-effects of consecutive sessions of transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) in a rat model of chronic inflammation. Exp Brain Res. 2012 Aug;221(1):75-83. doi: 10.1007/s00221-012-3149-x. Epub 2012 Jul 3.</citation>
    <PMID>22752510</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Le Bars D, Dickenson AH, Besson JM. Diffuse noxious inhibitory controls (DNIC). II. Lack of effect on non-convergent neurones, supraspinal involvement and theoretical implications. Pain. 1979 Jun;6(3):305-27.</citation>
    <PMID>460936</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 16, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 8, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Osteoarthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Electro acupuncture</keyword>
  <keyword>Deep intramuscular stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain pressure threshold</keyword>
  <keyword>Conditioned pain modulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Clinical trial</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
