<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="36929">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02029521</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FIMP/clin.stud/2010/1.</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02029521</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Supplementation of Oral Reduced Glutathione in Pediatric Cystic Fibrosis Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Supplementation of Oral Reduced Glutathione in Pediatric Cystic Fibrosis for Growth Failure</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Clark Bishop</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brigham Young University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Italy: Federazione Italiana Medici Pediatri (Verbano Cusio Ossola)</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Many individuals with cystic fibrosis experience growth failure.  The reasons are not clear,
      but inflammation of the gut in these patients seems to be one important reason.
      Glutathione is important to normal function of the intestine and lungs.  Glutathione
      functions to decrease inflammation and to thin mucus.  However, in cystic fibrosis,
      glutathione gets trapped inside of cells, so it cannot travel to the surface of the cells
      and perform its proper function.  Moreover, glutathione has been shown to improve
      nutritional status in patients with AIDS and cancer.

      Investigators hypothesize that supplementation of oral glutathione to pediatric individuals
      with cystic fibrosis could improve growth failure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cystic fibrosis (CF) is known principally for its pulmonary consequences.  However, for most
      individuals with CF, the earliest manifestations are not pulmonary, but gastro-intestinal.
      Many children experience growth failure.  Chronic gut inflammation also develops. Research
      has also established that lung function scores are significantly correlated with Body Mass
      Index (BMI) and weight percentile  in CF. Therefore, interventions to improve the
      gastro-intestinal dimension of CF in early childhood have the potential to ameliorate the
      course of the disease over the life span of the patient. Both Cochrane Database reviews and
      a recent review commissioned by the Cystic Fibrosis Foundation found only fair evidence for
      current nutritional guidelines.Therefore, there is a pressing need for a treatment for CF
      growth failure that is more effective and less invasive than current treatments.

      The discovery that CF is associated with significantly diminished efflux of reduced
      glutathione (GSH) from most cells in the body offers a new perspective on the
      pathophysiology of this disease.  GSH plays several important roles; among the most
      important are the following: 1) primary water-soluble antioxidant; 2) mucolytic capable of
      cleaving disulfide bonds; and 3) regulator of immune system function. The relationship
      between redox ratio (GSH:GSSG) and total glutathione (GSH+GSSG) and the initiation of
      inflammation is well established in the research literature.

      GSH is also an important component of the epithelial lining fluid of the intestines, helping
      to keep intestinal mucus thin, serving to defend the intestinal system against reactive
      oxygen species, and keeping inflammation in check under normal circumstances. GSH is an
      FDA-approved treatment for AIDS-related cachexia.  The growing recognition of GSH system
      dysfunction in CF, coupled with an established research literature on the role of GSH in
      gastro-intestinal function and weight gain in non-CF contexts, suggest a new intervention
      for growth failure in early childhood in CF patients.  Specifically, investigators
      hypothesized that oral glutathione could effectively treat CF growth failure in pediatric
      patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Body Mass Index</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Body Mass Index may improve if the treatment is successful.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight Percentile</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subjects were weighed 4 times.  Wt percentile based on age was calculated.  The experiment was to determine if treatment improved wt percentile over the course of the treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Height Percentile</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The subjects were measured over the course of the study to determine if treatment improved height percentile.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fecal Calprotectin</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Fecal Calprotectin, a measure of gut inflammation, was measured to see if the treatment decreased this outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Forced Vital Capacity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>If able, subjects Forced Vital Capacity was measured to determine if the treatment improved this measure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Forced Expiratory Volume measured at one second (FEV1)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>FEV1 was measured at the beginning and end of the study to determine if this measure improved with the treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>C-Reactive Protein (CRP)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>CRP was measured to determine if this test fell during the course of treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>White Blood Cell Count</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>White blood cell count was measure at the beginning and end of the study to determine if treatment affected this test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vitamin E</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Serum Vitamin E levels were measured to determine if treatment affected this test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alanine aminotransferase (ALT)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>ALT was measured to determine if liver function was affected by treatment over the course of the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">44</enrollment>
  <condition>Cystic Fibrosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oral reduced l-glutathione</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The treatment was pharmaceutical-grade Reduced L-Glutathione (GSH) with a daily dose of 65 mg/kg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Calcium Citrate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The placebo was calcium citrate with a daily dose of 65 mg/kg. The daily dose of each substance was divided into three doses given at mealtime.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oral reduced l-glutathione</intervention_name>
    <description>The treatment was pharmaceutical-grade Reduced L-Glutathione (GSH) with a daily dose of 65 mg/kg. The placebo was calcium citrate with a daily dose of 65 mg/kg. The daily dose of each substance was divided into three doses given at mealtime.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oral reduced l-glutathione</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        -Diagnosis of Cystic Fibrosis by either of the following criteria: &gt;60 sweat chloride test
        or paired deleterious DNA CFTR mutations (Ambry genetics, Genetech or ARUP);

        -Pancreatic insufficient as defined by doctor's prescription of pancreatic enzymes.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Hospitalized for bowel obstruction or surgery in the six months prior to enrollment;

          -  had had a pulmonary exacerbation or oral steroid use or IV antibiotics within one
             month of enrollment,

          -  who had been taking either GSH or NAC within the 12 month period immediately prior to
             the trial,

          -  chronically infected with B. cepacia.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>10 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Clark T Bishop, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Intermountain Health Care</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Turin</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 6, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 30, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Brigham Young University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Clark Bishop</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Co investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cystic fibrosis</keyword>
  <keyword>growth Failure</keyword>
  <keyword>glutathione</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cystic Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
