<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="72039">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01696942</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>36497</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01696942</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cimzia Versus Mesalamine for Crohn's Recurrence</brief_title>
  <official_title>Use of Certolizumab Following Ileocolectomy Lowers Endoscopic and Histological Recurrence Rates for Crohn's Disease at One Year Compared to Mesalamine</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>UCB, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hypothesis: Cimzia provides superior reduction in endoscopic and clinical recurrence rates
      compared to mesalamine in the treatment of Crohn's disease one-year following ileocolectomy
      for Crohn's disease.

        1. To evaluate the difference in clinical recurrence rates between certolizumab and
           mesalamine after 4 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 9 months, and 12 months of use following
           ileocolectomy for Crohn's disease using the Crohn's Disease Activity Index (CDAI).

        2. To compare the endoscopic recurrence rates at one year following surgery between
           patients treated with certolizumab and mesalamine.

        3. To compare medication side-effects and tolerance of therapy, including the need to
           interrupt therapy due to side-effects, the incidence of opportunistic infections, and a
           general assessment of each patient's health and well-being using the short-form 36
           (SF-36).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Crohn's disease is an autoimmune, pan-intestinal disease which can affect any portion of the
      alimentary tract, but which has a preference for the small intestine, the colon, and the
      anus. It is now well established that Crohn's disease most commonly presents with an
      ileocolic distribution, followed by involvement of the small intestine, the colon, and the
      anus. Treatment for Crohn's disease is principally medical, reserving surgery to address
      complications from the disease which cannot be adequately resolved with medication alone.
      The single greatest challenge in treating this incurable disease is dealing with its
      recurrence rate. The cumulative probability of disease recurrence is quite high, with 75% of
      Crohn's patients requiring abdominal surgery at some point during their life.

      Following surgery, recurrence rates are significant, varying depending on the manner in
      which recurrence is defined. With regard to clinical recurrences, where the recrudescence of
      the disease is associated with symptoms caused by new intestinal lesions, the recurrence
      rate is 10-20% per year.In some instances, clinical recurrences can appear within 3 months
      of surgery. Taking into account the need for additional surgery as defining a &quot;surgical
      recurrence&quot;, reoperation rates for Crohn's disease range from 16% to 65% 10 years after a
      previous surgery. When recurrence is viewed from the vantage point of evidence of new
      Crohn's disease activity based on radiographic studies, radiographic recurrences range from
      41-60% over the first 10 years following surgery. One of the most common measures of
      recurrence has become demonstrating evidence of new Crohn's disease activity based on
      colonoscopy. This endoscopic recurrence has consistently been shown to be as high as 50-75%
      at 3 months after surgery, and 50-90% at 12 months. It is widely accepted by physicians
      treating Crohn's patients that the appearance of endoscopic lesions has prognostic
      significance, as endoscopic evidence of Crohn's disease temporally precedes radiographic,
      clinical and surgical recurrences.

      The role that Cimzia should play in preventing recurrence of Crohn's disease following
      ileocolectomy for Crohn's disease remains to be determined, as does its relative advantages
      and disadvantages compared to the use of mesalamine.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical recurrence rates of Crohn's disease</measure>
    <time_frame>One year following enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the difference in clinical recurrence rates between certolizumab and mesalamine after 4 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 9 months, and 12 months of use following ileocolectomy for Crohn's disease using the Crohn's Disease Activity Index (CDAI).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Endoscopic recurrence of Crohn's disease</measure>
    <time_frame>One year following enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To compare the endoscopic recurrence rates at one year following surgery between patients treated with certolizumab and mesalamine.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Crohn's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cimzia treatment arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Beginning at 4 weeks after surgery, patients would be randomly assigned      using a pulled card method to receive certolizumab at a dose of 400 mg subcutaneously at weeks 4, 6, and 8 after surgery, and then every 4 weeks thereafter up to 12 months after enrollment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mesalamine treatment arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Beginning at 4 weeks after surgery, patients would be randomly assigned to receive mesalamine 800 mg orally three times daily for twelve months following enrollment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cimzia</intervention_name>
    <description>400 mg subcutaneously at weeks 4, 6, and 8 after surgery, and then every 4 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cimzia treatment arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Certolizumab</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mesalamine</intervention_name>
    <description>mesalamine 800 mg orally three times daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mesalamine treatment arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Mesalamine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients ≥18 years of age or older with Crohn's disease of any phenotype  (luminal
             disease, perforating disease, stricturing disease) with an ileocolic distribution.

          -  Ileocolic Crohn's disease severe enough to require ileocolectomy (either open or
             laparoscopic).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients younger than 18 years of age, as there is little data on pediatric patients
             and since the Colorectal Surgery service only treats patients 18 years of age or
             older.

          -  Patients undergoing an ileocolectomy for any reason besides Crohn's disease.

          -  Patients requiring a stoma.

          -  Patients with short-bowel syndrome.

          -  Patients who are incarcerated, due to difficulties with frequent clinic    visits
             given their incarceration and transportation issues.

          -  Patients who received previous anti-TNF therapy from infliximab or adalimumab within
             three months of surgery, or patients who have a history of a severe hypersensitivity
             reaction to infliximab or adalimumab

          -  Patients with a positive PPD and a suspicious finding on a chest x-ray suggestive of
             tuberculosis, or any patient with a history of tuberculosis.

          -  Patients who require postoperative therapy besides either mesalamine or certolizumab
             (steroids, antibiotics, and immunomodulator therapy would not be permitted starting
             at 4 weeks after ileocolectomy).

          -  Patients with significant psychiatric disorders (i.e. schizophrenia) and those with
             significant cognitive disorders, due to the difficulties with this patient group
             remaining compliant with frequent clinic visits, and due to the difficulty evaluating
             quality of life measures in these patients.

          -  Patients with a history of malignancy.

          -  Patients with a history of any demyelinating neurologic disease or a history of
             seizures.

          -  Patients with a history of severe congestive heart failure.

          -  Patients with a history of hepatitis B or C virus.

          -  Patients who are pregnant or who become pregnant.

          -  Involvement in any other clinical studies which use study medications.

          -  The subject has a condition, which, in the opinion of the investigator, would
             compromise the study or well-being of the subject or prevent the subject from meeting
             or performing the study requirements.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David B Stewart, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David B Stewart, MD</last_name>
    <phone>717-531-5164</phone>
    <email>dstewart@hmc.psu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Emmanuelle Williams, MD</last_name>
    <phone>717531-8741</phone>
    <email>ewilliams@hmc.psu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Penn State Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hershey</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>17033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>LeeAnn Smith, RN</last_name>
      <phone>717-531-0003</phone>
      <phone_ext>285155</phone_ext>
      <email>lsmith1@hmc.psu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David B Stewart, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Emmanuelle Williams, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrew Tinsley, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Walter A Koltun, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Evangelos Messaris, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Whelan G, Farmer RG, Fazio VW, Goormastic M. Recurrence after surgery in Crohn's disease. Relationship to location of disease (clinical pattern) and surgical indication. Gastroenterology. 1985 Jun;88(6):1826-33.</citation>
    <PMID>3996839</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mekhjian HS, Switz DM, Watts HD, Deren JJ, Katon RM, Beman FM. National Cooperative Crohn's Disease Study: factors determining recurrence of Crohn's disease after surgery. Gastroenterology. 1979 Oct;77(4 Pt 2):907-13.</citation>
    <PMID>467942</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kyle J. Prognosis after ileal resection for Crohn's disease. Br J Surg. 1971 Oct;58(10):735-7.</citation>
    <PMID>5097949</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lennard-Jones JE, Stalder GA. Prognosis after resection of chronic regional ileitis. Gut. 1967 Aug;8(4):332-6.</citation>
    <PMID>6039720</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Greenstein AJ, Sachar DB, Pasternack BS, Janowitz HD. Reoperation and recurrence in Crohn's colitis and ileocolitis Crude and cumulative rates. N Engl J Med. 1975 Oct 2;293(14):685-90.</citation>
    <PMID>1160935</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Regueiro M, Schraut W, Baidoo L, Kip KE, Sepulveda AR, Pesci M, Harrison J, Plevy SE. Infliximab prevents Crohn's disease recurrence after ileal resection. Gastroenterology. 2009 Feb;136(2):441-50.e1; quiz 716. Epub 2008 Oct 31.</citation>
    <PMID>19109962</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cottone M, Mocciaro F, Orlando A. Infliximab prevents Crohn's disease recurrence after ileal resection. Expert Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2009 Jun;3(3):231-4.</citation>
    <PMID>19485805</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schreiber S. Certolizumab pegol for the treatment of Crohn's disease. Therap Adv Gastroenterol. 2011 Nov;4(6):375-89. doi: 10.1177/1756283X11413315.</citation>
    <PMID>22043230</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sandborn WJ, Schreiber S, Feagan BG, Rutgeerts P, Younes ZH, Bloomfield R, Coteur G, Guzman JP, D'Haens GR. Certolizumab pegol for active Crohn's disease: a placebo-controlled, randomized trial. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2011 Aug;9(8):670-678.e3. doi: 10.1016/j.cgh.2011.04.031. Epub 2011 May 13.</citation>
    <PMID>21642014</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Feagan BG, Sandborn WJ, Wolf DC, Coteur G, Purcaru O, Brabant Y, Rutgeerts PJ. Randomised clinical trial: improvement in health outcomes with certolizumab pegol in patients with active Crohn's disease with prior loss of response to infliximab. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2011 Mar;33(5):541-50. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2036.2010.04568.x. Epub 2011 Jan 12.</citation>
    <PMID>21223344</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 26, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 25, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David B. Stewart, MD, FACS, FASCRS</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Crohn's disease</keyword>
  <keyword>certolizumab</keyword>
  <keyword>mesalamine</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrence</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Crohn Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Recurrence</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Mesalamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
