<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="92593">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02140554</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HGB-206</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02140554</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study Evaluating the Safety and Efficacy of the LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product in Severe Sickle Cell Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1 Study Evaluating Gene Therapy by Transplantation of Autologous CD34+ Stem Cells Transduced Ex Vivo With the LentiGlobin BB305 Lentiviral Vector in Subjects With Severe Sickle Cell Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>bluebird bio</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>bluebird bio</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a non-randomized, open label, multi-site, single-dose, Phase 1 study in up to 8
      adults with severe sickle cell disease (SCD). The study will evaluate the safety and
      efficacy of the LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product [consisting of autologous CD34+ hematopoietic
      stem cells (HSC) transduced with LentiGlobin BB305 lentiviral vector encoding the human beta
      A-T87Q-globin gene].
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Subject participation for this study will be 2 years post-treatment. Subjects who enroll in
      this study will be asked to participate in a subsequent long-term follow up study that will
      monitor the safety and efficacy of the treatment they receive for up to 13 years
      post-transplant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>1-24 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety will be evaluated by the following:
success and kinetics of hematopoietic stem cell (HSC) engraftment
incidence of treatment related mortality
incidence of mortality through 2 years after drug product infusion
detection of vector derived replication competent lentivirus (RCL) in any subject
characterization of events of insertional mutagenesis leading to malignancy
monitoring of laboratory parameters and frequency and severity of clinical AEs, as assessed by the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE), version 4.03</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical efficacy will be evaluated by comparing the frequency of clinical events secondary to sickle cell disease</measure>
    <time_frame>1-24 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Efficacy will be evaluated by the following:
severe vaso-occlusive crisis (VOC). A severe VOC is defined as an episode of pain lasting more than 2 hours severe enough to require care at a medical facility. Priapism that lasts more than 2 hours and requires care at a medical facility is considered a severe VOC
acute chest syndrome events, defined as an acute event with pneumonia like symptoms and the presence of a new pulmonary infiltrate
strokes or transient ischemic attacks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">8</enrollment>
  <condition>Sickle Cell Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product (autologous CD34+ hematopoietic stem cells transduced with LentiGlobin BB305 lentiviral vector encoding the human beta-A-T87Q globin gene</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product</intervention_name>
    <description>LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product is administered by IV infusion following myeloablative conditioning with busulfan.</description>
    <arm_group_label>LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>autologous CD34+ hematopoietic stem cells transduced with LentiGlobin BB305 lentiviral vector encoding the human beta-A-T87Q globin gene</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. 18 years of age or older.

          2. Diagnosis of sickle cell disease (SCD), with either βS/βS or βS/β0 genotype.

          3. Have severe SCD. i.e., in the setting of appropriate supportive care measures for SCD
             (e.g., pain management plan, transfusion regimens, hydroxyurea), as judged by the
             Investigator, have experienced one or more of the following events:

               -  Recurrent severe vaso occlusive crises (VOC) (at least 2 episodes per year in
                  the preceding 2 years). To meet this criterion, subjects must have either
                  experienced hydroxyurea failure at any point in the past (defined as &gt; 1 VOC or
                  ≥ 1 ACS after taking hydroxyurea for at least 3 months) or must have intolerance
                  to hydroxyurea.

               -  Acute Chest Syndrome (ACS) (at least 2 total episodes in the prior 2 years, with
                  at least one episode in the past year), defined as an acute event with
                  pneumonia-like symptoms and the presence of a new pulmonary infiltrate. To meet
                  this criterion subjects must have either experienced hydroxyurea failure or have
                  intolerance to hydroxyurea, as defined above.

               -  History of an overt stroke. An overt stroke is defined as a sudden neurologic
                  change lasting more than 24 hours that is accompanied by cerebral MRI changes.

               -  Echocardiographic evidence of a tricuspid regurgitant jet velocity (TRJV) of &gt;
                  2.5 m/s.

          4. Medically eligible to undergo hematopoietic stem cell transplant  (HSCT).

          5. Karnofsky performance status of ≥ 60.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Positive for any active infection.

          2. Any major organ dysfunction (renal, liver, lung and cardiac abnormalities).

          3. Inadequate bone marrow function, as defined by an absolute neutrophil count of &lt;
             1000/µL (&lt; 500/µL for subjects on hydroxyurea treatment) or a platelet count &lt;
             50,000/µL.

          4. Moyamoya disease on cerebral MRI. Subjects with a history of a revascularization
             procedure for Moyamoya disease (e.g., encephaloduroarteriosynangiosis (EDAS)
             procedure) are eligible if the procedure occurred &gt; 1 year prior to study entry.

          5. Contraindication to anesthesia for bone marrow harvesting.

          6. Any prior or current malignancy or immunodeficiency disorder, except previously
             treated, non-life threatening, cured tumors such as squamous cell carcinoma of the
             skin.

          7. Prior receipt of an allogeneic transplant.

          8. Immediate family member with a known or suspected Familial Cancer Syndrome

          9. Pregnancy, or breastfeeding in a postpartum female, or absence of adequate
             contraception for fertile subjects.

         10. Prior receipt of gene therapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sandeep Soni, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>bluebird bio, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>bluebird bio</last_name>
    <email>clinicaltrials@bluebirdbio.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 14, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Sickle Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
