<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="110781">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01686165</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-0288-04</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-01131</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01686165</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Belinostat and Yttrium Y 90 Ibritumomab Tiuxetan in Treating Patients With Relapsed Aggressive B-Cell Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Exploratory Study of PXD-101(Belinostat) Followed by Zevalin in Patients With Relapsed Aggressive High-Risk Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Arizona</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Arizona</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study looks at what effects (good and bad) a drug called PXD-101 (belinostat) in
      combination with the radioactive drug Zevalin (yttrium Y 90 ibritumomab tiuxetan) has on
      patients with relapsed aggressive (high-risk) non-Hodgkin lymphoma. Studies in the
      laboratory suggest that drugs such as PXD101 can act upon specific cancer cell processes to
      cause either death of the cancer cells or prevention of their growth. In human studies with
      a small number of patients with this lymphoma, PXD-101 has shown the ability to shrink and
      slow tumor growth. When Zevalin is delivered directly to the tumor, the lymphoma cells are
      destroyed and this may result in the disappearance of the tumor (remission)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To document the complete response rate and overall response for patients with relapsed
      aggressive high-risk non-Hodgkin's lymphoma treated with two cycles PXD-101 followed by one
      cycle of Zevalin.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To estimate 2-year progression-free survival in patients with relapsed aggressive
      high-risk non-Hodgkin's lymphoma treated with two cycles PXD-101 followed by one cycle of
      Zevalin.

      II. To evaluate the toxicity of two cycles PXD-101 and one cycle of Zevalin in patients with
      relapsed aggressive high-risk non-Hodgkin's lymphoma.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive belinostat intravenously (IV) over 30-60 minutes on days 1-5. Treatment
      with belinostat repeats every 21 days for 2 courses. Patients then receive rituximab IV on
      days 1 and either 7, 8, or 9, and yttrium Y 90 ibritumomab tiuxetan IV over 10 minutes on
      day 50. Treatment continues in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 3 months for 2 years and
      then every 6 months for 3 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be estimated using a Kaplan-Meier estimate. The observed 2-year progression-free survival rate will be estimated (with a 95% confidence interval) from the Kaplan-Meier curve.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of adverse events and serious adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after patient receives last dose of study drug</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The proportion of patients with a given adverse event will be tabulated and the 95% confidence interval computed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">13</enrollment>
  <condition>Anaplastic Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Diffuse Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Mantle Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (belinostat, yttrium Y 90 ibritumomab tiuxetan)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive belinostat IV over 30-60 minutes on days 1-5. Treatment with belinostat repeats every 21 days for 2 courses. Patients then receive rituximab IV on days 1 and either 7, 8, or 9, and yttrium Y 90 ibritumomab tiuxetan IV over 10 minutes on day 50. Treatment continues in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>belinostat</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (belinostat, yttrium Y 90 ibritumomab tiuxetan)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PXD101</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>rituximab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (belinostat, yttrium Y 90 ibritumomab tiuxetan)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IDEC-C2B8</other_name>
    <other_name>IDEC-C2B8 monoclonal antibody</other_name>
    <other_name>Mabthera</other_name>
    <other_name>MOAB IDEC-C2B8</other_name>
    <other_name>Rituxan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>yttrium Y 90 ibritumomab tiuxetan</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (belinostat, yttrium Y 90 ibritumomab tiuxetan)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>90Y ibritumomab tiuxetan</other_name>
    <other_name>IDEC Y2B8</other_name>
    <other_name>Y90 Zevalin</other_name>
    <other_name>Y90-labeled ibritumomab tiuxetan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have biopsy confirmed, cluster of differentiation (CD)20 positive
             diffuse large B-cell lymphoma, mantel cell, high grade-B-cell or anaplastic large B
             cell non-Hodgkin lymphoma (NHL); AND bone marrow must show =&lt; 20% CD20+ B-cells with
             &gt;= 15% cellularity within 42 days of study registration

          -  Any stage disease is allowed

          -  Patients must have been previously treated:

               -  &gt;= 3rd line if bone marrow transplant (BMT) candidate OR

               -  &gt;= 2nd line if not BMT candidate OR

               -  &gt;= 2nd relapse for BMT candidate OR

               -  &gt;= 1st relapse for non- BMT candidate

          -  Patients must have a diagnostic quality contrast computed tomography (CT) scan of the
             chest, abdomen and pelvis OR baseline positron emission tomography (PET)-CT scan
             performed within 28 days prior to registration

          -  All patients must have bidimensionally measurable disease with lesions at least 1.5
             cm in one dimension all measurable disease must be assessed within 28 days of
             registration

          -  For purposes of determining prior drug regimens the following should be used as a
             standard; radiation therapy counts as 1 treatment, BMT including induction counts as
             one treatment, radioimmunotherapy is not considered a chemotherapy regimen, rituximab
             alone is not considered a treatment; all prior therapy must have been completed at
             least 30 days prior to registration; patients should not have taken valproic acid, or
             any other histone deacetylase inhibitor (eg., vorinostat, romidepsin), for at least
             30 days prior to registration; patients must have recovered from any toxicities
             related to therapies prior to registration

          -  Patients must not have clinical evidence of central nervous system involvement by
             lymphoma, since proposed treatment would not be able to address it adequately; any
             laboratory (eg., lactate dehydrogenase [LDH]) or radiographic tests performed to
             access central nervous system (CNS) involvement must be negative and must be
             performed within 42 days prior to registration

          -  Patients must have unilateral or bilateral bone marrow biopsy performed within 42
             days prior to registration

          -  Life expectancy of greater than 3 months

          -  Karnofsky performance status &gt;= 60%

          -  Leukocytes &gt;= 3,000/mcL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1,500/mcL

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100,000/mcL

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase
             [SGOT])/alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamic pyruvate transaminase [SGPT])
             =&lt; 2.5 X institutional upper limit of normal

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 X institutional upper limit of normal (unless associated with
             Gilbert's syndrome)

          -  Serum creatinine &lt; 2 x institutional upper limit of normal OR

          -  Measured creatinine clearance &gt;= 60 mL/min

          -  LDH &lt; 1.50 X institutional upper limit of normal

          -  Patients must have an electrocardiogram (EKG) with no significant abnormalities
             within 28 days prior to registration

          -  The effects of PXD-101 on the developing human fetus at the recommended therapeutic
             dose are unknown; for this reason women of child-bearing potential and men must agree
             to use adequate contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control;
             abstinence) prior to study entry and for the duration of study participation; should
             a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while she or her partner is
             participating in this study, the patient should inform the treating physician
             immediately

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have had chemotherapy or radiotherapy within 30 days (6 weeks for
             nitrosoureas or mitomycin C) prior to study screening or those who have not recovered
             from adverse events due to agents administered more than 4 weeks earlier

          -  Prior radioimmunotherapy

          -  Pregnant or nursing

          -  Clinical evidence of CNS involvement by lymphoma

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to PXD-101 or Zevalin or other agents used in the study

          -  Concomitant medication that may cause Torsade de Pointes, i.e. prolongation of the QT
             interval &gt; 500 msec

          -  Significant cardiovascular disease including unstable angina pectoris, uncontrolled
             hypertension, congestive heart failure related to primary cardiac disease, any
             condition requiring anti-arrhythmic therapy, ischemic or valvular heart disease, or a
             myocardial infarction within the past 6 months

          -  Current long QT syndrome or baseline prolongation of QT/QTcF interval, i.e.
             demonstration of a QTcF interval &gt; 450 msec

          -  Clinical evidence of severe peripheral vascular disease, diabetic ulcers or venous
             stasis ulcers, or history of deep venous or arterial thrombosis within 3 months prior
             to screening

          -  Known to be human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positive or with known acquired
             immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS) syndrome

          -  Patients may not be receiving any other investigational agents
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Soham Puvvada</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Arizona</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Soham D Puvvada, MD</last_name>
    <email>sohampuvvada@email.arizona.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ruth Canamar</last_name>
    <phone>520-626-6515</phone>
    <email>RCanamar@uacc.arizona.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Arizona Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tucson</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85724-5024</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>SOham D Puvvada, MD</last_name>
      <email>sohampuvvada@email.arizona.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ruth Canamar</last_name>
      <phone>(520) 626-6515</phone>
      <email>rcanamar@uacc.arizona.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Soham D Puvvada</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 20, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 12, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large B-Cell, Diffuse</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large-Cell, Anaplastic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Mantle-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
