<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="126044">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01875874</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VTI-212</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01875874</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy of ELAD to Treat Fulminant Hepatic Failure (FHF)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Open-Label, Multicenter, Controlled Study to Assess Safety and Efficacy of ELAD in Subjects With Fulminant Hepatic Failure (FHF)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Vital Therapies, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Vital Therapies, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is developed to determine if ELAD helps survival (up to 28 days) in subjects that
      have fulminant hepatic failure (FHF) which is acute liver failure with no pre-existing liver
      disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      VTI-212 is a randomized, multicenter, open-label, controlled study of subjects with
      fulminant hepatic failure (FHF).  Approximately 126 evaluable subjects meeting the
      eligibility requirements of the study will be randomly assigned in a 1:1 ratio to receive
      either standard of care treatment, as defined in the protocol (SOC) for FHF plus treatment
      with the ELAD system (ELAD group), or SOC for FHF alone (Control group).

      Central randomization will be performed to ensure that neither site nor study personnel will
      have any foreknowledge of subject treatment assignment, and to ensure treatment group
      balance for the following pre-specified stratification factors that may define patient
      subgroups with a potential for different outcomes:

        1. FHF following acetaminophen overdose,

        2. Subjects with non-acetaminophen or an unknown cause of FHF.

      Screening evaluations and assessments will be completed for both ELAD and Control subjects
      and reviewed against inclusion/exclusion criteria.  Confirmation of the subject's
      eligibility will be determined in the same manner for both ELAD and Control subjects.

      For both study groups, the time of randomization will define the time of study entry (Hour
      0, Study Day 1, study baseline) and inclusion in the ITT population.

      Subjects in both groups will be evaluated throughout the 28-day study period.

      If standard of care therapy as defined by the institution and this protocol is consistent
      with discharging the subject home, then the subject should be discharged.  Prior to
      discharge, the subject will be advised to attend all follow-up visits.

      Following ELAD treatment, subjects treated with ELAD will receive standard medical therapy
      and be followed through Study Day 28.

      An extension of this study, VTI-212E, will provide extended follow up of subjects enrolled
      in VTI-212 over a period of 5 years to determine incidence of survival, cancer, liver
      transplant, ans assess quality of life.  Data obtained from the extension study will be
      assessed separately from the data obtained in the 28-Day VTI-212 trial.  The database for
      VTI-212E will be a separate database with a separate analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary outcome is to measure the proportion of subjects that survive up to Study Day 28 (irrespective of orthotopic liver transplant) .</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Day 1 through Study Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>A secondary outcome is to measure the proportion of subjects with either orthotopic liver transplant or survival without orthotopic liver transplant up to Study Day 28 (bridge to transplant or recovery, BTTR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Day 1 through Study Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">126</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Liver Failure</condition>
  <condition>Fulminant Hepatic Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care (Control)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>A &quot;standardized&quot; standard of care (defined treatment for common problems that accompany FHF, such as infection and renal failure) is used for both Control and Treated subjects.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ELAD therapy plus standard of care treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ELAD continuous extracorporeal treatment for a minimum of 3 days to a maximum of 10 days in addition to a protocol &quot;standardized&quot; standard of care (defined treatment for common problems that accompany FHF, such as infection and renal failure)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ELAD</intervention_name>
    <description>Continuous treatment with the ELAD System for a minimum of 3 days to a maximum of 10 days.  The subject's ultrafiltrated blood is circulated through 4 cartridges, each containing approximately 110 grams of C3A cells (approximately 440 grams total).</description>
    <arm_group_label>ELAD therapy plus standard of care treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Weight ≥ 40 kg

          2. Age ≥ 18 and ≤ 65 years

          3. Diagnosis of Fulminant Hepatic Failure (acute liver failure with no preexisting liver
             disease)

          4. Subject or designated representative must provide Informed Consent

        AND ONE OF THE FOLLOWING CRITERIA:

        6. Known acetaminophen ingestion or diagnostic serum level, and at least one of the
        following:

          1. Prothrombin time (PT) &gt; 100 seconds (International Normalized Ratio [INR] &gt; 6.5), OR

          2. Encephalopathy Grade II, III, or IV and at least one of the following:

        i.  Arterial pH &lt; 7.30 at ≥ 2 hours after initial diagnosis, OR ii.  Renal failure
        documented by urine output &lt; 0.5 mL/kg/hr over 12 hours, OR iii.  Creatinine &gt; 2.5 mg/dL
        OR 7. Patients with non-acetaminophen-induced FHF - Stage II, III, or IV encephalopathy,
        and the presence of at least two of the following five criteria

          1. Viral Hepatitis other than A, B or C or drug (non-acetaminophen)-induced FHF

          2. Serum bilirubin &gt; 17 mg/dL

          3. Patient &gt; 40 years old

          4. Prothrombin time &gt; 50 seconds (INR &gt; 3.5)

          5. Jaundice to encephalopathy time ≥ 7 days

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Cerebral Perfusion Pressure ≤ 40 mm Hg for 1 hour or longer as measured by an
             intracranial pressure (ICP) monitor. (NOTE: In those cases where ICP monitor
             placement cannot be performed prior to study enrollment, this exclusion criterion
             will not apply)

          2. Chronic liver disease (e.g., compensated cirrhosis of any etiology, chronic
             hepatitis, nonalcoholic steatohepatitis, cholestatic liver disease, or metabolic
             liver disease); steatosis is not an exclusion criterion

          3. Concomitant disease including chronic congestive heart failure, severe vascular
             disease, emphysema, AIDS, cancer (except non-melanoma skin cancer), acute fatty-liver
             disease, hepatitis due to herpes virus or Budd-Chiari syndrome

          4. Portal hypertension (e.g., variceal bleed, caput Medusae)

          5. Liver dysfunction due to trauma

          6. Irreversible brain death (i.e., blood flow studies positive for herniation and/or
             pupillary reflex absent)

          7. Platelet count &lt; 50,000/mm3

          8. Severe hypotension - Mean arterial pressures (MAP) ≤ 50 mm Hg for 1 hour or longer
             with or without low-dose vasopressor support

          9. Evidence of hemodynamic instability

         10. Clinical or radiographic evidence of active or recent stroke or intracranial
             hemorrhage

         11. Seizures uncontrolled by medication

         12. Acute myocardial infarction based on clinical and/or electrocardiographic evidence

         13. Lung disease defined by a PaO2 ≤ 60 mm Hg or an FiO2 ≥ 0.6, not corrected by medical
             management (including continuous venovenous hemofiltration [CVVH] if indicated) and
             ventilation with a Positive End Expiratory Pressure (PEEP) of &gt; 8cm H2O

         14. Suspicion of ARDS

         15. Pregnancy as determined by beta-human chorionic gonadotropin (β-hCG) results

         16. ≤ 2 weeks postpartum

         17. In the Investigator's opinion likely to survive &lt; 48 hours

         18. Participation in another drug/device investigational study involving drug/device
             intervention within 30 days of enrollment

         19. Prior ELAD therapy

         20. Previous liver transplant
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Robert Ashley</last_name>
    <phone>520-289-3236</phone>
    <email>rashley@vitaltherapies.copm</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>George Pool</last_name>
    <phone>858-673-6840</phone>
    <email>gpool@vitaltherapies.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 2, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 5, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>liver failure</keyword>
  <keyword>acute liver failure</keyword>
  <keyword>fulminant hepatic failure</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Failure, Acute</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
