<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="159773">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01898494</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>E3311</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-00814</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U10CA021115</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01898494</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Transoral Surgery Followed By Low-Dose or Standard-Dose Radiation Therapy With or Without Chemotherapy in Treating Patients With HPV Positive Stage III-IVA Oropharyngeal Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Randomized Trial of Transoral Surgical Resection Followed by Low-dose or Standard-dose IMRT in Resectable p16+ Locally Advanced Oropharynx Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized phase II trial studies how well transoral surgery followed by low-dose or
      standard-dose radiation therapy works in treating patients with human papilloma virus
      positive stage III-IVA oral cancer. Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays to kill tumor
      cells. Drugs used in chemotherapy work in different ways to stop the growth of tumor cells,
      either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing. Giving radiation therapy with
      chemotherapy may kill any tumor cells that remain after surgery. It is not yet known how
      much extra treatment needs to be given after surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Accrual, risk distribution, and surgical quality will be used to determine the
      feasibility of a prospective multi-institutional study of transoral surgery for human
      papilloma virus positive (HPV+) oropharynx cancer followed by risk-adjusted adjuvant
      therapy.

      II. To assess the oncologic efficacy following transoral resection and adjuvant therapy in
      patients determined to be at &quot;intermediate risk&quot; after surgical excision, the 2-year
      progression free survival (PFS) rate will be examined.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To estimate the patient distribution with various histologic risk features. II. To assess
      and compare early and late toxicities associated with transoral surgery (TOS) and the
      different doses of adjuvant postoperative radiotherapy (PORT).

      III. To evaluate swallowing function before and after TOS and risk-adjusted adjuvant
      therapy.

      IV. To evaluate quality of life (QOL), swallowing perception and performance, voice
      outcomes, and head and neck symptoms.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To correlate tumor TP53 mutation and other associated mutation profile with pathologic
      findings, with PFS and other outcome parameters in patients with resectable HPV-associated
      oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma (OPSCC) after the above treatments.

      II. To evaluate radiation resistance markers, including excision repair cross complementing
      1 (ERCC1) single nucleotide polymorphism and protein expression, and correlate them with
      treatment efficacy.

      III. To investigate the usefulness of biomarkers in predicting progression-free survival and
      biomarkers, including tumor ERCC1, epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR), plasma
      cytokine/chemokines, cellular immunity to HPV, and oral HPV deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA).

      OUTLINE: Patients are classified by risk status (low risk, intermediate risk, or high risk)
      and assigned to the appropriate treatment group. Patients classified as intermediate risk
      are randomized to 1 or 2 treatment arms.

      ARM A (low risk): Patients undergo transoral surgical resection of the oropharyngeal tumor.

      ARM B (intermediate risk): Patients undergo transoral surgical resection of the
      oropharyngeal tumor. Patients then undergo low-dose intensity modulated radiation therapy
      (IMRT) once daily (QD) five days a week for 5 weeks.

      ARM C (intermediate risk): Patients undergo transoral surgical resection of the
      oropharyngeal tumor. Patients then undergo standard-dose IMRT QD five days a week for 6
      weeks.

      ARM D (high risk): Patients undergo transoral surgical resection of the oropharyngeal tumor.
      Patients then undergo standard-dose IMRT QD five days a week for 6-7 weeks. Patients also
      receive cisplatin intravenously (IV) over 30 minutes or carboplatin IV over 30 minutes on
      days 1, 8, 15, 22, 29, 36, and 43 during radiation therapy.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 3 months for 3 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PFS rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Defined as the proportion of patients alive and progression-free at 24 months. Kaplan-Meier estimates will be calculated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Accrual rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Risk distribution</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A 90% binomial confidence interval will be estimated for the percentage of patients in each risk group.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Grade 3-4 bleeding events during surgery and positive margins after surgery, graded according to the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE) version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The percentage will be deemed too high if 13 or more patients reported with grade 3-4 bleeding in the operating room or with positive margins, which corresponds to an empirical rate of 22%. A 90% binomial confidence interval will be estimated for these events.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity evaluated using the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The difference between arms will be evaluated using Fisher's exact test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from registration onto the study until death from any cause, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Kaplan-Meier estimates will be calculated, along with their corresponding 95% confidence intervals. The median, 1-year, and 2-year survival rates will be estimated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Swallowing function before and after treatment, evaluated using the modified barium swallow (MBS) ratings</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in patient reported quality of life (QOL) as measured by Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-Head and Neck (FACT-H&amp;N)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 6 months post radiation therapy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient QOL will be grouped as &quot;improved&quot; (change &gt;= 7 points, 6 mo post-RT vs. baseline), &quot;worsened&quot; (change =&lt; -7 points) and &quot;stable&quot; (-6 =&lt; change =&lt; 6).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">377</enrollment>
  <condition>Human Papilloma Virus Infection</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Oropharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Oropharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Oropharynx</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (TOS)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo transoral surgical resection of the oropharyngeal tumor.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (TOS, low-dose IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo transoral surgical resection of the oropharyngeal tumor. Patients then undergo low-dose IMRT QD five days a week for 5 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm C (TOS, standard-dose IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo transoral surgical resection of the oropharyngeal tumor. Patients then undergo standard-dose IMRT QD five days a week for 6 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm D (TOS, standard-dose IMRT, chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo transoral surgical resection of the oropharyngeal tumor. Patients then undergo standard-dose IMRT QD five days a week for 6-7 weeks. Patients also receive cisplatin IV over 30 minutes or carboplatin IV over 30 minutes on days 1, 8, 15, 22, 29, 36, and 43 during radiation therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>therapeutic conventional surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo transoral surgical resection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (TOS)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (TOS, low-dose IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm C (TOS, standard-dose IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm D (TOS, standard-dose IMRT, chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>intensity-modulated radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo low-dose IMRT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (TOS, low-dose IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IMRT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cisplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm D (TOS, standard-dose IMRT, chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CACP</other_name>
    <other_name>CDDP</other_name>
    <other_name>CPDD</other_name>
    <other_name>DDP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm D (TOS, standard-dose IMRT, chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Carboplat</other_name>
    <other_name>CBDCA</other_name>
    <other_name>JM-8</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplat</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>intensity-modulated radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo standard-dose IMRT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm C (TOS, standard-dose IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm D (TOS, standard-dose IMRT, chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IMRT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (TOS)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (TOS, low-dose IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm C (TOS, standard-dose IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm D (TOS, standard-dose IMRT, chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>quality-of-life assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (TOS)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (TOS, low-dose IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm C (TOS, standard-dose IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm D (TOS, standard-dose IMRT, chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>quality of life assessment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  REGISTRATION TO SURGERY (ARM S)

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1

          -  Patients must have newly diagnosed, histologically or cytologically confirmed
             squamous cell carcinoma or undifferentiated carcinoma of the oropharynx; patients
             must have been determined to have resectable oropharyngeal disease; patients with
             primary tumor or nodal metastasis fixed to the carotid artery, skull base or cervical
             spine are not eligible

          -  Patients must have American Joint Committee on Cancer (AJCC) TNM tumor stage III, IV
             a, or IV b (with no evidence of distant metastases) as determined by imaging studies
             (performed &lt; 4 weeks prior to pre-registration) and complete head and neck exam; the
             following imaging is required: computed tomography (CT) scan with IV contrast or
             magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)

          -  Primary: patients must have measurable disease of the primary by both clinical and
             radiographic methods; to meet this criteria, a lesion must be &gt; 2 cm in at least one
             dimension by clinical exam AND by radiographic exam with CT or MRI; if radiographic
             exam utilizes spiral CT, lesion must be &gt; 1cm in at least one dimension; Nodes:
             although it is required that patients must have nodal stage beyond N0 confirmed by
             clinical or radiographic methods, measurable nodal disease is not required

          -  Carcinoma of the oropharynx associated with HPV as determined by p16 protein
             expression using immunohistochemistry (IHC) performed by a Clinical Laboratory
             Improvement Amendments (CLIA) approved laboratory; using p16 antibody obtained from
             Roche mtm laboratories AG (CINtec, clone E6H4) is recommended

          -  No prior radiation above the clavicles

          -  Patients with a history of a curatively treated malignancy must be disease-free for
             at least two years except for carcinoma in situ of cervix and/or non-melanomatous
             skin cancer

          -  Patients with the following within the last 6 months prior to pre-registration must
             be evaluated by a cardiologist and/or neurologist prior to entry into the study

          -  Patients must not have evidence of extensive or &quot;matted/fixed&quot; pathologic adenopathy
             on preoperative imaging

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1,500/mm^3

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100,000/mm^3

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; the upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Calculated creatinine clearance must be &gt; 60 ml/min using the Cockcroft-Gault formula

          -  Women must not be pregnant or breast-feeding due to the teratogenicity of
             chemotherapy; all females of childbearing potential must have a blood test or urine
             study within 2 weeks prior to registration to rule out pregnancy; a female of
             childbearing potential is any woman, regardless of sexual orientation or whether they
             have undergone tubal ligation, who meets the following criteria: 1) has not undergone
             a hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy; or 2) has not been naturally postmenopausal
             for at least 24 consecutive months (i.e., has had menses at any time in the preceding
             24 consecutive months)

          -  Patient must not have an intercurrent illness likely to interfere with protocol
             therapy or prevent surgical resection

          -  Patients must not have uncontrolled diabetes, uncontrolled infection despite
             antibiotics or uncontrolled hypertension within 30 days prior to pre-registration

          -  REGISTRATION/RANDOMIZATION TO STEP 2 - ARMS A, B, C AND D AND REGISTRATION TO STEP 3

          -  Histopathologic assessment of surgical pathology must include examination for
             perineural invasion (PNI) and lymphovascular invasion (LVI) and reported as absent or
             present; the absence or presence of extracapsular spread (ECS) requires gross and
             microscopic assessment and is defined to be:

               -  Absent (negative or nodal metastasis with smooth/rounded leading edge confined
                  to thickened capsule/pseudocapsule),

               -  Present - minimal (tumor extends &lt; 1 mm beyond the lymph node capsule), or

               -  Present - extensive (gross, tumor extends &gt; 1 mm beyond the lymph node capsule
                  (includes soft tissue metastasis)

          -  Patients must have ECOG performance status 0 or 1

          -  Patient must be registered/randomized within 5-7 weeks following surgery

          -  Women of childbearing potential and sexually active males are strongly advised to use
             an accepted and effective method of contraception
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Ferris</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 10, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 10, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Papilloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Virus Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oropharyngeal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Warts</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Papillomavirus Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
