<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="65498">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01972438</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130206</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-EI-0206</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01972438</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Randomized, Controlled, Double-masked, Clinical Trial of Autologous Serum Eye Drops for Severe Ocular Chronic Graft-versus-host Disease (GVHD) in Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant (HSCT) Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Controlled, Double-Masked, Clinical Trial of Autologous Serum Eye Drops for Severe Ocular Chronic Graft-versus-Host Disease (GVHD) in Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant (HSCT) Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objective: A common, serious and debilitating long term complication of hematopoietic stem
      cell transplant (HCST) is chronic graft-versus-host disease (GVHD). Ocular GVHD develops in
      up to 85% of patients with chronic GVHD. It is characterized by progressive keratitis sicca
      and cicatrizing ocular inflammatory surface disease with T cell mediated damage to
      conjunctival and corneal epithelium and lacrimal tissue. Various medical and surgical
      treatments have been used, such as various lubricating agents, steroid drops and ointments,
      cyclosporin drops, punctal plugs or cautery and partial tarsorrhaphy. However, in severe
      cases, none offer acceptable, long-lasting relief from pain, irritation, dryness and
      diminished vision associated with ocular GVHD. An alternative treatment that has previously
      been safely investigated is autologous serum eye drops (ASEDs). The objective of this study
      is to determine whether ASEDs are more effective than control (normal saline) in the
      treatment of severe chronic ocular GVHD in HSCT patients unresponsive to standard medical
      treatment.

      Study Population: Thirty-four (34) post-HSCT patients with severe ocular GVHD unresponsive
      to standard medical treatment will be initially enrolled. Up to an additional 10
      participants may be enrolled to account for participants who withdraw from the study prior
      to reaching Month 3.

      Design: This is a Phase 2, randomized, double-masked, controlled, crossover, single-center
      study to investigate ASEDs in participants with severe chronic ocular GVHD. During the
      initial crossover phase of the study, participants will participate in a two-period,
      six-month, crossover study in which participants will be randomized to one of two treatment
      sequence groups. The two groups are: 1) daily administration of ASEDs for the first three
      months and then crossover to control (normal saline) eye drops beginning at Month 3 through
      Month 6, or 2) daily administration of control (normal saline) eye drops for the first three
      months and then crossover to ASEDs beginning at Month 3 through Month 6. Participants in
      both groups will apply the assigned drops four times per day in both eyes for six months, as
      well as maintain their current standard ocular GVHD therapy. Following the initial crossover
      phase, beginning at the Month 6 visit, participants will be provided ASEDs as open-label
      treatment on an as-needed basis until study completion. Participants and investigators will
      remain masked to the masked treatment sequence group assignments. During the first year,
      required clinic visits will occur at Baseline, Months 3, 6 and 12 with required telephone
      follow-up visits at Months 7 and 9. Following the Month 12 visit, participants will be
      evaluated every six months, alternating telephone follow-up visits with clinic visits, until
      the last enrolled participant reaches his/her Month 12 visit. At the baseline visit and as
      needed thereafter, all participants will supply blood for the preparation of the ASEDs.

      Outcome Measures: The primary outcome is the proportion of participants experiencing a

      greater than or equal to 50% reduction in the combined score of the modified Oxford punctate
      keratopathy grading and the NIH/NEI visual analogue scale in the study eye from baseline to
      Month 3. A greater than or equal to 50% reduction in the combined score will be considered a
      treatment success. While the design is a crossover study, the primary outcome is assessed
      after the first period at Month 3. Secondary outcomes include changes in the combined score
      of the modified Oxford punctate keratopathy grading and the NIH/NEI visual analogue scale in
      the study eye from baseline to the end of each period, changes in the chronic ocular GVHD
      Composite Assessment Scale (CAS) score, objective testing, subjective testing and global
      chronic GVHD assessments in both eyes. Safety outcomes will be the number and severity of
      systemic and ocular toxicities and adverse events. The number of participants withdrawn from
      the study treatment due to vision loss, adverse events or treatment failure will also
      contribute to the assessment of safety.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective: A common, serious and debilitating long term complication of hematopoietic stem
      cell transplant (HCST) is chronic graft-versus-host disease (GVHD). Ocular GVHD develops in
      up to 85% of patients with chronic GVHD. It is characterized by progressive keratitis sicca
      and cicatrizing ocular inflammatory surface disease with T cell mediated damage to
      conjunctival and corneal epithelium and lacrimal tissue. Various medical and surgical
      treatments have been used, such as various lubricating agents, steroid drops and ointments,
      cyclosporin drops, punctal plugs or cautery and partial tarsorrhaphy. However, in severe
      cases, none offer acceptable, long-lasting relief from pain, irritation, dryness and
      diminished vision associated with ocular GVHD. An alternative treatment that has previously
      been safely investigated is autologous serum eye drops (ASEDs). The objective of this study
      is to determine whether ASEDs are more effective than control (normal saline) in the
      treatment of severe chronic ocular GVHD in HSCT patients unresponsive to standard medical
      treatment.

      Study Population: Thirty-four (34) post-HSCT patients with severe ocular GVHD unresponsive
      to standard medical treatment will be initially enrolled. Up to an additional 10
      participants may be enrolled to account for participants who withdraw from the study prior
      to reaching Month 3.

      Design: This is a Phase 2, randomized, double-masked, controlled, crossover, single-center
      study to investigate ASEDs in participants with severe chronic ocular GVHD. During the
      initial crossover phase of the study, participants will participate in a two-period,
      six-month, crossover study in which participants will be randomized to one of two treatment
      sequence groups. The two groups are: 1) daily administration of ASEDs for the first three
      months and then crossover to control (normal saline) eye drops beginning at Month 3 through
      Month 6, or 2) daily administration of control (normal saline) eye drops for the first three
      months and then crossover to ASEDs beginning at Month 3 through Month 6. Participants in
      both groups will apply the assigned drops four times per day in both eyes for six months, as
      well as maintain their current standard ocular GVHD therapy. Following the initial crossover
      phase, beginning at the Month 6 visit, participants will be provided ASEDs as open-label
      treatment on an as-needed basis until study completion. Participants and investigators will
      remain masked to the masked treatment sequence group assignments. During the first year,
      required clinic visits will occur at Baseline, Months 3, 6 and 12 with required telephone
      follow-up visits at Months 7 and 9. Following the Month 12 visit, participants will be
      evaluated every six months, alternating telephone follow-up visits with clinic visits, until
      the last enrolled participant reaches his/her Month 12 visit. At the baseline visit and as
      needed thereafter, all participants will supply blood for the preparation of the ASEDs.

      Outcome Measures: The primary outcome is the proportion of participants experiencing a

      greater than or equal to 50% reduction in the combined score of the modified Oxford punctate
      keratopathy grading and the NIH/NEI visual analogue scale in the study eye from baseline to
      Month 3. A greater than or equal to 50% reduction in the combined score will be considered a
      treatment success. While the design is a crossover study, the primary outcome is assessed
      after the first period at Month 3. Secondary outcomes include changes in the combined score
      of the modified Oxford punctate keratopathy grading and the NIH/NEI visual analogue scale in
      both eyes from baseline to the end of each period, changes in the chronic ocular GVHD
      Composite Assessment Scale (CAS) score, objective testing, subjective testing and global
      chronic GVHD assessments in both eyes. Safety outcomes will be the number and severity of
      systemic and ocular toxicities and adverse events. The number of participants withdrawn from
      the study treatment due to vision loss, adverse events or treatment failure will also
      contribute to the assessment of safety.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double-Blind, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary outcome is the proportion of participants experiencing a &amp; gt; = 50% reduction in the combined score of the modified Oxford punctate keratopathy grading and the NIH/NEI visual analogue scale in the study eye from baseline to Mont...</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">44</enrollment>
  <condition>Graft vs Host Disease</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Autologous Serum Eye Drops</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. Participant must be 18 years of age or older.

               2. Participant must understand and sign the protocol   s informed consent document.

               3. Participant must have severe ocular GVHD with the following characteristics in
                  the study eye:

                    1. Combined score of modified Oxford punctate keratopathy grading and NIH/NEI
                       visual analogue scale of greater than or equal to 4, and

                    2. Composite assessment scale score of greater than or equal 3, and

                    3. Schirmer   s tear test without anesthesia of less than or equal to 5 mm,
                       and

                    4. Not responsive to standard medical treatment for at least three months
                       prior to randomization. Standard medical treatment includes cyclosporine
                       (Restasis[R]) ophthalmic emulsion (if tolerated), steroid drops (unless
                       contraindicated), lubricating drops and ointments.

               4. Participant is enrolled in an NIH study at the NCI or NHLBI.

               5. Participant is willing and able to supply an adequate amount of blood to create
                  the ASEDs.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Participant is unable to comply with study procedures or follow-up visits.

          2. Participant has a confirmed-positive serologic and/or molecular test for HIV-1/2,

             HTLV-I/II, HBV or HCV.

          3. Participant has GVHD proliferative keratopathy, uveitis or GVHD retinopathy in either
             eye.

          4. Participant has an active ocular infection in either eye.

          5. Participant has an allergy to dilating or anesthetic eye drops.

          6. Participant has used Boston Scleral Lens (or similar lenses) in either eye or has
             used ASEDs in either eye within the past two months. Participants who have used the
             Boston Scleral Lens (or similar lenses) or ASEDs in either eye who did not respond to
             treatment and have stopped using them for at least two months are eligible.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Manuel B Datiles, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Eye Institute (NEI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Angel H Garced, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-5847</phone>
    <email>garceda@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Manuel B Datiles, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 594-7052</phone>
    <email>datilesm@nei.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-EI-0206.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Filipovich AH, Weisdorf D, Pavletic S, Socie G, Wingard JR, Lee SJ, Martin P, Chien J, Przepiorka D, Couriel D, Cowen EW, Dinndorf P, Farrell A, Hartzman R, Henslee-Downey J, Jacobsohn D, McDonald G, Mittleman B, Rizzo JD, Robinson M, Schubert M, Schultz K, Shulman H, Turner M, Vogelsang G, Flowers ME. National Institutes of Health consensus development project on criteria for clinical trials in chronic graft-versus-host disease: I. Diagnosis and staging working group report. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant. 2005 Dec;11(12):945-56.</citation>
    <PMID>16338616</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yamada C, King KE, Ness PM. Autologous serum eyedrops: literature review and implications for transfusion medicine specialists. Transfusion. 2008 Jun;48(6):1245-55. doi: 10.1111/j.1537-2995.2008.01665.x. Epub 2008 Apr 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18410252</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bron AJ, Evans VE, Smith JA. Grading of corneal and conjunctival staining in the context of other dry eye tests. Cornea. 2003 Oct;22(7):640-50. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14508260</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 23, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Graft Versus Host Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Graft vs Host Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Tetrahydrozoline</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
