<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1512">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01918800</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>F7777-R</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01918800</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Randomized Trial of Two Formal Group Programs for Multiple Sclerosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Trial of a Formal Group Program for Fatigue in Multiple Sclerosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oregon Health and Science University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare two different educational programs for people with
      multiple sclerosis (MS), which is a common and often disabling disease of the central
      nervous system. MS causes many symptoms including difficulty walking, loss of balance or
      muscle coordination, fatigue, numbness and tingling and stiffness. The investigators want to
      determine which program is better at helping improve quality of life and MS symptoms. Both
      programs use material from the National Multiple Sclerosis Society (NMSS). Both programs
      include 6 weekly 2-hour class sessions. Up to 600 participants will be enrolled total in 4
      VA sites, with about 150 at each site. There will be 10 study visits, all to occur within 11
      months. These include 1 baseline visit, 6 two-hour class visits, and 3 follow-up data
      collection visits. Participants will be randomly (by chance) assigned to be part of either
      group education program. They will have a 1:1 or 50% chance of being in either program. The
      primary outcome will be the Modified Fatigue Impact Scale. Secondary outcome measures will
      be the Multiple Sclerosis Self-Efficacy Scale and changes in medication usage, physical
      activity level and health-related quality of life.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Treatment of MS-related fatigue represents a significant challenge in providing symptomatic
      therapy for people with MS. In 1998 the MS Council for Clinical Practice Guidelines
      published Fatigue and MS, the first evidence based treatment guideline for MS recommending
      comprehensive treatment for fatigue. This guideline is widely distributed, but does not
      include a program for implementation. Fatigue: Take Control, is the first formal program
      modeled on the MS fatigue guidelines. This proposal entails performing a four-center single
      blind intent-to-treat randomized controlled two-arm parallel design trial of Fatigue: Take
      Control with MS participants to accomplish four Specific Aims.

      Specific Aim #1: Demonstrate that Fatigue: Take Control reduces fatigue in people with MS
      who are ambulatory and not depressed at the end of the intervention and at three and six
      months after the intervention compared to a general MS group education program. The primary
      outcome measure will be the Modified Fatigue Impact Scale (MFIS) chosen for its
      multi-dimensional nature, recommended use in the Fatigue and MS guideline and sensitivity to
      change in the pilot study.

      Specific Aim #2: Demonstrate that Fatigue: Take Control increases self-efficacy in people
      with MS who are ambulatory and not severely depressed. Fatigue affects a person's sense of
      control over his/her life. We will use the MS Self Efficacy Scale (MSSE) for this secondary
      objective. This measure also demonstrated improvement in the pilot study.

      Specific Aim #3: Demonstrate that Fatigue: Take Control results in changes in medication
      utilization, exercise participation, sleep and health-related quality of life in people with
      MS who are ambulatory and not depressed. Fatigue affects body functions/structure, activity
      and participation in all aspects of daily life. Fatigue: Take Control emphasizes the
      importance of medication optimization for managing all MS symptoms and regular exercise
      participation.

      Recognizing that treatment of MS-related fatigue is complex, Fatigue: Take Control was
      created to provide a framework for people with MS to learn about their fatigue and empower
      them with knowledge to take steps toward self-management in partnership with their
      healthcare providers. It specifically addresses management of all the secondary causes of
      fatigue as well as accepted principles such as employing energy conservation strategies to
      manage primary MS fatigue. It was not designed to identify which single treatment should be
      emphasized for a given participant, but rather to enable individuals to identify those areas
      most applicable to themselves and implement those identified behavioral and lifestyle
      changes. A basic premise of the program is that information on all aspects of MS fatigue
      will allow each individual to find those areas most helpful to their situation and make the
      necessary changes or request appropriate referrals to other healthcare providers, such as a
      physical therapist to help manage difficulty walking and falling. Fatigue: Take Control was
      created with the expectation that fatigue can be reduced by guiding individuals to make the
      environmental, behavioral and lifestyle changes necessary to manage MS fatigue.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor)</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Modified Fatigue Impact Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The self-report, retrospective MFIS measures fatigue symptoms. The full-length MFIS consists of 21 items scored 0-4 for a total score between 0 and 84 and has a coefficient alpha of .81. The MFIS provides a total score and scores for each of three subscales (physical, cognitive and psychosocial) and lower scores on the MFIS and its subscales indicate less fatigue. This is the primary outcome measure for the proposed study and is widely used to assess fatigue in MS.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Multiple Sclerosis Self Efficacy Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The self-report, retrospective MSSE is an 18-item scale of self-efficacy specifically designed for MS patients. This easy to use self-report measure demonstrates internal consistency estimates of about .89 for the full scale and a .75 test-retest correlation. Higher scores on the MSSE indicate higher self-efficacy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SF-36 Health Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The SF-36 is a widely used generic health survey designed to capture practical, reliable, and valid information about functional health and well being from the patient's point of view. Internal consistency was .92 for all items. Cronbach's alpha was .87 in a Turkish study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rapid Assessment of Physical Activity (RAPA)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The self-report, retrospective Rapid Assessment of Physical Activity (RAPA) was developed to provide an easily administered and interpreted means of assessing levels of physical activity. It consists of a nine-item questionnaire assessing strength, flexibility, and level and intensity of physical activity was developed. The RAPA is an easy-to-use, valid measure of physical activity for use in clinical practice with older adults.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) is a self-rated questionnaire which assesses sleep quality and disturbances over a l-month time interval. Nineteen individual items generate seven &quot;component&quot; scores: subjective sleep quality, sleep latency, sleep duration, habitual sleep efficiency, sleep disturbances, use of sleeping medication, and daytime dysfunction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Timed 25 foot walk (T25FW)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The time to walk 8 meters or 25 feet is strongly related to its ordinal counterpart the Ambulation Index (Spearman r = 0.91), without the variability that the ordinal scale reflects. T25-FW will be used in this study to measure ambulation status and as an additional measure of mobility.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beck Depression Inventory II (BDI-II)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The self-report, retrospective BDI-II is a validated 21-item self-report measure of depression widely used in MS studies . Each item is scored between 0 and 3. It is reported to have good reliability (Cronbach's alpha of .81) and validity. Assessing for depression is part of the inclusion/exclusion criteria. Excluding subjects with severe depression is necessary to avoid confounding effects of fatigue and depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">600</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fatigue: Take Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fatigue: Take Control, is the first formal education program modeled on the MS-related fatigue guideline</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MS: Take Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>MS: Take Control includes topics of interest to people with MS other than fatigue.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fatigue: Take control</intervention_name>
    <description>Fatigue: Take Control, is the first formal education program modeled on the MS-related fatigue guideline</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fatigue: Take Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MS: Take Control</intervention_name>
    <description>MS: Take Control includes topics of interest to people with MS other than fatigue.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MS: Take Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  A diagnosis of MS by 2010 updated McDonald Criteria

          -  At least 18 years of age

          -  Able to walk 60 feet without human assistance or architectural support (walls) but
             with any personal assistive device (cane, crutches, walker) (EDSS-S of 6.5 or less at
             Visit 1)

          -  Fluent in written and spoken English, as educational intervention and questionnaires
             have not been validated in languages other than English.

          -  Score of greater than 25 on MFIS indicating MS-related fatigue

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Severe depression (score on the Beck Depression Inventory II greater than 28)

          -  Current substance abuse disorder or psychosis

          -  Any significant uncontrolled medical problem that would limit participation or
             completion of the study

          -  MS relapse within the 30 days before screening

          -  Initiation of new disease modifying treatment within 3 months prior to start of study
             or participating in an interventional research study

          -  Current or prior participation in a fatigue management program

          -  Pregnant women
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dennis N. Bourdette, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Portland VA Medical Center, Portland, OR</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lucinda Hugos, MS</last_name>
    <phone>(503) 220-8262</phone>
    <phone_ext>52338</phone_ext>
    <email>cinda.hugos@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kristina Wick, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>(503) 220-8262</phone>
    <phone_ext>51717</phone_ext>
    <email>kristina.wick@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>North Florida/South Georgia Veterans Health System, Gainesville, FL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32608</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Toni Chiara</last_name>
      <email>toni.chiara@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baltimore VA Medical Center VA Maryland Health Care System, Baltimore, MD</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amy Kunce</last_name>
      <email>amy.kunce@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Portland VA Medical Center, Portland, OR</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lucinda Hugos, MS</last_name>
      <phone>503-220-8262</phone>
      <phone_ext>52338</phone_ext>
      <email>cinda.hugos@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kristina Wick, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>(503) 220-8262</phone>
      <phone_ext>51717</phone_ext>
      <email>kristina.wick@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dennis N. Bourdette, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Puget Sound Health Care System Seattle Division, Seattle, WA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alicia Sloan</last_name>
      <email>alicia.sloan@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 5, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>fatigue</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>self management</keyword>
  <keyword>energy effectiveness</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
