<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="3202">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01947101</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-30591</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>FMT- Ulcerative Colitis</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01947101</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fecal Microbiota Transplantation (FMT) for Treatment of Ulcerative Colitis in Children</brief_title>
  <acronym>FMT</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of Fecal Microbiota Transplantation (FMT) in Immunomodulator Dependent Pediatric Ulcerative Colitis (UC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Baylor College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Baylor College of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients diagnosed with ulcerative colitis (UC), a specific type of inflammatory bowel
      disease, will be invited to take part in this study. The investigators do not know what
      causes UC. However, the microbes (such as bacteria and viruses), which normally live in our
      intestines are thought to play an important role in the development of UC. There are many
      treatment options for UC such as steroids,and other medications that decrease inflammation.
      However, none of these can cure the disease.

      This study aims to treat pediatric UC in an alternative fashion by changing the microbes in
      the gut by giving the participant's stool specimens from healthy adult individuals. There is
      some evidence from a few cases of adult UC that this therapy may cure the disease or at
      least provide long lasting suppression (remission) of the symptoms. The investigators would
      like to test this therapeutic intervention in children with UC.

      The purpose of this study is to (1) examine the microbiome of stool and colon (2) and to
      determine whether healthy-donated stool enemas can treat pediatric ulcerative colitis. (3)
      The investigators will also study the effects of the treatment on colonic gene expression.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      FMT RECIPIENTS:

      Participants will be recruited from the patient population treated by the Pediatric
      Gastroenterology, Hepatology, and Nutrition Section at Baylor College of Medicine/Texas
      Children's Hospital.

      I. Activities prior to starting FMT therapy:

        1. Participants will be asked to discontinue or taper their current home medications for
           ulcerative colitis.

        2. Participants will be asked to complete enema training.

        3. The participant and family will be counseled in case emergency surgical and/or
           intensive care interventions are required.

        4. Survey Completion to assess clinical symptoms.

      II. Initiation of FMT Therapy:

        1. Pre-colonoscopy and FMT therapy preparation:

           One to two days prior to scheduled colonoscopy the study participant will be asked to
           provide a stool sample. They will also undergo a bowel clean-out with Miralax for
           colonoscopy preparation. Colonoscopy (endoscopic examination of the large bowel) will
           be used to deliver the first donor fecal transplant at the beginning of the therapeutic
           protocol.

        2. FMT treatment and Initial colonoscopy:

      Fecal microbiota transplantation is made possible by utilizing a donor (healthy adult)
      providing their stool sample. The donor's stool will be screened and tested for known
      disease-causing agents including viruses, bacteria and parasites to prevent spread of
      disease to the participant.

      On the first day of treatment, the participant will undergo a colonoscopy to deliver the
      filtered donor stool directly into their colon. Additionally, biopsies will be taken during
      this procedure for routine diagnostic as well as research purposes.

      III. Subsequent FMT treatments:

      Enemas will be given periodically to complete a total of 1-year therapy.

      IV. Follow-up endoscopy and samples:

      A similar but more limited procedure (sigmoidoscopy) will be repeated at 14 weeks into the
      study period. Biopsies will be taken during this procedure for routine diagnostic as well as
      research purposes.

      FMT DONORS:

      Potential healthy adult stool donors (between 18 and 45 years of age) will be recruited by
      the research staff. They will be asked to volunteer for the screening and regularly supply
      stool samples according to the study protocol.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess safety of FMT treatment by recording the frequency of adverse events.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the safety and associated toxicities of serial FMTs in pediatric UC following withdrawal from standard therapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess efficacy of FMT treatment with the aid of the Pediatric Ulcerative Colitis Activity (PUCAI) Index, a validated measure of clinical disease severity.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To preliminarily assess the efficacy of FMT in inducing or maintaining clinical remission of UC.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Ulcerative Colitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ulcerative Colitis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fecal Microbiota Transplant</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fecal Microbiota Transplant</intervention_name>
    <description>Fecal Microbiota Transplant will be endoscopically administered directly into the colon. Consecutive treatments will be given by rectal enema route.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ulcerative Colitis</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>stool transplant</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Patient Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have a diagnosis of ulcerative colitis based on clinical symptoms, as
             well as laboratory and colonoscopic findings, including histopathologic results of
             the intestinal mucosa.

          -  Pediatric Ulcerative Colitis Activity Index (PUCAI) &lt; 35 [mild activity] as assessed
             within 4 weeks prior to enrollment and clinical symptoms that are at least stable.

          -  Patients must be &quot;immunomodulator dependent,&quot; i.e., have a history of steroid
             dependency (lack of clinical remission for over 8 weeks without steroid therapy),
             and/or being immunomodulator (azathioprine, 6-mercaptopurine, methotrexate, etc.)
             treated, and/or biologic agent (infliximab, adalimumab, etc.) treated

          -  Patients ≥ 12 and &lt; 21 years of age are eligible for this trial.

          -  Patients must be willing to be off current UC therapies.

          -  Willingness to undergo a surgical consultation prior to FMT treatment.

          -  Patients who are not enema trained will be required to undergo enema training prior
             to the start of FMT treatment.

          -  All patients and/or their parents or legally authorized representatives must sign a
             written informed consent document. Assent, when appropriate, will be obtained
             according to institutional guidelines.

        Patient Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who are known to have the following will be excluded:

               1. Decompensated liver cirrhosis (bleeding varices, ascites, encephalopathy or
                  icterus)

               2. Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)/acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS)

               3. Bone marrow transplantation within the past 150 days

               4. Other severe immunodeficiency

          -  Patients with severe prior allergic reaction to food will be excluded from the
             protocol.

          -  Patients who are pregnant or lactating will be excluded from the protocol.

        Donor Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ≥ 18 years and &lt; 45 years

          -  Willing to provide stool and blood samples for laboratory testing.

          -  Body mass index &lt; 30

          -  Willing to fill out a detailed health screening questionnaire
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>20 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard Kellermayer, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine/Texas Children's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Richard Kellermayer, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-798-0319</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Texas Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard Kellermayer, MD</last_name>
      <phone>713-798-0319</phone>
      <email>kellerma@bcm.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Dora Nagy-Szakal, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>713-798-0315</phone>
      <email>nagyszak@bcm.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Richard Kellermayer, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.texaschildrens.org/Locate/Doctors/Kellermayer,-Richard/</url>
    <description>Physician Profile</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 23, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 13, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Richard Kellermayer</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stool transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>Ulcerative Colitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Fecal transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammatory Bowel Disease</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Colitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colitis, Ulcerative</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
