<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="14957">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01906008</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013-0323</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01906008</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase II Study of Minocycline for Reducing Symptom Burden in Colorectal Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Study of Minocycline for Reducing Symptom Burden in Patients With Colorectal Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>American Cancer Society, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn if minocycline can reduce numbness,
      pain, and/or loss of motor function in patients with colorectal cancer.  In this study,
      minocycline will be compared to a placebo.

      The study doctor can explain how the study drug is designed to work.

      A placebo is not a drug.  It looks like the study drug, but it is not designed to treat any
      disease or illness.  It is designed to be compared with a study drug to learn if the study
      drug has any real effect.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Nearly 40% of patients with colorectal cancer who receive oxaliplatin-based chemotherapy
      experience neuropathy (nerve damage that can include numbness, pain, and/or loss of motor
      function). Sometimes, this nerve damage is serious enough that the chemotherapy dose has to
      be lowered or stopped completely.  Researchers want to find out if taking minocycline can
      lower the side effects caused by chemotherapy given to treat colorectal cancer.

      Study Groups:

      If you agree to take part in this study, you will be randomly assigned (as in the flip of a
      coin) to 1 of 2 groups.  You will have an equal chance of being in either group:

        -  If you are in Group 1, you will take a placebo.

        -  If you are in Group 2, you will take minocycline.

      Neither you nor the study staff will know if you are receiving the study drug or the
      placebo.  However, if needed for your safety, the study staff will be able to find out what
      you are receiving.

      Study Drug Administration:

      Starting on Day 1 of Cycle 1 of chemotherapy, you will start taking the study drug/placebo
      capsule by mouth, twice a day every day.

      You should take the study drug/placebo with a full glass (8 ounces) of water.  You may take
      it with or without food, but if it causes an upset stomach, you should take it with food.

      You should not lie down for at least 30 minutes after taking the study drug/placebo to
      reduce the risk of side effects.

      Study Visits:

      Before you start taking the study drug/placebo:

        -  You will complete 4 questionnaires about pain and other symptoms, and your quality of
           life.  You will also complete a questionnaire about your tobacco history.  It should
           take about 15-25 minutes to complete all questionnaires.

        -  You may complete a sensory test.  For this test, researchers will try to find out how
           sensitive you are to touching things such as small bumps on a board.  This test will
           take about 10 minutes to complete.

        -  Blood (about 6 teaspoons) will be drawn to test for markers of inflammation.  Markers
           of inflammation are found in the blood and may be related to your symptoms.

           1 time each week:

        -  You will complete a questionnaire in the clinic or by telephone about any symptoms you
           may be having and how they may be affecting your daily activities.  The questionnaire
           should take about 3-5 minutes to complete each time.

      At each chemotherapy cycle:

      -You will fill out 2 questionnaires about pain and other symptoms.  It should take about
      10-15 minutes to complete the questionnaires.

      At about 2 months:

        -  Blood (about 6 teaspoons) will be drawn to test for markers of inflammation.

        -  You may complete a sensory test.  This test will take about 10 minutes to complete.

        -  You must bring the study drug/placebo container (along with any remaining
           drug/placebo).  The study staff will count the number of pills that you took so far.

      End-of-Treatment Visit:

      At about 4 months, you will return to the clinic.  The following tests and procedures will
      be performed:

        -  You will fill out the 4 questionnaires about your symptoms.  It should take about 15-20
           minutes to complete all of the questionnaires.

        -  Blood (about 6 teaspoons) will be drawn to test for markers of inflammation.

        -  You may complete a sensory test. This test will take about 10 minutes to complete.

        -  You must bring the study drug/placebo container (along with any remaining
           drug/placebo).  The study staff will count the number of pills that you took so far.

      Length of Study:

      You may continue taking the study drug/placebo for up to 4 months, if there are no treatment
      delays.  You will no longer be able to take the study drug if the disease gets worse, if
      intolerable side effects occur, or if you are unable to follow study directions.

      Your participation in the study will be over at the End-of-Study visit.

      End-of-Study Visit:

      At about 6 months, you will return to the clinic.  The following tests and procedures will
      be performed:

        -  You will fill out 4 questionnaires about pain and other symptoms and your quality of
           life.  You will also complete a questionnaire about your tobacco history.  It should
           take about 15-25 minutes to complete all of the questionnaires.

        -  Blood (about 6 teaspoons) will be drawn to test for markers of inflammation.

        -  You may complete a sensory test.  This test will take about 10 minutes to complete.

      This is an investigational study.  Minocycline is FDA approved and commercially available
      for the treatment of bacterial infection.  Its use in this study is investigational.

      Up to 96 participants will be enrolled in this study.  Up to 48 will take part at MD
      Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction of Acute Peripheral Neuropathy During Oxaliplatin-Based Chemotherapy</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary outcome variable is the AUC for numbness/tingling over ~4 months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">96</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Minocycline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group 2 receives minocycline 200 mg orally for the first dose, then 100 mg orally every 12 hours for 4 months beginning at chemotherapy initiation. Completion of questionnaires at baseline, 1 time each week, at each chemo cycle, at end of treatment visit, and at 6 month follow up visit. Sensory test performed at baseline, 2 months, end of treatment visit, and at 6 month follow up visit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group 1 receives a placebo 200 mg orally for the first day of chemotherapy, then 100 mg doses every 12 hours for 4 months beginning at chemotherapy initiation. Completion of questionnaires at baseline, 1 time each week, at each chemo cycle, at end of treatment visit, and at 6 month follow up visit. Sensory test performed at baseline, 2 months, end of treatment visit, and at 6 month follow up visit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Minocycline</intervention_name>
    <description>200 mg by mouth for the first dose, then 100 mg by mouth every 12 hours for 4 months beginning at chemotherapy initiation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Minocycline</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Dynacin</other_name>
    <other_name>Minocin</other_name>
    <other_name>Minocin PAC</other_name>
    <other_name>Myrac</other_name>
    <other_name>Solodyn</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>1 placebo by mouth for the first day of chemotherapy, then 1 dose every 12 hours for 4 months beginning at chemotherapy initiation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaires</intervention_name>
    <description>Completion of questionnaires at baseline, 1 time each week, at each chemo cycle, at end of treatment visit, and at 6 month follow up visit.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Minocycline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Surveys</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sensory Test</intervention_name>
    <description>Sensory test performed at baseline, 2 months, end of treatment visit, and at 6 month follow up visit.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Minocycline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with a pathologically proven diagnosis of CRC being treated either at MD
             Anderson or LBJ.

          2. Patients &gt; or = 18 years old.

          3. Patients who qualify for oxaliplatin-based chemotherapy (in the adjuvant or
             metastatic setting) and expected to receive at least 4 months of oxaliplatin;
             patients must be oxaliplatin naïve.

          4. Patients who speak English or Spanish (due to language options for the MDASI version
             being used in this study, we are only recruiting English-speaking or Spanish-speaking
             patients).

          5. Patients with an NCI-CTCv4 sensory neuropathy score of 0.

          6. Patients with normal renal function according to MD Anderson testing standards and no
             prior renal disease (serum creatinine must be &lt; 1.5 times the upper limit of normal).
             Test results must be no more than 3 months old.

          7. Patients with normal hepatic function according to MD Anderson testing standards and
             no prior liver disease (total bilirubin must be &lt; 2.0 times the upper limit of
             normal; alkaline phosphatase (ALP) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) must be &lt; 3.0
             times the upper limit of normal; aspartate aminotransferase (AST) must be &lt; 3.0 times
             the upper limit of normal). Test results must be no more than 3 months old.

          8. Patients willing and able to review, understand, and provide written consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with resectable metastatic disease for whom metastasectomy is planned within
             4 months.

          2. Patients continuously taking any minocycline within the last 15 days. Patients who
             have conditions that potentially preclude use of minocycline as determined by the
             treating physician.

          3. Patients continuously taking steroids within the last 15 days.

          4. Patients with known chronic inflammatory disorders (for example, systemic lupus
             erythematosus or rheumatoid arthritis).

          5. Patients who are pregnant; the absence of pregnancy will be confirmed by negative
             urine test.

          6. Hypersensitivity to any tetracyclines, or a history of other allergies or drug
             reactions that in the treating physician's judgment make the patient inappropriate
             for this study.

          7. Patients receiving vitamin K antagonist (warfarin).

          8. Patients with a BMI &gt;40 (Obese Class III criteria).

          9. Patients who will receive cetuximab or other targeted therapy where physicians may
             use topical doxycycline to reduce the rash associated with therapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cathy Eng, MD, BA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cathy Eng, MD, BA</last_name>
    <phone>713-745-3470</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>LBJ Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 31, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Colorectal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>CRC</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute peripheral neuropathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Numbness</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Loss of motor function</keyword>
  <keyword>Minocycline</keyword>
  <keyword>Dynacin</keyword>
  <keyword>Minocin</keyword>
  <keyword>Minocin PAC</keyword>
  <keyword>Myrac</keyword>
  <keyword>Solodyn</keyword>
  <keyword>Placebo</keyword>
  <keyword>Questionnaires</keyword>
  <keyword>Surveys</keyword>
  <keyword>Sensory tests</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Minocycline</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
