<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="51896">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01804530</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PLX119-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01804530</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 1 Study of PLX7486 as Single Agent and With Gemcitabine Plus Nab-Paclitaxel in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1 Study to Assess Safety, Pharmacokinetics, and Pharmacodynamics of PLX7486 as a Single Agent and in Combination With Gemcitabine and Nab-Paclitaxel in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Plexxikon</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Plexxikon</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      PLX7486 is a novel small molecule, selective inhibitor of the receptor tyrosine kinases Fms
      and TrkA, TrkB, and TrkC.

      Part 1 of this study will evaluate safety, pharmacokinetics, and pharmacodynamics of PLX7486
      as a single agent in patients with advanced solid tumors.

      Part 2 of this study will evaluate the safety of the triple drug combination of PLX7486-TsOH
      + gemcitabine + nab-paclitaxel in patients with solid tumors, with the primary objective of
      first determining the efficacy of the triple drug combination in (Part 2a) patients with
      solid tumors; and then in (Part 2b) patients with advanced, non-resectable pancreatic
      adenocarcinoma.

      Part 2c of the study will assess the efficacy of single-agent PLX7486 in patients with
      advanced non-resectable tumors of any histology with activating Trk (NTRK) point or NTRK
      fusion mutations (e.g., mammary analogue secretory carcinoma, secretory breast cancer,
      papillary thyroid cancer, congenital fibrosarcoma, congenital mesoblastic nephroma, lung
      cancer, melanoma, and colon cancer), using best overall response (OR) rate, as well as
      safety.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Part 1 of the study is an open-label, sequential PLX7486-TsOH single-agent dose escalation
      in patients with solid tumors.

      Part 2a of the study is also an open-label, sequential dose escalation of PLX7486-TsOH with
      fixed dose levels of nab-paclitaxel + gemcitabine in patients with solid tumors.

      Part 2b is an open-label extension cohort at the recommended phase 2 dose of PLX7486-TsOH in
      combination with fixed dose levels of nab-paclitaxel + gemcitabine in 28-day treatment
      cycles in patients with advanced, non-resectable pancreatic adenocarcinoma.

      Part 2c is an open-label extension cohort of single agent PLX7486-TsOH at the recommended
      phase 2 dose in patients with advanced non-resectable tumors of any histology with
      activating Trk (NTRK) point or NTRK fusion mutations.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of PLX7486 as single agent and in combination with gemcitabine and nab-paclitaxel</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured from baseline and weekly for the duration of drug administration, estimated to be ≤1 year.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Adverse events, physical examinations, vital signs, clinical laboratory tests (hematology, chemistry, and urinalysis), ECGs, ophthalmic examinations, will all be evaluated to determine dose-limiting toxicities, i.e., any adverse event that is temporally related to the study drug administration and is not due to the patient's underlying malignancy and for which there is no clear evidence for an alternative etiology.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient weight</measure>
    <time_frame>measured at each clinic visit for the duration of treatment, estimated to be ≤ 1 year.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in patient weight from baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain intensity</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured daily from baseline for the duration of treatment, estimated to be ≤ 1 year.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in pain reported using the Memorial Pain Assessment Card.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Analgesic consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured weekly from baseline for the duration of treatment, estimated to be ≤ 1 year.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in analgesic requirements will be recorded daily by the patient and measured weekly in morphine-equivalent milligrams.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Karnofsky Performance Status</measure>
    <time_frame>changes from baseline measured weekly for the duration of treatment, estimated to be ≤ 1 year.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in performance status from baseline, determined at each clinic visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of PLX7486</measure>
    <time_frame>first 21-days of drug administration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The pharmacokinetics of PLX7486 will be analyzed by measurement of area under the plasma concentration-time curve [AUC0-t, AUC0-inf], peak concentration (Cmax), time to peak concentration (Tmax), half-life (t1/2), and terminal elimination rate constant (Kel).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor response</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients that have received ≥2 administrations of gemcitabine + nab-paclitaxel and 21 days of PLX7486</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of remission (DOR)</measure>
    <time_frame>From documented initial response (PR or better) to disease progression/relapse, or death</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of complete remission (DOCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of initial response to first documented disease relapse or death.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>number of days from start of therapy to the date of documented disease progression/relapse, or death</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-Free Survival (DFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of the initial CR response to the date of documented disease relapse or death from any cause</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to end of study, estimated to be ≤ 1 year.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">118</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumors</condition>
  <condition>Untreated Pancreatic Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cancer Non-resectable</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Pancreatic Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Tumors of Any Histology With Activating Trk (NTRK) Point or NTRK Fusion Mutations</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Open-label, sequential PLX7486-TsOH single-agent dose escalation in approximately 50 patients with solid tumors.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2a</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Open-label, sequential dose escalation of PLX7486-TsOH with fixed dose levels of nab-paclitaxel + gemcitabine in approximately 30 patients with solid tumors.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2b</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Extension cohort at the RP2D of PLX7486-TsOH in combination with fixed dose levels of nab-paclitaxel + gemcitabine in approximately 50 patients with untreated, advanced, non-resectable or metastatic pancreatic adenocarcinoma.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2c</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Extension cohort of single agent PLX7486-TsOH at the recommended phase 2 dose in patients with advanced non-resectable tumors of any histology with activating Trk (NTRK) point or NTRK fusion mutations in approximately 50 patients.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PLX7486-TsOH</intervention_name>
    <description>Part 1: single-agent dose escalation Part 2a: sequential dose escalation with fixed dose levels nab-paclitaxel + gemcitabine Part 2b: Recommended phase 2 dose with fixed dose levels nab-paclitaxel + gemcitabine Part 2c: Recommended phase 2 dose as single agent</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2a</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2b</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2c</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>tosylate salt of PLX7486</other_name>
    <other_name>selective inhibitor for receptor tyrosine kinase Fms</other_name>
    <other_name>selective inhibitor for receptor tyrosine kinases TrkA,B,&amp; C</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>gemcitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Part 2a and 2b: 100 mg/m2 IV over 30-60 minutes on days 1, 8, and 15 of each 28-day cycle within 30 minutes after the nab-paclitaxel infusion.
Gemcitabine prophylaxis medications per institutional standard practice.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2a</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2b</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>nucleoside analog</other_name>
    <other_name>marketed as Gemzar, Eli Lilly and Company</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>nab-Paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Part 2a and 2b: 125 mg/m2 administered IV over approximately 30 minutes on days 1, 8, and 15 of each 28-day cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2a</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2b</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Albumin-bound paclitaxel</other_name>
    <other_name>Abraxane</other_name>
    <other_name>paclitaxel bound to albumin nano-particles</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female ≥18 years old

          2. Patients with solid tumors who:

               1. Part 1:  have tumor progression following standard therapy, have
                  treatment-refractory disease, or for whom there is no effective standard of
                  therapy

               2. Part 2a:  have received ≤2 prior chemotherapy regimens for the treatment of
                  their primary malignancy and for whom nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine would be
                  considered a reasonable chemotherapy option

               3. Part 2b:  have previously untreated locally advanced, non-resectable or
                  metastatic pancreatic adenocarcinoma that, in the opinion of the Principal
                  Investigator, are not candidates for FOLFIRINOX treatment (i.e., bolus and
                  infusional leucovorin, 5-fluorouracil, irinotecan, and oxaliplatin). Patients
                  who received prior neoadjuvant or adjuvant therapy with recurrent disease ≥6
                  months following completion of the regimen are also eligible.

               4. Part 2c: have advanced, non-resectable tumors of any histology with activating
                  Trk (NTRK) point or NTRK fusion mutations (e.g., mammary analogue secretory
                  carcinoma, secretory breast cancer, papillary thyroid cancer, congenital
                  fibrosarcoma, congenital mesoblastic nephroma, lung cancer, melanoma, and colon
                  cancer) AND have received prior treatment, if there is a known therapy that
                  results in increased survival for that particular disease (e.g., patients with
                  melanoma should have received treatment with ipilimumab or BRAF inhibitors,
                  patients with colon cancer should have received at least 2 prior lines of
                  therapy with a fluoropyrimidine in combination with oxaliplatin and irinotecan,
                  etc.).

          3. Patients in Part 2b must have measurable disease by RECIST criteria v1.1

          4. Women of child-bearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test within 7 days
             prior to initiation of dosing and must agree to use an acceptable method of birth
             control from the time of the negative pregnancy test up to 3 months after the last
             dose of study drug, Women of non-childbearing potential may be included if they are
             either surgically sterile or have been postmenopausal for ≥1 year. Fertile men must
             also agree to use an acceptable method of birth control while on study drug and up to
             3 months after the last dose of study drug.

          5. All associated toxicity from previous or concurrent cancer therapy must be resolved
             (to ≤ Grade 1 or Baseline) prior to study treatment administration.

          6. Patients with stable, treated brain metastases are eligible for this trial. However,
             patients must not have required steroid treatment for their brain metastases within
             30 days of Screening.

          7. Willing and able to provide written informed consent prior to any study related
             procedures and to comply with all study requirements.

          8. Karnofsky Performance Status ≥70%

          9. Life expectancy ≥3 months.

         10. Adequate hematologic, hepatic, and renal function (absolute neutrophil count ≥1.5 X
             109/L, Hgb &gt;9 g/dL, platelet count ≥100 X 109/L, AST/ALT ≤2.5 X ULN or &lt;5 X ULN in
             the presence of liver metastases, creatinine ≤1.5 X ULN or calculated CrCl &gt;60 mL/min
             using Cockcroft-Gault formula). Note:  patients must not have received RBC
             transfusions (within 4 weeks), platelet transfusions (within 1 week) or growth
             factors (within 1 week).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Other than the primary malignancy, active cancer (either concurrent or within the
             last 3 years) that requires non-surgical therapy (e.g., chemotherapy or radiation
             therapy), with the exception of surgically treated basal or squamous cell carcinoma
             of the skin, melanoma in-situ, or carcinoma in-situ of the cervix.

          2. Chemotherapy within 28 days prior to C1D1

          3. Biological therapy within 28 days prior to C1D1

          4. Radiation therapy within 28 days prior to C1D1

          5. Investigational drug use within 28 days or 5 half-lives, whichever is longer, prior
             to C1D1

          6. Part 1 only:  (a) Patients with active or a history of glucose intolerance or
             diabetes mellitus and (b) Hemoglobin A1c ≥7%.

          7. Part 2a and 2b only:  (a) Patients with a known hypersensitivity to nab-paclitaxel or
             gemcitabine and (b) Hemoglobin A1c &gt;8%.

          8. Part 2a and 2b:  Patients with uncontrolled diabetes. Patients with glucose
             intolerance or diabetes whose blood glucose levels are consistently well-controlled
             with the use of oral hypoglycemic agents and/or insulin are permitted.

          9. Part 2b only:  Patients who have received radiotherapy, surgery, chemotherapy or
             investigational therapy for the treatment of metastatic pancreatic adenocarcinoma.
             Prior treatment with 5-FU or gemcitabine administered as a radiation sensitizer in
             the adjuvant setting is allowed, provided at least 6 months have elapsed since
             completion of the last dose and no lingering toxicities are present. Patients having
             received cytotoxic doses of gemcitabine or any other chemotherapy in the adjuvant
             setting are not eligible for this study.

         10. ≥ Grade 2 sensory neuropathy at baseline

         11. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness (i.e., active infection) or concurrent condition
             that, in the opinion of the Investigator, would interfere with the study endpoints or
             the patient's ability to participate

         12. Refractory nausea and vomiting, malabsorption, or significant small bowel resection
             that, in the opinion of the Investigator, would preclude adequate absorption.

         13. QTcF ≥450 msec (for males) or ≥470 msec (for females) at Screening

         14. The presence of a medical or psychiatric condition that makes the patient
             inappropriate for inclusion in this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Karlin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Plexxikon Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David Karlin, MD</last_name>
    <phone>510-647-4100</phone>
    <email>dkarlin@plexxikon.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sandy Tong, MD</last_name>
    <phone>510-647-4100</phone>
    <email>stong@plexxikon.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Translational Genomics Research Institute (TGen)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85004</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Daniel Von Hoff, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, Los Angeles Medical Center (UCLA)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santa Monica</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90404</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Zev Wainberg, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical Universtiy of South Carolina (MUSC)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29425</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carolyn Britten, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Von Hoff DD, Ramanathan RK, Borad MJ, Laheru DA, Smith LS, Wood TE, Korn RL, Desai N, Trieu V, Iglesias JL, Zhang H, Soon-Shiong P, Shi T, Rajeshkumar NV, Maitra A, Hidalgo M. Gemcitabine plus nab-paclitaxel is an active regimen in patients with advanced pancreatic cancer: a phase I/II trial. J Clin Oncol. 2011 Dec 1;29(34):4548-54. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2011.36.5742. Epub 2011 Oct 3.</citation>
    <PMID>21969517</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 8, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 1, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pancreatic adenocarcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>solid tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>non-resectable pancreatic cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>metastatic pancreatic cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>activating NTRK point or fusion mutations</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Gemcitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
