<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="55209">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01711632</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-200</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01711632</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>BRAF Inhibitor, Vemurafenib, in Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Hairy Cell Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of the BRAF Inhibitor, Vemurafenib, in Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Hairy Cell Leukemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Northwestern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ohio State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Scripps Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>North Shore Long Island Jewish Health System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to find out what effects, good and/or bad, treatment with
      vemurafenib (also known as Zelboraf™) has on the patient and on  leukemia. Specifically, the
      researchers want to know how well vemurafenib eliminates leukemia from the blood.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>efficacy of vemurafenib</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>as assessed by overall response rates after three months of treatment in patients with relapsed or refractory HCL.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity (safety and tolerability)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Toxicity will be graded and recorded using the NCI Common Toxicology Criteria version 4.0.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the pharmacodynamics</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Peripheral blood and/or bone marrow aspirate samples from pretreatment and post-treatment at specified time points will be assessed by Western Blot or by phospho-flow for the downstream targets of BRAF (MEK, pMEK, ERK, pERK) to assess the ontarget effect of the Vemurafenib.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>evaluate biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Reactivation of MAPK pathways: Increased expression of the other RAF isoforms CRAF and ARAF), and MAPK (MAPK8 or COT) will be analyzed by Western Blot and/or real-time PCR39,40. Secondary BRAF mutations (all 18 BRAF exons) and RAS mutations40 will be analyzed by bidirectional Sanger sequencing and by Raindance multiplex PCR and Illumina next generation sequencing, respectively. Activation of RTKs (i.e. PDGFRβ and IGF-IR) will be assessed by Western Blot. Cell Biosciences NanoPro 1000 technology will be used to examine quantitative signaling on the entire MAPK, PI3K and JAK-STAT pathways41.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Hairy Cell Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vemurafenib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Eligible patients will receive vemurafenib at a dose of 960mg orally twice daily (b.i.d.) continuously in cycles of 4 weeks (28 days).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vemurafenib</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive vemurafenib at a dose of 960mg orally b.i.d. continuously in cycles of 4 weeks (28 days) as outpatient. A bone marrow aspirate and/or biopsy will be performed after the first cycle. After the completion of the third cycle, a repeat bone marrow aspirate and/or biopsy will be performed for assessment of response and evaluation of MRD. Patients who achieve CR with MRD or PR may be retreated with vemurafenib for up to 3 additional cycles at the treating physician's discretion. Patients who achieve a CR without MRD will be observed, and will be treated with vemurafenib for up to 3 additional cycles at the time of relapse (either hematologic or by MRD). Patients who are re-treated after observation will follow the treatment/evaluation plan of Cycles 1-3, except the Cycle 1 Week 1-3 research bloods and Cycle 2 Day 1research bone marrow biopsy and/or aspirate. Patients who achieve no response after the initial 3 cycles of vemurafenib will be removed from the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vemurafenib</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ≥ 18 years of age

          -  Histologically confirmed classical HCL with one of the following:

          -  Intolerance to purine analogs

          -  Failure to achieve any response (CR or PR) to the initial purine analog-based therapy

          -  Relapse ≤ 2 years of purine analog-based therapy

          -  ≥ 2 relapses Histologic confirmation of diagnosis will be performed at MSKCC or a
             participating site.

          -  Patients who meet the standard treatment initiation criteria, as defined by ANC ≤1.0,
             Hgb ≤ 10.0 or PLT ≤100K

          -  ECOG performance status of 0-2

          -  Acceptable pre-study organ function during screening as defined as: Total bilirubin ≤
             1.5 times the upper limit of normal (ULN), aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and
             alanine aminotransferase (ALT) ≤ 2.5x ULN, and serum creatinine ≤ 1.5x ULN

          -  Electrocardiogram (ECG) without evidence of clinically significant ventricular
             arrhythmias or ischemia as determined by the investigator and a rate-corrected QT
             interval (QTc, Bazett's formula) of &lt; 480 msec.

          -  For women of childbearing potential, agreement to the use of two acceptable methods
             of contraception, including one barrier method, during the study and for 6 months
             after discontinuation of vemurafenib

          -  For men with female partners of childbearing potential, agreement to use a latex
             condom and to advise their female partner to use an additional method of
             contraception during the study and for 6 months after discontinuation of vemurafenib

          -  Negative serum pregnancy test within 7 days of commencement of treatment in
             premenopausal women.

          -  Agreement not to donate blood or blood products during the study and for at least 6
             months after discontinuation of vemurafenib; for male partners, agreement not to
             donate sperm during the study and for at least 6 months after discontinuation of
             vemurafenib

          -  Ability to understand and willingness to sign a written informed consent document.

          -  Willingness and ability to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plans, laboratory
             tests, and other study procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant or breast-feeding

          -  Have had chemotherapy (including purine analogs, rituximab, and other investigational
             agents) within six weeks prior to entering the study

          -  Major surgery within 4 weeks prior to entering the study

          -  Invasive malignancy within the past 2 years prior to first study drug administration,
             except for adequately treated (with curative intent) basal or squamous cell
             carcinoma, melanoma, in situ carcinoma of the cervix, in situ ductal adenocarcinoma
             of the breast, in situ prostate cancer, or limited stage bladder cancer or other
             cancers from which the patient has been disease-free for at least 2 years

          -  Refractory nausea or vomiting, malabsorption, external biliary shunt, or history of
             any type of gastrointestinal surgery that would preclude adequate absorption of study
             drug

          -  Prior treatment with MEK or BRAF inhibitors

          -  Active HIV, hepatitis B and hepatitis C

          -  Patients with HCL variant (as defined by absence of expression of CD25 or absence of
             BRAF V600E mutation)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jae H. Park, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jae H Park, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212 639-4048</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Martin S. Tallman, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212 639-3842</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Scripps Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Jolla</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92037</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alan Saven, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alan Saven, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robert Stone, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert Stone, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jae Park, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-4048</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Martin S. Tallman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-3842</phone>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jae Park, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Grever, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Grever, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mskcc.org/</url>
    <description>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 26, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 17, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>VEMURAFENIB (PLX4032 or R05185426)</keyword>
  <keyword>BRAF Inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>12-200</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Hairy Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
