<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="121112">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02026271</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ATI001-102</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02026271</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase I Study of Ad-RTS-hIL-12, an Inducible Adenoviral Vector Engineered to Express hIL-12 in the Presence of the Activator Ligand Veledimex in Subjects With Recurrent or Progressive Glioblastoma or Grade III Malignant Gliomas</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of Ad-RTS-hIL-12, an Inducible Adenoviral Vector Engineered to Express hIL-12 in the Presence of the Activator Ligand Veledimex in Subjects With Recurrent or Progressive Glioblastoma or Grade III Malignant Gliomas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ziopharm</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ziopharm</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research study involves two investigational drugs, veledimex, an activator
      ligand(INXN-1001) in combination with an Adenovirus Vector Engineered to Express hIL-12
      (INXN-2001). IL-12 is a protein that may improve the body's natural response to disease by
      enhancing the ability of the immune system to kill tumor cells and may interfere with blood
      flow to the tumor.

      The main purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety and tolerability of tumor
      injections of INXN-2001 given in combination with different doses of veledimex.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of a single intra tumor Ad-RTS-hIL-12 dose (1.0x1012 viral particles) plus escalating oral veledimex doses in subjects with recurrent or progressive glioblastoma or Grade III malignant gliomas</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluation will be based on the incidence, intensity, and type of Adverse Events (AEs). Clinically significant changes in the subjects' physical examinations, vital signs, and ECG evaluations, and clinical manifestations relevant to abnormal laboratory values will be captured as AEs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Veledimex maximum tolerated dose (MTD) when given with a single intra tumor Ad-RTS-hIL-12 dose (1.0x1012 viral particles)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Veledimex pharmacokinetic profile and distribution to the tumor</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Veledimex PK parameters to be determined will include, but are not limited to, the maximum plasma concentration (Cmax), time to maximum plasma concentration (Tmax), half-life (t1/2), area-under-the-concentration versus time curve (AUC), volume of distribution (Vd), and clearance (CL).  Where possible, descriptive statistics of the PK parameters will be provided; individual subject veledimex concentrations, actual sampling times, and PK parameters will be listed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cellular and humoral immune responses elicited by Ad-RTS-hIL-12 and veledimex</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor Objective Response Rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Recurrent Glioblastoma</condition>
  <condition>Progressive Glioblastoma</condition>
  <condition>Grade III Glioma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Veledimex in combination with INXN-2001</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intratumoral injections of INXN-2001 (Ad-RTS-hIL-12) at a constant dose in combination with inter-cohort escalating doses of veledimex (activator ligand).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>INXN-2001</intervention_name>
    <description>approximately 1.0 x 1012 viral particles (vp) per injection
one intratumoral injection of INXN-2001</description>
    <arm_group_label>Veledimex in combination with INXN-2001</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ad-RTS-hIL-12</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>veledimex</intervention_name>
    <description>4 dose cohorts (40mg/day, 80mg/day, 100mg/day, and 120mg/day)
14 oral daily doses of INXN-1001
1 Expansion cohort at a single dose level at or below MTD</description>
    <arm_group_label>Veledimex in combination with INXN-2001</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>INXN-1001</other_name>
    <other_name>Activator Ligand</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Male or female subjects  ≥ 18 and ≤ 75 years of age 2. Provision of written
             informed consent for tumor resection, stereotactic surgery, tumor biopsy, samples
             collection and treatment with investigational products prior to undergoing any study
             specific procedures 3. Histologically confirmed supratentorial glioblastoma or other
             WHO grade III or IV malignant glioma from archival tissue.

             4. Evidence of tumor recurrence/progression by MRI (per Response Assessment in
             Neuro-oncology [RANO] criteria) post standard initial therapy.  Neuropathologic
             confirmation of malignant glioma diagnosis at time of tumor resection from frozen
             tissue.

             5. Previous standard of care anti-tumor treatment including surgery and/or biopsy and
             chemoradiation as per Stupp.  At the time of registration, patients must have
             recovered from the toxic effects of previous treatments as determined by the treating
             physician. The following waiting periods are recommended before Ad-RTS-hIL-12
             injection

             a. Nitrosoureas: 6 weeks b. Other cytotoxic agents: 4 weeks c. Anti-angiogenic agents
             including bevacizumab: 4 weeks d. Targeted agents  including small-molecule tyrosine
             kinase inhibitors: 2 weeks 6. Able to undergo standard MRI scans with contrast agent
             before enrollment and after treatment.

             7. Karnofsky Performance Status  ≥ 70 8. Adequate bone marrow reserves and  liver and
             kidney function, as assessed by the following laboratory requirements:

               1. Hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/L

               2. Lymphocytes &gt; 700/ mm3

               3. Absolute Neutrophil Count ≥ 1500/ mm3

               4. Platelets ≥ 100,000/ mm3

               5. Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 x ULN

               6. AST (SGOT) and ALT (SGPT) ≤ 2.5 x ULN. For subjects with documented liver
                  metastases, ALT and AST ≤ 5 × ULN

               7. Total bilirubin &lt; 1.5 x ULN

               8. International Normalized Ratio (INR) and activated Partial Thromboplastin Time
                  [PTT] within normal institutional limits 9. Male and female subjects must agree
                  to use a highly reliable method of birth control (expected failure rate less
                  than 5% per year) from the screening visit through 28 days after the last
                  veledimex dose. Women of childbearing potential (perimenopausal women must be
                  amenorrheic for at least 12 months to be considered of non-childbearing
                  potential) must have a negative pregnancy test at screening.

                  Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Patients who have received prior cytokine based therapies (e.g. interleukin,
             interferon) are not eligible.  Patients who have participated in previous vaccine
             based clinical trials are eligible to participate.

             2. Radiotherapy &lt; 12 weeks prior to starting first veledimex dose 3. Subjects with
             clinically significant increased intracranial pressure without indication for
             surgical resection as judged by the investigator (e.g., impending herniation),
             uncontrolled seizures, or requirement for immediate palliative treatment   Note: In
             the event that Ad-RTShIL-12 injection is not performed, subject will not continue
             with post resection veledimex dosing.

             4. Known immunosuppressive disease, autoimmune conditions, and /or chronic viral
             infections (e.g., HIV, hepatitis) 5. Use of systemic antibacterials, antifungals or
             antivirals for the treatment of acute clinically significant infection within 2 weeks
             of first veledimex dose. Concomitant therapy for chronic infections is not allowed.
             Subjects must be afebrile prior to Ad-RTS-hIL-12 injection; only prophylactic
             antibiotic use is permitted perioperatively.

             6. Use of enzyme-inducing anti-epileptic drugs (EIAED) within 7 days prior to the
             first veledimex dose.  (Levetiracetam (Keppra) is allowed).

             7. Other concurrent clinically active malignant disease, requiring treatment, with
             the exception of non-melanoma cancers of the skin or carcinoma in-situ of the cervix
             or non-metastatic prostate cancer.

             8. Nursing or pregnant females 9. Prior exposure to veledimex 10. Use of medications
             that induce, inhibit or are substrates of CYP450 3A4 within 7 days prior to the first
             veledimex dose, unless approved by the medical monitor 11. Presence of any
             contra-indication for a neurosurgical procedure 12. Unstable or clinically
             significant concurrent medical condition that would, in the opinion of the
             investigator, jeopardize the safety of a subject and/or their compliance with the
             protocol.  Examples include, but are not limited to, unstable angina, congestive
             heart failure,  myocardial infarction within 2 months of screening, on-going
             maintenance therapy for life-threatening ventricular arrhythmia or uncontrolled
             asthma
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nathan Demars, M.S.</last_name>
    <phone>617-259-1975</phone>
    <email>ndemars@ziopharm.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Georgina Weber, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>617-778-2262</phone>
    <email>gweber@ziopharm.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 23, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 16, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
