<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="107456">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01743963</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>176843</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01743963</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intervention to Increase Screening for Glucocorticoid Induced Diabetes</brief_title>
  <acronym>CDA-GID</acronym>
  <official_title>Intervention to Increase Screening for Glucocorticoid Induced Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Eastern Colorado Health Care System</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Eastern Colorado Health Care System</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Using glucocorticoid induced diabetes (GID) we will conduct a small feasibility randomized
      intervention trial to improve GID management for veterans who are prescribed chronic
      glucocorticoids. Approximately 20 primary care providers (caring for approximately 100
      veterans on chronic steroids) will receive decisional support (automatically-derived orders
      for hemoglobin A1C, to be co-signed by providers).  Approximately 20 providers (caring for
      100 veterans) who did not receive decisional support will serve as the control population.
      We will measure the time from randomization until the provider signs an order for hemoglobin
      A1C for both groups. The trial will be conducted at the VA's Eastern Colorado Health Care
      System (ECHCS) and will last approximately 6 months. After the completion of the trial for
      each provider, we will conduct a brief interview and survey of the participating providers
      to assess the acceptability of decisional support interventions to manage GID [protocol,
      page 1-2].  No patient data (PHI) will be collected by the providers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aim 1: Conduct a single site randomized controlled feasibility trial of a decisional support
      intervention to reduce ADRLLS by improving providers' adherence to GID prevention measures.
      Approximately 20 primary care providers (caring for approximately 100 veterans on chronic
      steroids who have not been screened for diabetes in the last year) will be randomly assigned
      to receive decisional support for GID prevention measures (automatically-derived orders for
      hemoglobin A1C, to be co-signed by providers). These providers will be compared with 20
      providers (caring for 100 veterans not screened for diabetes in the last year) who are
      randomly assigned to not receive decisional support for management of GID (i.e. the control
      group). The trial will be conducted at the VA's Eastern Colorado Health Care System (ECHCS)
      and will last approximately 6 months. Study administration will be coordinated through the
      Colorado Research Award Enhancement Program (Colorado REAP).

      Aim 1a) Procedural Endpoints: As a feasibility trial, this study includes multiple
      procedural endpoints, such as provider participation rates, to assess the viability of the
      intervention, rather than a single primary efficacy outcome measure (for details, pages
      6-7).

      Aim 1b) Preliminary Estimates of Efficacy: We will determine the Delay Interval—the number
      of days from when a provider is randomized until the provider orders the GID prevention
      measure.  Use of this continuous measure will maximize the power of this feasibility study,
      though we will also determine proportions of patients for whom these measures were ordered
      at six months, so that we may estimate the sample size for a subsequent multi-center
      randomized control trial.

      Aim 1c) Post-trial de-briefing: Using structured interviews, we will examine the opinions of
      providers after they have participated in the GID feasibility trial, in order to gather
      additional qualitative data regarding the ADRLL framework and refine the intervention for a
      subsequent randomized controlled trial.  Providers will also complete a brief survey
      assessing their preference for the intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Delay Interval (days from randomization until the provider signs the order for a hgbA1C level).</measure>
    <time_frame>6 MONTHS</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>For follow-up laboratory data within the VA system, adherence will be monitored through prospective accrual of administrative data and review of the medical record.  Results will be reported as the proportion receiving the preventive measure versus time, i.e. with Kaplan-Meier plots. We will then determine the variance of Delay Interval.   For the preliminary measure of efficacy, the Delay Interval will be compared between patients whose providers were assigned to the intervention and patients whose providers did not receive the intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility/Reach/Adoption</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measurements of intervention delivery include recruitment numbers and provider Participation Rates for enrollment and retention. The definition of study feasibility consists of provider enrollment rates &gt;= 50%. Results reported using descriptive statistics (proportions, means, standard deviations, and ranges).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility/Reach/Adoption</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measurements of intervention delivery include the &quot;representativeness&quot; of providers (differences between participants/non-participants). Results reported using descriptive statistics (proportions, means, standard deviations, and ranges).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility/Reach/Adoption</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measurements of intervention delivery include the rationale used by clinicians declining participation. Results reported using descriptive statistics (proportions, means, standard deviations, and ranges).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility/Reach/Adoption</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measurements of intervention delivery include numbers of veterans excluded from the intervention. Results reported using descriptive statistics (proportions, means, standard deviations, and ranges).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Glucocorticoid Induced Diabetes (GID)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Decision Support Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Clinical pharmacists mediated computerized decision support</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Clinicians' typical approach for GID monitoring</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Decision support</intervention_name>
    <description>Clinical pharmacists mediated computerized decision support</description>
    <arm_group_label>Decision Support Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care</intervention_name>
    <description>clinicians typical apporach for GID monitering</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Must be 18-90 years old

          -  Must be served by the ECHCS VA sytem

          -  Must have chronic glucocorticoid exposure (greater than or equal to 90 days of oral
             glucocorticoids)

          -  Eligible providers will consist of those primary care practitioners within the ECHCS
             with at least one patient meeting the above criteria. For each veteran, the primary
             care provider (PCP) will be defined as the patient's current general internal
             medicine or family practice practitioner. In the rare instance in which the patient
             has no PCP within the VA system, the specialist with the greatest number of patient
             encounters during the past 12 months will be eligible for inclusion. For every
             patient, only one provider will be randomized (to avoid multiple exposure to the
             intervention for some patients). The consent procedure is described below.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Veterans who have had a hgbA1C test within the previous 12 months will be excluded.

          -  Providers without eligible patients (described above), will be excluded.

          -  Providers declining to give consent will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Liron Caplan, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Veteran Affairs</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Liron Caplan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 20, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>VA Eastern Colorado Health Care System</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Liron Caplan MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>efficacy</keyword>
  <keyword>glucocorticoid</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Glucocorticoids</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
