<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="63886">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02063737</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRO13120428</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02063737</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>SleepTrackTXT Feasibility and Pilot Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>SleepTrackTXT</acronym>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pittsburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: University of Pittsburgh IRB - and Department of Emergency Medicine School of Medicine</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Aim 1: To determine if real-time assessments of perceived sleepiness and fatigue using
      text-messaging impacts an emergency medicine clinician's Attitudes, Perceived Norms,
      Self-Efficacy, Alertness Habits, Perceived Importance of Fatigue, Knowledge of
      Sleepiness/Fatigue, and Perceptions of Environmental Constraints regarding behaviors that
      can improve alertness during shift work.

      Aim 2: To determine if text-messaging emergency care workers fatigue-reduction strategies in
      real-time at the start and during shift work reduces worker perceived sleepiness and fatigue
      at the end of shift work.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      More than half (55%) of Emergency Medical Services (EMS) shift workers report severe mental
      and physical fatigue while at work,(Patterson et al, 2012) 36% report excessive daytime
      sleepiness,(Pirrallo et al; 2012) and 60% poor sleep quality.(Patterson et al; 2012)
      Sleepiness or fatigue while on duty can result in injuries to EMS workers and medical errors
      for patients.(Patterson et al; 2012) The investigators' recent research shows that odds of
      injury among fatigued EMS workers are 1.9 times higher than non-fatigued workers.(Patterson
      et al; 2012) Additional data show that other emergency workers (e.g., emergency physicians
      and nurses) are vulnerable to sleepiness and fatigue while at work.(Fisman et al; 2007;
      Machi et al; 2012; Thomas et al; 2006; Geiger-Brown et al; 2012).

      There are a number of individual and system factors that influence sleepiness and fatigue
      during shift work for emergency workers. Individual factors include sleep hygiene, medical
      conditions like obstructive sleep apnea, and other factors.(Schaefer et al; 2012; Simon et
      al; 2012) System factors include shift length, patient care intensity, and workload. Many
      factors are modifiable, yet some are more difficult than others to change or control.
      Reducing shift length and customary patterns of shift work, such as 12-hr and 24-hr shifts,
      is not feasible for many employers and shift workers in the emergency medicine care setting.
      In some locations, &gt;80% of EMS workers hold multiple jobs, 40% work more than 16 shifts per
      month, and many accumulate unsafe amounts of overtime in order to make a livable
      wage.(Patterson et al, 2010; Patterson et al, 2012; Bauder 2012) Other shift workers in
      emergency care settings face the same or similar obstacles as do EMS shift workers.

      An objective of this research study is to pilot test real-time assessment of emergency care
      worker sleepiness and fatigue. The investigators seek to determine if text-messaging
      fatigue-reduction strategies to emergency care workers that report a high-level of
      sleepiness or fatigue at the start or during their shift reduces perceived sleepiness or
      fatigue at the end of shift. A long term goal of this research is to determine if this
      innovative text-messaging tool can be used to reduce the likelihood of fatigue-related
      injury among emergency care shift workers.

      Aim 1: To determine if real-time assessments of perceived sleepiness and fatigue using
      text-messaging impacts a worker's Attitudes, Perceived Norms, Self-Efficacy, Alertness
      Habits, Perceived Importance of Fatigue, Knowledge of Sleepiness/Fatigue, and Perceptions of
      Environmental Constraints regarding behaviors that can improve alertness during shift work.

      Rationale: The investigators recognize that emergency care shift workers hold different
      beliefs and attitudes about the risk of sleepiness and fatigue on duty and are at different
      stages of adopting risk-reduction behaviors. Behavioral research shows that modifying one or
      more of these factors can impact future behavior and potentially reduce risk over the long
      term. Approach: The investigators have developed a list of candidate items that
      operationalize the Integrative Model of Behavioral Prediction. The investigators will
      administer these candidate items at baseline and again at the end of the study period to
      assess impact.

      Aim 2: To determine if text-messaging emergency care workers fatigue-reduction strategies in
      real-time at the start and during shift work reduces worker perceived sleepiness and fatigue
      at the end of shift work.

      Approach: At baseline, the investigators will randomly assign 100 emergency care workers to
      one of two groups (the control group or intervention group). The control group (n=50 / 50%)
      will receive standard text-message questions of sleepiness and fatigue at the beginning,
      during, and end of shift. The other 50% (n=50) will be assigned to our intervention group
      and receive the same text-message questions as the control group, as well as additional
      text-messages that include strategies that the investigators hypothesize will lead to a
      reduction in perceived sleepiness or fatigue at the end of shift work. With 100 EMS workers
      (50% intervention / 50% control), the investigators have 80% power to detect a difference
      (effect size of 0.78) in the self-reported fatigue levels reported at the end of shift by
      the control and intervention groups. The investigators will collect data over a 90-day study
      period.

      Eligibility Criteria include:

        1. The study subject must be 18 years of age or older;

        2. The study subject must currently work in the emergency medicine setting as an emergency
           physician, emergency nurse, or EMT / paramedic worker;

        3. The study subject must work shifts as part of your employment in the emergency medicine
           setting;

        4. The study subject must have a cell-phone / smartphone that can receive and send
           text-messages;

        5. The study subject must be willing to take part in a research study where he/she is
           required to send and receive multiple text-messages at the start, during, and end of
           scheduled shift work?
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 0</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Reported Fatigue at end of shift work</measure>
    <time_frame>Study subjects will be followed for 90-days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The study subjects will schedule multiple clinical shifts to work as clinicians. Investigators will assess the primary outcome measure (self-reported fatigue) at the start, during, and end of shift using repeated queries facilitated by text-messaging. The investigators will examine how these self-reported measures change during a shift and over time for a total period of 90 days.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported perceptions of behaviors and beliefs about fatigue and sleepiness during shift work</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and at end of 90-day study period</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will use multiple survey tools to capture a worker's Attitudes, Perceived Norms, Self-Efficacy, Alertness Habits, Perceived Importance of Fatigue, Knowledge of Sleepiness/Fatigue, and Perceptions of Environmental Constraints regarding behaviors that can improve alertness during shift work. We will capture these data at baseline and again at the end of the 90-day study period using cross-sectional survey techniques.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Fatigue</condition>
  <condition>Sleepiness</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group will receive text-message queries at the start, during, and end of shift. These queries will attempt to capture the worker's self-reported sleepiness, fatigue, and occurrence of work-related injury during shift work.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention group will receive the same text-message queries as the control group. In addition, these subjects will receive suggestions (strategies) for reducing fatigue and sleepiness during shift work if they report a high-level of fatigue or sleepiness at the start or during their shift. These subjects will then receive additional text-message queries at the end of their shifts to determine if they adopted a strategy for reducing perceived sleepiness or fatigue.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Text-message strategies</intervention_name>
    <description>If an intervention subject reports a high level of sleepiness or fatigue at the start or during their shift work, these subjects will receive additional text-messages that include strategies (suggestions) for reducing perceived fatigue or sleepiness during shift work. These subjects will also receive an additional text-message at the end of their shift to determine if the subject adopted the strategy suggested and if it helped reduced perceived fatigue or sleepiness.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Are 18 years of age or older;

          2. Currently work in the emergency medicine setting as an emergency physician, emergency
             nurse, or EMT / paramedic worker;

          3. Currently working shifts as part of your employment in the emergency medicine
             setting;

          4. Have a cell-phone / smartphone that can receive and send text-messages;

          5. Willing to take part in a research study where you are required to send and receive
             multiple text-messages at the start, during, and end of your shift work?

        Exclusion Criteria:

        1: Those that do not meet inclusion criteria.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel Patterson, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh Department of Emergency Medicine School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Daniel Patterson, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>412-647-3183</phone>
    <email>pdp3@pitt.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Matthew Weaver, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>412-647-1667</phone>
    <email>weavermd@upmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh Department of Emergency Medicine School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15260</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Matthew Weaver, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>412-647-1667</phone>
      <email>weavermd@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Maureen Morgan</last_name>
      <phone>412-647-3078</phone>
      <email>morgma@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.SleepTrackTXT.pitt.edu</url>
    <description>SleepTrackTXT home page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Patterson PD, Weaver MD, Hostler D, Guyette FX, Callaway CW, Yealy DM. The shift length, fatigue, and safety conundrum in EMS. Prehosp Emerg Care. 2012 Oct-Dec;16(4):572-6. doi: 10.3109/10903127.2012.704491. Epub 2012 Jul 23. PubMed PMID: 22823487.</citation>
    <PMID>22823487</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guyette FX, Morley JL, Weaver MD, Patterson PD, Hostler D. The effect of shift length on fatigue and cognitive performance in air medical providers. Prehosp Emerg Care. 2013 Jan-Mar;17(1):23-8. doi: 10.3109/10903127.2012.710719. Epub 2012 Aug 27.</citation>
    <PMID>22925035</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Patterson PD, Weaver MD, Frank RC, Warner CW, Martin-Gill C, Guyette FX, Fairbanks RJ, Hubble MW, Songer TJ, Callaway CW, Kelsey SF, Hostler D. Association between poor sleep, fatigue, and safety outcomes in emergency medical services providers. Prehosp Emerg Care. 2012 Jan-Mar;16(1):86-97. doi: 10.3109/10903127.2011.616261. Epub 2011 Oct 24.</citation>
    <PMID>22023164</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Patterson PD, Suffoletto BP, Kupas DF, Weaver MD, Hostler D. Sleep quality and fatigue among prehospital providers. Prehosp Emerg Care. 2010 Apr-Jun;14(2):187-93. doi: 10.3109/10903120903524971.</citation>
    <PMID>20199233</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Machi MS, Staum M, Callaway CW, Moore C, Jeong K, Suyama J, Patterson PD, Hostler D. The relationship between shift work, sleep, and cognition in career emergency physicians. Acad Emerg Med. 2012 Jan;19(1):85-91. doi: 10.1111/j.1553-2712.2011.01254.x. Epub 2012 Jan 5.</citation>
    <PMID>22221346</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 12, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 10, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Daniel Patterson, PhD, NREMT-P</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Emergency Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Shift work</keyword>
  <keyword>Fatigue</keyword>
  <keyword>Sleepiness</keyword>
  <keyword>Injury</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fatigue</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
