<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="35069">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01794520</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>M13-367</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-000589-38</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01794520</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase I Study Evaluating ABT-199 in Subjects With Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study Evaluating the Safety and Pharmacokinetics of ABT-199 in Subjects With Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AbbVie (prior sponsor, Abbott)</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genentech</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AbbVie</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>France: Committee for the Protection of Personnes</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objectives of this study are to assess the safety profile, characterize
      pharmacokinetics (PK) and determine the dosing schedule, maximum tolerated dose (MTD), and
      recommended phase 2 dose (RPTD) of ABT-199 when administered in subjects with relapsed or
      refractory multiple myeloma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number and percentage of subjects with adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>From subject's first dose of ABT-199 until 30 days after the subject's last dose of ABT-199; up to 2 years after last subject's first dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Collect all adverse events at each visit</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in physical exam findings including vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>From subject's baseline (prior to subject's first dose) up to 2 years following the last subject's first dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood pressure, heart rate and body temperature</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine dose and schedule of ABT-199</measure>
    <time_frame>Minimum first cycle of dosing (21 days) plus any lead-in period dosing (if used)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>ABT-199 will be dose escalated until the largest dose is reached that is felt to be safe based on adverse event reporting and dose-limiting toxicities information from all subjects</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in clinical laboratory test results</measure>
    <time_frame>From subject's baseline (prior to subject's first dose) up to 2 years following the last subject's first dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Hematology, chemistry, urinalysis, electrophoresis, immunofixation, viral serologies, free light chains</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cardiac assessment findings</measure>
    <time_frame>From subject's baseline (prior to subject's first dose) up to 2 years following the last subject's first dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Electrocardiogram and Multiple Gated Acquisition Scan and/or Echocardiogram</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of peak concentration (Cmax), trough concentration (Ctrough) and area under the concentration versus time curve (AUC) of ABT-199</measure>
    <time_frame>Dose Escalation Cohorts: once on Lead-in Days 1 and 8, Cycle 1 Day 1; 5 times on Cycle 2 Day 1; once on Cycle 2 Day 2 and Day 1 of Cycles 3, 5, 7 &amp; 9.  Safety Expansion Cohort: once on Lead-in Days 1 and 8; once on Day 1 of Cycles 1, 2, 3, 5, 7 &amp; 9.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood samples for pharmacokinetic analysis of ABT-199 will be collected at designated timepoints</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Calculation of Objective Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at Day 0, Cycle 3 Day 1, Cycle 5 Day 1 and Day 1 of every 4 cycles therafter (e.g., 9, 13, 17, etc.) up to 48 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The proportion of subjects with response using IMWG (International Myeloma Working Group) response criteria will be computed for all subjects with active disease at baseline (in the opinion of the investigator).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Calculation of Duration of Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at Day 0, Cycle 3 Day 1, Cycle 5 Day 1 and Day 1 of every 4 cycles therafter (e.g., 9, 13, 17, etc.) up to 48 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of days from the day of initial response is objectively documented to the day that disease progression is objectively documented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exploratory pharmacogenetic study: Evaluate blood samples to define relationship between drug concentration and disease status</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening (prior to subject's first dose)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood sample may be evaluated with goal of defining relationship between drug concentration and disease status</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Serum Markers and Plasma Markers Blood Samples</measure>
    <time_frame>From subject's baseline (prior to subject's first dose) up to 2 years following the last subject's first dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood samples may be evaluated with the goal of defining the relationship between drug concentration and disease status.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in bone marrow aspirate and core biopsy samples for Minimal Residual Disease (MRD), Cytogenetics/FISH, Bcl-2 Family Member Analysis, Bcl-2 Family Member Protein Analysis, in vitro Sensitivity, BH3 Profiling</measure>
    <time_frame>From subject's baseline (prior to subject's first dose) up to 2 years following the last subject's first dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Bone marrow aspirate and core biopsy samples may be evaluated with the goal of defining the relationship between drug concentration and disease status.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">54</enrollment>
  <condition>Relapsed/Refractory Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ABT-199 Dose Escalation Cohorts</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ABT-199 Safety Expansion Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ABT-199</intervention_name>
    <description>ABT-199 dosed at cohort-defined dosing schedules and dose levels for Dose Escalation Cohorts, ABT-199 dosed at defined dose and schedule for Safety Expansion Cohort</description>
    <arm_group_label>ABT-199 Dose Escalation Cohorts</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ABT-199 Safety Expansion Cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ECOG (Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group) performance score of 1 or 0.

          -  Diagnosis of multiple myeloma previously treated with more than 1 prior line of
             therapy, induction therapy followed by stem cell transplant and maintenance therapy
             will be considered a single line of therapy (dose escalation only); or fewer than 4
             separate lines of therapy (safety expansion only) including a proteasome inhibitor
             and an IMiD or immunomodulatory agent (e.g., thalidomide, lenalidomide), induction
             therapy followed by stem cell transplant and maintenance therapy will be considered a
             single line of therapy.

          -  Measurable disease at Screening: Serum monoclonal protein of at least 1.0 g/dL by
             protein electrophoresis or at least 200 mg of monoclonal protein in the urine on
             24-hr electrophoresis or serum immunoglobulin free light chain of at least 10 mg/dL
             and abnormal serum immunoglobulin kappa to lambda free light chain ratio.

          -  Subjects with a history of autologous or allogenic stem cell transplantation must
             have adequate peripheral blood counts independent of any growth factor support, and
             have recovered from any transplant related toxicity(s) and be at least 100 days
             post-autologous transplant prior to first dose of study drug or at least 6 months
             post-allogenic transplant prior to first dose of study drug and not have active
             graft-versus-host disease (GVHD), i.e., requiring treatment.

          -  Meet the following laboratory parameters, per the reference range: ANC of at least
             1000/μL (Subjects with bone marrow that is heavily infiltrated with underlying
             disease may use growth factor support to achieve ANC eligibility criteria, discussion
             should occur between investigator and sponsor medical monitor regarding any subject's
             use of growth factor to meet ANC criteria), AST and ALT not higher than 3 x ULN,
             Calculated creatinine clearance of at least 30 mL/min using a modified
             Cockcroft-Gault calculation (using Ideal Body Weight instead of Mass, subjects with
             calculated creatinine clearance less than or equal to 50 mL/min should have medical
             management discussed with sponsor medical monitor), platelet count of at least 30,000
             mm³ (independent of transfusion for 2 weeks), hemoglobin of at least 9.0 g/dL, total
             bilirubin not higher than 1.5 x ULN (subjects with Gilbert's Syndrome may have
             bilirubin higher 1.5 x ULN with approval of sponsor medical monitor) and aPTT and PT
             not higher than 1.2 x ULN.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Exhibits evidence of other clinically significant uncontrolled condition(s),
             including, but not limited to: uncontrolled systemic infection (viral, bacterial, or
             fungal), diagnosis of fever and neutropenia within 1 week prior to first dose of
             study drug.

          -  Cardiovascular disability status of New York Heart Association Class greater than 2.
             Class 2 is defined as cardiac disease in which patients are comfortable at rest but
             ordinary physical activity results in fatigue, palpitations, dyspnea or anginal pain.

          -  Significant history of renal, neurologic, psychiatric, endocrinologic, metabolic,
             immunologic, cardiovascular or hepatic disease, within the last 6 months that, in the
             opinion of the investigator, would adversely affect his/her participation in the
             study. For subjects who have required an intervention for any of the above diseases
             within the past 6 months, a discussion with the investigator and the AbbVie medical
             monitor must occur.

          -  History of other active malignancies other than multiple myeloma within the past 3
             years prior to study entry, with the following exceptions: adequately treated in situ
             carcinoma of the cervix uteri, basal cell carcinoma of the skin or localized squamous
             cell carcinoma of the skin, previous malignancy confined and surgically resected (or
             treated with other modalities) with curative intent.

          -  Tested positive for HIV.

          -  Seropositive for hepatitis A, hepatitis B surface antigen, or hepatitis C virus
             antibody or RNA.  Subjects with serologic evidence of prior vaccination to HBV may
             participate.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sari  Enschede, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>AbbVie</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lura  Morris, BA</last_name>
    <phone>847-937-7534</phone>
    <email>lura.morris@abbvie.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kaffa  Fakouhi, BS</last_name>
    <phone>847-935-6462</phone>
    <email>kaffa.fakouhi@abbvie.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site Reference ID/Investigator# 75808</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85259</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Site Reference ID/Investigator# 75808</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site Reference ID/Investigator# 74993</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Site Reference ID/Investigator# 74993</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site Reference ID/Investigator# 74994</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Site Reference ID/Investigator# 74994</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site Reference ID/Investigator# 76094</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110-1093</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Site Reference ID/Investigator# 76094</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site Reference ID/Investigator# 74995</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lille Cedex</city>
        <zip>59037</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Site Reference ID/Investigator# 74995</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site Reference ID/Investigator# 75033</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nantes Cedex 1</city>
        <zip>44093</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Site Reference ID/Investigator# 75033</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 12, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>relapsed multiple myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>refractory multiple myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>relapsed/refractory multiple myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>multiple myeloma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
