<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="95644">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01733056</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Emory IRB00044264</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>5-31040</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01733056</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immune Response to Vaccination in Patients Receiving Single Drug Immunosuppression</brief_title>
  <official_title>Characterization of Immune Response to Vaccination in Patients Receiving Single-Drug Immunosuppressive Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Biomedical Lay Summary Title: Characterization of immune response to vaccination in patients
      receiving single-drug immunosuppressive therapy Principal Investigator: Robert Swerlick, MD
      Other Investigators:   Rafi Ahmed, PhD Suephy Chen, MD Jens Wrammert, PhD Adam Sperduto

        1. Problem of Interest We are proposing to study the effectiveness of vaccines in people
           who are taking drugs that affect the immune system.  There are many populations of
           people who have chronic medical conditions that require them to have long-term
           treatment with immunosuppressive medications (drugs that decrease the function of the
           immune system).  Examples of these patients include organ transplant recipients,
           patients with immune cell cancers such as leukemia and lymphoma, patients with
           connective tissue disorders such as lupus, sarcoidosis, or scleroderma, and patients
           with skin conditions requiring steroid-based creams, ointments, pills, or injections.
           Patients who are taking these medications must receive appropriate vaccinations such as
           tetanus boosters, influenza vaccines, and pneumonia vaccines.  The effectiveness of
           vaccinations depends in large part on a strong response to the vaccine by the immune
           system.  Drugs that decrease immune system function therefore, may also decrease the
           effectiveness of vaccines.  To our knowledge, there is no data in the scientific
           literature regarding the effectiveness of vaccines in patients who are taking only one
           immunosuppressive medication.

        2. How the Problem of Interest will be studied

      We plan to give three different groups of participants influenza vaccinations and measure
      each participant's immune system response through blood tests.  The three groups will be:

        1. healthy people taking no immunosuppressive medications

        2. patients with skin conditions requiring treatment with azathioprine and currently
           taking no other immunosuppressive agents

        3. patients with psoriasis requiring treatment with TNF-alpha (tumor necrosis
           factor-alpha) and currently taking no other immunosuppressive medications.

      All participants will be between 40 - 60 years old and will not have had influenza
      vaccination within the previous six months.  We will administer the vaccination on day 0. We
      will take blood samples on days 0, 7, and 30 following vaccination.  We will use these blood
      samples to measure the amount of antibodies produced to the vaccine and the response of
      specific immune system cells known as B-lymphocytes.  Using statistical methods, we will
      compare these findings between the three groups of participants to determine if differences
      in response to the vaccination exist.

      3. How the research will advance scientific knowledge and/or human health To our knowledge
      there is no scientific data available regarding the effectiveness of vaccinations in
      patients receiving only one specific immunosuppressive medication.  We will also be using
      new techniques developed at Emory to measure the B-lymphocyte response to the vaccine.  This
      research could potentially help guide vaccination strategies for people requiring
      immunosuppressive medications and prevent infectious disease in these populations as well as
      the general population.

      4. Standard of Care This research study does not propose to treat any of the participants
      conditions.  Therefore, there is no &quot;standard of care.&quot;  This research study does propose to
      give influenza vaccinations to all participants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2011</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Specific Aim 1: Characterize influenza antibody titers before and after vaccination in patients taking azathioprine, TNF-alpha, or in healthy controls.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Specific Aim 1: Characterize influenza antibody titers before and after vaccination in patients taking azathioprine, TNF-alpha, or in healthy controls.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Specific Aim 2: Characterize the B cell responses to influenza vaccination in patients taking azathioprine, TNF-alpha, or in healthy controls.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Specific Aim 2: Characterize the B cell responses to influenza vaccination in patients taking azathioprine, TNF-alpha, or in healthy controls.
Measure the magnitude and specificity of influenza-specific B cell memory.
Analyze influenza-specific antibody secreting cells (ASC) appearing in blood after influenza vaccination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Immunosuppression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Volunteer</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Characterize influenza antibody titers before and after vaccination in patients taking azathioprine, TNF-alpha, or in healthy controls.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Azathioprine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Characterize influenza antibody titers before and after vaccination in patients taking azathioprine, TNF-alpha, or in healthy controls.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TNF alpha</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Characterize influenza antibody titers before and after vaccination in patients taking azathioprine, TNF-alpha, or in healthy controls.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Flu Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Fluzone (Influenza Vaccine)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Volunteer</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Azathioprine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>TNF alpha</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years or older

          -  Patient Taking azathioprine, Humira, Enbrel or Remicade

          -  Willing to participate in the healthy volunteer arm

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has received flu vaccine in past year

          -  Taking steroids or any other immunosuppressive drug
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>89 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University, Department of Dermatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bridget R Bradley, RN, FNP, CCRC</last_name>
      <phone>404-778-3084</phone>
      <email>brbradl@emory.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Rachel Sahn, MD</last_name>
      <phone>404-778-3158</phone>
      <email>rsahn@emory.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert A Swerlick, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 25, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 20, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Emory University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Robert A Swerlick MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dermatology</keyword>
  <keyword>Influenza Vaccine</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Azathioprine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
