<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="38380">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01754922</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>F1079-P</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1I21RX001079-01A</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01754922</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Deployment Exposures on Cardiopulmonary and Autonomic Function</brief_title>
  <acronym>AirHzds</acronym>
  <official_title>Effects of Deployment Exposures on Cardiopulmonary and Autonomic Function</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Following deployment to Operations Enduring and Iraqi Freedom and Operation New Dawn
      (OEF/OIF/OND), Veterans report breathing problems, difficulty exercising and other symptoms.
      These symptoms may be related to deployment exposures, such as regional dust and sand, smoke
      from burning trash, and local industry. Studies have reported poor air quality, but very
      little is known about the effect that exposure to this polluted air may have on Veterans'
      short- and long-term health. Investigators will determine whether deployment-related
      exposures have affected respiratory and nervous system function in these Veterans - data
      that may then be used to guide rehabilitation. Ultimately, the investigators' long-term goal
      is to prevent the development of chronic respiratory conditions in this group of OEF/OIF/OND
      Veterans.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Evidence is clear that Veterans deployed to Operations Enduring and Iraqi Freedom and
      Operation New Dawn (OEF/OIF/OND) have been exposed to high levels of particulate matter (PM)
      that exceeded environmental, occupational and military exposure guidelines. PM exposure is
      acknowledged as a risk factor for cardiovascular morbidity and mortality, and can increase
      the risk of and exacerbate airway disease. The reviewed epidemiology indicates a high
      prevalence of newly reported respiratory symptoms in OEF/OIF/OND Veterans that has
      significantly affected their deployment duties, including their physical exertion
      capability. Despite these retrospective data and limited air sampling reports, prospective
      studies are lacking. This pilot study will evaluate cardiorespiratory and autonomic function
      in OEF/OIF/OND Veterans as compared to Veterans never deployed to the region.

      To evaluate cardiopulmonary function, each Veteran will undergo a standardized exercise
      challenge and bronchodilator spirometry. To evaluate autonomic nervous system function,
      investigators will examine indices of heart rate variability and cardiovascular reflex
      regulation (e.g. baroreflex sensitivity and cerebral autoregulation) during a variety of
      tasks.

      Data derived from this pilot project will yield important insight on the extent and severity
      of cardiorespiratory and/or autonomic impairments - data that may provide intervention
      points for attenuating long-term adverse outcomes such as pulmonary and cardiovascular
      disease. Through early identification, treatment options (e.g. exercise therapy,
      pharmaceutical) may be implemented to enhance physiological function, with the goal of
      helping to alleviate symptoms and reduce chronic disease risk.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Cross-Sectional</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Spirometry, heart rate variability</measure>
    <time_frame>Once - cross-sectional</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Physiological variables obtained pre and post exercise</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">56</enrollment>
  <condition>Abnormality, Respiratory System</condition>
  <condition>Autonomic Nervous System</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exposed</arm_group_label>
    <description>Veterans  deployed to OEF/OIF/OND and environmentally exposed to high levels of particulate matter</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <description>OEF/OIF/OND Veterans deployed to regions other than Southwest Asia</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>None Retained</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      No biospecimens will be collected
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Community sample, outpatient clinic
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and female Veterans between 18 - 55 years of age will be identified and screened
             for our study.

          -  Two study cohorts will be recruited and attempts will be made to match group
             composition on age, body mass index and smoking history.

          -  Veterans assigned to the Exposed group must have been deployed to OEF/OIF for a
             minimum of 90 consecutive days.

          -  Our Control group will consist of Veterans never deployed to Southwest Asia (i.e.
             OEF/OIF, Persian Gulf War) but were deployed during the same time period.

          -  Each Veteran will complete a detailed exposure history questionnaire to confirm and
             support their group assignment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Participants must not meet any of the contraindications to exercise testing as described
        in the joint statement from the American College of Cardiology and American Heart
        Association. Also, individuals with history of any of the following will also be excluded:

          -  asthma (pre-military)

          -  cardiovascular disease

          -  neurological impairment/disorder

          -  pregnant

          -  uncontrollable hypertension (SBP &gt; 160; DBP &gt; 100)

          -  or have suffered severe/moderate traumatic brain injury within the last three years

          -  eye/chest/abdominal surgery in last 3 months

          -  tuberculosis exposure to self or household member

          -  history of aneurysm or collapsed lung

          -  history of detached retina

          -  stroke or heart attack in the last 3 months

          -  and history of coughing up blood in last three months

        (With the exception of hypertension and pregnancy (urine test), all exclusion criteria
        will be determined via self-report)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Joseph Falvo, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>East Orange Campus of the VA New Jersey Health Care System, East Orange, NJ</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael J Falvo, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(973) 676-1000</phone>
    <phone_ext>2423</phone_ext>
    <email>Michael.Falvo@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Drew A Helmer, MD MS</last_name>
    <phone>(800) 248-8005</phone>
    <email>drew.helmer@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>East Orange Campus of the VA New Jersey Health Care System, East Orange, NJ</name>
      <address>
        <city>East Orange</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07018</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sean L Johnson, BA</last_name>
      <phone>(973) 676-1000</phone>
      <phone_ext>1824</phone_ext>
      <email>Sean.Johnson2@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Joseph Falvo, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.warrelatedillness.va.gov/</url>
    <description>PI contact information and study site information</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 18, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>exercise tolerance</keyword>
  <keyword>veterans</keyword>
  <keyword>operation enduring freedom</keyword>
  <keyword>operation Iraqi freedom</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Congenital Abnormalities</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory System Abnormalities</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
