<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="156218">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01672892</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RTOG 1203</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CDR0000738944</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-02001</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01672892</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Standard Versus Intensity-Modulated Pelvic Radiation Therapy in Treating Patients With Endometrial or Cervical Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Phase III Study of Standard vs. IMRT Pelvic Radiation for Post-Operative Treatment of Endometrial and Cervical Cancer (TIME-C)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Radiation Therapy Oncology Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Radiation Therapy Oncology Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays and other types of radiation to kill
      tumor cells. Specialized radiation therapy that delivers a high dose of radiation directly
      to the tumor may kill more tumor cells and cause less damage to normal tissue.

      PURPOSE: This randomized phase III trial is studying two different methods of radiation and
      their side effects and comparing how well they work in treating endometrial and cervical
      cancer after surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      Primary

        -  To determine if pelvic intensity-modulated radiation therapy (IMRT) reduces acute
           gastrointestinal toxicity in the 5th week (after 23-25 fractions) of pelvic radiation
           as measured with the expanded prostate cancer index composite (EPIC) instrument.

      Secondary

        -  To determine if grade 2+ gastrointestinal toxicity (Common Terminology Criteria for
           Adverse Events version 4.0 [CTCAE v. 4.0]) is reduced with IMRT compared to
           conventional whole-pelvis radiation therapy (WPRT).

        -  To determine if grade 2+ hematologic toxicity (CTCAE v. 4.0) is reduced with IMRT
           compared to conventional WPRT.

        -  To determine if urinary toxicity is reduced with IMRT using the EPIC urinary domain.

        -  To validate EPIC bowel and urinary domains in women undergoing either IMRT pelvic
           radiation treatment or four-field pelvic radiation treatment for endometrial or
           cervical cancer.

        -  To assess the impact of pelvic IMRT on quality of life using the Functional Assessment
           of Cancer Therapy-General (FACT-G) with cervix subscale.

        -  To determine if there is any difference in local-regional control, disease-free
           survival, and overall survival between patients treated with IMRT as compared to
           conventional WPRT.

        -  To perform a health-utilities analysis to measure the financial impact of pelvic IMRT
           via the EQ-5D instrument.

        -  To identify molecular predictors of radiation toxicity and novel circulating cancer
           biomarkers.

      OUTLINE: This is a multicenter study. Patients are stratified according to type of cancer
      (endometrial vs cervical), chemotherapy (none vs 5 courses of weekly cisplatin at 40 mg/m²),
      and radiation dose (45 Gy vs 50.4 Gy). Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 treatment arms.

        -  Arm I: Patients undergo standard (3-dimensional) radiation therapy 5 days a week for up
           to 5-6 weeks.

        -  Arm II: Patients undergo intensity-modulated radiation therapy (IMRT) 5 days a week for
           up to 5-6 weeks.

      Some patients receive cisplatin IV over 1 hour on day 1. Treatment continues weekly for 5
      weeks, concurrently with radiation therapy, in the absence of unacceptable toxicity or
      disease progression.

      Tissue and blood samples may be collected for biomarker and correlative analysis.

      Quality of life may be assessed by questionnaires (including the Expanded Prostate Cancer
      Index Composite [EPIC], the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-General [FACT-G, Version
      4], the EQ-5D, and the Common Toxicity Criteria Adverse Events - Patient-Reported Outcome
      [PRO-CTCAE]) instruments at baseline and periodically during and after study therapy.

      After completion of study therapy, patients are followed every 6 months for the first 2
      years and then annually for 5 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute gastrointestinal toxicity, as measured by bowel domain of EPIC, at 5 weeks from the start of pelvic radiation</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 5 of Radiation Therapy (RT)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Validation of EPIC Bowel and Urinary domains</measure>
    <time_frame>Before study start, Week 3 of RT, Week 5 of RT, 4-6 Weeks after RT, 1 year from start of RT and 3 years from start of RT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity, as measured by CTCAE v. 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Before study start, Week 5 of RT, 4-6 Weeks after RT, 1 year from start of RT and 3 years from start of RT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urinary toxicity, as measured by EPIC urinary domain</measure>
    <time_frame>Before study start, Week 3 of RT, Week 5 of RT, 4-6 Weeks after RT, 1 year from start of RT and 3 years from start of RT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life, as measured by the FACT-G with cervix subscale</measure>
    <time_frame>Before study start, Week 5 of RT, 4-6 Weeks after RT, 1 year from start of RT and 3 years from start of RT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health utilities, as measured by EQ-5D</measure>
    <time_frame>Before study start, Week 5 of RT, 4-6 Weeks after RT, 1 year from start of RT and 3 years from start of RT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Local-regional control</measure>
    <time_frame>End of Study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>End of Study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>End of Study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Identification of molecular predictors of radiation toxicity and novel circulating cancer biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>End of Study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">281</enrollment>
  <condition>Cervical Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Endometrial Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Gastrointestinal Complications</condition>
  <condition>Perioperative/Postoperative Complications</condition>
  <condition>Radiation Toxicity</condition>
  <condition>Urinary Complications</condition>
  <condition>Urinary Tract Toxicity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo standard (3-dimensional) radiation therapy 5 days a week for up to 5.5 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo intensity-modulated radiation therapy (IMRT) 5 days a week for up to 5.5 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>3-dimensional conformal radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo radiation therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>intensity-modulated radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo radiation therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Pathologically proven diagnosis of endometrial or cervical cancer within 90 days of
             registration

          -  Patients must have undergone a hysterectomy (total abdominal hysterectomy, vaginal
             hysterectomy or radical hysterectomy, or total laparoscopic hysterectomy) for
             carcinoma of the cervix or endometrium within 49 days prior to registration

               -  Performance of a bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy will be at the treating
                  surgeon's discretion

               -  No positive or close (&lt; 3 mm) resection margins

          -  Appropriate stage for protocol entry, including no distant metastases, based upon the
             following minimum diagnostic workup:

               -  History/physical examination within 45 days prior to registration

               -  Computed tomography (CT), magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), or positron emission
                  tomography (PET)-CT including the abdomen and pelvis should be performed for
                  initial radiological staging (performed pre- or post-surgery within 90 days
                  prior to registration)

                    -  Imaging performed postoperatively should show no evidence of residual
                       disease

                    -  Any evidence of malignancy identified on preoperative imaging should have
                       been completely resected surgically prior to protocol treatment

               -  Chest x-ray or chest CT must be performed within 90 days prior to registration
                  (unless a PET-CT has been performed)

          -  Endometrial cancer:

               -  Patients with the following histologic features are eligible for pelvic
                  radiation therapy without weekly cisplatin:

                    -  Less than 50% myometrial invasion, grade 3 adenocarcinoma without uterine
                       serous carcinoma (USC), or clear cell histology

                    -  At least 50% myometrial invasion, grade 1-2 adenocarcinoma without USC, or
                       clear cell histology

               -  Patients with the following histologic features may be treated with pelvic
                  radiation with or without weekly cisplatin (the decision to add weekly cisplatin
                  for these patients is at the treating physician's discretion):

                    -  At least 50% myometrial invasion, grade 3 including USC and clear cell
                       carcinoma

                    -  International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics (FIGO) 2009 stage II
                       endometrial cancer of any grade including USC and clear cell carcinoma

                    -  FIGO 2009 stage IIIC1 (pelvic lymph node positive only, para-aortic nodes
                       sampled and negative) including USC and clear cell carcinoma

          -  Cervical cancer:

               -  Patients with the following pathology findings may be treated with pelvic
                  radiation with or without weekly cisplatin at the treating physician's
                  discretion:

                    -  Patients with intermediate-risk features including two of the following
                       histologic findings after radical hysterectomy:  1/3 or more stromal
                       invasion, lymph-vascular space invasion or large clinical tumor diameter (&gt;
                       4 cm)

                    -  Patients with cervical cancer treated with a simple hysterectomy with
                       negative margins

               -  Patients with any of the following criteria following radical hysterectomy are
                  eligible for this study and must receive weekly cisplatin:

                    -  Positive resected pelvic nodes (para-aortic nodes sampled and negative)

                    -  Microscopic parametrial invasion with negative margins

          -  No patients with para-aortic nodal disease or who require extended-field radiotherapy
             beyond the pelvis

          -  No patients with histology consisting of endometrial stromal sarcoma, leiomyosarcoma,
             malignant mixed mullerian tumor (MMMT), or carcinosarcoma

          -  No evidence of metastatic disease outside of the pelvis

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Zubrod performance status 0-2

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1,500 cells/mm³

          -  Platelets ≥ 100,000 cells/mm³

          -  Hemoglobin (Hgb) ≥ 8.0 g/dL (the use of transfusion or other intervention to achieve
             Hgb ≥ 8.0 g/dL is acceptable)

          -  For patients receiving chemotherapy:

               -  Within 14 days prior to registration, serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 mg/dL AND
                  calculated creatinine clearance ≥ 50 mL/min

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) ≤ 2 times upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  Bilirubin ≤ 2 times ULN

               -  Alkaline phosphatase, magnesium, blood urea nitrogen (BUN), and electrolytes
                  must be obtained and recorded

          -  Fertile patients must use effective contraception

          -  Not pregnant and/or breastfeeding

          -  Willing and able to complete the bowel and urinary domains of the expanded prostate
             cancer index composite (EPIC) instrument prior to registration

          -  No patients who exceed the weight/size limits of the treatment table or CT scanner

          -  No mental status changes or bladder control problems that make the patient unable to
             comply with bladder-filling instructions

          -  No prior invasive malignancy (except non-melanomatous skin cancer) unless
             disease-free for a minimum of 3 years

          -  No patients with active inflammatory bowel disease

          -  No severe, active co-morbidity, defined as follows:

               -  Unstable angina and/or congestive heart failure requiring hospitalization within
                  the last 6 months

               -  Transmural myocardial infarction within the last 6 months

               -  Acute bacterial or fungal infection requiring intravenous antibiotics at the
                  time of registration

               -  Other major medical illness that requires hospitalization or precludes study
                  therapy at the time of registration

               -  Hepatic insufficiency resulting in clinical jaundice and/or coagulation defects
                  (however, laboratory test coagulation parameters are not required for entry into
                  this protocol)

               -  Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS) based upon current CDC definition
                  (however, human immunodeficiency virus [HIV] testing is not required for entry
                  into this protocol)

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY:

          -  See Disease Characteristics

          -  No prior radiation therapy to the pelvis

          -  No prior treatment with platinum-based chemotherapy

          -  Patients may NOT receive amifostine or other protective reagents
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ann Klopp, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universtiy of Oklahoma Health Sciences Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Terence Herman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>405-271-3016</phone>
      <email>terence-herman@ouhsc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Reading Hospital and Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Reading</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Albert Yuen, MD</last_name>
      <phone>610-988-8000</phone>
      <email>yuena@readinghospital.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/RTOG-1203</url>
    <description>Clinical trial summary from the National Cancer Institute's PDQ® database</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 23, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>gastrointestinal complications</keyword>
  <keyword>perioperative/postoperative complications</keyword>
  <keyword>radiation toxicity</keyword>
  <keyword>urinary complications</keyword>
  <keyword>urinary tract toxicity</keyword>
  <keyword>endometrial clear cell carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>endometrial papillary serous carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IA endometrial carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IB endometrial carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage II endometrial carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IIIA endometrial carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IIIB endometrial carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IIIC endometrial carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>endometrial adenocarcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>cervical adenocarcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IB cervical cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IIA cervical cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IIB cervical cancer</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Endometrial Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uterine Cervical Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Postoperative Complications</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Radiation Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
