<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="68618">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01652040</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>B7867-W</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01652040</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Resistance Training and Testosterone After Spinal Cord Injury</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Evoked Resistance Training and Testosterone After Spinal Cord Injury</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Virginia Commonwealth University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this proposal is to investigate the efficacy of a complimentary approach of
      evoked resistance training and testosterone replacement therapy on the changes in body
      composition and metabolic profile after SCI. The proposed method could become a recommended
      and simple intervention especially for individuals with limited access and poor tolerance to
      exercise. The rationale is based on the evidence that individuals with SCI experience
      decline in anabolic hormones which may be responsible for the deterioration in body
      composition and metabolic profiles and leads to increase obesity, type 2 diabetes mellitus,
      dyslipidemia and subsequently cardiovascular disease. The designed study will provide
      explanation to the adaptations in the energy source of the muscle cells in response to
      training.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Individuals with spinal cord injury (SCI) are at a lifelong risk of increasing obesity and
      several chronic metabolic disorders such as glucose intolerance, insulin resistance and
      dyslipidemia secondary to deterioration in body composition. Within few weeks of injury,
      there are significant decrease in whole body fat-free mass (FFM), particularly lower
      extremity skeletal muscle mass and subsequent increase in fat mass (FM).  Resistance
      training (RT) is an important type of exercise that has been shown to induce positive
      physiological adaptations such as increasing lean mass and reducing metabolic disorders in
      other clinical populations.

      In a pilot work, the investigators provided evidence that evoked RT using surface
      neuromuscular electrical stimulation (NMES) for knee extensor muscle group resulted in
      significant increase skeletal muscle cross-sectional area (CSA), reduction in % leg FM and a
      trend towards decrease in visceral adipose tissue (VAT) CSA.  The favorable adaptations in
      body composition were associated with decrease in plasma insulin area under the curve and
      plasma triglycerides. The investigators attributed the adaptations in body composition and
      metabolic profile to an associated increase in plasma insulin-like growth factor (IGF-1).
      The investigators  concluded that twelve weeks of evoked RT targeted towards evoking
      skeletal muscle hypertrophy could result in significant body composition and metabolic
      adaptations in individuals with SCI.

      It is unclear if a longer RT program greater than 12 weeks would provide additional benefits
      to veterans with SCI. It is also unknown whether enhancing the decline anabolic homeostasis
      by providing testosterone (T) replacement therapy (TRT) would reverse body composition and
      metabolic profile changes in veterans with SCI.  The major research goal of this proposal is
      to investigate the effects of 16 weeks of evoked RT+TRT vs. TRT on body composition (muscle
      CSA, VAT, %FM) and the metabolic profiles (glucose and lipid metabolism) in individuals with
      motor complete SCI.  To address this goal, surface NMES accompanied with ankle weights will
      be conducted twice weekly to exercise the knee extensor skeletal muscle groups from sitting
      position. After 4 weeks of delayed entry approach, participants (n =24) will be randomly
      assigned into RT+TRT (n =12) or TRT (n =12) groups.  The TRT will be provided via
      transdermal T patches that will be alternated on both shoulders over the course of the
      study. We also propose to study the effects of detraining on body composition and metabolic
      profiles.

      The research plan includes three specific aims

      Specific aim 1 will demonstrate the effects of NMES RT and/or Testosterone patches (Tp) on
      the CSA of thighs and legs skeletal muscle groups, percentage FFM, and the CSA of VAT,
      intramuscular fat and percentage FM after 16 weeks of training+Tp and 16 weeks of
      detraining.

      Specific aim 2 will determine the changes in metabolic milieu (resting energy expenditure,
      glucose homeostasis, lipid profile, free fatty acids, serum total and free testosterone and
      IGF-1), and cytokines (c-reactive protein, tumor necrosis factor alpha and IL-6 as
      inflammatory biomarkers) after 16 weeks of training+Tp and detraining.

      Specific aim 3 will determine if 16 weeks of evoked RT and Tp will increase GLUT-4
      concentration, muscle IGF-1 and peroxisome-proliferator-activated receptor-gamma
      co-activator 1 (PGC-1) expressions, altered fiber type distribution and enhance the
      mitochondrial enzymatic activities (electron transport chain) compared to Tp only.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Factorial Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Composition</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in body composition fat mass</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Metabolic Profile</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Glucose, lipid, inflammatory biomarkers, Basal Metabolic Rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Spinal Cord Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RT+Tp</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Resistance training using electrical stimulation and ankle weights and Testosterone patches</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tp</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Applying Testosterone patches</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Resistance Training and Testosterone Patches</intervention_name>
    <description>We are going to activate the knee extensor muscle group to lift ankle weights over 16 weeks and we are going to provide Tp to improve anabolic profile.</description>
    <arm_group_label>RT+Tp</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Testosterone Patches</intervention_name>
    <description>The investigators will provide Tp patches for 16 weeks for patients with Spinal Cord Injury.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tp</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male with Spinal Cord Injury

          -  Between 18-50 years old

          -  BMI &lt; 30 Kg/m2

          -  Traumatic motor complete C5-L2 level of injury

          -  American Spinal Injury Classification (A and B; i.e. motor deficit below the level of
             injury)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Cardiovascular disease

          -  Uncontrolled type II DM and those on insulin

          -  Pressures sores stage 2 or greater

          -  Supra-physiological T level

          -  Hematocrit  above 50%

          -  Urinary tract infection or symptoms
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ashraf Gorgey, PhD PT</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hunter Holmes McGuire VA Medical Center, Richmond, VA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ashraf Gorgey, PhD PT</last_name>
    <phone>(804) 675-5000</phone>
    <phone_ext>3386</phone_ext>
    <email>ashraf.gorgey@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Robert A Adler, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(804) 675-5424</phone>
    <email>Robert.Adler@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hunter Holmes McGuire VA Medical Center, Richmond, VA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23249</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robert C Dresch</last_name>
      <phone>804-675-5151</phone>
      <email>robert.dresch@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Franklin J Zieve, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(804) 675-5151</phone>
      <email>franklin.zieve@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ashraf Gorgey, PhD PT</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gorgey AS, Mather KJ, Cupp HR, Gater DR. Effects of resistance training on adiposity and metabolism after spinal cord injury. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2012 Jan;44(1):165-74. doi: 10.1249/MSS.0b013e31822672aa.</citation>
    <PMID>21659900</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gorgey AS, Shepherd C. Skeletal muscle hypertrophy and decreased intramuscular fat after unilateral resistance training in spinal cord injury: case report. J Spinal Cord Med. 2010;33(1):90-5.</citation>
    <PMID>20397451</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Khalil RE, Gorgey AS, Janisko M, Dolbow DR, Moore JR, Gater DR. The role of nutrition in health status after spinal cord injury. Aging Dis. 2013 Feb;4(1):14-22. Epub 2012 Nov 30.</citation>
    <PMID>23423356</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gorgey AS, Dolbow DR, Cifu DX, Gater DR. Neuromuscular electrical stimulation attenuates thigh skeletal muscles atrophy but not trunk muscles after spinal cord injury. J Electromyogr Kinesiol. 2013 May 14. doi:pii: S1050-6411(13)00083-7. 10.1016/j.jelekin.2013.04.007. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>23683374</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 13, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Spinal Cord Injury</keyword>
  <keyword>Rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Electrical Stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Testosterone</keyword>
  <keyword>Body Composition</keyword>
  <keyword>Lipid and Glucose profile</keyword>
  <keyword>Ectopic Adiposity</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Testosterone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone enanthate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone undecanoate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone 17 beta-cypionate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methyltestosterone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
