<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="73823">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01846143</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15832</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01846143</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Immunogenicity Study of Multi-phosphopeptide Vaccine Plus PolyICLC in Participants With Melanoma</brief_title>
  <acronym>Mel59</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Safety and Immunogenicity of a Multi-phosphopeptide Vaccine Plus PolyICLC in Participants With Melanoma (Mel59)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Virginia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Virginia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to learn what effects (good and bad) experimental
      phosphopeptide vaccines  plus a tetanus peptide and other substances called polyICLC and
      Montanide ISA-51 have on people with melanoma. The investigators will also look at whether
      the experimental reagents cause any changes in the immune system.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days post administration of the last vaccine</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Adverse events occurring in each subject will be reported until 30 days post administration of the last vaccine.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunogenicity of phosphopeptide vaccines</measure>
    <time_frame>Through Day 85</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluation of immunogenicity will be measured by immune response to the phosphopeptides by ELIspot assay of PBL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: pBCAR3-phosphopeptide + tet vaccine plus polyICLC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>pBCAR3-phosphopeptide + tet vaccine plus polyICLC
The vaccines will be administered in two treatment cycles.  During cycle one, three vaccines will be administered over a 3-week period on days 1, 8, and 15.   During cycle two, three vaccines will be administered over a 9-week period on days 36, 57, 78.  Participants will be vaccinated with 100 mcg each of the phosphopeptides and 200 mcg of the tetanus peptide (Peptide-tet).  The peptides will be administered subcutaneously (0.5 ml) and intradermally (0.5 ml) in Montanide ISA-51 VG adjuvant at six separate vaccine sites in a minimum of two separate extremities.
Poly ICLC: PolyICLC will be administered by a separate 0.5 ml injection (0.25 ml subcutaneously and 0.25 ml intradermally), immediately after, and directly into the precise site where the peptide emulsion was given.  We will administer 1 mg per vaccine.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: pIRS2-phosphopeptide + tet vaccine plus polyICLC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The vaccines will be administered in two treatment cycles.  During cycle one, three vaccines will be administered over a 3-week period on days 1, 8, and 15.   During cycle two, three vaccines will be administered over a 9-week period on days 36, 57, 78.  Participants will be vaccinated with 100 mcg each of the phosphopeptides and 200 mcg of the tetanus peptide (Peptide-tet).  The peptides will be administered subcutaneously (0.5 ml) and intradermally (0.5 ml) in Montanide ISA-51 VG adjuvant at six separate vaccine sites in a minimum of two separate extremities.
Poly ICLC: PolyICLC will be administered by a separate 0.5 ml injection (0.25 ml subcutaneously and 0.25 ml intradermally), immediately after, and directly into the precise site where the peptide emulsion was given.  We will administer 1 mg per vaccine.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm C: 2-MpP+ tet vaccine plus polyICLC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The vaccines will be administered in two treatment cycles.  During cycle one, three vaccines will be administered over a 3-week period on days 1, 8, and 15.   During cycle two, three vaccines will be administered over a 9-week period on days 36, 57, 78.  Participants will be vaccinated with 100 mcg each of the phosphopeptides and 200 mcg of the tetanus peptide (Peptide-tet).  The peptides will be administered subcutaneously (0.5 ml) and intradermally (0.5 ml) in Montanide ISA-51 VG adjuvant at six separate vaccine sites in a minimum of two separate extremities.
Poly ICLC: PolyICLC will be administered by a separate 0.5 ml injection (0.25 ml subcutaneously and 0.25 ml intradermally), immediately after, and directly into the precise site where the peptide emulsion was given.  We will administer 1 mg per vaccine.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pBCAR3-phosphopeptide</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: pBCAR3-phosphopeptide + tet vaccine plus polyICLC</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>tet vaccine</other_name>
    <other_name>polyICLC</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pIRS2-phosphopeptide</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: pIRS2-phosphopeptide + tet vaccine plus polyICLC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>2-MpP (pBCAR3-phosphopeptide + pIRS2-phosphopeptide)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm C: 2-MpP+ tet vaccine plus polyICLC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically or cytologically proven melanoma that meets one of the following
             criteria:

               -  For Arms A and B: Stage IIIB-IV melanoma rendered clinically free of disease by
                  surgery, other therapy, or spontaneous remission

               -  For Arm C: Stage IIA-IV melanoma rendered clinically free of disease by surgery,
                  other therapy, or spontaneous remission

               -  For all Arms: Stage III or IV melanoma with disease.  Patients may be eligible
                  if there are definite or equivocal findings of persistent or metastatic disease
                  as long as those findings do not meet RECIST criteria for measurable disease

          -  Patients may have had one or more prior therapies for melanoma.

          -  Patients may have had multiple primary melanomas.

          -  Patients who have had brain metastases may be eligible if they meet the following
             criteria

          -  Patients with less than or equal to 5 metastases may be eligible as long as the
             following 3 criteria are true:

          -  The brain metastases have been completely removed by surgery or have been treated
             completely by stereotactic radiotherapy.  Stereotactic radiotherapy, such as gamma
             knife, can be used up to 1 week prior to study entry.

          -  There has been no evident growth of any brain metastasis since treatment.

          -  No metastasis greater than 2 cm at the time of protocol entry Patients with greater
             than 5 metastases may be eligible if the above 3 criteria are met and if at least one
             year has elapsed since the last treatment.

          -  All participants must have:

          -  ECOG performance status of 0 or 1

          -  Ability and willingness to give informed consent

          -  Patients must have at least one intact axillary and/or inguinal lymph node basin.  A
             patient with a prior lymph node biopsy may be a candidate if lymphoscintigraphy
             demonstrates intact drainage to a node in that basin.  A lymphoscintigram may be
             performed during screening to ensure that there is drainage to a regional node from a
             planned vaccine site. If the lymphoscintigram is performed and a sentinel lymph node
             is not located, the patient will be ineligible for this study if no other vaccine
             sites are available.

          -  Laboratory parameters as follows: The following laboratory parameters will be
             required for all participants.  If a lab value appears to be an error or a result of
             a transient or treatable condition, the investigator will use his/her clinical
             judgment to decide if the test may be repeated.  The requirements for inclusion are
             as follows:

               -  HLA-A2+

               -  ANC &gt; 1000/mm3

               -  Platelets &gt; 100,000/mm3

               -  Hgb ≥ 9 g/dL

               -  HGBA1C &lt; 7%

               -  Hepatic:

                    -  AST and ALT ≤ 2.5 x upper limits of normal (ULN)

                    -  Bilirubin ≤ 2.5 x ULN

                    -  Alkaline phosphatase ≤ 2.5 x ULN

               -  Renal

                    -  Creatinine ≤ 1.5 x ULN

               -  Serology (within 6 months of study entry)

                    -  HIV negative

                    -  Hepatitis C negative

               -  LDH up to 2 x ULN

          -  Participants must be 18 years or older at study entry.

          -  Patients who have recurred or progressed either after or during administration of a
             melanoma vaccine may be eligible to enroll 12 weeks following their last vaccination.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have had brain metastases unless they meet the criteria outlined in the
             inclusion criteria section of the protocol.

          -  Patients who are currently receiving systemic cytotoxic chemotherapy, radiation, or
             other experimental therapy, or who have received this therapy within the preceding 4
             weeks.  Gamma knife or stereotactic radiosurgery may be administered within the prior
             4 weeks, but must not be administered less than one week prior to study enrollment.
             Patients who are currently receiving nitrosoureas or who have received this therapy
             within the preceding 6 weeks.

          -  Patients will not be eligible if there is clinically detectable melanoma deemed
             likely by the investigator to require intervention during the first 12 weeks of the
             study that would require premature discontinuation.  Examples for such circumstances
             may include untreated bone metastases at risk for fracture, and rapidly progressive
             low volume disease.

          -  Patients with known or suspected allergies to any component of the vaccine.

          -  Patients receiving the following medications at study entry or within the preceding 4
             weeks are excluded:

          -  Agents with putative immunomodulating activity (with the exception of non-steroidal
             anti-inflammatory agents and topical steroids

          -  Allergy desensitization injections.

          -  Systemic corticosteroids, administered parenterally or orally

          -  Inhaled steroids (e.g. Advair®, Flovent®, Azmacort®) are not permitted. Topical
             corticosteroids are acceptable, including steroids with very low solubility
             administered nasally for local effects only (e.g. Nasonex®).

          -  Any pharmacologic growth factors (e.g. GM-CSF, G-CSF, erythropoietin).

          -  Interferon Therapy

          -  Interleukin-2 or other interleukins.

          -  Toll-like receptor agonists, including imiquimod, resiquimod, or polyICLC.

          -  Participants may not have been vaccinated previously with any of the synthetic
             phosphopeptides included in this protocol.

          -  Pregnancy or the possibility of becoming pregnant during vaccine administration.
             Female patients of child-bearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test
             (urinary or serum beta-HCG) prior to administration of the first vaccine dose.  Males
             and females must agree, in the consent form, to use effective birth control methods
             during the course of vaccination.  The methods are specified in the consent form and
             include the following: Norplant, IUD, Dep-Provera, Birth Control Pills, Birth Control
             Patch, and Sterilization.  The following may be used if combined with other birth
             control methods:  Condoms, Jellies or foam, Diaphragm, Rhythm, Withdrawal, Sponge, or
             Cervical cap.

          -  Women must also not be breast feeding.

          -  Patients in whom there is a medical contraindication or potential problem in
             complying with the requirements of the protocol, in the opinion of the investigator.

          -  Patients classified according to the New York Heart Association classification as
             having Class III or IV heart disease.

          -  Patients with a body weight &lt; 110 lbs because of the amount and  frequency with which
             blood will be drawn

          -  Participants must not have known inflammatory conditions of the gastrointestinal
             tract (oropharynx, esophagus, stomach, small bowel, colon, rectum, or anus) or the
             respiratory tract (airway and lungs) of autoimmune, infectious, or other cause.
             Examples may include but are not limited to, gastritis, C. difficile colitis,
             radiation proctitis, bronchitis. Patients may have had such conditions in the past if
             they have recovered completely at least 3 months prior, and are not expected to have
             relapses of the condition.

          -  Participants must not have had prior autoimmune disorders requiring cytotoxic or
             immunosuppressive therapy, or autoimmune disorders with visceral involvement.
             Participants with an active autoimmune disorder requiring these therapies are also
             excluded.  The following will not be exclusionary:

               -  The presence of laboratory evidence of autoimmune disease (e.g. positive ANA
                  titer) without associated symptoms

               -  Clinical evidence of vitiligo

               -  Other forms of depigmenting illness

               -  Mild arthritis requiring NSAID medications or no medical therapy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Victor Engelhard, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Virginia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Craig L. Slingluff, Jr., MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Virginia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Emily Allred, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>434-982-1902</phone>
    <email>eh4m@virginia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kristy Scott, BS</last_name>
    <phone>434-982-6714</phone>
    <email>KS4WW@hscmail.mcc.virginia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Virginia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlottesville</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22908</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Victor Engelhard, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 26, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 30, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Poly ICLC</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
