<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="134442">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01839279</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ZAN-QT-1006</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01839279</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Define the ECG Effects of Tizanidine Compared to Placebo and the Positive Control, Moxifloxacin, in Healthy Men and Women Using a Blinded ECG Evaluator: A Thorough ECG Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>TQT</acronym>
  <official_title>A Partial-Blind, Randomized, Parallel Design Study With a Nested Crossover Comparison to Define the ECG Effects of Tizanidine Compared to Placebo and the Positive Control, Moxifloxacin, in Healthy Men and Women Using a Blinded ECG Evaluator: A Thorough ECG Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Acorda Therapeutics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Acorda Therapeutics</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-center, partial-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled, parallel design
      study with a nested crossover comparison to define the ECG effects of tizanidine compared to
      placebo and the positive control, moxifloxacin, in healthy men and women. The study will be
      conducted in a Phase 1 unit with sufficient facilities to house subjects as required by the
      protocol.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>A single supratherapeutic oral dose of tizanidine 24 mg given with food and its effects on cardiac repolarization (QTc interval) in healthy volunteers</measure>
    <time_frame>on  Day 14</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary endpoint will be the baseline-adjusted, placebo-corrected effect on QTc (ΔΔQTc) on Day 14.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of a single therapeutic dose of tizanidine 8 mg given with food and its effects on cardiac repolarization (QTc) interval in healthy volunteers</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 5</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The baseline-adjusted, placebo-corrected (ΔΔQTc) on QTc method not selected as primary endpoint</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessing the relationship between changes in the QTc interval and plasma levels of tizanidine using concentration-effect modeling</measure>
    <time_frame>Days -1, 1, 5, 14, 15</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>1) Model 1 will be a linear model with an intercept; 2) Model 2 will be a linear model with mean intercept fixed to 0 (with variability); and 3) Model 3 will be a linear model with no intercept.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic (PK) profile of single doses of 8 and 24 mg tizanidine after reaching steady state</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 5 and 14</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve during a dosing interval (AUCt), maximum plasma concentration (Cmax), the lowest plasma concentration (Ctrough), and time to reach maximum plasma concentration (tmax).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">136</enrollment>
  <condition>Spasticity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tizanidine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oral dose of 2 and 4 milligram (mg) tablets</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo crossover to moxifloxacin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo followed by a single dose 400 mg moxifloxacin tablets.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Moxifloxacin crossover to placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>single dose of 400 mg moxifloxacin followed by placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tizanidine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Tizanidine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Zanaflex</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo crossover to moxifloxacin</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo crossover to moxifloxacin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Moxifloxacin crossover to placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Moxifloxacin crossover to placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women of childbearing potential should have a negative urine pregnancy test prior to
             Screening and Day -2 of the trial

          -  All subjects of childbearing potential must practice a highly effective method of
             birth control excluding oral contraceptives for the duration of the trial and up to 3
             months after the last dose of investigational product. Oral contraceptives are not
             allowed, based on the precaution listed in the Zanaflex package insert.

          -  Have a body mass index (BMI) ranging between 19 and 30 kg/m2

          -  Comprehend and be able to provide written informed consent

          -  Be willing and able to comply with all trial requirements

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Female who is either pregnant, breastfeeding or planning to become pregnant

          -  History of hypersensitivity or allergic reaction to tizanidine or moxifloxacin or any
             of the tablet components

          -  Any condition possibly affecting drug absorption, metabolism or excretion including
             previous surgery for removal of parts of stomach, bowel, liver, gall bladder, or
             pancreas

          -  History of Long QT Syndrome or a first-generation relative with this condition

          -  Evidence or history of clinically significant allergies except for untreated,
             asymptomatic, seasonal allergies at time of dosing, hematological, endocrine,
             pulmonary, gastrointestinal, cardiovascular, hepatic, renal, psychiatric, or
             neurological disease. Determination of clinical significance is to be made at the
             Investigator's discretion

          -  History or presence of any malignant or benign neoplasm considered by the
             investigator to be clinically significant

          -  History of drug or alcohol abuse or dependence within the last year

          -  Have an active infectious disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mathews Adera, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Acorda Therapeutics</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Covance- Dallas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75247</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 22, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Muscle Spasticity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Tizanidine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Moxifloxacin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Norgestimate, ethinyl estradiol drug combination</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
