<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="102691">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02119260</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>117387</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02119260</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A First Time in Human Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics, and Pharmacodynamics of GSK2798745 in Healthy Subjects and Stable Heart Failure Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-Centre, Sponsor Un-blinded, Placebo-controlled Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics, and Pharmacodynamics of Single and Repeat, Ascending Doses of GSK2798745 in Healthy Subjects and Stable Heart Failure Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is the first administration of GSK2798745 in humans. This will be a single
      centre, sponsor un-blinded, placebo-controlled study to investigate the safety,
      tolerability, pharmacokinetics (PK), and pharmacodynamics (PD) of GSK2798745, given as
      single and repeat oral doses to healthy subjects and stable heart failure (HF) subjects.
      Approximately 36 healthy subjects will be enrolled in the study cohorts (Cohort 1-3)
      involving single and repeat dose escalations of GSK2798745, while 15 stable heart failure
      subjects will be enrolled in Cohort 4 involving single and repeat dose administration of
      GSK2798745, with the dose selected based on data from healthy subject cohorts. The study
      duration, including screening and follow-up, is not expected to exceed 120 days for subjects
      in the study (in any cohort).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of single and repeat doses of GSK2798745 in healthy subjects as assessed by vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 45 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Vital sign measurements will include systolic and diastolic blood pressure, heart rate, and respiratory rate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of single and repeat doses of GSK2798745 in stable HF subjects as assessed by vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Vital sign measurements will include systolic and diastolic blood pressure, heart rate, and respiratory rate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of single and repeat doses of GSK2798745 in healthy subjects as assessed by telemetry monitoring</measure>
    <time_frame>2 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Continuous cardiac telemetry will be performed using a telemeter monitor</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of single and repeat doses of GSK2798745 in stable HF subjects as assessed by telemetry monitoring</measure>
    <time_frame>2 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Continuous cardiac telemetry will be performed using a telemeter monitor</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of single and repeat doses of GSK2798745 in healthy subjects as assessed by electrocardiogram (ECG)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 45 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Twelve-lead ECGs will be obtained using an ECG machine that automatically calculates the heart rate and measures PR, QRS, QT, and QTcF intervals. ECGs will be measured after resting in semi-supine position for 5 minutes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of single and repeat doses of GSK2798745 in stable HF subjects as assessed by ECG</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Twelve-lead ECGs will be obtained using an ECG machine that automatically calculates the heart rate and measures PR, QRS, QT, and QTcF intervals. ECGs will be measured after resting in semi-supine position for 5 minutes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of single and repeat doses of GSK2798745 in healthy subjects as assessed by clinical laboratory tests</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 45 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Clinical laboratory tests include hematology, clinical chemistry, urinalysis and additional parameters</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of single and repeat doses of GSK2798745 in stable HF subjects as assessed by clinical laboratory tests</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Clinical laboratory tests include hematology, clinical chemistry, urinalysis and additional parameters</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of single and repeat doses of GSK2798745 in healthy subjects as assessed by adverse events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 45 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>AEs will be collected from the start of study treatment and until the follow-up contact</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of single and repeat doses of GSK2798745 in stable HF subjects as assessed by AEs</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>AEs will be collected from the start of study treatment and until the follow-up contact</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite of pharmacokinetic (PK) parameters following single and repeat dose administration of GSK2798745 in healthy subjects</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1, 2, 3 and 4 for single dose; and Days 1, 2, 3, 4, 7, 10, 14, 15, 16 and 17 for repeat dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>From the plasma concentration-time data, the following PK parameters will be determined, as data permit: maximum observed plasma concentration (Cmax), time to Cmax (Tmax), area under the plasma concentration-time curve [AUC (0-t) and AUC (0-infinity)], and apparent terminal phase half-life (t1/2)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite of PK parameters following single and repeat dose administration of GSK2798745 in stable HF subjects</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1, 2, 3 and 4 for single dose; and Days 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 10 for repeat dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>From the plasma concentration-time data, the following PK parameters will be determined, as data permit: Cmax, Tmax, AUC (0-t) and AUC (0-infinity), and t1/2</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite of PK parameters following single dose of GSK2798745 in fed and fasted state</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1, 2, 3 and 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Effect of food on PK will be assessed by comparing AUC and Cmax values in fed and fasted state</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite of PK parameters following single dose of GSK2798745 liquid or capsule formulations</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1, 2, 3 and 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>From the plasma concentration-time data, the following PK parameters will be determined, as data permit: Cmax, Tmax, AUC (0-t) and AUC (0-infinity), and t1/2</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">51</enrollment>
  <condition>Oedema, Pulmonary</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Eight subjects will be randomized to 1 of 4 placebo-controlled dose sequences with 2 subjects in each sequence and each subject having four dose periods (3 active dose of GSK2798745 + 1 placebo dose). GSK2798745 will be administered in a liquid form (suspension or solution) in this cohort. The subjects will be fasting from the prior midnight to four hours post-dose.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Twelve subjects will receive GSK2798745 in three single-dose treatment periods in a fixed sequence. The actual dose-selected will be determined based on review of emerging efficacy and safety data from Cohort 1. The dosing will be done in 3 study periods for investigating bioavailability and food effects. In Period 1, subjects will receive GSK2798745 following a standard high fat/high calorie meal. In Period 2, subjects will be fasting from midnight to four hours post-dose and will receive GSK2798745 in a liquid form (suspension or solution). In Period 3, subjects will receive a capsule formulation of GSK2798745 under fasting conditions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sixteen subjects will be randomized to 2 repeat dose cohorts with 8 subjects in each cohort in a ratio of 6:2 (treatments: placebo). Doses and food intake timing will be determined based on data from Cohorts 1 and 2. Doses will be administered once daily from Day 1 to Day14 (inclusive). Dosing may be altered to twice daily based on the results obtained in Cohorts 1 and 2.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fifteen stable HF subjects will be randomized in this cohort with a treatment:placebo ratio of 12:3. The subjects will receive GSK2798745 in a single dose followed by a 7-day repeat dose. Dose determination and decision of food intake timing will be determined based on results from Cohorts 1 to 3. The highest safe and well tolerated dose will be administered.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GSK2798745 solution</intervention_name>
    <description>Clear, colourless GSK2798745 (0.1-0.4mg) solution in aqueous citrate buffer with 4% captisol</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GSK2798745 suspension</intervention_name>
    <description>Aqueous suspension of GSK2798745 (&gt;=0.5 mg)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GSK2798745 capsule</intervention_name>
    <description>White Opaque granule filled capsules of GSK2798745 (2.5-4.0 mg)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo solution</intervention_name>
    <description>Clear, colourless solution of aqueous citrate buffer with 4% captisol</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo suspension</intervention_name>
    <description>Visually matching aqueous suspension of hypromellose acetate succinate powder</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo capsule</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching White Opaque granule filled placebo capsule</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        For Healthy Subject Cohorts (1-3):

          -  Male or female 18-75 years of age inclusive, at the time of signing the informed
             consent.

          -  Healthy as determined by a responsible and experienced physician, based on an
             evaluation including medical history, physical examination, laboratory tests and
             cardiac evaluation including ECG and echocardiogram. A subject with a clinical
             abnormality or laboratory parameter(s) which is/are not specifically listed in the
             inclusion or exclusion criteria, outside the reference range for the population being
             studied may be included only if the Investigator in consultation with the GSK Medical
             Monitor agree and document that the finding is unlikely to introduce additional risk
             factors and will not interfere with the study procedures.

          -  Body weight &gt;=50 kilogram (kg) and Body Mass Index (BMI) within the range 18-32
             kilogram/ square meter (kg/m^2) (inclusive).

          -  A female subject is eligible to participate if she is of Non-childbearing potential
             defined as pre-menopausal females with a documented tubal ligation or hysterectomy
             for this definition, &quot;documented&quot; refers to the outcome of the
             Investigator's/designee's review of the subject's medical history for study
             eligibility, as obtained via a verbal interview with the subject or from the
             subject's medical records; or postmenopausal defined as 12 months of spontaneous
             amenorrhea. In questionable cases a blood sample with simultaneous follicle
             stimulating hormone (FSH) &gt; 40 milli-International Units per milliliter mIU/mL and
             estradiol &lt;40 picogram/millilitre (pg/mL) [&lt;147 picomoles/liter (pmol/L)] is
             confirmatory.

          -  Male subjects with female partners of child-bearing potential must agree to use a
             contraception method as per the protocol. This criterion must be followed from the
             time of the first dose of study medication until 2 weeks post last dose.

          -  Capable of giving written informed consent, which includes compliance with the
             requirements and restrictions listed in the consent form.

          -  Alanine transaminase (ALT), alkaline phosphatase and bilirubin &lt;= 1.5x Upper limit of
             normal (ULN) (isolated bilirubin &gt;1.5xULN is acceptable if bilirubin is fractionated
             and direct bilirubin &lt;35%).

          -  Based on averaged QTc values of triplicate ECGs obtained over a brief recording
             period: QTc &lt;450 milliseconds (msec); or QTc &lt;480 msec in subjects with Bundle Branch
             Block.

        For Heart Failure Subjects (Cohort 4):

          -  Established diagnosis of mild or moderate heart failure of any aetiology with
             symptoms defined as corresponding to the New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class II
             or III on stable heart failure therapy for at least 3 months and was not hospitalized
             for HF for the last three months.

          -  Male or female 18 years or older, age inclusive, at the time of signing the informed
             consent.

          -  ALT, alkaline phosphatase and bilirubin &lt;=1.5xULN (isolated bilirubin &gt;1.5xULN is
             acceptable if bilirubin is fractionated and direct bilirubin &lt;35%).

          -  Based on averaged QTc values of triplicate ECGs obtained over a brief recording
             period: QTc &lt;450msec; or QTc &lt;480msec in subjects with Bundle Branch Block.

          -  Female subject is eligible to participate if she is of: Non-childbearing potential
             defined as pre-menopausal females with a documented tubal ligation or hysterectomy
             for this definition, &quot;documented&quot; refers to the outcome of the
             Investigator's/designee's review of the subject's medical history for study
             eligibility, as obtained via a verbal interview with the subject or from the
             subject's medical records; or postmenopausal defined as 12 months of spontaneous
             amenorrhea. In questionable cases a blood sample with simultaneous follicle
             stimulating hormone (FSH) &gt;40mIU/mL and estradiol &lt;40pg/mL (&lt;147pmol/L) is
             confirmatory.

          -  Male subjects with female partners of child-bearing potential must agree to use one
             of the contraception methods listed in the protocol. This criterion must be followed
             from the time of the first dose of study medication until 2 weeks post-last dose.

          -  Body weight &gt;=50kg and BMI within the range 18-32kg/m^2 (inclusive).

          -  Capable of giving written informed consent, which includes compliance with the
             requirements and restrictions listed in the consent form.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current or chronic history of liver disease, or known hepatic or biliary
             abnormalities (with the exception of Gilbert's syndrome or asymptomatic gallstones).

          -  Chronic angina, unstable angina, or history of acute coronary syndromes, coronary
             angioplasty, or stenting within the past 6 months.

          -  History of regular alcohol consumption within 6 months of the study defined as an
             average weekly intake of &gt;21 units for males or &gt;14 units for females. One unit is
             equivalent to 8 gram (g) of alcohol: a half-pint (approximately 240mL) of beer, 1
             glass (125mL) of wine or 1 (25mL) measure of spirits.

          -  History of sensitivity to any of the study medications, or components thereof or a
             history of drug or other allergy that, in the opinion of the Investigator and/or GSK
             Medical Monitor, contraindicates their participation.

          -  History of seizure disorder and or stroke.

          -  History of active ulcer disease or gastrointestinal (GI) bleeding.

          -  Current smokers.

          -  A positive pre-study Hepatitis B surface antigen or positive Hepatitis C antibody
             result within 3 months of screening.

          -  A positive pre-study drug/alcohol screen.

          -  A positive test for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) antibody.

          -  A screening cardiac Troponin (cTn) level &gt;ULN.

          -  Baseline presence of severe aortic stenosis.

          -  The subject has participated in a clinical trial and has received an investigational
             product within the following time period prior to the first dosing day in the current
             study: 30 days, 5 half-lives or twice the duration of the biological effect of the
             investigational product (whichever is longer).

          -  Exposure to more than four new chemical entities within 12 months prior to the first
             dosing day.

          -  Subjects who are taking &gt;= 20 milligrams (mg) of any statin (HF subjects only).

          -  Left ventricular ejection fraction &lt;50% - (Healthy subjects only).

          -  Subject who, in the Investigator/designee's judgement, poses a significant suicide
             risk. Evidence of serious suicide risk may include any history of suicidal behaviour
             and/or any evidence of suicidal ideation on any questionnaires e.g., Type 4 or 5 on
             the Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS) in the last 5 years.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
    <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 8, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 17, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>First Time in Human</keyword>
  <keyword>TRPV4 inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart failure</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Edema</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
