<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="60581">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02154035</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999914123</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>14-I-N123</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02154035</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Quantitative Measurement and Correlates of the Latent HIV Reservoir in Virally Suppressed Ugandans</brief_title>
  <official_title>Quantitative Measurement and Correlates of the Latent HIV Reservoir in Virally Suppressed Ugandans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) is the virus that causes AIDS. HIV can hide in the blood
      for many years, even in people who have their HIV infection under control. HIV that is
      hiding in the blood is called the    latent HIV reservoir.    Researchers want to find out
      more about it in this study. This knowledge may help them develop new ways to prevent or
      control HIV. This study will draw its participants from the Rakai Health Sciences Program in
      rural southwestern Uganda.

      Objective:

      - To measure and learn about the latent HIV reservoir in Ugandans with HIV.

      Eligibility:

      - Men and women at least 18 years of age with HIV.

      Design:

        -  Participants will have a medical history and physical exam. Their medical records will
           be reviewed. Researchers will ask participants about their health and recent illnesses.
           Participants able to get pregnant will have their urine tested for pregnancy.

        -  Participants will have their finger pricked to see if they have enough red blood cells
           to be eligible for the study.

        -  If eligible, participants will have blood drawn through a needle in the arm. Their
           blood will also be tested for other diseases.

        -  After the blood draw, participants will be asked to stay seated or lying down if they
           are not feeling well for up to 30 minutes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Despite prolonged antiretroviral therapy (ART), HIV   1 can persist as transcriptionally
      inactive proviruses in resting memory CD4+T cells. This latent reservoir has a long half
      life, and is believed to be the largest impediment to a cure by ART alone. The latent
      reservoir may be established when activated CD4+ T cells become infected and subsequently
      revert back to a resting memory state. A major approach to eradicating HIV   1 involves
      reversing latency in patients on ART. Cells harboring induced proviruses could be lysed by
      HIV   1   specific cytolytic T lymphocytes, while ART blocks new rounds of infection. The
      descriptions of the    Berlin patient    and    Mississippi baby    suggest that a
      functional cure for HIV is possible. This has led to an expansion of research examining HIV
      latency in the context of sustained viral suppression with an eye towards developing a
      possible cure regimen that could be used on a large scale. However, it has recently been
      demonstrated that the latent HIV reservoir could be 60 times larger than previously
      believed. The recent report that two HIV patients receiving CCR5    competent bone marrow
      transplants had a reemergence of circulating HIV after fully suppressive therapy was
      discontinued suggests that a functional cure for large groups of individuals will continue
      to be an elusive goal.

      The vast majority of HIV   infected individuals currently live in sub   Saharan Africa where
      fully suppressive ART is expanding rapidly. Due to this expansion, a large number of
      Africans will be eligible candidates for cure treatment when one comes available. However,
      strategies needed to establish a functional cure may differ in African populations due to
      differences in endemic infectious disease load and in cellular immune activation among
      Africans as compared to Western populations. To date, there have been no systematic studies
      to quantify the latent reservoir in HIV   infected Africans. This is a crosssectional,
      descriptive study to measure the size of the latent HIV reservoir in virally suppressed
      HIVinfected individuals residing in Uganda and to examine the immunological and virologic
      correlates of the latent reservoir. The study will draw its participants from a National
      Institutes of Health (NIH) International Center for Excellence in Research (ICER) site,
      located at the Rakai Health Sciences Program (RHSP) in rural southwestern Uganda. One group
      of subjects will be comprised of 70 HIV   infected patients who are on ART with suppressed
      viral loads &lt; 40 copies per ml over a period of 10   18 months. A second group will be
      comprised of 10 HIV   infected subjects with suppressed viral load &lt; 40 copies per ml over a
      period of 10   18 months and not on antiretroviral drugs (elite suppressors). Study
      participation will require only one visit with a fingerstick hemoglobin screening and a
      blood draw. Plasma and cells from the blood will be separated and processed for quantitative
      viral latency, circulating cytokine and chemokine analysis, co   culture, and flow
      cytometric and serologic assays for selected immunological parameters. Viral latency results
      will be interpreted in relation to values previously collected from HIVinfected individuals
      in the United States.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Cross-Sectional</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Examine and measure the levels of latent HIV reservoirs in virally suppressed Ugandans and compare to that observed in Western (US) cohorts</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the role of endemic infectious diseases, nadir CD4 count, and length of fully suppressive therapy on latent HIV reservoir size</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Explore the level of immune activation in virally suppressed HIV-infected Africans in correlation with the size of the reservoir</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. At least 18 years of age

               2. Hemoglobin &gt; 9g/dL as assessed by fingerstick rapid test

               3. A historical diagnosis of HIV infection as indicated by any positive serological
                  test (ELISA, HIV rapid test, or Western Blot)

               4. Virally suppressed as defined as at least two historical viral loads &lt; 40
                  copies/ml obtained between 10   18 months apart, and no intervening detectable
                  viral load result &gt; = 40 copies/ml obtained during this period

               5. Most recent historical viral load result obtained within a year prior to the
                  screening visit

               6. Willingness to undergo genetic testing

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Women who are pregnant will be excluded as the required blood draw may cause anemia

          2. Inability to follow study instructions or to provide informed consent

          3. Any condition deemed by the investigators to be a contraindication to study
             participation including active, serious infections (other than HIV infection) during
             the 2 weeks prior to enrollment

          4. Malignancies of any kind (e.g., Kaposi's sarcoma)

          5. Therapy with systemic steroids, immunosuppressants or immunomodulating agents

          6. Coagulation defects or other serious bleeding disorders

          7. Current use of medications which could affect clotting
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas C Quinn, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kevin O Newell</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 846-5365</phone>
    <email>newellk@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Thomas C Quinn, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(410) 955-7635</phone>
    <email>tquinn@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rakai Health Sciences Program Uganda Virus Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kalisizo</city>
        <country>Uganda</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Uganda</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ho YC, Shan L, Hosmane NN, Wang J, Laskey SB, Rosenbloom DI, Lai J, Blankson JN, Siliciano JD, Siliciano RF. Replication-competent noninduced proviruses in the latent reservoir increase barrier to HIV-1 cure. Cell. 2013 Oct 24;155(3):540-51. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2013.09.020. Epub 2013 Oct 24. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>24243014</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wightman F, Ellenberg P, Churchill M, Lewin SR. HDAC inhibitors in HIV. Immunol Cell Biol. 2012 Jan;90(1):47-54. doi: 10.1038/icb.2011.95. Epub 2011 Nov 15. Review. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>22083528</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wei X, Ghosh SK, Taylor ME, Johnson VA, Emini EA, Deutsch P, Lifson JD, Bonhoeffer S, Nowak MA, Hahn BH, et al. Viral dynamics in human immunodeficiency virus type 1 infection. Nature. 1995 Jan 12;373(6510):117-22.</citation>
    <PMID>7529365</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 31, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 31, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Viral Suppression</keyword>
  <keyword>Functional Cure</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
