<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="68836">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01934140</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>116725</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01934140</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Evaluate the Long-term Antibody Persistence of GlaxoSmithKline (GSK) Biologicals' MenACWY-TT Vaccine (GSK134612) Versus Mencevax ACWY in Healthy Adolescents and Adults and Booster Response to MenACWY-TT Vaccine Administered at 10 Years Post-primary Vaccination</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Long-term Antibody Persistence of GSK Biologicals' MenACWY-TT Vaccine (GSK134612) Versus Mencevax ACWY in Healthy Adolescents and Adults and Booster Response to MenACWY-TT Vaccine Administered at 10 Years Post-primary Vaccination</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Philippines: Philippines Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the long-term antibody persistence from 6, 7, 8, 9
      to 10 years post-administration of MenACWY-TT conjugate vaccine as compared to Mencevax ACWY
      when given to healthy subjects 11 to 55 years of age. In addition, the safety and
      immunogenicity of a booster dose of MenACWY-TT vaccine administered to all eligible subjects
      10 years after the primary vaccination will be evaluated.

      All Filipino subjects who received the primary vaccination in the primary vaccination study
      107386 (NCT00356369) will be invited to enrol in the long-term follow up and booster phase.
      No new subjects will be enrolled.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunogenicity with respect to the components of the investigational vaccine in terms of antibody titres</measure>
    <time_frame>During the long-term follow-up phase (6, 7, 8, 9 and 10 years after primary vaccination in Study MENACWY-TT-015)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>rSBA-MenA, rSBA-MenC, rSBA-MenW-135 and rSBA-MenY antibody titres ≥ 1:8, ≥ 1:128 and geometric mean titres (GMTs)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunogenicity with respect to the components of the investigational vaccine in terms of antibody titres and antibody concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>One month post booster vaccination at ten years after primary vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of solicited local and general symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 0-3 following the booster vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of unsolicited symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 31 days following booster vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of serious AEs, and new onset chronic illness(es) (e.g. autoimmune disorders, asthma, type 1 diabetes and allergies), GBS (Guillain-Barre Syndrome) and meningococcal disease</measure>
    <time_frame>From administration of the vaccine dose until study end (Month 126)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Infections, Meningococcal</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ACWY-TT group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All subjects vaccinated with MenACWY-TT in study MENACWY-TT-015 will be assigned to this group. At Month 120 after primary vaccination, these subjects will be vaccinated with a booster dose of MenACWY-TT in this study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MenPS group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All subjects vaccinated with Mencevax ACWY in study MENACWY-TT-015 will be assigned to this group. At Month 120 after primary vaccination, these subjects will be vaccinated with a dose of MenACWY-TT in this study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Meningococcal vaccine GSK134612</intervention_name>
    <description>1 dose administered intramuscularly in the non-dominant deltoid region.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MenPS group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ACWY-TT group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        All subjects must satisfy the following criteria at study entry to the persistence phase:

          -  Subjects who, in the opinion of the investigator, can and will comply with the
             requirements of the protocol. Or /and subjects' parent(s)/Legally Acceptable
             Representative(s) [LAR(s)] who, in the opinion of the investigator, can and will
             comply with the requirements of the protocol.

          -  A male or female between and including 17 and 66 years of age at the time of entry
             into the present study.

          -  Has completed the vaccination phase of the vaccination study MENACWY-TT-015.

          -  In alignment with local laws and regulations, written informed consent obtained from
             parents/LAR(s) of the subject and written informed assent obtained from the subject
             if the subject is less than 18 years of age, or written informed consent obtained
             from the subject if the subject has achieved the 18th birthday. The subjects ≥18
             years of age at the time of enrollment will sign the informed consent form, even if
             the parent/ LAR previously signed the ICF before the subject reached the legal age of
             consent.

          -  Healthy subjects as established by medical history and history-directed physical
             examination before entering into the study.

        All subjects must satisfy the following additional criteria prior to entry of the booster
        phase:

          -  Female subjects of non-childbearing potential may be enrolled in the study.

               -  Non-childbearing potential is defined as pre-menarche, current tubal ligation,
                  hysterectomy, ovariectomy or post-menopause.

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential may be enrolled in the study, if the
             subject:

               -  has practiced adequate contraception for 30 days prior to vaccination, and

               -  has a negative pregnancy test on the day of vaccination, and

               -  has agreed to continue adequate contraception during the entire treatment period
                  and for 2 months after completion of the vaccination series.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Child in care.

          -  Previous vaccination with meningococcal polysaccharide or conjugate vaccine outside
             of study MENACWY-TT-015.

          -  History of meningococcal disease due to serogroup A, C, W-135 or Y.

          -  Any confirmed or suspected immunosuppressive or immunodeficient condition, including
             Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) infection, based on medical history and physical
             examination.

          -  Major congenital defects or serious chronic illness.

          -  Family history of congenital or hereditary immunodeficiency.

          -  History of chronic alcohol consumption and/or drug abuse.

        Additional exclusion criteria for booster phase at Month 120 study entry (to be checked at
        Month 120) for all subjects

          -  Use of any investigational or non-registered product other than the study vaccine
             within 30 days preceding the booster dose of study vaccine, or planned use during the
             follow-up period.

          -  Chronic administration (defined as more than 14 days in total) of immunosuppressants
             or other immune-modifying drugs within six months prior to the booster vaccine dose.
             Inhaled and topical steroids are allowed.

          -  Administration of a vaccine not foreseen by the study protocol in the period starting
             30 days before the booster dose of study vaccine or planned administration within 30
             days after vaccination (with the day of vaccination considered Day 0), with the
             exception of a licensed inactivated influenza vaccine.

          -  Administration of immunoglobulins and/or any blood products within the three months
             preceding the booster vaccination or planned administration during the follow-up
             period.

          -  Concurrently participating in another clinical study, at any time during the study
             period, in which the subject has been or will be exposed to an investigational or a
             non-investigational vaccine/product.

          -  Previous vaccination with tetanus toxoids within the last month.

          -  History of any reaction or hypersensitivity likely to be exacerbated by any component
             of the vaccines.

          -  History of any neurological disorders or seizures, including Guillain-Barré syndrome
             (GBS). History of a simple, single febrile seizure is permitted.

          -  Acute disease and/or fever at the time of enrollment.

               -  Fever is defined as temperature ≥ 37.5°C for oral, axillary or tympanic route,
                  or ≥ 38.0°C for rectal route. The preferred route for recording temperature in
                  this study will be oral.

               -  Subjects with a minor illness without fever may, be enrolled at the discretion
                  of the investigator.

          -  Pregnant or lactating female.

          -  Female planning to become pregnant or planning to discontinue contraceptive
             precautions.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>17 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>66 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
    <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Muntinlupa</city>
        <zip>1781</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Philippines</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 8, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 22, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Healthy</keyword>
  <keyword>Adults</keyword>
  <keyword>Safety</keyword>
  <keyword>Neisseria meningitidis</keyword>
  <keyword>Booster response</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunogenicity</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescents</keyword>
  <keyword>Serogroups A, C, W-135, and Y</keyword>
  <keyword>long-term antibody persistence</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Meningococcal Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
