<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="105920">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01944462</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Merck IISP ID 50926</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01944462</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact and Cost of a Pharmacist Pneumococcal Vaccination Program With PNEUMOVAX® 23 at an Urban Senior Center</brief_title>
  <acronym>PPVP</acronym>
  <official_title>Impact and Cost of a Pharmacist Pneumococcal Vaccination Program With PNEUMOVAX® 23 at an Urban Senior Center for Adults Aged 65 Years or Older or Those With Defined Risk Factors for Invasive Pneumococcal Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Thomas Jefferson University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Thomas Jefferson University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall goals of this program are to measure the impact of a pharmacist pneumococcal
      vaccine education program (PPVP) using a senior center model of care and provide the
      pneumococcal vaccine to eligible participants.

      Hypotheses

        1. PPVP will result in improved knowledge and awareness in older minorities in the senior
           center setting (primary hypothesis);

        2. Participants who are vaccinated through the project will experienced increased trust in
           receiving vaccines from a pharmacist;

        3. Participants will be satisfied with and trust the PV information provided by
           pharmacists in the PPVP;

        4. PPVP is an efficient approach to educating patients in the senior center based on its
           costs;

        5. Participating pharmacists will be activated to implement PPVP learnings in their
           practice.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Knowledge and awareness of pneumococcal disease</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 month, 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in knowledge and awareness of pneumococcal disease over time will be assessed with an 8-10 item inventory encompassing the following domains: susceptibility to infection, symptoms of disease, severity of illness, and vaccination with an emphasis on vaccine efficacy, safety, and eligibility.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Activation</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Activation will be measured as percent of participants receiving the pneumococcal vaccine either on the study Vaccination Day or from another healthcare provider.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trust in pharmacists as vaccine providers</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Trust in pharmacists as vaccine providers will be measured by comparing responses to the trust items in the baseline survey to the trust item responses in the 3 month assessment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction with PPVP</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Satisfaction with PPVP will be measured as participants' overall satisfaction with the content and delivery of the PPVP, extent to which the participant felt engaged, satisfaction with information received from the pharmacists during breakout sessions, trust in the pharmacists' PV knowledge, and willingness to receive pneumococcal vaccination from a pharmacist.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention cost</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measures PPVP intervention costs in terms of PPVP time and supply costs per participant, for those receiving the educational components only compared to those receiving the educational components as well as the optional pneumococcal vaccine on Vaccination Day.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacist activation</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Pharmacists who participate in the small group component of the PPVP intervention will be asked to complete a qualitative reflection statement assessing their activation to incorporate learnings into practice.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Study is Open to Seniors Age 50 or Older</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pharmacist Pneumococcal Vaccine Program (PPVP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individuals receiving the PPVP intervention which consists of the educational program delivered on site at the collaborating senior center.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pharmacist Pneumococcal Vaccine Program (PPVP)</intervention_name>
    <description>1.5 hour educational intervention delivered onsite at collaborating senior center consisting of 3 components: presentation about pneumococcal disease and the vaccine given by a infectious disease-certified pharmacist; 2) skits given by volunteer actors at the senior center to illustrate real world scenarios related to pneumococcal disease and the vaccine; 3) action planning to consist of small group breakouts led by licensed pharmacists and 4) vaccination day which is an optional component following the education program, for participants eligible to receive the vaccine. Vaccination to be provided free of charge to eligible participants who opt to receive it.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pharmacist Pneumococcal Vaccine Program (PPVP)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        A. Inclusions for PPVP:

          1. Age ≥ 50 years old

          2. Can attend a 1.5-hour session at CIP

          3. Cognitively intact based on responses to an Abbreviated Mental Test Score (AMTS) of
             ≥7 (see Appendix for AMTS instrument)

          4. Can speak and read English at ≥4th grade level as evidenced by ability to read a
             brief passage

          5. Access to a telephone

        B. Inclusions to receive the optional pneumococcal vaccination:

        Patient meets ≥1 of the following criteria for receiving their first pneumococcal
        vaccination:

          1. All adults age 65 years and older who have not had the vaccine previously

          2. Age 50-64 years with any of the following conditions:

               1. Cigarette smokers age 19 years and older

               2. Chronic cardiovascular disease (e.g., congestive heart failure,
                  cardiomyopathies; excluding hypertension)

               3. Chronic pulmonary disease (including COPD and emphysema, and for adults ages 19
                  years and older, asthma)

               4. Diabetes mellitus

               5. Alcoholism

               6. Chronic liver disease, cirrhosis

               7. Candidate for or recipient of cochlear implant

               8. Functional or anatomic asplenia (e.g., sickle cell disease, splenectomy)

               9. Immunocompromising conditions or on immunosuppressive therapy

              10. Chronic renal failure or nephrotic syndrome

        OR

        Patient meets ≥1 of the following criteria for receiving a booster dose of the
        pneumococcal vaccination:

          1. Adults age 65 years and older who received their first dose for any indication when
             they were younger than age 65 years.

          2. Adults age 50-64 who have not received the vaccine for ≥5 years and have one of the
             following conditions:

               1. Functional or anatomic asplenia (including persons with sickle cell disease or
                  splenectomy patients);

               2. Chronic renal failure (including dialysis patients) or nephrotic syndrome;

               3. Immunocompromising conditions or on immunosuppressive therapy

        Exclusion Criteria:

        A. Exclusions to the PPVP program: none

        B. Exclusions to receiving the optional pneumococcal vaccine:

          1. Participant has a history of allergic reaction to pneumococcal vaccine

          2. Participant has a history of allergic reaction to any component of any vaccine

          3. Participant with moderate or severe illness (these individuals will be advised to
             speak to their doctor regarding the vaccine)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Laura Pizzi, PharmD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Thomas Jefferson University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Laura Pizzi, PharmD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>215.955.1159</phone>
    <email>laura.pizzi@jefferson.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jason Schafer, PharmD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>215.503.7522</phone>
    <email>jason.schafer@jefferson.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center in the Park</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19144</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Laura Pizzi, PharmD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cdc.gov/vaccines/hcp/vis/vis-statements/ppv.pdf</url>
    <description>US Centers for Disease Control. Vaccine Information Statement on Pneumococcal Polysaccharide Vaccine.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 5, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pneumococcal vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacist vaccination</keyword>
  <keyword>Pneumovax 23</keyword>
  <keyword>pneumococcal vaccine polyvalent</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
