<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="107495">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01782963</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-498</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01782963</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lenalidomide/Bortezomib/Dexamethasone for Multiple Myeloma (MM)</brief_title>
  <acronym>RVD Lite</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Modified Lenalidomide, Bortezomib and Dexamethasone for Transplant-Ineligible Patients With Newly Diagnosed Multiple Myeloma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research study is a Phase II clinical trial. Phase II clinical trials test the
      effectiveness of an investigational combination of drugs. The purpose is to learn whether
      the combination of drugs works in treating a specific cancer. &quot;Investigational&quot; means that
      the combination of drugs is still being studied. It also means that research doctors are
      trying to find out more about it. Examples of what they want to learn about are the safest
      dose to use, the side effects it may cause, and if the combination of drugs works for
      treating different types of cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      If you are willing to participate in this study you will be asked to undergo some screening
      procedures and tests to confirm that you are eligible. Many of these tests and procedures
      are likely to be part of regular cancer care. They may be done even if it turns out that you
      do not take part in the research study. If you have had some of these tests or procedures
      recently, they may or may not have to be repeated. These tests and procedures include: a
      medical history, physical exam, performance status, vital signs, neurological exam, bone
      imaging studies, chest x-ray, bone marrow aspirate, ECG, blood tests and urine tests. If
      these tests show that you are eligible to participate in the research study, you will begin
      the study treatment. If you do not meet the eligibility criteria, you will not be able to
      participate in the research study.

      For cycles 1-9 (each cycle lasts 35 days) you will receive the following: Lenalidomide-once
      a day on Days 1-21. You will take Lenalidomide by mouth at the same time each day.
      Bortezomib- once a day on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22. If you are one of the first ten patients
      enrolled you will get Bortezomib as an intravenous injection for the first cycle. You will
      get Bortezomib as an injection under the skin for all other cycles. If you are not one of
      the first 10 patients enrolled you will get Bortezomib as an injection under the skin for
      all cycles. Dexamethasone-if you are 75 years old or younger you will get Dexamethasone on
      Days 1, 2, 8, 9, 15, 16, 22 and 23. If you are more than 75 years old you will get
      Dexamethasone on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22. You will take Dexamethasone by mouth at the same time
      each day.

      For cycles 10-15 (each cycle lasts 28 days) you will receive the following:
      Lenalidomide-once a day on Days 1-21. You will take Lenalidomide by mouth at the same time
      each day. Bortezomib-Once a day on Days 1 and 15. You will get Bortezomib as an injection
      under the skin. You will be given a drug diary to record taking your doses of the drugs. The
      study staff will tell you how to complete the diary.

      During the study you will have to come to the clinic for visits. The tests and procedures
      that will be done at each visit are listed below:

      Day 1 of all cycles: questions about health, medications etc., physical exam, performance
      status, vital signs, neurological exam, questionnaires, bone imaging studies, bone marrow
      aspirate, blood tests, pregnancy test, education and counseling, collection of bone marrow,
      plasma and serum (cycle 1 only), urine test.

      Day 8 of cycles 1-9: questions about health, medications etc., vital signs, blood tests.

      Day 15 of all cycles: questions about health, medications, etc., vital signs, blood tests,
      pregnancy test.

      Day 22 of cycles 1-9: questions about health, medications, etc., vital signs, blood tests.

      After the final dose of the study drug you will have an End of Treatment visit. The
      following tests and procedures will be done at this visit: questions about health,
      medications etc., physical exam, performance status, vital signs, neurological exam,
      questionnaires, bone imaging studies, bone marrow aspirate, blood tests, pregnancy test,
      education and counseling, collection of bone marrow, plasma and serum, urine test.

      After your End of Treatment visit, we would like to follow your status every 2 months until
      your disease gets worse. The following tests and procedures will be done at these follow-up
      visits: questions about health, medications, symptoms etc., blood tests and urine test.

      If you are one of the first twenty patients enrolled in the study you will also be asked to
      provide additional blood samples to study what the body does to the study drug. We will take
      one sample at five time points during cycle 1 and 2. Collection of these samples may require
      you to come back into the clinic on additional days when you are not receiving study drugs.

      You will be in this research study for about 15 months. You can be in this study for a
      maximum of 15 cycles. If your disease gets worse before the 15th cycle you will be taken off
      the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the objective response rate (PR [Partial Response] + VGPR [Very Good Partial Response] + CR [Complete Response]) of modified RVD (weekly subcutaneous bortezomib [Velcade], lenalidomide [Revlimid], and dexamethasone) in previously untreated multiple myeloma patients who are ineligible for high dose therapy with autologous stem cell transplant.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of Safety Profile</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the safety profile of modified RVD in previously untreated MM patients who are transplant-ineligible</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the progression-free survival of modified RVD</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the overall survival of modified RVD</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Response and Response Duration</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluate the time to response and response duration of modified RVD</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response Rate with Respect to Cytogenetic Characteristics</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the response rate with respect to cytogenetic characteristics of the bone marrow plasma cells.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate Pharmacokinetic Profile</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the pharmacokinetic profile of intravenous and subcutaneous bortezomib administration in combination with lenalidomide and dexamethasone.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate Pharmacogenomic Markers</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate pharmacogenomic markers among patients with treatment related neuropathy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Induction (Cycles 1-9): Lenalidomide orally, days 1-21. Bortezomib injection, days 1, 8, 15, 22. Dexamethasone orally, days 1, 2, 8, 9, 15, 16, 22, 23 (for subjects 75 years of age or younger), or Dexamethasone orally days 1, 8, 15, 22 (for subjects greater than 75 years of age)
Consolidation (cycles 10-15): Lenalidomide po daily (1-21). Bortezomib sc on days 1, 15</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lenalidomide</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Revlimid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bortezomib</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Velcade</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Documented symptomatic myeloma, with organ damage related to myeloma

          -  Myeloma that is measurable either by serum or urine evaluation of the monoclonal
             component or by assay of serum free light chains

          -  Must commit to complete abstinence from heterosexual contact or begin two acceptable
             method of birth control, one highly effective method and one additional effective
             (barrier) method

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Eligible for autologous stem cell transplantation

          -  HIV positive on combination antiretroviral therapy

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding

          -  Treated with any prior systemic therapy

          -  Primary amyloidosis or myeloma complicated by amyloidosis

          -  Receiving other investigational agents within 14 days of the start of this trial or
             during this trial

          -  Known brain metastases

          -  Poor tolerability or known allergy to any of the study drugs or similar compounds

          -  Intercurrent illness

          -  Previous history of another malignant condition except for basal cell carcinoma or
             stage I cervical cancer

          -  Inability to comply with an anti-thrombotic treatment regimen

          -  Peripheral neuropathy greater than or equal to grade 2
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Noopur Raje, MD</last_name>
    <phone>6177260711</phone>
    <email>nraje@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Noopur Raje, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-726-0711</phone>
      <email>nraje@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Noopur Raje, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jacob Laubach, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-632-4218</phone>
      <email>jlaubach@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jacob Laubach, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham and Women's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jacob Laubach, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-632-4218</phone>
      <email>jlaubach@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jacob Laubach, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Avigan, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-632-8696</phone>
      <email>daviga@bidmc.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Avigan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital/North Shore Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Danvers</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>01923</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andrew Yee, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-726-6801</phone>
      <email>ayee1@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrew Yee, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 12, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 15, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Noopur Raje</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Newly diagnosed</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone 21-phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bortezomib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
