<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="115924">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01815268</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GRC75-EXT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01815268</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>High Dose Influenza Vaccine in Nursing Homes</brief_title>
  <official_title>High Dose Influenza Vaccination and Morbidity &amp; Mortality in U.S. Nursing Homes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Insight Therapeutics, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Brown University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Healthcentric Advisors</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Case Western Reserve University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Insight Therapeutics, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to prospectively evaluate relative effectiveness of high dose
      influenza vaccine in preventing influenza mortality, hospitalization, and functional decline
      in a nursing home population in the U.S., compared to the standard dose trivalent seasonal
      influenza vaccine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      SUMMARY: This study includes estimated 6782 Medicare-certified nursing homes (NHs)
      co-located within 50 miles of the 122 cities reporting to Center for Disease Control and
      Prevention (CDC) weekly influenza surveillance. In total, 1000 facilities will be enrolled
      for random assignment to either 1) the licensed high dose (HD) trivalent influenza vaccine
      (Fluzone HD [HD vaccine]),or 2) the standard dose (SD) trivalent influenza vaccine (Fluzone
      [SD vaccine]) for their residents and free SD vaccine vs. usual care (no free vaccine) for
      staff.

      BACKGROUND: Lower respiratory tract infection (LRI), which includes pneumonia, bronchitis,
      and tracheobronchitis, is the leading cause of mortality and hospitalization in older
      adults, and NH residents. Often, the signs and symptoms of pneumonia, in particular, are not
      apparent in elderly patients, making diagnosis more complicated. In addition, clinician
      visits to these residents are few and sporadic and radiological facilities are not readily
      available. LRI may or may not directly lead to hospitalization, but LRIs are associated with
      considerable other morbidity than can result in hospitalization. Hospitalization rates for
      NH residents vary considerably between facilities, but the majority of hospitalizations
      occur during the 12 weeks in which influenza peaks each year.

      Influenza is the most common viral infection of older adults. Influenza and pneumonia
      account for the majority of infectious morbidity and mortality in late life, and possibly
      for at least some of temporally associated—and vaccine preventable—vascular mortality such
      as heart attacks and strokes.  Influenza can cause more than just viral pneumonia because it
      results in a systemic inflammatory response that is thrombogenic. Some experts believe that
      influenza vaccine can prevent thrombotic outcomes, such as strokes and heart attacks,
      mechanistically by reducing the overall inflammatory response through targeted priming of
      the immune system.

      Influenza vaccination has been associated with reduced hospitalization, strokes, heart
      attacks and death in non-institutional older adult populations, but the benefit of influenza
      vaccine for the oldest population has been questioned. Also, influenza vaccination rates
      vary substantially between NHs.

      OBJECTIVES: The primary objective is to estimate the differences in all-cause
      hospitalization rates during flu season experienced by long stay nursing home residents in
      facilities using the HD vaccine vs. usual care vaccination nursing homes. The secondary
      objective is to estimate the differences in the likelihood of Activities of Daily Living
      (ADL) functional decline experienced during the influenza season by long stay nursing home
      residents of facilities using the HD vaccine vs. the level of functional decline experienced
      by residents of usual care nursing homes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total influenza mortality per nursing home based on vaccination status</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>LINKED AT THE FACILITY LEVEL. The primary outcome measure will determine influenza mortality.
[Vaccine uptake information will be collected for flu season November 2013 to March 2014. There is a data lag of 18 months for this cohort, therefore data analysis will be completed by December 2016.]</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in activities of daily living (ADL) scores per NH resident by vaccination status</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>LINKED AT THE RESIDENT LEVEL. The secondary outcome measure evaluates comparative vaccine effectiveness for functional status of HD vaccine compared to no or SD vaccine. Changes in ADL scores from baseline (Oct 2013 or prior and closest to Oct 2013) to any post-baseline MDS assessment (2014).
[Vaccine uptake information will be collected for flu season November 2013 to March 2014. There is a data lag of 18 months for this cohort, therefore data analysis will be completed by December 2016.]</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in hospitalization claims based on staff vaccination status</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>LINKED AT THE FACILITY LEVEL. The exploratory outcome measure evaluates comparative cost effectiveness high dose vaccine compared to no or standard dose vaccine, and effect on clinical outcomes based on staff vaccine uptake. The facilities will be compared to test the main effect of staff vaccination on NH resident hospitalization rate.
[Staff vaccine uptake information will be collected for flu season November 2013 to March 2014. There is a data lag of 18 months for the NH cohort, therefore data analysis will be completed by December 2016.]</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">800</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HD Vaccine with Free Staff Vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>NH facilities randomized to receive high dose trivalent influenza vaccine (HD Fluzone) for the residents and provided free SD vaccine (Fluzone) for the staff.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HD Vaccine with No Free Staff Vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>NH facilities randomized to receive high dose trivalent influenza vaccine (HD Fluzone) for the residents and not provided free SD vaccine (Fluzone) for the staff.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SD Vaccine and Free Staff Vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>NH facilities randomized to receive SD influenza vaccine (Fluzone) for the residents and provided free SD vaccine (Fluzone) for the staff.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SD Vaccine with No Free Staff Vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>NH facilities randomized to receive SD influenza vaccine (Fluzone) for the residents and not provided free SD vaccine (Fluzone) for the staff.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HD Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>HD Vaccine with Free Staff Vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>HD Vaccine with No Free Staff Vaccine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SD Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>SD Vaccine and Free Staff Vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SD Vaccine with No Free Staff Vaccine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Free Staff Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>HD Vaccine with Free Staff Vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SD Vaccine and Free Staff Vaccine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No Free Staff Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>[Note: For the group 'No free staff vaccine', Insight will not be providing free SD vaccine, however, staff vaccine will be available as per standard of care.]</description>
    <arm_group_label>HD Vaccine with No Free Staff Vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SD Vaccine with No Free Staff Vaccine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Long-term care facilities within 50 miles of one of the 122 cities that serve as CDC
             surveillance sites

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Facilities already systematically administering HD vaccine to their residents

          -  Facilities having fewer than 50 long-stay residents

          -  Hospital-based facilities

          -  Facilities with more than 20% of the population under age 65

          -  Facilities not submitting Minimum Data Set (MDS) data
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stefan Gravenstein, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Case Western Reserve University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vincent Mor, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Brown University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ed Davidson, PharmD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Insight Therapeutics, LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Case Western Reserve University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brown University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02912</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Insight Therapeutics, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Norfolk</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23510</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.sanofipasteur.com/articles/1254-sanofi-pasteur%E2%80%99s-fluzone-high-dose-vaccine-significantly-more-effective-than-standard-dose-fluzone-vaccine-in-preventing-influenza-in-adults-65-years-of-age-and-older.html</url>
    <description>SANOFI PASTEUR'S FLUZONE HIGH-DOSE VACCINE SIGNIFICANTLY MORE EFFECTIVE THAN STANDARD DOSE FLUZONE VACCINE IN PREVENTING INFLUENZA IN ADULTS 65 YEARS OF AGE AND OLDER</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thompson WW, Shay DK, Weintraub E, Brammer L, Cox N, Anderson LJ, Fukuda K. Mortality associated with influenza and respiratory syncytial virus in the United States. JAMA. 2003 Jan 8;289(2):179-86.</citation>
    <PMID>12517228</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thompson WW, Shay DK, Weintraub E, Brammer L, Bridges CB, Cox NJ, Fukuda K. Influenza-associated hospitalizations in the United States. JAMA. 2004 Sep 15;292(11):1333-40.</citation>
    <PMID>15367555</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hayward AC, Harling R, Wetten S, Johnson AM, Munro S, Smedley J, Murad S, Watson JM. Effectiveness of an influenza vaccine programme for care home staff to prevent death, morbidity, and health service use among residents: cluster randomised controlled trial. BMJ. 2006 Dec 16;333(7581):1241. Epub 2006 Dec 1.</citation>
    <PMID>17142257</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deguchi Y, Nishimura K. Efficacy of Influenza Vaccine in Elderly Persons in Welfare Nursing Homes: Reduction in Risks of Mortality and Morbidity During an Influenza A (H3N2) Epidemic. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci. 2001 Jun;56(6):M391-4.</citation>
    <PMID>11382801</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gozalo PL, Pop-Vicas A, Feng Z, Gravenstein S, Mor V. Effect of influenza on functional decline. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2012 Jul;60(7):1260-7. doi: 10.1111/j.1532-5415.2012.04048.x. Epub 2012 Jun 21.</citation>
    <PMID>22724499</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barker WH, Borisute H, Cox C. A study of the impact of influenza on the functional status of frail older people. Arch Intern Med. 1998 Mar 23;158(6):645-50.</citation>
    <PMID>9521230</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jackson LA, Jackson ML, Nelson JC, Neuzil KM, Weiss NS. Evidence of bias in estimates of influenza vaccine effectiveness in seniors. Int J Epidemiol. 2006 Apr;35(2):337-44. Epub 2005 Dec 20.</citation>
    <PMID>16368725</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simonsen L, Viboud C, Taylor R. Influenza vaccination in elderly people. Lancet. 2005 Dec 17;366(9503):2086.</citation>
    <PMID>16360785</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fiore AE, Shay DK, Haber P, Iskander JK, Uyeki TM, Mootrey G, Bresee JS, Cox NJ; Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices (ACIP), Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Prevention and control of influenza. Recommendations of the Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices (ACIP), 2007. MMWR Recomm Rep. 2007 Jul 13;56(RR-6):1-54.</citation>
    <PMID>17625497</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kingston BJ, Wright CV Jr. Influenza in the nursing home. Am Fam Physician. 2002 Jan 1;65(1):75-8, 72.</citation>
    <PMID>11804444</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Menec VH, Black C, MacWilliam L, Aoki FY. The impact of influenza-associated respiratory illnesses on hospitalizations, physician visits, emergency room visits, and mortality. Can J Public Health. 2003 Jan-Feb;94(1):59-63.</citation>
    <PMID>12583681</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mor V, Intrator O, Unruh MA, Cai S. Temporal and Geographic variation in the validity and internal consistency of the Nursing Home Resident Assessment Minimum Data Set 2.0. BMC Health Serv Res. 2011 Apr 15;11:78. doi: 10.1186/1472-6963-11-78.</citation>
    <PMID>21496257</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 30, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 11, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Randomized Controlled Trial</keyword>
  <keyword>Influenza</keyword>
  <keyword>Influenza vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>Flu Vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>Fluzone</keyword>
  <keyword>HD Fluzone</keyword>
  <keyword>Nursing Home</keyword>
  <keyword>Hospitalization</keyword>
  <keyword>Mortality</keyword>
  <keyword>Health Care worker vaccination</keyword>
  <keyword>ADL decline</keyword>
  <keyword>Effectiveness</keyword>
  <keyword>Elderly</keyword>
  <keyword>Morbidity</keyword>
  <keyword>Nursing Home resident</keyword>
  <keyword>Frail</keyword>
  <keyword>Institutionalized</keyword>
  <keyword>Epidemiology</keyword>
  <keyword>CDC</keyword>
  <keyword>US</keyword>
  <keyword>city</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
