<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="102438">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01796860</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MS AFO</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01796860</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of Ankle Foot Orthoses on Gait in Multiple Sclerosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Impact of Ankle Foot Orthosis (AFO) on Gait Recovery in Select Individuals With Multiple Sclerosis (MS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate the impact of a specifically designed ankle foot
      orthosis (AFO, hinged, with tamarack joint and adjustable check strap) on the spatial and
      temporal gait parameters, electromyography (EMG), and walking endurance, in select
      individuals living with MS.  This orthotic is fabricated to allow ankle range of motion
      required for normal gait kinematics.  Additionally, it controls forward progression of the
      tibia during the stance phase of gait.  This study has three hypotheses 1. Individuals who
      are fit with the AFO will demonstrate improvements in spatial and temporal gait parameters
      2. Individuals who are fit with the AFO will demonstrate improvements in walking endurance,
      and 3. Individuals who are fit with the AFO will demonstrate improvements in muscle firing
      profiles/EMG measures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a non-randomized, single group (N=15), repeated measures study.  The study will take
      place at the David M. Crowley Research and Rehabilitation Lab in the School of Health
      Professions at University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center.  The outcome measures for
      the study include: 1. GAITRite System for temporal and spatial parameters, 2. EMG of the
      anterior tibialis, gastrocnemius, and vastus lateralis muscles, 3. 6 Minute Walk Test (gait
      endurance) 4. Lower extremity strength, 5. MS Fatigue scale, 6. Observational Gait Analysis
      - Video tape of over ground walking.  This study will be 13 weeks long.  Over the 13 week
      period, the subject will participate in 5 gait training sessions which will be at weeks 1,
      2, 3, 7, and 10.  They will be 60 minutes in duration.  Outcome measures will be assessed at
      the following times: initial (T1), week 5 (T2), and week 13 (T3).  Subjects will be closely
      monitored throughout the 13 week study and will be un-enrolled by self-request or the
      following medical reasons: 1. Acute exacerbation of MS symptoms, 2. New diagnosis with
      direct consequences affecting gait training, 3. Inability to tolerate the study AFO.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Modifications were made to protocol, new IRB pending
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in gait parameters from baseline testing using computerized gait analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Comptuerized gait analysis will be done at the time of enrollment, week 5 and week 13.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants will be asked to walk on a 12-16 foot long vinyl pad placed on the floor. The mat will record and analyze temporal and spatial gait parameters.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in muscle activity from baseline with surface electromyography (EMG) of key lower extremity muscles</measure>
    <time_frame>Surface EMG will be done at the time of enrollment, at week 5 and week 13.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Surface electromyography will be done on key muscles in the lower extremity (quadriceps, anterior tibialis, gastrocnemius) during computerized gait assessment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in  walking endurance from baseline using a 6-Minute Walk Test (6MWT)</measure>
    <time_frame>6MWT will be done at the time of enrollment, at week 5 and week 13.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Each participant will be asked to walk at a self-selected velocity on level surfaces for 6 minutes. They will be allowed to use assistive devices as necessary.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AFO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>All persons in the study will be fit with the same AFO (Tamarack joint with adjustable check strap).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AFO</intervention_name>
    <description>The purpose of this study is to investigate the impact of a specifically designed ankle foot orthosis (AFO, hinged, with tamarack joint and adjustable check strap) on the spatial and temporal gait parameters, electromyography (EMG), and walking endurance, in select individuals living with MS. Over the 13 week period, the subject will participate in 5 gait training sessions which will be at weeks 1, 2, 3, 7, and 10.</description>
    <arm_group_label>AFO</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals with a primary diagnosis of multiple sclerosis

          -  Individuals &gt;21 and &lt;60 years old

          -  Individuals who are able to maintain a walking velocity of 60 cm/sec for at least 2
             minutes independently or with the use of a single tip assistive device.

          -  Current or past history of single or bilateral AFO use, including neuroprostheses

          -  Evidence of weakness in plantarflexors

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The presence of co-morbidities (neuromuscular or musculoskeletal) that would
             negatively impact gait training

          -  Individuals with BMI with &gt;/= 35kg/m2

          -  Individuals with range of motion deficit in the ankle limiting passive range of
             motion to neutral dorsiflexion

          -  Individuals that will begin the use of Ampyra during the course of the study

          -  Individuals for whom the cost of an orthosis would represent a financial burden

          -  Individuals who are receiving concurrent physical therapy services elsewhere,

          -  Multiple Sclerosis Neuropsychological Questionnaire (MSNQ) of &gt;22

          -  Individuals for whom bilateral AFOs are indicated, but have different design
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, School of Health Professions</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 21, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Karen McCain</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor, School of Health Professions</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gait</keyword>
  <keyword>AFO</keyword>
  <keyword>MS</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
