<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="82436">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02078648</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STML-701-0114</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02078648</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy Study of SL-701, a Glioma-Associated Antigen Vaccine To Treat Recurrent Glioblastoma Multiforme</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1/2 Study of SL-701, a Subcutaneously Injected Multivalent Glioma-Associated Antigen Vaccine, in Adult Patients With Recurrent Glioblastoma Multiforme (GBM)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stemline Therapeutics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stemline Therapeutics, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the safety and efficacy of SL-701 as a treatment
      for recurrent glioblastoma multiform (GBM).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Characterize the safety and tolerability of SL-701</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months and ongoing</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimate the percent of patients alive 12 months after the initiation of SL-701 (OS-12)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimate the objective response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimate duration of response</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimate the percent of patients alive and progression-free survival at 6 months (PFS-6) after the initiation of SL-701.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimate the distributions of progression-free survival (PFS) and overall survival (OS).</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Adult Brain Glioblastoma</condition>
  <condition>Glioblastoma Multiforme</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SL-701; Imiquimod Cream 5% and Leukine as adjuvants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>SL-701 in Montanide 1.0mL injection taken from 0.7mL of SL-701 mixed at 1:1 ratio with 0.7mL of Montanide every 14 days for the first 155 days then every 28 days thereafter.
Imiquimod Cream 5% applied with each SL-701 administration and 24 hours after each SL-701 administration
Leukine [Granulocyte macrophage-colony stimulating factor (GM-CSF)] 150 micrograms administered within 20 minutes after each SL-701 administration</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SL-701; Imiquimod Cream 5%; Leukine 150 micrograms</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>SL-701; Imiquimod Cream 5% and Leukine as adjuvants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Imiquimod Cream 5%</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>SL-701; Imiquimod Cream 5% and Leukine as adjuvants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Leukine 150 micrograms</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>SL-701; Imiquimod Cream 5% and Leukine as adjuvants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years of age or older.

          -  Histologically confirmed GBM or World Health Organization (WHO) Grade IV variants
             (gliosarcoma, glioblastoma with oligodendroglial features, or giant cell
             glioblastoma).

          -  Unequivocal evidence of a first tumor recurrence or progression on the initial
             treatment regimen (prior to enrollment on this study), consisting of surgical
             resection, radiation, and temozolomide chemotherapy, as assessed by MRI or CT scan of
             the brain with and without contrast within 14 days prior to the start of SL-701.  If
             receiving corticosteroids, the dose must be stable or decreasing for at least 5 days
             prior to the scan.  Patients unable to undergo MRI because of non-compatible devices
             can be enrolled, provided CT scans are obtained and are of sufficient quality.
             Patients without non-compatible devices may not have CT scans performed to meet this
             requirement.  For each patient, the same imaging technique should be performed
             throughout the study, for purposes of assessing tumor response or progressive disease
             (PD).

          -  For patients who have undergone resection of recurrent or progressive tumor prior to
             study enrollment, the following conditions must apply:

               -  Recovery from the effects of surgery.

               -  Residual disease following resection of recurrent tumor is not mandated for
                  eligibility into the study.  To best assess the extent of residual disease
                  post-operatively, an MRI should be performed:

                    -  No later than 96 hours (h) in the immediate post-operative period; or

                    -  At least 4 weeks post-craniotomy (7 days for stereotactic biopsy), within
                       14 days prior to the start of SL-701, and on a corticosteroid dosage that
                       has been stable or decreasing for at least 5 days.

          -  No evidence of hemorrhage on the baseline MRI or CT scan other than those that are
             Grade ≤ 1 and either post-operative or stable on at least two consecutive scans.

          -  Recovery from prior therapy toxicity, defined as resolution of all treatment-related
             adverse events (AEs) to Grade ≤ 1 or pre-treatment baseline (except alopecia and
             lymphopenia).

          -  At least 12 weeks from prior radiotherapy to the start of SL-701 unless there is new
             enhancement outside of the radiation field or unequivocal histopathologic evidence of
             recurrent tumor.

          -  No chemotherapy or investigational agent for at least 3 weeks prior to the start of
             SL-701, with at least 6 weeks of elapsed time from last dose of nitrosoureas.

          -  Human leukocyte antigen (HLA)-A2 positive.

          -  If tumor tissue is collected and available prior to study entry, post-vaccine, or at
             any time point throughout the duration of the study, then a sample must be submitted
             for immunohistochemical analysis.

          -  Karnofsky performance status (KPS) score ≥ 70%.

          -  Adequate organ function, including the following:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1,000/μL, platelets ≥ 100,000/μL.

               -  Serum creatinine &lt; 1.5 × the upper limit of normal (ULN).

               -  Bilirubin &lt; 1.5 × ULN.

               -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &lt; 2.5 × ULN.

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test
             within 3 days prior to the start of SL-701 treatment.

          -  Female patients of childbearing potential and sexually active male patients must
             agree to use an acceptable form of contraception for heterosexual activity (ie, oral
             contraceptives, double barrier methods, hormonal injectable, transdermal, or
             implanted contraceptives, tubal ligation, or vasectomy of their sexual partner(s) for
             &gt; 40 days before Screening, during the study, and for 60 days after the last dose of
             study drug.  Men should not donate semen during the study and for 60 days after the
             last dose of study drug.

          -  Female patients without childbearing potential (spontaneous amenorrhea for &gt; 12
             months or surgically sterilized by tubal ligation, hysterectomy, or bilateral
             oophorectomy &gt; 6 months before Screening) are eligible for inclusion without
             contraceptive use restriction.

          -  Able and willing to comply with protocol requirements, in the opinion of the
             investigator.

          -  A written and voluntarily signed informed consent must be obtained from the patient
             or legally authorized representative, in accordance with local regulations, before
             the initiation of any study related procedures.  The patient or legally authorized
             representative must be able to read and understand the informed consent form (ICF).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior cancer chemotherapy, bevacizumab (or other vascular endothelial growth factor
             [VEGF]/VEGF receptor [VEGFR]-directed agent), or an investigational agent for
             recurrent/progressive GBM or prior bevacizumab as part of initial therapy.

          -  Contrast-enhancing tumor that is any of the following:

               -  Multi-focal (defined as two separate areas of contrast enhancement measuring at
                  least 1 cm in 2 planes that are not contiguous on either fluid-attenuated
                  inversion recovery (FLAIR) or T2 sequences);

               -  Associated with either diffuse subependymal or leptomeningeal dissemination; or

               -  ≥ 4 cm in any dimension.

          -  Requirement of systemic corticosteroid therapy &gt; 4 mg/day of dexamethasone or
             equivalent or requirement of increasing dose of systemic corticosteroids during the 7
             days prior to the start of SL-701 treatment.

          -  Surgical resection or major surgical procedure within 4 weeks prior to the start of
             SL-701, or stereotactic biopsy within 7 days prior to the start of SL-701.

          -  Radiation therapy, local therapy (except for surgical re-resection), or systemic
             therapy following first recurrence/progressive disease.  Excluded local therapies
             include stereotactic radiation boost, implantation of carmustine biodegradable wafers
             (Gliadel), intratumoral or convection-enhanced delivery administered agents, etc.

          -  Active infection requiring intravenous antibiotics.

          -  History of cancer (other than GBM) within the past 2 years that has metastatic or
             local recurrence potential and could negatively impact survival and/or potentially
             confound tumor response assessments within this study.

          -  Clinically significant cardiovascular disease (eg, uncontrolled or any New York Heart
             Association Class 3 or 4 congestive heart failure, uncontrolled angina, history of
             myocardial infarction or stroke within 6 months of study entry, uncontrolled
             hypertension or clinically significant arrhythmias not controlled by medication).

          -  Known immunosuppressive disease or active systemic autoimmune disease such as
             systemic lupus erythematosus, human immunodeficiency virus infection, Hepatitis B, or
             Hepatitis C, or has taken an immunosuppressive agent within 4 weeks prior to the
             start of SL-701 treatment.  Patients with vitiligo, type 1 diabetes mellitus,
             hypothyroidism due to autoimmune condition only requiring hormone replacement
             therapy, psoriasis not requiring systemic therapy, or conditions not expected to
             recur in the absence of an external trigger are permitted to enroll.

          -  Any condition which in the investigator's opinion makes the patient unsuitable for
             study participation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eric Rowinsky, MD</last_name>
    <phone>646-502-2304</phone>
    <email>erowinsky@stemline.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Henry Ford Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stephanie Marl, RN</last_name>
      <phone>313-916-7231</phone>
      <email>smarl1@hfhs.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tom Mikkelsen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 28, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 20, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Glioma Associated Antigen</keyword>
  <keyword>Vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>Adult</keyword>
  <keyword>Recurrent Glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunotherapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Imiquimod</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
