<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="163323">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02135796</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Echo in Septic Shock-1009957</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02135796</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ICU Echocardiography in Septic Shock</brief_title>
  <official_title>ICU Echocardiography in Resuscitation of Severe Sepsis and Septic Shock</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Intermountain Health Care, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Intermountain Health Care, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators hypothesize that not all patients with severe sepsis or septic shock with
      a Central Venous Oxygen Saturation (ScvO2) less than 70% have cardiac dysfunction that would
      benefit from inotropic therapy (a key strategy in early goal directed therapy in patients
      with sepsis). Echocardiography might show that despite an adequate Central Venous Pressure
      (CVP), intravascular volume status is low and further volume expansion is warranted.
      Alternatively, echocardiography may indicate that left atrial pressure is elevated, and
      further intravascular volume resuscitation should be limited. Such observations may lead to
      a role for echocardiography within the parameters of the early goal-directed therapy
      protocol that may improve treatment of cardiac dysfunction and hypovolemia.

      The study objective is to correlate echocardiographic findings with objective parameters,
      namely central venous pressure (CVP) and central venous oxygen saturation (ScvO2), measured
      during the early resuscitation of critically ill patients with severe sepsis and septic
      shock.

      Aim #1: Correlate echocardiographic findings of right ventricular (RV) systolic function and
      dilation, left ventricular (LV) systolic function and dilation, and left ventricular
      diastolic function with CVP and ScvO2 in the early hours of resuscitation in patients with
      severe sepsis and septic shock.

      Aim #2: Evaluate the change in RV and LV dysfunction over time in patients with severe
      sepsis and septic shock and correlate with mortality.

      Aim #3: Evaluate the efficacy of bedside echocardiography performed by the intensivist in
      the ICU in the evaluation of patients with severe sepsis and septic shock.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlate echo findings and CVP &amp; ScvO2</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 12 hours of Intensive Care Unit admission</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Correlate echocardiographic findings of right ventricular (RV) systolic function and dilation, left ventricular (LV) systolic function and dilation, and left ventricular diastolic function with CVP and ScvO2 in the early hours of resuscitation in patients with severe sepsis and septic shock.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">172</enrollment>
  <condition>Septic Shock</condition>
  <condition>Severe Sepsis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Severe Sepsis/Septic Shock</arm_group_label>
    <description>Individuals who are admitted to the Intensive Care Unit (ICU) with a serious infection called Sepsis or Septic Shock</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Echocardiography</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Severe Sepsis/Septic Shock</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients admitted to an Intensive Care Unit (ICU) with an initial diagnosis of severe
        sepsis or septic shock.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  at least 13 years of age

          -  suspected infection

          -  two or more systemic inflammatory response syndrome (SIRS) criteria (white blood cell
             count less than 4,000 per mm3 or greater than 12,000 per mm3 or differential with
             greater than 10% immature band forms

          -  heart rate greater than 90 beats per minute

          -  respiratory rate greater than 20 breaths per minute or PaCO2 less than 32 mmHg,

          -  temperature less than 36oC or greater than 38oC)

          -  refractory hypotension (a systolic blood pressure less than90 mmHg despite an
             intravenous fluid challenge of at least 20ml/kg),

          -  or evidence of hypoperfusion (a blood lactate concentration greater than 4mmol/L),

          -  And the intent of the clinical team to place a central venous catheter if one is not
             already in place.

          -  Enrollment of patients should occur within 8 hours of meeting criteria for severe
             sepsis or septic shock

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  known pregnancy

          -  primary diagnosis of acute coronary syndrome or

          -  major cardiac dysrhythmia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Intermountain Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Murray</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84157</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Lanspa, MD</last_name>
      <phone>801-507-6556</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Lanspa, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 8, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 8, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Septic Shock</keyword>
  <keyword>Severe Sepsis</keyword>
  <keyword>ICU</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Sepsis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Toxemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Shock</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Shock, Septic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
