<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="35159">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01915420</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ASSURE ROT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01915420</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The ASSURE ROT Registry: Bioresorbable Vascular Scaffold Following Rotablation for Complex Coronary Lesions</brief_title>
  <acronym>ASSURE ROT</acronym>
  <official_title>Postmarketing Surveillance Registry to Monitor Everolimus-eluting Bioresorbable Vascular Scaffold Following Rotational Atherectomy for the Treatment of Complex Coronary Lesions - The ASSURE ROT Registry</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical Care Center Prof. Mathey, Prof. Schofer, Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical Care Center Prof. Mathey, Prof. Schofer, Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The registry aims to evaluate the safety, performance and efficacy of the Everolimus-eluting
      bioresorbable vascular scaffold (BVS) system following rotational atherectomy in patients
      with complex de novo native coronary artery lesions in all-day clinical practice.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Bioresorbable scaffolds are transient implants. They act like drug-eluting metallic stents
      (DES) during the first 3 months by supporting the vessel wall thereby keeping the artery
      patent. Subsequently, resorption of the scaffold begins and its structure loosens. As a
      result of everolimus release, neointimal growth is inhibited similar to DES. Finally the
      implant is reabsorbed completely in about 2-3 years. BVS in terms of late stent thrombosis
      may be safer than DES. Transiently scaffolded vessels may regain their natural curvature and
      angulation as well as response to nitroglycerine and endothelial function.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <target_duration>3 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Major Adverse Cardiac Event (MACE)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Composite of ischemia driven target lesion revascularisation (TLR), myocardial infarction and cardiac death</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute procedural success</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of hospital stay (maximum of 7 days)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Achievement of final in-scaffold residual stenosis of &lt; 50% and TIMI flow 3 of the target site. Successful delivery and deployment of at least one study scaffold at the intended target lesion and successful withdrawal of the delivery system for all target lesions without occurrence of cardiac death, target vessel MI or repeat TLR during hospital stay (maximum of 7 days). In dual target lesion setting both lesions must meet clinical procedure success criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute device success</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Successful delivery and deployment of the first scaffold at the intended target lesion (in overlapping setting both planned scaffolds) and successful withdrawal of delivery system. Attainment of &lt; 50 % residual stenosis and TIMI flow 3 of the target site, using the BVS without the need for other non-	 study stents.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Scaffold thrombosis</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of intervention, and at 6, 12, 24, and 36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiac death</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of intervention, and at 6, 12,24, and 36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Myocardial infarction</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of intervention, and at 6, 12, 24, and 36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ischemia driven target lesion revascularisation (TLR)</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of intervention, participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay (an expected average of 3 days), at 6, 12, 24, and 36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Composite of ischemia driven target lesion revascularisation (TLR), myocardial infarction and cardial death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ischemia driven target vessel revascularisation (TVR)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 6, 12, 24, and 36 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>In-lesion % diameter stenosis</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and final at time of intervention and at 24 months FU</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>QCA: Independent CoreLab</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Minimal lumen diameter (MLD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and final at time of intervention and at 24 months FU</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>QCA: Independent CoreLab</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>In-scaffold late lumen loss (LLL)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 24 months FU</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">42</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <condition>Myocardial Ischemia</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Restenosis</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Stenosis</condition>
  <condition>Arteriosclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Arterial Occlusive Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Vascular Diseases</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with complex coronary artery lesions
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        The recommendation to implant BVS in an individual patient in whom rotational atherectomy
        of a complex target lesion has been conducted, is purely based on clinical grounds. These
        are determined by the instructions for use (IFU) of the BVS and by the clinical experience
        accumulated so far from clinical studies.These studies suggest that the BVS should be
        implanted under certain conditions, which are determined by the patient and the coronary
        lesion treated:

        Eligible:

        Regarding to patient

          -  Patient ≥ 18 and ≤ 75 years with a live expectancy of at least 5 years with ischemic
             heart disease (chronic, NSTEMI and unstable angina) due to one or more complex de
             novo native coronary artery lesions

          -  Patients with evidence of myocardial ischemia

        Regarding to lesion

          -  Reference vessel diameter ≥ 2.5 mm and ≤ 3.8 mm, visually estimated or by online QCA

          -  Percent diameter stenosis ≥ 50% and &lt; 100%, visually estimated or by online QCA

          -  TIMI ≥1

          -  Previous interventions of target vessel lesions should have been done ≥ 6 months
             prior to index procedure and &gt; 10 mm distal to the target lesion

          -  Previous interventions of non-target vessel lesions should have been done ≥ 30 days
             prior to index procedure

        Not eligible:

        Regarding to patient

          -  Patient in whom antiplatelet therapy and/or anticoagulant therapy is contraindicated

          -  Patient with a known hypersensitivity or contraindication to aspirin, both heparin
             and bivalirudin, clopidogrel, ticlopidine, prasugrel and ticagrelor, everolimus, poly
             (L-lactide), poly (D,L-lactide), or platinum, or with contrast sensitivity, who
             cannot be adequately premedicated

          -  Patient has a known diagnosis of acute myocardial infarction (STEMI) within 72 hours
             preceding the index procedure and CK and CK-MB have not returned within normal limits
             at the time of procedure

          -  Patient is currently experiencing clinical symptoms consistent with STEMI

          -  Patient has current unstable arrhythmias

          -  Patient has a known left ventricular ejection fraction &lt; 30%

          -  Patient has received a heart transplant or any other organ transplant or is waiting
             for any organ transplant

          -  Patient receiving or scheduled to receive chemotherapy for malignancy within 30 days
             prior to or after procedure

          -  Patient is receiving immunosuppression therapy and has known immunosuppressive or
             autoimmune disease

          -  Patient is receiving or scheduled to receive chronic anticoagulation therapy

          -  Elective surgery is planned within the first 6 month after the procedure that will
             require discontinuing either aspirin or clopidogrel

          -  Patient has a platelet count &lt; 100 000 cells/mm3 or &gt; 700 000 cells/mm3, a WBC of

          -  &lt; 3000 cells/mm3, or documented or suspected liver disease

          -  Patient has known renal insufficiency

          -  Patient has a history of bleeding diathesis or coagulopathy or will refuse blood
             transfusions

          -  Patient has cerebrovascular accident or transient ischemic neurological attack within
             the past six month

          -  Patient has had a significant GI or urinary bleed within the past six months

          -  Patient has extensive peripheral vascular disease that precludes safe 6 French sheath
             insertion

          -  Patient has other medical illness (e.g., cancer or congestive heart failure) or known
             history of substance abuse (alcohol, cocaine, heroin etc.) that may cause
             noncompliance with the clinical study plan, confound the data interpretation or is
             associated with a limited life expectancy (i.e., les than one year)

          -  Women of childbearing potential who have not undergone surgical sterilization or are
             not post- menopausal

        Regarding to lesion

        Target lesion(s) meets none of the following criteria:

          -  Aorto-ostial location

          -  Left main location

          -  Located within 2 mm of the origin of LAD or LCX

          -  Located within an arterial or saphenous vein graft or distal to a diseased (defined
             as vessel irregularity per angiogram and &gt; 20% stenosed lesion by visual estimation)
             arterial or saphenous vein graft

          -  Ostial lesion &gt; 40% stenosed by visual estimation or side branch requiring
             predilation

          -  Excessive tortuosity proximal to or within the lesion (extreme angulation proximal to
             or within the lesion)

          -  Restenotic from previous intervention

        Target vessel is not containing thrombus
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Detlef G Mathey, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical Care Center Prof. Mathey, Prof. Schofer GmbH</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Detlef G Mathey, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>+4940889009</phone>
    <phone_ext>152</phone_ext>
    <email>dgmathey@web.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical Care Center Prof. Mathey, Prof. Schofer GmbH</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>22391</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Detlef G Mathey, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+4940889009</phone>
      <phone_ext>152</phone_ext>
      <email>dgmathey@web.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joachim Schofer, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carsten Schwencke, PD Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Serruys PW, Onuma Y, Dudek D, Smits PC, Koolen J, Chevalier B, de Bruyne B, Thuesen L, McClean D, van Geuns RJ, Windecker S, Whitbourn R, Meredith I, Dorange C, Veldhof S, Hebert KM, Sudhir K, Garcia-Garcia HM, Ormiston JA. Evaluation of the second generation of a bioresorbable everolimus-eluting vascular scaffold for the treatment of de novo coronary artery stenosis: 12-month clinical and imaging outcomes. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2011 Oct 4;58(15):1578-88. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2011.05.050.</citation>
    <PMID>21958884</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dudek D, Onuma Y, Ormiston JA, Thuesen L, Miquel-Hebert K, Serruys PW. Four-year clinical follow-up of the ABSORB everolimus-eluting bioresorbable vascular scaffold in patients with de novo coronary artery disease: the ABSORB trial. EuroIntervention. 2012 Jan;7(9):1060-1. doi: 10.4244/EIJV7I9A168.</citation>
    <PMID>21959320</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Basavarajaiah S, Naganuma T, Latib A, Colombo A. Can bioabsorbable scaffolds be used in calcified lesions? Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2013 Apr 16. doi: 10.1002/ccd.24939. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>23592566</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Patel N, Banning AP. Bioabsorbable scaffolds for the treatment of obstructive coronary artery disease: the next revolution in coronary intervention? Heart. 2013 Mar 8. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>23474621</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 11, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 29, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Drug eluting stent</keyword>
  <keyword>Bioabsorbable</keyword>
  <keyword>Bioresorbable</keyword>
  <keyword>Coronary Stent</keyword>
  <keyword>Scaffold</keyword>
  <keyword>Stents</keyword>
  <keyword>Angioplasty</keyword>
  <keyword>Coronary Artery Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Stentthrombosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Rotational  atherectomy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Arterial Occlusive Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arteriosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Stenosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Restenosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
