<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="40184">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01905423</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201103313</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01905423</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Optimization of Mass Drug Administration With Existing Drug Regimens for Lymphatic Filariasis and Onchocerciasis</brief_title>
  <acronym>DOLF-Indo</acronym>
  <official_title>Optimization of Mass Drug Administration With Existing Drug Regimens for Lymphatic Filariasis and Onchocerciasis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>University of Indonesia IRB:</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Approximately 3,500 people will participate per year. The study population will include
      females and males over 5 years of age who live in filariasis endemic areas. The study will
      be performed in Indonesia in B. timori and W. bancrofti endemic areas over a period of 4
      years. Participants will be studied only once in cross-sectional surveys. Some subjects may
      be included in more than one annual population survey, but this is not a longitudinal study.
      Purpose of the study is to evaluate different mass drug administration (MDA) regimens for
      lymphatic filariasis and also to study the impact of MDA on soil transmitted helminth
      infections (STH).  MDA will administered by others (e.g., Ministry of Health). Results of
      this study may enhance efforts to control and eliminate these important neglected tropical
      diseases.

      The investigators will test the hypothesis that accelerated mass drug administration will be
      superior to annual MDA for elimination of lymphatic filariasis and for control of soil
      transmitted helminth infections (STH):

        1. Compare the relative impact and cost effectiveness of annual vs. twice yearly mass drug
           administration (MDA) for elimination of lymphatic filariasis (LF).

        2. Study the impact of annual vs. semiannual MDA on soil transmitted helminth (STH)
           infection in these populations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Lymphatic filariasis (LF) is a deforming and disabling infectious disease that causes
      elephantiasis and genital deformity (especially hydroceles). The infection affects some 120
      million people in 81 countries in tropical and subtropical regions with well over 1 billion
      people at risk of acquiring the disease. LF is caused by Wuchereria bancrofti and Brugia
      spp. (B. malayi and B.timori), nematode parasites that are transmitted by mosquitoes. This
      study is based on the assumption that currently used mass drug administration (MDA) regimens
      and schedules are not optimal for achieving elimination of LF. These regimens (either annual
      Albendazole (Alb) 400 mg plus diethylcarbamazine (DEC) 6 mg/kg or Alb 400 mg plus ivermectin
      (Iver) 200 µg/kg for LF) were developed more than 10 years ago.

      Drugs used for LF MDA are also active against soil transmitted helminth infections (STH,
      e.g., Ascaris, Hookworm, and Trichuris). De-worming campaigns using anthelminthics usually
      target special groups of the population, such as schoolchildren, and have limited impact on
      the transmission. Treatment of the total population and semiannual treatments may reduce
      re-infection considerably and will most likely lead to reduced infection densities and
      infection prevalences. Suppression of STH is an important ancillary benefit of MDA programs
      for filarial infections.

      Purpose: The study aims to compare the effectiveness once yearly (1X) versus twice yearly
      (2X) mass drug administration (MDA) for the elimination of lymphatic filariasis and for
      control of soil-transmitted helminths (intestinal parasites) in large populations. Mass drug
      administration will be provided by the Indonesia Ministry of Health. This project will
      assess the impact of the public health program.

      Procedures: Study procedures include collection of finger prick blood that will be tested
      for microfilaremia and for serology testing (antigenemia and antibody testing). Stool
      samples will be collected to detect STH infections. All assays will be performed in
      Indonesia (filarial serology tests, blood smears for detection of microfilariae (MF), and
      stool examinations for detection of worm eggs).

      Washington University researchers developed the protocol, will provide training and guidance
      to Indonesian researchers, and work with them to analyze the data. Indonesian researchers
      will consent the participants, obtain stool and blood specimens, perform laboratory tests on
      the specimens, and enter data on participants and lab results.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Ecologic or Community, Time Perspective: Cross-Sectional</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Microfilaria prevalence in blood by microscopy</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Microfilariae (filarial parasites) will be detected in blood smears by microscopy. Samples will be collected in annual community surveys. Microfilaremia is a categorical variable (positive or negative). Prevalence rates are expressed as % positive.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Filarial antigenemia in blood and worm parasite eggs in stool by microscopy</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Secondary outcomes for the study include prevalence of filarial antigenemia (detected with the Binax Filariasis Now card test) and prevalence of worm eggs in stool detected by the Kato-Katz test. Both of these prevalence outcomes are qualitative with no units of measure (positive or negative). Prevalence date are expressed as % positive. Other secondary outcome measures will be intensity of parasite infections (microfilariae per ml of blood and the number of worm eggs per gram of stool).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">14000</enrollment>
  <condition>Lymphatic Filariasis</condition>
  <condition>Soil Transmitted Helminth Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Annual MDA treated Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group will receive annual MDA (Albendazole 400 mg plus diethylcarbamazine 6 mg/kg) which will be administered by the Indonesian Ministry of Health as part of their national filariasis elimination program.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Semiannual MDA treated group</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group will receive semiannual MDA (Albendazole 400 mg plus diethylcarbamazine 6 mg/kg) which will also be administered by the Indonesian Ministry of Health.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Albendazole and diethylcarbamazine</intervention_name>
    <description>Albendazole 400 mg plus diethylcarbamazine 6 mg/kg once yearly vs twice yearly</description>
    <arm_group_label>Annual MDA treated Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Semiannual MDA treated group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Albenza (Albendazole, also known as ALB)</other_name>
    <other_name>Diethylcarbamazine, Also known as DEC, (N, N-diethyl-4-methyl-1-piperazine carboxamide dihydrogen citrate). ATC Code: P02CB02 QP52AH02</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Study procedures include collection of finger prick blood that will be tested for
      microfilaremia and for serology testing (antigenemia and antibody testing). We will also
      collect stool samples to detect STH infections.

      All assays will be performed in Indonesia (filarial serology tests, MF smears, stool
      examinations).
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study populations are people who live in areas of Indonesia that are endemic for
        lymphatic filariasis.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Areas should be endemic for filariasis and have limited or no prior experience with
             MDA. Males and Females  greater than 5 years of age.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children less than 6 years of age.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter U Fischer, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gary J Weil, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Taniawati Supali, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Indonesia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gary J Weil, MD</last_name>
    <phone>314-747-5198</phone>
    <email>Gweil@dom.wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Peter U Fischer, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>314-747-5198</phone>
    <email>PUFische@dom.wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Indonesia, Department of Parasitology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jakarta</city>
        <state>Java</state>
        <zip>10430</zip>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Taniawati Supali, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>011 62 21 391 4607</phone>
      <email>Taniawati@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Taniawati Supali, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Indonesia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.dolf.wustl.edu/</url>
    <description>Death to Onchocerciasis and Lymphatic Filariasis (DOLF)</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 18, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 11, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gary Weil, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine/ Microbiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Filariasis</keyword>
  <keyword>Albendazole</keyword>
  <keyword>Diethylcarbamazine</keyword>
  <keyword>STH Soil Transmitted Helminths</keyword>
  <keyword>MDA Mass Drug Administration</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Elephantiasis, Filarial</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Elephantiasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Filariasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Helminthiasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Onchocerciasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Albendazole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diethylcarbamazine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
