<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="45331">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02024126</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TOM-TOR-2009</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>KI-TOM-TOR-2013</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02024126</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dose-response Effects of Medical Exercise Therapy in Patients With Osteoarhritis of the Knee</brief_title>
  <official_title>Dose-response Effects of Medical Exercise Therapy in Patients With Osteoarhritis of the Knee - A Nordic Multicenter Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Karolinska Institutet</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sweden</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Västervik hospital (Västervik)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>City Rehab (Luleå)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Norway</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Moholt Fysioterapi (Trondheim)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Rosenborg klinikken (Trondheim)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Frisk 3 (Mosjöen)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Karolinska Institutet</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Sweden: Karolinska Institutet</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Osteoarthritis (OA) is one of the most common form of diseases in the adult population, and
      approximately 800 000 people in Sweden (population of 9 million people) suffer from this
      disease, which causes joint pain, stiffness, swelling, loss of function and sick leave.
      Studies from Sweden, United Kingdom and USA show that costs for osteoarthritis are about
      1-2.5 % of GDP.

      There is increasing evidence that exercise therapy is effective for patients with knee OA.
      However, there is little knowledge what type of exercises, combination of exercises and
      exercise dosage is most effective.

      In this present clinical trial, which is a Nordic collaborative project with researchers
      from three different research groups in Sweden and Norway, we intend to investigate short
      and long-term effects comparing high repetitive high dosage medical exercise therapy (each
      treatment lasting 80 to 90 minutes) versus a relatively low repetitive low dosage exercise
      program (each treatment lasting 25 to 30 minutes) in patients diagnosed with knee OA.
      Patients in both intervention groups receive three treatments a week for 12 weeks making a
      total of 36 treatments.

      Primary outcome is pain (VAS) and function (The Knee Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score
      (KOOS)). Secondary outcome is three different functional tests. Regarding predictors for
      outcome, we plan also to investigate different psychosocial variables as well as patient's
      beliefs regarding exercise.

      Patients are being assessed at inclusion, at end of intervention (3 months), and at six and
      12 months after end of treatment. We are also planning to assess pain and function during
      the intervention period after every 6th treatment, a total of six evaluations. The
      physiotherapists performing the objective tests at inclusion and at end of treatment are
      blinded in relation to intervention group.

      In this randomized controlled trial we are planning to include a total of 200 patients from
      primary health care settings, two in Norway and two in Sweden, with radiographic-verified
      knee OA with knee pain and decreased function. The patients have to be within the 45 to 85
      age group. Patients are excluded if they have been scheduled for knee surgery or have some
      other form of illness/disease that limits the exercise tolerance (e.g. heart disease or
      systemic/metabolic diseases or chronic obstructive airways disease).

      A major goal is to grade exercises so that they are performed pain-free or close to
      pain-free in both intervention groups. The principle of deloading is used to meet this goal
      using a high number of repetitions in sets as pain modulation. The exercises are
      standardized for both exercise programs, however individualized and graded continuously in
      relation to the patient's clinical status. All treatments are carried out under the
      supervision of experienced physiotherapists.

      The results from this study will give new information about the effectiveness of graded
      exercise therapy in patients with knee OA, and new knowledge if outcome can be related to
      the exercise dosage performed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Osteoarthritis (OA) is one of the most common form of diseases in the adult population, and
      approximately 800 000 people in Sweden (population of 9 million people) suffer from this
      disease, which causes joint pain, stiffness, swelling, loss of function and sick leave.
      Studies from Sweden, United Kingdom and USA show that costs for osteoarthritis are about
      1-2.5 % of GDP.

      There is increasing evidence that exercise therapy is effective for patients with knee OA.
      However, there is little knowledge what type of exercises, combination of exercises and
      exercise dosage is most effective.

      In this present clinical trial, which is a Nordic collaborative project with researchers
      from three different research groups in Sweden and Norway, we intend to investigate short
      and long-term effects comparing high repetitive high dosage medical exercise therapy (each
      treatment lasting 80 to 90 minutes) versus a relatively low repetitive low dosage exercise
      program (each treatment lasting 25 to 30 minutes) in patients diagnosed with knee OA.
      Patients in both intervention groups receive three treatments a week for 12 weeks making a
      total of 36 treatments.

      Primary outcome is pain (VAS) and function (The Knee Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score
      (KOOS)). Secondary outcome is three different functional tests. Regarding predictors for
      outcome, we plan also to investigate different psychosocial variables as well as patient's
      beliefs regarding exercise.

      Patients are being assessed at inclusion, at end of intervention (3 months), and at six and
      12 months after end of treatment. We are also planning to assess pain and function during
      the intervention period after every 6th treatment, a total of six evaluations. The
      physiotherapists performing the objective tests at inclusion and at end of treatment are
      blinded in relation to intervention group.

      In this randomized controlled trial we are planning to include a total of 200 patients from
      primary health care settings, two in Norway and two in Sweden, with radiographic-verified
      knee OA with knee pain and decreased function. The patients have to be within the 45 to 85
      age group. Patients are excluded if they have been scheduled for knee surgery or have some
      other form of illness/disease that limits the exercise tolerance (e.g. heart disease or
      systemic/metabolic diseases or chronic obstructive airways disease).

      A major goal is to grade exercises so that they are performed pain-free or close to
      pain-free in both intervention groups. The principle of deloading is used to meet this goal
      using a high number of repetitions in sets as pain modulation. The exercises are
      standardized for both exercise programs, however individualized and graded continuously in
      relation to the patient's clinical status. All treatments are carried out under the
      supervision of experienced physiotherapists.

      The results from this study will give new information about the effectiveness of graded
      exercise therapy in patients with knee OA, and new knowledge if outcome can be related to
      the exercise dosage performed.

        Osteoarthritis is one of the most common form of diseases in the adult population, and
      approximately 800 000 people in Sweden (population of approximately 9 million people) suffer
      from this disease, which causes joint pain, stiffness, swelling, loss of function and sick
      leave. Studies from Sweden, United Kingdom (UK) and USA show that costs for osteoarthritis
      are about 1-2.5 % of GDP. With increasing life expectancies and the general decrease in
      physical activity in western industrialized countries, it is expected that more people will
      suffer from this disease. In a recent international literature review of clinical studies on
      the effectiveness of exercise therapy, the authors concluded that there is some evidence
      that therapeutic exercise is effective reducing knee pain and improving activities of daily
      living. In a compilation of scientific studies by the Swedish Council on Technology
      Assessment in Health Care (SBU), it was concluded that strength and flexibility exercises
      resulted in positive short-term effects compared to information only. However, there is
      currently no scientific study that has evaluated dose-response effects of exercise therapy.
      To improve life quality for individuals with osteoarthritis and the use of exercise therapy
      in primary and secondary health care settings, research on dose response effects in patients
      with osteoarthritis is important. This view is supported by various systematic reviews
      including the report from Swedish Council on Health Technology Assessment (SBU) latest
      compilation.

      Exercise dosage is a factor of exercise frequency, intensity and duration. Recent clinical
      trials show positive effects at both short term-(end of intervention) and at long term
      follow ups (6- and 12 months), in favor of  high repetitive high dosage medical exercise
      therapy (MET) compared to a relatively lower exercise dosage in patients with long-term
      subacromial pain and in patients with long term patello femoral pain syndrome. Compared to
      treatment as usual, medical exercise therapy has also been shown to be effective as
      postsurgical rehabilitation after arthroscopic surgery in patients with knee pain with a
      verified ruptured mensicus. In this present clinical trial, which is a Nordic collaborative
      project with researchers from three different research groups in Sweden and Norway, we
      intend to investigate short and long-term effects comparing high repetitive high dosage
      medical exercise therapy versus a low repetitive low dosage exercise program in patients
      diagnosed with knee osteoarthritis. Primary outcome is pain (VAS) and knee function (The
      Knee Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS)). Since it is unknown which patients
      will respond to the different exercise dosages, we will also look at different prognostic
      factors related to patient`s beliefs regarding exercise therapy as well as different
      psychosocial variables as anxiety, depression, fear of movement, catastrophizing, life
      satisfaction and level of self-efficacy. We hope this study will increase our knowledge
      regarding positive and negative predictors for outcome.

      Thus, the main aim of the study is to evaluate two modes of exercise therapy  focusing on
      exercise dosage; 1) medical exercise therapy (MET) with an exercise dosage lasting 80 - 90
      minutes duration at each treatment compared to; 2) low dosage exercise therapy (conventional
      exercise treatment) lasting 20-30 minutes at each treatment) in patients with long-term knee
      osteoarthritis. All patients in both intervention groups will receive three treatments a
      week for 12 weeks making a total of 36 treatments. Physiotherapists at four different
      intervention centers will treat patients from both exercise interventions. Assessments will
      be performed at inclusion, after end of treatment, and at six and 12 months follow up.
      Objective tests (20 meter walk test, sit to stand in 30 seconds and maximum number of single
      knee flexion/extension in 30 seconds) is tested out at inclusion and at end of treatment.
      The testers are blinded regarding intervention group. Questionnaires are filled out by the
      patient at inclusion, end of treatment, at six and 12 months follow up. To assess when
      possible clinical interesting changes start to occur during the three month treatment
      period, patients are filling out KOOS (function) and VAS (pain) after every 6th treatment
      making a total of six measurements during the intervention period.

      Patients are recruited from primary care health care settings in Västervik and Luleå in
      Sweden and in Trondheim and Mosjöen in Norway. Patients are informed about the project both
      verbally and also through written information. Based on this information, patients that
      would like to participate in the project, contact the local investigation center to be
      assessed for possible inclusion. We are planning to include a total of 200 patients with
      radiographic-verified knee osteoarthritis with knee pain and decreased function. The
      patients have to be within the 45 to 85 age group, come for three treatments a week, a total
      of 36 treatments for 12 weeks, and must not have had any treatments or organized form of
      exercise therapy for their knee pain the last three months. Patients are also excluded if
      they have been scheduled for knee surgery or have some other form of illnesses/disease that
      limits exercise tolerance (e.g. heart disease or systemic/metabolic diseases or chronic
      obstructive airways disease). Patients that fulfill the inclusion criteria will be
      randomized either to high repetitive, high dosage medical exercise therapy or low repetitive
      low dosage exercise therapy.

      Each treatment in the high repetitive high dosage MET group consist of 20 minutes global
      exercise (e.g. stationary cycling), then four local knee exercises either open or closed
      chain performing three sets of 30 repetitions or five minutes continuous repetitions, then
      another five minutes cycling followed by another four local knee exercises three sets of 30
      repetitions or five minutes continuous repetitions and finishing with 10 minutes cycling.
      Each treatment lasts 80 to 90 minutes. The patients in this group shall also perform one
      home exercise every day performing three sets of five minutes deloaded knee extension with
      therabands. In the low dosage exercise group the patients perform a total of five exercises;
      10 minutes warm up using a stationary bicycle, then four different knee exercises performing
      two sets of 10 repetitions. Each treatment last 20 to 30 minutes.

      For all patients in both intervention groups the same methods are applied for testing out
      exercises at the start of the treatment, and for grading exercises during the treatment
      period. A major goal is to grade exercises so that they are performed pain-free or close to
      pain-free in both intervention groups. The exercises are standardized for both exercise
      programs, however individualized and graded continuously in relation to the patient's
      clinical status. All treatments are carried out under the supervision of experienced and
      skilled physiotherapists.

      The treating physiotherapists are instructed to be neutral regarding their beliefs of which
      treatment they believe is most effective informing the patient; in this study we are
      comparing two different forms of exercise therapy and we do not know if one exercise mode is
      better than the other or if they have equal effects.

      The theoretical basis for MET and the exercise progressions have been described in
      scientific articles and book chapters. Self-assessed pain, function and quality of life are
      monitored both during treatment and after treatment, and at six and 12 months follow-up.
      Prognostic markers evaluated by following analyze background information and early test
      results relate to the long-term treatment outcome. Health economic calculation is done by
      synchronizing the data obtained with the Insurance central registry.

      Our project team has extensive experience with the practical implementation of clinical
      controlled studies and analytical methodology linked to registries and health economic cost
      estimates. From this study we expect increased knowledge of whether clinical outcomes from
      exercise therapy may be related to exercise dosage and how exercise therapy need to be
      individualized according to the patient's history, clinical picture and coping strategies
      obtaining. In a recent report from the Swedish Council on Health Technology Assessment (SBU)
      they requested such data evaluating both the effects of exercise treatment analyzes that
      support personalized rehabilitation.

      The results from this study will give new information about the effectiveness of exercise
      therapy for patients with knee osteoarthritis, and new knowledge if outcome can be related
      to the dosage of exercise performed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Self-assessed function (KOOS) at three months follow-up (other follow-ups with this measure includes six and 12 months follow-up)</measure>
    <time_frame>At three months follow-up, i.e. after end of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary outcome measure is the disease specific Knee injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS). The KOOS assesses the patients' self-report of  pain, other symptoms, activities of daily living, sport and recreation function, and knee-related quality of life, answering 42 questions which take about 10 minutes to complete. The KOOS is scored from 0 to 100, separately for each subscale, 0 indicating extreme problems and 100 indicating no problems.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in self assessed pain using a visal analogue scale (VAS) at three months follow-up (other follow-ups with this measure includes six and 12 months follow-up)</measure>
    <time_frame>At three months follow-up, i.e. after end of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Pain is measured using a 100 mm long line with no pain at 0 and the worst imaginable pain at 100 mm. The patient make a line vertically on the 100mm long line according to the pain experience.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>After treatment at three months follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Reflects patients satisfaction with treatment, using self-rated Patient Satisfaction scale (6 point scale)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety and depression</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, at three months, at six months and at one year follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Hospital Anxiety and Depression scale (HAD), measured with HAD questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Catastrophizing</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, at three months, at six months and at one year follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients level of catastrophizing using Catastrophizing Scale (PCS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tama Scale of Kinesiophobia (TSK)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, at three months, at six months and at one year follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients beliefs  and attitudes regarding pain and physical activity using the self-rated Tampa Scale of Kinesiophobia (TSK).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>20 min walk test.</measure>
    <time_frame>At inclusion and at three months follow-up, i.e. after end of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>20 m walk test. Patients are asked to walk between two visible lines marked on the floor; first with their usual pace, and then at the maximal pace the patient feel secure.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>30s Maximal Repeated Unilateral Knee Bending test</measure>
    <time_frame>At inclusion and at three months follow-up, i.e. after end of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The test evaluates the maximum number of knee bends in 30 seconds performed on one leg in standing. Both (legs)knees are tested</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>the Five Time Repeated Chair Stands.</measure>
    <time_frame>At inclusion and at three months follow-up, i.e. after end of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The patient is seated in a standard chair (seat height, 40 cm) without armrests, and is instructed to rise to a fully erect standing position five times as fast as possible without using their hands. Outcome is time the patient use to perform the five time repeated chair stands.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Knee Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High dosage exercise therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>High dosage exercise therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low dosage exercise therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Low dosage exercise therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Exercise therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>High dosage exercise therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Low dosage exercise therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age 45-85 yrs with an x-ray verified knee osteoarthritis with pain and decreased
             function.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inflammatory joint disease, current anterior cruciate ligament injury, hip symptoms
             more aggravating than the knee symptoms, scheduled to have knee replacement surgery
             within 12 months, and co-morbidities not allowing exercise like cardiovascular,
             respiratory, systemic, or metabolic conditions limiting exercise tolerance.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Björn O Äng, Associate prof</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Karolinska Institutet</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tom A Torstensen, PhD-cand</last_name>
    <email>Tom.Torstensen@ki.se</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Karolinska Institutet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Huddinge</city>
        <state>Stockholm</state>
        <zip>SE-14183</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tom Arild Torstensen, PhD-student</last_name>
      <phone>+46707344102</phone>
      <email>Tom.Torstensen@ki.se</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Björn O Äng, Associated prof</last_name>
      <phone>+46852488861</phone>
      <email>Bjorn.Ang@ki.se</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tom A Torstensen, PhD-cand</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 26, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 17, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Karolinska Institutet</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Björn Äng</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Knee osteoarthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>RCT</keyword>
  <keyword>Intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Knee pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Muticenter</keyword>
  <keyword>Knee function</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
