<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="58651">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01838434</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A051201</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-01734</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U10CA031946</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01838434</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lenalidomide and Rituximab With or Without Idelalisib in Treating Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Mantle Cell Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/Randomized Phase II Trial of Idelalisib, Lenalidomide and Rituximab in Patients With Relapsed/Refractory Mantle Cell Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Alliance for Clinical Trials in Oncology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Celgene Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Gilead Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Alliance for Clinical Trials in Oncology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This Phase I/II trial studies the safety and effectiveness of lenalidomide in combination
      with rituximab with or without idelalisib. Biological therapies, such as lenalidomide, may
      stimulate the immune system in different ways and stop cancer cells from growing. Monoclonal
      antibodies, such as rituximab, can block cancer growth in different ways. Some block the
      ability of cancer cells to grow and spread. Others find cancer cells and help kill them or
      carry cancer-killing substances to them. Idelalisib may stop the growth of cancer cells by
      blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell growth. It is not yet known whether
      lenalidomide and rituximab is more effective with or without idelalisib in treating mantle
      cell lymphoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Outline: This is a phase I, dose-escalation study followed by a phase II study.

      The phase I treatment plan includes the following:

        1. Lenalidomide will be tested at sequential dose levels in a standard 3+3 design.

             1. Dose Level 0 = 15mg/day for days 1-21 every 28 days

             2. Dose Level 1 = 20mg/day for days 1-21 every 28 days and

             3. Dose Level 2 = 25mg/day for days 1-21 every 28 days.

           Patients can continue lenalidomide for up to 48 weeks (12 cycles) of treatment.

        2. Idelalisib will be orally administered starting at Dose Level 1 (150 mg twice daily)
           for continuous 28-day cycles until progression, intolerence, or patient/physician
           discretion.

        3. Rituximab will be administered intravenously at 375 mg/m2 for cycle 1 (ie, cycle 1, day
           1, day 8, day 15, day 22) and then on day 1 of cycles 4,6,8,10. There will be no dose
           reductions or escalations of rituximab.

      Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 treatment arms in the Phase II treatment plan described in
      the &quot;Arms&quot; section. The primary and secondary objectives for this study are:

        1. Phase I Primary Objective: To determine the safety and tolerability of the combination
           of lenalidomide and rituximab with idelalisib in sequential dose cohorts.

        2. Phase II Primary Objective: To determine the progression-free survival (PFS) of the
           combination of lenalidomide and rituximab, with or without idelalisib in a randomized
           phase II design.

        3. Phase II Secondary Objectives:

             1. To determine the overall response rate (ORR), complete response rate (CR), and
                overall survival (OS) of the combination of lenalidomide and rituximab, with or
                without idelalisib in a randomized phase II design.

             2. To determine the prognostic and/or predictive significance of proliferation
                markers and cell cycle components in patients with relapsed/refractory mantle cell
                lymphoma (MCL) treated with idelalisib and lenalidomide.

             3. To determine whether phosphorylated protein kinase B (pAKT) expression levels are
                correlated with response to idelalisib plus lenalidomide.

             4. To determine whether notch homolog 1, translocation-association (NOTCH1)
                intracellular domain (ICD) immunohistochemistry (IHC) correlates with mutation and
                outcome in MCL patients treated with idelalisib and lenalidomide.

             5. To determine whether sex determining region Y-box 11 (SOX11) expression correlates
                with response in patients with relapsed/refractory MCL treated with idelalisib and
                lenalidomide.

             6. To correlate cereblon (CRBN) expression with response in patients with
                relapsed/refractory MCL treated with idelalisib and lenalidomide.

             7. To evaluate several plasma cytokines and correlate observed changes to objective
                response rates.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of idelalisib and lenalidomide, determined according to incidence of dose-limiting toxicity (DLT) graded using the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0 (Phase I)</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival (PFS) of the combination of lenalidomide and rituximab, with or without idelalisib (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Time between registration and disease progression or death, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS) (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate (partial or complete response) (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">99</enrollment>
  <condition>Relapsed/Refractory Mantle Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>lenalidomide and rituximab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Lenalidomide will be administered orally on days 1-21, repeated every 28 days for a maximum of 12 cycles (48 weeks). Rituximab will be administered intravenously and weekly for cycle 1 (i.e. cycle 1, day 1, day 8, day 15, day 22) and then on day 1 of cycles 4, 6, 8, and 10. (Phase II)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>lenalidomide, rituximab and idelalisib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Lenalidomide will be administered orally  and daily on days 1-21, repeated every 28 days for a maximum of 12 cycles (48 weeks). Rituximab will be administered intravenously and weekly for cycle 1 (i.e. cycle 1, day 1, day 8, day 15, day 22) and then on day 1 cycles 4, 6, 8, and 10. Idelalisib will be orally administered  for continuous 28-day cycles until progression, intolerance, or patient/physician discretion. (Phase II)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>lenalidomide</intervention_name>
    <description>given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>lenalidomide and rituximab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>lenalidomide, rituximab and idelalisib</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>idelalisib</intervention_name>
    <description>given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>lenalidomide, rituximab and idelalisib</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>rituximab</intervention_name>
    <description>given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>lenalidomide and rituximab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>lenalidomide, rituximab and idelalisib</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        1. Documentation of Disease:

               1. Histologically documented mantle cell lymphoma, with the following
                  immunophenotypic characteristics: cluster of differentiation (CD)5+, (CD)23-,
                  cyclin D1+; this may be from an initial diagnostic biopsy, or one obtained at
                  time of relapse

               2. Institutional flow cytometry or immunohistochemistry must confirm CD5 antigen
                  expression, lack of CD23 antigen expression, and expression of cyclin D1.

          2. Prior Treatment - Patients must have prior treatment with at least one regimen, which
             may have been single agent or multi-agent, and consisted of traditional cytotoxic
             agents and/or biologic agents. Patient must not have received prior idelalisib or
             lenalidomide therapy. Patient must have progressive disease or refractory disease
             following the initial regimen(s). Refractory disease will be defined as stable
             disease (SD) or progressive disease (PD) as best response to prior therapy, or
             complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) as initial response followed by
             disease progression within 6 months. Prior autologous, but not allogeneic, stem cell
             transplant is allowed. No corticosteroids within two weeks prior to study, except for
             maintenance therapy for a non-malignant disease. Maintenance therapy dose may not
             exceed 20 mg/day prednisone or equivalent.

          3. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status - Patients must have
             ECOG performance status of 0-2.

          4. Measurable Disease must be present either on imaging studies. Non-measurable disease
             alone is not acceptable. Any tumor mass &gt; 1 cm by computed tomography (CT), magnetic
             resonance imaging (MRI), or conventional radiograph is acceptable. Lesions that are
             considered non-measurable include the following:

               1. Bone lesions (lesions, if present, should be noted)

               2. Ascites

               3. Pleural/pericardial effusion

               4. Lymphangitis cutis/pulmonis

               5. Bone marrow (involvement by non-Hodgkin lymphoma should be noted)

          5. Central Nervous System (CNS) Involvement - Patients must have no known CNS
             involvement by lymphoma.

          6. Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) Infection - Patients with HIV infection are
             eligible, provided they meet the following:

               1. CD4+ cell count &gt; 350/mm3

               2. Treatment sensitive HIV and, if on anti-HIV therapy, HIV viral load &lt; 50
                  copies/mm3

               3. No history of Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS)-defining conditions or
                  other HIV related illness

               4. No concurrent zidovudine or stavudine because of overlapping toxicities with
                  protocol therapy

               5. Patients with known HIV positivity must have CD4 assessment and viral load at
                  baseline and every 6 months while on study.

          7. Pregnancy and Nursing Status - Patients must be non-pregnant and non-nursing. Females
             of childbearing potential (FCBP) must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test
             with a sensitivity of at least 50 mIU/mL within 10-14 days prior to registration.
             Further, they must either commit to continued abstinence from heterosexual
             intercourse or begin TWO acceptable methods of birth control: one highly effective
             method and one additional effective method AT THE SAME TIME, at least 28 days before
             starting lenalidomide. FCBP must also agree to ongoing pregnancy testing. Men must
             agree to use a latex condom during sexual contact with a FCBP, even if they have had
             a successful vasectomy. A FCBP is a sexually mature woman who: 1) has not undergone a
             hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy, or 2) has not been naturally postmenopausal
             for at least 24 consecutive months (i.e., has had menses at any time preceding 24
             consecutive months).

          8. Deep Vein Thrombosis/Pulmonary Embolism (DVT/PE) - Patients with a recent history
             (within 3 months of study entry) of DVT/PE are not eligible. Patients with a distant
             history (greater than 3 months before study entry) of DVT/PE are eligible, but must
             receive either prophylactic aspirin or low molecular weight heparin, unless
             contraindicated.

          9. Congestive Heart Failure - Patients must have no New York Heart Association (NYHA)
             Class III or Class IV congestive heart failure at study entry.

         10. Myocardial Infarction - Patients must have no myocardial infarction within 6 months
             prior to study entry.

         11. Hepatitis - Patients must not have known positivity for hepatitis B, as evidenced by
             + HBsAg or +anti-HBc, and must not have known history of hepatitis C.

         12. Patients must be ≥ 18 years of age.

         13. Cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) Strong Inducers and Inhibitors - Patients must not be on
             strong CYP3A4 inhibitors and/or inducers.

               1. The following strong inhibitors are prohibited: indinavir, nelfinavir,
                  ritonavir, clarithromycin, itraconazole, ketoconazole,nefazodone

               2. The following strong inducers are prohibited: carbamazepine, phenobarbital,
                  phenytoin, pioglitazone, rifabutin, rifampin, St. John's Wort, troglitazone

         14. Required Initial Laboratory Values:

               1. ANC      ≥ 1,000/µL, ≥ 500/µL if marrow involvement

               2. Platelets      ≥ 75,000/µL

               3. Creatinine     ≤ 1.5 x ULN, and estimated creatinine clearance ≥ 60 mL/min
                  (patients on dialysis not eligible), unless attributable to non-Hodgkin lymphoma

               4. Total bilirubin ≤ 2 x ULN, unless attributable to non-Hodgkin lymphoma or
                  Gilbert's disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sonali Smith, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Chicago</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sonali Smith</last_name>
      <phone>773-702-9251</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 9, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 19, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Mantle-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
