<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="30284">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02141217</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>117044</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02141217</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>AUGMENTIN™ in Dental Infections</brief_title>
  <acronym>AUGDENT</acronym>
  <official_title>Efficacy, Safety and Tolerability of Amoxicillin + Clavulanic Acid (875mg/125mg) Two Times a Day Compared to Clindamycin (150mg) Four Times a Day for 5-7 Days in Treatment of Acute Odontogenic Infection With or Without Abscess</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Philippines: Philippines Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Malaysia: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>Thailand: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Vietnam: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In clinical practice, amoxicillin + clavulanic acid is widely used in the treatment of
      odontogenic infection. Therefore, this study is designed to generate data to support its use
      by demonstrating efficacy, safety and tolerability in comparison with clindamycin in
      subjects with acute odontogenic infections with or without abscess. This will be a two-arm,
      parallel, comparative, observer blind, randomised study to assess efficacy, safety and
      tolerability of amoxicillin + clavulanic acid (875mg/125mg) in comparison with clindamycin
      (150mg) administered for 5-7 days in subjects with acute odontogenic infections with or
      without abscess. The study will be performed in adult subjects both male and female ≥18
      years of age who present with acute odontogenic infections. A total of 472 subjects will be
      randomized in 1:1 ratio, i.e. 236 subjects in each treatment arm. The treatment duration of
      the study will be at least 5 days or maximum 7 days depending upon the treatment response.
      Subjects will be assessed on Day 5 and if Investigator feels the need of continuing the
      treatment at Day 5 then treatment will be continued till Day 7. For subjects who do not show
      treatment response on Day 5, assessments will be performed on Day 7.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This two-arm, parallel, comparative, observer blind, randomised study will be performed in
      adult subjects both male and female ≥18 years of age who present with acute odontogenic
      infection with or without abscess. A total of 472 subjects will be randomised in 1:1 ratio
      to get 205 evaluable subjects in each study arm. After obtaining informed consent, subject
      will undergo surgical intervention including surgical incisions, drainages, removal of the
      involved tooth, debridement, puncture lavage or trephination, if deemed necessary by the
      Investigator. These surgical interventions will be performed before the start of study
      treatment. On Day 0 after confirming the eligibility, subjects will be randomised to either
      of the study arms. The treatment duration of the study will be at least 5 days which may
      increase to 7 days, if Investigator feels the need of continuing the treatment at Day 5. In
      such cases clinical assessment will be done again at Day 7. Thus the efficacy evaluation
      will be performed at baseline (Day 0) prior to study drug administration and on Day 5 and/
      or 7. Safety laboratory evaluations will be performed at Screening Visit and will be
      repeated at end of study treatment i.e. either on Day 5 or Day 7. On Baseline, Day 2, Day 5
      and/ or Day 7, Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) will be used to measure amount of pain and
      swelling that a subject will experience. This scale has numerical ratings from 0 to 10. Zero
      would mean &quot;No pain&quot; and 10 would mean &quot;Worst possible pain&quot;. The subject will be asked to
      choose the most appropriate score on VAS which best describes his/her pain status over last
      24 hours. While using VAS for swelling, zero would mean &quot;No swelling&quot; and 10 would mean
      &quot;Maximum possible swelling&quot;. The Investigator will choose the most appropriate score on VAS
      which best describes subject's swelling.

      Sample for microbiological culture will be obtained at the discretion of Investigator while
      performing the surgical procedure. When microbiological culture is indicated and feasible,
      two sets (each consisting of aerobic and anaerobic media) will be obtained. This sampling
      will be done in approximately 80 subjects randomly who will provide consent at Screening.
      The sample will be collected and dispatched in appropriate transport medium to the central
      laboratory for culture and antibiotic susceptibility.

      Protocol waivers or exemptions will not be allowed.

      The total duration of each subject's participation will be 6-9 days including Screening
      period of 0-1 day (Day -1 to Day 0) and Treatment period of 5-7 days (Day 0 to Day 5-7).

      The primary objective of the study is to compare clinical efficacy (cure and improvement) of
      both the treatment arms which uses VAS for assessment of pain and swelling. Since the
      clinical efficacy parameters are subjective, it is mandatory to keep the
      observer/Investigator blinded during the study assessment. In addition, designing blinded
      study is challenging owing to different dosage regimen and formulation of study drugs. The
      study design of double blind double dummy is not recommended in view of increased pill
      burden which in turn can have an impact on treatment compliance. The possibility of
      over-encapsulation is ruled out due to large pill size of amoxicillin + clavulanic acid.
      Therefore to maintain blinding of Investigators, the study is designed as observer blind
      with Investigator remaining blinded throughout the study period. An unblinded study team
      member will be appointed for each site who will be involved in dispensing of the study drugs
      to subjects. The unblinded study team member will remain present during subject assessment
      for all study visits and will ensure that Investigator remains blinded to treatment
      assignment.

      Study treatment includes amoxicillin + clavulanic acid (875mg/125mg) two times daily or
      clindamycin (150mg) four times daily for 5-7 days both administered orally with meal.
      Augmentin™ (amoxicillin + clavulanic acid) from GSK and Dalacin-C (clindamycin) from Pfizer
      will be used as study treatments. The contents of the label will be in accordance with all
      applicable regulatory requirements.

      Patients can receive additional medical therapy such as analgesics or anti-inflammatory
      drugs. However, opioid analgesics and any other antibiotic apart from study drugs will not
      be permitted during entire study period.

      This study will be conducted in accordance with ICH GCP, all applicable subject privacy
      requirements, and the ethical principles that are outlined in the Declaration of Helsinki
      2008, including IRB/ IEC review and approval of study protocol and any subsequent
      amendments, subject informed consent and Investigator reporting requirements.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Success at End of Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>EOT (day 5/7)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>• Percentage of subjects achieving clinical success (cure or improvement) at end of treatment (Day 5/7)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical success at Day 5</measure>
    <time_frame>5 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>•	Percentage of subjects achieving clinical success at Day 5</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Visual analogue Scale for Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 2,5 and 7</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>•	Change in score on Visual Analogue Scale for assessment of pain from baseline to Day 2, 5 and 7</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual analogue Scale for Swelling</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 2, 5 and 7</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>•	Change in score on Visual Analogue Scale for assessment of swelling from baseline to Day 2, 5 and 7</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 7</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of subjects having adverse events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">472</enrollment>
  <condition>Focal Infection, Dental</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Amoxicillin/clavulanate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Amoxicillin/ clavulanate 1 g bd for for at least 5 days upto seven days depending on treament response</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Clindamycin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Clindamycin 150 mg qid for at least 5 days or maximum 7 days depending upon treatment response</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Amoxicillin/clavulanate</intervention_name>
    <description>Amoxicillin/clavulanate 1 g bd for at least 5 days or maximum 7 days depending upon the treatment response.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Amoxicillin/clavulanate</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clindamycin</intervention_name>
    <description>Clindamycin 150 mg qid for at least 5 days or maximum 7 days depending upon the treatment response.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Clindamycin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Inclusion Criterion:

               -  Adult (≥18 years of age) males and females

               -  Subjects with diagnosis of acute odontogenic infections of following types
                  requiring antibiotic therapy

          -  Periapical abscess

          -  Aute periodontitis

          -  Pericoronitis • Provision of voluntary written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects presenting with complications like osteomyelitis, dentocutaneous fistula,
             dentoalveolar fistula, draining sinus, facial-space swelling, necrotizing fasciitis
             OR subjects requiring hospitalization, aggressive intravenous antimicrobial therapy,
             requiring local application of antimicrobials for the treatment of odontogenic
             infection.

          -  Subjects presenting with odontogenic infections secondary to traumatic injury to the
             face.

          -  Subjects with valvular heart disease, prosthetic heart valves, congenital heart
             disease or any other conditions prone to infective endocarditis

          -  Subjects with a known clinically significant abnormality identified at screening on
             physical examination or known laboratory tests which, in the judgment of the
             Investigator, would preclude safe completion of the study

          -  Subject who has taken a systemic antibiotic within 2 weeks before study drug
             administration or a long-acting injectable antibiotic (e.g., penicillin G benzathine)
             within 4 weeks before study drug administration

          -  Immunocompromised subjects or subjects on immunosuppressants or systemic
             corticosteroids

          -  Subjects with chronic gingivitis or chronic periodontitis

          -  Subjects with uncontrolled diabetes mellitus or HIV infection

          -  History of hypersensitivity or allergic reactions to any beta-lactam such as
             penicillin, cephalosporin, moxicillin/clavulanic acid or clindamycin

          -  Concomitant infection, that requires additional antimicrobial therapy during the
             study period

          -  Subjects with clinically significant liver disease as defined by alanine
             aminotransferase (ALT) or aspartate minotransferase (AST) levels &gt;2.5 times the upper
             limit of normal (ULN) or a diagnosis of chronic active hepatitis including that of
             viral etiology, or on antiviral or immunosuppressive therapy.

          -  Subjects with renal impairment with serum creatinine &gt; 1.7 mg/dl in men and &gt;1.5mg/dl
             in women.

          -  Subjects with infectious mononucleosis

          -  Subjects with history of documented Clostridium difficile-associated diarrhoea or
             existing diarrhoea

          -  Concomitant treatment with oral anticoagulants, methotrexate or probenicid

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential in whom pregnancy cannot be excluded by a
             negative pregnancy test and who are not using reliable method of contraception

          -  Subjects with lactose intolerance or Lapp lactase deficiency or glucose-galactose
             malabsorption

          -  Pregnant or lactating female subjects
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kuala Lumpur</city>
        <zip>50050</zip>
        <country>Malaysia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Perak</city>
        <zip>31350</zip>
        <country>Malaysia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Putrajaya</city>
        <zip>62250,</zip>
        <country>Malaysia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Selangor</city>
        <zip>68100</zip>
        <country>Malaysia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cebu</city>
        <zip>6000</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Davao City</city>
        <zip>8000</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Quezon</city>
        <zip>1100</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Quezon</city>
        <zip>1109</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lampang</city>
        <zip>52000</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pranburi,</city>
        <zip>77120</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Songkhla</city>
        <zip>90112</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hanoi</city>
        <zip>Hoan Kiem District</zip>
        <country>Vietnam</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ho Chi Minh City</city>
        <zip>District 10</zip>
        <country>Vietnam</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ho Chi Minh City</city>
        <zip>District 1</zip>
        <country>Vietnam</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ho Chi Minh City</city>
        <zip>District 5</zip>
        <country>Vietnam</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Malaysia</country>
    <country>Philippines</country>
    <country>Thailand</country>
    <country>Vietnam</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 15, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 15, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Odontogenic (Dental) Infections</keyword>
  <keyword>Dental infections, periapical abscess</keyword>
  <keyword>Bacterial infection</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Focal Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Focal Infection, Dental</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Amoxicillin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Clindamycin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Clindamycin-2-phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Amoxicillin-Potassium Clavulanate Combination</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Clavulanic Acids</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Clavulanic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
