<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="4947">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02014402</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IG1202</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02014402</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy of Topical Thrombin (Human) Grifols as an Adjunct to Hemostasis During Open Surgeries</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Randomized, Double-blind, Phase II Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of Topical Thrombin (Human) Grifols as an Adjunct to Hemostasis During Vascular, Parenchymous, Soft Tissue, and Spinal Open Surgeries</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Grifols Biologicals Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Grifols Biologicals Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This purpose of this clinical trial is to study the safety and efficacy of Topical Thrombin
      (Human) Grifols as an add-on treatment to help stop bleeding during vascular, parenchymous
      tissue (liver), soft tissue, and spinal open surgical procedures.  Approximately 180
      subjects will be treated with either Topical Thrombin (Human) Grifols (120 subjects) or
      Bovine Thrombin JMI® (60 subjects).  Subjects will be evaluated for identification of a
      target bleeding site (TBS) in which control of bleeding by standard surgical techniques is
      ineffective or impractical and requires an additional treatment to stop the bleeding.  The
      Investigator (surgeon) will rate the intensity of bleeding at the TBS. Topical Thrombin
      (Human) Grifols or Bovine Thrombin JMI will then be applied to the TBS and the amount of
      bleeding at the TBS will be examined.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, randomized, double-blind, controlled, Phase II study to evaluate the
      safety and efficacy of Topical Thrombin (Human) Grifols as an adjunct to hemostasis during
      vascular, parenchymous tissue (hepatic), soft tissue, and spinal open surgical procedures.
      Approximately 180 subjects will be randomized into 1 of 2 treatment groups in a 2:1 ratio:
      Topical Thrombin (Human) Grifols (120 subjects) or Bovine Thrombin JMI (60 subjects).
      Randomized subjects will be evaluated for identification of a target bleeding site (TBS) in
      which control of bleeding by conventional surgical techniques (including suture, ligature
      and cautery) is ineffective or impractical and requires an adjunct treatment to achieve
      hemostasis.  The Investigator will rate the intensity of bleeding at the TBS. Topical
      Thrombin (Human) Grifols or Bovine Thrombin JMI will be applied to the TBS and hemostasis
      will be assessed at various timepoints during a 5-minute observation period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects achieving hemostasis at the TBS</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes following the start of treatment application</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Hemostasis at the TBS defined by 'Yes&quot; or &quot;No&quot; response (by Investigator) without the occurrence of re-bleeding through the completion of surgical closure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment-emergent adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment application through post-operative Day 30</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Treatment-emergent adverse events defined as adverse events (including suspected adverse reactions) occurring after the start of treatment until 30 (+/- 4) days post-surgery.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Hemostasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Topical Thrombin (Human) Grifols</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Topical Thrombin (Human) Grifols</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bovine Thrombin JMI®</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Bovine Thrombin JMI®</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Human thrombin</intervention_name>
    <description>Thrombin purified from human plasma reconstituted as a 1000 IU/mL solution in blinded syringes and applied using Gelfoam® or Surgifoam® sponges.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Topical Thrombin (Human) Grifols</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bovine thrombin</intervention_name>
    <description>Thrombin of bovine origin reconstituted as a 1000 IU/mL solution in blinded syringes and applied using Gelfoam® or Surgifoam® sponges</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bovine Thrombin JMI®</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pre-operative (at Baseline Assessments Visit) hemoglobin (Hgb) ≥9.0 g/dL (deciliter)

          -  Pre-operative (at Baseline Assessments Visit) fibrinogen level ≥1.5 g/dL (functional
             method).

          -  Require one of the following procedures:

               1. An elective (non-emergency), open (non-laparoscopic; non- endovascular) surgical
                  procedure involving a native artery-graft end-to-side proximal anastomosis
                  utilizing coated or uncoated polytetrafluoroethylene (PTFE) graft.

               2. An elective (non-emergency), open (non-laparoscopic) hepatic resection (anatomic
                  and non-anatomic resections of at least one anatomical hepatic segment or
                  equivalent tissue volume).

               3. An elective (non-emergency), open (non-laparoscopic), surgical procedure
                  involving soft (non-parenchymous) tissue.

               4. An elective (non-emergency), open (non-laparoscopic), spinal surgery surgical
                  procedure in which the epidural venous plexus should be exposed.

          -  A target bleeding site (TBS) can be identified according to the Investigator's
             judgment, and the TBS has mild or moderate bleeding according to the Investigator's
             judgment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Requires surgical procedure due to trauma (except for spinal surgery).

          -  Infection in the anatomic surgical area.

          -  History of severe (e.g. anaphylactic) reactions to blood or to any blood-derived
             (human or animal) product.

          -  Previous known sensitivity to any Topical Thrombin (Human) Grifols component, any
             Bovine Thrombin JMI component, porcine collagen, and heparin or protamine (vascular
             surgery only) component.

          -  Receiving an organ transplant.

          -  Undergoing another concurrent major surgical intervention beyond the liver (applies
             to parenchymous tissue surgery only; concurrent interventions on the pancreas, gall
             bladder, bile duct, or intestines are allowed).

          -  Undergoing a re-operative procedure, which is defined as a second, or successive,
             surgical procedure on the same anatomic location.

          -  Undergoing other vascular procedures during the same surgical session (applies to
             vascular surgery only; stenting and/or endarterectomy of the same artery are
             allowed).

          -  Undergone a therapeutic surgical procedure within 30 days from screening (diagnostic
             procedures are allowed).

          -  Previously included in this trial (i.e. each subject can only be enrolled once in
             this study).

          -  TBS cannot be identified according to the investigator's judgment.

          -  TBS has a severe bleeding according to the Investigator's judgment.

          -  Occurrence of major intra-operative complications that require resuscitation or
             deviation from the planned surgical procedure.

          -  Application of any topical haemostatic material on the resection surface of the liver
             prior to application of the study treatment (applies to parenchymous tissue surgery
             only).

          -  Radiofrequency precoagulation of the liver resection surface, except focal use of
             radiofrequency as primary haemostatic treatment (applies to parenchymous tissue
             surgery only).

          -  Intra-operative change in planned surgical procedure which results in subject no
             longer meeting preoperative inclusion and/or exclusion criteria.

          -  Application of any topical haemostatic material on the cut soft tissue surface prior
             to application of the study treatment (applies to soft tissue surgery only).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paul J Pinciaro, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <email>Paul.Pinciaro@grifols.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Pasadena</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Las Vegas</city>
        <state>Nevada</state>
        <zip>89144</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77024</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Spokane</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>99208</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 17, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hemostasis</keyword>
  <keyword>Vascular open surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatic open surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Soft tissue open surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Spinal open surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>during vascular, parenchymous tissue (hepatic), soft tissue, and spinal open surgical procedures.</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Thrombin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemostatics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
