<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="39989">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01654523</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HUM00050426</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01654523</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Awareness Enhancement and Monitoring Device for Treatment of Trichotillomania</brief_title>
  <official_title>Awareness Enhancement and Monitoring Device for Treatment of Trichotillomania</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goals of the study are to further design, develop, and test an awareness enhancement and
      monitoring device, which will be used in the self-awareness training and general treatment
      of patients with compulsive hair-pulling behaviors, or trichotillomania.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      DESCRIPTION (provided by applicant): The goal of the proposed research is to further refine
      and evaluate an inconspicuous, awareness- enhancement and monitoring device (AEMD) which
      will assist the treatment of trichotillomania (TTM). TTM is associated with significant
      impairments in social functioning and often has a profound negative impact on self- esteem
      and well being. Conservative estimates suggest that 0.6% percent of the US population, or
      about 1.8 million people, meet full diagnostic criteria for TTM and approximately 7.5
      million US residents have significant hair pulling problems. Of those treated, 60% to 70%
      are wholly or partially refractory to standard behavioral and pharmacological treatments and
      could therefore potentially benefit from this device.  Best practice treatment for TTM
      involves a form of behavioral therapy known as habit reversal therapy (HRT). HRT requires
      persons with TTM to be aware of their hair pulling behaviors, yet the majority of persons
      with TTM pull most of their hair outside of their awareness. HRT also requires TTM sufferers
      to record the frequency and duration of their hair pulling behaviors yet it is impossible
      for a person to monitor behaviors that they are unaware of. Our Phase I efforts have
      produced a prototype device (AEMD) that solves these two problems. The prototype AEMD
      signals the TTM sufferer if their hand approaches their hair, thereby bringing
      pulling-related behavior into awareness. The prototype AEMD also logs the time, date,
      duration, and user classification of hair pulling related events. Our published pilot study
      and subsequent investigations establish that the prototype AEMD successfully alerts TTM
      sufferers to pulling-related behaviors and monitors TTM-related behavior in a laboratory
      setting. With respect to technological innovation, this project has the potential to develop
      the first available miniaturized, wearable, patient interactive, real-time data collecting
      and proximity-sensing device that both alerts sufferers to the presence of mental illness
      symptoms as they occur and keeps track of the frequency and intensity of the problem. The
      patented technologies developed for the AEMD have the potential to be of great value for a
      range of other health/mental health conditions or industrial applications.  Our overall
      Phase II aim is to further refine the AEMD and to evaluate its acceptance and utility when
      used in an open trial course of professionally-led habit reversal therapy. It is
      hypothesized that the AEMD will be enthusiastically accepted by TTM sufferers and their
      clinicians and that it will perform as designed during the clinical trial. The Phase II AEMD
      will include a bracelet(s)/watch to be worn on each wrist, another element to be placed at
      the rear base of the neck, and a pager-like alert device to be worn at the belt-line or in a
      pocket.  The AEMD, if found to be useful and effective, has the potential to significantly
      reduce the symptoms of TTM and its associated functional impairments. The AEMD also has
      great potential to improve assessment and monitoring of TTM behaviors which could be
      invaluable to clinicians planning treatment and to researchers evaluating the efficacy of
      various treatment strategies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2005</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Awareness Enhancement and Monitoring Device (AEMD)</measure>
    <time_frame>1/1/2005 - 1/1/2013 (8 years)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participant use of the AEMD will be electronically monitored via the AEMD's internal date/time tracking capabilities.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Trichotillomania</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Awareness Enhancement and Monitoring Device for Treatment of Trichotillomania</intervention_name>
    <description>Awareness Enhancement and Monitoring Device for Treatment of Trichotillomania</description>
    <other_name>AEMD</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must have active hair pulling over the month prior to enrollment

          -  Must have noticeable hair loss

          -  Must experience significant distress related to Trichotillomania

          -  Must primarily pull from the head area

          -  Subjects taking medications will be included

          -  Must be able to read/write English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current substance use diagnosis

          -  Chronic neurological disorder (other than chronic tics)

          -  Mental retardation

          -  Schizophrenia and other psychotic disorders

          -  Bipolar I disorder

          -  Prominent suicidal/homicidal ideation with imminent risk
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joseph A Himle, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 10, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Joseph Himle</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Trichotillomania</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Trichotillomania</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
