<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="40358">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02132923</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR103420</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>ObserveRSV0002</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02132923</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study in Japanese Children Hospitalized With Respiratory Syncytial Virus Related Lower Respiratory Tract Infections</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective Study in Japanese Children Hospitalized With Respiratory Syncytial Virus Related Lower Respiratory Tract Infections</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Janssen R&amp;D Ireland</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Janssen R&amp;D Ireland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Japan: Pharmaceuticals and Medical Devices Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to assess viral kinetics and clinical symptoms kinetics of
      Respiratory Syncytial Virus (RSV) in pediatric patients hospitalized with RSV confirmed
      lower respiratory tract infection (LRTI).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an exploratory prospective study (a study in which the patients are identified and
      then followed forward in time for the outcome of the study). The study will consist of two
      phases: a screening phase (Day 1) and an assessment phase (Day 2 to Day 7). During screening
      phase, pediatric patients consecutively hospitalized with RSV-related infection will be
      enrolled in the study within 24 hours of admission if symptomatic for maximum 5 days before
      the hospital admission and if the informed consent form (ICF) was obtained. The diagnosis of
      RSV infection will follow using a standard of care (SOC) rapid point point of care (POC)
      detection method available in the hospital unit on nasal specimens .During the assessment
      phase the collection of nasal specimens will be done daily for a maximum of 6 days (Day 2 to
      Day 7 of hospitalization) or until patients will be discharged from hospital. Approximately
      50 patients will be enrolled in this study. The total duration of the study for each patient
      will be approximately 7 days. The study duration will extend until the targeted number of 50
      RSV hospitalized children have completed the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 0</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case-Only, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Respiratory Syncytial Viral Load (rate of viral clearance)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 (baseline) to Day 3</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>RSV viral clearance, defined as the change in log viral load (VL) from Day 1 to Day 3, where the VL is measured in nasal specimens with quantitative reverse transcript poly cycle reaction (qRT-PCR).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Clinical Symptoms Score (CSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 (baseline) to Day 3</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The severity of the RSV disease will be assessed using CSS. CSS will be computed based on clinical parameters (O2 saturation, heart rate, respiratory rate) and lung auscultation examination. CSS score ranges from 0 (best) to 15 (worst). Higher scores indicate worsening.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Medical Support Score (MSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 (baseline) to Day 3</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The severity of the RSV disease will be assessed using MSS. MSS will take into account the use of supplementary oxygen, the request for mechanical ventilation, intensive care unit admission and the length of hospitalization. The MSS score ranges from 0 (best) to 5 (worst). Higher scores indicate worsening.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Respiratory Syncytial Virus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) infection</arm_group_label>
    <description>The RSV infection is laboratory confirmed</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>This is an observational study. The children hospitalized with lower respiratory tract infection (LRTI) with a laboratory confirmed RSV infection will be monitored for maximum 7 days or until hospital discharge.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) infection</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Pediatric patients hospitalized with a laboratory confirmed Respiratory Syncytial Virus
        (RSV) lower respiratory tract infection.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Legal representative has provided Ethics Committee approved written informed onsent
             prior to any study-related procedure(s) being performed and is willing to allow the
             participation of child to the study for 7 consecutive days or until hospital
             discharge (whatever comes first)

          -  Patient hospitalized with lower respiratory tract infection (LRTI) during respiratory
             syncytial virus (RSV) epidemics, within 24h of hospitalization. The diagnosis of LRTI
             will follow the standard medical procedure in the hospital unit

          -  Onset of acute respiratory symptoms was less than or equal to 5 days ago

          -  Patient is RSV positive based on a rapid point of care (POC) detection method. The
             diagnosis of RSV infection will follow the standard medical procedure in the hospital
             unit

        Exclusion Criteria:

        - Patient does not fulfill the inclusion criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>5 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janssen R&amp;D Ireland Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Janssen R&amp;D Ireland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Use link at the bottom of the page to see if you qualify for an enrolling site (see list). If you still have questions:</last_name>
    <email>JNJ.CT@sylogent.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Tokyo</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://pam.sylogent.com/cr/CR103420</url>
    <description>To learn how to participate in this trial please click here.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 6, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 6, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Respiratory syncytial virus</keyword>
  <keyword>RSV</keyword>
  <keyword>Lower respiratory tract infection</keyword>
  <keyword>LRTI</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute respiratory infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Japanese children</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Tract Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Virus Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
