<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="116108">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02049268</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012P000217</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02049268</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neural Mechanisms Underlying Nicotine and Alcohol Combinations</brief_title>
  <acronym>QfMRI</acronym>
  <official_title>Neural Mechanisms Underlying Nicotine and Alcohol Combinations</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mclean Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mclean Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Nicotine and alcohol are frequently used together and their combined use contributes to more
      than half a million deaths each year, with more alcoholics dying from smoking-related
      diseases than from alcohol-related diseases. Using a new multi-modal MRI approach combined
      with data fusion, the investigators propose to study how nicotine modulates alcohol-induced
      changes in the function of brain circuits. The investigators hypotheses are:

        -  functional connectivity (FC) in the reward network, containing components of the
           mesolimbic dopamine system, will be altered by alcohol, and additional increases in FC
           will be observed if nicotine is also present (e.g., additive effects).

        -  co-administration of nicotine will counteract the effects of alcohol on FC in multiple
           brain networks, including visual, sensorimotor and motor brain circuits, that may be
           associated with the impairing effects of alcohol
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacodynamics Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional connectivity of reward-related brain circuit</measure>
    <time_frame>1.5 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In a single 1.5 hour MRI session, functional connectivity of the reward circuit will be assessed with either nicotine or placebo nicotine on board. Participants will then drink an alcoholic or placebo alcohol beverage (whilst still in the scanner) and will be rescanned after a 20 minute resting period (also still in the scanner). The primary outcome is the pre- minus the post-alcohol functional connectivity of the reward brain circuit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional connectivity of visual, motor, and sensorimotor brain circuits</measure>
    <time_frame>1.5 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In a single 1.5 hour MRI session, functional connectivity of the reward circuit will be assessed with either nicotine or placebo nicotine on board. Participants will then drink an alcohol or placebo alcohol beverage (whilst still in the scanner) and will be rescanned after a 20 minute resting period (also still in the scanner). The primary outcome is the pre- minus the post-alcohol functional connectivity for each brain circuit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exploratory investigation of oxygen metabolism and perfusion underlying the functional connectivity effects</measure>
    <time_frame>1.5 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>An exploratory data fusion approach will be applied to the MRI measurements to evaluate patterns of related cerebrovascular and neural function in all brain circuits that are associated with nicotine and alcohol effects.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Focus: Effects of Nicotine and Alcohol on Brain Circuits</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nicotine + Alcohol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A nicotine patch will be applied to the subject. After a 3-4 hour uptake period, subjects will undergo a single MRI session. Baseline (nicotine only) measurements will be made, then participants will drink an alcoholic beverage. Post-alcohol measurements will be made after a 20 minute uptake period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Nicotine + Alcohol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A placebo nicotine patch will be applied to the subject. After a 3-4 hour uptake period, subjects will undergo a single MRI session. Baseline (placebo nicotine) measurements will be made, then participants will drink an alcoholic beverage. Post-alcohol measurements will be made after a 20 minute uptake period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nicotine + Placebo Alcohol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A nicotine patch will be applied to the subject. After a 3-4 hour uptake period, subjects will undergo a single MRI session. Baseline (nicotine only) measurements will be made, then participants will drink a placebo alcoholic beverage. Post-alcohol measurements will be made after a 20 minute uptake period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nicotine + Alcohol</intervention_name>
    <description>14 mg nicotine patch applied in combination with vodka and orange juice alcoholic beverage (to reach blood alcohol level (BAL) = 0.08 based on subject weight, which is approximately 2-3 drinks for 400 mL volume)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nicotine + Alcohol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Nicoderm CQ Clear</other_name>
    <other_name>Absolute Vodka</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Nicotine + Alcohol</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo nicotine patch applied in combination with vodka and orange juice alcoholic beverage (to reach BAL = 0.08 based on subject weight, which is approximately 2-3 drinks for 400 mL volume)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Nicotine + Alcohol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Nicoderm CQ Clear</other_name>
    <other_name>Absolute Vodka</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nicotine + Placebo Alcohol</intervention_name>
    <description>14 mg nicotine patch applied in combination with 400 mL orange juice beverage with a trace of alcohol to create placebo alcohol mixture.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nicotine + Placebo Alcohol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Nicoderm CQ Clear</other_name>
    <other_name>Absolute Vodka</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male

          -  21 to 40 years old

          -  Physically healthy (normal physical exam, ECG, blood and urine chemistries)

          -  Light/moderate cigarette smokers (greater than 10-20 cigarettes per week)

          -  Alcohol drinkers (10 or greater drinks per week)

          -  Must not be seeking treatment for their alcohol or tobacco use

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Female

          -  Diagnosis of past or current alcohol dependence as assessed by Diagnostic and
             Statistic Manual, DSM-IV, criteria for alcohol dependence

          -  Diagnosis of cocaine, sedative, or opiate dependence using DSM-IV criteria

          -  Current diagnosis of Axis I disorder using DSM-IV criteria, or any Axis I disorder
             within past 5 years (excluding alcohol abuse, marijuana dependence or abuse)

          -  Current daily use of antipsychotic, antidepressant, or other psychoactive
             prescription drug, as well as daily use of non-prescription drugs

          -  Life threatening or unstable medical illness, or one that can create marked change in
             mental state

          -  Heavy caffeine use (greater than 400 mg on a regular, daily basis)

          -  History of seizure disorder

          -  Hepatitis B or C positive, or history of i.v. drug use
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>McLean Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Belmont</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02478</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lisa D Nickerson, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>617-855-3548</phone>
      <email>lisa_nickerson@hms.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lisa D Nickerson, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 28, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mclean Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lisa Nickerson, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Instructor in Psychiatry</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>alcohol</keyword>
  <keyword>nicotine</keyword>
  <keyword>addiction</keyword>
  <keyword>functional MRI</keyword>
  <keyword>functional connectivity</keyword>
  <keyword>brain circuits</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ethanol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nicotine polacrilex</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nicotine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
