<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="168353">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02150499</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SEP051-361</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02150499</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Levalbuterol Tartrate HFA Inhalation Aerosol Metered Dose Inhaler (MDI) in Pediatric Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Safety and Tolerability Study of Levalbuterol Tartrate HFA Inhalation Aerosol Metered Dose Inhaler (MDI) in Pediatric Subjects Birth to ≤ 48 Months of Age With Reactive Airways Disease in an Acute Setting</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sunovion</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sunovion</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a study of levalbuterol tartrate HFA inhalation aerosol MDI in pediatric subjects
      birth to ≤ 48 months of age who go to the Emergency Department (ED) or their physician's
      office with an acute bronchospasm. Subjects presenting to the ED or physician's office with
      an acute bronchospasm must have a history of reactive airways disease, based on subjects'
      parent/guardian report.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a study to determine the safety and tolerability of cumulative dosing with
      levalbuterol tartrate HFA inhalation aerosol MDI using a valved holding chamber and facemask
      in pediatric subjects birth to ≤ 48 months of age with acute bronchospasm. It is a
      randomized, double-blind, parallel-group, multicenter, trial of 3 doses of levalbuterol
      tartrate HFA inhalation aerosol MDI in pediatric subjects birth to ≤ 48 months of age who
      present to either the Emergency Department (ED) or their physician's office with an acute
      bronchospasm. Subjects presenting to the ED or physician's office with an acute bronchospasm
      must have a history of reactive airways disease, based on subjects' parent/guardian report.

      Eligible subjects whose parent(s) or legal guardian(s) provide written informed consent to
      participate will be randomized to 1 of 2 treatments. Treatment 1 consists of 3 doses, with
      each dose comprised of 8 puffs (4 puffs of levalbuterol tartrate HFA inhalation aerosol 45
      mcg/puff plus 4 puffs of placebo HFA [cumulative dose of 540 mcg levalbuterol tartrate HFA
      inhalation aerosol]); Treatment 2 consists of 3 doses, with each dose comprised of 8 puffs
      of levalbuterol tartrate HFA inhalation aerosol 45 mcg/puff (4 puffs of levalbuterol
      tartrate HFA inhalation aerosol 45 mcg/puff plus 4 puffs of levalbuterol tartrate HFA
      inhalation aerosol 45 mcg/puff [cumulative dose of 1080 mcg of levalbuterol tartrate HFA
      inhalation aerosol]). For each Treatment, study medication will be administered every 20
      minutes over a period of 1 hour for three doses.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The overall safety of treatment with levalbuterol tartrate HFA inhalation aerosol as measured by the number and percentage of subjects with treatment-emergent adverse events.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The overall safety of treatment with levalbuterol tartrate HFA inhalation aerosol as measured by the number and percentage of subjects with serious adverse events.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The overall safety of treatment with levalbuterol tartrate HFA inhalation aerosol as measured by the number and percentage of subjects with treatment-emergent adverse events leading to discontinuation.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Pulmonary Score (total score) to end of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Pulmonary Score (individual component scores) to end of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Pulmonary Score (total score) after each dose</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes, 40 minutes, 60 minutes</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Pulmonary Score (individual component scores) after each dose</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes, 40 minutes, 60 minutes</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number and percentage of subjects determined to be stabilized after treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>levalbuterol tartrate HFA inhalation aerosol plus placebo HFA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Three doses. Each dose comprised of 8 puffs (4 puffs of levalbuterol tartrate HFA inhalation aerosol 45 mcg/puff plus 4 puffs of placebo HFA) for 24 total puffs, cumulative dose of 540 mcg levalbuterol tartrate HFA inhalation aerosol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>levalbuterol tartrate HFA inhalation aerosol plus levalbuterol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Three doses. Each dose comprised of 8 puffs (4 puffs of levalbuterol tartrate HFA inhalation aerosol 45 mcg/puff plus 4 puffs of levalbuterol tartrate HFA inhalation aerosol 45 mcg/puff) for 24 total puffs, cumulative dose of 1080 mcg levalbuterol tartrate HFA inhalation aerosol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>levalbuterol tartrate HFA inhalation aerosol</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>levalbuterol tartrate HFA inhalation aerosol plus placebo HFA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>levalbuterol tartrate HFA inhalation aerosol plus levalbuterol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Xopenex HFA® (Levalbuterol tartrate) Inhalation Aerosol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>levalbuterol tartrate HFA inhalation aerosol plus placebo HFA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female from birth to 48 months of age, inclusive, whose parent(s) or legal
             guardian(s) provide written informed consent prior to study participation and are
             willing to comply with study procedures.

          2. Subject experiencing acute bronchospasm requiring a bronchodilator and who have a
             history of wheezing.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject with a severe illness that, in the opinion of the Investigator, could
             jeopardize subject safety.

          2. Subject received ≥ 8 puffs (MDI) of a beta-2 agonist or 2.5 mg of nebulized
             levalbuterol, or albuterol 5.0 mg within 4 hours prior to ED or physician's office
             admittance.

          3. Subject received ipratropium within 4 hours prior to ED or physician's office
             admittance.

          4. Subject who participated in an investigational drug study within 30 days prior to
             enrollment, or who previously participated in the current study.

          5. Subject with a known sensitivity to levalbuterol or racemic albuterol or any of the
             excipients contained in any of these formulations.

          6. Subject using any prescription drug (including beta-blockers) with which levalbuterol
             or racemic albuterol sulfate administration is contraindicated.

          7. Subject with a history of clinically significant abnormalities that could interfere
             with the metabolism or excretion of the study medication (eg, renal, hepatic,
             metabolic, or endocrine abnormalities).

          8. Subject with a history of cancer.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>48 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Respiratory Medical Director, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Sunovion</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Study Manager</last_name>
    <phone>866-503-6351</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 30, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 27, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Acute Asthma exacerbation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Albuterol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
