<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="8343">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02042404</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EarLens CRP00004</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02042404</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The EarLens System Long Term Safety and Efficacy Definitive Multi-Center Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>The EarLens System Long Term Safety and Efficacy Definitive Multi-Center Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>EarLens Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>EarLens Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The EarLens System is an assistive hearing device that is intended to provide amplification
      for the treatment of patients with sensorineural hearing impairment. The purpose of this
      multi-center definitive study is to assess the safety and efficacy of the EarLens System for
      subjects with bilateral mild to severe sensorineural hearing impairments wearing the fully
      activated system in their daily lives for a 4 month period of time. This study is designed
      to support US and International marketing applications to commercialize the EarLens System.
      The main efficacy hypothesis is that the EarLens System will be shown to improve hearing in
      frequencies up to 10,000 Hz for the study population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional gain over the frequency range from 2000 to 10,000 Hz</measure>
    <time_frame>At least 30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>10 dB (decibel) improvement improvement in thresholds for the subject population over the frequency range from 2000 to 10,000 Hz. Measurement to be used in analysis are the baseline unaided soundfield thresholds measured prior to device placement and the aided soundfield thresholds measured at least 30 days post placement.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in aided HINT 90 speech reception thresholds (SRTs) when compared to the baseline unaided condition.</measure>
    <time_frame>At least 30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Improvement in aided HINT 90 speech reception thresholds (SRTs) when compared to the baseline unaided condition. SRTs will be measured using HINT materials with the signal (speech level presented from 0 degrees) adapted relative to the noise (presented from 90 degrees held fixed at 60 dB SPL) to determine the signal-to-noise ratio for reporting the whole sentence correct 50% of the time (Nilsson et al., 1994). HINT 90 will be measured twice, once with the noise 90 degrees to the right and once with the noise 90 degrees to the left; the SRTs will be averaged to obtain the per subject HINT SRT. All subject data will be averaged to obtain the means. The baseline unaided measurements will be made prior to device placement, and the aided condition will be measured at least 30 days post placement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in mean aided Word Recognition Scores (WRS) when compared to the baseline unaided condition.</measure>
    <time_frame>At least 30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Improvement in mean aided Word Recognition Scores (WRS) when compared to the baseline unaided condition. WRS will be measured using 50-word NU-6 (Northwestern University Auditory Test No.6) recorded materials, presented at 45 dB Hearing Level on a per-ear basis with the test ear isolated for measurement and the results averaged across the two ears for each subject. All subject data will then be averaged to obtain the means. The baseline unaided measurements will occur prior to device placement, and the aided condition will be measured at least 30 days post placement.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Determine real change in baseline hearing due to device usage using multi-frequency threshold criteria.</measure>
    <time_frame>At least 30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The unaided air conduction hearing thresholds will be measured for each individual ear twice before device placement at Visit #1 and averaged to obtain the baseline unaided air conduction hearing thresholds, and the post wear unaided air conduction hearing thresholds will be measured after device removal at Visit #5. A PTA4 (500, 1000, 2000, and 4000 Hz) will be computed both for baseline unaided hearing pre-placement and unaided hearing post-removal. A determination of &quot;No Hearing Change&quot; for the subject population will be made if the calculated Hearing Changes of the subject population are 10 dB or less.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the incidence of serious device- and procedure-related adverse events.</measure>
    <time_frame>At least 30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The analysis of the incidence of serious device- and procedure-related adverse events through the study period. All adverse events will be recorded on case report forms and determinations will be made as to the whether the events are related to the investigational device.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Hearing Impairment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mild to severe hearing impairment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sound amplification provided via the EarLens System assistive hearing device.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sound amplification provided via EarLens System.</intervention_name>
    <description>The EarLens System has two primary components: 1) an external Behind the Ear (BTE) Sound Processing Unit, and 2) a Tympanic Membrane Transducer (TM Transducer). In this system, light is used to wirelessly transmit both signal and power from the BTE Sound Processor to the TM Transducer. The BTE is designed to be able to be removed, reprogrammed, and have the battery recharged as needed, similar to a BTE for an air conduction hearing aid. The removable TM Transducer is custom made for each patient, is placed and removed by a physician in an office visit procedure, and is designed to reside in the ear in a safe and stable manner for long periods of time.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mild to severe hearing impairment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18 to 85 years

          -  Mild to severe hearing impairment between 125 to 4000 Hz

          -  No significant conductive hearing impairment

          -  Able and willing to commit to travel and time demands of the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Must not have known or active medical issues that would preclude having a     device
             including:

               1. an abnormal tympanic membrane

               2. an abnormal middle ear or history of prior middle ear surgery other than
                  tympanostomy tubes

               3. an ear canal anatomy that prevents physicians from seeing adequate amount of the
                  tympanic membrane

          -  Must not have other known or active medical issues including:

               1. history of chronic and recurrent ear infections in the past 24 mouths

               2. history of dizziness and/or vertigo in the past 24 months

               3. taking medications/treatments with known ototoxic effects

               4. a rapidly progressive or fluctuating hearing impairment

               5. having been diagnosed with having a compromised immune system

          -  Must not fit the definition of a vulnerable subject, as per FDA regulations 21 CFR
             Parts 50 and 56

          -  Must not have an ear canal anatomy that preclude manufacture of the device as
             determined by EarLens manufacturing personnel
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Murray, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Camino Ear, Nose, and Throat Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rodney Perkins, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>EarLens Corp.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kinuko Masaki, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>650-366-3636</phone>
    <email>kmasaki@earlenscorp.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tanya Arbogast, Sc.D.</last_name>
    <phone>650-366-3636</phone>
    <email>tarbogast@earlenscorp.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>EarLens Corporation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Redwood City</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94063</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kinuko Masaki, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>650-366-3636</phone>
      <email>kmasaki@earlenscorp.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Suzy Levy, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>650-366-3636</phone>
      <email>slevy@earlenscorp.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rodney Perkins, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Camino Ear Nose and Throat Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Jose</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95138</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Murray, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.earlenscorp.com</url>
    <description>EarLens Corporation website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fay JP, Perkins R, Levy SC, Nilsson M, Puria S. Preliminary evaluation of a light-based contact hearing device for the hearing impaired. Otol Neurotol. 2013 Jul;34(5):912-21. doi: 10.1097/MAO.0b013e31827de4b1.</citation>
    <PMID>23524632</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 20, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 20, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hearing impairment</keyword>
  <keyword>Hearing loss</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Deafness</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hearing Loss</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
