<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="115869">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01742468</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H53-12</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01742468</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intervention With n-3 Polyunsaturated Fatty Acids in Patients With Rheumatoid Arthritis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Intervention With Products Enriched With Long Chain n-3 Polyunsaturated Fatty Acids (n-3 LC-PUFA)in Patients With Rheumatoid Arthritis - Influence on Disease Activity and Inflammation Status</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Jena</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>German Federal Ministry of Education and Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Jena</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Ethics committee of the medical faculty of the Friedrich Schiller University Jena: Germany</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study was performed to investigate the effects of a daily consumption of n-3 LC-PUFA
      supplemented products (sausage, tomato spread, milk beverage) on disease activity,
      inflammatory markers, and cardiovascular risk factors in patients with rheumatoid arthritis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recent studies suggest that the daily intake of n-3 LC-PUFA (eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) and
      docosahexaenoic acid (DHA)) can support the therapy of chronic-inflammatory diseases and
      might be useful to prevent coronary heart diseases. The majority of these studies do not
      differentiate between the effects of EPA and DHA. The present study investigate the effects
      of DHA in patients with rheumatoid arthritis.

      As a precondition for participating in this study, the patients were provided information in
      writing and verbally about the details of the study. Written informed consent was obtained
      from all volunteers. Before the beginning of the study, all patients were subject to a
      medical examination by their general rheumatologist. Thirty five patients with rheumatoid
      arthritis (DAS ≥ 2.6, erythrocyte sedimation rate (ESR (1h) ≥ 12 mm) should entered the
      study.

      The placebo-controlled, randomized double-blind cross-over study consists of two
      investigation periods of 10 weeks, with a ten-week washout period in between. After the
      washout period the intervention was crossed between the groups and the respective products
      were consumed for another 10 weeks. Patients in the placebo period receive 60g sausage, 8g
      tomato spread and one bottle of the milk beverage daily. These products were enriched with
      sunflower oil (8g/d).

      In the intervention period, the products (60g sausage, 8g tomato spread and one bottle of
      the milk beverage) were enriched with 8g alga oil (IOI) The daily dose of docosahexaenoic
      acid (DHA) amounted to 2.8 g.

      Venous blood is collected at the beginning and at the end of each period.

      • Disease activity was determined by joint score DAS68, rheumascan, common inflammatory
      markers (ESR, C reactive protein), ultrasonic (US-7 score), HAQ questionnaire and further
      lifestyle forms
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>arachidonic acid/docosahexaenoic acid ratio in plasmal lipids and erythrocyte membranes</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>arachidonic acid is a precursor of eicosanoids (leukotriens 4 series, prostaglandins 2 series) docosahexaenoic acid is a precursor of (resolvins and protectins (pro-resolving)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>inflammation markers such as erythrocyte sedimation rate (ESR), C reactive protein (CRP), adhesion molecules, disease activity score DAS 28 and DAS68, US-7 score, rheumascan</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>disease acitvity parameters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>blood lipids (total cholesterol, high density lipoprotein (HDL), low density lipoprotein (LDL), triacylglycerol (TAG), ox LDL, lipoprotein a)</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>cardiovascular risk factors</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Inflamatory Markers and Disease Activity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>n-3 LC-PUFA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>algal oil (rich in docosahexaenoic acid) 8 g/day (included in 60g sausage, 8g tomato spread, 30g milk powder)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>sunflower oil</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>sunflower oil 8 g/day (included in 60g sausage, 8g tomato spread, 30g milk powder)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>n-3 LC-PUFA</intervention_name>
    <description>verum (algal oil)</description>
    <arm_group_label>n-3 LC-PUFA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo (sunflower oil)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>sunflower oil</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient has a diagnosis of RA according to the revised 1987 ACR classification
             criteria for at least 6 months prior to randomization.

          -  Patient has a moderate disease activity as defined by disease activity score DAS28 ≥
             2.6, ESR ≥ 12 mm/hour.

          -  Patient has the ability to comprehend the full nature and purpose of the study,
             including possible risks and side effects, to cooperate with the investigator, to
             understand verbal and written instructions, and to comply with the requirements of
             the entire study.

          -  stable dosis of disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs within 4 weeks prior to
             randomization and presumably over the study periods (30 weeks).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Intra-articular corticosteroids within 4 weeks prior to randomization or blood sample
             taking

          -  Patients are permitted to receive either oral or parenteral glucocorticoids
             equivalent to ≤10 mg daily prednisone and nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug, if
             they have received a stable dose for at least 4 weeks prior to randomization and
             presumably over the study periods (30 weeks).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Friedrich Schiller University, Institute of Nutrition</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jena</city>
        <zip>07743</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Friedrich Schiller University, Clinic for Internal Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jena</city>
        <zip>07743</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 10, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 3, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Jena</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gerhard Jahreis</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>n-3 LC-PUFA, DHA, rheumatoid arthritis</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
