<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="53809">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02111031</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>JDX-2014-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02111031</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Utility of CTC Test in Medicare-Eligible Metastatic Breast Cancer Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>Novitas</acronym>
  <official_title>Registry to Demonstrate the Clinical Utility of CELLSEARCH® Circulating Tumor Cell (CTC) Test in Medicare-Eligible Metastatic Breast Cancer Patients - Jurisdiction J12 and Jurisdiction JH Perspective</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Janssen Diagnostics, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Cleveland Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Janssen Diagnostics, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of the registry study is to demonstrate the clinical utility of the
      CELLSEARCH® CTC Test among the Medicare-Eligible metastatic Breast Cancer (mBC) patients in
      the United States of Jurisdiction J12 adn JH.  Specifically, the proportion and timing of
      treatment switching among CTC-tested and untested mBC patients will be described and
      compared.  Further, the impact of CTC testing on physician behavior with respect to CTC test
      results will be evaluated via a one-time physician survey.

      This study is IDE-exempt since CELLSEARCH® CTC Test  is a legally marketed device in the US,
      and is being used in accordance with its labeling.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case Control, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <target_duration>12 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of mBC treatment modifications</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The incidence of mBC treatment modifications, calculated by dividing the total number of mBC treatment modifications by the total person-time at risk</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>mBC treatment modification during the follow-up time between cases and their selected matched controls.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The proportion of patients who experienced mBC treatment modification anytime during the minimum follow-up time between cases and their selected matched controls.  Treatment modification can be any type of change in mBC treatment, including switching, discontinuation, or augmentation of mBC Treatments.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The durations of mBC treatments prior to modification</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The durations of mBC treatments prior to modification, calculated as the mean (+/- standard deviation [SD]) length of all 'full' treatment courses during follow-up.  Full treatment courses will be defined as courses for which both the start and end dates occurred during follow-up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">350</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Case</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with documented (histologically/pathologically confirmed) mBC diagnosis less than or equal to 6 months before registry enrollment with metastatic breast cancer, diagnosis of metastases secondary to breast cancer, date of diagnosis for metastases on or after date of diagnosis for breast cancer who are female gender, at lease 65 years of age at documented mBC diagnosis, and actively treated by a physician at a participating cancer center who routinely (i.e., test at lease every quarter) use CTC testing (excluding patients who sought consults or second opinions).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Pool</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with documented mBC diagnosis ICD-9 codes (ICD-9 codes: 174.xx [breast]; 196.xx, 197.xx and 198.xx [secondary malignancies]), diagnosis of metastases secondary to breast cancer, date of diag. for mets on or before date of diag. for breast cancer, actively treated by a MD at a cancer center in the Altos OncoEMR™ system who does not incorporate CTC testing in their management of mBC patients, such that the pt. has no record of CTC use at all (excluding patients who sought consults or second opinions).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        &quot;Cases&quot; of CTC-tested mBC patients being cared for by physicians who routinely (i.e., test
        at least once every quarter) incorporate CTC testing in their management of mBC patients.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patients meeting all of the following criteria will be eligible for registry enrollment as
        cases:

          -  Documented (histologically/pathologically confirmed) mBC diagnosis ≤6 months before
             registry enrollment by meeting all of the following:

               -  Metastatic Breast Cancer

               -  Diagnosis of Metastases secondary to breast cancer

               -  Date of diagnosis for metastases on or after date of diagnosis for breast cancer

          -  Patient is at least 65 years of age at time of mBC diagnosis

          -  Patient is female

          -  Patient is being actively treated at the cancer center by a physician who uses or
             plans to use CTC testing on his mBC patients at lease every quarter.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient's breast cancer is secondary not primary
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alberto Montero, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cleveland Clinic Main Campus</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alberto Montero, MD</last_name>
    <email>montero2@ccf.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 8, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CELLSEARCH</keyword>
  <keyword>CTC</keyword>
  <keyword>metastatic breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>mBC</keyword>
  <keyword>Novitas</keyword>
  <keyword>Registry</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
