<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="147814">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01679587</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16370</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-002375-33</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01679587</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dose Escalation Study to Investigate Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacodynamics, and Pharmacokinetics of BAY85-3934 in Subjects With Chronic Kidney Disease (CKD)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Multicenter, Randomized, Single-blind, Placebo-controlled, Combined 2-fold Cross-over and Group-comparison, Dose Escalation Study to Investigate Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacodynamics, and Pharmacokinetics of Single Oral Doses of BAY85 3934 in Subjects With Chronic Kidney Disease (CKD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bayer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bayer</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The phase I study will investigate the hemodynamic effects as well as safety, tolerability,
      and pharmacokinetics of BAY 85-3934 in patients with chronic kidney disease (CKD).

      For hemodynamic evaluation blood pressure, heart rate and cardiac output will be measured.
      Blood samples will be taken for safety laboratory, the measurement of BAY 85-3934
      concentrations and biomarkers.

      A maximum of 4 dose-escalation steps are planned.  Each dose step consists of 2 study
      periods which are separated by a wash-out period of at least 1 week.  Subjects will receive
      in a cross-over design a single dose of either active drug or placebo in these periods
      according to randomization. The planned dose steps are single oral doses of 80, 120mg and
      optionally 40 and/ or 160 mg given as tablets.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacodynamics Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject)</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with adverse events as a measure of safety and tolerability of BAY85-3934</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after last dosing</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood pressure (systolic, diastolic, mean)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemodynamic assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>non-invasive stroke volume and cardiac output</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart rate and heart rate over 1 min</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic profile determined by plasma concentration of BAY85-3934</measure>
    <time_frame>15 min, 30 min, 45 min, 1 h, 1.5 h, 2 h, 3 h, 4 h, 6 h, 8 h, 10 h, 12 h, 24 h,36 h, 48 h post dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hematology profile</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to Day 1 after single dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Hematology profile includes blood concentration of erythropoietin, reticulocytes, erythrocytes, hemoglobin, hematocrit, and exploratory biomarkers.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with abnormal Electrocardiogram (ECG) measured by QTcBazett &gt; 500 msec</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with clinically relevant laboratory deviations.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 3</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Kidney Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive a single oral dose of 80 mg BAY85-3934 in the first period and placebo in the second period, separated by a wash-out period of at least 1 week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive a single oral dose of 120 mg BAY85-3934 in the first period and placebo in the second period, separated by a wash-out period of at least 1 week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive a single oral dose of 40 mg BAY85-3934 in the first period and placebo in the second period, separated by a wash-out period of at least 1 week. This is an optional dose escalation step.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive a single oral dose of 160 mg BAY85-3934 in the first period and placebo in the second period, separated by a wash-out period of at least 1 week. This is an optional dose escalation step.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BAY85-3934</intervention_name>
    <description>Four escalated single oral dose steps of BAY85-3934 will be given - step 1 - 40mg (optional), step 2 - 80mg; step 3 - 120mg step 4 - 160mg (optional). Per arm one dose step will be conducted.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 4</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Single oral dose of matching placebo will be given in each treatment step</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 4</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of chronic kidney disease (CKD) not on dialysis assessed by medical history
             and eGFR (MDRD) = &lt; 60 mL/min estimated at the pre-study visit

          -  Stable renal disease, ie not expected to begin dialysis during the study

          -  Systolic blood pressure =&gt;110 mmHg and =&lt;160 mmHg

          -  Heart rate =&lt;100 BPM

          -  Hemoglobin = &gt;9 g/dL

          -  Female subjects without child-bearing potential, ie postmenopausal women with 12
             months of spontaneous amenorrhea or with 6 months of spontaneous amenorrhea and serum
             FSH levels &gt;30 mIU/mL, women with 6 weeks post bilateral ovariectomy, women with
             bilateral tubal ligation, and women with hysterectomy

          -  Body mass index (BMI): = &gt;18 and = &lt; 35 kg/m2 at the pre-study visit

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Incompletely cured pre-existing diseases for which a relevant impairment of
             absorption, distribution, metabolism, elimination or effects of the study drug is
             assumed

          -  Known hypersensitivity to the study drugs (active substances or excipients of the
             preparations)

          -  Known severe allergies, non-allergic drug reactions, or multiple drug allergies

          -  Chronic heart failure, New York Heart Association (NYHA) III-IV

          -  Coronary artery disease with uncured significant stenosis

          -  Angina pectoris

          -  Significant stenosis of cerebral vessels

          -  Significant uncorrected rhythm or conduction disturbances such as a second- or
             third-degree atrioventricular block without a cardiac pacemaker or episodes of
             sustained ventricular tachycardia

          -  Subjects with impaired liver function (Child Pugh B to C based on medical history)

          -  History of thrombotic or thromboembolic events (eg myocardial infarction, stroke,
             transient ischemic attack, deep vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolism) within the
             recent 6 months

          -  Proliferative choroidal or retinal disease, such as neovascular age-related macular
             degeneration or proliferative diabetic retinopathy that required or is likely to
             require treatment (intraocular injections or laser photocoagulation) during the study

          -  Subjects with a history of malignant disease during the last 5 years

          -  Treatment with EPO-stimulating agents (ESA) or rhEPO within the last 2 weeks before
             first intake of study drug

          -  Suspicion of drug or alcohol abuse

          -  Positive results for hepatitis B virus surface antigen (HBsAg), hepatitis C virus
             antibodies (anti-HCV), human immune deficiency virus antibodies (anti-HIV 1+2) at the
             pre-study visit
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>79 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bayer Study Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Bayer</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>München</city>
        <state>Bayern</state>
        <zip>81241</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Mönchengladbach</city>
        <state>Nordrhein-Westfalen</state>
        <zip>41061</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kiel</city>
        <state>Schleswig-Holstein</state>
        <zip>24105</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.fda.gov/cder/drug/DrugSafety/DrugIndex.htm</url>
    <description>Click here and search for drug information provided by the FDA.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.fda.gov/medwatch/safety.htm</url>
    <description>Click here and search for information on any recalls, market or product safety alerts by the FDA which might have occurred with this product.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 6, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 3, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
