<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="115945">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01829568</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2013-00792</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-00792</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CALGB-A051103</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>A051103</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>A051103</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA014236</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U10CA031946</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01829568</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rituximab, Lenalidomide, and Ibrutinib in Treating Patients With Previously Untreated Stage II-IV Follicular Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of Rituximab, Lenalidomide, and Ibrutinib in Previously Untreated Follicular Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I clinical trial studies the side effects and best dose of lenalidomide and
      ibrutinib when given together with rituximab in treating patients with previously untreated
      stage II-IV follicular lymphoma. Lenalidomide may stimulate the immune system in different
      ways and stop cancer cells from growing. Ibrutinib may stop the growth of cancer cells by
      blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell growth. Monoclonal antibodies, such as
      rituximab, can block cancer growth in different ways. Some block the ability of cancer cells
      to grow and spread. Others find cancer cells and help kill them or carry cancer-killing
      substances to them. Giving lenalidomide and ibrutinib together with rituximab may be an
      effective treatment for follicular lymphoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the recommended phase II doses of ibrutinib and lenalidomide for combination
      with rituximab in previously untreated follicular lymphoma.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine pharmacokinetics of ibrutinib and its major metabolite (PCI-45227) when
      combined with lenalidomide and rituximab.

      II. To determine the pharmacodynamics of basophil activation and Bruton tyrosine kinase
      (BTK) occupancy in peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) over a 24-hour period of
      ibrutinib when given in combination with lenalidomide and rituximab.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study of lenalidomide and ibrutinib.

      Patients receive lenalidomide orally (PO) once daily (QD) on days 1-21 and ibrutinib PO QD
      on days 1-28. Treatment repeats every 28 days for up to 18 courses in the absence of disease
      progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients also receive rituximab intravenously (IV) on
      days 1, 8, 15, and 22 of course 1 and once weekly at weeks 13, 21, 29, and 37.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 4 months for 2 years and
      then every 6 months for 8 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximally tolerated dose (MTD) of lenalidomide and ibrutinib for combination with rituximab, determined by dose-limiting toxicities (DLT) graded using the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Defined as the highest dose at which 0 or 1 of 6 patients experience DLT.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicities by attribute and grade, assessed using NCI CTCAE version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Summarized for each dose level.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated for each dose level.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated for each dose level.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>The time between registration and disease progression or death, assessed up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated by Kaplan-Meier method for the whole number of patients in this study and at the MTD.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>The time between registration and death, assessed up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated by Kaplan-Meier method for the whole number of patients in this study and at the MTD.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameters of iburitinib and major metabolite PCI-45227</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 and 15 of course 1 and week 13 (pre-dose, 1, 2, 4, 7, and 24 hours post-ibrutinib dose)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Tabulated and summarized using descriptive statistics.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>BTK parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>At 4 hours and 24 hours post ibrutinib dosing</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Tabulated and summarized using descriptive statistics.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">33</enrollment>
  <condition>Contiguous Stage II Grade 1 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Contiguous Stage II Grade 2 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Contiguous Stage II Grade 3 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Noncontiguous Stage II Grade 1 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Noncontiguous Stage II Grade 2 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Noncontiguous Stage II Grade 3 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Grade 1 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Grade 2 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Grade 3 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Grade 1 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Grade 2 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Grade 3 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (lenalidomide, ibrutinib, and rituximab)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive lenalidomide PO QD on days 1-21 and ibrutinib PO QD on days 1-28. Treatment repeats every 28 days for up to 18 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients also receive rituximab IV on days 1, 8, 15, and 22 of course 1 and once weekly at weeks 13, 21, 29, and 37.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>lenalidomide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (lenalidomide, ibrutinib, and rituximab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CC-5013</other_name>
    <other_name>IMiD-1</other_name>
    <other_name>Revlimid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ibrutinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (lenalidomide, ibrutinib, and rituximab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Bruton's tyrosine kinase inhibitor PCI-32765</other_name>
    <other_name>BTK inhibitor PCI-32765</other_name>
    <other_name>CRA-032765</other_name>
    <other_name>Imbruvica</other_name>
    <other_name>PCI-32765</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>rituximab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (lenalidomide, ibrutinib, and rituximab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IDEC-C2B8</other_name>
    <other_name>IDEC-C2B8 monoclonal antibody</other_name>
    <other_name>Mabthera</other_name>
    <other_name>MOAB IDEC-C2B8</other_name>
    <other_name>Rituxan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (lenalidomide, ibrutinib, and rituximab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pharmacological studies</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (lenalidomide, ibrutinib, and rituximab)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Previously untreated, histologically confirmed follicular lymphoma, World Health
             Organization (WHO) classification grade 1, 2, or 3a (&gt; 15 centroblasts per high power
             field with centrocytes present) that is stage III, IV, or bulky (i.e., single mass &gt;=
             7 cm in any unidimensional measurement) stage II and requires therapy at the
             discretion of the primary physician

               -  Bone marrow biopsies as the sole means of diagnosis are not acceptable, but they
                  may be submitted in conjunction with nodal biopsies; fine needle aspirates are
                  not acceptable for diagnosis

               -  Failure to submit pathology specimens within 60 days of patient registration
                  will be considered a major protocol violation

               -  Institutional flow cytometry or immunohistochemistry must confirm cluster of
                  differentiation 20 (CD20) antigen expression

               -  All risk by follicular lymphoma international prognostic index (FLIPI): 0-5 risk
                  factors

          -  No prior systemic therapy for non-Hodgkin lymphoma (NHL) including chemotherapy or
             immunotherapy (e.g., monoclonal antibody-based therapy), radiation therapy, or
             radioimmunotherapy

          -  For non-NHL conditions, no chemotherapy, radiotherapy, or major surgery within 4
             weeks (6 weeks for nitrosureas or mitomcyin C) of enrollment; no patients who have
             ongoing adverse events from agents administered more than 4 weeks previously

          -  No prior exposure to any of the study agents

          -  No corticosteroids within two weeks prior to study entry, except for maintenance
             therapy for a non-malignant disease; dose of corticosteroid or prednisone (or its
             equivalent) should not exceed 20 mg per day; corticosteroid premedication for
             rituximab is allowed

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status must be =&lt; 2

          -  Measurable disease must be present either on physical examination or imaging studies;
             non-measurable disease alone is not acceptable; any tumor mass &gt; 1 cm is acceptable;
             lesions that are considered non-measurable include the following:

               -  Bone lesions (lesions if present should be noted)

               -  Ascites

               -  Pleural/pericardial effusion

               -  Lymphangitis cutis/pulmonis

               -  Bone marrow (involvement by NHL should be noted)

          -  Patients with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection are eligible, provided
             they meet the following:

               -  No evidence of coinfection with hepatitis B or C

               -  Cluster of differentiation 4 (CD4)+ cell count &gt;= 400/mm^3

               -  No evidence of resistant strains of HIV

               -  If not on anti-HIV therapy, HIV viral load &lt; 10,000 copies HIV ribonucleic acid
                  (RNA)/mL

               -  If on anti-HIV therapy, HIV viral load &lt; 50 copies HIV RNA/mL

               -  No history of acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS)-defining conditions

               -  No use of strong cytochrome P450, family 3, subfamily A, polypeptide 4/5
                  (CYP3A4/5) inhibitors or inducers

          -  No known central nervous system (CNS) involvement by lymphoma

          -  No treatment with strong inhibitors or inducers of CYP3A4/5

          -  No evidence of active hepatitis B or C infections (i.e., no positive serology for
             anti-hepatitis B virus [HBV] or anti-hepatitis C virus [HCV] antibodies); HBV
             seropositive patients (hepatitis B surface antigen [HBsAg] +) are eligible if they
             are closely monitored for evidence of active HBV infection by HBV deoxyribonucleic
             acid (DNA) testing and receive suppressive therapy with lamivudine or other HBV
             suppressive therapy until 6 months after the last rituximab dose

          -  No history of erythema multiforme, toxic epidermal necrolysis or Stevens-Johnson
             syndrome

          -  No history of uncontrolled seizures

          -  No autoimmune disorder that requires active immunosuppression

          -  No intracranial hemorrhage within the last 6 months

          -  Non-pregnant and non-nursing; females of childbearing potential (FCBP) must have a
             negative serum or urine pregnancy test with a sensitivity of at least 50 mIU/mL
             within 10-14 days prior to registration; further, they must either commit to
             continued abstinence from heterosexual intercourse or begin TWO acceptable methods of
             birth control: one highly effective method and one additional effective method AT THE
             SAME TIME, at least 28 days before starting lenalidomide; FCBP must also agree to
             ongoing pregnancy testing; men must agree to use a latex condom during sexual contact
             with a FCBP, even if they have had a successful vasectomy; a FCBP is a sexually
             mature woman who: 1) has not undergone a hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy, or
             2) has not been naturally postmenopausal for at least 24 consecutive months (i.e.,
             has had menses at any time preceding 24 consecutive months)

          -  No known human anti-chimeric antibody (HACA) positivity

          -  No anticoagulation with warfarin is allowed; patients must not have received warfarin
             within 28 days prior to registration; alternative anticoagulant may be used

          -  Patients must not be receiving concurrent treatment with other investigational drugs

          -  Patients must not have a history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of
             similar chemical or biologic composition to lenalidomide, ibrutinib, or other agents
             used in study

          -  Patients must not have presence of transfusion-dependent thrombocytopenia

          -  No currently active clinically significant cardiovascular disease including the
             following:

               -  No uncontrolled arrhythmia

               -  No congestive heart failure

               -  No class 3 or 4 cardiac disease as defined by the New York Heart Association
                  Functional Classification

               -  No history of myocardial infarction, deep venous or arterial thrombosis within 6
                  months prior to registration

          -  No prior malignancy with the exceptions listed below:

               -  Malignancy treated with curative intent and with no evidence of active disease
                  for more than 3 years prior to screening and felt to be at low risk for
                  recurrence by the treating physician

               -  Adequately treated non-melanomatous skin cancer or lentigo maligna melanoma
                  without current evidence of disease

               -  Adequately treated cervical carcinoma in situ without current evidence of
                  disease

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1,000/microliter

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) =&lt; 2.5 x upper
             limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x ULN unless attributable to NHL; unless attributable to
             Gilbert's syndrome, or disease infiltration of the liver is present

          -  Creatinine clearance &gt; 60 mL/min (patients on dialysis are not eligible); to be
             calculated by method of Cockcroft-Gault, using actual weight

          -  Creatinine =&lt; 2 x ULN

          -  Platelet count &gt;= 75,000/microliter
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chaitra Ujjani</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cancer and Leukemia Group B</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lombardi Comprehensive Cancer Center at Georgetown University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20057</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chaitra S. Ujjani</last_name>
      <phone>202-444-0381</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chaitra S. Ujjani</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cancer and Leukemia Group B</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60606</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chaitra S. Ujjani</last_name>
      <phone>202-444-0596</phone>
      <email>chaitra.s.ujjani@gunet.georgetown.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chaitra S. Ujjani</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sonali M. Smith</last_name>
      <phone>773-834-7424</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sonali M. Smith</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ann S. LaCasce</last_name>
      <phone>866-790-4500</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ann S. LaCasce</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14263</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Myron S. Czuczman</last_name>
      <phone>877-275-7724</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Myron S. Czuczman</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Peter Martin</last_name>
      <phone>212-746-1848</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Martin</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven I. Park</last_name>
      <phone>877-668-0683</phone>
      <email>cancerclinicaltrials@med.unc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steven I. Park</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kristie A. Blum</last_name>
      <phone>866-627-7616</phone>
      <email>osu@emergingmed.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kristie A. Blum</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 19, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 9, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Follicular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
