<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="28501">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02005016</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>O0832-R</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1I01RX000832-01A2</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02005016</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dosage and Predictors of Naming Treatment Response in Aphasia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Dosage and Predictors of Naming Treatment Response in Aphasia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study examines aphasia treatment response among veterans living with aphasia. It seeks
      to identify cognitive and neural factors which are predictive of positive response to
      treatment targeting naming impairments in aphasia. It also examines the dose-response
      relationship for naming treatment. More broadly, it seeks to determine who aphasia therapy
      works best for, and how much aphasia therapy is sufficient to achieve positive treatment
      response.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Language and communicative impairments following stroke (aphasia) affect more than 30% of
      stroke survivors, with an incidence of over 180,000 new cases annually. The consequences of
      aphasia are far reaching and can affect psychosocial adjustment, family role participation,
      vocational opportunities, and the ability to function independently in society. Recent
      estimates suggest that VHA outpatient clinics see 2000 new cases of aphasia each year,
      meaning that approximately 20,000 enrolled VHA patients and 100,000 United States veterans
      are currently living with the condition. In response to this need, the VA Pittsburgh
      Healthcare System Geriatric Research, Education, and Clinical Center (GRECC) initiated the
      Program for Intensive Residential Aphasia Treatment and Education (PIRATE) in January 2009.
      PIRATE is a clinical demonstration project that provides approximately 100 hours of
      cognitive-linguistically oriented aphasia treatment to community dwelling veterans over a
      4-week period. PIRATE currently serves 18 veterans per year in bi-monthly sessions. Resource
      limitations associated with PIRATE and aphasia treatment in general require that treatments
      be offered in the most cost-effective doses to those veterans most likely to benefit from
      them.

      This treatment-effectiveness research study addresses these issues by examining the
      dose-response relationship for semantically-oriented naming treatment, and identifying
      cognitive, psycholinguistic and neuroanatomical predictors of treatment success. Study
      participants (n=60, over a 4-year period) will be recruited nationwide from veterans
      enrolled in PIRATE. They will have their naming performance measured prior to PIRATE entry,
      during each week of treatment, and at program exit/follow-up. A battery of cognitive
      measures and structural magnetic resonance images of their brains will also be collected
      prior to treatment. Participants' performance on trained and untrained lexical items and a
      standardized measure of naming performance will be compared across time intervals to specify
      the therapy amounts for which maximum treatment benefits are achieved. Their treatment
      outcomes will also be correlated with specific cognitive test scores and the location and
      extent of their brain lesions to identify cognitive and neurological markers predictive of
      positive treatment response. Treatment response will also be compared across participants
      with different psycholinguistic profiles, to determine which groups of patients show
      greatest benefit from semantically-oriented naming treatment.

      This study should provide answers to two interlocking questions: for whom is aphasia therapy
      most effective, and how much of it is needed to optimize treatment outcomes. These answers
      have the potential to set transformative new standards for how aphasia treatment is
      delivered within VHA and to stroke survivors with aphasia more broadly.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Philadelphia Naming Test</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be administered after completion of intervention, the day after intervention is complete.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Philadelphia Naming Test is a performance-based measure commonly used to assess naming (word production) ability among adults with aphasia.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comprehensive Aphasia Test</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be administered after completion of intervention, the day after intervention is complete.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Comprehensive Aphasia Test is a performance-based measure of language processing across multiple language domains commonly used to assess language-processing ability among adults with aphasia.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Aphasia</condition>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All study participants will be assigned to this arm of this single-arm study.  Participants will receive intensive behavioral therapy intended to improve their naming (word production) ability.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Naming therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive behavioral therapy which is designed to stimulate semantic (meaning) representations which are required for successful naming (word production). Therapy will be administered for 4 weeks on an intensive schedule (5 days a week, approximately 4.5 hours per day).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Semantic feature analysis</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        All study participants will be community-dwelling adults with aphasia who are accepted
        into the Program for Intensive Residential Aphasia Treatment and Education (PIRATE) of the
        VA Pittsburgh Healthcare System (VAPHS). PIRATE participants are veterans, who are
        referred nationally to VAPHS.  Aphasia diagnosis is provided by the referring medical
        provider, based on performance on standardized aphasia-assessment measures, and will be
        verified by PIRATE staff prior to enrollment. Diagnosis will be based on clinical
        impression and performance on the Comprehensive Aphasia Test (CAT).

        Study participants must also meet the following inclusion criteria:

          -  18 years of age or older

          -  Eligible for participation in the standard PIRATE program

          -  Aphasia due to unilateral left hemisphere stroke equal to or more than 6 months post
             onset

          -  Overall CAT mean language modality t-score of less than or equal to 70

          -  CAT naming modality t-score greater than or equal to 40

          -  No progressive neurological disease or prior central nervous system injury/disorder

          -  No severe motor speech disorders (apraxia and/or dysarthria)

          -  Learned English as a first language

          -  Investigators able to construct lists of sufficient treatment targets and
             generalization probes based on performance on naming assessments

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Since study candidates must first be eligible for PIRATE enrollment, the following PIRATE
        exclusion criteria indirectly apply:

          -  Inability to carry out activities of daily living necessary for self-care as
             determined by an occupational therapy assessment prior to program entry

          -  Lack of physical independence

          -  History of significant mood or behavioral disorder that is not currently
             stable/medically managed

          -  History of progressive neurological disease

          -  History of drug or alcohol dependence that is not currently stable/medically managed

          -  Inability to tolerate intensive treatment as determined by previous therapy
             experiences and tolerance of the intensive initial PIRATE evaluation (2 days of
             testing)

          -  Medical conditions which would preclude independent living as determined by the
             medical assessment provided by a VAPHS physician prior to program entry
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Walsh Dickey, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Pittsburgh Healthcare System University Drive Division, Pittsburgh, PA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael W Dickey, PhD</last_name>
    <email>Michael.Dickey@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Pittsburgh Healthcare System University Drive Division, Pittsburgh, PA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15240</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael W Dickey, PhD</last_name>
      <email>Michael.Dickey@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Walsh Dickey, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.pittsburgh.va.gov/PIRATE/</url>
    <description>Click here for more information about this study: Dosage and Predictors of Naming Treatment Response in Aphasia</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 5, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 14, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Aphasia</keyword>
  <keyword>Language Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Acquired Language Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Semantics</keyword>
  <keyword>Stroke</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Aphasia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
