<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="43395">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01683825</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012P001322</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01683825</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Imaging Cardiac Amyloidosis: A Pilot Study Using F-18 Florbetapir Positron Emission Tomography</brief_title>
  <official_title>Imaging Cardiac Amyloidosis: A Pilot Study Using F-18 Florbetapir Positron Emission Tomography</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brigham and Women's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Amyloid Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brigham and Women's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary aim of this pilot study is to determine whether amyloid deposits in the heart
      can be measured non-invasively by F-18 florbetapir (Trade Name: Amyvid)  positron emission
      tomography (PET) in 10 individuals with documented cardiac amyloidosis. We will also enroll
      5 individuals without cardiac amyloidosis to undergo the F-18 florbetapir imaging as a
      control group.

      The primary hypothesis of this study is that a specific amyloid binding radiotracer will
      bind to the myocardial amyloid deposits and help quantify cardiac amyloid burden.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      F-18 florbetapir has been studied in multiple clinical trials to image beta-amyloid
      deposition in the brain of subjects with Alzheimers' disease. Florbetapir F-18 has been well
      tolerated in studies of more than 2000 human subjects. Biodistribution studies in humans
      revealed predominantly hepatobiliary excretion. The tracer clears rapidly from the blood
      pool in about 20 minutes. This radiotracer has been recently approved for clinical imaging
      of brain amyloid in subjects with suspected Alzheimers disease. The investigators propose to
      test this FDA approved radiotracer for an off label indication in a pilot study to evaluate
      its potential utility, if any, to image cardiac amyloidosis.

      Amyloid related heart disease is associated with LV wall thickening due to infiltration;
      however, this myocardial wall thickening is not definitively distinguishable from left
      ventricular myocyte hypertrophy from increased afterload to the heart from hypertension or
      aortic stenosis. Typically myocardial or other tissue biopsy with typical echo features of
      amyloidosis is required for confirmation of amyloidosis. This pilot study is designed to
      understand whether cardiac amyloid burden can be measured using a specific radiotracer
      targeted against amyloid protein (F-18 Florbetapir). At this point it is unknown of F-18
      Florbetapir will bind to either AL or TTR amyloid protein or to both of them or to neither
      of them. The investigators would like to study 5 patients with AL and 5 patients with TTR
      amyloidosis to understand these differences if any. The investigators also seek to
      understand if the signal to noise ratio of the circulating amyloid protein in the blood pool
      (AL amyloid disease) allows for good differentiation of myocardial amyloid uptake. 5
      individuals without cardiac amyloidosis will also be enrolled as controls for this study.

      The purpose of the proposed research study is to examine in detail, using quantitative PET,
      myocardial F-18 Florbetapir uptake in cardiac amyloidosis in order to better understand
      mechanisms of heart damage in this disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Myocardial Radiotracer Uptake</measure>
    <time_frame>This study will take about 1.5 hours to complete. This study entails measurement of mean myocardial radiotracer dose on the images obtained on the day of the study.No follow-up is planned.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This is a pilot feasibility study using the newly approved radiotracer F-18 florbetapir.  Mean myocardial uptake will be estimated in the subjects on the images obtained   Mean liver to heart ratio will be estimated. No follow-up images are planned.
The myocardial F-18 Florbetapir images will be processed and viewed in the standard cardiac imaging planes. Visual assessment of relative myocardial uptake of F-18 Florbetapir will be performed and scored using a 0-3 scale (0=normal, 1= mild uptake, 2= moderate uptake, 3=significant uptake). Myocardial uptake of F-18 Florbetapir will be quantified using a software on the Hermes system (image viewing station). Also, specific uptake values of the radiotracer in the myocardium will be computed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiac Amyloidosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>F-18 florbetapir PET</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>10 individuals with documented cardiac amyloidosis will undergo F-18 florbetapir (Trade Name: Amyvid) positron emission tomography (PET).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>5 individuals without documented cardiac amyloidosis will undergo F-18 florbetapir (Trade Name: Amyvid) positron emission tomography (PET).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>F-18 florbetapir PET</intervention_name>
    <description>Cardiac PET images will be obtained following injection of F-18 labeled Florbetapir (Trade Name: Amyvid)</description>
    <arm_group_label>F-18 florbetapir PET</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>F-18 labeled Florbetapir (Trade Name: Amyvid)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Inclusion criteria for amyloid subjects:

          -  Age &gt; 18 years

          -  Biopsy proven amyloidosis outside the heart with typical echocardiographic appearance
             of cardiac involvement, or a positive cardiac biopsy.

          -  Diagnosis of AL amyloidosis by standard criteria (evidence of plasma cell dyscrasia
             with appropriate tissue staining for AL) OR

          -  Diagnosis of TTR amyloidosis (no evidence of plasma call dyscrasia and positive TTR
             staining of amyloid in tissue biopsy)

          -  Able and willing to provide informed consent to participate in the study procedures

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Serious non-cardiac medical illness or a social situation which will preclude
             research study participation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sharmila Dorbala, MBBS, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Divya Vangala, MA</last_name>
    <phone>857-307-2045</phone>
    <email>dvangala@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham and Women's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sharmila Dorbala, MBBS, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>857-307-1957</phone>
      <email>sdorbala@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sharmila Dorbala, MBBS, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.brighamandwomens.org/Departments_and_Services/medicine/services/cvcenter/Amyloidosis/research.aspx</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 6, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 4, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sharmila Dorbala, MBBS</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Nuclear Cardiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Amyloidosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiac</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart</keyword>
  <keyword>Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Diagnosis</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Amyloidosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
