<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="119249">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01775670</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01775670</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Off-the-Shelf Splints Versus Occupational Therapy Splints for Treatment of Trapeziometacarpal Arthrosis</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The specific aim is to compare the effectiveness of Off-the-Shelf splints and splints
      provided by Occupational Therapy for treatment of trapeziometacarpal (TMC) arthrosis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Trapeziometacarpal (TMC) arthrosis is so common, particularly in women, that it should be
      considered a normal part of the aging process. Overall radiographic prevalence of TMC
      arthrosis has been described to be as high as 91% in patients older than eighty years of
      age. It increases steadily from the age of 41 years, more rapidly in women than in men.
      Another study, conducted in the Netherlands, showed that in a population of 55 years and
      older, 67% of women and 55% of men had radiographic signs of arthrosis of the hand. It also
      found that the distal interphalangeal (DIP) joints are most commonly affected (47%),
      followed by the TMC joint (36%). However, it has been reported that in symptomatic
      arthrosis, TMC arthrosis contributes more to pain and disability than arthrosis of the
      interphalangeal joints. Psychosocial factors have been recognized as the strongest
      determinants of highly variable pain intensity and arm-specific disability. The
      pathophysiologic and psychosocial differences between patients who present to the doctor for
      treatment and those who do not are incompletely understood.

      A hand-based thumb spica splint with the interphalangeal (IP) joint free is a specific
      nonoperative palliative treatment for TMC arthrosis. The goals of splint wear are improved
      comfort and function. The data regarding specific splint materials are limited, but suggest
      that shorter more flexible splints are preferred by patients and equally effective.
      Recently, the investigators looked into if there was a difference between thermoplast and
      neoprene hand-based thumb spica splints for treatment of TMC arthrosis. The neoprene splint
      was rated more comfortable than the thermoplast splint but otherwise there was no
      difference.

      To the investigators' knowledge no studies have looked at the added value of occupational
      therapy in splint treatment for TMC arthrosis. The investigators believe that the time spent
      by occupational therapists (OTs) coaching patients on adaptive and palliative measures is
      valuable in addition to their technical skills but the investigators cannot draw any
      conclusions until the investigators research this in a prospective trial.

      The investigators propose a two arm unblinded, randomized (1:1) controlled trial to evaluate
      if there is a difference between prefabricated off-the-shelf splints and splints provided by
      an OT with standard care coaching. The investigators want to determine if there is a
      difference in arm-specific disability, average pain, and satisfaction at an average of 2
      months between splints provided by an OT and prefabricated off-the-shelf splints.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand Quick Questionnaire (Quick-DASH)</measure>
    <time_frame>At enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Quick-DASH measures the patient's ability to do following activities in the week before a visit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from the baseline in the Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand Quick Questionnaire (Quick-DASH) at 2 months after enrollment</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months after enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>2-month change in the Quick-DASH, which measures the patient's ability to do following activities in the week before a visit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Thumb pain at enrollment</measure>
    <time_frame>At enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient's thumb pain will be recorded on a numerical rating scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Average thumb pain and satisfaction with the splint 2 months after enrollment</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2 months after enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Average thumb pain on a numerical scale and satisfaction with splint treatment will be assessed 2 months after enrollment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS) - Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>At Enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A computerized assessment of depression measured at enrollment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PROMIS Pain - Interference</measure>
    <time_frame>At Enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A computerized assessment of pain interference measured at enrollment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Thumb metacarpophalangeal (MCP) hyperextension, and grip and pinch strength</measure>
    <time_frame>At Enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Various measurements of thumb extension, grip and punch strength will be measured at enrollment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Trapeziometacarpal (TMC) Arthrosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Off-the-Shelf Splint</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this arm will be managed with off-the-shelf splints for TMC arthrosis.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>OT Splint</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this arm will be managed with a custom-made splint made by the MGH Occupational Therapists.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Off-the-shelf splint</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will use an off-the-shelf splint</description>
    <arm_group_label>Off-the-Shelf Splint</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>OT Splint</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will use a splint custom-made by MGH Occupational Therapists.</description>
    <arm_group_label>OT Splint</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. 40 years of age and older

          2. Clinical or radiological diagnosis of TMC arthrosis by MD

          3. English fluency and literacy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Prior surgical treatment of TMC arthrosis on same side

          2. Prior treatment of TMC arthrosis on same side with a splint during the  last two
             months

          3. Prior injury of the trapeziometacarpal joint

          4. Rheumatoid arthritis

          5. Pregnant women.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David C Ring, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 16, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 22, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David C. Ring, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Arthrosis</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Joint Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
