<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="149745">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02004288</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CSUB0083</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02004288</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Role of Lactobacillus Reuteri in Children and Adolescents With Anorexia Nervosa</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Role of Lactobacillus Reuteri in Nutritional Recovery and Treatment of Constipation in Children and Adolescents With Anorexia Nervosa - Randomised, Double Blind, Placebo Controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>BioGaia AB</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>BioGaia AB</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Croatia: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to investigate whether Lactobacillus reuteri could have a
      beneficial role in treatment of children and adolescents with Anorexia nervosa who develop
      motility disorder due to the malnutrition regarding the normalization of the motility, as
      well as the possible role of probiotics on nutritional recovery, especially on bone health.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pediatric patients with AN and constipation referred to gastroenterologist for nutritional
      rehabilitation at the Department of Pediatric Gastroenterology, Hepatology and Nutrition,
      Clinical Hospital Center Sestre Milosrdnice, Zagreb,  approximately 30 children, will be
      asked to participate.

      The evaluation of patients will be conducted through APA DSM-V diagnostic criteria for
      anorexia nervosa and Rome III criteria for constipation.

      During the hospitalization all of the patients will receive conventional nutritional
      rehabilitation that is composed of serving normal food under supervision of nurses that
      calculate daily caloric intake through 5-6 meals and according to that additional enteral
      nutrition that consist of polymeric enteral formula. Daily caloric intake is calculated as
      kcal/kg/day and is slowly rising through 2 weeks starting from 80% to the goal of 130% of
      daily energy requirements according to FAO 2004 recommendation.

      Anthropometry measures will be taken at the time of hospitalization and at every visit.

      Normalization of weight is when the Z-score for BMI is less than -1.5 according to CDC
      BMI-growth charts, or normalisation of menstrual cycle is achieved.

      In order to achieve adherence to therapeutic protocol parents will be contacted by phone at
      least once in 7-10 days. Participants will be instructed to keep diary on a daily basis
      (adherence to therapy, stool  diary). All patients will return packages with all used, and
      unused product.

      BASELINE -VISIT 1 Randomization at first day of hospitalization. In all patients
      anthropometry will be performed at the time of hospitalization, as well as dual-energy X-ray
      absorptiometry (DEXA) and serum D3 levels at first 2 days of hospitalization as a part of
      routine diagnostic protocol in heavily underweight patients with AN.

      VISIT 2 4 weeks after randomization, at discharge from hospital Anthropometry

      VISIT 3 8 weeks after randomization, 4 weeks after discharge from hospital Anthropometry

      END OF STUDY -VISIT 4 3 months after baseline Anthropometry

      VISIT 5 3 months after the end of study (6 months after baseline) At this point control
      serum D3 levels and DEXA will be performed at all patients Anthropometry

      All the symptoms and daily caloric intake will be monitored using diaries attached to
      protocol.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Drop out from Rome III criteria for constipation</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>normalization of body weight</measure>
    <time_frame>6 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Anorexia Nervosa</condition>
  <condition>Constipation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lactobacillus reuteri Protectis DSM17938</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>One chewable tablet per day with L reuteri Protectis DSM 17938, 1x108 CFU/tablet (colony forming unit)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>One chewable tablet with placebo per day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lactobacillus reuteri Protectis DSM17938</intervention_name>
    <description>One chewable tablet with L. reuteri or placebo taken once a day for 3 months. After the 3 month therapy both groups will be monitored for the next 3 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lactobacillus reuteri Protectis DSM17938</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pediatric patients with Anorexia nervosa and constipation, aged 8-18 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  AN and constipation present for less than 3 month prior to hospitalization

          -  any  disease that affects GI or other systems other than AN or functional
             constipation

          -  chronic disorder other than AN

          -  receiving probiotic and/or prebiotic products 14 days prior to enrolment

          -  receiving antibiotics 14 days prior to enrolment

          -  constipation prior AN

          -  receiving laxative as a therapy for constipation or abuse of laxative to lose weight
             prior to enrolment

          -  extraintestinal symptoms: fever, rash

          -  abnormalities in laboratory findings

          -  abnormalities in clinical findings: organomegaly, perianal disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Orjena Zaja Franulovic, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Pediatric Gastroenterology, Hepatology and Nutrition Clinical Hospital Centre  Sestre milosrdnice Vinogradska 29 Zagreb,  Croatia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Orjena Zaja Franulovic, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+ 385993787277</phone>
    <email>orjenazf@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tatjana Lesar, MD</last_name>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pediatric Department Clinical Hospital Centre Sestre milosrdnice Gastroenterology, Hepatology and Nutrition Ward</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zagreb</city>
        <country>Croatia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Orjena Zaja franulovic, PhD, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+38513787917</phone>
      <email>orjenazf@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Orjena Zaja Franulovic, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Croatia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 13, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 2, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Probiotics</keyword>
  <keyword>Anorexia nervosa</keyword>
  <keyword>Constipation</keyword>
  <keyword>Body weight</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anorexia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anorexia Nervosa</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Constipation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
