<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="117707">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01952769</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>antiPD1brainad</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01952769</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Anti PD1 Antibody in Diffuse Intrinsic Pontine Glioma and Relapsed Glioblastoma Multiforme</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/ II Clinical Trial of CT-011 (Pidilizumab) in Diffuse Intrinsic Pontine Glioma and Relapsed Glioblastoma Multiforme</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hadassah Medical Organization</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hadassah Medical Organization</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Israel :  Ministry of Health - Director General</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      patients with recurrent malignant gliomas or diffuse pontine gliomas are incurable with
      currently used treatments. based on data stating that progressive tumors inhibit immune
      system, would try to enhance immune system activity and tumor cell killing. anti PD1
      prevents one of the important mechanisms allowing the tumor to supress the immune system
      thus we hope it will allow for prolonged control of the tumors
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. Diffuse intrinsic pontine glioma Diffuse intrinsic pontine glioma (DIPG) is the most
           lethal pediatric malignant disease. Children are usually diagnosed at the age of 6-8
           years following a short history of neurological deterioration with often a combination
           of cranial nerve dysfunction, ataxia and long tract deficits. Diagnosis is MRI based
           and a biopsy is required only when tumor features on imaging are non-classic . As of
           today there is no curative treatment regardless of multiple clinical trials done in the
           past. Following diagnosis children undergo radiation therapy aiming at symptoms
           alleviation, with almost inevitable disease progression taking place several months
           later. Overall survival ranges between 9-12 months and death due to disease progression
           is the rule (1)

        2. Relapsed high grade glioma High grade glioma consists of more than 50% of brain tumors
           in the adult population. Cure rates are extremely low with median survival time of 8
           months and overall survival of 8-20% at  2 years. At tumor recurrence treatment options
           are highly limited. Bevacizumab may provide a further short term of stabilization but
           unfortunately in almost all cases relapsed/resistant high grade glioma is lethal.(2)

        3. Immunotherapy in brain tumors Data regarding possible role of the immune system in
           cancer was first presented in 2001 when Schreiber and Old demonstrated that
           lymphocytes, activated by interferon-γ, inhibit the development of spontaneous and
           carcinogen-induced tumors in immunodeficient mice (Shankaran et al, 2001).  Later
           studies demonstrated progressively decreasing immunogenicity in tumor cells of advanced
           cancer patients. Based on these and other data trials incorporating immunotherapy into
           treatment of relapsed high grade glioma were constructed.  Past trials centered upon
           active cell based  immunization trying to present the patients' immune system with
           specific antigens derived from their tumor while using different techniques to enhance
           immune response. These studies has shown positive results but the  need to prepare
           patient specific vaccination limited their use to highly specialized centers and
           results were hard to reproduce.(3)

        4. The role of PD-1 in cancer immunotherapy One of the mechanisms through which tumor
           cells escape immune detection is activation of the inhibitory lymphocyte receptor  PD-1
           (programmed death 1). Low grade activation of the T cell receptor-secondary to
           prolonged antigen exposure (as found in chronic disease or protracted exposure to
           malignant cells) - strongly activates- PD-1. Upon activation, PD-1 drives the
           lymphocyte towards apoptosis and  reduces cytokine production. PD-1/PD-1 ligand
           interaction promotes tolerance of the immune system to a specific antigen (4). Lately,
           studies reported  high levels of PD-1 expression in tumor infiltrating lymphocytes ,and
           strong expression of PD-ligand within multiple tumor types including high grade glioma
           .Both these findings support the data regarding the role of PD1 in cancer immune escape
           (5).

        5. Anti PD-1:Safety and efficacy in human studies Over the last two years data has been
           accumulating regarding efficacy and toxicity profile of anti PD-1.Topalian et.al
           reported at 2012 outcome of a large phase I study evaluating antiPD-1 in advanced
           cancers. Out of 296 participating patients 14% had Grade 3 or 4 drug-related adverse
           events with most being treated on an outpatient setup . Several patients were diagnosed
           with pneumonitis. Most were observed or treated successfully with steroids but three
           patients died. Among 236 patients in whom response could be evaluated, objective
           responses (complete or partial responses) were observed in those with non-small-cell
           lung cancer-a cancer not known to be immunoresponsive (18%), melanoma (28% ), or
           renal-cell cancer (27%). Responses were durable; 20 of 31 responses lasted 1 year or
           more (6). Further studies report a better toxicity profile with similar efficacy. Hamid
           et.al reported outcome of 135 patients with advanced melanoma. Side effects were mostly
           grade 1-2 with no treatment related mortality. Response rate among these patients was
           38% and most responses lasted at least 7 months (7). A study evaluating anti PD-1 in
           chronic HCV patient revealed similar safe profile. One patient out of 66  (10 mg/kg)
           experienced an asymptomatic grade 4 ALT elevation coincident with the onset of a 4-log
           viral load reduction. Six patients exhibited immune-related adverse events of
           mild-to-moderate intensity, including two cases of hyperthyroidism consistent with
           autoimmune thyroiditis (8).

        6. Anti CTLA-4 and anti PD-1 activity in brain tumors Unlike chemotherapy or targeted
           therapies, both antiCTLA-4 and anti PD-1 affect T lymphocytes rather than the tumor
           itself. Binding to the lymphocyte receptor may take place outside of the central
           nervous system. Following binding to their receptor the reactivated lymphocytes
           penetrate the brain and arrive to the tumor thus the antibodies are not required to
           cross the blood brain barrier. Data regarding activity of antiCTLA-4  within the brain
           may be retrieved from retrospective summary of melanoma patients with brain metastasis.
           These patients are usually ineligible for clinical trials due to their grim prognosis.
           Margolin e al reported partial response in 5 patients and stable disease for 12 weeks
           in another 4 out of 51 patients with asymptomatic brain melanoma metastasis. Patients
           with symptomatic lesions requiring steroid therapy did not respond. Di Giacomo reported
           disease stabilization in 5 and near total response in another 5 patients out of 20
           patients with asymptomatic metastatic melanoma lesions. These data provide proof of
           principle to the assumption that this regimen is active within the brain.

           Zeng et al reported improved survival of glioblastoma implanted mice following
           radiation and anti PD-1. Median survival was 25 days in the control arm, 27 days in the
           anti-PD-1 antibody arm, 28 days in the radiation arm, and 53 days in the radiation plus
           anti-PD-1 therapy arm, these data along with tolerability of  treatment calls for a
           clinical trial assessing this treatment in this population with extremely poor
           prognosis (9).

        7. CT011 mechanism of action and early efficacy data

      CT011 is one of several humanized anti PD1 antibodies currently under investigation in
      multiple tumors. A single dose of CT-011 given to mice with metastatic melanoma,
      fibrosarcoma,  lung carcinoma or colorectal adenocarcinoma led to significant reduction in
      lung and/or liver metastases along with prolonged survival. Combination of CT-011 with
      rituximab, chemotherapy and different types of vaccines has proven to be synergistic.

      In a phase I study enrolling 17 patients with advanced stage hematological malignancies
      (AML,CLL, Non-Hodgkin lymphoma, Hodgkin's disease and multiple myeloma)  5 patients had
      prolonged stable disease (averaging 60 weeks) and one patient with follicular lymphoma had a
      complete response.

      A Phase II study was conducted in 72 adult patients with DLBCL following autologous stem
      cell transplantation; in this study, CT-011 was given at a dose of 1.5 mg/kg per patient at
      3 cycles per patient every 42 days (treatment Days 1, 43, and 85). The PFS and OS 18 months
      after transplant were 72% and 85%, respectively. These values compare favorably with results
      obtained in previous similar cohorts. In addition, the ORR within the 40 patients who
      enrolled in the study with measurable disease was 45% (30%CR, 15%PR).

      A Phase II study was conducted in 30 adult patients with rituximab-sensitive, grade 1-2
      follicular lymphoma who relapsed after 1-4 prior therapies with measurable disease. CT-011
      was administered at 3 mg/kg IV every 4 weeks for 12 infusions and rituximab was dosed at 375
      mg/m2 IV weekly for 4 weeks starting 2 weeks after the first infusion of CT-011.  Of the 29
      patients eligible for efficacy analysis, 19 had an objective response for an ORR of 66%. CR
      was observed in 15 (52%) and PR in 4 (14%). Altogether, 25 (86%) patients had measurable
      tumor regression. The ORR of 66% and CR rate of 52% compare favorably with the previously
      reported ORR of 40% and CR rate of 11% with single agent rituximab retreatment in relapsed
      follicular lymphoma. Median time to response was 88 days. Of note, 17% of the patients
      achieved initial response &gt;3 months from first treatment. Median PFS was 19.6 months, and
      was not reached for the 19 responders or the 25 patients with measurable tumor regression.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>progression free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>rate of patients with stable disease at 6 months. stable disease is defined as no change in tumor measurements on MRI greater than 20% in two diameters</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>treatment related toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>monthly for 1 year or if treatment will be continued further due to response-throughout treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Treatment related toxicity according to NCI CTC Version 4.0 will be recorded monthly for 1 year or if treatment will be continued further due to response-throughout treatment. a patient with grade 3 or more treatment related toxicity will receive 50% dose reduction. if again grade 3 treatment related toxicity will occur the patient will be taken off study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>response on imaging and neurological examination</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Malignant Gliomas</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>recurrent/resistant malignant glioma</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>a. progressive or recurrent pathologically confirmed high grade glioma. Note: pathological confirmation for relapse is not needed  if there is pathology from primary diagnosis
intervention: CTO11 APPLICATION</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>diffuse pontine glioma</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>b.	DIPG diagnosed based on all the following: i.	Symptoms starting less than 6 weeks prior to diagnosis ii.	Symptoms include one or more of the following: cranial nerve deficit, cerebellar or long tract dysfunction iii.	MRI reveals a lesion infiltrating&gt;70% of the pons</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CT-011</intervention_name>
    <description>Eligible patients will be administered with CT-011 at 6.0mg/kg given as an IV infusion every other week until disease progression or a serious adverse event.</description>
    <arm_group_label>recurrent/resistant malignant glioma</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>diffuse pontine glioma</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pidilizumab</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age:3-90

          2. Diagnosis:

               1. progressive or recurrent pathologically confirmed high grade glioma. Note:
                  pathological confirmation for relapse is not needed  if there is pathology from
                  primary diagnosis.

               2. DIPG diagnosed based on all the following:

             i. Symptoms starting less than 6 weeks prior to diagnosis ii. Symptoms include one or
             more of the following: cranial nerve deficit, cerebellar or long tract dysfunction
             iii. MRI reveals a lesion infiltrating&gt;70% of the pons

             -

             Exclusion Criteria:

               1. grade 4 adverse event not improved by dose reduction of 50%

               2. withdrawal of informed consent

               3. disease progression
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Iris Fried, MD</last_name>
    <phone>97226777408</phone>
    <email>ishonet@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alex Lossos, MD</last_name>
    <email>alos@hadassah.org.il</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hadassah Hebrew University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jerusalem</city>
        <zip>91120</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Iris Fried, MD</last_name>
      <email>ishonet@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 26, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 15, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>anti PD1, malignant glioma. anaplastic astrocytoma.glioblastoma multiforme,diffuse pontine glioma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pontine Glioma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
