<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="99265">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02048358</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2B3-201-CR-001</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-004077-28</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02048358</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics Study With 2B3-201 in Healthy Subjects and Multiple Sclerosis(MS) Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo- and Active Comparator- Controlled Crossover Study in Healthy Male Subjects and an Open Label Study in Healthy Subjects and MS Patients to Assess the Safety, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of 2B3-201</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>to-BBB technologies B.V.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>to-BBB technologies B.V.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Netherlands: The Central Committee on Research Involving Human Subjects (CCMO)</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this first in human study the aim is to assess the safety, pharmacokinetics and
      pharmacodynamics of 2B3-201 in a randomized, first in human, double-blind, placebo- and
      active comparator- controlled 3-way crossover study in 18 healthy male subjects (part 1).
      Furthermore, the findings obtained from part 1 will be extended and confirmed in a
      subsequent parallel open label study in 18 healthy male and 6 MS patients and an open label
      study with methylprednisolone as comparator in 6 female volunteers (part 2).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with adverse events as a measure of safety and tolerability of 2B3-201</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety and tolerability of 2B3-201, in comparison to free methylprednisolone hemisuccinate and placebo and the safety and tolerability of 2B3-201amongst the different study populations: healthy male and female subjects and MS patients, additionally the safety and tolerability of 2B3-201 with hydroxypropyl β-cyclodextrin added to the infusion bag will be assessed in healthy male subjects</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics in plasma of intravenously administered 2B3-201 in terms of Cmax, Volume of distribution, half-life (T1/2), area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC), Clearance (CL)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Pharmacokinetics of 2B3-201, in comparison to free methylprednisolone hemisuccinate and placebo and the pharmacokinetics of 2B3-201amongst the different study populations: healthy male and female subjects and MS patients. Additionally the pharmacokinetics of 2B3-201 with hydroxypropyl β-cyclodextrin added to the infusion bag will be assessed in healthy male subjects</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure changes in central nervous system (CNS) functioning after intravenous administration of 2B3-201 by using the Neurocart test battery</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Neurocart test battery (Pharmaco-EEG, Maze learning, Visual verbal Learning test, Stroop test, Adaptive tracking, VAS Bond &amp; Lader and VAS Bowdle, Eye movements, LSEQ sleep questionnaire) as a measure of pharmacodynamic effects of 2B3-201 on CNS functioning in comparison to free methylprednisolone hemisuccinate and placebo;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in levels of Hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis hormones as a measure of pharmacodynamic effects of 2B3-201 in comparison to free methylprednisolone hemisuccinate and placebo;</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in levels of fasting blood glucose as a measure of pharmacodynamic effects of 2B3-201 in comparison to free methylprednisolone hemisuccinate and placebo;</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in levels of osteocalcin concentrations as a measure of pharmacodynamic effects of 2B3-201 in comparison to free methylprednisolone hemisuccinate and placebo;</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in levels of lymphocyte count as a measure of pharmacodynamic effects of 2B3-201 in comparison to free methylprednisolone hemisuccinate and placebo;</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in levels of complement factors during infusion as a measure of pharmacodynamic effects of 2B3-201 in comparison to free methylprednisolone hemisuccinate and placebo;</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Optimization of the infusion schedule for 2B3-201 with or without the addition of an anti-histaminic drug to minimize the likelihood of non-allergic infusion reactions.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in neurological examination, Expanded Disability Systems Score (EDSS) and Multiple Sclerosis functional composite (MSFC) after a single dose of 2B3-201 in patients with RRMS having an acute disease exacerbation, as a measure of clinical efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>8</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2B3-201 150mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>2B3-201 150mg, once, IV infusion in 1000ml 5% dextrose/ Methylprednisolone hemisuccinate 1000mg, once, IV infusion in 1000ml 5% dextrose/ Placebo, once, IV infusion 1000ml 5% dextrose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2B3-201 300mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>2B3-201 300mg, once, IV infusion in 1500ml 5% dextrose/ Methylprednisolone hemisuccinate 300mg, once, IV infusion in 1500ml 5% dextrose/ Placebo, once, IV infusion 1500ml 5% dextrose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2B3-201 450mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>2B3-201 450mg, once, IV infusion in 2500ml 5% dextrose/ Methylprednisolone hemisuccinate 1000mg, once, IV infusion in 2500ml 5% dextrose/ Placebo, once, IV infusion 2500ml 5% dextrose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>450mg 2B3-201</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>2B3-201 450mg, once, IV infusion in 2500ml 5% dextrose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>300mg 2B3-201</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>2B3-201 300mg, once, IV infusion in 1500ml 5% dextrose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2B3-201 450mg male volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>2B3-201 450mg, once, IV infusion in 1500ml 5% dextrose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2B3-201 300mg or 450mg female volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>2B3-201 300mg or 450mg, once, IV infusion in 1500 or 2500ml 5% dextrose/ Methylprednisolone hemisuccinate 1000mg, once, IV infusion in 1500 or 2500ml 5% dextrose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RRMS patients; 2B3-201 450 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>2B3-201 450mg, once, IV infusion in 2500ml 5% dextrose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>2B3-201</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>2B3-201 150mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2B3-201 300mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2B3-201 450mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>450mg 2B3-201</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>300mg 2B3-201</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2B3-201 450mg male volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2B3-201 300mg or 450mg female volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>RRMS patients; 2B3-201 450 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>2B3-201: glutathione PEGylated-liposomal methylprednisolone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>2B3-201 150mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2B3-201 300mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2B3-201 450mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>5% Dextrose</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methylprednisolone hemisuccinate</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>2B3-201 150mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2B3-201 300mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2B3-201 450mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2B3-201 300mg or 450mg female volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Solu-Medrol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Healthy subjects

          -  Healthy male or female subjects, 18 to 45 years of age, inclusive. Healthy status is
             defined by absence of evidence of any active or chronic disease following a detailed
             medical and surgical history, a complete physical examination including vital signs,
             12-lead ECG, hematology, blood chemistry, and urinalysis.

          -  Body mass index (BMI) between 18 and 30 kg/m2, inclusive, and with a minimum weight
             of 50 kg.

          -  Able to participate and willing to give written informed consent and to comply with
             the study restrictions.

        Relapsing remitting MS patients

          -  Age: 18 to 65 years, both men and women.

          -  RRMS according to the 2010 McDonald criteria.

          -  An estimated Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS) score prior to acute
             exacerbation: 0 to 5.0.

          -  A moderate (increase 1-2.5 points on EDSS score) or severe (increase ≥3 points on
             EDSS score) clinical acute exacerbation without improvement at the time of inclusion;

          -  Recent clinical exacerbation onset (&lt;10 days) without fever;

          -  One month of clinical stability prior to the acute exacerbation.

          -  Able to participate and willing to comply with the study restrictions. Understands
             and signs the written informed consent prior to any of the testing under this
             protocol, including screening tests and evaluations that are not considered part of
             the subject's routine care.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Healthy volunteers:

          -  Any subject who is pregnant or breastfeeding. A urine pregnancy test should be
             performed in female subjects of childbearing potential (defined as &lt; 2 years after
             last menstruation and not surgically sterile) prior to the start of the study
             treatment.

          -  For female subjects of childbearing potential (defined as &lt; 2 years after last
             menstruation and not surgically sterile) and male subjects who are not surgically
             sterile or with female partners of childbearing potential: absence of effective,
             non-hormonal means of contraception (intrauterine contraceptive device, barrier
             method of contraception in conjunction with spermicidal gel) will be a
             contraindication.

          -  Not willing to use double-barrier contraception, for the duration of the study and
             for 3 months after the last dose.

          -  Positive test for drugs of abuse at screening or pre-dose.

          -  History of alcohol consumption exceeding 2 standard drinks per day on average (1
             standard drink = 10 grams of alcohol) within 3 months of screening.  Alcohol
             consumption will be prohibited during study confinement and at least 48 hours before
             screening, before dosing, and before each scheduled visit.

          -  History or symptoms of any significant disease including (but not limited to),
             neurological, psychiatric, endocrine, cardiovascular, respiratory, gastrointestinal,
             hepatic, or renal disorder.

          -  Positive Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), Hepatitis C antibody (HCV Ab), or human
             immunodeficiency virus antibody (HIV Ab) at screening.

          -  Systolic blood pressure (SBP) greater than 140 mm Hg or less than 90 mm Hg, and
             diastolic blood pressure (DBP) greater than 90 mm Hg or less than 50 mm Hg.

          -  Use of any medications (prescription or over-the-counter [OTC]), vitamin, mineral,
             herbal, and dietary supplements within 21 days of study drug administration.
             Exceptions are paracetamol (up to 4 g/day).

          -  Use of CYP3A4-inhibiting drugs, including quinine containing drinks (bitter lemon and
             tonic water) is prohibited within 21 days of study drug administration

          -  Subject has used grapefruit, grapefruit juice, grapefruit-containing products,
             Seville oranges, or pomelo-containing products, within 14 days prior to day -1.

          -  Clinically significant abnormalities, as judged by the investigator, in laboratory
             test results (including hepatic and renal panels, complete blood count, chemistry
             panel and urinalysis). In the case of uncertain or questionable results, tests
             performed during screening may be repeated before randomization to confirm
             eligibility or judged to be clinically irrelevant for healthy subjects.

          -  Participation in an investigational drug or device study within 3 months prior to
             screening.

          -  Donation of blood over 500 mL within three months prior to screening.

          -  Concomitant disease or condition that could interfere with, or for which the
             treatment of might interfere with, the conduct of the study, or that would, in the
             opinion of the Investigator, pose an unacceptable risk to the subject in this study.

          -  Smoker of more than 10 cigarettes per day prior to screening or who use tobacco
             products equivalent to more than 10 cigarettes per day.

          -  Clinically significant abnormal ECG, as judged by the Investigator.

          -  Current infection or inflammation study within 1 month prior to screening

          -  Recent vaccinations study within 3 months prior to screening.

          -  Positive Mantoux test of 5 mm or more.

          -  Any confirmed significant allergic reactions (urticaria or anaphylaxis) against any
             drug, or multiple drug allergies (non-active hay fever is acceptable).

          -  Unwillingness or inability to comply with the study protocol for any other reason.

        MS patients:

          -  Previous acute exacerbations, and/or corticosteroid treatment or ACTH &lt; 1 month
             before present exacerbation, Primary Progressive Multiple Sclerosis (PPMS) or
             Secondary progressive MS without superimposed acute exacerbations.

          -  Symptoms of the acute exacerbation include a solitary optical neuritis. Unable to
             complete the EDSS scoring (while inability to complete one of the other scores would
             be acceptable).

          -  Peripheral or cranial neuropathy as the sole problem of the acute exacerbation
             episode.

          -  Hypersensitivity to methylprednisolone.

          -  Prior use of immunosuppressive treatments / disease-modifying drugs (DMDs) other than
             interferon-beta, glatiramer acetate, fingolimod or teriflunomide within 12 months of
             the index episode. Shorter periods may be allowed at the discretion of the PI and
             after approval from the sponsor. Subjects may continue their current therapy with
             interferons, glatiramer acetate, fingolimod, or teriflunomide throughout the course
             of the study.

          -  Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents, including salicylic acid, should be avoided
             during the administration of the steroid therapy. If absolutely necessary they are
             permitted for subjects to treat interferon side effects, when the patient is not
             responding to acetaminophen/paracetamol.

          -  Current or recent (within 30 days of first study treatment) treatment with any other
             investigational drug or participation in any other investigational study

          -  Evidence of psychiatric illness

          -  History of any significant cardiac, gastrointestinal, hepatic, pulmonary, renal or
             active immunosuppressive disease.

          -  Immune deficiency or any other medical conditions that would preclude corticosteroid
             therapy.

          -  Any patient who is pregnant or breastfeeding. A urine pregnancy test should be
             performed in female subjects of childbearing potential (defined as &lt; 2 years after
             last menstruation and not surgically sterile) prior to the start of the study
             treatment.

          -  For female subjects of childbearing potential (defined as &lt; 2 years after last
             menstruation and not surgically sterile) and male subjects who are not surgically
             sterile or with female partners of childbearing potential: absence of effective,
             non-hormonal means of contraception (intrauterine contraceptive device, barrier
             method of contraception in conjunction with spermicidal gel) will be a
             contraindication.

          -  Physical examination results or laboratory findings that may interfere with the
             planned treatment, affect patient compliance or place the patient at a high risk of
             treatment-related complications.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to any of the cyclodextrin or any excipients in 2B3-201 (e.g.
             PEG, Cholesterol, HSPC or GSH).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Geert-Jan Groeneveld, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Center for Human Drug Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ioanna Stavrakaki, PharmD,PDEng</last_name>
    <phone>+31(0)713322255</phone>
    <email>IoannaStavrakaki@tobbb.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre for Human Drug Research (CHDR)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leiden</city>
        <zip>2333 CH</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kawita Kanhai, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+31(0)715246468</phone>
      <email>kkanhai@chdr.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Geert-Jan Groeneveld, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gaillard PJ, Appeldoorn CC, Rip J, Dorland R, van der Pol SM, Kooij G, de Vries HE, Reijerkerk A. Enhanced brain delivery of liposomal methylprednisolone improved therapeutic efficacy in a model of neuroinflammation. J Control Release. 2012 Dec 28;164(3):364-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jconrel.2012.06.022. Epub 2012 Jun 23.</citation>
    <PMID>22732475</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 17, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Healthy volunteers</keyword>
  <keyword>first in human</keyword>
  <keyword>2B3-201</keyword>
  <keyword>methylprednisolone</keyword>
  <keyword>CNS-targeting</keyword>
  <keyword>liposomal</keyword>
  <keyword>crossover</keyword>
  <keyword>placebo controlled</keyword>
  <keyword>active controlled</keyword>
  <keyword>multiple sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>multiple sclerosis relapse</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone Hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone phosphate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
