<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="90853">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02065453</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>22548</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02065453</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Disposable Energy Sources and Operating Room Time for Laparoscopic Hysterectomy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Disposable Energy Sources and Operating Room Time for Laparoscopic Hysterectomy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Louis University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Louis University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Over 600,000 hysterectomies are performed each year nationwide. Over 99% of these are
      accomplished laparoscopically in the investigators current surgical practice to allow women
      a quicker recovery than a traditional large incision. Disposable laparoscopic devices have
      been developed to assist in the completion of hysterectomies. These disposable energy
      sources are only used once, but offer an improved safety and energy profile in that they
      reliably control bleeding with little damage to surrounding tissue and potentially save
      time. Reusable energy instruments can be sterilized and reused for multiple cases. Operating
      room time is expensive. The investigators calculate that if 6.7 minutes of time can be saved
      using the disposable device, Ligasure (Covidien), versus the reusable Robi bipolar and Storz
      Laparoscopic Shears, the time savings could justify the cost of the device.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This will be a randomized, prospective study. The investigators study design would have each
      patient serve as their own control. One side of the uterine attachments would be transected
      using the disposable device, Ligasure (Covidien), and the other using the two reusable
      devices (Robi bipolar and Storz laparoscpic shears). It is the investigators standard
      practice that the attending surgeon is on the patient's left side while the resident
      physician is on the patients right. To eliminate the bias of surgical experience, the
      investigators will randomize the energy source used on each side for every case. Therefore,
      the number of cases performed by the attending surgeon with the disposable or reusable
      energy sources, will equal that of the less experienced resident surgeon.

      The primary endpoint of this study would be the time difference between cauterizing one side
      of the uterine attachments, from the round ligament to the uterine artery on one side, to
      the time detaching the same tissues on the other side. The vesico-uterine peritoneum or
      &quot;bladder flap&quot;, will always be transected from the left for consistency. Sealed, opaque
      envelopes will be randomized to determine which side of the uterus will get the single
      disposable instrument, and which will get the 2 reusable instruments.

      A time savings of 6.7 minutes for the total case can also be explained by a 3.35 minute time
      savings PER SIDE of the uterine attachments, given each uterus has two &quot;sides&quot;. There is no
      pre-existing data on time needed for coagulation and cutting of the vascular tissues. Based
      on experience, the investigators estimate that it takes on average about 20 min total time
      for vessel sealing, with an estimated variability that approximately 70% of the time, vessel
      sealing is done within 35 minutes. Given these estimates, and using a power of 0.8, the
      sample size needed is 45.

      The primary endpoint of surgical time will be initially assessed for each individual patient
      by determining the difference between the half of the laparoscopic hysterectomy procedure
      performed with the disposable device, specifically the Ligasure (Covidien) and the half of
      the laparoscopic hysterectomy procedure performed with the two reusable devices (Robi
      Bipolar and Storz laparoscopic shears) and determining if the mean difference score summed
      across all patients differs significantly from zero. Subsequent analyses will examine
      surgical times for attending physicians and residents separately where those using the
      disposable device are compared to those using the two reusable devices with independent
      students t test or the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test depending on the normality of the
      distributions. Parallel analyses will be performed for the secondary endpoint of estimated
      blood loss. Secondary endpoints of organ damage and other categorical intraoperative
      complications will be compared between the disposable and reusable device groups using
      chi-square and Fisher's Exact test.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary endpoint of this study is time difference between cauterizing one side of the uterine attachments, from the round ligament to the uterine artery on one side, to the time detaching the same tissues on the other side</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients are consented on the day of surgery.  Primary outcome study data is collected with the first incision and completed with skin closure at the completion of the surgery.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A time savings of 6.7 minutes is needed to pay for the cost of the device.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary endpoints will be the number of Participants with complications (vascular and ureteral).</measure>
    <time_frame>Study patients are monitored for complications for 6 weeks after their surgical procedure.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>estimated blood loss and complications (vascular and ureteral).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Laparoscopic Hysterectomy</condition>
  <condition>Benign Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>disposable or reusable energy sources</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Our study design would have each patient serve as their own control. One side of the uterine attachments would be transected using the disposable device, the Ligasure, and the other using the two reusable devices, the Robi bipolar and Storz laparoscopic shears. It is our standard practice that the attending surgeon is on the patient's left side while the resident physician is on the patients right. To eliminate the bias of surgical experience, we will randomize the energy source used on each side for every case. Therefore, the number of cases performed by the attending surgeon with the disposable or reusable energy sources, will equal that of the less experienced resident surgeon.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>disposable device (Ligasure, Covidien), and  the reusable devices,(Robi bipolar and Storz laparoscopic shears).</intervention_name>
    <description>Each patient serve as their own control where one side of the uterine attachments would be transected using the disposable device (Ligasure, Covidien), and the other using the reusable Robi bipolar and Storz laparoscopic shears. We will randomize the side for each energy source used on each side for every case. The number of &quot;sides&quot; performed by the attending surgeon will equal that of the less experienced resident surgeon.</description>
    <arm_group_label>disposable or reusable energy sources</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>The disposable device (Ligasure made by Covidien).</other_name>
    <other_name>Reusable energy sources, the Robi bipolar and Storz laparoscopic shears.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 21 to 80 years of age

          -  Scheduled for laparoscopic hysterectomy (prospectively)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Under 21 years of age

          -  Known or anticipated malignancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mary B Holloran-Schwartz, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Louis University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Saint Louis University</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63117</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 11, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>St. Louis University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mary Brigid Holloran-Schwartz, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>laparoscopic hysterectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Women in need of a laparoscopic hysterectomy for benign disease.</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
