<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="95790">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01931956</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0401B</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>0401</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01931956</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Real World Expanded Multi-center Study of the MitraClip System (REALISM)</brief_title>
  <acronym>REALISM</acronym>
  <official_title>A Continued Access Registry of the Evalve® MitraClip® System: EVEREST II Real World Expanded Multi-center Study of the MitraClip System (REALISM)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Evalve</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Evalve</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Prospective, multi-center, continued access registry of the MitraClip® Cardiovascular Valve
      Repair System in the treatment of mitral valve regurgitation.  Clinical follow-up at
      discharge, 30 days, 6 months, 12 months, and 2-, 3-, 4-, and 5-years.  The study consists of
      two arms: a high risk group and a non-high risk group. Enrollment in high risk arm is
      ongoing. Enrollment in non-high risk arm concluded in April 2011.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The EVEREST II REALISM study (REALISM study) is a continued access registry designed for
      continued data collection on the use of Abbott Vascular's System (MitraClip device).  After
      the completion of enrollment in the pivotal EVEREST II Randomized Controlled Trial (RCT) and
      EVEREST II High Risk Registry Study (HRR), continued access to the technology was warranted
      to collect additional safety and effectiveness data on the MitraClip device.  This continued
      access study was approved by FDA on November 21, 2008 (G030064).  There are two arms (High
      Risk and Non-High Risk) in the REALISM study.  Enrollment in the Non-High Risk arm of the
      study concluded on April 14, 2011 and enrollment in the High Risk arm is ongoing.

      REALISM is a prospective, multi-center, study of the safety and effectiveness of an
      endovascular approach to the treatment of mitral valve regurgitation using the Evalve
      Cardiovascular Valve Repair System (MitraClip® implant). Patients with moderate-to-severe
      (3+) or severe (4+) mitral regurgitation (MR), as determined by the site from a
      transthoracic echocardiogram (TTE), were considered for enrollment in this study. The TTE
      and a transesophageal echocardiogram (TEE) are used to assess eligibility criteria for MR
      severity, valve anatomy and left ventricular parameters.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>No longer available</overall_status>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Expanded Access</study_type>
  <study_design>N/A</study_design>
  <condition>Mitral Valve Insufficiency</condition>
  <condition>Mitral Valve Regurgitation</condition>
  <condition>Mitral Valve Incompetence</condition>
  <condition>Mitral Regurgitation</condition>
  <condition>Mitral Insufficiency</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MitraClip</intervention_name>
    <description>Percutaneous mitral valve repair using MitraClip implant</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Candidates for the non-high risk arm must meet all of the following Inclusion criteria:

          -  Age 18 years or older.

          -  Moderate to severe (3+) or severe (4+) chronic mitral valve regurgitation and:

               1. Symptomatic with &gt; 25%  left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) and Left
                  ventricular end systolic dimension (LVESD) ≤ 55mm or,

               2. Asymptomatic with one or more of the following:

             i. LVEF 25% to 60% ii. LVESD ≥ 40 mm iii. New onset of atrial fibrillation iv.
             Pulmonary hypertension defined as pulmonary artery systolic pressure (PASP) &gt;50mmHg
             at rest or &gt;60mmHg with exercise.

          -  Candidate for mitral valve repair or replacement surgery, including cardiopulmonary
             bypass.

          -  The primary regurgitant jet originates from malcoaptation of the A2 and P2 scallops
             of the mitral valve. If a secondary jet exists, it must be considered clinically
             insignificant.

          -  Male or non-pregnant female (confirmed by negative serum pregnancy test within 7 days
             prior to procedure).

          -  The subject or the subject's legal representative has been informed of the nature of
             the study and agrees to its provisions and has provided written informed consent as
             approved by the Institutional Review Board of the respective clinical site.

          -  The subject and the treating physician agree that the subject will return for all
             required post-procedure follow-up visits.

          -  Trans-septal catheterization is determined to be feasible by the treating physician.

        Candidates for the high risk arm must meet all of the following Inclusion criteria:

          -  Predicted procedural mortality risk calculated using the Society for Thoracic
             Surgeons (STS) surgical risk calculator of ≥ 12% or in the judgment of a cardiac
             surgeon the patient is considered a high risk surgical candidate due to the presence
             of one of the following indications:

               1. Porcelain aorta or mobile ascending aortic atheroma

               2. Post-radiation mediastinum

               3. Previous mediastinitis

               4. Functional MR with EF&lt;40

               5. Over 75 years old with EF&lt;40

               6. Re-operation with patent grafts

               7. Two or more prior chest surgeries

               8. Hepatic cirrhosis

               9. Three (3) or more of the following STS high risk factors

             i.  Creatinine &gt; 2.5 mg/dL ii.  Prior chest surgery iii.  Age over 75 iv.  EF&lt;35

          -  Age 18 years or older.

          -  Symptomatic moderate to severe (3+) or severe (4+) chronic mitral regurgitation (MR)
             and in the judgment of the investigator intervention to reduce MR is likely to
             provide symptomatic relief for the patient. MR is determined as defined in Attachment
             A.

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) physical status classification of ASA IV
             or lower.

          -  The primary regurgitant jet originates from malcoaptation of the A2 and P2 scallops
             of the mitral valve.

          -  Male or non-pregnant female.

          -  The subject or the subject's legal representative has been informed of the nature of
             the study and agrees to its provisions and has provided written informed consent as
             approved by the Institutional Review Board of the respective clinical site.

          -  The subject and the treating physician agree that the subject will return for all
             required post-procedure follow-up visits.

          -  Transseptal catheterization is determined to be feasible by the treating physician.

        Exclusion Criteria

        Candidates will be excluded from the non-high risk arm of the study if any of the
        following conditions are present:

          -  Evidence of an acute myocardial infarction in the prior 12 weeks of the intended
             treatment (defined as: Q wave or non-Q wave infarction having creatine kinase (CK)
             enzymes ≥2X the upper laboratory normal limit with the presence of a creatine kinase
             MB isoenzyme (CK-MB) elevated above the institution's upper limit of normal).

          -  The need for any other cardiac surgery including surgery for coronary artery disease,
             atrial fibrillation, pulmonic, aortic or tricuspid valve disease.

          -  Any endovascular therapeutic interventional or surgical procedure performed within 30
             days prior to the index procedure.

          -  In the judgment of the Investigator, the femoral vein cannot accommodate a 24 F
             catheter or the presence of an inferior vena cava (IVC) filter would interfere with
             advancement of the catheter or ipsilateral DVT is present.

          -  Severe left ventricular dysfunction, defined as an ejection

          -  Mitral valve orifice area &lt;4.0 cm2.

          -  If leaflet flail is present

               1. Flail Width: the width of the flail segment is greater than or equal to 15 mm,
                  or

               2. Flail Gap: the flail gap is greater than or equal to 10 mm.

          -  If leaflet tethering is present:

             a. Coaptation Length: the vertical coaptation length is less than 2 mm.

          -  Severe mitral annular calcification.

          -  Leaflet anatomy which may preclude clip implantation, proper clip positioning on the
             leaflets or sufficient reduction in MR. This may include:

               1. Evidence of calcification in the grasping area of the A2 and/or P2 scallops

               2. Presence of a significant cleft of A2 or P2 scallops

               3. More than one anatomic criteria dimensionally near the exclusion limits

               4. Bileaflet flail or severe bileaflet prolapse

               5. Lack of both primary and secondary chordal support

          -  Hemodynamic instability defined as systolic pressure &lt; 90 mmHg without afterload
             reduction or cardiogenic shock or the need for inotropic support or intra-aortic
             balloon pump.

          -  Need for emergency surgery for any reason.

          -  Prior mitral valve surgery or valvuloplasty or any currently implanted mechanical
             prosthetic valve or currently implanted ventricular assist device (VAD).

          -  Systolic anterior motion of the mitral valve leaflet.

          -  Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy.

          -  Echocardiographic evidence of intracardiac mass, thrombus or vegetation.

          -  Active endocarditis or active rheumatic heart disease or leaflets degenerated from
             either endocarditis or rheumatic disease (i.e. noncompliant, perforated).

          -  History of a stroke or documented  Transient Ischemic Attack (TIA) within the prior 6
             months.

          -  Upper GI bleeding within the prior 6 months.

          -  History of bleeding diathesis or coagulopathy or subject will refuse blood
             transfusions.

          -  Concurrent medical condition with a life expectancy of less than 12 months (please
             refer to definition in Section 7).

          -  A platelet count &lt;75,000 cells/mm³.

          -  Renal insufficiency (Creatinine &gt;2.5mg/dL).

          -  Active infections requiring current antibiotic therapy (if temporary illness,
             patients may enroll 2 weeks after discontinuation of antibiotics). Patients must be
             free from infection prior to treatment. Any required dental work should be completed
             a minimum of 3 weeks prior to treatment.

          -  Intravenous drug abuse or suspected inability to adhere to followup.

          -  Patients in whom transesophageal echocardiography (TEE) is contraindicated.

          -  A known hypersensitivity or contraindication to study or procedure medications which
             cannot be adequately managed medically.

          -  In the judgment of the Investigator, patients in whom the presence of a permanent
             pacemaker or pacing leads would interfere with placement of the test device or the
             placement of the test device would disrupt the leads.

          -  Currently participating in an investigational drug or another device study that has
             not completed the primary endpoint or that clinically interferes with the current
             study endpoints. [Note: Trials requiring extended follow-up for products that were
             investigational, but have since become commercially available, are not considered
             investigational trials].

        Candidates will be excluded from the high risk arm of the study if any of the following
        conditions are present:

          -  Evidence of an acute myocardial infarction in the prior 2 weeks of the intended
             treatment (defined as: Q wave or non-Q wave infarction having CK enzymes ≥ 2X the
             upper laboratory normal limit with the presence of a CK-MB elevated above the
             institution's upper limit of normal).

          -  In the judgment of the Investigator, the femoral vein cannot accommodate a 24 F
             catheter or presence of ipsilateral deep vein thrombosis (DVT).

          -  Ejection fraction &lt; 20%, and/or end-systolic dimension &gt; 60 mm.

          -  Mitral valve orifice area &lt; 4.0 cm2.

          -  If leaflet flail is present:

               1. Flail Width: the width of the flail segment is greater than or equal to 15 mm

               2. Flail Gap: the flail gap is greater than or equal to 10 mm

          -  If leaflet tethering is present, Coaptation Length: the vertical coaptation length is
             less than 2 mm.

          -  Leaflet anatomy which may preclude clip implantation, proper clip positioning on the
             leaflets or sufficient reduction in MR. This may include:

               1. Evidence of calcification in the grasping area of the A2 and/or P2 scallops

               2. Presence of a significant cleft of A2 or P2 scallops

               3. More than one anatomic criteria dimensionally near the exclusion limits

               4. Bileaflet flail or severe bileaflet prolapse

               5. Lack of both primary and secondary chordal support

          -  Hemodynamic instability defined as systolic pressure &lt; 90 mmHg without after load
             reduction or cardiogenic shock or the need for inotropic support or intra-aortic
             balloon pump.

          -  Need for emergent or urgent surgery for any reason.

          -  Prior mitral valve leaflet surgery or any currently implanted mechanical prosthetic
             mitral valve.

          -  Echocardiographic evidence of intracardiac mass, thrombus or vegetation.

          -  Active endocarditis or active rheumatic heart disease or leaflets degenerated from
             rheumatic diseased (i.e. noncompliant, perforated).

          -  History of bleeding diathesis or coagulopathy or subject will refuse blood
             transfusions.

          -  Active infections requiring current antibiotic therapy (if temporary illness,
             patients may enroll 2 weeks after discontinuation of antibiotics). Patients must be
             free from infection prior to treatment. Any required dental work should be completed
             a minimum of 3 weeks prior to treatment.

          -  Intravenous drug abuse or suspected inability to adhere to followup.

          -  Patients in whom transesophageal echocardiography (TEE) is contraindicated.

          -  A known hypersensitivity or contraindication to study or procedure medications which
             cannot be adequately managed medically.

          -  In the judgment of the Investigator, patients in whom the presence of a permanent
             pacemaker or pacing leads would interfere with placement of the test device or the
             placement of the test device would disrupt the leads.

          -  Currently participating in an investigational drug or another device study that has
             not completed the primary endpoint or that clinically interferes with the current
             study endpoints. [Note: Trials requiring extended follow-up for products that were
             investigational, but have since become commercially available, are not considered
             investigational trials].

          -  Any medical condition(s) that in the opinion of the investigator is likely to result
             in death within 12 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ted Feldman, M.D. Feldman, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>NorthShore University HealthSystem</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Donald D Glower Jr., MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90048</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baptist Hospital of Miami, FL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33176</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Virginia Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlottesville</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22903</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mitralregurgitation.org</url>
    <description>Web site listing study sites and describing mitral regurgitation, symptoms, clinical consequences and treatments</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.abbottvascular.com/us/index.html</url>
    <description>Sponsor information</description>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Grayburn PA, Roberts BJ, Aston S, Anwar A, Hebeler RF Jr, Brown DL, Mack MJ. Mechanism and severity of mitral regurgitation by transesophageal echocardiography in patients referred for percutaneous valve repair. Am J Cardiol. 2011 Sep 15;108(6):882-7. doi: 10.1016/j.amjcard.2011.05.013. Epub 2011 Jul 7.</citation>
    <PMID>21741608</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pope NH, Lim S, Ailawadi G. Late calcific mitral stenosis after MitraClip procedure in a dialysis-dependent patient. Ann Thorac Surg. 2013 May;95(5):e113-4. doi: 10.1016/j.athoracsur.2012.10.067.</citation>
    <PMID>23608290</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 5, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 27, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mitral Valve Insufficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>Mitral Valve Regurgitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Mitral Valve Incompetence</keyword>
  <keyword>Mitral Regurgitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Mitral Insufficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>Mitral Valve</keyword>
  <keyword>MR</keyword>
  <keyword>Mitral Valve Prolapse</keyword>
  <keyword>E2E - Edge to Edge</keyword>
  <keyword>Alfieri Technique</keyword>
  <keyword>MitraClip</keyword>
  <keyword>Functional MR</keyword>
  <keyword>Degenerative MR</keyword>
  <keyword>Echocardiogram</keyword>
  <keyword>CAD - Coronary Artery Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart Failure</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart Attack</keyword>
  <keyword>EVEREST</keyword>
  <keyword>EVEREST I</keyword>
  <keyword>EVEREST II</keyword>
  <keyword>REALISM</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Mitral Valve Insufficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
