<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="115954">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01854268</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>32-2013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01854268</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Respiratory Kinematics During Voluntary and Reflex Cough in Healthy Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>Respiratory Kinematics During Voluntary and Reflex Cough in Healthy Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cough is a defensive behavior that involves three stages.  A large inspiratory phase, a
      compression phase where the vocal folds close and subglottal pressure is developed, and an
      expiratory phase.  Cough serves to protect the upper and lower airways from material such as
      liquids, solids, or saliva, that have been aspirated.  There are two types of cough:
      voluntary and reflex cough.  Voluntary cough involves a cough to command.  Reflex cough is a
      cough that is generated secondary to a stimulus in or near the airway.  There has been some
      research regarding the differences between voluntary and reflex cough.  However, no research
      has described the differences in airflow or movement pattern (kinematics) between the two
      types of cough.  This study seeks to determine the respiratory kinematics and airflow
      differences between voluntary and reflex cough in healthy participants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      As a participant, completion of this study will require the following:

      Investigators will first place cotton elastic bands around your chest and abdomen so that
      measures of chest wall and abdominal movements can be measured.  Then, tests of your
      breathing made from pulmonary function testing will be completed.

      Investigators will then have you complete a maximum inspiration followed by a maximum
      expiration three times.

      Investigators will ask you to produce a voluntary cough three times into a facemask which is
      attached to a computer.

      Then the investigators will provide you with nebulized water (FOG) through the facemask for
      up to a minute three times.  You will have a minute break in between each presentation.

      Finally, the investigators will provide you with a nebulized dose of Capsaicin, which is
      derived from hot peppers, through the same facemask used in all of the above tasks.  You
      will receive three doses of capsaicin and be provided with water at any time during the
      study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Respiratory kinematics during voluntary and reflex cough in healthy adults</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Respiratory kinematic measures: lung volume initiation (LVI), lung volume termination (LVT), and total lung volume excursion (LVE).
Airflow measures: Compression phase duration, peak expiratory flow rate, peak expiratory flow rise time, and cough volume acceleration.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Respiratory kinematics during voluntary and reflex cough in healthy adults</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Urge to cough rating: Borg scale (0-10; 0 equals no urge to cough, 10 equals maximal urge to cough)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Adults</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy adults who receive capsaicin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single treatment consisting of healthy adults.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Healthy adults who receive capsaicin</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be seated in a comfortable chair and fitted with cotton elastic bands designed to measure changes in chest wall and abdominal movement during cough.  The participant will hold a facemask attached to a pneumotachograph, nebulized, and dosimeter.  The participant will receive 3 nebulized doses of 200 microMolar capsaicin through the facemask.  The participants will have a minute in between each presentation and water will be available at all times.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy adults who receive capsaicin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>capsaicin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pulmonary function testing</intervention_name>
    <description>Investigators will first place cotton elastic bands around your chest and abdomen so that measures of chest wall and abdominal movements can be measured. First, tests of your breathing using pulmonary function testing will be completed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy adults who receive capsaicin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Pulmonary function testing</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nebulized water (Fog)</intervention_name>
    <description>The investigators will provide you with nebulized water (FOG) through the facemask for up to a minute three times. You will have a minute break in between each presentation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy adults who receive capsaicin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Nebulized water (Fog)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy adults between the ages of 18-80 years.

          -  Ability to provide informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No history of smoking within the last 5 years as this reduces the sensitivity to
             capsaicin

          -  No history of neurological disease (i.e. Parkinson's disease, stroke, traumatic brain
             injury, etc.)

          -  No known allergy to capsaicin

          -  No history of respiratory disease (i.e. asthma, chronic obstructive pulmonary
             disease, or respiratory infection within the last 5 weeks.)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alexandra E. Brandimore, M.A.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida, Dauer Hall</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 10, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Healthy adults</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Capsaicin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
