<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="112808">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02146066</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0202EA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02146066</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Expanded Access Protocol for GBM Patients With Already Manufactured DCVax®-L Who Have Screen-Failed Protocol 020221</brief_title>
  <acronym>DCVax-L EAP</acronym>
  <official_title>An Expanded Access Protocol for the Treatment of Glioblastoma Multiforme in Patients With Already Manufactured DCVax®-L, Autologous Dendritic Cells Pulsed With Tumor Lysate Antigen Who Have Screen-Failed Protocol 020221</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northwest Biotherapeutics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwest Biotherapeutics</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study is an open-label expanded access study for patients for whom vaccine was
      manufactured during the Northwest Biotherapeutics' 020221 DCVax-L for GBM screening process,
      but who subsequently failed to meet specific enrollment criteria. Patients will receive
      therapy per investigator discretion (standard of care) as well as active vaccine per the
      020221 protocol administration schedule. It is estimated that approximately 99 patients will
      enroll in this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients who are being screened under protocol 020221 who are not eligible for enrollment
      due to a) evidence of disease progression or pseudo-progression post chemo-radiation or b)
      insufficient (&lt;5 doses) vaccine manufactured, and for whom the DCVax-L treatment was
      manufactured and released are eligible for this study.

      Treatment Schedule:

      Open label vaccine injections will be give per the associated 020221 protocol. Injections
      will be given at days 0, 10, 20, and at months 2, 4, 8, 12, 18, 24 and 30. There are no
      therapeutic restrictions, but guidelines for drug administration are recommended as per the
      020221 protocol.

      Data collected includes vaccine administration information, and any vaccine related adverse
      event. Patient MRIs will be collected centrally for future review. Patients will be followed
      for disease progression and survival.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Available</overall_status>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Expanded Access</study_type>
  <study_design>N/A</study_design>
  <condition>GBM</condition>
  <condition>Glioblastoma Multiforme</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DCVax-L</intervention_name>
    <description>Autologous Dendritic Cells Pulsed with Tumor Lysate Antigen</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Screen-Fail for protocol 020221 due to either:

               -  Radiographic evidence of disease progression or pseudoprogression at the
                  Baseline visit under protocol 020221, as determined by central imaging review,
                  OR

               -  Insufficient vaccine manufactured for protocol 020221 (i.e. less than 5 doses).

          2. Patients must have a KPS rating of ≥70 at the Baseline Visit (Visit 5) (refer to
             Appendix D, Performance Status Scales).

          3. Patients may have received steroid therapy as part of their primary treatment.
             Steroid treatment should preferably be stopped; or if continued steroid use is
             clinically indicated, be tapered down to no more than 4 mg dexamethasone qd at least
             7 days prior to the first immunization .

          4. DCVax-L product manufactured and released.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Active uncontrolled infection, or acute infection requiring antibiotic or antifungal
             therapy. Antibiotic and antifungal therapy should be completed approximately 7 days
             prior to the first immunization.

          2. Fever ≥101.5oF. If considered possibly transient, retesting is allowed.

          3. Unstable or severe intercurrent medical conditions.

          4. Females of child-bearing potential who are pregnant or lactating or who are not using
             adequate contraception (abstinence, surgical, hormonal or double barrier, i.e. condom
             and diaphragm). 020221 Baseline lab results and or local lab results are acceptable.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marnix Bosch, MBA PhD</last_name>
    <phone>240 497 9022</phone>
    <email>marnix@nwbio.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Meghan Swardstrom</last_name>
    <phone>425 492 6036</phone>
    <email>mswardstrom@nwbio.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 21, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>GBM</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain tumor WHO grade IV</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
