<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="87218">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01731951</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MC1285</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-02036</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01731951</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Imetelstat Sodium in Treating Patients With Primary or Secondary Myelofibrosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Open-Label Study of the Efficacy and Safety of Imetelstat (GRN163L) in Patients With DIPSS_plus Intermediate-2 or High Risk Primary Myelofibrosis (PMF), Post-Polycythemia Vera Myelofibrosis (Post-PV MF), or Post-Essential Thrombocythemia Myelofibrosis (Post-ET-MF).</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This pilot clinical trial studies how well imetelstat sodium works in treating patients with
      primary or secondary myelofibrosis. Imetelstat sodium may stop the growth of cancer cells by
      blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell growth
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate overall response rate.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the safety and tolerability of imetelstat (imetelstat sodium) in
      myelofibrosis (MF) (per common terminology criteria for adverse events, version 4.03).

      II. To evaluate the efficacy of imetelstat in the reduction of spleen size, as measured by
      physical examination (palpable distance from the left costal margin).

      III. To evaluate the efficacy of imetelstat in inducing red blood cell
      transfusion-independence in previously transfusion-dependent patients (per International
      Working Group for Myelofibrosis Research and Treatment [IWG-MRT] criteria).

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the effect of imetelstat on bone marrow histology and karyotype. II. To
      evaluate the effect of imetelstat on leukocytosis and thrombocytosis.

      OUTLINE: Patients receive imetelstat sodium intravenously (IV) over 2 hours on day 1.
      Treatment repeats every 21 days for up to 52 courses in the absence of disease progression
      or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 6 months for 5 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate defined as a clinical improvement (CI), partial remission (PR), or complete remission (CR) according to the IWG-MRT consensus criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 27 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be estimated by the number of successes divided by the total number of evaluable patients. Ninety-five percent Duffy Santner confidence intervals for the true success proportion will be calculated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum grade for each type of adverse event for each patient</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Frequency tables will be reviewed to determine patterns. Additionally, the relationship of the adverse event(s) to the study treatment will be taken into consideration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Spleen response defined as either a minimum 50% reduction in palpable splenomegaly of a spleen that is at least 10 cm at baseline or a spleen that is palpable at more than 5 cm at baseline becomes not palpable</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 27 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be calculated by the number of patients who achieve spleen response divided by the total number of evaluable patients with spleen involvement at baseline (estimated to be approximately 80% of patients). Ninety-five percent exact binomial confidence intervals for the true proportion of patients with spleen response will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients achieving transfusion independence</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 27 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be estimated by the number of patients who achieve transfusion independence divided by the total number of evaluable patients who were transfusion dependent at baseline Ninety-five percent exact binomial confidence intervals for the true proportion of patients who become transfusion independent will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Primary Myelofibrosis</condition>
  <condition>Secondary Myelofibrosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm - A  (imetelstat sodium)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive imetelstat sodium IV over 2 hours on day 1. Treatment repeats every 21 days for up to 52 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm - B  (imetelstat sodium)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive first cycle imetelstat sodium IV over 2 hours on day 1, 8, 15. Treatment repeats every 21 days for up to 52 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>imetelstat sodium</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm - A  (imetelstat sodium)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm - B  (imetelstat sodium)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>GRN163L</other_name>
    <other_name>telomerase inhibitor GRN163L</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of one of the following:

               -  PMF per the revised World Health Organization (WHO) criteria

               -  Post-ET/PV MF per the IWG-MRT criteria

          -  High-risk or Intermediate-2 risk MF (as defined by the Dynamic International
             Prognostic Scoring System [DIPSS-plus])

          -  Life expectancy of &gt;= 12 weeks

          -  Able to provide informed consent and be willing to sign an informed consent form

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0, 1 or 2

          -  Serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT) (aspartate aminotransferase [AST]) =&lt;
             2.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) (or =&lt; 5 x ULN if in the investigator's opinion the
             elevation is due to extramedullary hematopoiesis)

          -  Serum glutamic pyruvate transaminase (SGPT) alanine aminotransferase (ALT) =&lt; 2.5 x
             upper limit of normal (ULN) (or =&lt;5 x ULN if in the investigator's opinion the
             elevation is due to extramedullary hematopoiesis)

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 3.0 mg/dL (or direct bilirubin &lt; 1 mg/dL)

          -  Creatinine =&lt; 3.0 mg/dL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1000/uL

          -  Platelet count &gt;= 50,000/uL

          -  Absence of active treatment with systemic anticoagulation and a baseline prothrombin
             time (PT) and activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) that does not exceed 1.5 x
             ULN

          -  Females of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test =&lt; 7 days prior
             to registration, unless they are surgically sterile for at least 3 months (i.e.,
             hysterectomy), OR postmenopausal for at least 12 months (follicle-stimulating hormone
             [FSH] &gt;30 U/mL)

          -  Females of childbearing potential must agree to take appropriate precautions to avoid
             pregnancy (with at least 99% certainty) from screening through end of study;
             permitted methods for preventing pregnancy must be communicated to study subjects and
             their understanding confirmed

          -  Males must agree to take appropriate precautions to avoid fathering a child (with at
             least 99% certainty) from screening through follow-up; permitted methods for
             preventing pregnancy should be communicated to the subjects and their understanding
             confirmed

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Females who are pregnant or are currently breastfeeding

          -  Any chemotherapy (e.g., hydroxyurea), immunomodulatory drug therapy (e.g.,
             thalidomide), immunosuppressive therapy, corticosteroids &gt; 10 mg/day prednisone or
             equivalent, growth factor treatment (e.g., erythropoietin) or Janus kinase (JAK)
             inhibitor therapy =&lt; 14 days prior to registration

          -  Subjects with another active malignancy

               -  Note: patients with early stage squamous cell carcinoma of the skin, basal cell
                  carcinoma of the skin or cervical intraepithelial neoplasia are eligible for
                  enrollment

          -  Known positive status for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)

          -  Any unresolved toxicity greater or equal to grade 2 from previous anticancer therapy,
             except for stable chronic toxicities not expected to resolve

          -  Incomplete recovery from any prior surgical procedures or had surgery =&lt; 4 weeks
             prior to registration, excluding the placement of vascular access

          -  Presence of acute active infection requiring antibiotics

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness or any concurrent condition that, in the
             Investigator's opinion, would jeopardize the safety of the patient or compliance with
             the protocol
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ayalew Tefferi, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 28, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 18, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ayalew Tefferi, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Primary Myelofibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thrombocythemia, Essential</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
