<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="137974">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02024581</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VIR003-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02024581</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Dose Range-Finding Phase 2 Trial of a Botanical Drug for the Treatment of Molluscum Contagiosum in Pediatric Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multi-Center, Double-Blind, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Safety and Efficacy Trial of VIR003 at Three Dose Levels for the Treatment of Molluscum Contagiosum in Pediatric Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>ViroXis Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>ViroXis Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This trial will examine the safety, tolerability and efficacy of three strengths of East
      Indian sandalwood oil (EISO) in a cream base compared to a placebo for treatment of
      molluscum contagiosum in pediatric subjects. Trial participants will be asked to apply study
      medication twice a day for sixty (60) days. Efficacy will be evaluated by clinical staff and
      patients will be asked to assess tolerability as well as any improvement experienced during
      the trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This trial will be a multi-center, double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled safety and
      efficacy trial to evaluate the efficacy and safety of VIR003 treatment regimen when
      administered to pediatric subjects with molluscum contagiosum.

      Once subject eligibility is confirmed the subject will start the Treatment Period of the
      study.  All subjects will receive one of three active treatments or placebo with the first
      dose applied at the Day 0 Study Visit.  Subjects will be instructed on how to apply the
      study medication twice a day for 60 days of treatment.  Subjects will return to the clinic
      on Study Days, 7, 14, 30, 45, and 60 for routine evaluations and then on Study Day 90 for
      the Final Study Visit.

      The study will be monitored by a data safety monitoring board (DSMB) comprised of a medical
      monitor, dermatologist and statistician.  The purpose of the DSMB will be to monitor the
      emergence of adverse events (AEs) and serious adverse events (SAEs) at periodic intervals
      throughout the enrollment and treatment phases of the study
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete resolution of lesions</measure>
    <time_frame>Outcome measured after 60 days of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The preliminary efficacy evaluation for the study will be the complete resolution of lesion following 60 days of treatment and assessed at Study Day 60.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in lesion count</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured following 60 days of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percent change in lesion count from Baseline to Study Day 60 in evaluable subjects</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in GAIS score</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured following 60 days of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of subjects who are very much improved, much improved, or improved (treatment success) at Day 60, as judged by the Global Aesthetic Improvement Scale (GAIS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety profile of the treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Subjects will be queried for adverse events at each visit during the treatment period (Visit 2 (Day 7), Visit 3 (Day 14), Visit 4 (Day 30), Visit 5 (Day 45) and Visit 6 (Day 60))</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary purpose of this study is to determine the safety profile of VIR003 at 3 dose concentration.
Safety will be assessed by evaluating adverse events (AEs) with respect to severity, duration, and relationship to study drug compared to placebo.
In addition the following cutaneous safety evaluations will be performed at each study visit.
Scaling on a scale of 0 to 3.
Erythema on a scale of 0 to 3</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Tolerability of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Subjects will answer treatment tolerability questions at each visit during the treatment period (Visit 2 (Day 7), Visit 3 (Day 14), Visit 4 (Day 30), Visit 5 (Day 45) and Visit 6 (Day 60))</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Tolerability will be assessed on a scale of 0 to 3 for itching, scaling, burning dryness and stinging.  The number and percentage of subjects reporting burning, itching, scaling, erythema, dryness or stinging (Grade 1 or higher) will be tabulated by severity.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Molluscum Contagiosum</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2.5% East Indian sandalwood oil cream</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>East Indian sandalwood oil in a cream formulation administered twice a day for sixty (60) days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>5% East Indian sandalwood oil cream</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>East Indian sandalwood oil in a cream formulation administered twice a day for sixty (60) days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>10% East Indian sandalwood oil cream</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>East Indian sandalwood oil in a cream formulation administered twice a day for sixty (60) days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo cream</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A scented cream formulation administered twice a day for sixty (60) days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>2.5% East Indian sandalwood oil cream</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>2.5% East Indian sandalwood oil cream</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Albuterpenoids</other_name>
    <other_name>EISO</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>5% East Indian sandalwood oil cream</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>5% East Indian sandalwood oil cream</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Albuterpenoids</other_name>
    <other_name>EISO</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>10% East Indian sandalwood oil cream</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>10% East Indian sandalwood oil cream</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Albuterpenoids</other_name>
    <other_name>EISO</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Cream</intervention_name>
    <description>A scented cream matching the appearance of the active comparator creams</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo cream</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Subjects will be included in the trial if they meet all of the following criteria:

          -  Are between 2 and 18 years of age, at Screening.

          -  Have a diagnosis of molluscum contagiosum that is treatable with a topical agent.

          -  Are free of any systemic or dermatologic disorder, which, in the opinion of the
             investigator will interfere with the study results or increase the risk of adverse
             events.

          -  Are willing to refrain from using non-approved lotions, sunscreen, moisturizer,
             cleansers, cosmetics or creams on the affected areas during the treatment period.

          -  Whose parent or guardian is able to give written informed consent in a manner
             approved by the Institutional Review Board and comply with the requirements of the
             study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects will be excluded from the trial if they meet any of the following criteria:

          -  Are immunosuppressed.

          -  Have used or are planning to use immunosuppressive or immunomodulatory medication
             (including oral or parenteral corticosteroids) in the previous 30 days.

          -  Are undergoing treatment or have been treated in the last 30 days prior to Screening
             with isotretinoin or any other type of topical therapy (e.g., corticosteroids,
             cantharidin, podophyllin, podofilox, iodine, salicylic acid, retinoids, diclofenac,
             hyaluronic acid, potassium hydroxide, imiquimod).

          -  Have used liquid nitrogen in the treatment area in the last 30 days prior to
             Screening.

          -  Have undergone curettage, electrocoagulation, taping or clamping of the infected
             area.

          -  Are taking antiviral medication including but not limited to cimetidine and
             cidofovir.

          -  Have any active skin malignancy or infection.

          -  Have a molluscum contagiosum infection in an untreatable area (i.e., periorbital,
             urogenital, etc.).

          -  Have any condition that in the opinion of the investigator would confound the safety
             and/or efficacy assessments.

          -  Have participated in any clinical trial in the previous 30 days.

          -  Have a known sensitivity to any of the constituents of the test product including
             sensitivities to sandalwood oil, fragrances or any member of the Compositae family of
             vascular plants (e.g., sunflowers, daisies, dahlias, etc.).

          -  Are pregnant, breastfeeding, or unwilling to practice an acceptable form of birth
             control during the study, if applicable.

          -  Have a present condition or abnormality that in the opinion of the Investigator would
             compromise the safety of the subject or the quality of the data
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John C. Browning, MD FAAD FAAP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Texas Dermatology and Laser Specialists</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>John C. Browning, MD FAAD FAAP</last_name>
    <phone>(210) 829-5180</phone>
    <email>drbrowning@texasdls.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Texas Dermatology and Laser Specialists</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78218</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Valerie A. Cozad, CRC</last_name>
      <phone>210-829-5180</phone>
      <phone_ext>308</phone_ext>
      <email>vcozad@texasdls.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 26, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 19, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pediatric</keyword>
  <keyword>dermatology</keyword>
  <keyword>East Indian sandalwood oil</keyword>
  <keyword>pox virus</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Molluscum Contagiosum</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
