<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="154641">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01787591</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012H0344</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01787591</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dairy Fat as a Mediator of Vitamin E Adequacy in Individuals With Metabolic Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Dairy Fat as a Mediator of Vitamin E Adequacy in Individuals With Metabolic Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ohio State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ohio State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is conducted to investigate if vitamin E status in healthy individuals and
      individuals with metabolic syndrome can be improved by dairy fat. The investigators
      hypothesize that full-fat dairy will substantially increase the bioavailability of
      alpha-tocopherol, a form of vitamin E. The results of this study will contribute to the
      application of dairy fat as a simple and effective strategy for improving vitamin E status,
      which is partly due to poor vitamin E intake. By completing this study, the investigators
      anticipate developing new dietary recommendations to achieve adequate vitamin E status
      through the regular consumption of dairy fat paired with foods containing vitamin E.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Nonalcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH) is the hepatic manifestation of metabolic syndrome and
      affects &gt;70 million Americans. Weight loss and vitamin E supplementation are leading
      strategies for preventing and/or treating NASH. However, the long-term success of weight
      loss is limited and &gt;92% of Americans fail to meet dietary recommendations for vitamin E.
      Thus, the investigators' objective is to define the extent to which dairy fat facilitates
      adequate vitamin E status in individuals with metabolic syndrome, a population at high-risk
      for NASH, by improving α-tocopherol bioavailability. The investigators'  central hypothesis
      is that full-fat dairy will substantially increase alpha-tocopherol (a-T) bioavailability to
      the extent needed to facilitate production of alpha-carboxyethyl-hydroxy-chromanol (a-CEHC),
      a metabolite of a-T that predict a-T status. The investigators  will therefore complete the
      following specific aims: 1) define milk fat-mediated improvements in a-T bioavailability,
      and 2) define dairy fat-mediated improvements in a-T status. This study involves a
      randomized crossover study design where healthy adults and those with metabolic syndrome (n
      = 10/group) will ingest deuterium-labeled a-T with fat-free milk, low-fat milk, whole milk,
      or soy milk. Urine and blood samples will be collected at timed intervals prior to and
      following milk consumption. Blood collection will be performed using single needle sticks or
      cannula (for frequent blood collections) by skilled personnel. Plasma samples will be
      analyzed by liquid chromatography with mass spectrometry to determine pharmacokinetic
      parameters and vitamin E adequacy by measuring labeled and unlabeled a-T and a-CEHC. Risk to
      participants is expected to be minimal and will be outlined in the informed consent form in
      clear and simple terms. Upon successful completion of this study, the investigators expect
      to demonstrate that whole milk, compared to low-fat and fat-free milk, increases a-T
      bioavailability in a milk fat-dependent manner and that low-fat milk compared to soy milk
      (both beverages contain identical amounts of total fat, but differ in fatty acid profile),
      significantly improves a-T bioavailability. The investigators' results will provide timely
      evidence demonstrating the amount and type of fat needed to achieve optimal vitamin E status
      specifically in a population of significant public health concern. Overall, these studies
      will fill a substantial knowledge gap regarding the importance of dairy fat in contributing
      to optimal health and provide a simple dietary approach to ameliorate poor vitamin E status
      among a significant proportion of Americans.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma deuterium labeled and unlabeled alpha-tocopherol</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 3, 6, 9, 12, 24, 36, 48, and 72 h post test meal</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Plasma alpha-tocopherol concentrations will be assessed from blood samples that will be collected prior to (0 h) and at 3, 6, 9, 12, 24, 36, 48, and 72 h following each test meal.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma alpha-CEHC</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 3, 6, 9, 12, 24, 36, 48, and 72 h post test meal</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Alpha-CEHC concentrations will be assessed from blood samples that will be collected prior to (0 h) and at 3, 6, 9, 12, 24, 36, 48, and 72 h following each test meal.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urinary alpha-CEHC</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 8, 16, 24 h post test meal</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Alpha-CEHC concentrations will be assessed from urine samples collected prior to (0 h) and 8, 16, and 24 h following each test meal.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver</condition>
  <condition>Metabolic Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Acute Fat-Free Milk Ingestion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will ingest 1 cup of fat-free milk with 15 mg deuterium-labeled alpha-tocopherol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Acute Low-Fat Milk Ingestion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will ingest 1 cup of low-fat milk with 15 mg deuterium-labeled alpha-tocopherol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Acute Full-Fat Milk Ingestion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will ingest 1 cup of full-fat milk with 15 mg deuterium-labeled alpha-tocopherol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Acute Soy Milk Ingestion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will ingest 1 cup of soy milk with 15 mg deuterium-labeled alpha-tocopherol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fat-Free Milk</intervention_name>
    <description>Fat-free milk ingestion with 15 mg deuterium-labeled alpha-tocopherol.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Acute Fat-Free Milk Ingestion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Low-Fat Milk</intervention_name>
    <description>Low-fat milk ingestion with 15 mg deuterium-labeled alpha-tocopherol.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Acute Low-Fat Milk Ingestion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Full-Fat Milk</intervention_name>
    <description>Full-fat milk ingestion with 15 mg deuterium-labeled alpha-tocopherol.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Acute Full-Fat Milk Ingestion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Soy Milk</intervention_name>
    <description>Soy milk ingestion with 15 mg deuterium-labeled alpha-tocopherol.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Acute Soy Milk Ingestion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  specific criteria of the metabolic syndrome: large waist circumference (&gt;102 or &gt;89
             cm for men and women, respectively), high fasting triglycerides (150-300 mg/dL), low
             fasting HDL (&lt;40 and &lt;50 mg/dL for men and women, respectively), high blood pressure
             (&gt;130/85 mm Hg) and high fasting glucose (110-180 mg/dL)

          -  BMI: &gt;30 kg/m2,

          -  non-dietary supplement users for &gt;2-mo

          -  no use of medications known to affect lipid metabolism

          -  no history of gastrointestinal disorders

          -  resting blood pressure &lt;140 mm Hg

          -  not taking any medications that control hypertension

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  lactose-intolerance

          -  excessive alcohol consumption (&gt;3 drinks/d)

          -  &gt;5 h/wk of aerobic activity

          -  women who are pregnant, lactating, or have initiated or changed birth control in the
             past 3-mo

          -  plasma alpha-tocopherol &gt;20 μmol/L.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard Bruno, PhD, RD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ohio State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eunice Mah, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>6142920951</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 27, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 6, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ohio State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Richard Bruno</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Vitamin E</keyword>
  <keyword>Metabolic syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Liver disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-alcoholic liver steatohepatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Fatty liver</keyword>
  <keyword>Dairy consumption</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fatty Liver</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Syndrome X</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamin E</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alpha-Tocopherol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tocopherols</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tocotrienols</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
