<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="163093">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01865396</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012/865</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01865396</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Early Palliative Care on Quality of Life of Patients With Advanced Cancer: a Randomised Controlled Trial.</brief_title>
  <acronym>IPaC</acronym>
  <official_title>Effect of Early Palliative Care on Quality of Life of Patients With Advanced Cancer: a Randomised Controlled Trial.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Ghent</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Vrije Universiteit Brussel</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fund for Scientific Research, Flanders, Belgium</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Ghent</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Belgium: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The World Health Organization (WHO) defines palliative care as an approach to improve the
      quality of life of patients and their families facing life-threatening illness, through
      prevention and relief of pain and of physical, psychosocial and spiritual problems. The WHO
      stresses that palliative care is applicable early in the course of the illness together with
      other therapies that are intended to cure or prolong life, such as chemotherapy or radiation
      therapy. For the benefit of the patient, palliative care is however often given (too) late
      in the course of the disease of incurably ill patients.

      The aim of our study is to measure the effect of interventional palliative care on quality
      of life, mood and end-of-life care of patients with advanced cancer and their families.
      These patients have a limited life expectancy and a high symptom burden, this leads us to
      suggest that these patients may be benefited with palliative care soon after diagnosis of
      metastatic disease (interventional palliative care).

      The research design of this study is a randomized controlled trial with, on the one hand, an
      intervention group in which patients and their families receive interventional palliative
      care in combination with standard cancer care and on the other hand a control group in which
      patients and their families receive only standard oncologic care. Participants in the
      intervention group will meet the palliative support team shortly after diagnosis.
      Afterwards, the palliative support will meet them at least once a month. This intervention
      focuses on topics such illness understanding, symptom management, decision making and coping
      with the disease. Participants in the control group will only meet with the palliative
      support team at the patient's own request or after referral by the oncologist or the nursing
      staff.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life of the patient and his family caregiver at baseline.</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This will be measured with validated questionnaires(EORTC-QLQ C30, McGill QoL, SF-36).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life of the patient and his family caregiver at 12 weeks.</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This will be measured with validated questionnaires (EORTC-QLQ C30, McGill QoL, SF-36).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life of the patient and his family caregiver, 6-weekly after 12 weeks.</measure>
    <time_frame>6-weekly after 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This will be measured with validated questionnaires (EORTC-QLQ C30, McGill QoL, SF-36).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Influence of palliative care on mood and illness-understanding of patients and family caregivers at baseline.</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This will be measured with validated questionnaires (HADS, PHQ-9, illness understanding).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Influence of palliative care on mood and illness-understanding of patients and family caregivers at 12 weeks.</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This will be measured with validated questionnaires (HADS, PHQ-9, illness understanding).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Influence of palliative care on mood and illness-understanding of patients and family caregivers 6-weekly, after 12 weeks.</measure>
    <time_frame>6-weekly, after 12 weeks.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This will be measured with validated questionnaires (HADS, PHQ-9, illness understanding).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Influence of palliative care on the decision of physicians with regards to end-of-life-care.</measure>
    <time_frame>after death of patient</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This will be measured with the questionnaire for decisions wuth regards to end-of-life decision making for physicians.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Life-limiting Cancer With Prognosis of Approximately 1 Year</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>early palliative care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Interventional palliative care, after diagnosis and once a month.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive the standard oncologic care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Interventional palliative care</intervention_name>
    <description>Palliative support team will meet the patient soon after diagnosis of incurable disease and will meet the patient at least once a month. The patient will also receive the standard oncologic care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>early palliative care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard oncologic care</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive standard oncologic care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patients with life-limiting cancer (prognosis of approximately 1 year) are eligible if:

          -  Patients are within 12 weeks of referral from an other hospital after receiving first
             line treatment or within 8 to 12 weeks of a new diagnosis (histological and
             cytological confirmed):

               -  Metastatic and advanced pancreatic, stomach, oesophageal and biliary tract
                  adenocarcinoma;

               -  Metastatic or advanced NSCLC (stage IIIB or IV) or metastatic SCLC,

               -  Malignant pleural mesothelioma

               -  Metastatic or advanced head and neck cancer (stage III or IV)

          -  Patients are within 12 weeks of progression after receiving treatment and have an
             prognosis of approximately 1 year:

               -  Metastatic and locally advanced colorectal cancer, with progression after second
                  line treatment

               -  Metastatic or advanced prostate carcinoma, after second line treatment

               -  Advanced breast cancer with visceral and/or brain metastasis, with progression
                  on second or third line treatment

               -  Metastatic melanoma,

               -  Metastatic or advanced kidney cancer,

               -  Metastatic or advanced bladder cancer after first line treatment,

        An Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0, 1 or 2 and ability
        to read and respond to questions in Dutch.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Patients under 18 years old

          -  Patients with impaired cognition

          -  Patients who met the palliative support team more then once or had a consultation
             within 6 months of inclusion.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Simon Vanbelle, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Ghent University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Luc Deliens, PhD, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Vrije Universiteit  Brussel and Ghent University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gaëlle Vanbutsele</last_name>
    <phone>09/332 07 92</phone>
    <email>gaelle.vanbutsele@uzgent.be</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ghent University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ghent</city>
        <zip>9000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gaëlle Vanbutsel</last_name>
      <email>gaelle.vanbutsel@uzgent.be</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gaëlle Vanbutsele</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 25, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 24, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
