<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="85780">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02029950</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2013-02426</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-02426</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NA_00089739</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>J13128</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>9524</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA006973</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U01CA070095</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02029950</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pomalidomide After Combination Chemotherapy in Treating Patients With Newly Diagnosed Acute Myeloid Leukemia or High-Risk Myelodysplastic Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of Pomalidomide Given at the Time of Lymphocyte Recovery Following Induction Timed Sequential Chemotherapy With Cytarabine, Daunorubicin and Etoposide (AcDVP16) in Patients With Newly Diagnosed Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML) and High-Risk MDS</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial studies the side effects and best dose of pomalidomide after combination
      chemotherapy in treating patients with newly diagnosed acute myeloid leukemia or high-risk
      myelodysplastic syndrome. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as cytarabine, daunorubicin
      hydrochloride, and etoposide, work in different ways to stop the growth of cancer cells,
      either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing. Pomalidomide may kill cancer
      cells by stopping blood flow to the cancer and by stimulating white blood cells to kill
      cancer cells. Giving more than one drug (combination chemotherapy) and pomalidomide may kill
      more cancer cells.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To define the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of pomalidomide when given at the time of
      early lymphocyte recovery following intensive induction timed sequential therapy (TST) with
      cytosine arabinoside (cytarabine), daunorubicin (daunorubicin hydrochloride) and etoposide
      (AcDVP-16) in patients with newly diagnosed intermediate- and poor-risk acute myeloid
      leukemia and high-risk myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS).

      II. To evaluate the safety, tolerability and toxicity of pomalidomide given at the time of
      early lymphocyte recovery following induction AcDVP-16 chemotherapy in adults with newly
      diagnosed intermediate- and poor-risk acute myeloid leukemia and high-risk MDS.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the safety, tolerability and toxicity of pomalidomide given as a continuation
      therapy following induction and/or consolidation chemotherapy in adults with newly diagnosed
      intermediate- and poor-risk acute myeloid leukemia and high-risk MDS.

      II. To document responses (complete remission [CR], CR with incomplete count recovery [CRi],
      partial remission [PR]) to AcDVP-16 followed by pomalidomide at the time of lymphocyte
      recovery in newly diagnosed adults with intermediate- and poor-risk AML and high-risk MDS,
      including duration of response, disease-free and overall survival.

      III. Correlative pharmacodynamics studies: a) to characterize the effects of pomalidomide on
      the functional dynamics of different lymphocyte subpopulations (effector T [Teff],
      regulatory T [Treg], natural killer [NK] cells) and its impact on tumor-associated antigen
      (TAA)-specific T cell immunity when given following induction and as a maintenance; b) to
      examine for the presence of minimal residual disease (MRD) before and after pomalidomide
      administration during induction and continuation therapy; c) to examine cereblon expression
      in primary leukemia cells at diagnosis and in sorted T cells prior to and after pomalidomide
      treatment.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study of pomalidomide.

      INDUCTION: Patients receive cytarabine intravenously (IV) continuously and daunorubicin
      hydrochloride IV on days 1-3, and etoposide IV over 3 hours on days 8-10. At the time of
      early lymphocyte recovery (after day +14), patients also receive pomalidomide orally (PO)
      for 10-21 days.

      CONSOLIDATION: Patients achieving CR or CRi receive cytarabine IV continuously on days 1-3
      and 10-12, and daunorubicin hydrochloride IV on days 1-3 beginning 21-63 days following
      blood count recovery.

      CONTINUATION: Patients achieving CR or CRi who did not undergo allogeneic stem cell
      transplant receive pomalidomide PO daily on days 1-21 beginning 6 +/- 2 weeks following
      blood count recovery. Treatment repeats every 4-6 weeks for up to 4 courses in the absence
      of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for 2 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MTD of pomalidomide, defined as the highest dose at which 0 or 1 dose-limiting toxicities (DLT) are observed in 6 patients according to National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE) version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 21 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The proportion of DLTs at each dose level will be reported with exact binomial 95% confidence intervals. Adverse events will be summarized by dose level for all doses. All toxicities by type and grade will be reported.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of toxicities in the expansion cohort graded according to NCI CTCAE version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The proportion of toxicities by type and grade in the expansion cohort will be reported with exact binomial 95% confidence intervals.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients achieving CR, CRi, or PR</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The proportion of patients achieving each category of response will be reported with 95% exact binomial confidence intervals.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from start of treatment to time of progression or relapse or death, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Standard life table methods will be used to analyze PFS. One-year and median PFS with 95% confidence intervals will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Time of enrollment onto this study to the time of death, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Standard life table methods will be used to analyze overall survival.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in lymphocyte subpopulations</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Boxplots and line plots will be used to visual trends in the lymphocyte subpopulations. Changes and percentage changes in variables will be summarized. 95% confidence intervals will be obtained by exponentiating the endpoints of confidence intervals for the differences of mean logarithms. A regression model using generalized estimating equations or mixed model used to asses T cell changes. Association of bone marrow and peripheral blood measurements assessed using scatterplots and Spearman's rank correlation coefficients.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in levels of antigen-specific CD8+ T cell responses</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>McNemar's test will be used to compare proportions with positive tumor specificity before and after pomalidomide treatment. Sensitivity and specificity of induction responses for predicting CR status will be estimated.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of MRD-leukemic stem cells (LSC) in marrow</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Presence or absence of MRD on day 14 will be correlated with MRD following induction pomalidomide. McNemar's test will be used to compare proportions. Presence or absence of residual LSCs immediately following induction will be correlated with PFS using the Kaplan-Meier survival method.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in level of cereblon expression in AML cells and sorted T cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">63</enrollment>
  <condition>Adult Acute Megakaryoblastic Leukemia (M7)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Minimally Differentiated Myeloid Leukemia (M0)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Monoblastic Leukemia (M5a)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Monocytic Leukemia (M5b)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloblastic Leukemia With Maturation (M2)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloblastic Leukemia Without Maturation (M1)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With 11q23 (MLL) Abnormalities</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With Del(5q)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With Inv(16)(p13;q22)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With t(16;16)(p13;q22)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With t(8;21)(q22;q22)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myelomonocytic Leukemia (M4)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Erythroleukemia (M6a)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Pure Erythroid Leukemia (M6b)</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Myelomonocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>de Novo Myelodysplastic Syndromes</condition>
  <condition>Previously Treated Myelodysplastic Syndromes</condition>
  <condition>Untreated Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (combination chemotherapy, pomalidomide)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>INDUCTION: Patients receive cytarabine IV continuously and daunorubicin hydrochloride IV on days 1-3, and etoposide IV over 3 hours on days 8-10. At the time of early lymphocyte recovery (after day +14), patients also receive pomalidomide PO for 10-21 days.
CONSOLIDATION: Patients achieving CR or CRi receive cytarabine IV continuously on days 1-3 and 10-12, and daunorubicin hydrochloride IV on days 1-3 beginning 21-63 days following blood count recovery.
CONTINUATION: Patients achieving CR or CRi who did not undergo allogeneic stem cell transplant receive pomalidomide PO daily on days 1-21 beginning 6 +/- 2 weeks following blood count recovery. Treatment repeats every 4-6 weeks for up to 4 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cytarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (combination chemotherapy, pomalidomide)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ARA-C</other_name>
    <other_name>arabinofuranosylcytosine</other_name>
    <other_name>arabinosylcytosine</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytosar-U</other_name>
    <other_name>cytosine arabinoside</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>daunorubicin hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (combination chemotherapy, pomalidomide)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cerubidin</other_name>
    <other_name>Cerubidine</other_name>
    <other_name>daunomycin hydrochloride</other_name>
    <other_name>daunorubicin</other_name>
    <other_name>RP-13057</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>etoposide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (combination chemotherapy, pomalidomide)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>EPEG</other_name>
    <other_name>VP-16</other_name>
    <other_name>VP-16-213</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pomalidomide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (combination chemotherapy, pomalidomide)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CC-4047</other_name>
    <other_name>Pomalyst</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (combination chemotherapy, pomalidomide)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histologically or cytologically confirmed:

               -  Pathologically confirmed intermediate or poor risk newly diagnosed AML (subtypes
                  M0,1,2,4-7)

               -  MDS with high risk features as defined by fibroblast growth factor (INT-2) or
                  high International Prognostic Scoring System (IPSS) score with &gt; 10% blasts in
                  the bone marrow

               -  Chronic myelomonocytic leukemia-2 (CMML-2) defined as having &gt; 10% blasts
                  (including promonocytes) in the bone marrow or &gt; 5-19% blasts (including
                  promonocytes) in the peripheral blood

          -  Patients who have received hydroxyurea alone or have received non-cytotoxic therapies
             previously for treatment of MDS or myeloproliferative neoplasm (MPN) (e.g.
             azacitidine, decitabine, histone deacetylase inhibitors, tyrosine kinase inhibitors,
             hematopoietic growth factors, interferon, lenalidomide, thalidomide) will be eligible
             for this trial as long as immunomodulatory drugs (e.g. lenalidomide, thalidomide)
             have not been used in the past 3 months; patients must be off all non-cytotoxic
             chemotherapies or biologic agents (e.g. azacitidine, decitabine, histone deacetylase
             inhibitors, tyrosine kinase inhibitors, hematopoietic growth factors, interferon, but
             excluding hydroxyurea and cyclophosphamide) for at least 2 weeks prior to starting
             induction chemotherapy and all adverse events (excluding alopecia, acne, rash) due to
             agents administered more than 2 weeks earlier should recover to =&lt; grade 1; patients
             with hematologic malignancies are expected to have hematologic abnormalities at study
             entry; these abnormalities which are thought to be primarily related to the
             underlying leukemia, are not considered to be toxicities (adverse events [AE]) and do
             not need to resolve to =&lt; grade 1; patients with therapy-related AML or MDS should
             have not received prior cumulative anthracycline (daunorubicin equivalent) lifetime
             dose &gt; 450 mg/m^2 and any radiation therapy or chemotherapy within 4 weeks of
             starting induction chemotherapy

          -  Cytoreduction allowed:

               -  Hydroxyurea, corticosteroids, leukopheresis can be used prior to start of
                  induction chemotherapy

               -  Cyclophosphamide up to dose 50-60 mg/kg is allowed for cytoreduction, but must
                  be given at least 7+2 days before start of induction chemotherapy

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status =&lt; 2 (Karnofsky &gt;= 50%)

          -  Total bilirubin &lt; 2.0 mg/dL unless due to Gilbert's Disease, hemolysis or leukemia

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase
             [SGOT])/alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT])
             =&lt; 5 × institutional upper limit of normal unless due to leukemic infiltration

          -  Creatinine =&lt; 2.0 mg/dL

          -  Left ventricular ejection fraction &gt;= 45%

          -  Females of child-bearing (FCBP) must have a negative pregnancy test with a
             sensitivity of at least 25 mIU/mL within 10-14 days prior to and again within 24
             hours of starting pomalidomide; FCBP must either commit to continued abstinence from
             heterosexual intercourse or begin two acceptable methods of birth control, one highly
             effective and one additional effective method at the same time; FCBP must agree to
             ongoing pregnancy testing; men must agree to use a latex condom during sexual contact
             with FCBP even if they had vasectomy for the duration of study participation, and 28
             days after completion of pomalidomide administration; all patients must be counseled
             at a minimum of every 28 days about pregnancy precautions and risks of fetal exposure
             while taking pomalidomide; should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant
             while she or her partner is participating in this study, she should inform her
             treating physician immediately

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent
             document; consent will be obtained by day 14 of AcDVP-16 induction regimen

          -  Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infected patients (HIV testing will not be
             performed as a part of screening) on combination antiretroviral therapy are eligible
             for inclusion; the use of zidovudine is not allowed

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have had chemotherapy or radiotherapy within 4 weeks (6 weeks for
             nitrosoureas or mitomycin C) prior to entering the study or those who have not
             recovered from adverse events due to agents administered more than 4 weeks earlier;
             patients who have had non-cytotoxic therapies and biologic agents within two weeks
             prior to entering the study or those who have not recovered from adverse events due
             to non-cytotoxic therapies and biologic agents administered more than 2 weeks earlier

          -  Patients who are receiving any other investigational agents or who have received
             pomalidomide in the past

          -  Patients with known active central nervous system leukemia should be excluded from
             this clinical trial ; patient receiving intrathecal chemotherapy prophylaxis should
             not receive pomalidomide for &gt;= 7 days after administration

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to pomalidomide (e.g. lenalidomide, thalidomide) or other agents used in
             study

          -  The development of erythema nodosum if characterized by a desquamating rash while
             taking thalidomide, lenalidomide or similar drugs in the past

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, active and
             uncontrolled infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina
             pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would
             limit compliance with study requirements; patients with infection under active
             treatment and controlled with antibiotics are eligible

          -  Any other medical condition that in opinion of investigator would place patient at
             increased risk for toxicity during pomalidomide treatment (i.e. history of recurrent
             or serious thromboembolic events)

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study; breastfeeding should be discontinued if
             the mother is treated with pomalidomide

          -  Known positive patients for infectious hepatitis, type A, B, C

          -  Core binding factor (CBF) AMLs associated with t(8;21) or M4eo subtype (inv[16] or
             t[16;16]), as diagnosed by morphologic criteria, flow cytometric characteristics, and
             rapid cytogenetics or fluorescent in situ hybridization (FISH) or molecular testing

          -  Acute progranulocytic leukemia (APL, M3)

          -  Active graft-versus-host disease (GVHD) following allogeneic stem cell transplant for
             non-AML condition (ex. MDS, MPN, lymphoid malignancy, aplastic anemia) requiring
             ongoing use of immunosuppressants

          -  Patients with mental deficits and/or psychiatric history that preclude them from
             giving informed consent or from following protocol
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ivana Gojo</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University/Sidney Kimmel Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University/Sidney Kimmel Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ivana Gojo</last_name>
      <phone>410-502-7726</phone>
      <email>igojo1@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ivana Gojo</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 6, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Congenital Abnormalities</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Erythroblastic, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Megakaryoblastic, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Monocytic, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelomonocytic, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelomonocytic, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cytarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Daunorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
