<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="36742">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01805921</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RSV001</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2011-003589-34</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01805921</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>RSV001 - A New Vaccine to Prevent Severe Viral Chest Infections.</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study to Assess Safety and Immunogenicity of a New Respiratory Syncytial Virus (RSV) Vaccine Based on the RSV Viral Proteins F, N and M2-1 Encoded by Simian Adenovirus (PanAd3-RSV) and Modified Vaccinia Virus Ankara (MVA-RSV)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Okairos</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Okairos</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: National Health Service</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study we are testing a new vaccine against Respiratory Syncytial Virus (RSV).

      This virus can cause respiratory infections such as bronchiolitis and pneumonia. It affects
      all ages, but especially infants, adults with a suppressed immune system, and the elderly.
      RSV only infects humans and occurs in epidemics each winter. It is the single most common
      cause of severe respiratory illness in children.

      There is no effective anti-viral medication to treat RSV infections. There is a monoclonal
      antibody, which can be given to 'at-risk' children given by injection on a monthly basis
      during winter to provide short term protection against infection, but it is only partially
      effective and prohibitively expensive. Currently, there is no licensed vaccine to prevent
      RSV infection and there remains a real need to develop a vaccine as a cost-effective method
      to save lives and reduce the cost of disease caused by RSV.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We are testing two new RSV vaccines, given in different combinations and by different routes
      of administration. Each vaccine uses the same RSV proteins to stimulate immune responses.
      These proteins are the F (Fusion), N (Nucleocapsid) and M2-1 (Matrix) proteins. The F
      protein sits on the surface of the virus and is needed to infect human cells. Antibodies to
      this protein are an important mechanism to prevent infection. The N and M2-1 proteins are
      needed for viral replication and are targets of immune recognition.

      The two vaccines in this study contain all three of these proteins. However, they are
      delivered into the body using different 'vectors', which are harmless carrier viruses. In
      this study, we have employed two different vectors:a simian adenoviruses (PanAd3)and
      Modified Vaccinia virus Ankara (MVA).

      We intend to administer these vaccines using a 'prime-boost' strategy, in which one of these
      vaccines is used to 'prime' the immune system, which is then 'boosted' 4 or 8 weeks later
      (depending on the groups, by administration of an alternative vaccine or the same vaccine
      given by a different route.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>34 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The recording and assessment of local and systemic adverse events following administration of each vaccine dose;
Fever
Headache
Nausea and/or vomiting
Malaise
Myalgia
Arthralgia
Injection site adverse events (for IM administered vaccine); pain or tenderness, induration, redness and swelling
Nasal site adverse events (for IN administered vaccine); pain or tenderness, irritation and discharge
Blood parameters
Any unsolicited symptom(s) not listed above</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunogenicity</measure>
    <time_frame>34 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Immunological assays to study immune responses to each vaccine, including:
Serum antibody response to RSV F antigen
Serum antibody response capable of RSV neutralization
Quantification of circulating vaccine-induced B-cell secreting antibodies (IgA and IgG) against RSV F antigen
Quantification of circulating vaccine-induced T-cell responses against RSV antigens F, N and M2-1
Any further exploratory immunology to detect vaccine related immune responses</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Respiratory Syncytial Virus Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PanAd3-RSV (IM), MVA-RSV (IM)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>1A. Low dose prime PanAd3-RSV given by intra-muscular injection (IM) - low dose boost MVA-RSV given by intra-muscular injection (IM) (2 volunteers). Interval: 8 weeks.
1B. High dose prime PanAd3-RSV given by intra-muscular injection (IM) - high dose boost MVA-RSV given by intra-muscular injection (IM) (8 volunteers). Interval: 8 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prime PanAd3-RSV (IM), boost PanAd3-RSV (IM)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>2A. Low dose prime PanAd3-RSV given by intra-muscular injection (IM) - low dose boost PanAd3-RSV given by intra-muscular injection (IM) (2 volunteers). Interval: 4 weeks.
2B. High dose prime PanAd3-RSV given by intra-muscular injection (IM) - high dose boost PanAd3-RSV given by intra-muscular injection (IM) (8 volunteers). Interval: 4 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prime PanAd3-RSV (IN), boost MVA-RSV (IM)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>3A. Low dose prime PanAd3-RSV given intra-nasally (IN) - low dose boost MVA-RSV given by intra-muscular injection (IM) (2 volunteers). Interval: 8 weeks.
3B. High dose prime PanAd3-RSV given intra-nasally (IN) - high dose boost MVA-RSV given by intra-muscular injection (IM) (8 volunteers). Interval: 8 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prime PanAd3-RSV (IN), boost PanAd3-RSV (IM)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>4A. Low dose prime PanAd3-RSV given intra-nasally (IN) - low dose boost PanAd3-RSV given by intra-muscular injection (IM) (2 volunteers). Interval: 8 weeks.
4B. High dose prime PanAd3-RSV given intra-nasally (IN) - high dose boost PanAd3-RSV given by intra-muscular injection (IM) (8 volunteers). Interval: 8 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PanAd3-RSV given intra-nasally</intervention_name>
    <description>Low dose = 5x10^9 vp; high dose = 5x10^10 vp</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prime PanAd3-RSV (IN), boost MVA-RSV (IM)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Prime PanAd3-RSV (IN), boost PanAd3-RSV (IM)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MVA-RSV given by intra-muscular injection</intervention_name>
    <description>Low dose = 1x10^7 pfu; high dose = 1x10^8 pfu</description>
    <arm_group_label>PanAd3-RSV (IM), MVA-RSV (IM)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Prime PanAd3-RSV (IN), boost MVA-RSV (IM)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PanAd3-RSV given by intra-muscular injection</intervention_name>
    <description>Low dose = 5x10^9 vp; high dose = 5x10^10 vp</description>
    <arm_group_label>PanAd3-RSV (IM), MVA-RSV (IM)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Prime PanAd3-RSV (IM), boost PanAd3-RSV (IM)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Prime PanAd3-RSV (IN), boost PanAd3-RSV (IM)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Willing and able to give informed consent for participation in the study

          -  Aged between 18 and 50 years

          -  In good health as determined by medical history, physical examination and the
             clinical judgement of the investigators

          -  Willing to use effective contraception

          -  Able to attend the scheduled visits and to comply with all study procedures

          -  Willing to allow his or her General Practitioner and/or Consultant, if appropriate,
             to be notified of participation in the study

          -  Confirmation from general practitioner (GP) that they are aware of the inclusion and
             exclusion criteria and are satisfied from their knowledge of the volunteer that they
             are suitable to enrol

          -  Willing to provide their National Insurance/Passport number for the purpose of TOPS
             registration

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of significant organ/system disease that could interfere with trial conduct
             or completion

          -  Have any known or suspected impairment or alteration of immune function

          -  Planning to receive any other vaccine, anaphylaxis reaction to a vaccine in the past
             or previously having received a recombinant simian or human adenoviral vaccine or
             recombinant MVA vaccine

          -  Detection of IgA deficiency, anti-HIV antibody, hepatitis B surface antigen, anti-HCV
             (hepatitis C virus) antibody or any other significant abnormalities on screening
             investigations at the discretion of an Investigator

          -  Known or suspected drug and/or alcohol misuse

          -  Nasal septal pathology including congenital deformities, previous cauterization,
             rhinoplasty or nasal surgery of any kind or recurrent epistaxis

          -  Scheduled procedures requiring general anaesthesia during the study

          -  Participation in another research study involving an investigational product in the
             past 12 weeks, or are planning to do so within the 34 weeks of this study

          -  Inability, in the opinion of the Investigator, to comply with all study requirements

          -  Female participants who are pregnant, lactating or planning pregnancy during the
             course of the study

          -  Any other significant disease or disorder which, in the opinion of the Investigator,
             may put the participants at risk because of participation in the study, influence the
             result of the study or impair the participant's ability to participate in the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrew J Pollard, FRCPCH PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Oxford. Department of Paediatrics</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Andrew J Pollard, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>01865 857420</phone>
    <email>andrew.pollard@paediatrics.ox.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Christopher A Green, MRCP(UK)</last_name>
    <phone>01865 857420</phone>
    <email>christopher.green@paediatrics.ox.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre for Clinical Vaccinology &amp; Tropical Medicine (CCVTM)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oxford</city>
        <state>Oxfordshire</state>
        <zip>OX3 7LE</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christopher A Green, MRCP(UK)</last_name>
      <phone>01865 857420</phone>
      <email>christopher.green@paediatrics.ox.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Richard P Sewell</last_name>
      <phone>01865 857420</phone>
      <email>richard.sewell@paediatrics.ox.ac.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrew J Pollard, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ovg.ox.ac.uk/recruiting-studies</url>
    <description>More study information will be available from the Oxford Vaccine Group website once recruitment opens</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 27, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 5, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Respiratory Syncytial Virus</keyword>
  <keyword>RSV</keyword>
  <keyword>Vaccine</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Syncytial Virus Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Virus Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
