<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="127673">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01797575</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HSC-MS-12-0046</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>SMRI</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>SMRI#11T-009</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01797575</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>N-Acetyl Cysteine and Aspirin as an Adjunctive Treatment for Bipolar Disorder</brief_title>
  <acronym>SMRI-Bipolar</acronym>
  <official_title>A Double-blind Randomized Placebo-controlled Study of Aspirin and N-acetyl Cysteine as Adjunctive Treatments for Bipolar Disorder Patients (SMRI 11T-009)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Stanley Medical Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      We propose to conduct a double-blind placebo-controlled trial with a widely available and
      prototypical non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agent, aspirin, and an antioxidant agent, NAC,
      involving symptomatic Bipolar Disorder type I and II patients having a depressive or mixed
      episode currently. This will be the first controlled study to test the hypothesis that
      aspirin and NAC, by themselves or in combination, will be beneficial in treating depression
      in bipolar disorder patients and in promoting mood stabilization.

      Our study has the following Aims:

      Aim I - Examine efficacy of aspirin in treating depression in bipolar patients in a
      double-blind placebo-controlled add-on design; Aim II - Examine efficacy of NAC in treating
      depression in bipolar patients in a double-blind placebo-controlled add-on design; Aim III -
      Examine efficacy of combined treatment with aspirin and NAC looking for synergistic,
      potentiating effects; Aim IV - Examine the role of markers of neuroinflammation, as possible
      mediators or modulators in therapeutic response in the treatment of depression in patients
      with Bipolar Disorder.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      study design: BD type I or II patients (n=160), on a depressive or mixed episode, who were
      on therapeutic doses of any of the commonly utilized mood stabilizing agents (lithium,
      anticonvulsants, atypical antipsychotics) for at least one month and who were still
      symptomatic (MADRAS &gt;20) will be enrolled. Patients will be randomly assigned to orally
      receive one of 4 conditions: aspirin 1000 mg (2 capsules of 500 mg) qam, NAC 1000 mg (2
      capsules of 500 mg) bid, combined aspirin and NAC at same doses as given individually or
      matched placebo, as an add-on medication to their ongoing treatment regimen, for an 16-week
      double-blind trial. After the first 8 week of the double blind treatment, the responders
      will keep taking the same study drug, whichever it is. And the non-responders will be
      re-randomized for one of the other three groups of study drugs they haven't tried yet.

      Inclusion criteria:

        1. Age 18 to 65 years

        2. A diagnosis of BD type I or II according to SCID-I interview;

        3. Currently in a depressive or mixed episode, based on DSM-IV/ SCID-I criteria;

        4. MADRAS &gt;20 at entry in the study;

        5. No CURRENT liver, kidney, heart disease or ulcers or bleeding dyscrasia;

        6. No HYSTORY of kidney dysfunction or cardiac problems;

        7. ON therapeutic doses of a mood stabilizing drug (lithium, anticonvulsants, any atypical
           antipsychotics) or combinations for at least ONE month.

        8. Allowed psychiatric co-morbid conditions, such as anxiety disorders, PTSD and substance
           use (as long as do NOT meet abuse or dependence criteria according to the SCID-I in the
           past 2 months).

      Exclusion criteria:

        1. CANNOT be on any :

           Anti-inflammatory: NSAIDs: Aspirin (bufferin, bayer aspirin, ecotrin), diflunisal
           (dolobid, diflunisal),Salsalate (amigesic, salflex), Ibuprofen (motrin, advil),
           Naproxen (naprosyn,aleve, midol extended relief), Fenoprofen (nalfon), Ketoprofen
           (actron), dexketoprofen(ketron D), Flurbiprofen (ansaid), Oxaprozin (daypro),
           Loxoprofen (loxfen, loxonin), Indomethacin (indocin, indocin SR), Sulindac (clinoril),
           Etodolac (lodine), Ketorolac (toradol), diclofenac (voltaren, cataflam),Nabumetone
           (Relafen) Piroxicam (feldene), Meloxicam (mobic), Tenoxicam (mobiflex), Lornoxicam
           (xefo), mefenamic acid (ponstel), meclofenamic acid (meclofenamate sodium), celecoxib
           (celebrex)Anticoagulants: Coumadin (Warfarin), Heparin Anti-oxidant agents Fish oil NAC
           ( N-acetyl cysteine)

        2. Pregnancy

        3. CANNOT change the dose of the psychotropic medications during the trial

      Procedures to be used:

      The study will be carried out at the outpatient clinics affiliated with the UT Health
      Science Center at Houston. After signing informed consent, patients will be submitted
      initially to a structure psychiatric diagnostic interview(SCID-I) to confirm the psychiatric
      diagnosis, followed by a physical examination and routine labs (CBC, liver function tests,
      electrolytes, kidney functions tests, thyroid function tests, urinalyses) to rule out
      relevant medical problems. Physically healthy BD patients on psychotropic medications or
      combinations will be enrolled and randomly assigned to receive, orally, aspirin 1000 mg qam,
      NAC 1000 mg bid, combination of aspirin 1000 mg qam and NAC 1000 mg bid, or placebo. The
      study drugs doses will remain the same for the duration of the study.

      Patients can be on any mood stabilizing agents or combinations, as well as on other
      psychotropic medications at study entry, and the doses of those medications cannot be
      changed during the trial. They cannot be on any anti-inflammatory or anti-oxidant agents or
      anticoagulant at the point they are enrolled. If patients decompensate significantly, and/or
      become acutely suicidal, participation on the trial will be terminated.

      If patients qualify for the study initially based on SCID-I interview, physical examination,
      and routine labs (CBC, liver functions tests, electrolytes, kidney function tests, thyroid
      function tests, and urinalyses), but are not currently taking an approved psychotropic
      medication or combinations they are eligible to participate in a lead-in phase. This phase
      would be starting at their screening visit and last approximately 6 to 8 weeks depending on
      the patient's mood. During this lead-in phase, either the PI or Co-PI will evaluate the
      patient and prescribe either Lithium or Depakote. The patient will be monitored during this
      treatment phase by the PI or Co-PI and will return after two weeks for an evaluation. The
      evaluation will include the Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale(CSSR-S) to assess risk of
      suicide, the Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale(MADRAS) to assess the severity of
      depression and the UKU side effects rating scale. If the patient is prescribed lithium,
      their lithium levels will be tested. The patient will continue to follow up every two weeks.
      At the 4 week visit, the patient will also come in for evaluation (CSSR-S MADRAS and UKU
      side effects rating scale).

      At the 6 week visit, the patient will be re-evaluated for the double-blind study trial. If
      the patient has been on an adequate dose of the psychotropic medication for at least 4 weeks
      and score greater than 20 on the Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS), then
      they will be enrolled.

      If they do not meet inclusion criteria at the week 6 lead-in phase visit, they will return
      at Week 8 and be re-evaluated. PI and Co-PI will continue to prescribe the psychotropic
      medication throughout the lead-in phase (up to 8 weeks) and through the trial (up to 16
      weeks).

      During the lead-in phase participants will not be compensated. They will receive a voucher
      for their parking for each visit. They will be responsible for filling and paying for all
      prescriptions in both the lead-in phase and through the trial (up to 16 weeks).

      Upon completion of the first 8-week double-blind trial, patients who responded to the active
      medication will continued on the same study drug for an additional 8 week double-blind
      treatment. The non-responders to one of the study drugs will be re-randomized for one of the
      other three groups of study not received and will remain in treatment for an additional 8
      week double-blind treatment. Treatment response will be defined as improvement in the MADRS
      scores of at least 50%.

      During the first 8-week trial, patients will be seen at weeks 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6 and 8 for
      clinical assessment and mood ratings. During the continuation trial, they will be seen at
      weeks 8, 10, 12, 14 and 16.

      Routine labs (CBC, liver function tests, electrolytes, kidney functions tests, thyroid
      function tests, urinalyses) will be repeated at week 8 and week 16.

      The main outcome measure for the study will be the scores on the Montgomery-Asberg
      Depression Rating Scale, MADRAS, which assess the severity of depressive symptoms. All
      patients will also be assessed with the Young Mania Rating Scale, YMRS,which assess the
      severity of manic symptoms. the Clinical Global Impression-Bipolar version,severity of
      illness, CGI-S,which is used to measure the severity of depressive, mania and severity
      overall. And,  the UKU side-effects scale, which will assess all the side effects related or
      not to the study group treatments.  In all visits, patients will be seen by the study
      psychiatrist and the research staff will complete mood ratings with the MADRAS, YMRS,
      CGI-BD, and the UKU side-effects scale.

      At baseline (before randomization), week 8 and week 16 blood will be sampled for
      proinflammatory markers (C-reactive protein, soluble interleukin (IL)-2 receptor, IL-6 and
      tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-alpha), and oxidative stress markers (superoxide dismutase
      activity and catalase activity, serum thiobarbituric acid reactive substances (TBARS), which
      have been reported to be elevated in BD patients. These blood samples will be stored for
      possible future research on biomarkers or future genetic studies for up to 20 years, for use
      in pharmacogenetic research during this 20 year timeframe. The samples will be stored at the
      Wet Lab, in a double locked -80 degrees freezer, at BBSB, Department of Psychiatry at
      University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston. (1941 East Road, suite# 3170
      Houston-TX 77054) for future use studying factors of Bipolar Disorder. When (or before) the
      20 year period ends, the blood sample will be destroyed.

      At the screening visit, week 8, and week 16 we will also be testing the Lithium levels in
      all patients that have been prescribed and currently taking the medication for study
      purposes. This extra test will be conducted for the safety of the patient and more Lithium
      level tests can be ordered under the PI's discretion throughout the 16 week trial.

      Risks and potential benefits:

      Aspirin is a safe medication for administration to humans and is approved by the FDA as an
      anti-inflammatory and analgesic agent.  The dose proposed for this study is within the
      safety range as per medication package.  Its side-effect profile is overall very favorable
      and it has met widespread use worldwide over the past decades.  The main safety issues
      relate to the possibility of gastrointestinal complications, which are rare (and will be
      closely monitored in the weekly or biweekly visits that the study requires), and the
      propensity to interfere with coagulation and cause consequent bleeding (which will be
      prevented by excluding any individuals on use of anticoagulants or with active bleeding
      problems).  There were a few case reports and small case series with other non-steroidal
      anti-inflammatory agents suggesting worsening of depressive symptoms related to treatment
      (e.g., indomethacin, ibuprofen, naproxen), but those were uncontrolled reports with
      individuals who suffered from other medical illnesses (rheumatologic diseases).

      For our proposed trial, because some patients may be on lithium at the time they start on
      aspirin, we will exclude individuals with pre-existing cardiac and kidney disease.  For
      patients on lithium, we will carefully monitor their serum lithium levels every two weeks
      during the course of the trial.  Therefore, at the doses that are being proposed we do not
      anticipate any significant problems related to safety of the proposed intervention.

      NAC is a safe compound that is commonly available and utilized over-the-counter.  In a
      recent study the tolerability was excellent and main side effects included changes in energy
      level, headaches, heartburn and joint pain

      Blood Draws: When the blood is drawn, there may be some minimal discomfort and/or bruising.
      Infection, excess bleeding, clotting, or fainting is also possible, although unlikely. All
      usual precautions will be taken to prevent these possibilities and these risks will be
      minimized by using trained staff to perform the blood draws

      Women Able to Become Pregnant: Participation in this study may involve risks to an embryo,
      fetus, or unborn child. If the subject is a female and able to become pregnant, a urine
      pregnancy test will be performed which must be negative prior to enrolling into the study,
      and the subject must agree not to become pregnant during the study. Urine pregnancy tests
      will be performed at Screening visit and week 8. The study staff will review adequate birth
      control methods with the subject and will remind her that she should not become pregnant
      during the study. Appropriate methods of birth control include: hormonal contraceptives
      (such as birth control pills, patches, and implants), barrier methods (such as a condom and
      diaphragms and spermicidal foam or jelly, surgical (hysterectomy or tubal ligation) or
      intrauterine device (IUD). The subject will be instructed to notify the study doctor
      immediately if there is a chance that she has become pregnant.

      Also, if the subject is breast-feeding an infant or plan on breast-feeding an infant, she
      must notify the study doctor. It is not known if this drug is excreted in human milk;
      therefore, breast-feeding is not permitted during the study

      Subjects will be carefully monitored. If a subject's condition worsen to the point that
      he/she might become suicidal or severely depressed, we will terminate the subject's
      participation in the study and referred to his/her psychiatrist for psychiatric treatment.

      Breach of Confidentiality: Every effort will be made to protect the subject identity and
      information during the study. All lab work and scan reports will be de-identified and the
      medical records will be protected. However, there is a small chance that the subject
      information may be viewed by someone that is not involved in the research study.

      The study drug must be taken only by the person for whom it has been prescribed, and it must
      be kept out of the reach of children or persons of limited capacity to read or understand.

      By sharing your sample with the study doctor, there is a risk of the possible loss of the
      subject privacy. Although no identifiable (name, address, etc.) information will be shared
      with others outside of this research project. The clinical information obtained from
      subjects will be part of their medical records and maintained at UT Center of Excellence on
      Mood Disorders, in the Department of Psychiatry at UTHSC-H, in facilities with adequate
      safeguards for the protection of confidentiality. The research data will be collected and
      recorded using only arbitrary code numbers for identification, in order to safeguard the
      confidentiality. All data will be kept in a secure area. Only the members of the UT Center
      of Excellence on Mood Disorders research group, who will get approval from CPHS, will have
      access to the data files, or to the master list for the codes. For publications purposes,
      the patients will be designated only by their assigned codes.

      These blood samples, for use in pharmacogenetic research during this 15 year timeframe,
      samples will be stored at the Wet Lab, in a double locked -80 degrees freezer, at BBSB,
      Department of Psychiatry at University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston. (1941 East
      Road, suite# 3170 Houston-TX 77054) The possibility exists that the subject information may
      be taken and used for reasons outside of this project. The United States' Genetic
      Information Nondiscrimination, Act (GINA) of 2008, does not allow for employers or health
      insurance companies to discriminate against the research subject based on his/her genetic
      information. This means that health insurance companies or employers are NOT ALLOWED BY LAW
      to ask or use any of the subject genetic information (DNA, RNA, etc.) gained through testing
      to make decisions that affect the subject or hisher family's health coverage or income in a
      negative way

      Importance of knowledge that may reasonably be expected to result:

      The study will examine possible novel mechanism of actions with modulation of inflammatory
      mechanisms and oxidative stress and could result in the development of novel, low cost, safe
      and widely available treatments for BD patients who have not responded to other commonly
      utilized alternatives
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients demonstrating &gt; 50% decrease in depression scores on the MADRS, as a function of treatment (on aspirin treatment only).</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Examine efficacy of aspirin in treating depression in bipolar patients in a double-blind placebo-controlled add-on design;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modulators of therapeutic response</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Examine the role of markers of neuroinflammation, oxidative stress and cytokines as possible mediators or modulators in therapeutic response in the treatment of depression in patients with Bipolar Disorder</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients demonstrating &gt; 50% decrease in depression scores on the</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Examine efficacy of NAC in treating depression in bipolar patients in a double-blind placebo-controlled add-on design;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients demonstrating &gt; 50% decrease in depression scores on the MADRS, as a function of treatment (on NAC/Aspirin combination treatment).</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Examine efficacy of NAC/Aspirin combination in treating depression in bipolar patients in a double-blind placebo-controlled add-on design.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Bipolar Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Asprin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>research  subject will be taking aspirin 1000mg (2 capsules of 500mg) every morning in addition to his/her mood stabilizing drug (lithium, anticonvulsants, any atypical antipsychotics) or combinations</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>N-acetyl-cysteine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>research subject will be taking N-acetyl-cysteine (NAC) 1000mg (2 capsules of 500mg) two times a day in addition to his/her mood stabilizing drug (lithium, anticonvulsants, any atypical antipsychotics) or combinations</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Asprin and NAC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>research subject will be taking  aspirin 1000mg (2 capsules of 500mg) every morning and NAC 1000mg (2 capsules of 500mg) two times a day in addition to his/her mood stabilizing drug (lithium, anticonvulsants, any atypical antipsychotics) or combinations.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar Pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>research subject will be taking 4 capsules of matching sugar pill( placebo) in the morning and 2 capsules of matching placebo in the evenings in addition to his/her mood stabilizing drug (lithium, anticonvulsants, any atypical antipsychotics) or combinations</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Asprin</intervention_name>
    <description>aspirin 1000mg (2 capsules of 500mg) every morning in addition to his/her  antidepressant and/or mood stabilizer medicine</description>
    <arm_group_label>Asprin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ecotrin</other_name>
    <other_name>Bayer Aspirin</other_name>
    <other_name>Bufferin</other_name>
    <other_name>Acetylsalicylic Acid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>N-acetyl-cysteine (NAC)</intervention_name>
    <description>taking N-acetyl-cysteine (NAC) 1000mg (2 capsules of 500mg) two times a day in addition to his/her  antidepressant and/or mood stabilizer medicine</description>
    <arm_group_label>N-acetyl-cysteine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Acetylcysteine</other_name>
    <other_name>N-Acetyl Cysteine</other_name>
    <other_name>NAC</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Asprin and NAC</intervention_name>
    <description>aspirin 1000mg (2 capsules of 500mg) every morning and NAC 1000mg (2 capsules of 500mg) two times a day in addition to his/her antidepressant and/or mood stabilizer medicine</description>
    <arm_group_label>Asprin and NAC</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ecotrin</other_name>
    <other_name>Bayer Aspirin</other_name>
    <other_name>Bufferin</other_name>
    <other_name>Acetylsalicylic Acid</other_name>
    <other_name>+</other_name>
    <other_name>Acetylcysteine</other_name>
    <other_name>N- Acetyl Cysteine</other_name>
    <other_name>NAC</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sugar Pill</intervention_name>
    <description>research subject will be taking placebo in addition to his/her antidepressant and/or mood stabilizer medicine</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar Pill</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sugar pill</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 18 to 65 years

          2. A diagnosis of BD type I or II according to SCID-I interview;

          3. Currently in a depressive or mixed episode, based on DSM-IV/ SCID-I criteria;

          4. MADRAS &gt;20 at entry in the study;

          5. No CURRENT liver, kidney, heart disease or ulcers or bleeding dyscrasia;

          6. No HYSTORY of kidney dysfunction or cardiac problems;

          7. ON therapeutic doses of a mood stabilizing drug (lithium, anticonvulsants, any
             atypical antipsychotics) or combinations for at least ONE month.

          8. Allowed psychiatric co-morbid conditions, such as anxiety disorders, PTSD and
             substance use (as long as do NOT meet abuse or dependence criteria according to the
             SCID-I in the past 2 months).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. CANNOT be on any :

             Anti-inflammatory: NSAIDs: Aspirin (bufferin, bayer aspirin, ecotrin), diflunisal
             (dolobid, diflunisal),Salsalate (amigesic, salflex), Ibuprofen (motrin, advil),
             Naproxen (naprosyn,aleve, midol extended relief), Fenoprofen (nalfon), Ketoprofen
             (actron), dexketoprofen(ketron D), Flurbiprofen (ansaid), Oxaprozin (daypro),
             Loxoprofen (loxfen, loxonin), Indomethacin (indocin, indocin SR), Sulindac
             (clinoril), Etodolac (lodine), Ketorolac (toradol), diclofenac (voltaren, cataflam),
             Nabumetone (Relafen) Piroxicam (feldene), Meloxicam (mobic), Tenoxicam (mobiflex),
             Lornoxicam (xefo),mefenamic acid (ponstel), meclofenamic acid (meclofenamate sodium),
             celecoxib (celebrex) Anticoagulants: Coumadin (Warfarin), Heparin Anti-oxidant agents
             Fish oil NAC ( N-acetyl cysteine)

          2. Pregnancy

          3. CANNOT change the dose of the psychotropic medications during the trial
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jair C Soares, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jair Soares, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+1 (713) 486-2627</phone>
    <email>utmooddisorders@uth.tmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Giovana Zunta Soares, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+1 (713)-486-2629</phone>
    <email>giovana.b.zuntasoares@uth.tmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT Center of Excellence on Mood Disorders</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77054</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Danielle E Spiker, BA</last_name>
      <phone>713-486-2627</phone>
      <email>danielle.e.spiker@uth.tmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Lindsay D Harris, BS</last_name>
      <phone>+1 (713) 486-2527</phone>
      <email>lindsay.d.harris@uth.tmc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jair C Soares, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://med.uth.tmc.edu/departments/psychiatry/utmooddisorders/index.html</url>
    <description>UT Center of Excellence on Mood Disorders at Houston</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 17, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 8, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jair Soares</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor &amp; Chairman - PSY-Behavioral Sciences</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bipolar Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Mood Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Bipolar Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Mood Swings</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Bipolar Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Acetylcysteine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>N-monoacetylcystine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aspirin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Contraceptives, Oral</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
