<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="13205">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01810107</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11-006H</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01810107</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Evaluate the Efficacy of Optical Imaging to Evaluate the Anatomy of the Developing Pediatric Vocal Fold</brief_title>
  <official_title>Study to Evaluate the Efficacy of Optical Imaging to Evaluate the Anatomy of the Developing Pediatric Vocal Fold</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts Eye and Ear Infirmary</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts Eye and Ear Infirmary</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The specific aim of this study is to develop a growth and development chart (similar to a
      height or weight chart for children) that identifies the pattern of development of the
      pediatric vocal cord lamina propria from a single to a three layer structure.  A secondary
      aim is to identify whether this growth chart shows a pattern of linear development or
      whether there are clear critical periods of development.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to identify critical periods of development when the lamina
      propria structure of the pediatric vocal fold matures. A Universal Modular Glottiscope will
      be utilized for adequate laryngeal exposure.  An operating microscope will be used for
      magnification.  This setup will allow for the Optical Coherence Tomography (OCT) imaging
      probe to be introduced using a laryngoscope to provide stability.  The optical imaging probe
      will then be directed, or gently applied towards, the glottal surface, and an image field of
      500 microns x 500 microns x 350 microns will be obtained.  As the probe is moved along the
      medial and superior mucosal surfaces of the vocal folds, &quot;real-time&quot; images will be obtained
      and digitally stored for review. The digitally stored images will be assessed and analyzed
      for their optical characteristics. The optical imaging probe will then be withdrawn from the
      patient and the original operative procedure will then be performed.  Images can be attained
      in both &quot;non-contact&quot; mode (where the probe tip remains in the space between each vocal
      fold) and &quot;contact&quot; mode (where the probe tip is gently placed against the glottal tissue to
      compress it).  The contact mode allows for deeper imaging (much like an ultrasound), which
      would be useful in situations involving larger (thicker) vocal folds. The study will end
      when images are acquired from a range of developmental ages to be able to refine the optical
      characteristics of the optical imaging system.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 0</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vocal Fold Development</measure>
    <time_frame>30 seconds to a minute, in the operating room, before the otolaryngology procedure that they are originally there for. This time frame is all that is needed to image their vocal cords.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The goal of this study is to identify critical periods of development when the lamina propria structure of the pediatric vocal fold matures. The major analysis will be to validate the age dependent laminar structure using a cohort of 720 subjects between age 0-18 as well as estimate the probability of future events of developing two- or three laminar structure given a subject's age. We will perform one-sided two-sample binomial tests to examine as well as model the patterns of the rates of bi- and tri-laminar structure patterns by using logistic model or discrete or continuous time Cox's proportional hazards model of which the predictor variables are determined based on the discriminant model described above. In addition, as a parallel approach we will analyze the Optical Coherence Tomography (OCT) data of each of the trilaminar system by using linear or curve-linear regression models which will provide a prediction model of the mean OCT at various critical ages.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">720</enrollment>
  <condition>Vocal Fold Development</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Children Examined with the OCT Probe</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Children undergoing surgery will also have the Optical Coherence Tomography probe.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Children Examined with the OCT Probe</intervention_name>
    <description>The child undergoing therapy will have the Optical Coherence Tomography (OCT) probe to examine the vocal fold.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Children Examined with the OCT Probe</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children ages 1 month to 18 undergoing laryngoscopy and bronchoscopy for airway
             evaluation where the children will be already scheduled for general anesthesia with
             intravenous catheter placement as part of standard routine. Children undergoing any
             pediatric otolaryngology procedure where there is no indication of airway obstruction
             or risk of abnormal vocal chords. For instance, children undergoing adenoidectomy,
             sinus surgery or tracheotomy are all good candidates for studying the normal vocal
             chord development.

          -  Children whose parents have given and signed an informed consent and HIPAA
             Authorization and who have signed an assent form (if they are 7 and older) agreeing
             to participate in the study. Eligibility will be determined by the Principal
             Investigator.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children with any form of laryngeal anomaly or pathology.  Children who have
             previously been intubated. Children and adolescents who smoke. Exclusion will be
             determined by the Principal Investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Month</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christopher Hartnick, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts Eye and Ear Infirmary</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>March 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 11, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 19, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
