<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="109304">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01955564</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NW-3509A/001/I/2011</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01955564</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase I- Sequential Cohort Dosing to Determine Maximum Tolerated Dose in Healthy Male Volunteers.</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I, Prospective, Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Sequential-cohort, Escalating, Single-dose Study Designed to Determine the Maximum Tolerated Oral Dose of NW-3509A in Healthy, Male Volunteers.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Newron Sweden AB</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Newron Sweden AB</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, 8-day, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled,
      sequential-cohort study designed to evaluate the safety, tolerability, and MTD of single
      escalating oral doses of NW-3509A in healthy male volunteers. Five independent cohorts of 12
      volunteers each will participate in this study, with the first 9 volunteers in each cohort
      to qualify being randomized to receive study medication and the remaining 3 to be used as
      backups/ alternates. In each cohort, 6 subjects will be randomly assigned to receive
      NW-3509A and 3 subjects will receive placebo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate safety and tolerability and maximum tolerated dose of NW-3509a in Healthy Male Volunteers</measure>
    <time_frame>Day -1(predose) through Day 3 -Discharge)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Cardiac monitoring of subjects includes ECG extractions, continuous Holter Monitoring, vitals signs, blood testing, SSRS (suicidality) performed,and adverse event assessment to be performed</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate safety and tolerability and maximum tolerated dose of NW-3509a in Healthy Male Volunteers</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 5 phone contact</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Determine occurrence of any adverse events</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate safety and tolerability and maximum tolerated dose of NW-3509a in Healthy Male Volunteers</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessment of any adverse events, laboratory tests, ECG and a physical/neurological examination. An assessment of suicidality (through performing a C-SSRS, since last visit).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the pharmacokinetics of NW-3509a at doses tested</measure>
    <time_frame>PK collected prior to dosing and through Day 3 of study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>5</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Schizophrenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <description>NW-3509a - 1mg or placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <description>NW-3509a 2mg or placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <description>NW-3509a 5mg or placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4</arm_group_label>
    <description>NW-3509a 10 mg or placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 5</arm_group_label>
    <description>NW-3509a 20 mg or placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NW-3509a</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 5</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      PK specimens will be drawn to determine the maximum tolerated dose of NW-3509a in heathly
      male volunteers
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Healthy Male Vounteers
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Demographics

        Volunteers will meet the following demographic inclusion criteria:

          1. Age - between 18 and 45 years of age, inclusive.

          2. Sex - males.

          3. The subject has a body weight of at least 45 kg and a body mass index of ≤30.

             Procedural

             Volunteers will meet the following procedural criteria:

          4. They are cooperative, able to take oral medication, willing to complete all aspects
             of the study, and capable of doing so.

          5. They will be able to understand the instructions and fully participate.

          6. They will have provided written informed consent prior to participating in the study.

          7. The  subject  is  in  good  health  with  no  history  of  significant  medical
             disease  as  determined  by  the investigator.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        The presence of any of the following will exclude a subject from study enrollment:

        General Medical Status

          1. An advanced, severe, or unstable disease of any type that may interfere with any of
             the study evaluations, including any medical condition that could be expected to
             progress, recur, or change to such an extent that it may bias the assessment of the
             clinical or mental status of the volunteer to a significant degree or put the
             volunteer at special risk (e.g., liver or kidney disease; malignancy);

          2. A disability that may prevent the volunteer from completing all study requirements
             (e.g., blindness, deafness, severe language difficulty);

          3. A current diagnosis of active, uncontrolled peptic ulceration within the last year;

          4. A current diagnosis of acute, severe, or unstable asthmatic condition.

             Cardiovascular

          5. A current diagnosis of severe or unstable cardiovascular disease;

          6. A current diagnosis of sick-sinus syndrome or conduction deficits (e.g., sino-atrial
             block (&lt;0.22), second or third degree atrio-ventricular block);

          7. Any history or current evidence of a cardiac illness as determined by the
             investigator;

          8. Any clinically significant ECG abnormality, including a disorder of rate, rhythm, or
             conduction, or other morphological changes, or a QTcF interval (Fridericia's
             correction formula) on the ECG &gt;450 msec. The 12-lead ECG will be used for
             determining the suitability of the subject for inclusion in the study (determined by
             the investigator);

          9. Vital signs (supine) outside the following ranges:

               -  Systolic blood pressure below 100 or above 139 mmHg;

               -  Diastolic blood pressure below 50 or above 89 mmHg;

               -  Radial pulse below 50 or above 90 bpm.

             CNS related

         10. Any history or current diagnosis of any neurodegenerative illness;

         11. History or current diagnosis of epilepsy or seizure disorder.

             Psychiatric

         12. Any past or current psychiatric illness (DSM-IV-TR Axis 1 diagnosis);

         13. Subjects with current or past suicidal ideation.

             Study-specific criteria

         14. History of serious adverse reactions or hypersensitivity to any drug;

         15. Presence or history of allergies requiring acute or chronic treatment (except
             seasonal allergic rhinitis);

         16. Alcohol or drug abuser; currently or at any time in the last 5 years;

         17. Abnormal physical findings of clinical significance at the screening examination or
             baseline that would interfere with the objectives of the study;

         18. Need of any prescription medication within 14 days prior to the administration of the
             study drug, and/or non-prescription medication within 7 days prior to the
             administration of the drug;

         19. Participation in  other  clinical  trials  during  the  last  2  months  in  which an
              investigational  drug or  a commercially available drug was tested;

         20. Loss of 500 ml or more of blood during the 3-month period before the study, e.g. as a
             donor.

         21. Existence of any surgical or medical condition which might interfere with the
             absorption, distribution, metabolism or excretion of the study drug, i.e. impaired
             renal or hepatic function, diabetes mellitus, cardiovascular abnormalities,
             inflammatory bowel disease, chronic symptoms of pronounced constipation or diarrhea,
             or conditions associated with total or partial obstruction of the urinary tract;

         22. Symptoms of  a  significant  somatic  or  mental  illness in  the  four-week  period
             preceding  study drug administration;

         23. History of hepatitis B and/or C, and/or positive serology results, which indicate the
             presence of hepatitis B and/or C (Hepatitis B surface antigen and/or antibody to
             Hepatitis C);

         24. Positive results from the HIV serology;

         25. Positive results of the drug and alcohol tests at screening and/or check-in at the
             unit;

         26. Smoker; currently or at any time in the last 5 years;

             Laboratory abnormalities

         27. Clinically significant abnormalities in routine laboratory examinations (hematology;
             blood chemistry, including electrolytes and liver and kidney function tests;
             urinalysis), as determined by the Principal Investigator in consultation with the
             Sponsor, at the screening evaluation;

         28. Clinically important laboratory abnormalities in thyroid function tests at screening:

             • TSH &gt; 8.0 mU/L and/or Free T4 &lt; 9 pmol/L;

             Concomitant therapy

         29. A known exaggerated pharmacological sensitivity or hypersensitivity to drugs similar
             to NW-3509A. Possible examples are volunteers who have experienced hypersensitivity
             reactions to sodium channel blockers;

         30. Ingested any of the following substances:

               -  An investigational drug during the past 2 months;

               -  A drug or treatment known to cause major organ system toxicity during the past
                  year;

               -  Any prescription drug or OTC product if taken continuously (Medical Monitor from
                  Newron should be contacted if the Investigator wants to include a volunteer who
                  is taking an OTC product);

               -  Alcohol intake should be limited to 2 drinks per day during the 2 weeks prior to
                  dosing; alcohol consumption will be prohibited from 72 hours prior to
                  admittance on Day -1 through to the final safety evaluations on Day 8.

               -  Caffeine-containing products should be limited (equivalent of 2 cups of coffee
                  per day) during the 2 weeks prior to dosing and through to the final safety
                  evaluations on Day 8.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Leibowitz, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Collaborative Neuroscience Network Phase I Unit</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ravi Anand, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Newron Sweden AB</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mark Leibowitz, MD</last_name>
    <phone>562-304-1750</phone>
    <email>markleibowitz@cnstrial.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Marian Sidlowski, MS</last_name>
    <phone>484-340-6189</phone>
    <email>msidlowski@clinirx.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Collaborative Neuroscience Network-Clinical Pharmacology Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Long Beach</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90806</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hannah Voltattorni</last_name>
      <phone>562-304-1742</phone>
      <email>hannavoltattorni@cnstrial.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Anne Cabral</last_name>
      <phone>562-304-1742</phone>
      <email>annecabral@cnstrial.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark Leibowitz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 17, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 21, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
