<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="80697">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02004847</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PsoriasisCT02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02004847</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Blue Light for Treating Psoriasis Vulgaris</brief_title>
  <official_title>Monocenter, Randomized, Double Blinded, Intraindividual, Exploratory Study of Effectiveness and Safety of 3 Months Treatment With 2 Peak Intensities of 453nm Blue Light for the Treatment of Mild Plaque Type Psoriasis Vulgaris</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Light and Health Venture</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Light and Health Venture</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Ethics Commission</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the efficacy and safety of a blue light device for
      treating Psoriasis vulgaris. The study will compare a blue light treated plaque with an
      untreated control plaque. Additionally, two intensities of blue light are compared.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Blue light has been shown to release bioactive nitric oxide (NO) from nitrite and nitrosated
      proteins found in high concentrations in the skin.  This bioactive NO has many physiological
      functions regulating immune responses, proliferation / differentiation as well as local
      blood Perfusion of the skin. The study will test the PSO-CT02 device, an new investigational
      medical device emitting blue light with a peak wavelength of 453nm on treating localised
      mild Psoriasis vulgaris. It can be worn on the Skin above the effected skin area. In this
      study Treatment (target) and control area as well as intensity of blue light are randomized.
      The control area will serve as reference. 50 Patients will treat the target area daily (at
      least 5 times/week) at home for an initial treatment period of 4 weeks. During those 4
      weeks, patients will return to the study site for safety and effectiveness assessments
      twice. After this initiation period patients will treat their plaque for further 8 weeks (3
      times/week). This is followed by a 4 week follow up phase without treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline (visit 2) of the local Psoriasis area severity index (PASI) of the target area (High Intensity (HI) group) as compared to the control area at end of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline of the local Psoriasis area severity index (PASI) of the target area (High Intensity) as compared to the control area at end of treatment during the attack period</measure>
    <time_frame>week 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Week 12 of the local Psoriasis area severity index (PASI) of the target area (High Intensity) as compared to the control area at end of follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline (visit 2) of the local Psoriasis area severity index (PASI) of the target area (Low Intensity (LI) group) as compared to the control area</measure>
    <time_frame>week 4, 12, 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in change from baseline of local Psoriasis area severity index (PASI) between target and control area of the High Intensity (HI) group as compared to the Low Intensity (LI) group</measure>
    <time_frame>week 4, 12, 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline of the individual symptoms of the target area of High Intensity (HI) and Low Intensity (LI) as compared to the control area</measure>
    <time_frame>week 4, 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Week 12 (end of treatment) of the individual symptoms of the target area of High Intensity (HI) and Low Intensity (LI) as compared to the control area at end of follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline of inflammation (erythema) evaluated by mexameter of the target area of High Intensity (HI) and Low Intensity (LI) as compared to the control area</measure>
    <time_frame>week 4, 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Week 12 (end of treatment) of inflammation (erythema) evaluated by mexameter of the target area of High Intensity (HI) and Low Intensity (LI) as compared to the control area at end of follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>System Usability Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI)</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first use of topical co-treatment with Vitamin D of High Intensity (HI) and Low Intensity (LI) as compared to the control area</measure>
    <time_frame>patients will be followed for the complete duration of the clinical study for 16 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total duration of topical co-treatment with Vitamin D of High Intensity (HI) and Low Intensity (LI) as compared to the control area</measure>
    <time_frame>week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Hyperpigmentation of &quot;normal skin areas&quot; surrounding the target area exposed to blue light and control area not exposed to blue light- evaluation by Mexameter</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0, 2, 8, 12, 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Structured patient assessment of tolerability using the symptoms inflammation (erythema), itching, burn and pain (range: 0-4 per symptom) applied to a. Target area (exposed to blue light) b. Control area (not exposed to blue light)</measure>
    <time_frame>week 2, 4, 8, 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events (serious and non-serious)</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0, 1, 2, 4, 8, 12, 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse device events (serious and non-serious)</measure>
    <time_frame>for 16 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Device deficiencies</measure>
    <time_frame>for 16 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The actual number of device deficiencies will be given.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Thermal comfort</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12, 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Recovery of hyperpigmentation during follow up period</measure>
    <time_frame>week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Patient acceptance of hyperpigmentation</measure>
    <time_frame>week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">47</enrollment>
  <condition>Psoriasis Vulgaris</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High Intensity (HI) vs control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PSO-CT02 device: Light wavelength 453nm, high intensity, compared to contralateral untreated control plaque on the same patient.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low Intensity (LI) vs control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PSO-CT02 device: Light wavelength 453nm, low intensity, compared to contralateral untreated control plaque on the same patient.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PSO-CT02</intervention_name>
    <description>The PSO-CT02 device is a non CE marked investigational medical device that is worn on the affected skin area where it irradiates the Psoriasis plaque for 30 minutes with blue light.</description>
    <arm_group_label>High Intensity (HI) vs control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Low Intensity (LI) vs control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Signed and dated informed consent prior to any study mandated procedure

          2. Good health according to physical examination as determined by the Investigator

          3. Willing and able to comply with study requirements

          4. Skin type I-IV according to Fitzpatrick

          5. Mild plaque-type psoriasis vulgaris with a Psoriasis area severity index (PASI) ≤10
             and Body surface area (BSA)

             ≤10 and Dermatology Life quality index (DLQI) ≤ 10 at screening.

          6. Presence of two comparable psoriatic plaques suitable to be defined as study areas as
             follows:

               1. located on extremities (plaques located on the palms or sole of the feet are not
                  suitable)

               2. Both areas located either on lower or upper extremity

               3. Can be located on the same extremity

               4. Distance between the two study areas &gt; 10cm (border to border)

               5. If lesion is too large to be fully covered, partial treatment possible

          7. Aged ≥ 18 years up to &lt;75 years

          8. Reliable method of contraception for women of childbearing potential (i.e. low
             failure rate less than 1% per year; e.g. oral contraceptives, intra-uterine device
             [IUD] or transdermal contraceptive patch)

          9. Willing to abstain from excessive sun / UV exposure (e.g. sunbathe, solarium) during
             the course of the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        General

          1. Inmates of psychiatric wards, prisons, or other state institutions

          2. Investigator or any other team member involved directly or indirectly in the conduct
             of the clinical study

          3. Participation in another clinical trial within the last 30 days

          4. Pregnant or lactating women Medical History

          5. Photodermatosis and/or Photosensitivity

          6. Porphyria and/or hypersensitivity to porphyrins

          7. Patients with current diagnosis of erythrodermic, exfoliative or pustular psoriasis

          8. Congenital or acquired immunodeficiency

          9. Patients with any of the following conditions present on the study areas: Malignoma
             of the skin or severe actinic damage of the skin, atypical naevi or signs of
             hyperpigmentation, viral (e.g. herpes or varicella) lesions of the skin, fungal and
             bacterial skin infections, parasitic infections and atrophic Skin

         10. Patients with genetic deficiencies attached with increased sensitivity to light or
             increased risk to dermatologic cancer (i.e. Xeroderma pigmentosum, Cockayne Syndrome,
             Bloom- Syndrome)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Verena von Felbert, PD, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Clinic for Dermatology and Allergology, Medical Faculty of the RWTH Aachen, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Dermatology and Allergology, Medical faculty of the RWTH Aachen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aachen</city>
        <zip>52074</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 19, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Psoriasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
