<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="129351">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01789476</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR845 CLIN2003</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01789476</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase 2 Study to Evaluate Analgesic Effect of IV CR845 For Pain Following Bunionectomy Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-Center, Randomized, Double-Blind, Parallel Group, Placebo-Controlled Study to Evaluate the Analgesic Efficacy and Safety of CR845 Dosed in Patients With Pain Following Bunionectomy Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cara Therapeutics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cara Therapeutics, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-center, randomized, double blind, placebo controlled, parallel group proof
      of concept study to evaluate the analgesic efficacy as well as the safety, tolerability and
      pharmacokinetic profile of CR845 in patients with pain following bunionectomy surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Currently, the most widely used drugs to treat pain after surgery are opiates, such as
      morphine. Morphine works mainly by activating one of several types of opiate receptors that
      control some of our pain sensation - the so-called mu opiate receptors. These receptors are
      located in many areas of the brain and also outside of the brain. By activating these
      receptors, morphine provides significant pain relief, but also causes side effects that
      limit its use. Some of these side effects include: respiratory depression or arrest (slowed
      or stopped breathing), sedation (a state of calmness or extreme relaxation), euphoria (an
      exaggerated feeling of physical and mental well-being), constipation, nausea, vomiting, and
      drug addiction.

      In order to avoid the side effects of morphine and other mu opiates, the present
      experimental drug CR845 was designed to work at a different type of opiate receptor - called
      kappa - that can also provide pain relief, by acting on sensory nerves outside the brain.
      CR845 was designed to penetrate the brain much less than other opiate drugs, which should
      result in pain relief similar to that of morphine, but with fewer side effects. Because
      CR845 activates kappa receptors instead of mu receptors, the side effects are different than
      with a morphine-type drug. In particular, kappa opiates, such as CR845, do not cause
      respiratory depression or arrest, euphoria, constipation, drug tolerance, physical drug
      dependence or drug addiction. For these reasons, CR845 may present a distinct advantage over
      other opiates that are currently used for pain relief and post-operative pain in particular.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time-specific VAS difference-the 24 hour summed pain intensity differences (SPID24)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Pain Intensity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the efficacy of CR845 compared to placebo in reducing pain following bunionectomy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Pain Intensity, Pain Relief, Global Assessment Measures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the effect of CR845 compared to placebo on the use of rescue opioid analgesics during the postoperative period</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Amount of rescue opioid required</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">51</enrollment>
  <condition>Postoperative Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CR845</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Use of peripheral kappa receptor agonist IV for pain</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo Arm for comparison</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CR845</intervention_name>
    <description>CR845 dosage = 0.005 mg/kg per dose. The initial dose is administered upon reaching a qualifying pain intensity score and followed by a supplemental dose, if requested by patient for pain.  Additional doses can be administered every 8 hours up to 48 hours.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CR845</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Active treatment for post-operative pain</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo administered using same dosing algorithm as the active arm</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Post-operative placebo for pain</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Able to provide written informed consent prior to any study procedures;

          2. Able to communicate clearly with the Investigator and staff;

          3. Males and females aged 18 years or older;

          4. Scheduled for elective primary unilateral first metatarsal bunionectomy surgery
             (osteotomy and internal fixation) with no collateral procedures;

          5. Females physically incapable of childbearing potential (postmenopausal for more than
             1 year or surgically sterile) or practicing an acceptable method of contraception
             (hormonal, barrier with spermicide, intrauterine device, vasectomized partner, or
             abstinence).  Subjects using hormonal birth control must have received at least 1
             cycle of treatment prior to randomization.  All females of childbearing potential
             must have a negative pregnancy test and not be breast feeding at Baseline;

          6. Negative urine drug screen for drugs of abuse at Screening and at Baseline; a
             positive drug screen result may be permitted if the patient has been on a stable dose
             of an allowed medication for &gt;30 days (antipsychotics, antiepileptics, sedatives,
             hypnotics, or antianxiety agents, selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors [SSRIs],
             tricyclic antidepressants) or &gt;3 months (opioid analgesics or systemic steroids);

          7. American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) risk class of I to II;

          8. Body weight &lt;170 kg

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Has known allergies to opioids, unless has subsequently tolerated other opioids and
             in the opinion of the PI could tolerate study drug;

          2. Has a known or suspected history of Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental
             Disorders, Fourth Edition (DSM-IV)-diagnosed alcohol, opiate or other drug abuse or
             dependence within 12 months prior to screening;

          3. Is unable to refrain from alcohol consumption for a period beginning 24 hours prior
             to surgery through the end of the Treatment Period;

          4. Has taken non-opioid analgesics (including cyclooxygenase-2 [COX-2] inhibitors) or
             nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) within 12 hours of the Baseline
             assessments;

          5. Has taken any opioid analgesics or used systemic steroids within 4 days of surgery OR
             has been using opiates chronically for a period of &lt; 3 months; (Note: Patients on
             stable chronic opioids for ≥ 3 months will need to discontinue them for 4 days prior
             to surgery);

          6. Has used antipsychotics, antiepileptics, sedatives, hypnotics, or antianxiety agents,
             selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), tricyclic antidepressants for &lt; 30
             days prior to surgery or had a dose change within the previous 30 days;

          7. Has taken any prescription or over-the-counter medication within 4 days prior to
             surgery that, in the opinion of the Investigator, is expected to confound the
             analgesic response;

          8. Has taken herbal agents or nutraceuticals (i.e., chaparral, comfrey, germander, jin
             bu huan, kava, pennyroyal, skullcap, St. John's wort, or valerian)  during any of the
             7 days prior to surgery;

          9. Has any clinically significant condition or a significant laboratory abnormality that
             would, in the Investigator's or designee's opinion, preclude study participation

         10. Has received another investigational drug within 30 days of scheduled surgery.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Derek Muse, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Jean Brown Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jean Brown Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84124</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 13, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 8, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pain</keyword>
  <keyword>acute pain</keyword>
  <keyword>kappa agonis</keyword>
  <keyword>opioid analgesia</keyword>
  <keyword>bunionectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>peripheral nervous system agents</keyword>
  <keyword>physiological effects of drugs</keyword>
  <keyword>surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>post-operative</keyword>
  <keyword>post-operative complications</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Analgesics</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Nervous System Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Physiological Effects of Drugs</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
