<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="119360">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01921270</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00064292</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01921270</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dysport for the Treatment of OMD</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Dose Ranging Study of Dysport® (AbobotulinumtoxinA) in the Treatment of Oromandibular Dystonia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ipsen Biopharmaceuticals Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to study the efficacy, safety, and proper dosing of
      AbobotulinumtoxinA (Dysport) for use in Oromandibular Dystonia (OMD).  The study hypothesis
      is that one of the dosing levels used will have adequate safety and efficacy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Design:

      Interventional , single site, prospective study with 2 parts:

        1. Dose raging (aim 1): 3 oromandibular Dystonia (OMD) groups undergoing 3 different
           Dysport® dosages with a step-wise approach based on safety response. 6 weeks duration
           for the 3 groups.

        2. Efficacy &amp; safety assessment of Dysport® selected dose from study part 1 (aim 2): 1
           single arm with OMD subjects. 12 weeks duration.

      Study Specific Aims:

      Aim 1: To determine the best dose range for Dysport® for the treatment of OMD

      In order to address Aim 1, patients with OMD who have been previously treated with Botox®
      (onabotulinumtoxinA) and responded will be recruited into this study.  The muscles to be
      injected will be tailored to the individual's presentation and up to the injector's
      discretion, but if a muscle is chosen it will be given a set amount of Dysport®
      (abobotulinumtoxinA )(see table 2).  The subject will be injected with Dysport® only, with
      an unblinded open-label disclosure.  There will be three dose levels and three subjects will
      be injected in each (OMD type for each group: 2 jaw opening + 1 jaw closing).

      This optimal dosage will be the safest dosage that provides adequate efficacy. This will be
      based on the Clinical Global Impression Scale's Efficacy Index.  Subjects from Aim 1 will be
      offered enrollment into Aim 2.

      Aim 2: To determine the efficacy and safety of Dysport® for the treatment of oromandibular
      dystonia

      20 subjects will be included in the second part of the study and will be injected with the
      determined optimal dosage found at the end of the first study part.  They would be injected
      for Aim 2 after at least 12 weeks have passed, given that the effect from the prior
      injection had either completely abated or at least declined significantly.  The 9 subjects
      from Aim 1 will be offered to enter study part 2 unless they have severe adverse event (AE),
      ongoing AE or AE considered inappropriate for study continuation.  Their previous injections
      with Dysport® should not confound the results of Aim 2 since both Botox® and Dysport® should
      both have minimal clinical effect at 12 weeks out from injection.  Since the local
      population suffering from OMD is small, the inclusion of the Aim 1 subjects into Aim 2 would
      lead to a much more rapid completion of recruitment.

      In both Aim 1 and Aim 2, the safety and efficacy will be recorded for all subjects that
      undergo injection.  All subjects will be examined and videotaped at the injection visit,
      then at 6 and 12 weeks after injection with a standardized protocol.  The primary outcome
      will be blinded examination scores of the videos performed after the study is complete. The
      evaluators will be  two different movement disorders experts, not otherwise involved in the
      study, who will review the videotaped examinations, presented in a random order, using the
      Global Dystonia Rating scale (GDS).  They will rate the dystonia at baseline (injection
      visit) and 6 weeks after injection.  The change in GDS score from baseline to 6 weeks after
      injection is the best objective measure of efficacy and will serve as the study's primary
      endpoint.  The investigators chose the GDS over other dystonia scales because of its ease of
      use, sensitivity to clinical changes because of its continuous rating system, internal
      consistency, and inter-rater reliability.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Global Dystonia Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>0,6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This scale measures the severity of dystonia for a certain body part--in this study it will be &quot;lower face&quot; and &quot;jaw and tongue&quot; sections.  The primary outcome will be the difference in the baseline score to the 6 week score.  For the primary outcome, a BLINDED VIDEO EVALUATOR will be completing this evaluation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Global Dystonia Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>0,12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This scale measure the severity of dystonia in a certain body part.  The change from baseline to 6 weeks is the primary outcome, but from baseline to 12 weeks is a secondary outcome. For this secondary outcome measure, the scale will be completed by the BLINDED VIDEO EVALUATOR.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Global Dystonia Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>0,6,12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This is a scale that measures the severity of dystonia in a certain body part.  For a SECONDARY outcome, the scale will be completed by the injecting practitioner and not the blinded evaluator.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Analogue Pain Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 6, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measure of jaw pain by visual analogue scale (0-100)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SCS-PD (Sialorrhea Clinical Scale for PD)</measure>
    <time_frame>0,6,12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measure of drooling</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimated amount of tongue bites per day</measure>
    <time_frame>0,6,12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The patient will be asked to estimate how many times they tend to accidentally/involuntarily bite their tongue per day</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Swallowing Disturbance Questionnaire(SDQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>0,6,12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Ease of chewing and  swallowing modified to exclude questions 5, which is redundant since it regards drooling, already covered, and question 15 which is not relevant to the study as it involves prior aspiration pneumonias)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fahn-Marsden Part B &quot;Speech&quot; Question</measure>
    <time_frame>0,6, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Question regarding ease of speech</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oromandibular Dystonia Quality of Life Questionnaire (OMDQ-25)</measure>
    <time_frame>0,6,12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Subjective quality of life measurement made for patients with Oromandibular Dystonia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Global Clinical Impression Scale (CGI) with Efficacy Index</measure>
    <time_frame>0,6,12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>A measure of improvement relative to the burden of side effects</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Unified Dystonia Rating Scale (UDRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>0,6,12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Rating by BLINDED video evaluators regarding severity of subject's dystonia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">29</enrollment>
  <condition>Oral Dystonia</condition>
  <condition>Tardive Dystonia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High Dose AbobotulinumtoxinA (Dysport)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm refers to Aim 1 of the study in which different dosages will be administered.  For a particular muscle that is appropriate to inject, the established &quot;high&quot; dose will be given. It will be injected once at Week 0.
Dosage of AbobotulinumtoxinA (Dysport) per muscle:
Medial Pterygoid:     100 units Masseter:            75 units Lateral Pterygoid:   100 units Anterior digastrics: 30 units Genioglossus:        35 units</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Medium Dose AbobotulinumtoxinA (Dysport)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm refers to Aim 1 of the study in which different dosages will be administered.  For a particular muscle that is appropriate to inject, the established &quot;medium&quot; dose will be given. It will be injected once at Week 0.
Dosage of AbobotulinumtoxinA (Dysport) per muscle:
Medial Pterygoid:     75 units Masseter:            50 units Lateral Pterygoid:   75 units Anterior digastrics: 20 units Genioglossus:        25 units</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low Dose AbobotulinumtoxinA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm refers to Aim 1 of the study in which different dosages will be administered.  For a particular muscle that is appropriate to inject, the established &quot;low&quot; dose will be given. It will be injected once at Week 0.
Dosage of AbobotulinumtoxinA (Dysport) per muscle:
Medial Pterygoid:     50 units Masseter:            25 units Lateral Pterygoid:   50 units Anterior digastrics: 10 units Genioglossus:        15 units</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AbobotulinumtoxinA</intervention_name>
    <description>Medication will be reconstituted at 1.5 cc of normal saline for every 300 units of abobotulinumtoxinA, then injected.</description>
    <arm_group_label>High Dose AbobotulinumtoxinA (Dysport)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Medium Dose AbobotulinumtoxinA (Dysport)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Low Dose AbobotulinumtoxinA</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Dysport</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  a diagnosis of primary or tardive OMD

          -  moderate or severe severity, defined as GDS score ≥4 in either &quot;lower face&quot; or &quot;jaw
             and tongue&quot; section

          -  age&gt;18 years

          -  capability of attending the scheduled visits

          -  only those who have been previously injected with onabotulinumtoxinA and responded to
             that treatment, and are at least 12 weeks post last injection

          -  Women of childbearing age need to use contraception in order to be included.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Existence of a systemic disease that could confound the evaluation

          -  previous placement of Deep Brain Stimulation electrodes to treat dystonia

          -  concomitant oral medications that could interfere with the action of botulinum toxin
             Type A (e.g., aminoglycosides)

          -  on an unstable dosage of any medication prescribed to treat dystonia (e.g.,
             benzodiazepines, baclofen or anticholinergics)

          -  any known hypersensitivity to any botulinum toxin preparation and allergy to cow's
             milk protein

          -  immunoresistance to other forms of botulinum toxin type A

          -  existence of a concomitant neuromuscular disorder (e.g., Myasthenia Gravis or
             Lambert-Eaton syndrome, etc)

          -  infection at the proposed injection sites

          -  pregnant women

          -  women of childbearing age NOT on contraception

          -  breastfeeding women

          -  inability to comply with scheduled visits

          -  patients who had been previously injected with botulinum toxin type A but who did not
             respond
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stewart A Factor, DO</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael R Silver, MD</last_name>
    <phone>404-778-3444</phone>
    <email>michael.r.silver@emory.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Elaine Sperin, LPN</last_name>
    <phone>404-728-4786</phone>
    <email>esperin@emory.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wesley Woods Health Center; Emory University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30329</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael R Silver, MD</last_name>
      <phone>404-778-3444</phone>
      <email>michael.r.silver@emory.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Elaine Sperin, LPN</last_name>
      <phone>404-728-4786</phone>
      <email>esperin@emory.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stewart A Factor, DO</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tan EK, Jankovic J. Botulinum toxin A in patients with oromandibular dystonia: long-term follow-up. Neurology. 1999 Dec 10;53(9):2102-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10599789</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosales RL, Ng AR, Santos MM, Fernandez HH. The broadening application of chemodenervation in X-linked dystonia-parkinsonism (Part II): an open-label experience with botulinum toxin-A (Dysport®) injections for oromandibular, lingual, and truncal-axial dystonias. Int J Neurosci. 2011;121 Suppl 1:44-56. doi: 10.3109/00207454.2011.558260.</citation>
    <PMID>21348790</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 9, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 9, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Emory University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Stewart Factor</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Oromandibular Dystonia</keyword>
  <keyword>Oral Dystonia</keyword>
  <keyword>Tardive Dystonia</keyword>
  <keyword>botulinum toxin</keyword>
  <keyword>abobotulinumtoxinA</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dystonia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dystonic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Movement Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Botulinum Toxins, Type A</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
