<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="144776">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02115685</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01 NS079751</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02115685</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sympathetic-Somatomotor Coupling in Human Spinal Cord Injury</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rehabilitation Institute of Chicago</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Marquette University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rehabilitation Institute of Chicago</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Significance: The long term objective of this study is to improve physical therapy and
      fitness programs in people with spinal cord injury. The results of the study will
      demonstrate the importance of matching blood flow to a muscle with exercise of that same
      muscle.

      Scientific Objective: The objective of the study is to measure how the body regulates
      bloodflow to a muscle during exercise. We intend to study these effects by triggering blood
      flow changes during movement, and measuring bloodflow changes during exercise in people with
      spinal cord injury. We will also look at the long term effects of different exercise
      programs on bloodflow during exercise.

      Study Populations: This study will involve people with partial spinal cord injury and age
      and sex matched controls without injury.

      Specific Aims: Aim 1 will be to measure bloodflow during exercise of the legs (below the
      injury). This aim will examine the control of bloodflow and muscle contractions and how it
      changes after spinal cord injury. In Aim 2, we will identify changes in the bloodflow during
      exercise of the arms (above the spinal injury). Aim 3 will then look at changes in bloodflow
      during exercise after training. Three different eight week exercise training programs will
      be tested including 1) upper body ergometry, 2) treadmill training with exertion level
      matched to the upper body ergometry and 3) treadmill training with heart rate matched to an
      initial test of upper body ergometry.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Arterial blood flow</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subject will be tested with doppler ultrasonography immediately pre and post sympathetic stressor. Testing sessions will take anywhere between 3-6 hours.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Graded Treadmill Exercise Test</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Graded treadmill exercise test will be tested at multiple intervals pre and post training paradigms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart rate</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Heart rate will be tested continuously during sympathetic stressors and at multiple intervals pre and post training paradigms with a Finapres.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee torque</measure>
    <time_frame>8 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Knee torque will be tested with the Biodex both pre and post sympathetic stressors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tendon tap reflexes</measure>
    <time_frame>8 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Tendon tap reflexes will be tested during one day testing pre and post sympathetic stressors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Spinal Cord Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>One day testing of sympathetic nervous system</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Aim 1 will be to measure bloodflow during exercise of the legs (below the injury). This aim will examine the control of bloodflow and muscle contractions and how it changes after spinal cord injury.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Upper body ergometry effects on sympathetic measures in SCI.</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Upper body ergometry: Aim 2, we will identify changes in the bloodflow during exercise of the arms (above the spinal injury).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Effects of long term training on sympathetic measures in SCI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Aim 3 will then look at changes in bloodflow during exercise after training. Three different eight week exercise training programs will be tested including 1) upper body ergometry, 2) treadmill training with exertion level matched to the upper body ergometry and 3) treadmill training with heart rate matched to an initial test of upper body ergometry.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Upper body ergometry training</intervention_name>
    <description>Training will be provided during scheduled 1 hr sessions 3-5X per week.  Following graded UBE testing (described below), subjects will be asked to work at an rating of perceived exertion (RPE) of 16-17 while cycling an ergometer (Reck Motomed, Betzenweiler, Germany) at 60-70 rpm with resistance graded according to patient tolerance/responses while heart rate is monitored.  Power (W) will be increased 5-10 W as tolerated to maintain 16-17 RPE throughout training.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Upper body ergometry effects on sympathetic measures in SCI.</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>UBE training</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Treadmill Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Matched Intensity Treadmill Training: Training will be provided during scheduled 1 hr sessions 3-5X per week.  Treadmill training will be performed at intensities approaching 85% of maximum predicted heart rate and recommended by the American College of Sports Medicine.  Training intensity will be monitored during the training session, maintaining an RPE score similar to UBE training (16-17).
Matched Heart Rate Treadmill Training: Similar treadmill training paradigms as described above will be performed during Matched Heart Rate Training on the treadmill.  Following graded testing with UBE (see below) the heart rate measured during an RPE of 16-17 during UBE testing will be utilized as the initial goal for treadmill walking.  The matched heart rate will normalize cardiovascular stress between UBE and treadmill stepping.  Weight support and robotic or therapist assistance will be utilized as described above.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Effects of long term training on sympathetic measures in SCI</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  incomplete SCI

          -  subjects will be over age 18

          -  to fit in the apparatus and to assure a mature gait pattern

          -  at least 6 months post injury, and medically stable with an incomplete lesion between
             levels T1-T10

          -  lower extremity motor score of 10 or greater

          -  presence of intact stretch reflexes, detected clinically

          -  no previous history or evidence of peripheral nerve damage in the lower extremities

          -  Subjects must be able to step on a treadmill with no more than 40% body weight
             support.

        Healthy controls will be age and sex matched to the subjects with spinal cord injury.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  unhealed decubiti,

          -  bladder or other infection

          -  severe contracture or osteoporosis

          -  heterotopic ossification

          -  cardiac arrhythmia

          -  inability to give informed consent

          -  an episode of autonomic dysreflexia in the past year

          -  use of spasticity or cardiovascular medications (e.g. baclofen)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brian D Schmidt, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Marquette University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>T. George Hornby, PT, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Illinois at Chicago</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>T. George Hornby, PT, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>3122381397</phone>
    <email>tgh@uic.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rehabilitation Institute of Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>T. George Hornby, PT, PHD</last_name>
      <phone>3122381397</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>T. George Hornby, PT, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 15, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 14, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Rehabilitation Institute of Chicago</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>T. George Hornby</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PT, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>spinal cord injury</keyword>
  <keyword>sympathetic nervous system</keyword>
  <keyword>locomotor training</keyword>
  <keyword>exercise</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
