<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="159958">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02151994</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BIA-51058-101</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02151994</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetic, Including Food Interaction, and Pharmacodynamic Profile of BIA 5-1058, in Healthy Male Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double-blind, Randomised, Placebo-controlled, Combined Single and Multiple Ascending Dose Study to Investigate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetic, Including Food Interaction, and Pharmacodynamic Profile of BIA 5-1058, in Healthy Male Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bial - Portela C S.A.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bial - Portela C S.A.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Netherlands: The Central Committee on Research Involving Human Subjects (CCMO)</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to to assess the safety and tolerability of BIA 5 1058 after
      single and multiple oral doses
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This was a Phase 1, double blind, randomised, placebo-controlled combined single ascending
      dose (SAD), including food interaction (food effect, FE) analysis, and multiple ascending
      dose (MAD) study.

      The SAD part consisted of 9 groups of 8 healthy young male subjects each receiving an oral
      single dose (SD) of BIA 5-1058 or placebo (6 verum and 2 placebo); in the first group, 2
      subjects (1 verum and 1 placebo) were dosed 24 h before the remaining 6 subjects (5 verum
      and 1 placebo). If the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) had not been reached after completing
      the 8 originally planned sequential groups, additional groups could be included to a maximum
      of 12 sequential groups in total. Although the MTD was not reached, it was deemed sufficient
      by the Sponsor to include only 1 additional group. The FE part consisted of 12 healthy young
      male subjects each receiving a single dose of BIA 5 1058 in either the fed or fasted state
      in an open-label, two-way crossover design. Each treatment was separated by at least 7 days.
      The MAD part consisted of 5 groups of 8 young healthy male subjects each receiving an oral
      dose of BIA 5 1058 or placebo (6 verum and 2 placebo) once-daily (QD) for 10 days. If the
      MTD had not been reached after completing the 4 sequential groups originally planned,
      additional groups could be included to a maximum of 8 sequential groups in total. Although
      the MTD was not reached, it was deemed sufficient by the Sponsor to include only 1
      additional group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Nº of Adverse Events (AEs) reported per participant</measure>
    <time_frame>throughout the study (until 72 h after (last) drug administration)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Just before drug administration and twice daily until 72 h after (last) drug administration, subjects were asked non-leading questions to determine the occurrence of AEs. Subjects were asked in general terms about any AEs at regular intervals during each study period. In addition, all AEs reported spontaneously during the course of the study were recorded. All answers were assessed by the MI, coded using the Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities (MedDRA; Version 14.0) and recorded in the AEs Record. The intensity of the AEs was rated as &quot;mild&quot;, &quot;moderate&quot; or &quot;severe&quot; and the relationship between the AEs and the study medication was indicated as &quot;not related&quot;, &quot;unlikely&quot;, &quot;possible&quot;, &quot;probable&quot; or ''definite&quot;.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">124</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension and Chronic Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BIA 5-1058</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tablets</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>tablets, visually matching active medication</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BIA 5-1058</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>BIA 5-1058</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Subjects were eligible for the study if they met all the following inclusion criteria:

          -  Gender -  male

          -  Age - 18 - 55 years, inclusive

          -  Body Mass Index (BMI) - 18.0 - 30.0 kg m2 (BMI (kg m2) = Body weight (kg) - Heigh t2
             (m 2))

          -  Ability and willingness to abstain from alcohol, methylxanthine-containing beverages
             or food (coffee, tea, cola, chocolate, power drinks), grapefruit (juice) and tobacco
             products from 48 h prior to entry in the clinical research centre until discharge

          -  Medical history without major pathology

          -  Normal resting supine blood pressure and pulse rate showing no clinically relevant
             deviations as judged by the MI

          -  Computerised (12-lead) ECG recording without signs of clinically relevant pathology
             or showing no clinically relevant deviations as judged by the MI

          -  All values for haematology and for clinical chemistry tests of blood and urine within
             the normal range or showing no clinically relevant deviations as judged by the MI

          -  Willingness to sign the written ICF

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects were excluded from participation if any of the following exclusion criteria
        applied

          -  Any significant cardiovascular (e.g. hypertension), hepatic, renal, respiratory (e.g.
             childhood asthma), gastrointestinal, endocrine (e.g. diabetes, dyslipidemia),
             immunologic, haematological, neurologic, or psychiatric disease

          -  An automatic ECG QTc interval reading at screening or enrolment of + 440 ms.

          -  Evidence of clinically relevant pathology

          -  Mental handicap

          -  History of relevant drug and or food allergies

          -  Smoking more than 10 cigarettes and or cigars and or pipes daily

          -  History of alcohol abuse or drug addiction (including soft drugs like cannabis
             products)

          -  Use of any prescription drug within 30 days before study drug administration with the
             exception of influenza vaccination

          -  Use of any over-the-counter drugs including health supplements, herbal supplements
             such as St. John's Wort extract (except for the occasional use of acetaminophen
             (paracetamol), aspirin and vitamins - 100  recommended daily allowance) within 7 days
             before study drug administration. The use of paracetamol and  or topical medication
             was allowed up to 3 days before entrance into the clinical research facility

          -  Participation in a drug study within 90 days prior to drug administration

          -  Participation in more than 3 other drug studies in the 10 months preceding the start
             of this study (this was the first administration of study drug)

          -  Donation of more than 50 mL of blood within 90 days prior to first drug
             administration

          -  Donation of more than 1.5 litres of blood in the 10 months preceding the start of
             this study (this was the first administration of study drug)

          -  Positive screen on drugs of abuse (opiates, methadone, cocaine, amphetamines,
             cannabinoids), barbiturates, benzodiazepines, tricyclic antidepressants and alcohol

          -  Intake of more than 24 units of alcohol per week (1 unit of alcohol equals
             approximately 250 mL of beer, 100 mL of wine or 35 mL of spirits)

          -  Positive screen on hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg)

          -  Positive screen on anti hepatitis C virus (HCV)

          -  Positive screen on anti human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) 1 - 2

          -  Acute disease state indicated as clinically relevant by the MI (e.g. nausea,
             vomiting, fever, diarrhoea) within 7 days before the first drug administration

          -  Non-willingness to consume the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) breakfast (FE part
             only)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>PRA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zuidlaren</city>
        <zip>9471 GP</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 30, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 26, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>BIA 5-1058</keyword>
  <keyword>hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic heart failure</keyword>
  <keyword>cardiovascular disorders</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
