<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="119344">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01897870</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ZGA-1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01897870</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of a Pharmacist Home Visit on Drug-related Problems Post-discharge.</brief_title>
  <acronym>HomeCoMe</acronym>
  <official_title>The Effect of a Home-based Community Pharmacist-led Medication Management Program (HomeCoMe-program) Complementary to an In-hospital Medication Reconciliation Program on Drug-related Problems Post-discharge: A Prospective Cohort Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>H.T. Ensing, PharmD, MSc</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Zorggroep Almere</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Flevoziekenhuis, Almere</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Zorggroep Almere</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Netherlands: Medical Ethics Review Committee (METC)</authority>
    <authority>Netherlands: The Central Committee on Research Involving Human Subjects (CCMO)</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      the purpose of this study is to determine the the effect of a home-based medication
      management program on drug-related problems post-discharge.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Inaccuracy of medication histories and lack of knowledge on actual medication use results in
      confusion about medication regimens and medication mismanagement before- during - and after
      hospital admission. This phenomenon accounts for many readmissions, longer duration of
      admission and preventable and serious Adverse Drug Events (ADEs) as a result of Drug Related
      Problems (DRPs). Several studies show that discharge medication reconciliation (MR) and
      counseling by a pharmacy employee reduces the amount of discrepancies in the discharge
      prescription lists. Still, no unequivocal effect of MR on the occurrence of DRPs after
      discharge has been shown. This is due to a shift in underlying potential harmful
      discrepancies from mainly patient based (unintended nonadherence) to mainly system based (eg
      dispensing errors) and might be explained by (1) suboptimal transfer of information (2) an
      overload of information during a stressful situation and (3) difficulty to implement changes
      in medication at home. Therefore the reduction of DRPs, improvement of patients' medication
      knowledge and initial adherence can probably most effectively be addressed in a multifaceted
      integrated transmural intervention. Repetition of important information is the key to
      success. Moreover, the first weeks following hospital discharge are most crucial in
      preventing drug-related problems as patients could slip back in old medication schemes, or
      new problems may arise, such as emerging ADEs due to medication changes made during
      hospitalization.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Identifying and solving adverse drug events (ADEs) and other drug-related problems (DRPs) post-discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>within 7 days post-discharge</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The total number of assessed and solved ADEs post-discharge will be measured. Assessing and solving ADEs takes place during the pharmacist home visit.
Using START-STOPP criteria on patients medication records, ADEs will also be compared between the intervention and usual care group.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement of adherence to medication at hospital discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months after discharge</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The &quot;medication possession ratio&quot; will be calculated retrospectively from pharmacy dispensing data after 6 months to investigate patient's adherence and compared between the intervention and control group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient assessment of medication knowledge at time of home visit</measure>
    <time_frame>within 7 days after discharge</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>At time of the home visit patients are asked about their knowledge (e.g. indication, dose regime, etc) regarding the medication they are taking. Knowledge is scored and lack of knowledge is solved by teaching the patient.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Types of interventions made at the pharmacist home visit</measure>
    <time_frame>within 7 days after discharge</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The types of intervention the pharmacist works on during the 7 day follow-up home visit are assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction with the pharmacist home visit</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after receiving the home visit</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The satisfaction survey consists of 13 interview questions, where the subject subjectively scores each question on a four-point scale, developed specifically for this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of patient reported health rating</measure>
    <time_frame>at 14 days after discharge</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient are asked by telephone to report their health on a scale from 1 (worst imaginable health) to 10 (best imaginable health). Number are compared between the intervention and control group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>General practitioners satisfaction with the pharmacist home visit</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after the home visit is executed</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The satisfaction survey consists of 13 interview questions, where the subject subjectively scores each question on a four-point scale, developed specifically for this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of patient reported health rating</measure>
    <time_frame>at 42 days after discharge</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient are asked by telephone to report their health on a scale from 1 (worst imaginable health) to 10 (best imaginable health). Number are compared between the intervention and control group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">675</enrollment>
  <condition>Adverse Drug Event</condition>
  <condition>Patient Readmission</condition>
  <condition>Patient Compliance</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HomeCoMe-program group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>the arm receiving the pharmacist home visit</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual care group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>the arm receiving usual pharmacy care</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HomeCoMe-program</intervention_name>
    <description>A home visit by patients own community pharmacist within seven days after hospital discharge. The community pharmacist will perform a semi-structured interview on (1) actual use of the prescribed medication regimen, (2) possible ADEs and other DRPs, (3) adherence issues, to embed the patient's new medication situation in his or her life, by (a) assessing patient's needs, beliefs and wishes around his pharmacotherapy, (b) identifying and solving obstacles for medicines intake, (c) checking on the need for a compliance aid, coming to an agreement with the patient on introduction (if needed), (d) collecting spare medication with a check on dispensation date, expiration date and cause for discontinuation (e.g. due to a side effect being not reported to the prescriber) and finally (4) knowledge on medication use, when to take which medicine and why, and medication changes made during the hospitalisation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>HomeCoMe-program group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patient uses more than three prescribed systemic drugs intended for chronic use at
             admission and discharge

          -  patient has an expected length of stay of 48 hours or longer

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients admitted for scheduled chemotherapy

          -  Patients admitted for radiation therapy

          -  Patients admitted for transplantation

          -  Patients transferred from another hospital

          -  Patients transferred from another non-eligible ward within the same hospital

          -  No informed consent signed

          -  A live expectancy less than 6 months

          -  Inability to be counselled (e.g. cognitive dysfunction, language constraints who
             cannot be solved with an interpreter)

          -  Discharge to a nursing home (presuming dependence on medication administration)

          -  If patients' community pharmacy is not participating in this study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marcel L Bouvy, Prof, PharmD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UIPS</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hendrik T Ensing, PharmD, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>+31365454378</phone>
    <email>rensing@zorggroep-almere.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Zorgapotheken Flevoland</name>
      <address>
        <city>Almere</city>
        <state>Flevoland</state>
        <zip>1315RA</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hendrik T Ensing, PharmD, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>+31365454378</phone>
      <email>rensing@zorggroep-almere.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hendrik T Ensing, PharmD, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schnipper JL, Kirwin JL, Cotugno MC, Wahlstrom SA, Brown BA, Tarvin E, Kachalia A, Horng M, Roy CL, McKean SC, Bates DW. Role of pharmacist counseling in preventing adverse drug events after hospitalization. Arch Intern Med. 2006 Mar 13;166(5):565-71.</citation>
    <PMID>16534045</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Al-Rashed SA, Wright DJ, Roebuck N, Sunter W, Chrystyn H. The value of inpatient pharmaceutical counselling to elderly patients prior to discharge. Br J Clin Pharmacol. 2002 Dec;54(6):657-64.</citation>
    <PMID>12492615</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kwint HF, Faber A, Gussekloo J, Bouvy ML. The contribution of patient interviews to the identification of drug-related problems in home medication review. J Clin Pharm Ther. 2012 Dec;37(6):674-80. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2710.2012.01370.x. Epub 2012 Aug 3.</citation>
    <PMID>22861493</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 11, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 2, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Zorggroep Almere</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>H.T. Ensing, PharmD, MSc</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PharmD, MSc</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>continuity of care</keyword>
  <keyword>medicines management</keyword>
  <keyword>home visit</keyword>
  <keyword>drug-related problems</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Drug Toxicity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
