<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="112610">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01886066</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-0257-C</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01886066</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Accuracy of Sentinel Lymph Node Biopsy and Gadofosveset-Enhanced MR in Nodal Staging of High Risk Endometrial Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>Ablavar</acronym>
  <official_title>Accuracy of Sentinel Lymph Node Biopsy and Gadofosveset-Enhanced MR in Nodal Staging of High Risk Endometrial Cancer: A Prospective Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Health Network, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Health Network, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: University Health Network Research Ethics Board</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The standard of care for women with high risk endometrial cancer is the removal of all
      visible lymph nodes in the pelvis and lower abdomen to identify if disease has spread to
      these areas. It is estimated that no more than 25% of all women with presumed early stage
      high risk endometrial cancer will have positive lymph nodes however currently the majority
      of women are subjected to extensive resection of all pelvic lymph and or para-aortic lymph
      nodes and its associated morbidities. The objective of this study is to determine if the
      combination of preoperative MR imaging with intraoperative sentinel lymph node (SLN) mapping
      will improve the assessment of regional lymph nodes and enhance the detection of lymph nodes
      with metastatic disease in endometrial cancer. This would benefit the majority of women with
      early stage high risk endometrial cancer and would prevent the associated complications of
      pelvic lymph node dissection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      If the SLN can be accurately identified and the detection of metastatic lymph nodes in women
      with early stage high risk endometrial cancer can be improved then the majority of women
      could avoid a complete systematic pelvic lymphadenectomy. Pelvic lymphadenectomy is
      associated with many intraoperative and postoperative complications such as hemorrhage,
      lymphocyst formation, nerve injury and chronic lower extremity lymphedema.  If less invasive
      techniques to assess regional lymph node involvement, such as preoperative imaging
      techniques and SLN mapping, replaced routine pelvic lymphadenectomy the complications
      associated with more extensive pelvic surgery could be avoided.

      This will be a prospective cohort study. The population to be studied will be patients with
      newly diagnosed early stage high risk endometrial cancer who will undergo primary surgical
      intervention that includes hysterectomy and bilateral pelvic and inframesenteric para-aortic
      lymphadenectomy via laparotomy, laparoscopy or robotic-assisted. Patients will have a
      preoperative Gadofoveset trisodium (Ablavar)-enhanced MRI within 4 weeks of their surgery.
      On the morning of surgery, preoperative injection of a radiolabeled colloid will occur in
      the Nuclear Medicine Dept. All patients will have preoperative SPECT/CT performed for
      preoperative mapping.  Patients will be taken to the operating room for their planned
      procedure.  After initiation of general anesthesia, blue dye will be injected into the
      patient's cervix. The surgery will proceed and all lymph nodes that are &quot;blue&quot; and/or &quot;hot&quot;
      will be removed surgically and their anatomic location and laterality documented. The
      hysterectomy and lymphadenectomy will then be performed.  The SLN status will be compared to
      the status of the other nodes removed at complete lymphadenectomy.  All data on these
      patients will be prospectively collected.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Performance Analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Year 3</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Performance analyses of SLN and Ablavar-enhanced MR will be performed. In particular, sensitivity, specificity, and predictive accuracy of SLN and Ablavar-enhanced MRI in the mapping and detection of lymph nodes with metastatic disease will be calculated using the pathology results of the surgical intervention as the Standard of Reference. Performance analyses will be evaluated at both the lesion and patient level. Generalized estimating equations will be used to adjust for correlations of repeated measures within patients.  Raw performance estimates will be reported with adjusted 95% confidence intervals.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>High Grade Endometrial Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Sentinel Lymph Node Mapping</condition>
  <condition>Ablavar</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gadofosveset Trisodium (Ablavar)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ablavar (Gadofosveset Trisodium) will be used as an MRI contrast agent to identify metastatic lymph nodes prior to surgery. The contrast agent solution will be administered intravenously at a dose of 0.12mL/kg bodyweight.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gadofosveset Trisodium (Ablavar)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Gadofosveset Trisodium (Ablavar)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women with endometrial cancer with high risk histologic subtypes including
             carcinosarcoma, grade 3 endometrioid, serous, clear cell, undifferentiated
             adenocarcinoma

          -  Clinical stage 1 disease- no evidence of metastatic disease beyond the uterus by
             physical exam or preoperative imaging if  performed.

          -  Patients who have signed an approved informed consent.

          -  Patients who will undergo surgery that includes a abdominal hysterectomy and
             bilateral pelvic and inframesenteric para-aortic lymphadenectomy via laparotomy,
             laparoscopy or robotic-assisted.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with evidence of metastatic disease on preoperative imaging.

          -  Patients with evidence of intraperitoneal metastatic disease intraoperatively
             (patients with suspicious retroperitoneal lymph nodes intraoperatively will still be
             included).

          -  Patients with known allergy to triphenylmethane compounds.

          -  Contraindications for MRI: The contraindications for MR are as per departmental
             safety guidelines. Specifically patients with cardiac pacemaker, cochlear implants,
             insulin pumps, nerve stimulators, lead wires, prosthetic heart valves or haemostatic
             clips will be excluded.

          -  Contraindications for contrast (Gadovosfeset trisodium):

               1. History of a prior allergic reaction to a gadolinium-based contrast agent.

               2. High risk for nephrogenic systemic fibrosis. The precautions as per  routine
                  departmental protocol for use of Gadolinium-based contrast agent  will be
                  applied (For the purpose of this study, patients with eGFR less  than 30 will be
                  excluded from the study).

               3. Patients with documented prolonged QTc.

          -  Pregnant patient.

          -  Patients with previous retroperitoneal surgery.

          -  Patients with previous history of pelvic/abdominal radiation.

          -  Patients with recurrent endometrial cancer.

          -  Any patient treated with neoadjuvant chemotherapy and/or radiation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sarah Ferguson, MD</last_name>
    <phone>416-946-4501</phone>
    <phone_ext>6597</phone_ext>
    <email>Sarah.Ferguson@uhn.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Safia Nazarali</last_name>
    <phone>416-946-4501</phone>
    <phone_ext>3969</phone_ext>
    <email>Safia.Nazarali@uhn.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Health Network - Princess Margaret Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5T 2M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sarah Ferguson, MD</last_name>
      <phone>416-946-4501</phone>
      <phone_ext>6597</phone_ext>
      <email>Sarah.Ferguson@uhn.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Safia Nazarali</last_name>
      <phone>416-946-4501</phone>
      <phone_ext>3969</phone_ext>
      <email>Safia.Nazarali@uhn.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M4N3M5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Danielle Vicus, MD</last_name>
      <phone>416-480-4378</phone>
      <phone_ext>4026</phone_ext>
      <email>danielle.vicus@sunnybrook.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 20, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 20, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Health Network, Toronto</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Safia Nazarali</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Research Associate</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Endometrial cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Sentinel lymph node</keyword>
  <keyword>Ablavar</keyword>
  <keyword>Sentinel lymph node mapping</keyword>
  <keyword>Sentinel lymph node identification</keyword>
  <keyword>Technetium</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Endometrial Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma, Endometrial Stromal</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
