<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="164864">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01961297</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GCO 09-1156</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01961297</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Voice Tremor in Spasmodic Dysphonia: Central Mechanisms and Treatment Response</brief_title>
  <official_title>Voice Tremor in Spasmodic Dysphonia: Central Mechanisms and Treatment Response</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kristina Simonyan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed research aims to determine brain abnormalities in patients with spasmodic
      dysphonia (SD) and voice tremor (VT) as the basis for characterization of central mechanisms
      underlying symptom improvement following the use of sodium oxybate, a novel oral medication
      for the treatment of ethanol-responsive dystonia. The proposed research is relevant to
      public health because the elucidation of disorder-specific mechanistic aspects of brain
      organization in SD vs. SD/VT is ultimately expected to lead to establishment of enhanced
      criteria for clinical management of these disorders, including differential diagnosis and
      treatment. Thus, the proposed research is relevant to the part of NIH's mission that
      pertains to developing fundamental knowledge that will help to reduce the burdens of human
      disability.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Spasmodic dysphonia (SD) is a chronic debilitating condition, characterized by selective
      loss of voluntary voice control during speech production due to uncontrolled spasms in the
      laryngeal muscles. SD becomes even more incapacitating when it is associated with
      action-induced voice tremor (VT) due to its poor response to gold standard treatment with
      botulinum toxin. There is, therefore, a critical need to identify new treatment
      opportunities for SD/VT patients who receive limited, if any, benefits from botulinum toxin
      injections. The design and use of novel therapeutic approaches for these patients will,
      however, be largely unattainable if the central mechanisms of SD and VT development remain
      unknown. Our long-term goal is to determine the pathophysiology of SD and related disorders,
      such as VT, for the development of new diagnostic and treatment options for these patients.
      The objective of this application is to identify brain abnormalities in SD and SD/VT
      patients as the basis for characterization of central mechanisms underlying symptom
      improvement following the use of sodium oxybate, a novel pharmacological agent for treatment
      of ethanol-responsive dystonia. Our central hypothesis is that, compared to SD patients,
      SD/VT patients will have additional brain abnormalities within the sensorimotor brain
      circuits controlling voice production, which are being modulated to a greater extent with
      sodium oxybate treatment. We further postulate that clinical efficacy of sodium oxybate
      treatment will correlate with its central modulatory effects. The rationale for the proposed
      research is that identification of distinct brain mechanisms underlying SD and SD/VT
      clinical manifestations would provide the necessary insights into the pathophysiology of
      these disorders, while understanding the neural correlates of sodium oxybate action would
      allow establishment of a scientific rationale for the use of a novel treatment in these
      disorders. Using a comprehensive approach of multi-modal neuroimaging and clinico-behavioral
      testing, our central hypothesis will be tested by pursuing two specific aims: (1) determine
      disorder-specific brain abnormalities in SD and SD/VT patients, and (2) characterize the
      central effects of sodium oxybate treatment in ethanol-responsive SD and SD/VT patients.
      This research is innovative because it focuses not only on identification of distinct
      pathophysiological factors contributing to SD and VT development, but also on discovery of
      mechanisms of central effects of a novel oral medication, sodium oxybate, which holds
      promise for treatment of refractory symptoms in SD and SD/VT. The proposed research is
      significant because it will advance our understanding of the pathophysiology of dystonia in
      general and SD in particular as well as will have direct impact on improvement of clinical
      management of SD and SD/VT patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Brain Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Central effects of sodium oxybate in improvement of voice symptoms in spasmodic dysphonia and voice tremor as measured by brain activity with MRI</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">95</enrollment>
  <condition>Spasmodic Dysphonia</condition>
  <condition>Voice Tremor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sodium oxybate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oral administration of a single dose of sodium oxybate (0.75-2.0 gm)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sodium oxybate</intervention_name>
    <description>Sodium oxybate</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sodium oxybate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Xyrem</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinically documented diagnosis of SD and/or VT with positive effects of alcohol on
             their symptoms;

          -  Age from 21 to 80 years;

          -  Native English speakers;

          -  Right-handedness (based on Edinburgh Handedness Inventory).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who are incapable of giving an informed consent;

          -  Pregnant and breastfeeding women until a time when they are no longer pregnant or
             breastfeeding will be excluded from the study. All patients of childbearing potential
             will be required to agree to use a reliable method of contraception prior and during
             the treatment with sodium oxybate and prior to receiving botulinum toxin. The method
             of contraception will be documented in the patient's research chart. All women of
             childbearing potential will undergo a urine pregnancy test, which must be negative
             for study participation;

          -  Subjects with past or present medical history of

               1. any neurological disorders, except for spasmodic dysphonia and voice tremor,
                  will be excluded from the study in order to maintain the homogenous patient
                  population, allow for the evaluation of drug effect on CNS without confounding
                  by the presence of other neurological conditions, and identify SD and VT
                  disorder-specific changes in brain function and structure. Patients who report
                  other past or present neurological problems, such as stroke, movement disorders
                  other than SD and VT, brain tumors, traumatic brain injury with loss of
                  consciousness, ataxias, myopathies, myasthenia gravis, demyelinating diseases,
                  alcoholism, drug dependence will be excluded. As voice tremor is one of the
                  forms of essential tremor, patients with moderate to severe essential tremor
                  affecting other body parts will be excluded from the study. All patients who
                  have dystonic movements in other than larynx body regions will also be excluded
                  from the study;

               2. psychiatric problems, such as schizophrenia, major and/or bipolar depression,
                  obsessive-compulsive disorder, will be excluded to maintain the homogenous
                  patient population, allow for the evaluation of drug effect on CNS without
                  confounding by the presence of psychiatric conditions and identify
                  disorder-specific changes in brain function and structure;

               3. laryngeal problems, such as vocal fold paralysis, paresis, vocal fold nodules
                  and polyps, carcinoma, chronic laryngitis;

               4. known past or present history of grade 2 or higher hepatic and renal dysfunction
                  according to the NCI criteria.;

               5. known past or present history of moderate to severe congestive heart failure;

               6. known past or present history of cognitive impairment and active suicidal
                  ideations;

          -  Patients who are not symptomatic due to treatment with botulinum toxin injections
             into the laryngeal muscles. The duration of positive effects of botulinum toxin vary
             from patient to patient but lasts on average for 3-4 months. All patients will be
             evaluated to ensure that they are fully symptomatic prior to the entering the study,
             except the substudy, which will examine the effects of combined botulinum toxin and
             sodium oxybate treatments on abnormal brain function in SD and VT patients;

          -  To avoid the possibility of confounding effects of drugs acting upon the central
             nervous system, all study participants will be questioned about any prescribed or
             over-the-counter medications as part of their initial intake screening. Those
             patients who receive medication(s) affecting the central nervous system (except
             sodium oxybate) will be excluded from the study.

          -  The participants will be asked whether they have undergone any head and neck
             surgeries, particularly any brain surgery and laryngeal surgeries, such as
             thyroplasty, laryngeal denervation, and selective laryngeal adductor
             denervation-reinnervation. Because both brain and laryngeal surgery may potentially
             lead to the brain structure and function re-organization, all subjects with history
             of brain and/or laryngeal surgery will be excluded from the study.

          -  The subjects who have tattoos, ferromagnetic objects in their bodies (e.g., implanted
             stimulators, surgical clips, prosthesis, artificial heart valve, etc.) that cannot be
             removed for the purpose of MRI study participation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kristina Simonyan, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kristina Simonyan, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>212-241-0656</phone>
    <email>kristina.simonyan@mssm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kristina Simonyan, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steven J Frucht, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Simonyan K, Frucht SJ. Long-term Effect of Sodium Oxybate (Xyrem®) in Spasmodic Dysphonia with Vocal Tremor. Tremor Other Hyperkinet Mov (N Y). 2013 Dec 9;3. pii: tre-03-206-4731-1. eCollection 2013.</citation>
    <PMID>24386608</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 15, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 9, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kristina Simonyan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>dystonia</keyword>
  <keyword>tremor</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>sodium oxybate</keyword>
  <keyword>brain activity</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Tremor</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dysphonia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Sodium Oxybate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
