<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="29991">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01756417</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR013636</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>28431754NAP1004</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01756417</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Investigate Whether Pharmacokinetic and Pharmacodynamic Interactions Exist Between Metformin and Canagliflozin (JNJ-28431754) in Healthy Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label, Fixed Sequence, Single and Multiple Dose Study in Male and Female Subjects to Investigate the Potential for Pharmacokinetic and Pharmacodynamic Interaction Between Metformin and JNJ-28431754</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate whether there is a drug-drug interaction between
      multiple doses of canagliflozin (JNJ-28431754) and a single dose of metformin. The safety
      and tolerability of canagliflozin will also be assessed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is an open-label (all volunteers and study staff know the identity of the
      assigned treatment), fixed sequence (all volunteers receive the same medication on the same
      days), single and multiple-dose study to determine how metformin (a blood glucose-lowering
      agent used to treat patients with diabetes) affects the pharmacokinetics (ie, how the body
      affects the drug) and the pharmacodynamics (ie, how the drug affects the body) of
      canagliflozin (a drug currently being investigated for the treatment of type 2 diabetes
      mellitus). The effect of canagliflozin on the pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of
      metformin will also be evaluated. The study will consist of 3 phases: a screening phase, an
      open-label treatment phase, and an end-of-study (or follow-up) phase. Each volunteer will
      participate in the study for approximately 39 days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics/Dynamics Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The maximum plasma concentration (Cmax) of canagliflozin (JNJ-28431754)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Cmax (a measure of the body's exposure to canagliflozin [JNJ-28431754]) will be compared before and after administration of a single dose of metformin.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC) for canagliflozin (JNJ-28431754)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>AUC (a measure of the body's exposure to canagliflozin [JNJ-28431754]) will be compared before and after administration of a single dose of metformin.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The maximum plasma concentration (Cmax) of metformin</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Cmax (a measure of the body's exposure to metformin will be compared before and after administration of multiple doses of canagliflozin (JNJ-28431754).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC) for metformin</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>AUC (a measure of the body's exposure to metformin will be compared before and after administration of multiple doses of canagliflozin (JNJ-28431754).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>24-hour urine glucose excretion</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 10</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>24-hour urine glucose excretion will be compared following a single dose of metformin, multiple doses of canagliflozin (JNJ-28431754), or multiple doses of canagliflozin in combination with a single dose of metformin.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>24-hour area under the serum glucose concentration-time curve</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>24-hour area under the serum glucose concentration-time curve will be compared following a single dose of metformin, multiple doses of canagliflozin (JNJ-28431754), or multiple doses of canagliflozin in combination with a single dose of metformin.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of volunteers with adverse events as a measure of safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 18 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Metformin + canagliflozin (JNJ-28431754)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each volunteer will receive a single dose of metformin on Day 1 followed by canagliflozin (JNJ-28431754) once daily on Days 4 to 7. On Day 8, volunteers will receive a single dose of canagliflozin in combination with a single dose of metformin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metformin</intervention_name>
    <description>One 1,000 mg tablet of metformin taken orally (by mouth) on Day 1 and Day 8.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Metformin + canagliflozin (JNJ-28431754)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Canagliflozin (JNJ-28431754)</intervention_name>
    <description>Four 25 mg tablets of canagliflozin (JNJ-28431754) taken orally on Days 4 through 8.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Metformin + canagliflozin (JNJ-28431754)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>JNJ-28431754</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Volunteers must have a Body Mass Index (BMI [weight (kg) / height (m)2]) between 18.5
             and 35 kg/m2, inclusive

          -  Volunteers must be non-smokers or non-tobacco users

        Exclusion Criteria:

        - History of or currently active illness that the Investigator considers to be clinically
        significant and should exclude the volunteer from the study or that could interfere with
        the interpretation of the study results
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L. C. Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 26, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 20, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Healthy</keyword>
  <keyword>Canagliflozin (JNJ-28431754)</keyword>
  <keyword>Metformin</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacodynamics</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
