<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="87254">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01778751</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RRP 12-458</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01778751</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Advanced Comprehensive Diabetes Care for Veterans With Poorly-Controlled Diabetes</brief_title>
  <acronym>ACDC</acronym>
  <official_title>Advanced Comprehensive Diabetes Care for Veterans With Poorly-Controlled Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will determine whether Home Telehealth-based implementation of an evidence-based
      intervention targeting Veterans with persistent poorly-controlled diabetes can improve
      hemoglobin A1c, patient self-management, and comorbid depressive symptoms in this high-risk,
      high-cost population. If effective, this intervention (Advanced Comprehensive Diabetes Care)
      offers a feasible, sustainable, and generalizable approach to managing Veterans with
      persistent poorly-controlled diabetes, which can be implemented using only existing Home
      Telehealth services.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: Although efforts by VA providers and researchers have improved diabetes care
      quality for Veterans, individuals with persistent poorly-controlled diabetes mellitus (type
      1 or type 2 diabetes with hemoglobin A1c &gt;9.0% for &gt; 1 year despite receipt of medical care)
      have proven refractory to these widespread improvements, and remain at high risk for
      complications and accrued costs. Prior research has illustrated that medication regimen
      complexity, suboptimal self-care, and comorbid depressive symptoms interact to perpetuate
      suboptimal control among individuals with PPDM. Current models of clinic-based diabetes care
      do not meet these Veterans' needs. Without the implementation of care delivery strategies
      that target this population's unique barriers to improved diabetes control, these Veterans
      will continue to be left behind by progress in diabetes management throughout VA, and will
      remain at high risk for complications and high costs. We propose using existing local Home
      Telehealth services to implement Advanced Comprehensive Diabetes Care, a patient-centered,
      evidence-based intervention combining medication management, self-care behavior support, and
      depressive symptom management to Veterans with PPDM.

      Objectives:  The specific aims of this RRP are to: 1) evaluate the effectiveness of the
      Advanced Comprehensive Diabetes Care among Veterans with persistent poorly-controlled
      diabetes; 2) utilize a mixed method formative evaluation to assess our main implementation
      strategy, the use of existing Home Telehealth services to administer the intervention; and
      3) generate data we will use to refine local intervention implementation and inform the
      development of an SDP proposal evaluating broader implementation of the Advanced
      Comprehensive Diabetes Care intervention.

      Methods: We propose a pilot Effectiveness-Implementation Hybrid trial to study the Advanced
      Comprehensive Diabetes Care intervention in Veterans with persistent poorly-controlled
      diabetes. After baseline evaluation, 50 Veterans will be randomly assigned into intervention
      (n = 25) or control groups (n = 25). Veterans randomized to the intervention will be
      enrolled in the Home Telehealth program at Durham VAMC and will receive the study
      intervention (telehealth-based medication management, self-care behavior support, and
      depressive symptom management) for 6 months. Intervention-group Veterans with no depression
      on baseline assessment will not initially receive the depressive symptom management
      component, but will be monitored for new symptoms throughout the study. Veterans randomized
      to the control arm will receive diabetes educational materials and management per their
      primary provider. The primary effectiveness outcome for this study will be hemoglobin A1c.
      Secondary effectiveness outcomes will include measures of diabetes self-care, self-reported
      medication adherence, and depressive symptoms. This RRP will also include a mixed method
      formative evaluation to qualitatively and quantitatively assess patient-level,
      provider-level, and organizational barriers and facilitators influencing intervention
      implementation. Formative evaluation data will be analyzed during the study to consider
      whether adjustments to the intervention or its implementation may be indicated, and findings
      will also be used to inform future implementation efforts.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 0</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Diabetes Control</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in hemoglobin A1c from baseline to 6 months</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diabetes Self Care</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in Self-Care Inventory-revised from 0-6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported medication adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in Self-Reported Medication- Taking Scale from 0-6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in Patient Health Questionnaire from 0-6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Veterans will receive diabetes educational materials and management per their primary provider</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Veterans randomized to the intervention arm will be enrolled in the HT program, provided with standard telemonitoring equipment by HT nursing staff (current HT practice at DVAMC is use of the Health Buddy 3 device for patients with landline phones and the Cardiocom Interactive Voice Response System for patients with cell phones), and will receive the study intervention for 6 months. Veterans without depressive symptoms on baseline PHQ-9 assessment (PHQ-9 &lt; 10) will not initially be entered into the depressive symptom management component of the intervention, but will be monitored for new symptoms throughout the intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Home Telehealth with Behavioral Education Component</intervention_name>
    <description>The primary effectiveness outcome for this study will be hemoglobin A1c. Secondary effectiveness outcomes will include measures of diabetes self-care, self-reported medication adherence, and depressive symptoms.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Veterans with type 2 diabetes managed for &gt; 1 year at an eligible site (Durham,
             Raleigh, Greenville, or Morehead City) will be eligible for enrollment.

          -  We will identify Veterans with PPDM (defined as the presence of at least 2 A1c values
             of &gt; 9.0% during the past year with no readings of &lt; 9.0% despite ongoing medical
             care) by reviewing electronic medical records and soliciting referrals from primary
             physicians.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Exclusion criteria will include lack of telephone access or severe hearing/ speech
             impairment that would limit:

               -  telephone interaction

               -  metastatic cancer

               -  active psychosis documented in medical record

               -  active alcohol or substance abuse

               -  diagnosis of dementia

               -  known pregnancy (patients becoming pregnant during the study will be withdrawn
                  and referred to appropriate services)

               -  documented seizure history

               -  documented history of severe complications of hypoglycemia (such as coma or
                  seizure)

               -  documented refusal or inability to perform self-monitoring of blood glucose

               -  ongoing use of warfarin with prior history of major bleeding event

          -  Due to challenges with dose adjustment by phone, Veterans on continuous subcutaneous
             insulin infusion (insulin pumps) will not be eligible for this study.

               -  Due to challenges with regulations regarding testing supplies pts will need to
                  be taking insulin (a few patients had enrolled prior to this change.).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Matthew Crowley, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Medical Center, Durham</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Crowley MJ, Holleman R, Klamerus ML, Bosworth HB, Edelman D, Heisler M. Factors associated with persistent poorly controlled diabetes mellitus: Clues to improving management in patients with resistant poor control. Chronic Illn. 2014 Feb 24. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>24567193</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 20, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Self-Management Support</keyword>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Home Telehealth</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
