<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="4683">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01673802</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R11-153</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>117354</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01673802</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Role of Gadoxetate (Eovist) Enhanced CT in Evaluating Cholangiocarcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Role of Gadoxetate Enhanced Spectral Dual-Energy CT in Evaluating Hilar Cholangiocarcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alabama at Birmingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Society of Abdominal Radiology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alabama at Birmingham</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this project is to evaluate the role of gadoxetate (Eovist®) enhanced
      dual-energy CT in better evaluating perihilar cholangiocarcinoma.  This pilot project aims
      to address a long-term pitfall in the imaging of cholangiocarcinomas, by providing higher
      resolution delineation of these often infiltrative tumors on single-source, Dual-Energy
      Spectral Multi Detector CT (MDCT), capitalizing on improved spatial resolution achievable
      with MDCT compared to MRI and at the same time producing a non-invasive CT cholangiogram to
      aid in accurate diagnosis and treatment planning of cholangiocarcinoma, particularly, the
      hilar variety.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this project is to evaluate the role of gadoxetate (Eovist) enhanced
      dual-energy CT in better evaluating perihilar cholangiocarcinoma, by exploiting the
      combination of the physiologic behavior of gadoxetate in liver tissue combined with the
      advantageous mass attenuation coefficient of Gadolinium achievable through dual energy
      technique. This combination of unique CT imaging sensitivity, high resolution and
      differential enhancement potentially allows improved visualization and detection of tumor
      relative to enhancing surrounding hepatic parenchyma and ductal anatomy in the hepatobiliary
      phase, due to the biliary excretion of the agent.

      Cholangiocarcinoma is a hepatic adenocarcinoma that arises from the bile duct epithelium and
      is the second most prevalent liver cancer after hepatocellular carcinoma. The hilar
      intrahepatic variety of cholangiocarcinoma can present as an infiltrative, exophytic, or
      polypoid lesion. Most extra-hepatic cholangiocarcinomas are infiltrative, causing a focal
      stricture of the bile duct and result in proximal biliary ductal dilatation.

      While magnetic resonance (MR) cholangiography is diagnostic in the majority of patients with
      malignant hilar strictures, evaluation is limited by spatial resolution and in some
      patients, the inability to have an MRI scan. Standard Multi Detector CT (MDCT) using
      iodinated contrast agents, on the other hand, is limited in evaluation of
      cholangiocarcinomas, due to the lack of consistent enhancement of the tumor with iodinated
      contrast.

      Single-source, Dual-Energy (SSDE) Spectral MDCT utilizes a single fast switching x-ray beam
      source to acquire near simultaneous data sets at two different photon energies during a
      single acquisition. Data is acquired at 80 kilovolt peak (kVp) and 140 kVp with image
      reconstruction achievable as a selectable monochromatic presentation over a range of 40 -
      140 kiloelectron volt (keV), typically 70-78 keV for diagnostic image presentation. At lower
      tube voltage, the frequency of photoelectric interactions increases exponentially and is
      strongly dependent on the atomic number. Therefore, for substances with higher atomic
      number, such as iodine and gadolinium the increased frequency of photoelectric and k-edge
      interactions at low tube voltage substantially increases CT attenuation, thus improving
      contrast. Gadolinium is further unique with k-edge attenuation at approximately 53 keV,
      within the available monochromatic reconstruction range, thus allowing for significant
      greater detectability. Additional material decomposition technique allows for unique
      material presentation and analysis such as gadolinium/ water pair analysis with high spatial
      resolution.

      Dual-Energy technology is limited by the types of contrast agents currently available, all
      based on Iodine. Gadoxetate (Eovist) is a relatively new Gadolinium based MRI contrast agent
      that is capable of producing not only standard appearing MRI images in the hepatic arterial
      and portal venous phases, but also provides an opportunity to better visualize the bile
      ducts and liver parenchyma as it is excreted by the liver into the biliary system during the
      hepatobiliary phase.

      This pilot project aims to address a long-term pitfall in the imaging of
      cholangiocarcinomas, by providing higher resolution delineation of these often infiltrative
      tumors on single-source, Dual-Energy Spectral MDCT, capitalizing on improved spatial
      resolution achievable with MDCT compared to MRI and at the same time producing a
      non-invasive CT cholangiogram to aid in accurate diagnosis and treatment planning of
      cholangiocarcinoma, particularly, the hilar variety.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 0</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To obtain bi-directional measurements of  hilar cholangiocarcinoma tumor in centimeters, on the Dual Energy CT scan images.</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">43</enrollment>
  <condition>Cholangiocarcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CT imaging</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will undergo a standard of care Gadoxetate (Eovist) MRI for cholangiocarcinoma.  Patients will then be immediately placed on the CT scanner.  Patients will undergo a dual energy CT of the abdomen with no additional contrast.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CT scan</intervention_name>
    <description>Gadoxetate (Eovist) enhanced dual energy CT</description>
    <arm_group_label>CT imaging</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Dual Energy CT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects will be adult (age 19 or older) with suspected cholangiocarcinoma of the
             liver.

          2. Subject must be able to provide a written informed consent.

          3. Subject will be scheduled for gadoxetate contrast enhanced MRI scan of the liver
             (obtained as part of usual clinical practice).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Standard MRI safety screening criteria will be employed, and subject will be excluded
             if any contraindications to undergo MRI are met.

          2. Subjects with metallic biliary stents or multiple peripancreatic surgical clips on
             abdominal MDCT will be excluded.

          3. Subjects on hemodialysis or with glomerular filtration rate (GFR) less than 30 will
             be excluded.

          4. Subjects will not be excluded on the basis of gender, race, ethnicity, or religion.

          5. Subject may not be pregnant or lactating.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John V Thomas, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>John V Thomas, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(205) 975-4559</phone>
    <email>jvthomas@uabmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Stefanie Robinson</last_name>
    <phone>(205) 934-6499</phone>
    <email>syrobinson@uabmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alabama at Birmingham</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stefanie Y Robinson</last_name>
      <phone>205-934-6499</phone>
      <email>syrobinson@uabmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Marianne Vetrano, RN</last_name>
      <phone>(205) 934-4080</phone>
      <email>mvetrano@uabmc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John V Thomas, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Desiree E Morgan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David N Bolus, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lincoln L Berland, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 30, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 13, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>John V. Thomas</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cholangiocarcinoma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cholangiocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Klatskin's Tumor</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
