<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="18201">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01737710</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DAIT ADRN-05</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01737710</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Atopic Dermatitis Research Network (ADRN) Influenza Vaccine Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Open Label Mechanistic Study in Atopic Dermatitis to Assess the Immunogenicity of Fluzone® Intradermal and Intramuscular Vaccines</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Atopic Dermatitis Research Network (ADRN)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Atopic dermatitis, also called eczema, is a disease in which the skin is dry and scaly with
      severe itching. People who have atopic dermatitis often have complications from skin
      infections; these can include eczema herpeticum after herpes simplex virus infection or
      eczema vaccinatum after smallpox vaccination. People with atopic dermatitis may suffer from
      skin infections and may therefore respond differently to vaccinations.

      A new flu vaccine which is injected into the skin instead of into muscle has recently been
      approved by the Food and Drug Administration for vaccination of the general population
      including patients with atopic dermatitis. This new vaccine has been shown to work as well
      as the vaccine which is injected into muscle when tested in people without atopic
      dermatitis. The main purpose of this study is to compare how people with atopic dermatitis
      respond to this new flu vaccine compared to non-atopic volunteers without atopic dermatitis.
      The second purpose is to look at how people with atopic dermatitis respond to the new
      vaccine which is injected into the skin compared to the vaccine which is injected into
      muscle.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The difference in proportion of participants achieving seroprotection for each influenza strain between non-atopic controls and moderate to severe atopic dermatitis AD participants following intradermal vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28 post vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Seroprotection is defined as a post-vaccination serum HAI (hemagglutinin inhibition) antibody titer of 1:40 or greater. Fisher exact test will be used to examine the difference in rates of seroprotection between different groups of vaccine participants.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The fold difference in geometric mean titers for each influenza strain between non-atopic controls and AD participants following intradermal vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28 post vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Antibody levels to HA (hemagglutinin) measured in the serum. Higher antibody levels suggest better protection against the influenza virus.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The difference in proportion of participants achieving seroprotection for each influenza strain between AD participants receiving intradermal vaccination and AD participants receiving intramuscular vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28 post vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Seroprotection is defined as a post-vaccination serum HAI (hemagglutinin inhibition) antibody titer of 1:40 or greater. Fisher exact test will be used to examine the difference in rates of seroprotection between different groups of vaccine participants.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The difference in proportion of participants achieving seroconversion for each influenza strain between non-atopic controls and moderate to severe AD participants receiving intradermal vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28 post vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Seroconversion is defined as a 4-fold increase from baseline HAI (hemagglutinin inhibition) antibody titer. Fisher exact test will be used to examine the difference in rates of Seroconversion between different groups of vaccine participants.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The difference in proportion of participants achieving seroconversion for each influenza strain between AD participants receiving intradermal vaccination and AD participants receiving intramuscular vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28 post vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Seroconversion is defined as a 4-fold increase from baseline HAI (hemagglutinin inhibition) antibody titer. Fisher exact test will be used to examine the difference in rates of Seroconversion between different groups of vaccine participants.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">316</enrollment>
  <condition>Dermatitis, Atopic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>92 Nnon-atopic controls vaccinated with Fluzone® Intradermal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Non-atopic controls who will receive a single dose of the seasonal 2012-2013 Fluzone® Intradermal influenza vaccine via a single-dose pre-filled microinjection system (0.1mL).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Moderate to severe AD vaccinated with Fluzone® Intradermal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>92 moderate to severe atopic dermatitis participants who will receive a single dose of the seasonal 2012-2013 Fluzone® Intradermal influenza vaccine via a single-dose pre-filled microinjection system (0.1mL).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Moderate to severe AD vaccinated with Fluzone® (Intramuscular)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>92 moderate to severe atopic dermatitis participants who will receive a single dose of the seasonal 2012-2013 Fluzone® (Intramuscular) influenza vaccine from 0.5 mL single dose vials.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-atopic controls vaccinated with Fluzone® (Intramuscular)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>20 non-atopic controls who will receive a single dose of the seasonal 2012-2013 Fluzone® (Intramuscular) influenza vaccine from 0.5 mL single dose vials.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mild AD participants vaccinated with Fluzone® Intradermal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>20 mild atopic dermatitis participants who will receive a single dose of the seasonal 2012-2013 Fluzone® Intradermal influenza vaccine via a single-dose pre-filled microinjection system (0.1mL).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluzone® Intradermal Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>A 0.1mL single-dose, in a latex-free, pre-filled microinjection system with an ultra-fine micro-needle. The active substance is prepared from influenza viruses propagated in embryonated chicken eggs. Fluzone® Intradermal is approved for use in persons 18 through 64 years of age and will be purchased from Sanofi Pasteur, Inc.</description>
    <arm_group_label>92 Nnon-atopic controls vaccinated with Fluzone® Intradermal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Moderate to severe AD vaccinated with Fluzone® Intradermal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Mild AD participants vaccinated with Fluzone® Intradermal</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Influenza Virus Trivalent Vaccine (Types A and B) (Avian)</other_name>
    <other_name>Influenza Virus Vaccine, 2012-2013 Formula</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluzone® (Intramuscular) vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>A 0.5mL single-dose delivered via syringe using single-dose vials. The active substance is prepared from influenza viruses propagated in embryonated chicken eggs. Fluzone® for intramuscular injection is approved for persons 6 months and older and will be purchased from Sanofi Pasteur, Inc.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Moderate to severe AD vaccinated with Fluzone® (Intramuscular)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Non-atopic controls vaccinated with Fluzone® (Intramuscular)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Influenza Virus Trivalent Vaccine (Types A and B) (Avian)</other_name>
    <other_name>Influenza Virus Vaccine, 2012-2013 Formula</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  enrolled in the ADRN Registry study.

          -  active, mild to severe AD (lesions present) with or without a history of eczema
             herpeticum or who are non-atopic as diagnosed using the ADRN Standard Diagnostic
             Criteria.

          -  willing to sign the informed consent form prior to initiation of any study procedure.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  pregnant or lactating. Women of child bearing potential must avoid becoming pregnant
             (use of an effective method of contraception or abstinence) for the duration of their
             participation in the study.

          -  have a known allergy to any component of the Fluzone® Intradermal or Fluzone®
             (Intramuscular) vaccines, including egg protein, or have had a severe allergic
             reaction to a previous dose of any influenza vaccine.

          -  known or suspected congenital or acquired immunodeficiency or who have had
             immunosuppressive therapy (excluding steroids) such as anti-cancer chemotherapy or
             radiation therapy within the preceding 6 months.

          -  received systemic steroid therapy for 2 or more weeks at a dose ≥ 20 mg/day
             prednisone equivalent within 1 month prior to the day of vaccination or expect to
             receive within 3 weeks post-vaccination.

          -  received a cumulative dose of inhaled and/or intranasally administered
             corticosteroids ≥ 880 mcg/day fluticasone equivalent for 2 or more weeks within 1
             month prior to the day of vaccination or expect to receive within 3 weeks
             post-vaccination.

          -  a chronic illness, including but not limited to, cardiac, renal, or auto-immune
             disorders, or diabetes, at a stage that could interfere with study conduct or
             completion, based on the opinion of the Investigator. Asthma and underlying allergic
             conditions such as allergic rhinitis are not exclusionary.

          -  a neoplastic disease or any hematologic malignancy. Participants who have been
             disease free for at least six months will not be excluded.

          -  participated in another clinical trial investigating a vaccine, drug, medical device,
             or a medical procedure in the four weeks preceding the study vaccination or who plan
             to participate in another clinical trial during the present study period.

          -  any skin disease other than AD that might compromise the stratum corneum barrier
             (e.g., bullous disease, psoriasis, cutaneous T cell lymphoma [also called Mycosis
             Fungoides or Sezary syndrome], dermatitis herpetiformis, Hailey-Hailey, or Darier's
             disease).

          -  received blood or blood-derived products that might interfere with the assessment of
             immune response in the past 3 months prior to vaccination or who plan to receive such
             products during the study period.

          -  received previous vaccination (Fluzone® or another vaccine) against influenza in the
             past 6 months prior to vaccination.

          -  received any other live vaccines within 4 weeks or inactivated vaccines within 2
             weeks prior to study vaccination or who plan to receive any vaccination during the
             study period.

          -  thrombocytopenia or bleeding disorder in the 3 weeks preceding vaccination.

          -  personal or family history of Guillain-Barré Syndrome.

          -  a first degree relative already enrolled in the study.

          -  determined to be not eligible based on the opinion of the Investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Donald Leung, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>National Jewish Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Jewish Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80206</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boston Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Rochester Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oregon Health &amp; Science University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Protland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nationaljewish.org/adrn/index/</url>
    <description>Atopic Dermatitis Research Network (ADRN)</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.niaid.nih.gov/Pages/default.aspx</url>
    <description>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leung DY, Gao PS, Grigoryev DN, Rafaels NM, Streib JE, Howell MD, Taylor PA, Boguniewicz M, Canniff J, Armstrong B, Zaccaro DJ, Schneider LC, Hata TR, Hanifin JM, Beck LA, Weinberg A, Barnes KC. Human atopic dermatitis complicated by eczema herpeticum is associated with abnormalities in IFN-γ response. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2011 Apr;127(4):965-73.e1-5. doi: 10.1016/j.jaci.2011.02.010. Erratum in: J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2011 Oct;128(4):833.</citation>
    <PMID>21458658</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prymula R, Siegrist CA, Chlibek R, Zemlickova H, Vackova M, Smetana J, Lommel P, Kaliskova E, Borys D, Schuerman L. Effect of prophylactic paracetamol administration at time of vaccination on febrile reactions and antibody responses in children: two open-label, randomised controlled trials. Lancet. 2009 Oct 17;374(9698):1339-50.</citation>
    <PMID>19837254</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pulendran B, Li S, Nakaya HI. Systems vaccinology. Immunity. 2010 Oct 29;33(4):516-29. doi: 10.1016/j.immuni.2010.10.006. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21029962</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schneider L, Weinberg A, Boguniewicz M, Taylor P, Oettgen H, Heughan L, Zaccaro D, Armstrong B, Holliday A, Leung DY. Immune response to varicella vaccine in children with atopic dermatitis compared with nonatopic controls. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2010 Dec;126(6):1306-7.e2.</citation>
    <PMID>20889193</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 23, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 27, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Influenza Vaccines</keyword>
  <keyword>Dermatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Injections, Intradermal</keyword>
  <keyword>Injections, Intramuscular</keyword>
  <keyword>Skin Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Skin Diseases, Eczematous</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypersensitivity, Immediate</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypersensitivity</keyword>
  <keyword>Immune System Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Genetic Diseases, Inborn</keyword>
  <keyword>Skin Diseases, Genetic</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis, Atopic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
