<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="58798">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02030834</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UPCC 13413</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02030834</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase IIa Study of Redirected Autologous T Cells Engineered to Contain Anti-CD19 Attached to TCRz and 4-Signaling Domains in Patients With Chemotherapy Relapsed or Refractory CD19+ Lymphomas</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase IIa Study of Redirected Autologous T Cells Engineered to Contain Anti-CD19 Attached to TCRz and 4-Signaling Domains in Patients With Chemotherapy Relapsed or Refractory CD19+ Lymphomas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a single cohort, open-label pilot study to estimate the efficacy of a single
      infusion of autologous T cells expressing CD19 chimeric antigen receptors expressing tandem
      TCR and 4-1BB (TCR /4-1BB) costimulatory domains (referred to as CART-19 or CTL019 cells) in
      non-Hodgkins Lymphoma (NHL) patients. Single infusion of CART-19 cells administered by i.v.

      injection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">55</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-Hodgkins Lymphoma (NHL) Patients, With CD19+B Cell Lymphomas With no Available Potentially</condition>
  <condition>Curative Treatment Options Who Have a Limited Prognosis With Currently Available Therapies.</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CART-19</intervention_name>
    <description>Single infusion of CART-19 cells administered by i.v. injection (total dose of 1 - 5 x108 CART-19 cells, calculated as a range of 2-50% transduced cells in total cells).</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female subjects with CD19+ B cell lymphomas with no available curative
             treatment options (such as autologous or allogeneic SCT) who have a limited prognosis
             (several months to &lt;2 year survival) with currently available therapies will be
             enrolled. The study will enroll 30 patients, but will ensure that at least 8 patients
             each with DLBCL, MCL and FL are included.

               1. CD19+ lymphoma

                  a. Follicular lymphoma, previously identified as CD19+ i. At least 2 prior
                  chemotherapy or immunochemotherapy regimens (not including single agent
                  monoclonal antibody therapy) ii. Patients who progress within 2 years after
                  second or higher line of therapy will be eligible. For instance, patients who
                  have progression of lymphoma &lt; 2 years after second or greater line therapy, but
                  who have responded to their most recent treatment (3rd line or higher) will be
                  eligible. Patients may have progression, stable disease or responding disease at
                  the time of enrollment.

                  iii. Patients with a history of large cell transformation are eligible. b.
                  Mantle cell lymphoma i. Beyond 1st CR with relapsed disease, progressive disease
                  during first line rituximab-chemotherapy combination, or persistent disease
                  after first line rituximab-chemotherapy combination and not eligible or
                  appropriate for conventional allogeneic or autologous SCT.

                  ii. Relapsed after prior autologous SCT. c. Diffuse large B cell lymphoma,
                  previously identified as CD19+ i. Residual disease after primary therapy and not
                  eligible for autologous SCT ii. Relapsed or persistent disease after prior
                  autologous SCT iii. Beyond 1st CR with relapsed or persistent disease and not
                  eligible or appropriate for conventional allogeneic or autologous SCT iv.
                  Patients with an antecedent history of follicular lymphoma or CLL/SLL are
                  eligible.

               2. Age ≥18 years

               3. Expected survival &gt; 12 weeks

               4. Creatinine &lt; 1.6 mg/dL

               5. ALT/AST &lt; 3x upper limit of normal

               6. Bilirubin &lt;2.0 mg/dL, unless subject has Gilbert's Syndrome (&lt;3.0 mg/dL)

               7. Any relapse after prior autologous SCT will make patient eligible regardless of
                  other prior therapy.

               8. Patients with relapsed disease after prior allogeneic SCT (myeloablative or
                  non-myeloablative) will be eligible if they meet all other inclusion criteria
                  and

                    1. Have experienced graft rejection (no evidence of donor cells by STR
                       analysis on 2 occasions separated by at least 1 month).

                    2. Have no active GVHD and require no immunosuppression

                    3. Are more than 6 months from transplant

               9. Measurable or assessable disease according to the &quot;Revised Response Criteria for
                  Malignant Lymphoma&quot; (Cheson et al., J. Clin. Onc., 1999)105. Patients in
                  complete remission with no evidence of disease are not eligible.

              10. Performance status (ECOG) 0 or 1.

              11. Written informed consent is given.

              12. Successful T cell test expansion (first 10 subjects

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Pregnant or lactating women. The safety of this therapy on unborn children is not
             known. Female study participants of reproductive potential must have a negative serum
             pregnancy test at enrollment. A urine pregnancy test will be performed within 48
             hours before infusion.

             2. Uncontrolled active infection. 3. Active hepatitis B or hepatitis C infection. 4.
             Concurrent use of systemic steroids. Recent or current use of inhaled steroids is not
             exclusionary.

             5. Any uncontrolled active medical disorder that would preclude participation as
             outlined.

             6. HIV infection. 7. Patients with active CNS involvement by malignancy. Patients
             with prior CNS disease that has been effectively treated will be eligible providing
             treatment was &gt;4 weeks before enrollment 8. Patients in complete remission with no
             assessable disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen Schuster, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Stephen Schuster, MD</last_name>
    <phone>855-216-0098</phone>
    <email>PennCancerTrials@emergingmed.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stephen Schuster, MD</last_name>
      <phone>855-216-0098</phone>
      <email>PennCancerTrials@emergingmed.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephen Schuster, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 7, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
