<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="99065">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01794858</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>S12-00828</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01794858</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Therapeutic Hypothermia for Severe Acute Pancreatitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Therapeutic Hypothermia for Severe Acute Pancreatitis: A Clinical Model for &quot;Suspended Inflammation&quot;</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Acute pancreatitis is characterized by a high mortality rate (10%-15%), and a
      remarkably unpredictable clinical course. Approximately 50% of deaths in acute pancreatitis
      occur early—within the first 14 days—and early mortality is attributable to sequelae of a
      severe systemic inflammatory response syndrome (SIRS), which is associated with multi-organ
      dysfunction syndrome (MODS) that can escalate to renal failure, respiratory failure, and
      death. Significant improvements in acute pancreatitis mortality will demand innovative
      approaches to counteract early organ failure. A series of destructive cellular processes
      begins within minutes of initial pancreatic injury, and the ensuing inflammatory cascade is
      compounded by disease sequelae including edema, ischemia, and tissue necrosis. Early
      interventions to reduce inflammation within the first 36 hours have been shown to have
      significant effects in minimizing progressive organ dysfunction.

      Hypothermia is clinically employed to combat cellular injury and systemic responses
      following ischemia-reperfusion, and is been studied as a mechanism of acute inflammatory
      inhibition in processes including cardiogenic shock, lung injury, local intestinal injury,
      and reperfusion injuries to the lung, liver, and endothelium. In numerous studies, effective
      immunomodulations have been observed including reduction of pro-inflammatory cytokines
      (TNF-α, IL-6), stimulation of anti-inflammatory cytokines (IL-10), inhibition of
      pro-apoptotic JNK signaling, reduction of systemic oxidative stress, and inhibition of
      neutrophils, monocytes, and monocyte-derived macrophages. Most saliently, in the caerulein
      model of murine acute pancreatitis, therapeutic hypothermia has been shown to reduce serum
      IL-1, IL-6, and TNF-α, increased serum IL-10, decrease serum amylase and lipase, lower the
      histological grade of pancreatic injury as compared to normothermic mice, and significant
      survival benefit. Although therapeutic hypothermia is actively employed in the treatment of
      traumatic brain injury, neonatal asphyxia, spinal cord injury, and cardiac arrest, no
      studies have yet been made of its application to acute pancreatitis.

      Hypothesis: Patients treated with therapeutic hypothermia (32-34°C) will sustain reduced
      organ-specific injury in acute pancreatitis.

      Proposal: In a Phase IIa pilot clinical trial, we will examine the effects of therapeutic
      hypothermia on organ-specific outcomes during the early stage of acute pancreatitis. We will
      recruit five patients aged 18 to 80 receiving medically-necessitated ventilator support
      under ICU monitoring with core temperatures ≥36°C and severe acute pancreatitis defined as
      either a Ranson Score ≥7, a CT indicating ≥50% pancreatic necrosis, or a significant
      deterioration in clinical status including dysfunction of two or more organ systems (defined
      by ACCP/SCCM Organ Failure Guidelines, Chest 2009). All patients will receive current
      standard management for severe acute pancreatitis and a standardized protocol for
      application of therapeutic hypothermia and rewarming. Our primary endpoints are
      organ-specific cardiovascular, respiratory, hematological, renal, and metabolic dysfunction
      as measured at 28 days.  Logistic Organ Dysfunction Scores (LOD) will be compared before and
      after therapeutic hypothermia, establishing day 4 versus day 1 changes in LOD. Secondary
      endpoints include D-dimer, IL-6, C-reactive protein, APACHE II scores on day 1 and day 4,
      inpatient and ICU length-of-stay, infection, mortality, and hypothermia-associated side
      effects including cardiac arrhythmia, electrolyte imbalance, hyperglycemia, major bleeding,
      and acute pancreatitis. We believe that such a study will supply preliminary answers to our
      chief research questions: does therapeutic hypothermia reduce morbidity as assessed by
      organ-specific outcomes, does therapeutic hypothermia attenuate the steep rise in
      inflammation observed in severe acute pancreatitis, and does therapeutic hypothermia shorten
      the clinical course for these patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Organ specific outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Cardiovascular system dysfunction—either of the following:
Respiratory dysfunction—either of the following:
Hematological dysfunction—either of the following:
Renal dysfunction:
Metabolic dysfunction: unexplained metabolic acidosis, which was defined as:
Logistic Organ Dysfunction Score (LOD) will be compared before and after TH. Change in LOD will reflect LOD day 4 minus LOD day 1 (Ehrmann, Can J Anesth 2006).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment Effects</measure>
    <time_frame>28 Day Mortality</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Lab values: D-Dimer, IL-6, CRP
APACHE II Scores Day 1 and after TH (day 4)
Length of stay in the ICU and hospital
Prevalence of infections
28-day mortality
Hypothermia-related side effects: cardiac arrhythmia, electrolyte balance, hyperglycemia, bleeding, acute pancreatitis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreatitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Therapeutic Hypothermia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Primary - Organ specific outcome at 28 days Logistic Organ Dysfunction Score (LOD) will be compared before and after TH. Change in LOD will reflect LOD day 4 minus LOD day 1 (Ehrmann, Can J Anesth 2006).
Secondary
Lab values: D-Dimer, IL-6, CRP
APACHE II Scores Day 1 and after TH (day 4)
Length of stay in the ICU and hospital
Prevalence of infections
28-day mortality
Hypothermia-related side effects: cardiac arrhythmia, electrolyte balance, hyperglycemia, bleeding, acute pancreatitis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Therapeutic Hypothermia</intervention_name>
    <description>Will receive medically-necessitated ventilator support under ICU monitoring with core temperatures ≥36°C and severe acute pancreatitis defined as either a Ranson Score ≥7, a CT indicating ≥50% pancreatic necrosis, or a significant deterioration in clinical status including dysfunction of two or more organ systems. All patients will receive current standard management for severe acute pancreatitis and a standardized protocol for application of therapeutic hypothermia and rewarming. Our primary endpoints are organ-specific cardiovascular, respiratory, hematological, renal, and metabolic dysfunction as measured at 28 days.  Logistic Organ Dysfunction Scores will be compared before and after therapeutic hypothermia, establishing day 4 versus day 1 changes in LOD.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Therapeutic Hypothermia</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Aged 18 to 80

          2. Intubation with mechanical ventilatory support as medically necessary

        2) Cooling device or technique available for &gt;36 hours 3) Core temperature ≥36°C 4) SAP
        either by:

          -  Ranson Score of &gt; 7

          -  CT with pancreatic necrosis greater than 50%

          -  Significant deterioration of clinical status—dysfunction of 2 or more organ systems
             (defined by ACCP/SCCM Organ Failure guidelines Chest 2009) 5) ICU monitoring
             medically necessary

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient already receiving therapeutic hypothermia treatment

          2. Unlikely to survive for the next 24 hours in the opinion of the ICU Consultant or
             Surgical Consultant treating the patient

          3. Temperature ≤34°C at hospital admission

          4. Pregnancy (all female patients of child bearing age who meet the inclusion criteria
             will undergo a urine pregnancy test).

          5. History of Cryoglobulinemia

          6. No need for ICU monitoring
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Steven Cohen, DO</last_name>
    <phone>212-263-7302</phone>
    <email>steven.cohen@nyumc.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ashish Shaha, BA</last_name>
    <phone>212-263-2225</phone>
    <email>ashish.shaha@nyumc.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NYU Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven Cohen, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-263-7302</phone>
      <email>steven.cohen@nyumc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steven Cohen, DO</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 21, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 15, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hypothermia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
