<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="146310">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01922986</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Acute_rTMS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01922986</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation Use in Acute Stroke</brief_title>
  <official_title>Real vs Sham rTMS Combined With Conventional Therapy in Acute Stroke</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Data and Safety Monitoring Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      When a certain area of the brain is injured, like in stroke, several events occur. One side
      of the body may become weak. This weakness is called hemiparesis and it may create
      difficulty in performing tasks like writing, eating, and walking. The weakness results from
      two sources:

        1. death of some brain cells in the affected side (hemisphere) of the brain

        2. exaggerated inhibitory signals from the unaffected hemisphere acting on surviving
           neurons in the affected hemisphere.

      Investigators cannot change neurons that have died but they may be able to change the
      exaggerated inhibition that impairs the surviving neurons in the affected hemisphere.The
      purpose of this study is to try to decrease the exaggerated inhibition coming from the
      unaffected hemisphere, which suppresses the affected hemisphere, with transcranial magnetic
      stimulation (TMS). Investigators hypothesize that, from admission to discharge, active rTMS
      combined with conventional therapy will produce greater functional gains in the paretic hand
      compared to sham rTMS combined with conventional therapy, as measured by standard tests.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Stroke is the leading cause of long-term disability in the United States and people with
      stroke deserve our maximum effort to restore in them as much function as possible; yet,
      mainstream stroke rehabilitation remains mired in traditional treatment approaches that may
      be suboptimal.  However, for the past 5 years we have been endeavoring to advance stroke
      rehabilitation by including noninvasive brain stimulation.  This study will explore whether
      the safety and functional results from noninvasive brain stimulation in patients with
      chronic stroke when given by researchers in a laboratory setting can be replicated in acute
      stroke when given by trained clinicians in the real-world clinical setting.

      As background, a phenomenon in stroke is that compensatory overuse of the non-stroke
      hemisphere can inhibit surviving neurons in the stroke hemisphere.  In this way, people with
      stroke are &quot;doubly disabled&quot; - first, by the stroke itself and, second, by exaggerated
      interhemispheric inhibition (IHI) arising in the non-stroke hemisphere and acting on
      surviving neurons in the non-stroke hemisphere. Investigators cannot bring the killed
      neurons back to life but they can up-regulate the surviving neurons suppressed by IHI.
      Repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) is a noninvasive way to do this.

      rTMS has not yet entered mainstream clinical use for stroke, likely because it has not been
      explored in the acute rehabilitation setting with application by clinicians.  With prior
      National Institutes of Health funding, Dr. Carey has considerable experience in using rTMS
      in the laboratory setting for chronic stroke.  He will now take rTMS out of his lab and into
      the real-world setting of Courage Kenny Rehabilitation Institute (CKRI), the primary
      referral center for acute stroke rehabilitation in our region, where clinicians will be
      trained in rTMS.  Five daily rTMS treatments (active or sham) will be given to the
      non-stroke primary motor area (M1). After each treatment, patients will receive their
      conventional rehabilitation training.  This approach is innovative because of the rTMS
      parameters used and because the application will be given by trained clinicians with
      oversight by the Principal Investigator, as opposed to laboratory researchers. Expected
      outcomes are improved hand function with no major adverse effects.  Data will serve as a
      springboard to larger clinical trials.

      Specific Aim #1: Determine the safety of 5 treatments of 6-Hz primed low-frequency rTMS
      combined with conventional therapy in adults with acute stroke.

      Adverse effects will be measured through observation for seizures, investigator screening,
      physician exam, and tests of cognitive function and motor function in the nonparetic hand.

      Investigators hypothesize there will be a) no seizures, b) no cognitive decline and c) no
      motor decline.

      Specific Aim #2: Compare the effectiveness of active vs. sham rTMS on functional outcomes in
      adults with acute stroke.

      Adults with acute stroke will be randomized to receive either active rTMS or sham rTMS.
      Both groups will also receive conventional therapy, consisting of the normal rehabilitation
      used at this rehabilitation center.  Investigators hypothesize that, from admission to
      discharge, active rTMS will produce greater functional gains in the paretic hand compared to
      sham rTMS, as measured by standard tests.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Jebsen Taylor Hand Function test</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at pretest (day before treatments begin) and posttest (day following last treatment). Thus, 7 days of participation (1 pretest, 5 treatments, 1 posttest).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This is a test of function in daily tasks using the hand.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in finger tracking test</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at pretest (day before treatments begin) and posttest (day following last treatment). Thus, 7 days of participation (1 pretest, 5 treatments, 1 posttest).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>test of finger movement ability</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Motricity Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at pretest (day before treatments begin) and posttest (day following last treatment). Thus, 7 days of participation (1 pretest, 5 treatments, 1 posttest).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>test of hand strength</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">34</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active rTMS with conventional therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>20 minutes of active rTMS followed by conventional stroke therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>sham rTMS with conventional therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>20 minutes of sham rTMS stimulation followed by conventional stroke therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>active rTMS</intervention_name>
    <description>10 minutes of real high-frequency (6-Hz) rTMS priming (total priming pulses = 600) plus 10 minutes of low-rate (1Hz) rTMS (total low-rate pulses = 600).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active rTMS with conventional therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>sham rTMS</intervention_name>
    <description>20 minutes of sham rTMS stimulation</description>
    <arm_group_label>sham rTMS with conventional therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>conventional stroke therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>conventional stroke therapy consisting of exercises and physical training</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active rTMS with conventional therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>sham rTMS with conventional therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  stroke onset: within past 30 days but rTMS intervention will commence no sooner than
             5 days from stroke onset

          -  stroke location: cortical or subcortical

          -  stroke type: ischemic

          -  age: &gt;18 years

          -  paretic index finger must show either no or impaired flexion/extension motion at the
             metacarpophalangeal (MP) joint.

          -  Mini-Mental State Examination greater than or equal to 22

          -  ability to stand/transfer with no more than moderate assistance

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  seizure within past two years

          -  metal in head (dental permitted)

          -  pregnancy

          -  psychiatric disorders

          -  receiving tricyclic antidepressants or neuroleptics

          -  inability to follow three-step command

          -  hemineglect

          -  dependent on ventilator, nasogastric tube, or implanted medical device

          -  co-morbidities impairing upper extremity function

          -  anticipated stay at Courage Kenny Rehabilitation Institute shorter than 7  treatment
             days
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James R Carey, PhD, PT</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>James R Carey, PhD, PT</last_name>
    <phone>612-626-2746</phone>
    <email>Carey007@umn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Courage Kenny Rehabilitation Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55407</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lars Oddsson, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>612-868-7607</phone>
      <email>Lars.Oddsson@allina.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lars Oddsson, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 12, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 26, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>hemiplegia</keyword>
  <keyword>repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
