<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="60494">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02040935</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ML28878</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-000829-31</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02040935</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Subcutaneous Herceptin (Trastuzumab) Administered at Home By Single-Use Injection Device in Patients With Early HER2-Positive Breast Cancer (HOMERUS)</brief_title>
  <official_title>HOMERUS: A LOCAL OPEN LABEL, MULTICENTRE, PHASE IIIB STUDY, INVESTIGATING SUBCUTANEOUS TRASTUZUMAB ADMINISTERED AT HOME WITH SINGLE INJECTION DEVICE IN PATIENTS WITH HER2-POSITIVE EARLY BREAST CANCER</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hoffmann-La Roche</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hoffmann-La Roche</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Netherlands: Centrale Commissie Mensgebonden Onderzoek (CCMO)</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This single-arm, open-label, local multicenter study will evaluate the safety and
      tolerability of Herceptin (trastuzumab) administered subcutaneously by a single-use
      injection device (SID) in patients with HER2-positive early breast cancer. Following surgery
      (and neo-adjuvant or adjuvant chemotherapy), patients will receive Herceptin 600 mg
      subcutaneously by SID every 3 weeks for a total of 1 year, unless disease recurrence or
      unacceptable toxicity occurs. After the first 3 cycles, patients will be permitted to
      self-administer Herceptin under supervision of a HCP.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety: Incidence and severity of adverse events and serious adverse events by NCI CTAE version 4-0</measure>
    <time_frame>approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics: Trough concentrations (Ctrough) of trastuzumab following in-hospital and in-home administration via SID</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose Cycles 2, 3, 9, and 10 or 13 (Weeks 4, 7, 25, and 28 or 32)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported health/mental status assessed by questionnaire (SF-36 and MASQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>28 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">128</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Herceptin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>trastuzumab [Herceptin]</intervention_name>
    <description>600 mg subcutaneously every 3 weeks by single-use injection device</description>
    <arm_group_label>Herceptin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female and male patients, &gt;/= 18 years of age

          -  Histologically confirmed non-metastatic primary invasive adenocarcinoma of the breast

          -  HER2-positive disease

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0-1

          -  Hormonal therapy will be allowed as per institutional guidelines

          -  Prior use of anti-HER2 therapy will be allowed except for early breast cancer
             patients in the neo-adjuvant setting

          -  Left ventricular ejection fraction &gt;/= 55%

          -  No evidence of residual, locally recurrent or metastatic disease after completion of
             surgery and chemotherapy, or during concurrent chemotherapy (neo-adjuvant or
             adjuvant)

          -  Use of concurrent radiotherapy will be permitted

          -  Completion of surgery and chemotherapy (if applicable) for early breast cancer

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of other malignancy, except for patients with curatively treated carcinoma in
             situ of the cervix or basal cell carcinoma and patients with other curatively treated
             malignancies who have been disease-free for the last 5 years

          -  Patients with severe dyspnea at rest or requiring supplementary oxygen therapy

          -  Patients with other concurrent serious diseases that might interfere with planned
             treatment, including severe pulmonary conditions/illness

          -  Serious cardiac illness or medical conditions that would preclude the use of
             trastuzumab, specifically: history of documented congestive heart failure, high-risk
             uncontrolled arrhythmias, angina pectoris requiring medication, clinically
             significant valvular disease, evidence of transmural infarction on ECG, poorly
             controlled hypertension

          -  Pregnant or lactating women

          -  Women of childbearing potential and male patients with female partners of
             childbearing potential who are unable or unwilling to use adequate contraceptive
             methods during study treatment

          -  Concurrent enrolment in another clinical trial using an investigational anti-cancer
             treatment, including hormonal therapy, biphosphonate therapy and immunotherapy,
             within 28 days prior to the first dose of study treatment

          -  Known hypersensitivity to trastuzumab, murine proteins, to any excipients of
             Herceptin including hyaluronidase, or the adhesive of the SC device, or a history of
             severe allergic or immunological reactions, e.g. difficult to control asthma

          -  Inadequate bone marrow, hepatic or renal function
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Hoffmann-La Roche</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Reference Study ID Number: ML28878 www.roche.com/about_roche/roche_worldwide.htm</last_name>
    <phone>888-662-6728 (U.S. Only)</phone>
    <email>global.rochegenentechtrials@roche.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 17, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 15, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Trastuzumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
