<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="159698">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01821794</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130091</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-DK-0091</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01821794</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tenofovir DF With or Without Peginterferon for Chronic Hepatitis B</brief_title>
  <official_title>Combination Therapy of Pegylated Interferon Alfa-2a and Tenofovir DF Versus Tenofovir DF Monotherapy in HBeAg-Positive and HBeAg-Negative Chronic Hepatitis B</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - There are two forms of chronic hepatitis B. The difference between the forms is whether or
      not a viral protein called hepatitis B e antigen is present in the blood. Standard
      approaches to treating both forms of chronic hepatitis B involve different drugs. One drug
      is called peginterferon, another is called tenofovir DF. These drugs are often given
      separately and used for different forms of the disease. However, researchers want to see if
      combining peginterferon and tenofovir DF will be a more effective treatment than tenofovir
      DF alone.

      Objectives:

      - To see whether combining tenofovir DF and peginterferon, or using tenofovir DF alone, is a
      more effective treatment of chronic hepatitis B.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals at least 18 years of age who have chronic hepatitis B and are in the Hepatitis
      B Research Network Cohort study.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. Blood, urine,
           and liver tissue samples will be collected. Bone and liver imaging studies will also be
           performed.

        -  Participants will be divided into two groups. One group will have tenofovir DF alone
           for 192 weeks (about 4 years). The other group will have tenofovir DF and peginterferon
           for 24 weeks (about 6 months), and then tenofovir DF alone for 168 weeks (about 3.5
           years).

        -  Participants will take the study drugs on the schedule determined by their study
           doctors. They will keep a diary to record their doses and any side effects.

        -  Participants will have three study visits 4 weeks apart after the starting the
           treatment. At these visits, they will have a physical exam and provide blood samples.
           They may also provide urine samples and have imaging studies.

        -  After the first three study visits, participants will continue to have study visits
           every 12 weeks until the treatment ends at week 192. These visits will have many of the
           same tests as the first three visits. At some of these visits, they may fill out
           questionnaires about their quality of life.

        -  Participants who do not respond to the study drugs may have their medications changed.
           They may also be asked to stop treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized (1:1) parallel group design trial comparing (i) tenofovir DF 300 mg
      daily for 192 weeks (4 years) and (ii) peginterferon alfa-2a 180 micrograms/g weekly for 24
      weeks plus tenofovir DF 300 mg daily for 192 weeks (4 years). Enrolled participants will be
      stratified by HBeAg status (positive/negative), genotype (A vs. all others) and cirrhosis
      (present vs. absent). After 192 weeks of treatment, participants meeting criteria for
      treatment discontinuation will stop treatment and be followed for 48 weeks (total duration
      of treatment and follow up is 240 weeks). A liver biopsy will be obtained at the end-of
      treatment (week 180-192) to assess improvement in histology. Emtricitabine/tenofovir
      coformulated as Truvada, approved for treating HIV but not for treating HBV infection, will
      be offered to participants with primary nonresponse, partial virological response or
      confirmed virologic breakthrough.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HBsAg loss at the end of 48-weeks post-treatment follow-up (week 240)</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks post treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">31</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Hepatitis B e Antigen Positive</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Peginterferon and Tenofovir</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. Enrolled in the Hepatitis B Research Network (HBRN) Cohort Study or completed
                  the necessary components of the Cohort baseline evaluation by the end of the
                  baseline visit for this study.

               2. At least 18 years of age at the time of randomization (day 0).

               3. Chronic HBV infection as evidenced by at least one of the following:

                    1. HBsAg positive result within 8 weeks prior to randomization and another
                       time at least 24 weeks prior to randomization with no HBsAg negative result
                       in between.

                    2. HBsAg positive plus absence of detectable anti-HBc IgM in serum within 8
                       weeks prior to randomization.

                    3. HBsAg positive within 8 weeks prior to randomization and HBV DNA greater
                       than or equal to 1,000 IU/mL on 2 occasions at least 24 weeks apart (can
                       include result from screening visit within 8 weeks of randomization).

               4. HBeAg positive or negative.

               5. Serum HBV DNA greater than or equal to 1000 IU/mL on 2 occasions at least 4
                  weeks apart within the 32 weeks prior to randomization (can include result from
                  screening visit within 8 weeks of randomization).

               6. At least two elevated serum ALT levels (&gt; 45 U/L for males and &gt; 30 U/L for
                  females) at least 4 weeks, and no more than 32 weeks apart with the second being
                  within 8 weeks of randomization.

               7. Compensated liver disease, with total bilirubin less than or equal to 2 mg/dL
                  (except if Gilbert   s syndrome), direct bilirubin less than or equal to 0.5
                  mg/dL, INR less than or equal to 1.5, and serum albumin greater than or equal to
                  3.5 g/dL

               8. No evidence of HCC based upon alpha-fetoprotein (AFP) less than or equal to
                  20ng/mL within 8 weeks prior to randomization:

                    1. Participants who meet AASLD criteria for HCC surveillance must have
                       negative liver imaging by ultrasound (US), computerized tomography (CT) or
                       magnetic resonance imaging (MR) within 28 weeks of randomization as part of
                       standard of care.

                    2. Participants with AFP &gt; 20 ng/mL must be evaluated clinically with
                       additional imaging and shown not to have HCC on CT or MRI.

               9. Liver biopsy that shows findings consistent with chronic hepatitis B with
                  histology activity index (HAI) greater than or equal to 3 (necroinflammatory
                  component only) or Ishak fibrosis score greater than or equal to 1 or both, as
                  assessed by the local consortium pathologist on review of a liver biopsy done
                  within 144 weeks of randomization. Slides must be available for review by the
                  local consortium pathologist and meet adequacy requirements. If the participant
                  had received previous treatment for hepatitis B, the biopsy must have been done
                  after discontinuation of treatment.

              10. Females of child bearing potential must agree to use an adequate method of
                  contraception throughout the study and must have a negative pregnancy test
                  immediately prior to the start of treatment.

              11. Provide informed consent and agree to adhere to the requirements of the study.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Serum ALT &gt; 450 U/L for males and &gt; 300 U/L for females (participants are eligible
             for re-screening if ALT levels fall to the range of eligibility).

          2. Treatment with interferon or nucleos(t)ide analogues for hepatitis B within 48 weeks
             of randomization.

          3. More than 48 weeks of therapy with nucleos(t)ide analogues for hepatitis B at any
             time in the past.

          4. History of hepatic decompensation including, but not limited to, ascites, variceal
             bleeding, or hepatic encephalopathy.

          5. Known allergy or intolerance to any of the study medications.

          6. Females who are pregnant or breastfeeding.

          7. Previous organ transplantation including engrafted bone marrow transplant.

          8. Any other concomitant liver disease, including hemochromatosis or hepatitis C or D.
             Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) with steatosis and/or mild to moderate
             steatohepatitis is acceptable but NALFD with severe steatohepatitis is exclusionary.

          9. Positive anti-HIV (test to be completed within 8 weeks prior to randomization).

         10. Renal insufficiency with calculated (by MDRD method) creatinine clearance &lt; 60 mL/min
             within 8 weeks prior to randomization.

         11. Platelet count &lt; 90,000 /mm3, hemoglobin &lt; 13 g/dL (males) or &lt; 12 g/dL (females),
             absolute neutrophil count &lt; 1500 /mm3 (&lt; 1000/mm3 for African-Americans) within 8
             weeks prior to randomization.

         12. History of alcohol or drug abuse within 48 weeks of randomization.

         13. Pre-existing psychiatric condition(s), including, but not limited to:

               1. Current moderate or severe depression as determined by the study physician.

               2. History of depression requiring hospitalization within past 10 years.

               3. History of suicidal or homicidal attempt within the past 10 years.

               4. History of severe psychiatric disorders including, but not limited to,
                  schizophrenia, psychosis, bipolar disorder as determined by a study physician.

         14. History of immune-mediated disease, or cerebrovascular, chronic pulmonary or cardiac
             disease associated with functional limitation, retinopathy, uncontrolled thyroid
             disease, poorly controlled diabetes or uncontrolled seizure disorder, as determined
             by a study physician.

         15. Any medical condition that would, in the opinion of a study physician be predicted to
             be exacerbated by therapy or that would limit study participation.

         16. Any medical condition requiring, or likely to require, chronic systemic
             administration of corticosteroids or other immunosuppressive medications during the
             course of this study.

         17. Evidence of active or suspected malignancy, or a history of malignancy within the
             last 144 weeks prior to randomization (except adequately treated carcinoma in situ or
             basal cell carcinoma of the skin).

         18. Expected need for ongoing use of any antivirals with activity against HBV during the
             course of the study.

         19. Participation in any other clinical trial involving investigational drugs within 30
             days of randomization or intention to participate in another clinical trial involving
             investigational drugs during participation in this study.

         20. Any other condition that in the opinion of a study physician would make the
             participant unsuitable for enrollment or could interfere with the participant
             participating in and completing the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marc G Ghany, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Elenita Rivera, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-3531</phone>
    <email>erivera@cc.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Marc G Ghany, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-5115</phone>
    <email>mg228m@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-DK-0091.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoofnagle JH, Doo E, Liang TJ, Fleischer R, Lok AS. Management of hepatitis B: summary of a clinical research workshop. Hepatology. 2007 Apr;45(4):1056-75. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17393513</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shepard CW, Simard EP, Finelli L, Fiore AE, Bell BP. Hepatitis B virus infection: epidemiology and vaccination. Epidemiol Rev. 2006;28:112-25. Epub 2006 Jun 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16754644</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lok AS, McMahon BJ. Chronic hepatitis B. Hepatology. 2007 Feb;45(2):507-39. No abstract available. Erratum in: Hepatology. 2007 Jun;45(6):1347.</citation>
    <PMID>17256718</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 25, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 15, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hepatitis B</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti-Viral</keyword>
  <keyword>Pegylated Interferon</keyword>
  <keyword>Tenofovir Disoproxil Fumarate</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatitis B Surface Antigen</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis B</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis B, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Interferons</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tenofovir</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tenofovir disoproxil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peginterferon alfa-2a</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
