<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="164786">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01878097</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>5U01CE001675</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01878097</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Green Dot a Primary Prevention Intervention</brief_title>
  <official_title>Green Dot Across the Bluegrass: Evaluation of a Primary Prevention Intervention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Kentucky</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Kentucky</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the statewide application of Green Dot among high
      schools students. We hypothesize that students in high schools with Green Dot will over time
      report lower rates of sexual violence compared with students in comparable high schools
      randomized not to have Green Dot. This reduction in sexual violence will be mediated through
      a reduction in social norms supporting sexual violence and an increase in bystander
      behaviors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      &quot;Green Dot&quot; is a bystander intervention program that empowers students to actively question
      peer support for sexual violence (SV) and become change agents who play a significant role
      in preventing sexual violence. The purpose of this study is to evaluate the statewide
      application of Green Dot among high schools students. We hypothesize that students in high
      schools with Green Dot will over time report lower rates of SV compared with students in
      comparable high schools randomized not to have Green Dot. A high school based controlled
      intervention trial is being used to test the efficacy of Green Dot. Both panel and cohort
      survey methods will be used to provide baseline and prospective data on student's attitudes
      supporting SV, bystander behaviors and violence victimization and perpetration. In 13
      Kentucky regions, 2 demographically comparable high schools were recruited to participate in
      Green Dot intervention either as the intervention or control site. Schools were randomly
      assigned to the intervention. Study Population includes all students in participating high
      schools invited to complete anonymous panel surveys beginning spring 2010 through 2014. This
      state-wide, population-based, multi-site controlled intervention trial provides an empirical
      test of a promising intervention, which, if proven effective, could result in the primary
      prevention of SV and a reduction in the health and academic consequences of SV.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sexual Violence Victimization and Perpetration</measure>
    <time_frame>Survey all students in each high school between February-April 2010-2014(up to 4 years)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>3 items measuring sexual violence victimization and 3 items measuring sexual violence perpetration. Items address attempted or complete forced sexual activity; unwanted sex due to being too drunk or drugged to consent; coerced sexual activity.
These measures were based on the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) National Intimate Partner and Sexual Violence Survey (NISVS).
5 items addressing reproductive coercion were included (victimization only). These items were based on research by Miller, Elizabeth, Michele R. Decker, Heather L. McCauley, Daniel J. Tancredi, Rebecca R. Levenson, Jeffrey Waldman, Phyllis Schoenwald, and Jay G. Silverman. &quot;Pregnancy Coercion, Intimate Partner Violence and Unintended Pregnancy.&quot; Contraception 81.4 (2010): 316-22.
3 items addressing sexual harassment were also included and asked as both victimization and perpetration.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Increase in bystanding behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>Annual measures violence at baseline (pre-intervention) and 4 years post intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>7 items measuring self-reports of students actively engaging their peers in behaviors that may prevent violence.
Response options: 0 times, 1-2 times, 3-5 times, 6-9 times, 10 or more times, didn't see or hear someone doing this
Tell someone to stop talking down to, harassing, or messing with someone else.
Speak up when you heard that someone who was forced to have sex or hurt by a boyfriend/girlfriend was to blame.
Talk to a friend who was being physically hurt by a boyfriend/girlfriend.
Ask someone that looked very upset at a party if they were okay or needed   help.
Ask a friend if they needed to be walked or driven home from a party if they looked upset.
Spoke up to someone who was bragging or making excuses for forcing someone to have sex with them.
Got help for a friend because they had been forced to have sex or were physically hurt by a boyfriend/girlfriend.
Above items repeated to measure student observing others doing these behaviors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Social Norms of violence acceptance</measure>
    <time_frame>Annual measures violence at baseline (pre-intervention) and 4 years post intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Two measures used: Illinois Rape Myth Acceptance Scale measure students' beliefs about rape which may indicate social norms supporting sexual violence. 5-item Acceptance of General Dating Violence Scale(21) was used to measure norms supporting dating violence.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Social Networks</measure>
    <time_frame>Annual measures violence at baseline (pre-intervention) and 4 years post intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measure of how the bystander intervention is diffused throughout student social networks. Each trained student provides the names of 5 friends / acquaintances. Analyses measures the numbers of students indirectly receiving training via trained student. Panel surveys also measure impact of diffusion through observing others' bystanding behaviors</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80000</enrollment>
  <condition>Sex Offenses</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Green Dot Bystander Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>26 high schools: 13 receiving Green Dot intervention and 13 no intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Green Dot Bystander Intevention</intervention_name>
    <description>Intervention allocated at the school level</description>
    <arm_group_label>Green Dot Bystander Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Only high school students attending the intervention or comparison high schools will be
        eligible.  Two groups will be recruited: those receiving bystanding training and those not
        receiving such training who may or may not be in the social network of those receiving
        bystanding training.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        All other high school students in Kentucky
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>19 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ann L. Coker, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Kentucky</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ann L. Coker, PhD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>859-323-6758</phone>
    <email>Ann.Coker@uky.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Patricia G. Cook-Craig, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>859-323-7407</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Kentucky</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lexington</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40536-0293</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ann L. Coker, PhD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Patricia G. Cook-Craig, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Heather M. Bush, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 13, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 29, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Kentucky</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ann Coker</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor and Endowed Chair</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
