<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="127941">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02155075</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>960-CSP-ISR_ImplantsMC_ILS3</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02155075</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of a Novel Infra-red Breast Imaging System for Breast Cancer Risk Assessment in Women With Breast Implants</brief_title>
  <official_title>Data Collection Study for the Evaluation of REAL IMAGING'S 3D Functional Metabolic Imaging and Risk Assessment (&quot;3D MIRA&quot;) System in Women With Breast Implants.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Real Imaging Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Real Imaging Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Israel: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Three-dimensional functional Metabolic Imaging (3D MIRA) is a new infrared imaging
      technology using the Real Imager 8 (RI8) developed by Real Imaging.  This technology
      generates 3D metabolic maps of the breast and based on sophisticated machine learning
      technology, provides objective risk assessment for the presence of malignant tumor in the
      breast. The procedure is non-invasive, comfortable and does not involve ionizing radiation.
      It is based on acquiring infrared images of the breast. Those images are processed and
      analyzed by computers to provide the objective risk assessment.

      The technology is intended to be used as a screening tool for breast cancer and emerges as
      highly useful  in women for whom screening mammography is sub-optimal, such as women with
      dense breast. 3D MIRA is unaffected by breast density and is therefore ideal for evaluating
      patients with mammographically dense breasts.

      Another group of women for whom screening mammography is sub-optimal are women with breast
      implants. There is reason to believe that 3D MIRA technology can be applied successfully for
      breast cancer screening in women with implants.

      The purpose of this clinical study is to assess the ability of this novel technology to
      detect  breast cancer in augmented women.

      The investigators hypothesize that the presence of breast implants will not affect the
      ability of this new technology to correctly classify healthy women and breast cancer
      patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Breast cancer remains a leading cause of cancer death among women, with an estimated 1.5
      million new cases and over 400,000 deaths annually worldwide.

      In recent years, however, improvements in survival rate have been attributed to earlier
      diagnosis by national screening programs and better treatments. Although mammography has
      been the main screening modality of early detection, its limitations are well recognized and
      the search for more effective technologies for early detection has been receiving increased
      attention. This is true for the general population and for augmented women the challenge is
      even greater.

      Breast augmentation is one of the most popular plastic surgeries in the western world.

      In United States alone an estimated 286,000 such procedures were performed in 2012.  Breast
      cancer occurs in about 1 of every 8 women; a projected 32,000 women who received breast
      implants in 2012 will develop cancer.

      Based on these statistics, it can be projected that substantial numbers of augmented women
      will develop breast cancer at some time during their lives.

      Hence, the need to screen and diagnose augmented women for breast cancer is of crucial
      importance. Available screening modalities for augmented women are not different from
      non-augmented women: Mammography, Ultrasound and Magnetic resonance imaging.

      Mammographic screening in women with implants presents a special challenge since breast
      implants can obscure mammographic findings which can decreases the ability to reveal breast
      cancer. Under normal mammographic techniques, radiation does not penetrate breast implants,
      and therefore, breast tissue may not be visualized over and under the implant in case of
      both silicone implants and saline implants.

      To overcome the obscuring of tissue by the implant, the implant displacement technique
      Eklund technique, in which the breast tissue is gently pulled over and in front of the
      augmentation prosthesis, has been used to image more breast tissue.

      However, even with the implant displacement technique, studies show that augmentation
      decreases the sensitivity of screening Mammography.

      Since augmented women undergo four additional imaging using the Eklund technique (two for
      each side), the radiation dose during Mammography is double that of non-augmented women

      Another recommended imaging modality for women with breast implants is Ultrasound.

      Previous studies showed that US can detect more breast cancers not seen on Mammography,
      particularly in dense breasts which present a similar radiological challenge as augmented
      breasts.

      However, breast US sensitivity is not very high anf it is highly operator-dependent.

      As opposed to US, Breast MRI is highly sensitive, however, it is not used as a screening
      tool for the general population. The high cost of MRI, its relatively low speciﬁcity, its
      being time consuming and its need for intravenous contrast agent make it unsuitable as a
      breast screening tool for the general population.

      In light of these shortcomings of existing screening modalities described, there is a real
      need for a novel breast imaging technology that may outperform the current modalities
      available for women with implants.

      Real Imaging developed a new infrared imaging technology called 3D MIRA ,(Three-dimensional
      functional Metabolic Imaging and Risk Assessment) using medical device, Real Imager 8 (RI8).
      The MIRA technology generates three-dimensional (3D) infrared (IR) metabolic maps of the
      breast and developed to enable efficient, automated computer analysis of those metabolic
      maps.

      A breast with malignant tumor behaves differently from a healthy breast. In this regard, the
      breast tumor has specific signatures on the surface of the breast even if the tumor is
      deeply embedded inside. These signatures can be detected using infrared imaging. The
      infrared signal contains information on both anatomical structures and metabolic processes
      within the breast.

      Based on those infrared signals MIRA technology can provide an objective risk assessment for
      the presence of malignant tumor. The risk assessment is an index  that represents the
      likelihood that a given image dataset includes a malignant finding. The index scale ranges
      from -100 (normal) to 100 (abnormal). The risk model is based on training the parameters on
      a calibration set of clinically known cases.

      The Real Imager 8.0 (RI8) is composed of two optical heads, each of which includes infrared
      camera digital camera and video projector. RI8 offers a non-invasive method for Metabolic
      Imaging and Risk Assessment (MIRA). The RI8 scan enables the determination of risk for
      breast cancer malignancy, based on assessment of several metabolic parameters. The device
      does not provide diagnosis or location of cancer. It will offer the physician a support tool
      to guide the patient to further imaging workup in order to locate, diagnose and characterize
      the tumor.

      The Imaging process is as follows:

      The imager is positioned at a distance of approximately 70 cm from the subject who is seated
      upright throughout the examination. This position will be maintained throughout the imaging
      session. An initial period of temperature equilibrium precede the imaging process, during
      which the patient sits in the dedicated imaging room with room temperature set at 18-22
      degrees Celsius. Following the temperature equilibration phase, continuous infrared imaging
      will be acquired for a period of up to 7 minutes. Two minutes after beginning of infrared
      recording, a metabolic stress test will be induced by having the patient wear cold gloves
      (0-5 degrees Celsius), which will be removed after 1 minute. This is performed for the
      purpose of generating vasoconstriction in the breast vessels. The entire imaging session
      will last approximately 22 minutes. The procedure is comfortable, non-invasive and does not
      emit or involves any ionizing radiation.

      In clinical trials conducted so far by Real Imaging MIRA exam has been carried out only in
      non-augmented women. We believe that the technology can be applied to augmented women
      successfully.

      MIRA Technology is unaffected by breast density as opposed to Mammography  since it is a
      functional imaging, which provides information on the metabolic nature of breast tissue.
      This main characteristic of the technology indicates that it might not be affected by the
      obscuring effect of implants as much as Mammography imaging.

      Moreover, it is possible that the implant may even increase the accuracy of the technology,
      since it isolates the breast tissue from the background organs, thus enhancing the
      separation between background tissue and breast tissue so that the metabolic signal of
      breast tissue is enhanced.

      In this data collection study, approximately 300 female subjects with breast implants will
      be enrolled at Sheba's Meirav Breast-health Center. MIRA's risk assessment will not be
      provided to the physician nor the subject.

      In order to evaluate MIRA's ability to classify augmented healthy women from those who have
      breast cancer, the enrollment will include two groups:

        1. Screening Group - augmented healthy women with no breast findings in previous screening
           exams

        2. Pre-Biopsy Group - augmented women with suspicious findings on recent Mammography
           and/or US and/or MRI exams (BI-RADS 4/5/6) who are summoned for biopsy for further
           workup.

      Eligible recruited subjects who have signed an informed consent will undergo MIRA imaging
      prior to being imaged by any other conventional imaging method and if relevant, prior to
      undergoing a breast biopsy.

      MIRA's data of every individual patient will be used for development purposes. The subject's
      personal, medical, diagnostic examination information and pathology results will be recorded
      in CRF's specially designed for this study. Each subject's clinical information will be
      followed up in order to validate MIRA's results.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case Control, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sufficient number of cancer case and controls have been imaged</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>As this is a data collection study, end point will be reached when approximately 50 women with breast cancer and 100 healthy women (controls) are imaged by the device and sufficient for the comparison statistical analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Women aged 30 years and older, who have breast implants and who, regardless of this
        clinical trial are summoned for routine breast cancer screening exam or breast biopsy due
        to suspicious finding in recent screening exam.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female

          -  Woman has read, understood and signed the inform consent form

          -  Age: 30 years and older

          -  Woman has breast implants

          -  Women who are asymptomatic and are scheduled to undergo routine Mx and/or US
             screening OR Women summoned for breast biopsy following a suspicious finding in
             recent screening exam and was graded 4/5/6 on BI-RADS scale

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women who have had a Mx and/or US and/or MRI examination performed on the day of the
             study prior to MIRA scan

          -  Women who had a lumpectomy surgery preceding the study

          -  Women who had undergone mastectomy and/or breast reconstruction

          -  Women who have undergone any type of breast surgery preceding the study

          -  Women who have had a breast biopsy performed throughout the 6 weeks preceding the
             study

          -  Women who have a fever on the day of the MIRA imaging

          -  Women who are pregnant

          -  Women who are breast-feeding

          -  Women with implanted pacemaker/defibrillator, implanted venous access device
             (portacath) or other implanted devices in the chest area

          -  Women who are unable to read, understand and execute written informed consent

          -  Women who are currently undergoing chemotherapy and/or radiotherapy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Miri Sklair-Levy, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Chaim Sheba Medical center at Tel-Hashomer</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>MIri Sklair-Levy, MD</last_name>
    <phone>972-3-5302514</phone>
    <email>Miri.SklairLevy@sheba.health.gov.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Chaim Sheba Medical Center at Tel Hashomer</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ramat-Gan</city>
        <zip>5262000</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <phone>972-3-5302514</phone>
      <email>Miri.SklairLevy@sheba.health.gov.il</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Miri Sklair-Levy, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 1, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast neoplasm</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast implants</keyword>
  <keyword>Mammography</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Imaging augmented breast</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
