<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="95939">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02121756</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DAIDS-ES ID 11987</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U01AI110410</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02121756</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dipyridamole for Immune Activation in HIV</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Pilot Study of Dipyridamole as a Modulator of Immune Activation and Systemic Inflammation in HIV-1-Infected Subjects on Antiretroviral Therapy- DAIDS-ES ID 11987</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sharon Riddler</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Data and Safety Monitoring Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine if Dipyridamole (DP) will decrease inflammation in
      HIV-1-infected individuals who are already on antiretroviral treatment and have a low viral
      load.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Since HIV-infected individuals started taking anti-HIV medications, illnesses from AIDS
           have decreased, but other serious diseases have increased. Researchers think this may
           be caused by an increase in activity of the immune system that fights infection,
           leading to inflammation.  Inflammation is a normal body reaction to any infection.
           However, if inflammation lasts a long time, like in HIV infection, it may lead to
           complications such as heart disease, cancer, liver disease, and problems with thinking.
           Many HIV researchers are studying the harmful effects of this prolonged immune system
           activity and inflammation and possible ways to prevent these complications.

        -  A drug called dipyridamole is approved by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) under
           the trade name Persantine® for use with other drugs to reduce the risk of blood clots
           after heart valve replacement. Laboratory studies have shown that dipyridamole also
           lowers the level of immune system activity and inflammation measured in the blood.

      Objectives:

        -  To see how dipyridamole affects blood tests to measure immune system activity and
           inflammation and to look at the safety and tolerability of dipyridamole in people
           infected with HIV. This use of dipyridamole is investigational, or not approved by the
           FDA; however, the dose to be used in this study, 100mg four times a day, is the dose
           approved by the FDA.

      Eligibility:

        -  Individuals 18 years of age and older who have HIV infection and are taking medications
           to treat it, and have a low viral load (HIV-1 RNA &lt;50 copies/mL) for a minimum of 12
           months.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam, blood test, and medical history.
           Women of reproductive age will also receive a pregnancy test.

        -  Participants will take either Dipyridamole or a placebo for 12 weeks. Then they will
           take Dipyridamole for 12 weeks.

        -  During the study, participants will have frequent blood and urine tests. Dipyridamole
           drug levels, and liver and kidney function tests will be performed. HIV viral load (the
           amount of virus in the blood) will also be studied.

        -  Participants will have a final follow-up visit after an additional 4 weeks.

        -  Four brachial artery ultrasound images will be taken.

        -  Participants will receive rectal swabs at screening, and four flexible sigmoidoscopies
           with rectal biopsies of the sigmoid colon throughout the study. These studies of the
           lower colon and samples of the rectum will be used to explore the effects of
           Dipyridamole.  Participants can, however, opt out of all rectal procedures.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in plasma levels of immune activation inflammatory markers</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in Plasma levels of sCD14 from baseline to week 12
Change in Plasma levels of sCD163 from baseline to week 12
Change in Plasma levels of IL-6 from baseline to week 12</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in plasma levels of immune activation inflammatory markers</measure>
    <time_frame>Entry to week 12 and week 24 (as applicable)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>%HLA-DR expression in CD8+ T-cells
%HLA-DR expression in CD4+ T-cells
CD38+ expression in CD8+ T-cells
CD38+ expression in CD4+ T-cells
%CD69 expression in CD4+ T-cells
%CD69 expression in CD8+ T-cells
CD25+ expression in CD4+ T-cells
CD25+ expression in CD8+ T-cells
CD16 expression in monocytes
Tissue factor expression in monocytes
Plasma levels of biomarker of systemic inflammation:  sTNFαR
Plasma levels of biomarker of systemic inflammation:  TNFα
Plasma levels of biomarker of systemic inflammation:  hsCRP
Plasma levels of biomarker of coagulation:  D-dimer
Plasma levels of biomarker of coagulation:  tissue factor
Percent brachial artery flow-mediated dilation (FMD)
Proportion of cycling CD4+ T-cells as measured by Ki-67 expression
Proportion of cycling CD8+ T-cells as measured by Ki-67 expression</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events, discontinuations of study drug</measure>
    <time_frame>Entry through week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Grade 2 or higher adverse events
Treatment discontinuations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of plasma Dipyridamole level to markers of immune activation and inflammation</measure>
    <time_frame>Entry through week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Correlation of plasma DP level to urine adenosine
Correlation of plasma DP level to plasma IL-6</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dipyridamole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ARM A:  Dipyridamole 100 mg 4 times daily for 24 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo, then Dipyridamole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>ARM B:  Dipyridamole placebo 1 capsule 4 times daily for 12 weeks, then Dipyridamole 100 mg 4 times daily for 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dipyridamole</intervention_name>
    <description>Dipyridamole 100 mg 4 times daily for 24 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dipyridamole</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Permole®</other_name>
    <other_name>Persantine®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo, then Dipyridamole</intervention_name>
    <description>Dipyridamole placebo 1 capsule 4 times daily for 12 weeks, then Dipyridamole 100 mg 4 times daily for 12 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo, then Dipyridamole</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Permole®</other_name>
    <other_name>Persantine®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV-1 infection, documented by any licensed rapid HIV test or HIV enzyme or
             chemiluminescence immunoassay (E/CIA) test kit at any time prior to study entry and
             confirmed by a licensed Western blot or a second antibody test by a method other than
             the initial rapid HIV and/or E/CIA, or by HIV-1 antigen, plasma HIV-1 RNA viral load.

          -  On ART for at least 12 months prior to study entry with a regimen that includes three
             or more antiretroviral medications. More information on this criterion is available
             in the protocol.

          -  Plasma HIV-1 RNA &lt;50 copies/mL by any standard clinical assay at screening and for a
             minimum of 12 months prior to entry, confirmed by at least 2 measurements prior to
             study entry, one of which must be at least 48 weeks prior to study entry and one of
             which must be 61 days and 48 weeks prior to study entry. All plasma HIV-1 RNA
             measurements in the 12 months prior to study entry must be &lt;50 copies/mL (with the
             exception that a single detectable measurement of ≤ 200 copies/mL is permitted if the
             RNA levels immediately before and after are &lt;50 copies/mL).

          -  Stable ART regimen for at least 8 weeks prior to study entry and no plans to change
             ART regimen for at least 6 months following study entry.

          -  Ability and willingness to provide informed consent.

          -  In the opinion of the investigator, no medical, mental health or other condition that
             precludes participation.

          -  Laboratory values obtained within 60 days prior to entry.

               -  Hemoglobin ≥10.0 g/dL

               -  Platelet count ≥100,000/mm3

               -  INR ≤ 1.5 (for rectal tissue subset only)

               -  PTT &lt;2x ULN (for rectal tissue subset only)

               -  AST and ALT &lt; 2.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  Total bilirubin &lt; 2.5 x ULN (except if hyperbilirubinemia is secondary to
                  atazanavir).

               -  Creatinine ≤ 1.5 x ULN

               -  Hepatitis B surface antigen negative

               -  Hepatitis C antibody negative (note: subject with HCV Ab positive is eligible if
                  Hepatitis C RNA PCR (viral load) is undetectable)

          -  For females of reproductive potential, negative serum or urine pregnancy test at
             screening and within 72 hours prior to study entry. Females of reproductive potential
             include women who have not been post-menopausal for at least 24 consecutive months,
             (i.e., who have had menses within the preceding 24 months, or women who have not
             undergone surgical sterilization, specifically hysterectomy and/or bilateral
             oophorectomy).

          -  Females of reproductive potential who are participating in sexual activity that could
             lead to pregnancy must agree to use one method of acceptable contraception while
             receiving protocol-specified treatment and for 4 weeks after stopping the treatment.
             These methods include condoms (male or female) with or without a spermicidal agent;
             diaphragm or cervical cap with spermicide; intrauterine device (IUD); and
             hormone-based contraceptive.

          -  Females not of reproductive potential (girls who have not reached menarche, women who
             have been post-menopausal for at least 24 consecutive months, or women who have
             undergone surgical sterilization, e.g., hysterectomy, bilateral oophorectomy, or
             bilateral tubal ligation or salpingectomy) are eligible without requiring the use of
             a contraceptive. Self- report is acceptable documentation of sterilization, other
             contraceptive methods, and menopause.

          -  Rectal Tissue Subset only: Willing to abstain from receptive anal intercourse and
             practices involving insertion of anything in the rectum (drug, enema, penis, or sex
             toy) for 72 hours prior to rectal biopsy and for 7 days post-biopsy to minimize risk
             of bleeding complications.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy or breast-feeding.

          -  Known allergy/sensitivity or any hypersensitivity to components of study drug(s) or
             their formulation.

          -  Known cardiovascular disease (history of MI, coronary artery bypass graft surgery,
             percutaneous coronary intervention, stroke, transient ischemic attack, peripheral
             arterial disease with ABI &lt;0.9 or claudication).

          -  Uncontrolled type II diabetes mellitus.

          -  Known chronic inflammatory conditions such as, but not limited to, rheumatoid
             arthritis, systemic lupus erythematosus, sarcoidosis, inflammatory bowel disease
             (i.e., Crohn's disease or ulcerative colitis), chronic pancreatitis, or autoimmune
             hepatitis, myositis, or myopathy.

          -  History of asthma requiring medical treatment within 2 years prior to study entry
             with the exception of the use of albuterol inhaler for mild intermittent asthma.

          -  Serious illness requiring systemic treatment and/or hospitalization within 14 days
             prior to entry.

          -  Use of any of the following medications for more than 3 consecutive days within the
             60 days prior to study entry:

               -  Immunosuppressives (e.g., azathioprine, corticosteroids [physiologic replacement
                  doses are allowed], cyclosporine, mycophenolate, NSAIDs (nonsteroidal
                  anti-inflammatory drugs), sirolimus, sulfasalazine, tacrolimus)

               -  Immune modulators (e.g., cytokines [e.g., IL-2], granulocyte colony stimulating
                  factor, growth hormone, tumor necrosis factor antagonists, thalidomide)

               -  Antineoplastic agents

               -  Anticoagulants (e.g., warfarin and heparin)

               -  Anti-platelet drugs (e.g., clopidogrel and aspirin)

          -  Vaccinations within 1 week prior to the pre-entry or study entry visits. Routine
             standard of care vaccinations including hepatitis A and/or B, influenza,
             pneumococcal, and tetanus are permitted if administered at least 7 days before
             pre-entry and entry evaluations.

          -  Participation on any HIV immunotherapy or therapeutic vaccination trials within 6
             months prior to study entry.

          -  Active drug or alcohol use or dependence that, in the opinion of the site
             investigator, would interfere with adherence to study requirements.

          -  Use of investigational therapies within 30 days prior to study entry.

          -  Rectal Tissue Subset only:

               -  Abnormalities of the colorectal mucosa or significant colorectal symptom(s),
                  which in the opinion of the study investigator represent a contraindication to
                  biopsy (including but not limited to presence of any unresolved injury,
                  infectious or inflammatory condition of the local mucosa, and presence of
                  symptomatic external hemorrhoids.

               -  Active untreated gonorrhea, or chlamydia infection within 30 days prior to study
                  entry (subjects diagnosed with rectal gonorrhea or chlamydia infection at
                  screening may be treated during the screening period provided the treatment is
                  at least 30 days prior to entry).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sharon A. Riddler, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jennifer M. van Panhuis, BA, BSN</last_name>
    <phone>412-624-5732</phone>
    <email>jms367@pitt.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Patricia E. Peters, RPh</last_name>
    <phone>724-515-6006</phone>
    <email>pep1@pitt.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pitt Treatment Evaluation Unit / University of Pittsburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Renee Weinman, BS, CCRP</last_name>
      <phone>412-647-0322</phone>
      <email>weinmandr@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sharon A. Riddler, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bernard JC Macatangay, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kaleab Z. Abebe, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Aryan N. Aiyer, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cranston D. Cranston, MD, FRCP</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ken S. Ho, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Edwin K. Jackson, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ian M. McGowan, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Deborah K. McMahon, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John W, Mellors, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ramakrishna Prasad, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Charles R. Rinaldo, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Theresa L. Whiteside, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 27, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 21, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sharon Riddler</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dipyridamole</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>Immune Markers</keyword>
  <keyword>Immune Activation</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dipyridamole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
