<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="3085">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01787201</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LU4261</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>Centra Health</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01787201</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of Exercise on Depression Symptoms Using Levels of Neurotransmitters and EEG as Markers</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effects of Exercise on Depression Symptoms Using Levels of Neurotransmitters and EEG as Markers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Liberty University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centura Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Liberty University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to examine the effects of exercise on the symptoms of
      depression using serum levels of serotonin, catecholamine's, Alpha EEG asymmetry, and
      self-report of symptoms as markers.

      In an attempt to further understand the mechanisms of improved mood through exercise; this
      study will examine the known factors that contribute to depressed mood in a single study
      using serotonin and catecholamine levels via blood serum and EEG slow wave asymmetry. Such
      information can be useful in understanding the overall neurological components of depression
      and the effects of exercise on the brain in depressed individuals that would make the
      prescription of exercise a viable treatment option.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There is an increasing demand for clinical effective, safe, and cost conscious forms of
      treatment for depression. Research shows depression to account for the largest decrease in
      overall health compared to asthma, angina, arthritis, and diabetes (Maussavi, 2007). The
      cost of lost productivity at work due to depression is a new focus of research as no current
      and accurate numbers exist. Stewart, Ricci, Hahn, &amp; Morganstein (2013) were among the first
      to examine this issue and found that lost productivity due to depression cost an estimated
      $44 billion dollars per year in spite of current medical treatments commonly prescribed. The
      lost productivity among those with depression and the low level of treatment suggest that
      there may be cost effective opportunities for improving depression outcomes within the
      general workforce and society at large.

      The question of value regarding the use of exercise as a treatment for depression has
      remained a source of investigation in recent years. In cooperation with Centra Health and
      Liberty University, this study seeks to understand the mechanisms that make exercise a
      viable treatment in depression by examining self-report of symptoms, serum levels of
      serotonin and catecholamines (epinephrine, norepinephrine, and dopamine) and frontal slow
      wave EEG activity as markers. Although these markers have been examined individually in
      previous studies, this is the only known study that examines each of these components in a
      single study. Such information can be useful in understanding the overall neurological
      components of depression and the effects of exercise on the brain in depressed individuals
      that would make the prescription of exercise a viable treatment in depression.

      Multiple trials, meta-analyses, and reviews have been conducted in the attempt to clarify
      the use of exercise in depressed patients. Research has shown that exercise as a treatment
      may result in fewer relapses than sertraline (Strohle, 2009). Similar results are indicated
      when exercise is prescribed as an adjunct treatment with psychotherapy (Balon, Sidhu, &amp;
      Pankhuree, 2009; Blumenthal, Smith, &amp; Hoffman, 2012; Gill, Womack, &amp; Safranek, 2010).
      Preliminary characteristics of the ideal dosage of exercise as a treatment have been
      researched, although a definitive dose-response curve has yet to be produced (Callaghan,
      Khalil, Morres, &amp; Carter, 2011; Perraton, Kumar, &amp; Machotka, 2010).

      Electroencephalographic (EEG) scans have been shown to demonstrate a left frontal bias in
      alpha (8-12 Hz) and theta (4-7 Hz) wave activity (Allen, Urry, Hitt, &amp; Coan, 2004; Demos,
      2005; Iosifescu et al., 2008; Nissen et al., 2006). The up-training or down-training of
      individual bandwidths in the treatment of depression, anxiety, ADHD, and traumatic brain
      injury have long been established (La Vaque, 2002). Although there are no established norms
      for neurotransmitter levels, we know through clinical medication trials that the inhibition
      of the reuptake of serotonin and or norepinephrine improve mood. Previous studies examining
      low levels of serotonin and decreased mood have found a correlation between exercise and
      increased serotonin availability without the use of pharmaceuticals (Chaouloff et al., 1985;
      Ernst, Olsen, Pinel, Lam, &amp; Christie, 2006; Jacobs &amp; Fornal, 1999). More routine type
      studies often use neurotransmitter levels as markers (Lande, Williams, Fileta, 2012;
      Lidberg, Tuck, Asberg, Scalia-Tomba, &amp; Bertilsson, 1985; Mann &amp; Stanley, 1984).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Scores on the Beck Depression Inventory-II</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline in BDI-II scores at 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The BDI-II is a 21 item self-report screening tool that measures symptoms of depression.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum levels of serotonin and catecholamines</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline in serotonin and catecholimine levels at 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood collection pre and post intervention for the processing of serum for serotonin and catecholamines.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Mean EEG alpha frequency data in the pre-frontal cortex.</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline in alpha mean frequency at 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants will have an EEG measuring pre-frontal cortex mean alpha frequency.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">11</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral: Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The experimental group will engage in mild-moderate level of exercise. This program will be structured and clinically supervised. Exercise will take place 2-3 days per week for a duration of 30-45 mins. for 6 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No Intervention: Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control group will serve as a wait list and not be exposed to the intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>The experimental group will engage in mild-moderate level of exercise. This program will be structured and clinically supervised. Exercise will take place 2-3 days per week for a duration of 30-45 mins. for 6 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral: Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Exercise</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  primary diagnosis of depression 18-65 years of age Physically fit to engage in
             physical exercise

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants with a history or current symptoms of psychosis anticipation of
             psychiatric medication changes over the course of the study Bipolar disorder or other
             disorder reflecting reality testing impairment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Timothy H Barclay, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Liberty University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Raymond D Barclay, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stetson University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James E Schoffstall, Ed.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Liberty University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Scott Richards, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts College of Pharmacy and Health Scoences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Liberty University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lynchburg</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>24502</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centra Health; Health Works</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lynchburg</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>24503</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allen JJ, Urry HL, Hitt SK, Coan JA. The stability of resting frontal electroencephalographic asymmetry in depression. Psychophysiology. 2004 Mar;41(2):269-80.</citation>
    <PMID>15032992</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chaouloff F, Elghozi JL, Guezennec Y, Laude D. Effects of conditioned running on plasma, liver and brain tryptophan and on brain 5-hydroxytryptamine metabolism of the rat. Br J Pharmacol. 1985 Sep;86(1):33-41.</citation>
    <PMID>2413941</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iosifescu DV, Greenwald S, Devlin P, Perlis RH, Denninger JW, Alpert JE, Fava M. Pretreatment frontal EEG and changes in suicidal ideation during SSRI treatment in major depressive disorder. Acta Psychiatr Scand. 2008 Apr;117(4):271-6. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-0447.2008.01156.x. Epub 2008 Feb 26.</citation>
    <PMID>18307587</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perraton LG, Kumar S, Machotka Z. Exercise parameters in the treatment of clinical depression: a systematic review of randomized controlled trials. J Eval Clin Pract. 2010 Jun;16(3):597-604. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2753.2009.01188.x. Epub 2009 Dec 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20039997</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stewart WF, Ricci JA, Chee E, Hahn SR, Morganstein D. Cost of lost productive work time among US workers with depression. JAMA. 2003 Jun 18;289(23):3135-44. Erratum in: JAMA. 2003 Oct 22;290(16):2218.</citation>
    <PMID>12813119</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ströhle A. Physical activity, exercise, depression and anxiety disorders. J Neural Transm. 2009 Jun;116(6):777-84. doi: 10.1007/s00702-008-0092-x. Epub 2008 Aug 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18726137</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 21, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 5, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Liberty University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Timothy H. Barclay</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor; Licensed Clinical Psychologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neurotransmitter Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
