<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="35257">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02054520</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NLG0304</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1303-1217</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02054520</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immunotherapy Study for Patients With Stage IV Melanoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase IIB Study of Ipilimumab With or Without HyperAcute®- Melanoma Immunotherapy for Stage IV Melanoma Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NewLink Genetics Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NewLink Genetics Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      For our current experimental clinical trial, patients are given 4 injections of ipilimumab,
      given 3 weeks apart x 4 injections with or without HAM immunotherapy. We propose to test
      this dual therapy in patients with melanoma who have known stage IV, metastatic melanoma. We
      hypothesize that this form of combinatorial immunotherapy will result in tumor stabilization
      or shrinkage, significant prolongation of progression-free, disease-free or overall survival
      compared to the use of ipilimumab alone.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Unfortunately, despite the best clinical efforts and breakthroughs in biotechnology, most
      patients diagnosed with advanced stage melanoma continue to die from their disease. Reasons
      for this include: 1) patients are often diagnosed at a time when their melanoma has already
      spread to other sites such as the chest cavity, bone, liver, and brain limiting the options
      for surgical excision and 2) the cancer cells are resistant or become resistant to
      chemotherapy drugs used to treat the patient. Resistance to one type of chemotherapy agent
      often rapidly leads to resistance against many other chemotherapy drugs. These reasons are
      the major causes of cancer progression that are usually discussed when considering treatment
      options for patients with disease that continues to grow and spread. However, another
      important part of the body should be considered-- the immune system. Scientists have clearly
      shown that melanoma cells produce a number of abnormal proteins or abnormal amounts of
      certain proteins found in normal melanoma cells. Normally one would expect a patient to
      develop an immune response against these abnormal proteins found in their cancer and attack
      them much the way we would fight off an infection from a foreign bacteria or virus. However,
      for reasons that scientists do not fully understand, the immune system fails to respond
      adequately to these abnormal proteins and does not destroy the melanoma cells. This human
      clinical trial proposes a new way to make the immune system recognize the cancer cells and
      encourages it to attack and destroy them.

      In this project, we have put a mouse gene into human melanoma cancer cells, so that those
      cells produce these abnormal sugar patterns and stimulate the immune system to attack the
      melanoma. This strategy works well to kill other human cancer cells in the laboratory, but
      it needs to be tried in melanoma patients to see if it will be effective and to determine if
      such a treatment causes any side effects. We propose to test this new treatment in patients
      with melanoma to see if it can stop, slow or destroy tumors in these patients. Patients will
      be injected with an anti-tumor immunotherapy consisting of three types of dead human
      melanoma cancer cells that have been genetically altered to express the mouse gene
      responsible for making this abnormal sugar-protein on the cells.

      In this Phase IIB Study, patients with advanced stage melanoma will undergo a series of
      intradermal injections with an immunotherapy(HyperAcute®-Melanoma) composed of irradiated
      allogeneic melanoma cell lines (HAM-1, HAM-2 and HAM-3). These cell lines have been
      transduced with a recombinant Moloney murine leukemia virus (MoMLV)-based retroviral vector
      expressing the murine α(1,3)GT gene. In addition to the HyperAcute®-Melanoma immunotherapy,
      some patients will also receive ipilimumab as an important component of this immunization
      strategy that will attempt to enhance and activate the host immune system to destroy growing
      tumor cells. Endpoints of the study include safety assessments, and clinical, tumor and
      immunological responses.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the safety of administration of ipilimumab with or without HyperAcute® Melanoma (HAM) immunotherapy for patients with stage IV melanoma</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To estimate the clinical response rate of metastatic melanoma patients after immunotherapy with HAM plus ipilimumab</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To estimate the disease-free survival (DFS), progression-free survival (PFS), overall survival (OS) and duration of overall response, duration of complete response (CR) and duration of stable disease (SD) of patients with stage IV melanoma treated with ipilimumab with or without HAM immunotherapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-tumor Immune Response</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To measure anti-tumor immune responses in melanoma metastases in responding and non-responding patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune Activation</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To further determine whether the humoral and cellular mediated arms of the host immune system are activated secondary to HAM combined with ipilimumab.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-Tumor Mechanism</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To perform correlative studies of patient samples (blood and tumor when available) to determine the mechanism of any observed anti-tumor effect.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Stage IV Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HyperAcute®-Melanoma (HAM) Immunotherapy + Ipilimumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm 1 will receive ipilimumab at 3 mg/kg given every 3 weeks for 4 weeks and 300 Million HyperAcute®-Melanoma (HAM) Immunotherapy cells per each immunization, given every week for 4 weeks, every 2 weeks for 5 months, every month for 6 months, and every 3 months for one year.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ipilimumab  Alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm 2 will receive ipilimumab alone at 3 mg/kg every 3 weeks for a total of four doses.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HyperAcute®-Melanoma (HAM) Immunotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>The HyperAcute®-Melanoma Immunotherapy consists of equal quantities of three cellular components. The cellular components (HAM-1, HAM-2, and HAM-3) of HyperAcute-Melanoma immunotherapy have been derived from allogeneic melanoma cancer cell lines.
Arm 1 only: Patients will receive 300 Million HAM cells administered intradermally at each scheduled immunization. HAM will be given every week for 4 weeks, every 2 weeks for 5 months, every month for 6 months, and every 3 months for one year.</description>
    <arm_group_label>HyperAcute®-Melanoma (HAM) Immunotherapy + Ipilimumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>HyperAcute®-Melanoma</other_name>
    <other_name>HAM</other_name>
    <other_name>Dorgenmeltucel-L</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ipilimumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Arm 1 and Arm 2:
Ipilimumab administered intravenously  at 3 mg/kg every three weeks for a total of four doses.</description>
    <arm_group_label>HyperAcute®-Melanoma (HAM) Immunotherapy + Ipilimumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ipilimumab  Alone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>YERVOY</other_name>
    <other_name>MDX-010</other_name>
    <other_name>MDX-101</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histological diagnosis of melanoma. AJCC Stage IV (any T, any N, M1), metastatic,
             progressive, refractory, melanoma.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status ≤1.

          -  Serum albumin ≥3.0 gm/dL.

          -  Adequate organ function including:

               -  A. Marrow: Hemoglobin ≥10.0 gm/dL, absolute granulocyte count (AGC) ≥1,000/mm3,
                  platelets ≥75,000/mm3, absolute lymphocyte count ≥475/mm3.

               -  B. Hepatic: Serum total bilirubin ≤2.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN), ALT (SGPT)
                  and AST (SGOT) ≤2.5 x ULN.

               -  C. Renal: Serum creatinine (sCr) ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of normal.

          -  Prior therapy for melanoma that may include surgery, radiation therapy, immunotherapy
             including interleukins and interferon, and/or ≤2 different regiments of systemic
             chemotherapy, targeted therapy, or other experimental systemic therapies. Prior
             treatment with CTLA4 antibodies will be an exclusion criteria (see Exclusions).

          -  Patients must be ≥4 weeks since major surgery, radiotherapy, chemotherapy (6 weeks if
             they were treated with nitrosureas) or biotherapy/targeted therapies.

          -  Patients must have the ability to understand the study, its risks, side effects,
             potential benefits and be able to give written informed consent to participate.
             Patients may not be consented by a durable power of attorney (DPA).

          -  Male and female subjects of child producing potential must agree to use contraception
             or avoidance of pregnancy measures while enrolled on study and receiving the
             experimental drug, and for one month after the last immunization.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &lt;18-years-old.

          -  Active CNS metastases or carcinomatous meningitis. Patients with CNS lesions that
             have been treated and who have no evidence of progression in the brain on CT/MRI for

             ≥1 month are eligible. Pregnant or nursing women due to the unknown effects of
             immunization on the developing fetus or newborn infant.

          -  Other malignancy within five years, except the following may be eligible:

               -  patients curatively treated for localized squamous or basal cell carcinoma of
                  the skin or for carcinoma in situ of the uterine cervix (CIN) or breast,

               -  patients with a history of malignant tumor who have been disease free for at
                  least five years and are not currently being treated.

          -  History of an allogeneic solid organ transplant or bone marrow transplant, or current
             active immunosuppressive therapy such as cyclosporine, tacrolimus, etc.

          -  Subjects taking systemic (parentally or orally) corticosteroid therapy for any
             reason, including replacement therapy for hypoadrenalism, are not eligible. Topical
             steroids are acceptable as are intranasal steroids.

          -  Active infection or antibiotics within 48 hours prior to study enrollment, including
             unexplained fever (temp &gt; 38.1°C), if deemed clinically significant by the treating
             physician.

          -  Evidence of active autoimmune disease (e.g., systemic lupus erythematosis, rheumatoid
             arthritis, with the exception of vitiligo. Patients with a remote history of asthma
             or mild asthma are eligible.

          -  Other serious medical conditions that may be expected to limit life expectancy to
             less than 2 years (e.g., liver cirrhosis).

          -  Any condition, psychiatric or otherwise, that would preclude informed consent,
             consistent follow-up or compliance with any aspect of the study (e.g., untreated
             schizophrenia or other significant cognitive impairment, etc).

          -  Patients having previously undergone splenectomy.

          -  Patients with known hepatitis or unstable liver disease, and/or positive serologies
             for Hepatitis B or C and HIV.

          -  Patients with sickle-cell anemia or thalassemia major.

          -  Subjects who received prior treatment with ipilimumab or tremelimumab or other
             antibody to CTLA4.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicholas Vahanian, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>NewLink Genetics Corporation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Tennessee Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Knoxville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37920</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shanna Overbey</last_name>
      <phone>865-305-5281</phone>
      <email>soverbey@utmck.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Janakiraman Subramanian, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 1, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 3, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stage IV</keyword>
  <keyword>metastatic melanoma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
