<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="158181">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02046993</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KW/EX-13-026(60-09)</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HKCFPRFG2013</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02046993</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Smart Phone Based Telemonitoring on Blood Pressure Among Hypertensive Patients in Primary Care</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Smart Phone Based Telemonitoring on Blood Pressure Among Hypertensive Patients in Primary Care</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kwong Wah Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kwong Wah Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Hong Kong: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To test the hypothesis that hypertensive patients who participate in smart phone based
      telemonitoring of BP will conduct more home blood pressure monitoring, better self
      management behavior and greater reduction in blood pressure and better self management
      behaviour from baseline to 6 months follow up than those patients receiving usual care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A prospective, block randomized controlled 6 months study comparing the blood pressure
      control of hypertensive patients who participate in usual care plus smart phone based
      telemonitoring (TM) of BP to hypertensive patients receiving usual care (UC) alone in
      primary care setting. Following the inclusion and exclusion criteria, subjects will be
      recruited on voluntary basis for this study. The investigators plan to recruit 160 subjects
      based on our previous findings, 48% of hypertensive patients had recorded home blood
      pressure (BP) readings and only 14% of patients would present the BP record to doctors while
      on follow up, the investigators expect the rate will increase the rate to around 40% with
      the intervention. Therefore, for detecting the difference with 5% level of significance and
      80% of power, a sample size of 57 is needed at each comparison group. With attrition rate of
      30%, 80 patients will be allocated to each group.

      Having obtained informed consent, all subjects will be required to attend a hypertension
      workshop which includes overview of the disease, importance and benefits of self BP
      monitoring as well as teaching of correct techniques of BP measurement. All participants are
      required to pass the assessment on self BP measurement facilitated by trained research
      assistants, supervised by nurses or doctors. All participating subjects will be allocated
      using block randomization into the intervention group (TM) or control group (UC). Research
      assistants doing the assessments at baseline, 3 months and 6 months post intervention will
      be blinded to the groupings.At baseline and follow-up visits, research assistants who are
      blinded to allocation outcomes will measure blood pressure after 15 minutes rest with
      validated electronic automated sphygmomanometer. Four blood pressure readings taken at 1
      minute interval will done for each subject and the mean of the 2nd and 3rd readings would be
      used for the outcome measures. For intervention group, patients will be assisted to download
      a mobile application tool (apps), specifically developed for use in telerecording of
      readings from home self BP measurement. For the control group, patients will be encouraged
      on self BP monitoring and keep the BP diary.

      Comparisons between these two groups in terms of compliance to home BP measurement and
      readings,proportion of patients doing home BP monitoring,self-efficacy outcomes and
      improvement in clinic BP readings at 3 months and 6 months post-intervention will be
      assessed using statistical analysis.Data analyses were conducted using the Statistical
      package for the Social Sciences (SPSS) version 16.0. Descriptive statistics, including
      frequency and percentage for categorical variables and mean and standard deviation for
      continuous variable, were used to describe the demographic characteristics and summarize
      baseline characteristics of the variables. Paired T-test was performed to examine the
      differences of outcome measures before and after intervention program within group. Analysis
      of variance (ANOVA) is used to examine the differences of outcome variables between TM and
      UC group. A p-value of 0.05 was used as the level of statistical significance.

      The principal investigator and sub-investigator will do regular monitoring, conduct regular
      meetings with research team to ensure quality assurance in patient recruitment, data
      collection, data management, data analysis, reporting for adverse events.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects doing home BP monitoring</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of subjects doing home BP monitoring at least 3 times/week</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Systolic and diastolic mean blood pressure readings</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subjects' baseline clinic mean blood pressure readings will be compared with clinic mean blood pressure readings at 3 months and 6 months post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PAM-13</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient Activation Measure ( PAM-13) The Patient Activation Measure (PAM-13) assessment gauges the knowledge, skills and confidence essential to managing one's own health and healthcare.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-efficacy for Managing Chronic Disease: 6 Items Scale (SEMCD-6 Items).</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This is a 6-items scale for measuring self efficacy in patients with chronic disease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Smart phone based telemonitoring of HBP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Smart phone based telemonitoring home blood pressure (HBP)
. Patients do HBP monitoring
. record their BP readings into the smart phone with downloaded application.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hypertensive patients on usual care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Hypertensive patients on usual care
. Patients to do HBP measurement
. Record BP readings in their diary</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Smart phone telemonitoring HBP</intervention_name>
    <description>Smart phone telemonitoring home Blood pressure (HBP) Patients to do home BP measurement and input into their smart phone which is sent to the central server fortnightly</description>
    <arm_group_label>Smart phone based telemonitoring of HBP</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hypertensive patient on usual care</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient do home BP monitoring Record the Home BP monitoring in their diary</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hypertensive patients on usual care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. All hypertensive patients aged 30 or above and using smart phone

          2. Agrees to participate in this pilot study

          3. Competent in self BP measurement

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients could not use the smart phone independently, such as mentally or physically
             incapacitated.

          2. Patients are not competent in verbal or written communication.

             -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lorna Ng, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(852)35172310</phone>
    <email>ngl@ha.org.hk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kwong Wah Hospital General Out-Patient and Family Medicine Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <state>Kowloon, Hong Kong</state>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lorna Ng, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(852) 35172257</phone>
      <email>ngl@ha.org.hk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lorna Ng, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lap King Chiang, MBBS</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 27, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 25, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Kwong Wah Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lorna Ventura Ng</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior Medical Officer</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hypertension</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
