<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="77424">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02153645</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OS320-3005</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02153645</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety of Amantadine ER Tablets to Treat Parkinson's Disease Patients With Levodopa Induced Dyskinesia.</brief_title>
  <acronym>ALLAY-LID I</acronym>
  <official_title>A Multicenter, Randomized, Placebo-controlled, Double-blind, 16 Week Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Amantadine HCl Extended Release Tablets in Parkinson's Disease Subjects With Levodopa-Induced Dyskinesias</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Osmotica Pharmaceutical Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Osmotica Pharmaceutical Corp.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <authority>France: Agence Nationale de Sécurité du Médicament et des produits de santé</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Spanish Agency of Medicines</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Amantadine has been used for many years as a treatment for Parkinson's disease. It has been
      reported in the literature to effectively treat the motor complications of levodopa,
      especially dyskinesia, but it must be given 2 to 4 times a day. The purpose of this
      multi-center, randomized, double-blind, parallel-group, 16 week study is to compare the
      efficacy and safety of two different dose levels of Amantadine Extended Release Tablets to
      placebo for the treatment of levodopa induced dyskinesia in patients with Parkinson's
      disease. The dose will be given once a day in the morning so that amantadine concentrations
      are maintained throughout the day for treating the levodopa induced dyskinesia, but will be
      lower during the night, potentially reducing the negative impact of amantadine on sleep.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Unified Dyskinesia Rating Scale (UDysRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>14 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The change from baseline to day 98 (Visit 7) of treatment in the sum of the items comprising the Unified Dyskinesia Rating Scale (UDysRS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Unified Dyskinesia Rating Scale (UDysRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>14 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The change from baseline of treatment in the sum of the items comprising the Unified Dyskinesia Rating Scale (UDysRS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mobility State Self-Assessment (Subject Diary Cards)</measure>
    <time_frame>14 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The change from baseline in the percent of waking hours that subjects report being &quot;OFF&quot; having no dyskinesias, non-troublesome dyskinesias, and troublesome dyskinesias in the Mobility State Self-Assessment (Subject Diary Cards)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mobility State Self-Assessment (Subject Diary Cards)</measure>
    <time_frame>14 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The change from baseline in the percent of waking hours that subjects report being &quot;ON&quot; having no dyskinesias, non-troublesome dyskinesias, and troublesome dyskinesias in the Mobility State Self-Assessment (Subject Diary Cards)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MDS-UPDRS</measure>
    <time_frame>14 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The change from baseline in the sum of Parts II, and III of the MDS-UPDRS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fatigue Severity Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>14 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The change from baseline in the Fatigue Severity Scale (FSS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">162</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <condition>Levodopa Induced Dyskinesia (LID)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>240mg Amantadine HCl ER tablets</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Amantadine HCl ER Tablets 240mg daily for 12 weeks post two week titration phase.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>320mg Amantadine HCl ER tablets</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Amantadine HCl ER Tablets 320mg daily for 12 weeks post a two week dose titration phase.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Tablets for Amantadine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo Tablets matching Amantadine HCl ER Tablets taken daily for 16 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Amantadine ER Tablets</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>240mg Amantadine HCl ER tablets</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>320mg Amantadine HCl ER tablets</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ALLAY-LID I</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Tablets for Amantadine ER Tablets</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Tablets for Amantadine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Signed IRB/IEC informed consent form.,

          -  Idiopathic Parkinson's disease per the UK Parkinson's Disease Society Brain Bank
             criteria.

          -  Male or female 30 to 85 years old.

          -  Levodopa induced, predictable peak-effect dyskinesia considered problematic and/or
             disabling.

          -  Screening serum creatinine level within normal range

          -  On stable doses of all oral anti-Parkinson's medication, including any levodopa
             preparation, for 30 days and be willing to remain on the same doses throughout the
             trial.

          -  The subject/caregiver must demonstrate the ability to complete an accurate home diary
             based on training and evaluation during the screening period.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Secondary parkinsonian syndrome, such as vascular, postinflammatory,drug-induced,
             neoplastic and post-traumatic parkinsonism or any atypical parkinsonian syndrome
             (e.g., Progressive Supranuclear Palsy, Multi-System Atrophy, etc.);

          -  Use of amantadine within 14 days before study start, or previously had an adverse
             event to amantadine

          -  Currently taking neuroleptics and atypical antipsychotic agents, acetylcholinesterase
             inhibitors, apomorphine, rimantadine, memantine and dextromethorphan and quinidine if
             used in combination for treating dyskinesia.

          -  History of neurosurgical intervention for treating Parkinson's s disease (i.e.
             pallidotomy or implanted with a deep brain stimulator).

          -  Any medical condition or past medical history that would increase the risk of
             exposure to Amantadine HCl Extended Release Tablets or interfere with safety and
             efficacy evaluations.

          -  History of cancer within 5 years of screening with following exceptions: adequately
             treated non-melanomatous skin cancers, localized bladder cancer, non-metastatic
             prostate cancer or in situ cervical cancer.

          -  History or current diagnosis of schizophrenia or bipolar disorder;

          -  Inadequately treated Major Depressive Disorder. Subjects on stable doses of selective
             serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) or serotonin-norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors
             (SNRIs) are eligible for the study.

          -  Is at imminent risk of suicide or had a suicide attempt within 6 months of screening

          -  History or current diagnosis of Impulse Control Disorder

          -  Calculated plasma creatinine clearance of &lt;60 mL/min at screening

          -  History of or currently has any of the following clinically significant conditions,
             cardiovascular, respiratory, renal, hepatic, or gastrointestinal disease

          -  Any clinically significant vital sign, ECG, or laboratory abnormalities:

          -  A positive test for HIV antibody of history of HIV; hepatitis B surface antigen
             unless the positive test followed a recent (&lt;28 days) vaccination for hepatitis B;
             hepatitis C antibody.

          -  A positive urine drug test.

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding at screening or has a positive pregnancy test

          -  If a sexually active female, is not surgically sterile or at least 2 years
             post-menopausal, or does not agree to utilize an effective method of contraception
             from the screening visit to at least 4 weeks after the completion of study treatment.

          -  History of alcohol or narcotic substance abuse ≤1 year before screening. Has dementia
             or another psychiatric illness that prevents provision of informed consent.

          -  Has a known hypersensitivity to the study treatment(s), based on known allergies to
             drugs of the same class including rimantadine HCl and memantine HCl.

          -  Has participated in other studies involving investigational drugs or surgeries within
             the last 30 days or investigational biologics within the last 6 months prior to
             screening.

          -  Plans to undergo major elective surgery during the course of the study.

          -  Received administration of Live Attenuated Influenza Vaccine (LAIV) within 2 weeks.

          -  Cognitive impairment, as evidenced by a score &lt;26 on the Montreal Cognitive
             Assessment (MoCA) at the screening visit.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gene Wright, PharmD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Osmotica Pharmaceutical Corp.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gene Wright, PharmD, PhD</last_name>
    <email>gwright@osmotica.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Angela Dentiste, MBA</last_name>
    <email>dentiste@osmotica.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 30, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 30, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Parkinson's Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Levodopa Induced Dyskinesias (LID)</keyword>
  <keyword>Dyskinesias</keyword>
  <keyword>Parkinsonism</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dyskinesias</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Amantadine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levodopa</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
