<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="104334">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02083861</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ZetrOZ-01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R43MD008597-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02083861</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Wearable LITUS Device for Osteoarthritis of the Knee: a Randomized Double-Blind Placebo-Controlled Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>ZetrOZ Wearable Ultrasound Clinical Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>ZetrOZ, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Center on Minority Health and Health Disparities (NCMHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>ZetrOZ, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to measure the effectiveness of a wearable therapeutic
      ultrasound device in patients with stage I and stage II knee osteoarthritis. The ability of
      the device to reduce pain, increase mobility, increase range of motion and muscle strength
      of the affected leg, and improve quality of life in patients with knee osteoarthritis will
      be evaluated.

      While the use of ultrasound to treat pain is established in the field, the ability to
      deliver low intensity, therapeutic ultrasound on a daily basis is new. The use of a wearable
      ultrasound device to deliver daily, low intensity, long duration ultrasound has been
      approved by the FDA for pain relief, relief of joint contracture, relief of muscle spasm,
      and increased circulation; however, it is not yet indicated for relief of knee
      osteoarthritis. The interventional device in this study is self-applied by the patient and
      worn daily for 4 hours of continuous therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an eight week study to clinically evaluate the effect of the low intensity long
      duration (LITUS) ultrasound device on symptoms of patients suffering from knee
      osteoarthritis. The device, Sam® has been FDA-cleared for use. For the first two weeks of
      the study, baseline data will be collected as patients report pain scores (VAS) and an
      actigraph worn by the patient digitally records mobility data. During the following 6 weeks,
      patients will self-apply the wearable low intensity ultrasound device to their affected knee
      for 4 hours daily. Each day of the study, pain scores (VAS) and mobility data (actigraph)
      will be recorded. A quality of life assessment (WOMAC), muscle strength and range of motion
      assessment (JTech) will be performed prior to the patient beginning the protocol and at the
      conclusion of the protocol.

      80 subjects will be recruited from neighboring communities to the study site. The study is
      designed to reach a target patient population which includes rural citizens and
      socioeconomic disadvantaged individuals where non-pharmacotherapies do not exist to manage
      pain. Subjects will be randomly assigned to active (60%) and placebo groups (40%). The
      sponsor and investigators are blinded as to which type of device each patient is assigned.

      The study will be monitored by an external monitor and a data safety monitoring board
      (DSMB).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pain on the visual analog scale (VAS) from baseline to study conclusion</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pain score (VAS) from the previous day</measure>
    <time_frame>Daily: Day 0, Day 1...Day 56</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in mobility from baseline to study conclusion</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients wear an actigraph (a wearable accelerometer clinically proven to capture high resolution movement data and physical activity measures) throughout all waking hours of the study. (www.actigraphcorp.com)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in mobility from previous day</measure>
    <time_frame>Daily: Day 0, Day 1...Day 56</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients wear an actigraph (a wearable accelerometer clinically proven to capture high resolution movement data and physical activity measures) throughout all waking hours of the study. (www.actigraphcorp.com)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in quality of life from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>WOMAC questionnaire will be utilized (Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Arthritis Index)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in range of motion and muscle strength of affected knee vs. unaffected knee</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>JTech equipment will be leveraged to evaluate muscle strength and range of motion using a dynamometer and inclinometer (www.jtechmedical.com)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with Serious and Non-Serious Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline through Week 8 (duration of study)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Knee Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active ultrasound device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive treatment from the Sam Ultrasonic Diathermy Device for 4 hours every day for 6 weeks. The active device emits continuous ultrasound at 3 megahertz (MHz) frequency and 0.132 watts/cm2 intensity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo ultrasound device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients wear the Sam Ultrasonic Diathermy Device for 4 hours every day for 6 weeks. The placebo device appears and operates identically to the active device except that it does not emit ultrasound.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sam Ultrasonic Diathermy Device</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients apply the Sam Ultrasonic Diathermy Device daily for 4 hours of continuous therapeutic ultrasound at 3 megahertz (MHz) frequency and 0.132 Watts/cm2.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active ultrasound device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo ultrasound device</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ZetrOZ ultrasound device</other_name>
    <other_name>wearable ultrasound device</other_name>
    <other_name>long duration ultrasound</other_name>
    <other_name>LITUS device</other_name>
    <other_name>long duration low intensity device</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Physician-diagnosed mild to moderate knee osteoarthritis (OARSI atlas grades 1-2)
             based on fixed-flexion x-ray radiological findings for osteophytes and joint space
             narrowing within the past 12 months

          -  Fulfill the American College of Rheumatology clinical and radiological diagnostic
             criteria for knee OA

          -  35-80 years of age

          -  Report a frequent pain score between 3-7 (VAS range: 0-10) during the week preceding
             enrollment

          -  Report that knee pain negatively affects quality of life

          -  Willing not to use any cream, gel, or topical solution during the administration of
             treatment other than the approved ultrasound gel provided to the subject at the
             initiation of the study

          -  Deemed appropriate by their physician or by the study site physician to participate

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Cannot successfully demonstrate the ability to put on and take off the device

          -  Display any condition which, in the judgment of the investigator, would make
             participation in the study unacceptable, including, but not limited to, the subject's
             ability to understand and follow instructions.

          -  Have severe OA or have little to no cartilage in the knee

          -  Have knee replacement,  other surgical intervention, or hyaluronidase injection in
             the affected knee in the past 6 months

          -  Are non-ambulatory

          -  Participated in a clinical trial for an investigational drug and/or agent within 30
             days prior to screening

          -  Modify their medications during the course of the study (medications and doses must
             remain constant throughout the study)

          -  Currently taking steroids

          -  Have contraindication to radiograph

          -  Have a secondary cause of arthritis (metabolic or inflammatory)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ralph Ortiz, D.O., MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical Pain Consultants</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ralph Ortiz, D.O., MPH</last_name>
    <phone>607-844-9979</phone>
    <email>rodocdo@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Rebecca Taggart, B.S.</last_name>
    <phone>203-306-9241</phone>
    <email>rtaggart@zetroz.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical Pain Consultants</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dryden</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>13053</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ralph Ortiz, D.O., MPH</last_name>
      <phone>607-844-9979</phone>
      <email>rodocdo@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Rebecca Taggart, B.S.</last_name>
      <phone>203-306-9241</phone>
      <email>rtaggart@zetroz.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ralph Ortiz, D.O./MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>George K Lewis, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rebecca M Taggart, B.S.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vanessa Levine, M.S.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 7, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>osteoarthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>arthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>musculoskeletal</keyword>
  <keyword>connective tissue disease</keyword>
  <keyword>ultrasound</keyword>
  <keyword>pain</keyword>
  <keyword>mobility</keyword>
  <keyword>heat</keyword>
  <keyword>strength</keyword>
  <keyword>ZetrOZ</keyword>
  <keyword>LITUS</keyword>
  <keyword>Sam</keyword>
  <keyword>grade 1</keyword>
  <keyword>grade 2</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
