<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="21599">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01777412</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Avastin_NMO_1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01777412</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy of Bevacizumab (Avastin) in Treatment of Acute NMO Exacerbations</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label Phase 1b Study of Avastin® (Bevacizumab) for the Treatment of Acute Optic Neuritis and/or Transverse Myelitis in Neuromyelitis Optica (NMO) and Neuromyelitis Optica Spectrum Disorder (NMOSD).</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genentech</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Guthy Jackson Charitable Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase 1b interventional trial of bevacizumab (Avastin®) to evaluate the
      tolerability/safety and preliminary efficacy of bevacizumab (Avastin®) as add-on therapy for
      treatment of acute optic neuritis and/or transverse myelitis in neuromyelitis optica (NMO)
      and neuromyelitis optica spectrum disorder (NMOSD). A single infusion of Avastin® is added
      to standard-of-care high dose steroids and an additional dose of Avastin® is added to plasma
      exchange (if necessary). The primary outcomes are clinical changes in the Expanded
      Disability Severity Scale, Timed 25-foot Walk and Low Contrast Visual Acuity, MRI parameters
      and safety.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Objective: The overall objective is to evaluate the tolerability/safety and efficacy
      of adding bevacizumab (Avastin®) to standard of care therapy in improving clinical and
      radiologic outcomes of acute optic neuritis and/or transverse myelitis in neuromyelitis
      optica and neuromyelitis optica spectrum disorders.

      Primary Objective: To compare the clinical and radiographic outcome following acute optic
      neuritis and/or transverse myelitis in NMO/NMOSD in patients who receive 1-2 doses of 10
      mg/kg dose of bevacizumab (Avastin®) in addition to standard medical therapy.

      Secondary Objectives:

        -  To determine the effect of Avastin on NMO clinical scores (Expanded Disability Status
           Scale, Timed 25-foot Walk and Low Contrast Visual Acuity [LCVA]).

        -  To evaluate the safety and tolerability of a 10 mg/kg dose of intravenous Avastin.

        -  To determine the frequency of adverse events with Avastin in this patient population.

        -  To determine the effect of Avastin on MRI lesion size and extent.

      The duration of the investigation is 1-2 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite change in Expanded Disability Status Score (EDSS), Low Contrast Visual Acuity (LCVA) and Timed 25-Foot Walk</measure>
    <time_frame>91 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>EDSS
The EDSS provides a total score on a scale that ranges from 0 to 10.  The first levels 1.0 to 4.5 refer to people with a high degree of ambulatory ability and the subsequent levels 5.0 to 9.5 refer to the loss of ambulatory ability.
LCVA
Low Contrast Visual Acuity: Low-contrast Sloan letter charts are readily available and provide a practical, quantitative, and standardized assessment of visual function. 2.5% low contrast visual acuity will be measured daily during the steroid phase and weekly during the plasma exchange phase, the day after a bevacizumab (Avastin®) infusion.
Timed 25-Foot Walk
Timed 25-foot walking trials will be assessed every day during the steroid phase and weekly in the plasma exchange phase, the day after a bevacizumab (Avastin®) infusion.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>91 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Frequency and severity of adverse events.
Frequency of serious adverse events.
Percentage of subjects withdrawing due to adverse events.
Change from baseline in hematology, chemistry, and urinalysis parameters.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MRI changes</measure>
    <time_frame>91 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MRIs will be performed for standard of care purposes and will be used to make clinical decisions about escalation of immunosuppressive treatment. For this study, the MRIs will also be analyzed for two parameters: length of T2 hyperintensity in the spinal cord and optic nerve and volume and pattern of T1 post-contrast enhancement if available.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Neuromyelitis Optica</condition>
  <condition>Neuromyelitis Optica Spectrum Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bevacizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Bevacizumab 10 mg/kg intravenous infusion at onset of exacerbation and, if needed, a second time during the plasma exchange phase.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bevacizumab</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Bevacizumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Avastin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Subjects eligible for enrollment must meet all of the following criteria:

          1. Able and willing to provide written informed consent.

          2. 18-70 years of age.

          3. New acute optic neuritis and/or transverse myelitis. A clinical event is defined as
             an episode of inflammation in the spinal cord and/or optic nerve leading to
             neurologic symptoms not ascribed to another disease process.

          4. Known or suspected diagnosis of NMO according to the 2006 revisions of the Wingerchuk
             diagnostic criteria for NMO or AQP4 positive NMOSD per the EFNS Guidelines. For NMO,
             subjects must have two absolute criteria:

               1. optic neuritis

               2. myelitis and at least two of three supportive criteria:

               3. presence of a contiguous spinal cord MRI lesion extending over three or more
                  vertebral segments,

               4. MRI criteria NOT satisfying the revised McDonald diagnostic criteria for MS
                  [Polman, 2011]

               5. NMO-IgG (AQP4) in serum. For NMOSD, subjects must have longitudinally extensive
                  transverse myelitis (LETM) recurrent isolated optic neuritis (RION)/bilateral
                  optic neuritis (BON), or opticospinal multiple sclerosis (OSMS) that is AQP4
                  antibody positive

          5. A female subject is eligible to enter the study if she is:

        A. Not pregnant or nursing; B. Of non-childbearing potential (i.e. women who have had a
        hysterectomy, are postmenopausal, which is defined as &gt;2 years without menses (female
        subjects who have been post-menopausal for &lt;2 years must be confirmed with Follicle
        Stimulating Hormone (FSH) and estradiol levels), have both ovaries surgically removed or
        have current documented tubal ligation); or,

        C. Of childbearing potential (i.e. women with functional ovaries and no documented
        impairment of oviductal or uterine function that would cause sterility).  This category
        includes women with oligomenorrhoea (even severe), women who are perimenopausal or have
        just begun to menstruate. The subject must have a negative serum pregnancy test at
        screening and agrees to one of the following:

        i. Complete abstinence from intercourse for the period from consent into the study until 6
        months after the last dose of investigational product; or, ii. Consistent and correct use
        of one of the following acceptable methods of birth control for the period from consent
        into the study until 6 months after the last dose of investigational product:

          1. Oral contraceptives (either combined or progesterone only)

          2. Injectable progesterone

          3. Levonorgestrel implants

          4. Estrogenic vaginal ring

          5. Percutaneous contraceptive patches

          6. Intrauterine device (IUD) or intrauterine system (IUS) with a documented failure rate
             of &lt;1% per year

          7. Male partner sterilization (vasectomy with documentation of azoospermia) prior to the
             female subject's entry into the study; this male must be the sole partner for the
             subject

          8. Double barrier method: condom and an occlusive cap (diaphragm or cervical/vault caps)
             with a vaginal spermicidal agent (foam/gel/film/cream/suppository).

        Subjects meeting any of the following criteria are not eligible and cannot enroll in the
        study:

          1. Evidence or history of clinically significant infection including:

               1. Chronic or ongoing active infectious disease requiring long term systemic
                  treatment such as, but not limited to: PML, chronic renal infection, chronic
                  chest infection with bronchiectasis, tuberculosis, or active hepatitis C.

               2. Positive test for HBsAg.

               3. Prior history, or suspicion, of tuberculosis (TB)

               4. History of positive serology for HIV.

          2. Past or current malignancy, except for

               1. Cervical carcinoma Stage 1B or less

               2. Non-invasive basal cell and squamous cell skin carcinoma

               3. Cancer diagnoses with a duration of complete response (remission) &gt;5 years

               4. A history of hematologic malignancy excludes a subject from participation,
                  regardless of response.

          3. Recent major surgery within the last 28 days.

          4. Significant concurrent, uncontrolled medical condition including, but not limited to,
              cardiac, renal, hepatic, hematological, gastrointestinal, endocrine,
             immunodeficiency syndrome, pulmonary, cerebral, psychiatric, or neurological disease
             which could affect the subject's safety, impair the subject's reliable participation
             in the trial, impair the evaluation of endpoints, or necessitate the use of
             medication not allowed by the protocol.

          5. Use of an investigational drug or other experimental therapy for a condition other
             than NMO within 4 weeks, 5 pharmacokinetic half lives or duration of biological
             effect (whichever is longer) prior to screening.

          6. Current participation in any other interventional clinical trial.  Participation in
             non-interventional trial requires approval of the protocol by investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Levy, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Maureen Mealy, RN</last_name>
    <phone>410-502-8672</phone>
    <email>mmealy1@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Michael Levy, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>443-287-4412</phone>
    <email>nmo@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maureen Mealy, RN</last_name>
      <phone>410-502-8672</phone>
      <email>mmealy1@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Michael Levy, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>443-287-4412</phone>
      <email>nmo@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Levy, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/neurology_neurosurgery/research/neuromyelitis-optica-research-lab/nmo-clinic.html</url>
    <description>Johns Hopkins NMO Clinic</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.guthyjacksonfoundation.org/</url>
    <description>Guthy Jackson Charitable Foundation</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 20, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 21, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael Levy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>NMO</keyword>
  <keyword>NMOSD</keyword>
  <keyword>NMO-IgG</keyword>
  <keyword>Aquaporin-4</keyword>
  <keyword>AQP4</keyword>
  <keyword>anti-AQP4</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neuromyelitis Optica</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Bevacizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
