<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="31827">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01961518</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GGC001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01961518</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Screening an Orthopedic Population for Mildly-affected Individuals With Morquio Syndrome A and Maroteaux-Lamy Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Screening an Orthopedic Population for Mildly-affected Individuals With Morquio Syndrome Type A and Maroteaux-Lamy Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Greenwood Genetic Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shriners Hospitals for Children</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>BioMarin Pharmaceutical</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Greenwood Genetic Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to identify patients with Morquio syndrome type A (MPS IVA) and
      Maroteaux-Lamy syndrome (MPS VI) who may have been missed or misdiagnosed due to atypical
      clinical features, a milder course, and/or negative urine screening. We will recruit
      participants who have certain hip and/or joint problems that could potentially be caused by
      one of these two genetic conditions through a chart review process conducted at Shriners
      Hospital for Children in Greenville, SC. Diagnostic testing will be performed for each
      participant to determine if he or she is affected by one of these two conditions. Results
      will be disclosed to all participants and their legal guardians, and appropriate follow up
      will be recommended for those who are found to have abnormal results.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case-Only, Time Perspective: Retrospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of MPS IVA and MPS VI in an pediatric orthopedic population</measure>
    <time_frame>Data will be reviewed at the end of 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary objective of this study is to identify patients with Morquio syndrome type A or Maroteaux-Lamy syndrome who may have been missed or misdiagnosed due to atypical clinical features, a milder course, and/or negative mucopolysaccharidosis urine screening.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>DNA and urine collection and storage in a pediatric orthopedic population</measure>
    <time_frame>Specimen collection will occur within one year, and specimen storage will be indefinite</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The secondary objective of this study is to obtain and keep blood and urine samples for possible future research on Morquio syndrome type A, Maroteaux-Lamy syndrome, or other related or unrelated diseases.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Morquio Syndrome A</condition>
  <condition>Maroteaux Lamy Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>MPS IVA</condition>
  <condition>MPS VI</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Consent will be requested for specimen storage (DNA and urine) to allow use of the specimens
      for future research related or unrelated to the participant's condition.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        We plan to recruit 75 patients who will meet chart review criteria, selected from a
        population of 250-300 patients in the Shriners Hospitals for Children--Greenville (SHC)
        database. In addition, any patients evaluated at a monthly Genetics clinic held at SHC who
        meet eligibility criteria will be offered enrollment in the study in person (with a goal
        of 15). Participants of any ethnicity and both genders will be represented in this study.
        Since participants will be selected from the SHC patient database, as well as Greenwood
        Genetic Center clinics held at SHC in Greenville, SC, study participant's geographic
        location will be concentrated in the Southeastern region of the United States.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Eligible participants must currently receive care in the Shriners Hospitals for
             Children system, and therefore, will be under 19 years of age.

          -  Eligible participants must have one of the following diagnoses: bilateral
             Legg-Calve-Perthes disease, bilateral hip dysplasia, multiple joint pain,
             unidentified skeletal dysplasia

          -  Eligible participants (or legal guardian) must be able and willing to sign informed
             consent/assent in English or Spanish.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants with one or more or the above inclusion diagnoses who have a specific
             etiologic diagnosis will not be eligible to participate in this study.

          -  If we are unable to obtain the necessary specimens, the participant will be removed
             from the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard Curtis Rogers, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Greenwood Genetic Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Greenwood Genetic Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Greenville</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29605</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 9, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 8, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Greenwood Genetic Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>R. Curtis Rogers</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior Clinical Geneticst</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Mucopolysaccharidosis IV</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteochondrodysplasias</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mucopolysaccharidosis VI</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
