<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="35280">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02076620</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PH-L19TNFDOXO-01/12</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-000950-75</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02076620</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>L19TNFα in Combination With Doxorubicin in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumours</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Study of the Tumor-targeting Human L19TNFα Monoclonal Antibody-cytokine Fusion Protein in Combination With Doxorubicin in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumours</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Philogen S.p.A.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Philogen S.p.A.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Italy: National Institute of Health</authority>
    <authority>Italy: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Paul-Ehrlich-Institut</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Ethics Commission</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Phase Ib study of the tumor-targeting human L19TNFα monoclonal antibody-cytokine fusion
      protein in combination with doxorubicin in patients with advanced solid tumors.

      This study foresees the recruitment of up to 28 patients with advanced solid tumors who in
      the opinion of the Principal Investigator are deemed suitable for combination therapy of
      L19TNFα and doxorubicin.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      L19TNF is a recombinant fusion protein composed of a fully human recombinant monoclonal
      antibody (L19) and the human tumor necrosis factor-alpha, a primary mediator of immune
      regulation and inflammation.

      As an anti-tumor agent, TNF exerts its major effects via a preferential toxicity for the
      endothelial cells of the tumor-associated vasculature and an increase of the antitumor
      immune response. Given at sufficient doses (e.g. intratumorally or in the ILP setting with
      melphalan), TNF causes significant tumor shrinkage in solid cancer subjects.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) and recommended dose (RD)</measure>
    <time_frame>29 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Establish the MTD and the RD of L19TNFα when administered in combination with doxorubicin.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of L19TNFα in combination with doxorubicin</measure>
    <time_frame>29 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To investigate the safety, tolerability of L19TNFα and doxorubicin when given as a combination</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of L19TNFα</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigate the pharmacokinetics of L19TNFα</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Human anti-fusion protein antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>max. 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigate the potential induction of human anti-fusion protein antibodies (HAFA) through standard laboratory analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment efficacy (ORR, PFS, mOS)</measure>
    <time_frame>max. 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To investigate the antitumor activity in terms of objective response rate (ORR), progression -free survival (PFS) rate and median overall survival (mOS) of L19TNFα when administered in combination with a fixed dose of doxorubicin</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Advanced Tumors Amenable to Anthracycline Therapy</condition>
  <condition>Breast Cancer Amenable to Anthracycline Therapy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>L19TNFα + doxorubicin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Only one arm is specified. Patients will be treated in three cohorts with 3 different dosages of L19TNFα in combination with 60 mg/m2 of doxorubicin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Drug: L19TNFα in combination with doxorubicin</intervention_name>
    <description>Intravenous (i.v.) infusions of L19TNFα (from 10.4, 13 and 17μg/kg) on days 1, 3, and 5 over 120 minutes via automated device (perfusor).
Doxorubicin will be administered as a 15 minutes i.v. infusion on day 1 of each 3-week cycle prior L19TNFα administration.
Study design:
Cohort 1 --&gt; 10.4 μg/kg L19TNFα + Doxorubicin (fixed dose) Cohort 2 --&gt; 13 μg/kg L19TNFα + Doxorubicin (fixed dose) Cohort 3 --&gt; 17 μg/kg L19TNFα + Doxorubicin (fixed dose)
Patients with objective tumor responses or stable disease will receive repeated cycles of treatment starting on Day 22. Patients will receive additional cycles of combination therapy for a maximum of 4.5 months, or exhaustion of cumulative doxorubicin dose (360 or 550mg/m2) until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity,  withdrawal of consent or at the discretion of the treating physician, whichever occurs first.</description>
    <arm_group_label>L19TNFα + doxorubicin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with histologically or cytologically confirmed advanced solid cancer deemed
             suitable for combination therapy of L19TNFalfa and doxorubicin.

          -  For breast cancer patients only:

          -  Patients not suitable for trastuzumab therapy (i.e., no evidence of
             HER2-overexpressing disease, or trastuzumab therapy exhausted in HER2-overexpressing
             disease).

          -  Patients not suitable for lapatinib plus capecitabine therapy in HER2-overexpressing
             disease.

          -  Patients not suitable for lapatinib plus letrozolo therapy in HER2-overexpressing
             disease and HR + disease.

          -  Patients aged &gt;/= 18 years old with advanced or metastatic solid tumor in whom
             standard anticancer therapies have been exhausted, or who are amenable for a
             doxorubicin monotherapy according to the discretion of the Principal Investigators
             and previously treated with a cumulative dose of anthracyclines (&lt;/= 300 mg/mq), or
             chemotherapy- naive.

          -  Eastern cooperative oncology group (ECOG) performance status &lt;/= 2.

          -  Patients may have received previous chemotherapy (&gt;/=4 weeks prior therapy) or
             radiation therapy (&gt;/=6 weeks prior therapy), but they must be amenable for
             doxorubicin treatment according to the discretion of the Principal Investigator.

          -  Patients must have at least one unidimensionally measurable lesion by computed
             tomography as defined by criteria version 1.1. This lesion must not have been
             irradiated during previous treatments.

          -  Previous anthracycline therapy, including liposomal doxorubicin, for metastatic
             and/or adjuvant disease is allowed. However, patients must not have received a
             cumulative anthracycline dose of more than 300 mg/mq of doxorubicin, nor more than
             500 mg/mq of epirubicin, nor more than 600 mg/mq of pegylated or non-pegylated
             liposomal doxorubicin prior to study entry, in order to avoid
             anthracycline-associated cardiotoxicity.

          -  Life expectancy more than 3 months.

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &lt;/= 1.5 x 10^9/L, platelets &lt;/= 100 x 10^9/L and
             haemoglobin (Hb) &lt;/= 9.5 g/dl.

          -  All acute adverse effects (excluding alopecia) of any prior therapy (including
             surgery, radiation therapy, chemotherapy) must have resolved to &lt;/= Grade 1, except
             elevated liver transaminases judged to be associated with tumor infiltration (see
             below) (graded according to the National Cancer Institute CTCAE v.4.02 dated
             September 15, 2009).

          -  Alkaline phosphatase (AP), alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and/or aspartate
             aminotransferase (AST) &lt;/= 2.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN), and total bilirubin &lt;/=
             2.0 mg/gL, unless liver involvement by the tumor, in which case the transaminase
             levels up to 5 x ULN are allowed.

          -  Creatinine &lt;/= 1.5 ULN or 24 h creatinine clearance &lt;/= 60 mL/min.

          -  Testing negative for acute or chronic infection with hepatitis B or C virus, or human
             immunodeficiency virus 1 or 2.

          -  Negative pregnancy test for females of childbearing potential at the screening visit.

          -  Commitment from patient to practice medically appropriate/acceptable method of birth
             control beginning 30 days before study entry and continuing until 3 months following
             the last treatment with study drug. Excluding women without childbearing potential;
             menopause at least 2 years earlier, tubal ligation at least 1 year earlier, or total
             hysterectomy. The definition of effective contraception will be based on the
             guidelines ICH M3 rev2.

          -  Evidence of a personally signed and dated EC-approved ICF indicating that the patient
             (or legally acceptable representative) has been informed of all pertinent aspects of
             the study.

          -  Willingness and ability to comply with the scheduled visits, treatment plan,
             laboratory tests and other study procedures.

        ICF must be obtained for all the patients before enrollment into the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy or breast-feeding. Patients must agree to use effective contraception, or
             be surgically sterile or postmenopausal. The definition of effective contraception
             will be based on the guidelines ICH M3 rev2.

          -  Presence of active infections (e.g. requiring antimicrobial therapy) or other severe
             concurrent disease, which, in the opinion of the investigator, would place the
             subject at undue risk or interfere with the study.

          -  Presence of known brain metastases. If patient is symptomatic, negative CT scan
             within two months before study beginning is required. However, presence of controlled
             brain metastases (i.e., evaluated as SD of PR after radiotherapy) is allowed.

          -  Known cancer of other primary origin within the prior 5 years.

          -  History of chronic hepatitis B or C, or chronic active hepatitis or active autoimmune
             diseases.

          -  Cardiac disease as manifested by any of the following:

          -  &gt; Grade II heart failure, graded per New York Heart Association (NYHA) criteria.

          -  History within the last year of acute or subacute coronary syndromes including
             myocardial infarction, unstable or severe stable angina pectoris.

          -  Irreversible cardiac arrhythmias requiring permanent medication.

          -  Ejection fraction less than the institutional lower limit of normal as assessed by
             MUGA scan or echocardiogram.

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension.

          -  Ischemic peripheral vascular disease (Grade IIb-IV).

          -  Severe rheumatoid arthritis.

          -  Severe diabetic retinopathy.

          -  History of allograft or stem cell transplantation.

          -  Major surgery or trauma within 4 weeks prior to start of study treatment.

          -  Known history of allergy to TNFalfa, Anthracyclines or other intravenously
             administered human proteins/peptides/antibodies.

          -  Chemotherapy (standard or experimental), or therapy with an investigational agent
             within 4 weeks prior to start of study treatment, and radiation within 6 weeks prior
             therapy.

          -  Cumulative exposure to anthracycline-containing chemotherapy (patients received a
             cumulative anthracycline dose of more than 300 mg/mq of doxorubicin or of more than
             500 mg/mq of epirubicin or pegylated or non-pegylated liposomal doxorubicin), prior
             to study entry precluding the application of at least an additional 150 mg/mq
             doxorubicin (total dose for 2 cycles of study therapy).

          -  Treatment with an investigational study drug within six weeks before beginning of
             treatment with L19TNFalfa.

          -  Previous in vivo exposure to monoclonal antibodies for biological therapy in the 6
             weeks before administration of study treatment.

          -  Growth factors or immunomodulatory agents within 7 days prior to the administration
             of study treatment.

          -  Neuropathy &gt; Grade 1.

          -  Patient requires or is taking corticosteroids or other immunosuppressant drugs on a
             long-term basis. Limited use of corticosteroids to treat or prevent acute
             hypersensitivity reactions is not considered an exclusion criterion.

          -  Concurrent therapy with warfarin at doses greater than 1 mg/day or equivalent doses
             of other coumarin derivatives.

          -  Participation in another interventional clinical trial during participation in this
             trial.

          -  Expectation that the patient will not be able to complete at least 6 weeks of
             therapy.

          -  Any conditions that in the opinion of the investigator could hamper compliance with
             the study protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Filippo De Braud, Dr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Nazionale dei Tumori</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christoph Schliemann, Dr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universitätsklinikum Münster</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Leonardo Giovannoni, Dr</last_name>
    <phone>(0039) 0577 17816</phone>
    <email>regulatory@philogen.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Münster</name>
      <address>
        <city>Münster</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christoph Schliemann, Dr</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christoph Schliemann, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Nazionale dei Tumori</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milan</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Filippo De Braud, Dr</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Filippo De Braud, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 12, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 24, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>L19</keyword>
  <keyword>monoclonal</keyword>
  <keyword>antibody</keyword>
  <keyword>doxorubicin</keyword>
  <keyword>TNFα</keyword>
  <keyword>solid tumour</keyword>
  <keyword>breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>anthracycline</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Doxorubicin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
