<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="129536">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02039076</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>E5501-A001-018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02039076</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Five-Treatment-Period Study to Evaluate the Single-Dose Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of Avatrombopag in Healthy Japanese and White Subjects</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eisai Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eisai Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This will be a randomized, open-label, 5-treatment-period study to evaluate the PK and PD of
      avatrombopag following a single administration of avatrombopag in the fed and fasted
      condition, or the fed condition, to healthy Japanese and white subjects. A standard
      high-fat, high calorie breakfast will be used to assess the fed condition.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will comprise a Prerandomization Phase and a Randomization Phase. The
      Prerandomization Phase will include 2 periods, Screening and Baseline 1. The Screening
      Period will be up to 3 weeks (21 days) in duration. The Randomization Phase will consist of
      5 single-dose treatment periods, of which 3 will include administration of avatrombopag in
      the fed condition and 2 will include administration of avatrombopag in the fasted condition.
      Each treatment period will be separated by a wash out interval of at least 28 days. Before
      each treatment period, subjects will complete a baseline period (Baseline Periods 2, 3, 4,
      and 5), during which baseline assessments will be collected.  A Final Visit will occur 28
      days (+/- 1 day) after dosing in Treatment Period 5.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics/Dynamics Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic (PK) profiles of avatrombopag</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 23 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The following PK parameters will be estimated for plasma: Cmax, AUC, and t1/2.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic (PD) profiles of avatrombopag</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 23 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Analyses will carried out for AUEC(0-28d) and Emax using a mixed linear model including fixed terms for dose, race, food, sequence, and period with interaction terms for food by race and for dose by race and subject as random effect.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of PK and PD for avatrombopag</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 23 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess the similarity of the PK and PD of avatrombopag between healthy Japanese and white subjects after a single administration of avatrombopag under fasted conditions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events (AEs ) as a measure of safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 23 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety assessments include AEs, clinical laboratory results, vital signs, and ECGs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Laboratory assessments as a measure of safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 23 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Clinical laboratory assessments will include haematology, clinical chemistry, urinalysis and other screening tests</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vital signs as a measure of safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 23 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Vital sign measurements will include systolic and diastolic blood pressure (BP) and pulse rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Electrocardiogram (ECG) as a measure of safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 23 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Twelve-lead ECGs will be obtained as a measure of safety and tolerability</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Thrombocytopenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>avatrombopag</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each subject will receive a single administration during each of the 5 treatment periods as follows: 40 and 60 mg in the fed and fasted state, and 20 mg in the fed state.  Subjects will be randomized to one of four dosing sequences.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>avatrombopag</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>avatrombopag</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          1. Platelet count between the lower limit of normal and 350 x 109/L, inclusive, at
             Screening and each Baseline; measurements can repeated for verification, if necessary

          2. Nonsmoking, healthy white and Japanese adult male and female subjects, greater than
             or equal to 20 years and less than or equal to 55 years old at the time of informed
             consent. (Nonsmokers are defined as those who have discontinued smoking for at least
             4 weeks before dosing.)

          3. Japanese subjects must be born in Japan of Japanese parents and Japanese
             grandparents, must have lived no more than 5 years outside of Japan, and must not
             have changed their lifestyle or habits, including diet, while living outside of
             Japan.

          4. Body mass index greater than or equal to 18 and less than or equal to 28 kg/m2 at
             Screening and Baseline Period 1. The BMI in white subjects must be within +/- 2 kg/m2
             of the BMI in Japanese subjects.

          5. Nonsmoking, healthy  white and Japanese adult males and females between the ages of
             20 and 55, inclusive

          6. BMI between 18 and 28. inclusive

          7. Females must not be pregnant or lactating, and if they are of childbearing potential
             they must agree to use a highly effective method of contraception or abstain

          8. Males must have a vasectomy or they and their partner must use a highly effective
             method of contraception

        Exclusion Criteria

          1. Evidence of organ dysfunction or any clinically significant deviation from normal in
             their medical history (eg, history of splenectomy); history of arterial or venous
             thrombosis, including partial or complete thromboses (eg, stroke, transient ischemic
             attack, myocardial infarction, deep vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolism); known
             family history of hereditary thrombophilic disorders (eg, Factor V Leiden,
             antithrombin III deficiency)

          2. Recent clinically significant illness or infection that requires medical treatment

          3. Evidence of disease that may influence the outcome of the study (eg, psychiatric
             disorders, disorders of the gastrointestinal tract, liver, kidney, respiratory
             system, endocrine system, hematological system, neurological system, or
             cardiovascular system), or subjects who have a congenital abnormality in metabolism

          4. Any history of gastrointestinal surgery (eg, hepatectomy, nephrotomy, digestive organ
             resection)

          5. Any clinically abnormal symptom or organ impairment found by medical history,
             physical examination, vital sign electrocardiogram (ECG) assessment, or laboratory
             test results

          6. A known or suspected history of drug or alcohol dependency or abuse or a positive
             urine drug, cotinine, or alcohol test

          7. Positive results for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis B surface antigen
             (HBsAg), or hepatitis C virus (HCV) antibody at Screening

          8. Weight loss or gain of &gt;10% within 4 weeks before dosing

          9. Known history of clinically significant drug or food allergy

         10. Currently enrolled in another clinical trial
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eisai Medical Services</last_name>
    <phone>1-888-422-4743</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Parexel International Early Development Clinical Units</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glendale</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 19, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 13, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Thrombocytopenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
