<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="63807">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01953237</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R34MH094555</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01953237</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MedActive: A Smartphone Intervention to Improve Adherence to Antipsychotic Medications</brief_title>
  <official_title>MedActive: A Smartphone Intervention to Improve Adherence to Antipsychotic Medications</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Maryland Health Care System</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Maryland Health Care System</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      We propose to develop and pilot test the effect of a mobile smartphone intervention,
      MedActive, on improving antipsychotic adherence among individuals with schizophrenia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Up to 60% of individuals with schizophrenia do not take their antipsychotic medications as
      prescribed, which can lead to symptom relapse, decreased functioning, hospitalization, and
      increased healthcare costs. Recent studies of both patient- and pharmacy-based interventions
      utilizing behavioral tailoring, environmental supports, and medication monitoring have shown
      promise in improving antipsychotic adherence. However, there is continued need for effective
      adherence-enhancing interventions (AEIs) that are less resource intensive and more widely
      accessible by the broad range of individuals in need of assistance with medication
      management. Over the last decade, technological advances in internet and cellular
      communication, including the emergence of mobile 'smartphones', have revolutionized the way
      our society communicates. Whereas a variety of mobile phone-based applications have been
      shown to be effective for improving health outcomes such as medication adherence for a
      number of medical conditions, few such applications have been developed for individuals with
      schizophrenia. Therefore, in response to NIMH PAR-09-173, we propose to develop and pilot
      test the effect of a mobile smartphone intervention, MedActive, on improving antipsychotic
      adherence among this population. We used the Information-Motivation-Behavioral (IMB) Skills
      Model of adherence as the theoretical framework to inform the conceptualization of
      MedActive. The IMB Skills Model posits that individuals who are well-informed and motivated
      to adhere will enact adherence-related behavioral skills that lead to adherence behaviors
      and favorable health outcomes. MedActive will provide personalized reminders to patients to
      take their antipsychotic medications as prescribed and will query them about their
      intentions to take the medication, the occurrence of side effects, and the presence of
      positive psychotic symptoms. Summaries of these ecological momentary assessments of
      adherence, symptoms, and side effects will be made available to the individual on the phone
      and to their psychiatrist through a secure, online clinician interface. Using an iterative
      user-centered design approach, the specific aims of this proposal are to (1) collaborate
      with individuals with schizophrenia, psychiatrists and an expert advisory group to develop
      the initial version of MedActive; (2) conduct laboratory usability testing and a short-term
      field trial in 10 individuals with schizophrenia and their psychiatrists to determine the
      preliminary acceptability and feasibility of MedActive in clinical practice; and (3) conduct
      a randomized pilot trial of MedActive compared to providing a smartphone alone in 40
      individuals with schizophrenia and their psychiatrists to evaluate its effect on
      antipsychotic adherence. We will also explore whether psychiatric symptoms and
      neuropsychological impairments moderate the effect of MedActive on adherence. If shown to be
      effective, MedActive will introduce a paradigm shift in medication self-management by
      individuals with schizophrenia and in treatment monitoring by their clinicians.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to Antipsychotic medications</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month period</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individuals randomized to the control condition will be provided with a smartphone free of charge with unlimited use of the phone's voice and internet capabilities. All participants randomized to this condition will also have their antipsychotic medication adherence assessed over the 3-month period.   All participants will be contacted by research staff to trouble-shoot problems with the smartphone at the end of the first week, but will receive no additional contact from research staff until the end of the trial.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MedActive</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to the MedActive condition will complete a 1-hour training session on MedActive, which will include ascertaining their antipsychotic administration schedule that will be pre-programmed into the application along with other personalized features. Each participate will be asked to use the medActive application over the following three months.  All participants randomized to this condition will also have their antipsychotic medication adherence assessed over the 3-month period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MedActive</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants randomized to the MedActive condition will complete a 1-hour training session on MedActive, which will include ascertaining their antipsychotic administration schedule that will be pre-programmed into the application along with other personalized features. Each participate will be asked to use the medActive application over the following three months.  All participants randomized to this condition will also have their antipsychotic medication adherence assessed over the 3-month period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MedActive</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Smartphone</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Decisional capacity to provide informed consent

          -  Chart diagnosis of schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder

          -  Currently prescribed at least one oral antipsychotic medication

          -  Self administers at least one oral antipsychotic medication

          -  18-64 years of age

          -  English Speaking

          -  Be able to read English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has visual, hearing, voice, or motor impairment that would prevent completion of
             study procedures or use of mobile phone
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Julie A Kreyenbuhl, Pharm.D PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Maryland Health Care System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Outpatient clinics within the University of Maryland Division of Community Psychiatry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 27, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 25, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>VA Maryland Health Care System</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Julie Kreyenbuhl</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Health Science Specialist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Schizophrenia</keyword>
  <keyword>antipsychotic medication adherence</keyword>
  <keyword>mobile phones</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antipsychotic Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
