<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="8088">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01718704</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NA_00069795</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01718704</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Viberect Penile Vibratory Stimulation to Enhance Recovery of Erectile Function and Urinary Continence Post-Prostatectomy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Study of Non-Invasive Viberect® Penile Vibratory Stimulation Regimen to Enhance Recovery of Erectile Function/Rigidity and Urinary Control/Continence After Nerve Sparing Radical Prostatectomy (RP) for Clinically Localized Prostate Cancer.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to verify whether using penile vibratory stimulation with the
      Viberect handheld device can help the recovery of erections and urinary control after
      radical prostatectomy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Prostate cancer screening programs have led to thousands of sexually healthy men being
      diagnosed with prostate cancer every year. Recent literature suggests that up to 80% of
      these cancers are confined to the prostate gland. Currently, radical prostatectomy (RP)
      remains the best option for management of clinically localized prostate cancer in men with
      life expectancy greater than 10 years. Despite providing optimal cancer control, surgery can
      lead to quality of life (QOL) problems such as urinary incontinence and erectile dysfunction
      (ED). Refinement of surgical technique have improved sexual and continence outcomes; however
      erectile function lags behind other QOL measures by 1-2 years, and quality of returning
      erections is often inferior. This can have profound biological, marital, and psychological
      consequences in potent men undergoing RP.

      Erectile dysfunction (ED) is the inability to develop and maintain an erection for
      satisfactory sexual intercourse or activity. ED after nerve-sparing RP is related to a
      certain degree with functional impairment of cavernous nerves (CN) that travel along the
      prostate to the penis. This neuropraxia can last as long as 2 years. Pro-erectile nerve
      stimulus is vital for replenishment of corporal oxygen supply and other metabolic needs.
      Several histological analyses have demonstrated decreased smooth muscle number, cell-cell
      contact, venous leakage, collagen deposition, and additional harmful effects to corporal
      tissue after injury to CN.

      Awaiting post-surgical neuropraxia recovery, urologists have proposed a proactive approach
      to use of oral, intraurethral or injectable pharmacotherapy, neuromodulation, or
      vacuum-assisted regimens in erectile rehabilitation programs. Several studies demonstrate
      variable functional improvement in erectile function. Unfortunately, prohibitive costs of
      medications, poor response, and pain from injectables or intraurethral application often
      lead to high dropout rates.

      In addition to erectile dysfunction, a significant proportion of men after surgery develop
      and suffer from urinary incontinence (Stress, Urge, Mixed) requiring wearing pads with
      bothersome complaints persisting for months, even years after radical prostatectomy.

      The primary objective is to assess the role of penile vibratory stimulation by the Viberect
      device in enhancing the recovery of erectile function/rigidity and urinary continence after
      radical prostatectomy for clinically localized prostate cancer. The difference in penile
      length will be compared in each arm.

      The secondary objective is to obtain a formal risk analysis (RA). Other objectives are to
      assess the ease of use and acceptability of vibratory stimulation at home.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recovery of erectile function following radical prostatectomy.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post-radical prostatectomy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients will visit with investigators. Physical examination will be performed, including genital exam for any signs of penile irritation. Study subjects will complete the IIEF, EPIC urinary and sexual domain, AUA, EHS, EDITS and TSS questionnaires. Penile length will be measured from pubis to corona of the glans penis (dorsally) and recorded in centimeter using a standard wooden ruler.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recovery of continence after radical prostatectomy</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post-prostatectomy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients will visit with investigators. Physical examination will be performed, including genital exam for any signs of penile irritation. Study subjects will complete the IIEF, EPIC urinary and sexual domain, AUA, EHS, EDITS and TSS questionnaires. Penile length will be measured from pubis to corona of the glans penis (dorsally) and recorded in centimeter using a standard wooden ruler.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">105</enrollment>
  <condition>Erectile Dysfunction Following Radical Prostatectomy</condition>
  <condition>Urinary Incontinence of Non-organic Origin</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Viberect device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Men in this group will begin using the Viberect device 3 days after Foley catheter removal after surgery on daily (or at least 4 times a week)  basis for 7-10 minutes in a relaxed setting.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No Viberect</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Men in this group will not be provided with the Viberect device.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Viberect device</intervention_name>
    <description>Men who begin using the Viberect device 3 days after Foley catheter removal on daily (or at least 4 times a week)  basis for 7-10 minutes in a relaxed setting with sexual thoughts or foreplay for one year.  Viberect method can be performed by the person's sexual partner.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Viberect device</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with biopsy proven low/moderate risk prostate cancer (Gleason 3+3=6,
             3+4=7, 3+2=5, 2+3=5, cT1c, cT2a, cT2b, PSA less than 10)

          -  between ages 40-70

          -  preoperative IIEF (erectile function section) score equal or greater than 20

          -  AUA symptom score less than 10 and no urinary incontinence

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Men with neurological disease

          -  IIEF score less than 20

          -  high risk prostate cancer (Gleason 4+3=7, 4+4=8, any Gleason 5, cT2c, cT3, PSA &gt; 10)

          -  spinal cord injury

          -  history of transurethral resection of prostate (TURP) or other prostate ablative
             procedures

          -  history of priapism, pelvic neuropathy, penile skin lesions/ulcers

          -  inability to understand and demonstrate device use instructions.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Arthur L Burnett, MD, MBA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kambiz Tajkarimi, MD</last_name>
    <phone>1-202-321-8162</phone>
    <email>Kambiz123@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jordan Dimitrakoff, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>410-502-5384</phone>
    <email>jdimitr1@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jordan Dimitrakoff, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>410-502-5384</phone>
      <email>jdimitr1@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Brian Le, M.D.</last_name>
      <email>ble6@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Arthur L Burnett, MD, MBA</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Frederick Urology Specialists</name>
      <address>
        <city>Frederick</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21701</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kambiz Tajkarimi, MD</last_name>
      <email>kambiz123@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kambiz Tajkarimi, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 20, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 24, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Arthur L. Burnett, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Patrick C. Walsh Professor of Urology, Cellular and Molecular Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>erectile dysfunction</keyword>
  <keyword>incontinence</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Urinary Incontinence</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Erectile Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
