<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="90832">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02060253</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NYU S12-03732</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2014-00177</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016087</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02060253</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ganetespib, Paclitaxel and Trastuzumab for Advanced or Metastatic Human Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor 2 Positive (HER2+) Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Clinical Trial of Ganetespib (Heat Shock Protein 90 Inhibitor) in Combination With Paclitaxel and Trastuzumab in Human Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor-2 Positive (HER2+) Metastatic Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Synta Pharmaceuticals Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial studies the side effects and best dose of ganetespib when given with
      paclitaxel and trastuzumab in treating patients with advanced or metastatic human epidermal
      growth factor receptor 2 positive (HER2+) breast cancer. HER2+ describes cancer cells that
      have too much of a protein called HER2 on their surface. In normal cells, HER2 helps to
      control cell growth. When it is made in larger than normal amounts by cancer cells, the
      cells may grow more quickly and be more likely to spread to other parts of the body.
      Checking to see if a cancer is HER2+ may help plan treatment, which may include drugs that
      kill HER2+ cancer cells. Ganetespib may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking some of
      the enzymes needed for cell growth. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as paclitaxel, work in
      different ways to stop the growth of tumor cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping
      them from dividing. Monoclonal antibodies, such as trastuzumab, can block the ability of
      tumors to grow and spread. Giving ganetespib with paclitaxel and trastuzumab may be an
      effective treatment for patients with HER2+ breast cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To establish the safety, tolerability, maximum tolerated dose (MTD) and the recommended
      phase II dose of ganetespib plus paclitaxel in conjunction with trastuzumab in patients with
      HER2+ metastatic breast cancer (MBC).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the possible effects of ganetespib on the pharmacokinetics (PK) of
      paclitaxel.

      II. To make a preliminary assessment of the efficacy of the combination of ganetespib,
      paclitaxel and trastuzumab as measured by objective response rate (ORR), progression-free
      survival (PFS), duration of response, and clinical benefit rate (complete response + partial
      response + stable disease &gt; 24 weeks).

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive trastuzumab IV over 30 minutes on days 1, 8, 15, and 22, paclitaxel IV over
      1 hour on days 1, 8, 15, and 22, and ganetespib intravenously (IV) over 1 hour on days 1, 8,
      and 15. Courses repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable
      toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 12 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of ganetespib when combined with paclitaxel and trastuzumab</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Defined as the percentage of patients who have achieved complete response or partial response assessed based on Response evaluation criteria in solid tumors 1.1 (RECIST 1.1).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical benefit rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Defined as the percentage of patients who have achieved complete response, partial response, or stable disease for at least 24 weeks assessed based on RECIST 1.1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The duration of response is measured from the time of response to disease progression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The median time of progression-free survival will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters of paclitaxel (such as area under the curve and maximum concentration)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 7, 21, 24, 27, and 31 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be examined descriptively to evaluate the effect of ganetespib on the paclitaxel absorption.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">18</enrollment>
  <condition>HER2-positive Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Male Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIA Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ganetespib, paclitaxel, and trastuzumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive trastuzumab IV over 30 minutes on days 1, 8, 15, and 22, paclitaxel IV over 1 hour on days 1, 8, 15, and 22, and ganetespib intravenously (IV) over 1 hour on days 1, 8, and 15. Courses repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ganetespib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>ganetespib, paclitaxel, and trastuzumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Hsp90 inhibitor STA-9090</other_name>
    <other_name>STA-9090</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>ganetespib, paclitaxel, and trastuzumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Anzatax</other_name>
    <other_name>Asotax</other_name>
    <other_name>TAX</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>trastuzumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>ganetespib, paclitaxel, and trastuzumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>anti-c-erB-2</other_name>
    <other_name>Herceptin</other_name>
    <other_name>MOAB HER2</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pathologically confirmed diagnosis of breast cancer (central confirmation is not
             required)

          -  Patients must be at least 18 years of age

          -  Metastatic or advanced breast cancer that is evaluable OR metastatic or advanced
             breast cancer that is measurable for response as per Response Evaluation Criteria in
             Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0-2

          -  Life expectancy of at least 3 months as assessed by the investigator

          -  Patients with estrogen receptor (ER)+ breast cancer must have received prior
             treatment with at least one hormone therapy

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1,500 cells/uL

          -  Platelets &gt;=100,000/uL

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 9.0g/dL

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x the upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) =&lt; 2.5 x ULN

          -  Albumin &gt;= 3.0 g/dL

          -  Serum creatinine =&lt; 1.5 x ULN

          -  Willingness and ability to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plans, laboratory
             tests, and other study procedures

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential and males must agree to use adequate
             contraception (e.g., hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) for the
             duration of study treatment

          -  Female subjects of childbearing age must have a negative serum pregnancy test at
             study entry

          -  Patients with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)/acquired immune deficiency syndrome
             (AIDS) are allowed on study if they have an undetectable viral load, cluster of
             differentiation (CD)4 &gt; 300 and are on a stable highly active antiretroviral therapy
             (HAART) regimen for 1 month prior to study enrollment

          -  Patients are required to have HER2+ breast cancer defined as a fluorescent in situ
             hybridization (FISH)- ratio of &gt;= 2.0 or immunohistochemistry (IHC) 3+

          -  Any number of prior chemotherapies or biological therapies are allowed, patients are
             required to have prior treatment with pertuzumab and ado-trastuzumab emtansine with
             the exceptions listed below:

               -  Metastatic patients who have not received prior pertuzumab are eligible if:
                  heavily pretreated prior to Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approval of
                  pertuzumab (08-Jun-2012) for first line treatment of HER2+ MBC

               -  Metastatic patients who have not received ado-trastuzumab emtansine are eligible
                  if: heavily pretreated prior to FDA approval of ado-trastuzumab emtansine
                  (22-Feb-2013) for the treatment of patients with HER2+ MBC who previously
                  received trastuzumab and a taxane, separately or in combination

          -  No prior history of intolerance or hypersensitivity to trastuzumab and/or adverse
             events related to trastuzumab, murine proteins, or any of the excipients that
             resulted in trastuzumab being permanently discontinued

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Fewer than 21 days since last anti-tumor therapy, including chemotherapy, biologic
             except trastuzumab, experimental, immune, radiotherapy for the treatment of breast
             cancer, with the following exceptions:

               -  Hormone therapy

               -  Palliative radiation therapy involving =&lt; 25% of marrow-bearing bone is allowed
                  if completed within &gt;= 14 days prior to first study treatment

          -  Surgery, radiotherapy, or lesion ablative procedure to the only area of
             measurable/evaluable disease

          -  Major surgery within 4 weeks prior to first dose of ganetespib

          -  Poor venous access for study drug administration

               -  Study drug administration via indwelling catheters is allowed only if the
                  catheter is made of silicone material

          -  History of severe (grade 3 or 4) allergic or hypersensitivity reactions to excipients
             (e.g., polyethylene glycol [PEG] 300 and polysorbate 80)

          -  History of intolerance or hypersensitivity to paclitaxel and/or adverse events
             related to paclitaxel that resulted in paclitaxel being permanently discontinued

          -  Peripheral neuropathy of grade &gt;= 2 per National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common
             Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE), version 4.0, at the time of or
             within 3 weeks prior to the first study therapy

          -  Baseline QTc &gt; 470 msec (average of triplicate ECG recordings); a consistent method
             of QTc calculation must be used for each patient's QTc measurements. QTcF
             (Fridericia's formula) is preferred

          -  Use of medications that have been linked to the occurrence of torsades de pointes

               -  Patients will be eligible for the study if they discontinue any of the listed
                  medications two weeks prior to registration and study enrollment

               -  Stable regimen of antidepressants of the SSRI class is allowed (common SSRIs
                  include escitalopram oxalate, citalopram, fluvoxamine, paroxetine, sertraline
                  and fluoxetine)

          -  Left ventricular ejection fraction (EF) &lt; 50% at baseline

          -  Serum potassium, magnesium, and  calcium levels (corrected for albumin) outside the
             laboratory's reference range despite correction

          -  Treatment with chronic immunosuppressants (e.g., cyclosporine following
             transplantation)

          -  Women who are pregnant or lactating

          -  Current known active infection with HIV, hepatitis B or C viruses

          -  Uncontrolled systemic disease (e.g., clinically significant cardiac, pulmonary or
             metabolic disease)

          -  Other medications, or severe acute/chronic medical or psychiatric condition, or
             laboratory abnormality that may increase the risk associated with study participation
             or study drug administration, or may interfere with the interpretation of study
             results in the judgment of the investigator

          -  History of clinically significant cardiac dysfunction, including:

               -  Unstable angina

               -  Unstable atrial fibrillation

               -  Symptomatic bradycardia

               -  Indwelling temporary pacemaker

               -  History of MI within 6 months prior to first study treatment

               -  History of symptomatic CHF (grade &gt; 3 by NCI CTCAE or Class &gt; II by New York
                  Heart Association (NYHA) criteria

               -  Ventricular tachycardia or a supraventricular tachycardia that requires
                  treatment with a Class 1a antiarrhythmic drug (eg quinidine, procainamide,
                  disopyramide) or Class III antiarrhythmic drug (eg sotalol, amiodarone,
                  dofetilide). Use of other antiarrhythmic drugs is permitted

               -  Second or third degree atrioventricular (AV) block unless treated with a
                  permanent pacemaker

               -  Complete left bundle branch block (LBBB)

               -  History of long QT syndrome or a family member with this condition

          -  Brain metastases that are:

               -  Progressive or

               -  Have required any type of therapy (including radiation, surgery or steroids) to
                  control symptoms from brain metastases within 60 days prior to the first study
                  treatment

          -  History of an invasive second primary malignancy diagnosed within the previous 3
             years, except for appropriately treated stage I endometrial or cervical carcinoma or
             prostate carcinoma treated surgically, and non-melanoma skin cancer
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Komal Jhaveri</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>New York University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shanu Modi</last_name>
      <phone>646-888-5243</phone>
      <email>modis@mskcc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Shanu Modi</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NYU Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Komal Jhaveri</last_name>
      <phone>212-731-5835</phone>
      <email>Komal.Jhaveri@nyumc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Komal Jhaveri</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 30, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms, Male</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Mitogens</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Trastuzumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
