<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="4838">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01872702</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BAKMAL1305</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01872702</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Defining the Micro-epidemiology and Elimination Strategy of Falciparum Malaria in Areas of Artemisinin Resistance</brief_title>
  <acronym>TME</acronym>
  <official_title>Defining the Micro-epidemiology and Elimination Strategy of Falciparum Malaria in Areas of Artemisinin Resistance: Targeted Chemo-elimination to Eradicate Malaria in Areas of Suspected or Proven Artemisinin Resistance in Southeast Asia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mahidol Oxford Tropical Medicine Research Unit, Thailand</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shoklo Malaria Research Unit, Thailand</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Centre for Parasitology Entomology and Malaria Control, Cambodia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Family Health International, Cambodia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oxford University Clinical Research Unit, Vietnam</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Malaria Control Program, Vietnam</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mahidol Oxford Clinical Research Unit, Myanmar</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Malaria Control Program, Myanmar</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall aim of this study is two fold:

        1. to pilot targeted chemo-elimination of plasmodium falciparum malaria in known areas of
           artemisinin resistance in South East Asia.

        2. to understand the micro-epidemiology of malaria in these areas; chiefly, the prevalence
           and importance to on-going transmission of sub-clinical p.f malaria infections.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The spread of artemisinin resistance in Plasmodium falciparum, which compromises the
      therapeutic efficacy of artemisinin combination treatments (ACTs), is the greatest threat to
      current global initiatives to control and eliminate malaria and is considered the highest
      priority of the WHO Global Malaria Programme. If not eliminated, resistant parasites could
      spread across Asia to Africa, as happened with resistance to other antimalarials in the
      past.

      Conventional descriptions of the epidemiology of malaria in low transmission settings
      suggest that malaria prevalences are low (&lt;10%) and heterogeneous. Most or all infections
      are thought to be symptomatic so the focus of malaria control activities is on the
      identification and treatment of symptomatic individuals. We and others have shown recently
      that artemisinin resistant P. falciparum is prevalent in Western Cambodia, and that it is
      now also found along the Thailand-Myanmar border and Vietnam. We have recently developed
      highly sensitive quantitative PCR (qPCR) methods for parasite detection using &gt;1mL of blood
      which are 5,000 times more sensitive than conventional microscopy, and 100 times more
      sensitive than currently used PCR.

      We have studied villages along the Thai-Myanmar border which are typical for the region and
      are classified by conventional epidemiological techniques as low-transmission (5-20% malaria
      prevalence). Our studies suggest that the majority of the population is infected. In Pailin,
      Western Cambodia, in areas where the National Malaria Control Programme and WHO believe that
      malaria has been all but eliminated, we have also found very high rates (&gt;80%) of
      sub-microscopic parasitaemia in patients with fever or history of fever who are RDT
      negative. Thus, there is a lot more asymptomatic malaria in low transmission settings than
      previously thought, suggesting that control and elimination activities need to be rethought.

      This study is designed to conduct and evaluate the efficacy of pilot implementation of
      targeted chemo-elimination in selected areas with the goal of eliminating malaria in these
      regions. This differs from mass drug administration (MDA); it is a strategy used to identify
      specific areas where mass treatment is necessary, in this case to eliminate all malaria
      parasites. Elimination will be targeted at communities with significant levels of
      subclinical infection and transmission which will be identifiable in the future by comparing
      rates of positivity by RDT or microscopy from new population samples against our qPCR data,
      which shows the true falciparum prevalence.

      The study will assess the feasibility, safety and acceptability of this strategy and its
      impact on the transmission of malaria and the progression of artemisinin resistance. In
      addition it will evaluate the contribution of low parasitaemia carriage to transmission of
      artemisinin resistant malaria. These pilot studies are a necessary prelude to future scale
      up and policy implementation.

      Dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine (DP) is a highly efficacious and inexpensive ACT which is
      well tolerated by all age groups when used to treat uncomplicated multi-drug resistant
      falciparum malaria in South East Asia. Monthly DP treatments have proved highly effective
      and well tolerated. When used as part of a MDA strategy, the addition of a gametocytocidal
      drug contributes towards the goal of malaria elimination by adding a strong transmission
      blocking activity to the regimen. Primaquine (PQ), the only currently licensed
      8-aminoquinoline, is relatively safe and very effective when used at a dose of 0.25 mg
      base/kg, and does not require G6PD screening. Thus, we propose to evaluate the potential of
      this strategy to eliminatie malaria focally in areas where artemisinin resistance in P.
      falciparum is prevalent using DP plus PQ.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>prevalence of falciparum malaria measured by qPCR (quantitative real time polymerase chain reaction), 12 months after the first administration of treatment with dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine and primaquine.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage falls in asymptomatic malaria prevalence in the intervention villages vs control villages, as determined by highly sensitive qPCR, 12 months after the first administration of treatment with dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine and primaquine.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and acceptability of targeted malaria elimination</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety and acceptability of targeted malaria elimination with dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine and low dose primaquine, evaluated by questionnaires filled out by participants or care givers.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Effect on gametocyte carriage by targeted malaria elimination</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Effect on gametocyte carriage by targeted malaria elimination, measured by the proportions of gametocyte carriers over the 12 month period</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Characterize parasite carriage using highly sensitive techniques in four geographically separate sites where resistance to artemisinin has been documented</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Characterize parasite carriage using by molecular analysis of parasite genotypes, markers of resistance and parasite population genetic structure</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">8000</enrollment>
  <condition>Plasmodium Falciparum Malaria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>malaria elimination using DP and low-dose primaquine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Two villages randomly allocated to intervention (chemo-elimination) at each of the 4 sites (population approximately 500 people in each village). In these villages the entire population will be invited to receive three, monthly rounds of treatment with dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine and primaqunine to kill malaria parasites. The micro-epidemiology of malaria will be studied and prevalence and patterns of transmission used for comparison. NB, in Cambodia there will be no intervention villages and all four villages will be used to study the micro-epidemiology of malaria transmission in the absence of malaria elimination.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control villages</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Two villages randomly allocated to control (no chemo-elimination) at each of the 4 sites (population approximately 500 people in each village). In these villages only the micro-epidemiology of malaria will be studied and prevalence and patterns of transmission used for comparison. NB, in Cambodia there will be no intervention villages and all four villages will be used to study the micro-epidemiology of malaria transmission in the absence of malaria elimination.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>malaria elimination using DP and low-dose primaquine</intervention_name>
    <description>Treatment of all persons resident in the intervention villages including those who do not have malaria parasites as detected by rapid diagnostic test. This is to interrupt p.f malaria transmission by removing the reservoir of all potentially infectious people from the area.</description>
    <arm_group_label>malaria elimination using DP and low-dose primaquine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Three monthly rounds of:</other_name>
    <other_name>Dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine</other_name>
    <other_name>Low-dose primaquine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  willingness to comply with study protocol

          -  no known allergy to study drugs

          -  informed consent obtained

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  unwillingness to comply with study protocol

          -  known allergy to study drugs

          -  informed consent not obtained

          -  exclusive breastfeeding

          -  pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicholas J White, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Oxford</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nicholas J White, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+66 (0)22036333</phone>
    <email>nickwdt@tropmedres.ac</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Arjen Dondorp, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+66 (0)22036333</phone>
    <email>arjen@tropmedres.ac</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Centre for Parasitology, Entomology and Malaria Control</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phnom Penh</city>
        <zip>372</zip>
        <country>Cambodia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rupam Tripura, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+66 857795804</phone>
      <email>Rupam@tropmedres.ac</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Chea Nguon, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+855 12532946.</phone>
      <email>cheanguon@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Char Meng Chuor, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chea Nguon, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rupam Tripura, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Song Ngak</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mahidol Oxford Clincal Research Unit, Myanmar</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rangoon</city>
        <country>Myanmar</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kyaw Myo Tun, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kyaw Myo Tun, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shoklo Malaria Research Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mae Sot</city>
        <state>Tak</state>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Francois Nosten, PhD</last_name>
      <email>francois@tropmedres.ac</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Khin M Lwin, MD</last_name>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Francois Nosten, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oxford University Clinical Research Unit - Vietnam</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ho Chi Minh city</city>
        <zip>Ward 1, District 5</zip>
        <country>Vietnam</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tran Tinh Hien, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+84 (8) 3923 7954</phone>
      <email>hientt@oucru.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tran T Hien, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Cambodia</country>
    <country>Myanmar</country>
    <country>Thailand</country>
    <country>Vietnam</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.tropmedres.ac</url>
    <description>The Mahidol Oxford Tropical Medicine Research Unit</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dondorp AM, Nosten F, Yi P, Das D, Phyo AP, Tarning J, Lwin KM, Ariey F, Hanpithakpong W, Lee SJ, Ringwald P, Silamut K, Imwong M, Chotivanich K, Lim P, Herdman T, An SS, Yeung S, Singhasivanon P, Day NP, Lindegardh N, Socheat D, White NJ. Artemisinin resistance in Plasmodium falciparum malaria. N Engl J Med. 2009 Jul 30;361(5):455-67.</citation>
    <PMID>19641202</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tran TH, Dolecek C, Pham PM, Nguyen TD, Nguyen TT, Le HT, Dong TH, Tran TT, Stepniewska K, White NJ, Farrar J. Dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine against multidrug-resistant Plasmodium falciparum malaria in Vietnam: randomised clinical trial. Lancet. 2004 Jan 3;363(9402):18-22.</citation>
    <PMID>14723988</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smithuis F, Kyaw MK, Phe O, Aye KZ, Htet L, Barends M, Lindegardh N, Singtoroj T, Ashley E, Lwin S, Stepniewska K, White NJ. Efficacy and effectiveness of dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine versus artesunate-mefloquine in falciparum malaria: an open-label randomised comparison. Lancet. 2006 Jun 24;367(9528):2075-85.</citation>
    <PMID>16798391</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ashley EA, Krudsood S, Phaiphun L, Srivilairit S, McGready R, Leowattana W, Hutagalung R, Wilairatana P, Brockman A, Looareesuwan S, Nosten F, White NJ. Randomized, controlled dose-optimization studies of dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated multidrug-resistant falciparum malaria in Thailand. J Infect Dis. 2004 Nov 15;190(10):1773-82. Epub 2004 Oct 18. Erratum in: J Infect Dis. 2005 Apr 1;191(7):1204.</citation>
    <PMID>15499533</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ashley EA, McGready R, Hutagalung R, Phaiphun L, Slight T, Proux S, Thwai KL, Barends M, Looareesuwan S, White NJ, Nosten F. A randomized, controlled study of a simple, once-daily regimen of dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated, multidrug-resistant falciparum malaria. Clin Infect Dis. 2005 Aug 15;41(4):425-32. Epub 2005 Jul 15.</citation>
    <PMID>16028147</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Myint HY, Ashley EA, Day NP, Nosten F, White NJ. Efficacy and safety of dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine. Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg. 2007 Sep;101(9):858-66. Epub 2007 Jul 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17659311</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 4, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 4, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Malaria elimination</keyword>
  <keyword>Chemotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Epidemiology</keyword>
  <keyword>South East Asia</keyword>
  <keyword>Artemisinin resistance</keyword>
  <keyword>Dihydroartemisinin piperaquine</keyword>
  <keyword>Primaquine</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Malaria, Falciparum</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Primaquine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Artemisinins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dihydroquinghaosu</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Piperaquine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Artemisinine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
