<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="127906">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02109575</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHW 10/83</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL119747</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02109575</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Targeted, Highly Sensitive, Non-Invasive Cardiac Transplant Rejection Monitoring</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Highly Sensitive and Targeted Non-Invasive Test for the Surveillance of Rejection in Cardiac Transplant Recipients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical College of Wisconsin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical College of Wisconsin</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigator's primary goal is to quantitatively detect donor-specific DNA in plasma of
      organ transplant recipients.  The investigator believe's that donor specific DNA can be
      isolated and quantified from transplant recipient serum. The investigator hypothesizes that
      the percent level of donor DNA circulating in recipient serum will reflect transplant
      rejection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Early detection of rejection is a major focus of organ transplant care. The use of
      aggressive immunosuppressive therapy has been shown to alter the prognosis of heart
      transplant patients who have acute rejection. There are many modalities utilized in the
      routine surveillance of cardiac transplant patients, each with limitations. Screening
      transthoracic echocardiography focusing on indices of systolic and diastolic dysfunction,
      along with regional wall abnormalities, has been shown to have poor sensitivity and does not
      effectively discriminate between patients with and without rejection. Newer
      echocardiographic parameters including myocardial performance or diastolic velocity indices
      may be a better means of detecting subtle changes in cardiac function in the setting of
      heart transplant, but these tools are most helpful after the insult caused by rejection has
      already occurred. Hemodynamic changes measured during cardiac catheterization have also been
      evaluated as a means of detecting rejection. Rosenthal et al found that although there were
      statistically significant differences between patients with higher or lower grades of
      rejection scores, cardiac catheterization did not permit effective discrimination of
      patients with moderate to severe rejection. Cardiac biomarkers, including c-reactive
      protein, brain natriuretic peptides, and troponin, have been studied as non-invasive
      measures of determining cardiac dysfunction or rejection. These surrogates are weakly
      associated with different rejection grades on biopsy and have a poor predictive capacity for
      biopsy-detected rejection. Recently, Microarray technology has been used to screen for genes
      expressed in cardiac allograft rejection using peripheral leukocytes from blood samples
      obtained at the time of endomyocardial biopsy. This technique was shown to have a high
      negative predictive value for the diagnosis of acute cellular rejection but it is unable to
      detect low grades of rejection. Overall, these technologies are limited in the ability to
      consistently and accurately predict the presence of rejection and have low positive
      predictive values when compared to biopsy.

      The current gold standard in detection of rejection is the use of endomyocardial biopsy.
      Attaining these samples is invasive and long term repeated central venous access can be
      difficult. Risk of endomyocardial biopsy includes perforation leading to cardiac tamponade,
      arrhythmias including atrial fibrillation, pneumothorax, hemothorax, and valvular
      regurgitation secondary to rupture of chordae or damage to valve leaflets themselves. There
      is variability in pathological interpretation of histologic grades, especially at higher
      grades of rejection due to the difficulty in interpretation of nodular infiltrates. The
      revised International Society for Heart and Lung Transplantation (ISHLT) grading system has
      simplified the grading system of cellular rejection and now includes assessment of antibody
      mediated rejection. This may improve the utility of endomyocardial biopsy, but much
      controversy still exists on the method of grading rejection and its clinical implications.
      Thus, the development of a noninvasive, relatively inexpensive method that accurately
      predicts the presence of rejection is critical.

      Detection of donor deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) after transplantation has been proposed as a
      means of detecting acute rejection in solid organ transplant patients, however there are
      significant barriers to detection and quantification on the sub-1 % level. Lo et al found
      that donor-specific DNA sequences were present in the plasma of liver and kidney transplant
      patients. Gadi et al detected soluble donor-specific DNA in patients who received
      pancreas-kidney transplants. In addition, in a single pancreas-kidney transplant recipient
      they demonstrated increased levels of donor specific DNA during a rejection episode. Garcia
      Moreira et al identified donor-specific cell free DNA in the serum and urine sample of renal
      transplant patients. They reported analysis by quantitative polymerase chain reaction (PCR)
      with marked increases of total cell-free DNA during episodes of acute rejection. Hubacek et
      al established the presence of donor DNA in recipient plasma in small concentrations in
      cardiac transplant patients. However, at their levels of detection, they observed
      significant background problems. They postulated the need for multiple markers to avoid this
      contamination.

      Pediatric liver transplantation has advanced significantly over the last 20 years. One year
      patient and graft survival following liver transplant in pediatric recipients is
      approximately 95% due to advances in surgical technique, anesthesia, critical care, and
      immunosuppression. Despite these advancements, rejection remains a significant problem and
      will occur in up to 30% of recipients during their first year after transplant. The current
      gold standard for diagnosing rejection is a liver biopsy. Although multiple serum markers of
      liver function are followed after transplantation, none have been definitively associated
      with rejection. Liver biopsy is an invasive procedure, often requiring general anesthesia in
      infants and small children, and is associated with multiple potential complications
      including bleeding, pneumothorax, bowel perforation and even death. The frequency of these
      complications varies from 10 - 20% depending on the publication. Consequently, the
      development of a serum marker for rejection after pediatric liver transplant is critical and
      could lead to a significant improvement in patient safety as well as quality of care.

      Donor specific cell free DNA (dsCFDNA) has been demonstrated in the serum of both liver and
      kidney recipients following transplantation. These investigators originally speculated that
      the concentration of donor DNA in the recipient's plasma may be a marker for rejection.

      Recent data has suggested that cell-free DNA increases with rejection in renal transplant
      recipients. No data exists to our knowledge regarding dsCFDNA following liver
      transplantation.

      As in other transplanted organs biopsy remains the gold standard for diagnosing rejection
      following renal transplant. Although renal biopsy is a safe procedure, it is costly and is
      not without risk. Development of a noninvasive biomarker of allograft status is an important
      objective in transplantation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Donor-Specific Cell-Free DNA in Plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>1 to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assay and laboratory protocol development and optimization.  To develop and optimize an assay and protocol to detect donor-specific cell free DNA from recipient plasma.  This aim will be ongoing throughout the multicenter study and the lab process is unblinded.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Circulating Donor-Specific Cell Free DNA</measure>
    <time_frame>2 to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the threshold of elevation of circulating donor specific cell free DNA (cfDNA) and develop an accurate predictive model for cardiac allograft rejection. Clinical and demographic factors as well as quantification of donor specific and total cfDNA will contribute to the predictive model. This phase of the lab process is blinded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Measure true positive and true negative Donor Specific Cell Free DNA</measure>
    <time_frame>4 to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To validate the threshold and predictive model to evaluate sensitivity and specificity of donor specific cell free DNA to detect donor injury on a cellular level. This phase of the lab process is blinded.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Disease</condition>
  <condition>Acute Rejection of Cardiac Transplant</condition>
  <condition>Cardiac Transplant Rejection</condition>
  <condition>Heart Transplant Failure and Rejection</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Whole Blood
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Study population will include patients of any age who have undergone cardiac transplant or
        who are listed to undergo cardiac transplant.  Pediatric and adult heart transplant
        patients will be recruited from six cardiac transplant sites:  Children's Hospital of
        Wisconsin, Arkansas Children's Hospital, Emory University, Duke Children's Hospital and
        Health Center, Columbia University Medical Center, and Vanderbilt University.  The
        multicenter study will recruit up to 1,000 subjects over five years; of those,
        approximately 480 will be new transplant subjects. The multicenter study will expand a
        pilot study already implemented at Children's Hospital of Wisconsin.  Children's Hospital
        of Wisconsin/Medical College of Wisconsin will serve as Coordinating Center for the
        Multicenter phase.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Any patient who is &quot;listed&quot; to undergo or has in the past undergone heart
             transplantation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any patient who is not currently listed to undergo heart transplantation and has not
             previously received a heart transplant, or who is unable or unwilling to provide
             documented informed consent for self or through a legally authorized representative.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Mitchell, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael Mitchell, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(414) 266-2491</phone>
    <email>mmitchell@chw.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Anne Laulederkind, BSN</last_name>
    <phone>(414) 805-8932</phone>
    <email>alaulede@mcw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical College of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Mitchell, MD</last_name>
      <email>mmitchell@chw.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Anne Laulederkind, BSN</last_name>
      <email>alaulede@mcw.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Mitchell, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mats Hidestrand, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steven Zangwill, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 10, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Acute Rejection</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiac Biomarkers</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiac Catheterization</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiomyopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Cell-Free DNA</keyword>
  <keyword>Congenital Heart Defect</keyword>
  <keyword>Congenital Heart Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Coronary Angiogram</keyword>
  <keyword>Donor Specific DNA</keyword>
  <keyword>Donor Specific Cell-Free DNA</keyword>
  <keyword>Endomyocardial Biopsy</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart Failure</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart Transplant Failure</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart Transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart Transplant Rejection</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
