<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="126132">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01988974</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-007768</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01988974</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Feasibility Testing of the Alert for Atrial Fibrillation Program</brief_title>
  <official_title>Feasibility Testing of the Alert for Atrial Fibrillation Program</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the psychometric properties of the Knowledge,
      Attitudes, and Beliefs about Atrial Fibrillation Survey (KABAFS) and to generate critical,
      practical knowledge about the feasibility of conducting a randomized trial to test the
      effect of the Alert for Atrial Fibrillation program on treatment-seeking for symptoms of
      Atrial Fibrillation (AF).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the proposed research is to evaluate the psychometric properties of the
      Knowledge, Attitudes, and Beliefs about Atrial Fibrillation Survey (KABAFS), which is an
      instrument designed to tailor the delivery of the Alert for Atrial Fibrillation program. The
      proposed research will also test the feasibility of studying the effect of the Alert for
      Atrial Fibrillation program on treatment-seeking for symptoms of AF in a larger, randomized
      trial. This research is significant, because current research suggests that treatment
      seeking for AF is hindered when people do not recognize symptoms that represent AF,
      attribute those symptoms to alternative causes, or do not believe symptoms are serious
      enough to require medical evaluation. Interventions tailored to modify patient-specific
      knowledge, attitudes, and beliefs that hinder early treatment-seeking are critically needed
      in order to improve early detection of AF. The long term goal of this research is to improve
      health outcomes of those at risk for developing AF.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes on the Knowledge, Attitudes, and Beliefs about Atrial Fibrillation Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, One Month, Two Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The KABAFS assesses patient knowledge of Atrial Fibrillation (AF) and the belief factors associated with delay in seeking treatment for AF.  Participants will be measured at baseline (before the intervention), and then at 1 and 2 months after the intervention to identify if participants' knowledge and beliefs about treatment seeking have improved and continue to be improved from baseline as indicated by the KABAFS score.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Alert for AF Program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will participate in the Alert for Atrial Fibrillation program.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Alert for Atrial Fibrillation Program</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants' baseline knowledge of AF symptoms, and attitudes and beliefs about AF will be assessed using the KABAFS, and patients will receive cognitive-behavioral training directed toward survey responses associated with delay of treatment. Training will incorporate the content developed by the American College of Cardiology Foundation (ACCF), and participants will receive education about how to recognize an irregular pulse, and how to record the pulse rhythm in a daily log. The PI/RN coordinator will review the completed KABAFS to assess knowledge deficits, and identify attitudes and beliefs about AF that may hinder early treatment-seeking.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Alert for AF Program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  65 years of age or older

          -  Under the care of providers from the Department of Medicine

          -  English-speaking

          -  Community dwelling,

          -  Have access to and ability to communicate via a telephone

          -  Have one or more risks for developing AF

          -  Not be diagnosed with AF

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Documented cognitive impairment

          -  Uncompensated hearing or visual deficits

          -  Scheduled for surgery or have undergone a surgical procedure in the last 30 days,

          -  Undergoing active treatment for a malignancy

          -  Receiving hospice care will be excluded
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pamela J McCabe, PhD, RN</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Pamela J. McCabe, PhD, RN</last_name>
    <phone>507-293-1515</phone>
    <email>mccabe.pamela2@mayo.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pamela McCabe, PhD, RN</last_name>
      <phone>507-293-1515</phone>
      <email>mccabe.pamela2@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 26, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 14, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Pamela J. McCabe, R.N., Ph.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Nursing</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
