<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="116098">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02041468</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Q-CROC-05</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02041468</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Evaluate Resistance Mechanisms and Real-world Pharmacoeconomics of Crizotinib in NSCLC Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase IV Multicenter Trial to Evaluate the Resistance Mechanisms and Real-world Pharmacoeconomics of Crizotinib and Its Companion Diagnostic Test in Advanced ALK-positive Non-small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jewish General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Jewish General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Ethics Review Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase IV multicenter trial to evaluate the mechanisms of resistance and
      pharmacoeconomic (PE) impact of crizotinib and its companion diagnostic test used in a
      real-life setting in advanced ALK-positive non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) patients.

      NSCLC represent 80% of all new cases of lung cancer. One molecular subtype of NSCLC is the
      ALK-positive subtype. The anaplastic lymphoma kinase (ALK) is a transmembrane receptor
      tyrosine kinase. Activation of ALK occurs through the formation of gene fusions and in
      NSCLC, the gene fusion partner for ALK is primarily EML4. The resulting fusion protein is
      capable of activating the ALK kinase domain, leading to cell growth. The estimated
      prevalence for ALK rearrangements in NSCLC is 3-5%, and is more commonly found amongst
      patients with adenocarcinoma histology, in never smokers and in those who are known to be
      wild type for EGFR and KRAS.

      Crizotinib is a potent inhibitor of ALK and is approved for the treatment of advanced ALK+
      NSCLC patients. This is an example of personalized medicine, where patients are selected for
      treatment based upon a molecular assay, and are provided a specific therapy (crizotinib) for
      their disease. The pharmacoeconomic impact of using genetic information in early treatment
      decisions in NSCLC has not been determined. Despite the benefits of crizotinib, some
      patients do not respond to treatment and most patients will eventually develop resistance.
      To date, it is unclear why some rare patients do not respond to treatment and the resistance
      mechanisms of crizotinib have not been fully elucidated.

      The study will address two anticipated issues surrounding personalized medicine and
      treatment with crizotinib:

        -  it will enable real-life Heath Economics and Outcome Research (HEOR)

        -  it will validate and/or identify new blood-based or tissue-based biomarkers of
           resistance to crizotinib.

      Approximately 90 patients will be recruited in Quebec and Ontario for the PE study. Patients
      will be asked to complete quality-of-life questionnaires at regular intervals in a real-life
      setting of treatment with crizotinib. Approximately 25 patients will be recruited to the
      biomarker sub-study to understand resistance mechanisms of crizotinib. In these patients, a
      biopsy from any accessible metastatic lesion will be obtained when the patient is no longer
      responding to treatment, as well as blood sampling during regular treatment visits.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The pharmacoeconomic impact of using personalized medicine for the treatment of ALK+ lung cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of registration until date of death from any cause, assessed up to 60 months.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Pharmacoeconomic impact (cost-effectiveness and cost utility) will be evaluated by questionnaires completed by the patient and caregiver. These include quality of life, health resource utilization, work productivity and activity impairment, and health questionnaires</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Type of resistance mechanisms identified in crizotinib-resistant tumors</measure>
    <time_frame>At progression of disease, an expected average of 24 months.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A biopsy will be taken from a metastatic lesion that has progressed despite treatment with crizotinib. Genomic material will be isolated and sequenced to identify causes of acquired resistance to crizotinib.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in blood-based biomarkers of response to crizotinib.</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of registration until the date of treatment discontinuation, an expected average of 24 months.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Plasma will be isolated from patients pre-treatment, at every disease assessment, at progression of disease, and at treatment discontinuation. This will be used to identify changes in blood-based biomarkers using proteomics analysis by mass spectrometry.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with adverse events related to the biopsy procedure.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Adverse events possibly, probably or definitely related to the biopsy procedure will be reported according to the The NCI's Common Toxicity Criteria version 4.0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-small Cell Lung Cancer Metastatic</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      The study will collect plasma, platelet-depleted plasma, tumor tissue (biopsy of a
      metastatic site that has acquired resistant to treatment) and primary archived tissue.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with locally advanced or metastatic non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) found
        positive for ALK mutation from participating hospitals in Quebec.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with histologically confirmed locally advanced or metastatic NSCLC

          -  Presence of the ALK-fusion oncogene (ALK+) as determined using a validated testing
             platform

          -  Measurable disease according to RECIST v. 1.1

          -  Planned or ongoing treatment with crizotinib

          -  Signed and dated IRB-approved informed consent document

          -  Ability to read and understand English or French

          -  18 years of age or older

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS-related illnesses) or known HIV disease.

          -  Unwilling to provide consent for genetic studies of the tumor, whole blood, or plasma
             specimens.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jason Agulnik, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Jewish General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Victor Cohen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Jewish General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Julie Martin, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>450-629-2200</phone>
    <phone_ext>231</phone_ext>
    <email>jmartin@scimega.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Caroline Rousseau, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>514 340-8222</phone>
    <phone_ext>5074</phone_ext>
    <email>crousseau@jgh.mcgill.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>McGill University Health Center (JGH, St-Mary's, MGH, RVH)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H3T 1E2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laurent Seti</last_name>
      <phone>514.340.8222</phone>
      <phone_ext>4785</phone_ext>
      <email>lseti@jgh.mcgill.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ginette Ricard</last_name>
      <phone>514.934.1934</phone>
      <phone_ext>43129</phone_ext>
      <email>ginette.ricard@muhc.mcgill.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jason Agulnik, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Victor Cohen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vera Hirsh, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Scott Owen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joan Zidulka, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Richard Dalfen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Donna Stern, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Adrian Langleben, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre hospitalier de l'Université de Montréal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Normand Blais, MD,MSc,FRCPC</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Universitaire de cardiologie et de pneumonologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Quebec</city>
        <zip>G1V 4G5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Brigitte Fortin</last_name>
      <phone>(418) 656-8711</phone>
      <phone_ext>2639</phone_ext>
      <email>brigitte.fortin@criucpq.ulaval.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lise Tremblay, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Francis Laberge, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Simon Martel, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yves Lacasse, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bruno Raby, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vincent Gaudreau, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Katayama R, Shaw AT, Khan TM, Mino-Kenudson M, Solomon BJ, Halmos B, Jessop NA, Wain JC, Yeo AT, Benes C, Drew L, Saeh JC, Crosby K, Sequist LV, Iafrate AJ, Engelman JA. Mechanisms of acquired crizotinib resistance in ALK-rearranged lung Cancers. Sci Transl Med. 2012 Feb 8;4(120):120ra17. doi: 10.1126/scitranslmed.3003316. Epub 2012 Jan 25.</citation>
    <PMID>22277784</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Camidge DR, Doebele RC. Treating ALK-positive lung cancer--early successes and future challenges. Nat Rev Clin Oncol. 2012 Apr 3;9(5):268-77. doi: 10.1038/nrclinonc.2012.43. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22473102</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kwak EL, Bang YJ, Camidge DR, Shaw AT, Solomon B, Maki RG, Ou SH, Dezube BJ, Jänne PA, Costa DB, Varella-Garcia M, Kim WH, Lynch TJ, Fidias P, Stubbs H, Engelman JA, Sequist LV, Tan W, Gandhi L, Mino-Kenudson M, Wei GC, Shreeve SM, Ratain MJ, Settleman J, Christensen JG, Haber DA, Wilner K, Salgia R, Shapiro GI, Clark JW, Iafrate AJ. Anaplastic lymphoma kinase inhibition in non-small-cell lung cancer. N Engl J Med. 2010 Oct 28;363(18):1693-703.</citation>
    <PMID>20979469</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Doebele RC, Pilling AB, Aisner DL, Kutateladze TG, Le AT, Weickhardt AJ, Kondo KL, Linderman DJ, Heasley LE, Franklin WA, Varella-Garcia M, Camidge DR. Mechanisms of resistance to crizotinib in patients with ALK gene rearranged non-small cell lung cancer. Clin Cancer Res. 2012 Mar 1;18(5):1472-82. doi: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-11-2906. Epub 2012 Jan 10.</citation>
    <PMID>22235099</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 20, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Jewish General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Jason Agulnik</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ALK-positive</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
