<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="95661">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01755156</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3102-024</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01755156</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, and Efficacy of the Addition of MK-3102 to Participants With Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus Who Have Inadequate Glycemic Control on Metformin Therapy (MK-3102-024)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multicenter, Randomized, Double-Blind Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, and Efficacy of the Addition of MK-3102 to Subjects With Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus Who Have Inadequate Glycemic Control on Metformin Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess the safety and efficacy of MK-3102 compared to
      placebo in participants with inadequate glycemic control on metformin monotherapy. The
      primary hypothesis is that after 24 weeks, the addition of treatment with MK-3102 provides
      greater reduction in hemoglobin A1c (A1C) than placebo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in A1C at Week 24</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants who experienced at least one adverse event</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 107 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants who discontinued study drug due to an adverse event</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 104 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants who experienced a laboratory abnormality</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 104 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in 2-hour post-meal glucose (PMG) at Week 24</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in fasting plasma glucose (FPG) at Week 24</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in A1C at Week 104</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 104</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in FPG at Week 104</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 104</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of participants attaining A1C glycemic goals of &lt;7% and &lt;6.5% after 24 weeks of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of participants attaining A1C glycemic goals of &lt;7% and &lt;6.5% after 104 weeks of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>104 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in PMG total area under the curve (AUC) at Week 24</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in fasting insulin at Week 24</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in fasting insulin at Week 104</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 104</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to rescue over 24 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to rescue over 104 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 104 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of participants requiring rescue therapy at Week 24</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of participants requiring rescue therapy at Week 104</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 104</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3102</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MK-3102 25 mg capsule administered orally once weekly for 104 weeks (24 weeks during Phase A, 80 weeks during Phase B) and matching placebo to glimepiride tablet administered orally once daily for 80 weeks (Phase B). Participants will continue pre-study metformin throughout the duration of the study. If necessary, rescue therapy may be initiated (open-label glimepiride during Phase A and open-label insulin glargine during Phase B).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Matching placebo to MK-3102</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Matching placebo to MK-3102 capsule administered orally once weekly for 104 weeks (24 weeks during Phase A, 80 weeks during Phase B) and  glimepiride 1 or 2 mg tablet administered orally once daily (titrated up to 6 mg daily) for 80 weeks (Phase B). Participants will continue pre-study metformin throughout the duration of the study. If necessary, rescue therapy may be initiated (open-label glimepiride during Phase A and insulin glargine during Phase B).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MK-3102</intervention_name>
    <description>MK-3102 25 mg capsule administered orally once weekly (preferably on the same day of each week)</description>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3102</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Matching placebo to MK-3102</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo to MK-3102 capsule administered orally once weekly (preferably on the same day of each week)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Matching placebo to MK-3102</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Glimepiride</intervention_name>
    <description>Glimepiride 1 or 2 mg tablet administered orally once daily and up-titrated to a maximum dose of 6 mg daily. Participants rescued with open-label glimepiride during Phase A will not receive glimepiride or matching placebo to glimepiride during Phase B.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Matching placebo to MK-3102</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Amaryl®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Matching placebo to glimepiride</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo to glimepiride tablet administered orally once daily and up-titrated to a mock maximum dose of 6 mg daily. Participants rescued with open-label glimepiride during Phase A will not receive glimepiride or matching placebo to glimepiride during Phase B.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3102</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Insulin glargine</intervention_name>
    <description>During Phase B of the study, participants who received a maximum up-titration of open-label glimepiride or blinded glimepiride/matching placebo to glimepiride, may be rescued with open-label insulin glargine.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3102</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Matching placebo to MK-3102</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lantus</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metformin</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants continue stable pre-study dose of metformin tablet(s) administered orally (&gt;= 1500 mg daily) throughout the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3102</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Matching placebo to MK-3102</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fortamet®</other_name>
    <other_name>Glucophage®</other_name>
    <other_name>Glucophage® XR</other_name>
    <other_name>Glumetza®</other_name>
    <other_name>Riomet®</other_name>
    <other_name>Metgluco®</other_name>
    <other_name>Glycoran®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Has type 2 diabetes mellitus

          -  Currently on a stable dose of metformin monotherapy (&gt;=1500 mg per day) for at least
             12 weeks prior to study participation

          -  Male, or female who is not of reproductive potential or if of reproductive potential
             agrees to abstain from heterosexual activity or use (or have their partner use)
             acceptable contraception to prevent pregnancy during the study and for 21 days after
             the last dose of study drug

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of type 1 diabetes mellitus or a history of ketoacidosis

          -  Has been treated with any antihyperglycemic agent (AHA) other than the
             protocol-required metformin within 12 weeks prior to study participation or with
             MK-3102 at any time prior to signing informed consent

          -  History of hypersensitivity to a dipeptidyl peptidase IV (DPP-4) inhibitor

          -  History of intolerance, hypersensitivity, or any other contraindication to metformin,
             glimepiride, or insulin glargine

          -  Is on a weight loss program and is not in the maintenance phase or has been on a
             weight loss medication in the past 6 months or has undergone bariatric surgery within
             12 months prior to study participation

          -  Has undergone a surgical procedure within 4 weeks of study participation or has
             planned major surgery during the study

          -  Is on or likely to require treatment for &gt;=2 consecutive weeks or repeated courses of
             corticosteroids (inhaled, nasal and topical corticosteroids are permitted)

          -  Currently being treated for hyperthyroidism or is on thyroid hormone replacement
             therapy and has not been on a stable dose for at least 6 weeks

          -  Is expecting to undergo hormonal therapy in preparation to donate eggs during the
             period of the trial, including 21 days after the last dose of blinded study
             medication

          -  History of active liver disease (other than non-alcoholic steatosis) including
             chronic active hepatitis B or C, primary biliary cirrhosis, or symptomatic
             gallbladder disease

          -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)

          -  New or worsening signs or symptoms of coronary heart disease or congestive heart
             failure within the past 3 months, or myocardial infarction, unstable angina, coronary
             artery bypass grafting, percutaneous transluminal coronary angioplasty, stroke, or
             transient ischemic attacks in the past 3 months

          -  Poorly controlled hypertension

          -  History of malignancy &lt;=5 years prior to study participation, except for adequately
             treated basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer or in situ cervical cancer

          -  Hematological disorder (such as aplastic anemia, myeloproliferative or
             myelodysplastic syndromes, thrombocytopenia)

          -  Positive urine pregnancy test

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding, or is expecting to conceive during the study including 21
             days following the last dose of blinded study drug

          -  User of recreational or illicit drugs or has had a recent history of drug abuse

          -  Routinely consumes &gt;2 alcoholic drinks per day or &gt;14 alcoholic drinks per week, or
             engages in binge drinking

          -  Has donated blood products or has had phlebotomy of &gt;300 mL within 8 weeks of study
             participation, or intends to donate blood products within the projected duration of
             the trial or has received, or is anticipated to receive, blood products within 12
             weeks of study participation or within the projected duration of the trial
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Bulgaria</country>
    <country>Hungary</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>Romania</country>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
    <country>Slovakia</country>
    <country>South Africa</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 19, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 18, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Glimepiride</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glargine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insulin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insulin, Long-Acting</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
