<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="120902">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01757171</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1208012946</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01757171</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase II Study of Cabazitaxel in Refractory Metastatic Gastric or Gastroesophageal Adenocarcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Labeled, Multicenter Phase II Study of Cabazitaxel in Refractory Metastatic Gastric or Gastroesophageal Adenocarcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sanofi</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cabazitaxel will be administered 25 mg/m2 IV over 1 hour every 3 weeks, as is the standard
      administration dose and schedule.  This application is a non-labeled indication for
      cabazitaxel and will inform future drug development in gastroesophageal malignancies, where
      docetaxel remains an approved first line agent, but is not routinely used due to excessive
      toxicity and marginal efficacy.

      At the conclusion of this study, we hope to demonstrate activity of single agent cabazitaxel
      in refractory gastric cancer, with preferential activity in one or more gastric cancer
      subtypes
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Prior to initiating protocol therapy, patients will undergo screening evaluations, to be
      done within 30 days of protocol initiation unless otherwise noted.

      Patients who are taxane naïve will be assigned to arm A and patients who have had prior
      taxane therapy will be assigned to Arm B. Each arm will be analyzed separately for the
      primary study endpoint of 3 month progression free survival rate (PFS), as defined as the
      time from the start of treatment to the date of disease progression or death. Cabazitaxel
      will be administered 25 mg/m2 IV over 1 hour every 3 weeks.

      In the absence of treatment delays due to adverse event(s), treatment may continue until
      disease progression; intercurrent illness that prevents further administration of treatment;
      unacceptable adverse event(s); patient decides to withdraw; general or specific changes in
      the patient's condition render the patient unacceptable for further treatment in the
      judgment of the investigator.

      Patients will be followed for 6 months after removal from study or until death, whichever
      occurs first.  Patients removed from study for unacceptable adverse events will be followed
      until resolution or stabilization of the adverse event.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response to cabazitaxel</measure>
    <time_frame>estimation of 4 years to determine response on all subjects</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To demonstrate the antitumor activity as assessed by the rate of progression free survival at three months of the sanofi-aventis product cabazitaxel 25mg/m2 IV over 1 hour every 3 weeks in subjects with previously treated metastatic gastroesophageal adenocarcinoma who are either taxane naïve, or taxane previously treated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Event free survival of subjects treated with cabazitaxel</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 4 years to assess response on all subjects accrued to the study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To examine other measures of efficacy including overall progression free and overall survival in all evaluable patients, and the objective response rate in patients with measurable disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity profile of cabazitaxel.</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximated 4 years to obtain safety data for all subjects.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The frequency of subjects experiencing toxicities will be tabulated. Toxicities will be assessed and graded according to CTCAE v. 4.0. Exact 95% confidence intervals around the toxicity proportions will be calculated to assess the precision of the obtained estimate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response to cabazitaxel across gastric cancer subtypes.</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 4 years to obtain efficacy data on all subjects.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Response will be measured by the disappearance of the sum of the diameters of all target lesions observed on CT/MRI scan.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">86</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastric Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Gastroesophageal Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Distal Esophageal Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (taxane naïve)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>No prior Taxane treatment. Cabazitaxel will be administered 25 mg/m2 IV over 1 hour every 3 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (prior taxane therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subject previously treated with taxane. Cabazitaxel will be administered 25 mg/m2 IV over 1 hour every 3 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cabazitaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>25mg IV over 1 hour every 3 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (taxane naïve)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (prior taxane therapy)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject must have histologically or cytologically confirmed gastric, or
             gastroesophageal adenocarcinoma, or distal esophageal adenocarcinoma.

          2. Subject must have unresectable or metastatic gastroesophageal adenocarcinoma.

          3. Subject must have evaluable disease as per RECIST criteria.

          4. Subject must have had at least one prior cytotoxic chemotherapy regimen for
             unresectable or metastatic disease. Prior taxane therapy is allowed.

          5. Age &gt;/=18 years old.

          6. ECOG performance status status &gt;/= 2

          7. Subject must have normal organ and marrow function as defined below:

               -  WBC &gt;/= 3,000/uL

               -  Total Bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x upper limits of normal

               -  AST (SGOT) ≤ 2.5 x upper limits of normal

               -  ALT (SGPT) ≤ 2.5 x upper limits of normal

               -  Hgb &gt; 7.5 g/dl (without transfusion within 7 days)

               -  ANC &gt; 1000 /ml

               -  Plt &gt; 75 K/ml (without transfusion)

               -  Creatinine* &lt; 2.0 g/dl *or a calculated creatinine clearance &gt; 45/cc (using
                  Cockroft-Gault formula)

        9. Women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
        (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry and for the
        duration of study participation. 10. Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a
        written informed consent document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject with previously untreated unresectable or metastatic gastroesophageal
             adenocarcinoma.

          2. Subject with more than 2 prior cytotoxic therapies (not including treatment
             administered for locally curable disease) for unresectable or metastatic
             gastroesophageal adenocarcinoma.

          3. Subject with CNS metastases with active neurologic dysfunction. These patients are
             excluded because of their poor prognosis and because they often develop progressive
             neurologic dysfunction that would confound the evaluation of neurologic and other
             adverse event.

          4. Significant medical co-morbidity that would preclude safe administration of cytotoxic
             therapy, including but not limited to:

             a.Cardiac disease i. Unstable angina ii. Myocardial infarction &lt; 3 months prior to
             study initiation b. Ongoing serious infection i. Bacteremia or sepsis requiring
             intravenous antibiotics ii. HIV with AIDS defining illness c.Inadequate oral
             nutritional intake i. Requirement for daily intravenous fluids or total parenteral
             nutrition. d. Psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirement

          5. Subject who has had chemotherapy or radiotherapy within 4 weeks (6 weeks for
             nitrosoureas or mitomycin C) prior to entering the study or those who have not
             recovered from prior treatment related toxicity with persistent symptoms &gt;/= grade 2
             due to agents administered more than 4 weeks earlier.

          6. Subject may not receive another investigational agent.

          7. History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to Cabazitaxel, or to drugs formulated with polysorbate 80.

          8. Pregnant (positive pregnancy test) and lactating women are excluded from the study
             because the risks to an unborn fetus or potential risks in nursing infants are
             unknown.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Manish Shah, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alice Mercado, RN</last_name>
    <phone>212-746-5430</phone>
    <email>alm2051@med.cornell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Weill Cornell Medical College</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Manish Shah, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-962-6200</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 24, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 6, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gastric Cancer</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stomach Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
