<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="72160">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01871142</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-4002H</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01871142</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Attenuation by Aes-103 of Hypoxia Mediated Decrements in Endurance Exercise Performance</brief_title>
  <official_title>Double-Blind, Placebo Controlled Evaluation of the Attenuation by Aes-103 of Hypoxia Mediated Decrements in Endurance Exercise Performance in Healthy Adult Humans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Colorado State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>AesRx, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Colorado State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In low oxygen environments, such as high-altitude, some adults may become ill and suffer
      from acute mountain sickness. Further, all adults will find that exercising becomes much
      more difficult when compared with exercise at lower altitudes (e.g. sea-level). The purpose
      of this investigation is to study the effects of a new medicine called Aes-103. A company
      called AesRx, LLC makes this medicine. The active ingredient in the medicine is
      5-Hydroxymethyl-2-Furfural (5HMF), a naturally occurring substance that can be found in
      coffee, honey, dried fruits, fruit juices, malt, barley, Balsamic vinegar and caramel.The
      investigators believe that Aes-103 may help people adjust to high-altitude quickly and
      prevent them from becoming ill. The purpose of the study is to determine if Aes-103 will
      promote endurance performance in low oxygen environments in healthy adult humans.

      Aes-103 is currently being investigated by AesRx, LLC (Newton, MA) in collaboration with the
      National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute of the NIH (Bethesda, MD) as a potential
      anti-sickling agent in sickle cell disease. Sickle-cell disease is characterized by problems
      in blood that prevent blood cells from carrying oxygen. Aes-103 might be able to help blood
      cells carry more oxygen. It is for this reason that the investigators in this study believe
      Aes-103 might help people adjust to high-altitude quickly.

      There are no known special safety considerations with the active ingredient in Aes-103
      (5-HMF). In recent, placebo controlled, clinical safety tests, Aes-103 was given in single
      doses of 300 mg, 1000 mg,2000 mg and 4000 mg to healthy normal volunteers. Additionally, the
      toxicological effects of Aes-103 have been studied when given acutely, sub-acutely, and
      chronically in rodents, and for up to 28 days in dogs. Based on these safety studies, single
      doses of Aes-103 are expected to have no significant negative/toxicological effect at the
      doses being evaluated in this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind blind, repeated measures (cross-over)
      study.  Approximately 12 healthy adult men will consume, in a random order, a placebo prior
      to exercise in normoxia, a placebo prior to exercise in hypoxia, 1000 mg of Aes-103 prior to
      exercise in hypoxia, and 3000 mg of Aes-103 prior to exercise in hypoxia.

      Study participants will report to the Human Performance/Clinical Research Laboratory (HPCRL)
      on 6 separate occasions.  On visit 1 study participants will undergo screening (e.g. medical
      history and 12-lead electrocardiogram and blood pressure at rest and during incremental
      exercise to volitional exhaustion), and will be instructed to avoid foods and drinks high in
      5-HMF (e.g., coffee, malt, barley, dried fruits, and caramel) for at least 3 days before
      each subsequent visit.  Visit 2 will comprise of a habituation visit during which subjects
      will be given the opportunity to rehearse the exercise test. Visits 3, 4, 5 and 6, will
      occur in a random order and be almost identical in nature.  Study participants will abstain
      from vigorous physical exercise and alcohol consumption during the 24-hours prior to each
      visit.  In addition, study participants will abstain from all food and beverages, except
      water, during the 4-hours prior to visits 3, 4, 5 and 6.  On arrival subjects will be
      instrumented for measurement of heart rate, blood pressure and blood oxygen saturation.
      Following baseline determination subjects will consume either: a placebo, 1000 mg of Aes-103
      or 3000 mg of Aes-103.  45 minutes after consumption, participants will enter our
      environmental chamber, adjusted randomly to either normoxia (21% oxygen) or hypoxia (15%
      oxygen).  The pairing of normoxia/hypoxia and supplement will be as follows: placebo +
      normoxia, placebo + hypoxia, 1000 mg + hypoxia, and 3000 mg + hypoxia.  Participants will
      remain seated in the environmental chamber for 15 minutes, after which they will complete a
      standardized warm-up bout of exercise (100 W for 30 minutes) followed by a brief time trial
      (time taken to cycle 12.5 km (~7.75 miles)). Heart rate, blood pressure and blood oxygen
      saturation will be recorded every 5 minutes.  During exercise, subjective ratings of
      perceived exertion (Borg Scale) will be recorded every 10 minutes, and at end-exercise.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary objective endurance exercise performance</measure>
    <time_frame>The time trial will begin after 1 hour after consumption of the intervention or placebo under normoxic or hypoxic conditions.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To quantify endurance exercise performance (time trial performance during stationary cycle ergometer exercise) in healthy adult men in four conditions: normoxia (normal oxygen; fraction of inspired oxygen = 0.21) following oral placebo consumption, hypoxia (low oxygen; fraction of inspired oxygen = 0.15) following oral placebo consumption, hypoxia following oral consumption Aes-103 (1000 mg) and hypoxia following oral consumption Aes-103 (3000 mg).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary Objective safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>AEs will be monitored at the time of visit and during the follow up period of 7 to 14 days.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess the safety and tolerability of single, escalating oral doses of Aes-103 compared with placebo in healthy adult men at rest and during stationary cycle ergometer exercise in normoxia and hypoxia by monitoring adverse events (AEs), electrocardiograms (ECGs), blood pressure, blood oxygen saturation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">11</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypoxia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normoxia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>single dose placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hypoxia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>single dose of 1000mg Aes-103, single dose of 3000mg Aes-103, single dose of placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aes-103</intervention_name>
    <description>single dose of 1000mg Aes-103, or single dose of 3000mg Aes-103</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hypoxia</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>5-Hydroxymethyl-2-Furfural (5-HMF)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>100 ml</description>
    <arm_group_label>Normoxia</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tropicana Pure Premium Orange Juice</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Be a healthy male volunteer, aged 18-40 years old, body mass index 18-30  kg/m2,
             inclusive

          -  Have successfully completed a screening visit consisting of medical history, physical
             examination, 12-lead ECG, blood pressure, blood oxygen saturation at rest and during
             incremental exercise to volitional exhaustion (Note: Subjects with abnormal screening
             values may be eligible if the results are not clinically significant, as judged by
             the investigator or medical monitor)

          -  Be able to understand and have provided written informed consent including signature
             on an informed consent form approved by an institutional review board

          -  Have provided written authorization for use and disclosure of protected   health
             information

          -  Agree to abide by the study schedule and dietary restrictions and to return for the
             required assessments

          -  Be willing to abstain from foods high in 5-HMF (e.g., coffee, malt, barley, balsamic
             vinegar, dried fruits,and caramel products) for at least 3 days prior to each dosing

          -  Be willing and able to repeatedly perform exhaustive cycle ergometer exercise

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Have evidence of clinically significant cardiovascular, respiratory, renal, hepatic,
             pulmonary, gastrointestinal, hematological, neurological, psychiatric, or other
             disease that may interfere with the objectives of the study or the safety of the
             subject, as judged by the investigator in agreement with the sponsor or medical
             monitor, have been hospitalized in the past 2 years as a result of these conditions,
              or are receiving pharmacological treatment for these conditions

          -  Have taken prescription drugs or herbal preparations in the 2 weeks before dosing

          -  Is currently enrolled in another clinical study for another investigational drug or
             has taken any other investigational drug within 30 days before the screening visit

          -  Habitual and/or recent use of recreational drugs, such as cocaine, marijuana,
             opiates, amphetamines, methamphetamines, benzodiazepines,

          -  Have taken disulfiram, 4-methylpyrazole, or any other drug that is an inhibitor of
             alcohol dehydrogenase or aldehyde dehydrogenase within the past 30 days

          -  Have engaged in strenuous physical activity within 24 hours prior to dosing

          -  Be considered not suitable for participation in this trial for any reason, as judged
             by the investigator
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christopher Bell, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Colorado State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Colorado State University, Dept. of Health and Exercise Science</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Collins</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80523-1582</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.chhs.colostate.edu</url>
    <description>Department of Health and Exercise Science, Colorado State University</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT01597401?term=Aes-103&amp;rank=1</url>
    <description>Initial Safety Trial For Treatments Under Investigation In Current Study</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 29, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Colorado State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Christopher Bell</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>5 Hydroxymethyl 2 Furfural</keyword>
  <keyword>AES103</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anoxia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
