<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9825">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01760005</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DIAN-TU-001</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>The Alzheimer's Association</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>1U01AG042791-01A1</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-000307-17</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01760005</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dominantly Inherited Alzheimer Network Trial: An Opportunity to Prevent Dementia. A Study of Potential Disease Modifying Treatments in Individuals at Risk for or With a Type of Early Onset Alzheimer's Disease Caused by a Genetic Mutation.</brief_title>
  <acronym>DIAN-TU</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase II/III Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Multi-Center Study of 2 Potential Disease Modifying Therapies in Individuals at Risk for and With Dominantly Inherited Alzheimer's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eli Lilly and Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hoffmann-La Roche</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Alzheimer's Association</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Avid Radiopharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>Italy: The Italian Medicines Agency</authority>
    <authority>Italy: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>Australia: Department of Health and Ageing Therapeutic Goods Administration</authority>
    <authority>Australia: National Health and Medical Research Council</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Agencia Española de Medicamentos y Productos Sanitarios</authority>
    <authority>France: Committee for the Protection of Personnes</authority>
    <authority>France: Agence Nationale de Sécurité du Médicament et des produits de santé</authority>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess the safety, tolerability and biomarker efficacy of
      Gantenerumab and Solanezumab in individuals who have an autosomal dominant Alzheimer's
      disease (ADAD) mutation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The mutations in presenilin 1 (PSEN1), presenilin 2 (PSEN2) and amyloid precursor protein
      (APP) that are associated with autosomal dominant Alzheimer's disease have very high
      penetrance (near 100%).  This study will target individuals who are either known to have a
      disease-causing mutation or who are at risk for such a mutation (the child or sibling of a
      proband with a known mutation) and unaware of their genetic status.   Because the age of
      onset of cognitive changes is relatively consistent within each family, an age of onset is
      determined for each affected parent as part of the DIAN longitudinal study protocol.
      Subjects will be eligible for enrollment in the DIAN-TU-001 study when they are between 15
      years younger (-15) to 10 years older (+10) than the age of onset of their affected parent.

      The ability to identify individuals destined to develop Alzheimer's disease (AD) within the
      next 10-15 years with a high degree of confidence provides a unique opportunity to assess
      the efficacy of therapies at asymptomatic and very early stages of dementia.  Although there
      are differences between dominantly inherited AD and the more common age-associated sporadic
      disease, the results of the early intervention in this study will have implications for
      future studies and treatments in sporadic AD.  Families with known disease-causing mutations
      are extremely rare and are geographically dispersed throughout the world.  These constraints
      necessitate a specialized study design.  Many of the subjects in this study will not yet
      have any cognitive symptoms of AD; they will be &quot;asymptomatic&quot; carriers of mutations that
      cause Autosomal Dominant Alzheimer's disease and would be expected to perform normally on
      standard cognitive and functional testing.  Imaging and fluid biomarkers will be used as the
      primary study endpoints to demonstrate that the treatment compounds have engaged their
      therapeutic targets.  A set of cognitive measures designed to assess the very earliest, most
      subtle cognitive changes will be collected, but will not be primary endpoints as many of
      these clinically asymptomatic individuals are likely to have minimal changes in cognitive
      measures during the study.  Additionally, because many at-risk individuals decide not to
      know whether they have the disease-associated mutation or not, some of the at-risk
      individuals enrolled in this study will not have the disease causing mutations; they will be
      &quot;mutation negative&quot;.  It is important to enroll non-carrier subjects to avoid coercion
      (e.g., potential subjects may be pressured into genetic testing to learn their genetic
      status in order to be eligible for the trial). These mutation negative individuals will be
      assigned to the placebo group; subjects and site study staff will remain blinded as to these
      individuals' active or placebo group assignment and mutation status.   Thus, the study will
      be double blinded for placebo and for mutation status, except for mutation positive subjects
      who are aware of their genetic status.  Two different therapies will be tested in order to
      increase the likelihood that an effective treatment will be discovered.  They were selected
      for this trial based on mechanism of action and available data on efficacy and safety
      profile.

      This study design is possible because the biomarker endpoints are relatively robust.  The
      study design includes a pooled placebo arm shared by all treatment groups.  Mutation
      positive subjects will be randomized to one of the three study arms (placebo, gantenerumab,
      solanezumab).  Mutation negative subjects will all receive placebo, but will be randomized
      to receive matching placebo for gantenerumab or solanezumab.   Importantly, subjects and
      study staff will not be blinded as to which treatment group each subject has been assigned;
      they will be blinded as to whether subjects have been randomized to active drug or placebo
      arms.  Biomarker endpoints will be specified for each treatment arm.  Biomarker endpoints
      will be assessed at least annually.  Biomarker data will be analyzed for pre-specified
      endpoints consistent with the drug's mechanism of action and known effects on the tested
      biomarkers.  At the end of the study period, the Sponsor will consider developing an
      extension study that would allow subjects enrolled in this study to rollover to a longer
      therapeutic trial with cognitive endpoints.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Gantenerumab: The amount of fibrillar amyloid deposition as measured by [11C]PiB-PET scans.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Solanezumab: The concentrations of CSF Aβ species, specifically different treatment effects on free CSF Aβ42 (increase/no change) and free CSF Aβ40 (decrease) with comparable treatment-associated increases in CSF total Aβ42 and total Aβ40.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Solanezumab Only:  Change in amyloid deposition as measured by [11C]PiB-PET mean composite SUVR (Standardized uptake value ratio)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gantenerumab Only: Change in Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) amyloid-beta peptide concentrations.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of CSF biomarkers tau and ptau181 values compared between subjects on active drug (gantenerumab or solanezumab) and mutation carriers in the pooled placebo group</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of brain atrophy in treatment groups vs. pooled placebo group as measured by cortical thickness of regions of interest (volumetric MRI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in 2-[18F] fluoro-2-deoxy-D-glucose (FDG) PET metabolism in specific regions of interest (e.g., precuneus) in treated group as compared to pooled placebo group measured</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of adverse events during the treatment period</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Nature and severity of adverse events during the treatment period</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in vital signs/physical findings</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in neurological findings</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in laboratory test results</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in ECG findings</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Exploratory Clinical Measures (annual rate of change)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Clinical Dementia Rating (CDR), including CDR sum of boxes (CDR-SB) and clinician's diagnostic assessment
Mini Mental Status Exam (MMSE)
Geriatric Depression Scale (GDS)
Neuropsychiatric Inventory Questionnaire (NPI-Q)
Functional Assessment Questionnaire (FAQ)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Exploratory Cognitive Measures (annual rate of change)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>International Shopping List Test (12-Item Word List Learning): 3 learning trials, Immediate Recall, 30-min Delayed Recall (CogState)
Groton Maze Learning Test: Timed Chase Task, 5 learning Trials, Immediate Recall, 30-min Delayed Recall (CogState)
Identification Test  (CogState)
One Card Learning Test (CogState)
Memory Complaint Questionnaire (MAC-Q)
Trails A &amp; B
Wechsler Memory Scale - Revised (WMS-R) Digit Span
Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale - Revised (WAIS-R) Digit-Symbol Substitution Test
Raven's Progressive Matrices (Set A)
Category Fluency to Animals &amp; Vegetables
Wechsler Memory Scale Logical Memory I Paragraph Memory (Immediate &amp; Delayed Recall)
Rentz Face-Name Association Memory Test (CogState)
Stark Pattern Separation Task (CogState)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">210</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimers Disease</condition>
  <condition>Dementia</condition>
  <condition>Alzheimers Disease, Familial</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gantenerumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Solanezumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Matching placebo (Gantenerumab)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Matching Placebo (Solanezumab)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gantenerumab</intervention_name>
    <description>225 mg subcutaneously every 4 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gantenerumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>RO4909832</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Solanezumab</intervention_name>
    <description>400 mg intravenous infusion every 4 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Solanezumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LY2062430</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Matching Placebo (Gantenerumab)</intervention_name>
    <description>subcutaneous injection of placebo every 4 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Matching placebo (Gantenerumab)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Matching Placebo (Solanezumab)</intervention_name>
    <description>intravenous infusion of placebo every 4 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Matching Placebo (Solanezumab)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Between 18-80 years of age

          -  Individuals who know they have an Alzheimer's disease-causing mutation or are unaware
             of their genetic status and have a 50% chance of having an autosomal dominant
             Alzheimer's disease (ADAD) mutation (e.g. parent or sibling with a known AD-causing
             mutation)

          -  Are within -15 to + 10 years of their parental age of symptom onset

          -  Cognitively normal or with mild cognitive impairment or mild dementia, Clinical
             Dementia Rating (CDR) of 0-1 (inclusive)

          -  Able to undergo Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI), Lumbar Puncture (LP), Positron
             Emission Tomography (PET), and complete all study related testing and evaluations.

          -  For women of childbearing potential, subject must agree to use effective
             contraceptive measures (hormonal contraception, intra-uterine device, sexual
             abstinence) if partner is not sterilized. Men must agree to use effective
             contraceptive measures.

          -  Adequate visual and auditory abilities to perform all aspects of the cognitive and
             functional assessments.

          -  Has a Study Partner who in the investigator's judgment is able to provide accurate
             information as to the subject's cognitive and functional abilities, who agrees to
             provide information at the study visits which require informant input for scale
             completion, and who signs the necessary consent form if applicable.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History or presence of brain MRI scans indicative of any other significant
             abnormality

          -  Presence of pacemakers, aneurysm clips, artificial heart valves, ear implants, or
             foreign metal objects in the eyes, skin or body which would preclude MRI scan.

          -  History or presence of clinically significant cardiovascular disease, hepatic/renal
             disorders, infectious disease or immune disorder, or metabolic/endocrine disorders

          -  Anticoagulants except low dose (≤ 325 mg) aspirin.

          -  Have been exposed to a monoclonal antibody targeting beta amyloid peptide within the
             past six months.

          -  History of cancer within the last 5 years, except basal cell carcinoma, non-squamous
             skin carcinoma, prostate cancer or carcinoma in situ with no significant progression
             over the past 2 years.

          -  Positive urine or serum pregnancy test or plans or desires to become pregnant during
             the course of the trial.

          -  Subjects unable to complete all study related testing, including implanted metal that
             cannot be removed for MRI scanning, required anticoagulation and pregnancy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Randall J Bateman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ellen Ziegemeier, MA</last_name>
    <phone>844-DIANEXR (342-6397)</phone>
    <email>dianexr@neuro.wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alabama in Birmingham</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Erik Roberson</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California San Diego Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Jolla</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92037</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Doug Galasko</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA Alzheimer's Disease Treatment Program</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Ringman</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSF Memory &amp; Aging Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94158</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Adam Boxer</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06510</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christopher Van Dyck</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30329</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James Lah</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Brandy Matthews</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University in St. Louis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Barbara Snider</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lawrence Honig</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John McDade</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Butler Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02096</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ghulam Surti</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Neuroscience Research Australia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Randwick</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2031</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>William Brooks</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mental Health Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3010</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Colin Masters</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The McCuster Foundation of Alzheimer's Disease Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nedlands</city>
        <state>Western Australia</state>
        <zip>6009</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Roger Clarnette</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UBC Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V6T 2B5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mario Hsiung</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M4N 3M5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robin Masellis</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>McGill Center for Studies in Aging</name>
      <address>
        <city>Verdun</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H4H 1R3</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Serge Gauthier</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU de Toulouse - Hôpital Purpan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulouse</city>
        <state>Haute Garonne</state>
        <zip>31059</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jérémie Pariente</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Roger Salengro - CHU Lille</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lille</city>
        <state>Nord</state>
        <zip>59037</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Florence Pasquier</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Groupe Hospitalier Pitie-Salpetriere</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris cedex 13</city>
        <state>Paris</state>
        <zip>69677</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bruno Dubois</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Neurologique Pierre Wertheimer</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bron cedex</city>
        <state>Rhone</state>
        <zip>69677</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maité Formaglio</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU de Rouen - Hôpital Charles Nicolle</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rouen</city>
        <state>Seine Maritime</state>
        <zip>76031</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Didier Hannequin</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IRCCS Centro San Giovanni di Dio Fatebenefratelli</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brescia</city>
        <zip>25125</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Giovanni Frisoni</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria Careggi</name>
      <address>
        <city>Firenze</city>
        <zip>50134</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sandro Sorbi</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Puerto Rico, School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Juan</city>
        <zip>00936</zip>
        <country>Puerto Rico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ivonne Jimenez-Velazquez</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Clínic I Provincial de Barcelona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>8036</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Raquel Sanchez Valle</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The National Hospital for Neurology and Neurosurgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Greater London</state>
        <zip>WC1B 3BG</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Catherine Mummery</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.dianexr.org/</url>
    <description>Expanded registry</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bateman RJ, Xiong C, Benzinger TL, Fagan AM, Goate A, Fox NC, Marcus DS, Cairns NJ, Xie X, Blazey TM, Holtzman DM, Santacruz A, Buckles V, Oliver A, Moulder K, Aisen PS, Ghetti B, Klunk WE, McDade E, Martins RN, Masters CL, Mayeux R, Ringman JM, Rossor MN, Schofield PR, Sperling RA, Salloway S, Morris JC; Dominantly Inherited Alzheimer Network. Clinical and biomarker changes in dominantly inherited Alzheimer's disease. N Engl J Med. 2012 Aug 30;367(9):795-804. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1202753. Epub 2012 Jul 11. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2012 Aug 23;367(8):780.</citation>
    <PMID>22784036</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farlow M, Arnold SE, van Dyck CH, Aisen PS, Snider BJ, Porsteinsson AP, Friedrich S, Dean RA, Gonzales C, Sethuraman G, DeMattos RB, Mohs R, Paul SM, Siemers ER. Safety and biomarker effects of solanezumab in patients with Alzheimer's disease. Alzheimers Dement. 2012 Jul;8(4):261-71. doi: 10.1016/j.jalz.2011.09.224. Epub 2012 Jun 5.</citation>
    <PMID>22672770</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 19, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 26, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Alzheimer's</keyword>
  <keyword>Alzheimer's Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Dementia</keyword>
  <keyword>Mutation</keyword>
  <keyword>Genetic Mutation</keyword>
  <keyword>Dominantly Inherited Alzheimer's Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Dominantly Inherited Alzheimer's Network</keyword>
  <keyword>Autosomal Dominant Alzheimer's Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Early Onset Alzheimer's Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>DIAN</keyword>
  <keyword>DIAN-TU</keyword>
  <keyword>DIAN TU</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
