<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1612">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02072200</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LOD13-KR-401</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02072200</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy of Lodotra®(Prednisone) in Reduction of Morning Stiffness Duration(K-IMPROvE)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A New Modified-Release Tablet Formulation of Prednisone in Patients With Rheumatoid Arthritis- Multicenter, Phase IV, Interventional Study to Assess Reduction of Morning Stiffness</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mundipharma Korea Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mundipharma Korea Ltd</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Korea: Ministry of Food and Drug Safety</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is multicenter, Ph IV, single arm, interventional study to assess relative
      reduction of morning stiffness of Lodotra® in Rheumatoid Arthritis patients.Study medication
      will start after study visit at baseline (week 0, visit 1) and follow-up visit will be after
      2, 6 and 12 weeks after treatment (visit 2,3,4).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Test Treatment, Dose, and Mode of Administration:

      Starting dose is 10mg, and depending on the clinical symptoms and the patient's response,
      the initial dose can quickly be reduced to a lower maintenance dose. When changing over from
      the standard regimen (glucocorticoid administration in the morning) to Lodotra® administered
      at bedtime (at about 10 pm), the same dose (in mg prednisone equivalent) should be
      maintained, if the subject has taken stable dose within 30 days. Lodotra® dose cannot exceed
      more than 10mg.

      Lodotra® should be taken at bedtime (at about 10 pm), with or after the evening meal and be
      swallowed whole with sufficient liquid. If more than 2 - 3 hours have passed since the
      evening meal, it is recommended to take Lodotra® with a light meal or snack.

      Modified-release tablets are not to be broken, divided or chewed.

      Treatment procedure:At Visit 1(week 0), subjects who qualify for entry into the study will
      medicated to Lodotra® starting dose of 10 mg daily. (Written informed consent has to be
      obtained, and subjects will undergo complete evaluation for study eligibility) No dose
      increase will be allowed for more than 10mg
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction rate of morning stiffness time duration by patient diary</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Data for the duration of morning stiffness will be obtained from patient diaries. Duration of morning stiffness will be from wake-up time to maximal reduction time of morning stiffness in both hands.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of  severity of morning stiffness via VAS scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Disability Index of the Health Assessment Questionnaire (K-HAQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">137</enrollment>
  <condition>Rheumatoid Arthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Modified release prednisone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single arm / Lodotra</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lodotra®</intervention_name>
    <description>Single arm will be received below  oral 10mg tablet daily and maximum 10mg/d depending on the clinical symptoms and the patient's response</description>
    <arm_group_label>Modified release prednisone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Modified Release Prednisone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who are diagnosed more than 3 months

          -  Morning stiffness on previous treatment with or without oral steroids (below or equal
             to 10mg per day, methylprednisolone doses were converted into prednisone doses as
             follows: prednisone dosed=methylprednisolone dose*1.25), average daily duration of 45
             min or more.

          -  Average daily maximum pain intensity score (100 mm VAS) of 30mm or more.

          -  DAS-ESR ≥3.2

          -  On DMARD treatment including MTX for ≥3months and stable treatment dose within the
             past 30 days. There are no limitations on number of DMARDs treatment.(Except patients
             who have experience of adverse drug reaction of MTX or difficulty to administer MTX
             due to disease specific condition.)

          -  Able to perform study procedures and given written informed consent.

          -  Naïve patients with Prednisone MR(Lodotra® ) or patients not treat with Prednisone
             MR(Lodotra®) within 4 weeks(28days)

          -  Subject who keeps to administer study drug at 22±30 daily

          -  Subject who provide signed and dated written voluntary informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who suffers from another disease, which requires glucocorticoid treatment
             during the study period.

          -  Synovectomy within 4 months prior to study start.

          -  Patients who underwent joint injections on only fingers and wrists(both sides) within
             4 weeks prior to first visit. Clinically significant disease which, in the
             investigator's opinion, would exclude the subject from the study.

          -  Significant renal impairment (serum creatinine&gt;2.0mg/dl)

          -  Significant hepatic impairment (&gt;3 times the upper limit of normal range in each
             site)

          -  All contra-indications for glucocorticoids.(established new osteoporotic fractures
             history of corticoid psychosis, herpes simplex and herpes zoster, varicella
             infection)

          -  Uncontrolled DM(HbA1c&gt;8.0)

          -  Women of child-bearing potential, defined as all women physiologically capable of
             becoming pregnant. UNLESS they are:

               -  women whose career, lifestyle, or sexual orientation precludes intercourse with
                  a male partner

               -  women whose partners have been sterilized by vasectomy or other means

               -  two birth control methods. The two methods can be a double barrier method or a
                  barrier method plus a hormonal method. Adequate barrier methods of contraception
                  include: diaphragm, condom (by the partner), intrauterine device (copper or
                  hormonal), sponge or spermicide. Hormonal contraceptives include any marketed
                  contraceptive agent that includes an estrogen and/or a progestational agent.

          -  Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women, where pregnancy is defined as the state of a
             female after conception and until the termination of gestation, confirmed by a
             positive urine pregnancy test

          -  Participation in another clinical study within the past 30 days

          -  Known hypersensitivity to prednisone

          -  Infection patients without effective antimicrobial and systemic mycosis infection
             patients(infection might be aggravated due to suppression of immunologic function.)

          -  Patients with immunization with live vaccines within 2 weeks of enrollment or planned
             during the study

          -  Since this drug contains glucose, patients with rare hereditary problems of galactose
             intolerance, Lapp lactase deficiency or glucose-galactose malabsorption should not
             take this drug.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Seungjae Hong, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kyunghee University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bongjin Lee, CRA</last_name>
    <phone>82-2-527-9228</phone>
    <email>bongjinlee@mundipharma.co.kr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Saerom Kim, CRA</last_name>
    <phone>82-2-527-9271</phone>
    <email>saerom.kim@mundipharma.co.kr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hallym University Sacred Heart Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pyeongchon</city>
        <state>Kyungkido</state>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Youngil Seo, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Youngil Seo, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 24, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 14, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>RA, MS, Safety, Efficacy, MR prednisone</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Prednisone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
