<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="107506">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01798563</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>10-1311</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01798563</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Functional Connectivity Parkinson Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Functional Connectivity of the Motor Network in Two Major Subtypes of Parkinson Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study the investigators are looking at two subtypes of Parkinson Disease (PD);
      &quot;tremor-dominant&quot; (TD) and postural imbalance and gait disorder (PIGD).  This study will use
      magnet resonance imaging (MRI) to see how the brain reacts while resting and doing a
      finger-tapping task while on and off PD medication.  This study will look at the differences
      between the two sub-types of PD and healthy volunteers.

      The investigators will test the hypothesis that connectivity at rest within the motor cortex
      and between the motor cortex and motor-associated regions such as the supplementary motor
      area and the pre motor cortex will not be as strong in PIGD compared to TD (increased
      activity and functional connectivity in TD group)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case Control, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>A measure of the correlation coefficients between nodes of the motor network at rest and during a tapping motor task between the &quot;OFF&quot; and &quot;ON&quot; dopaminergic medication states in the two motor subtype PD patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>at time of MRI scan. Patients undergo the first scanning session 12 or more hours after their last dose of dopaminergic medication, and the second scanning session 1 to 3 hours after taking their usual dose(s) dopaminergic medication(s).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Primary outcome measures for the second aim include differences in these same connectivity assessments between the &quot;OFF&quot; and &quot;ON&quot; dopaminergic medication states in the two motor subtype PD patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>A second level contrast between Parkinson Disease (PD) and Healthy Controls (HC) of the statistical parametric maps of correlation coefficients at rest and during a tapping motor task</measure>
    <time_frame>at time of MRI scan Patients undergo the first scanning session 12 or more hours after their last dose of dopaminergic medication, and the second scanning session 1 to 3 hours after taking their usual dose(s) dopaminergic medication(s).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Primary outcome measures for the first aim include differences in connectivity as measured by correlation coefficients between nodes of the motor network at rest and during a tapping motor task in PD patients of two motor subtypes and matched healthy controls.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Task-related whole-brain activations</measure>
    <time_frame>at time of MRI scan. Patients undergo the first scanning session 12 or more hours after their last dose of dopaminergic medication, and the second scanning session 1 to 3 hours after taking their usual dose(s) dopaminergic medication(s).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Secondary outcome measures include task-related whole-brain activations as assessed by changes in blood oxygen-dependent (BOLD) contrast during functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) scanning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Connectivity between other motor and non-motor brain regions during the tasks</measure>
    <time_frame>at time of MRI scan. Patients undergo the first scanning session 12 or more hours after their last dose of dopaminergic medication, and the second scanning session 1 to 3 hours after taking their usual dose(s) dopaminergic medication(s).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Secondary outcome measures include measuring the connectivity between other motor and non-motor brain regions during the tasks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlations of brain activity and functional connectivity to structural connectivity measures and behavioral and clinical assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>at time of MRI scan. Patients undergo the first scanning session 12 or more hours after their last dose of dopaminergic medication, and the second scanning session 1 to 3 hours after taking their usual dose(s) dopaminergic medication(s).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Secondary outcome measures include a measure of the correlations of brain activity and functional connectivity to structural connectivity measures as well as behavioral and clinical assessments.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tremor Dominant PD</arm_group_label>
    <description>Volunteers with predominantly tremor-related motor symptoms of PD</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Postural Instability &amp; Gait Difficulty PD</arm_group_label>
    <description>Volunteers with primarily walking &amp; balance-related motor symptoms of PD.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>Healthy volunteers consisting of people of same age as PD volunteers, w/o a diagnosis of PD.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with PD according to UK Brain Bank Criteria will be recruited from the UCD
        Neurology clinic. Controls will be recruited from spouses and from the community
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  English as their primary language

          -  Patients with Parkinson disease and healthy controls will be enrolled

          -  Parkinson patients must be on a dopaminergic medication (levodopa or dopamine
             agonist) and on a stable dose over the prior month

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  If unable to provide informed consent

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Excess of 300lbs

          -  Claustrophobia

          -  Metal in body

          -  Untreated neurological or psychiatric condition, who are delusional or have
             hallucinations, with cognitive impairment (MOCA&lt;26), with a history of head injury
             sufficient to cause a concussion, or with significant systemic medical diseases (e.g.
             heart failure, liver failure, kidney failure, poorly controlled diabetes, etc.)

          -  Healthy control subjects will be excluded if taking any type of dopaminergic or
             anti-dopaminergic medication

          -  Subjects who are unable to demonstrate understanding of the study procedures and
             risks will be excluded
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brian Berman, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Denver</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Erika Shelton</last_name>
    <phone>303-724-5865</phone>
    <email>erika.shelton@ucdenver.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Denver</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 21, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 11, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Parkinson</keyword>
  <keyword>Parkinson Disease</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
