<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="14915">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01825408</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-2377</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01825408</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Duration of Antibiotic Therapy as Part of Maximal Medical Therapy for Chronic Rhinosinusitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Cohort Trial Evaluating Duration of Antibiotic Therapy as Part of Maximal Medical Therapy for Chronic Rhinosinusitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the best duration(3 versus 6 weeks) of antibiotics
      as part of maximal medical therapy for treating chronic sinusitis and thus preventing
      patients from having to have sinus surgery. The hypothesis is that in the context of maximal
      medical therapy 3 weeks of antibiotics is not worse than 6 weeks of antibiotics at
      successfully treating chronic sinusitis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OVERVIEW This is a prospective randomized cohort study assessing duration of antibiotics (3
      vs 6 weeks) as part of maximal medical therapy for chronic rhinosinusitis. Up to 100
      subjects will be prospectively enrolled from patients visiting the Department of
      Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery clinics at UNC Hospitals.

      INITIAL CLINIC VISIT At the time of a clinical visit, the attending otolaryngologists will
      identify their patients with chronic rhinosinusitis (CRS) who are appropriate for maximal
      medical treatment, including antibiotics. They will introduce the study to these patients
      and invite them to learn more about it.

      If the patient is interested in learning more about the study, the study coordinators will
      be contacted to provide additional information and, if the patient would like to participate
      in the study, provide informed consent.

      If the patient is a premenopausal woman, she will be asked if she is pregnant or
      breastfeeding.

      If she is either of these, she will be excluded from the study. All remaining women will
      receive a urine pregnancy test. If this urine pregnancy test is positive, the patient will
      be excluded from the study. Thus, for premenopausal female patients, a negative urine
      pregnancy test is necessary for inclusion in the study. These women will be informed that
      they should use an effective method of birth control during the study:

        -  Combined oral contraceptives

        -  Patch contraceptives

        -  Vaginal ring contraceptives

        -  Injectable contraceptives

        -  Implantable contraceptives

        -  Intrauterine devices or intrauterine systems

        -  Tubal ligation

        -  Barrier methods of contraception (male condom, female condom, cervical cap with
           spermicide, or diaphragm with spermicide)

        -  Vasectomy of your partner in a monogamous relationship

      Women enrolled in this study will be informed that if they have a failure of birth control
      method during the course of the study or become pregnant during the study, they will be
      withdrawn from the study and further treatment will be decided according to the clinical
      withdrawn from the study and further treatment will be decided according to the clinical
      expertise of the treating otolaryngologist.

        -  The study coordinators will assign the patients a unique Subject ID that will be used
           on all patient forms with the exception of the informed consent documents and HIPAA
           authorization forms.

        -  The patient will fill out a demographics and past medical history form.

        -  The patient will fill out two quality of life surveys: the Rhinosinusitis Disability
           Index (RSDI) and the Chronic Sinusitis Survey (CSS).

        -  Video recorded nasal endoscopy will be performed by the attending physician. The video
           file will be stored initially on a portable storage drive that will contain no patient
           identifiers. The file will be identified only with the SubjectID. The patient's face
           will not be recorded in the video. The file on the portable storage drive will be
           transferred to a password protected computer in the locked office of the principal
           investigator.

        -  Using a random-number generator, the patient will be randomized to receive either 3 or
           6 weeks of antibiotics.

        -  The subject will initially be given a prescription for empiric antibiotics.The choice
           of empiric antibiotics will differ based on the patient's nasal polyposis status:

        -  If the subject has CRS with nasal polyposis (CRSwNP), s/he will be given Doxycycline
           100mg BID or if allergic to doxycycline, then Augmentin 875mg BID for either 3 or 6
           weeks duration. These patients will also receive a course of Prednisone (30mg x 3d,
           20mg x 3d, 10mg x3d, 10mg every other day for 6 days (3 doses)) which is standard of
           care treatment for CRSwNP.

        -  If the subject has CRS without Nasal Polyposis (CRSwNP), s/he will be given
           Azithromycin 250mg daily, or if allergic to azithromycin, then Augmentin 875mg BID for
           either 3 or 6 weeks duration.

        -  If purulent nasal discharge is present that is appropriate for culture, the
           otolaryngologists will send this for culture and sensitivity analysis, which they would
           normally do as part of their routine clinical care. The patients will be informed that
           if their culture and sensitivity analysis indicates that they have an infection that
           can be treated with a less broad-spectrum antibiotic, then they will be prescribed
           culture-directed antibiotics. Otherwise, the patient can continue empiric antibiotics
           as previously specified.

        -  All study participants will also be prescribed standard of care intranasal steroids,
           and encouraged to perform BID saline sinus irrigation and use yogurt/over the counter
           probiotics to reduce GI side effects of antibiotics.

      AFTER THE INITIAL CLINIC VISIT

      The study personnel will access the patient's medical record via WebCIS to:

        -  Record the patient's allergy status, CBC with differential and IgE at the time of the
           initial visit. CBC and IgE labs are part of the routine clinical care for CRS. If these
           are not obtained during the initial clinic visit, they will be obtained at a later
           clinic visit (visit 2 or future pre-operative visit)

        -  View the patient's pre-treatment sinus CT scan and calculate a blinded Lund-Mackay
           score.

      4-5 WEEKS AFTER BEGINNING TREATMENT

      For subjects randomized to the 3 week antibiotic group, these subjects will been seen in
      clinic.

      During this visit (study visit #2), subjects will complete the RSDI and CSS. Subjects will
      be asked about antibiotic compliance and side effects. Recommendation for sinus surgery will
      be evaluated with video-recorded nasal endoscopy and a sinus CT.

      For subjects randomized to the 6 week antibiotic group, these subjects will be contacted by
      phone by the study coordinator to assess side effects and medication compliance.

      7-8 WEEKS AFTER BEGINNING TREATMENT

      For subjects randomized to the 6 week antibiotic group, these subjects will been seen in
      clinic.

      During this visit (study visit #2), subjects will complete the RSDI and CSS. Subjects will
      be asked about antibiotic compliance and side effects. Recommendation for sinus surgery will
      be evaluated with video-recorded nasal endoscopy and a sinus CT.

      At any of these study visits or a potential pre-operative visit, subjects will have blood
      drawn to record IgE and CBC with differential. These labs are routinely ordered in CRS both
      to characterize the disease and also for pre-operative planning.

      All video recorded nasal endoscopies will be blindly scored by Drs. Senior, Ebert, and
      Zanation with the Lund-Kennedy scoring system. All sinus CTs will be scored with the
      Lund-Mackay scoring system.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients recommended for sinus surgery after 3 weeks of antibiotic therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>4-5 weeks after starting antibiotics</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Recommendation for sinus surgery after completion of maximal medical therapy is determined by the subject's treating physician and is based on two citeria: (1) persistence of symptoms and (2) objective evidence of disease on post-treatment sinus CT scan or nasal endoscopy. Symptomatic improvement of sinusitis symptoms will be assessed by: patient self report, change in Chronic Sinusitis Survery (CSS) score and change in RhinoSinusitis Disibility Index (RSDI) score relative to initial pre-antibiotic CSS and RSDI survey scores.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients recommended for sinus surgery after 6 weeks of antibiotic therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>7-8 weeks after initiating antibiotics</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Recommendation for sinus surgery after completion of maximal medical therapy is determined by the subject's treating physician and is based on two citeria: (1) persistence of symptoms and (2) objective evidence of disease on post-treatment sinus CT scan or nasal endoscopy. Symptomatic improvement of sinusitis symptoms will be assessed by: patient self report, change in Chronic Sinusitis Survery (CSS) score and change in RhinoSinusitis Disibility Index (RSDI) score relative to initial pre-antibiotic CSS and RSDI survey scores.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Quality of Life after 3 weeks of antibiotics</measure>
    <time_frame>4-5 weeks after starting antibiotics</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Quality of life will be measured at the initial clinic visit and again 4-5 weeks after starting antibiotics. The quality of life assessments used in this study are the Chronic Sinusitis Survey and the RhinoSinusitis Disability Index.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Quality of Life after 6 weeks of antibiotics</measure>
    <time_frame>7-8 weeks after starting antibiotics</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Quality of life will be measured at the initial clinic visit and again 7-8 weeks after starting antibiotics. The quality of life assessments used in this study are the Chronic Sinusitis Survey and the RhinoSinusitis Disability Index.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Nasal endoscopy scores after 3 weeks of antibiotics</measure>
    <time_frame>4-5 weeks after starting antibiotics</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Nasal endoscopy is a routine standard of care procedure to assess the sinuses. It will be performed at the initial clinic visit and again at the follow up visit. Nasal endoscopies will be scored with the Lund-Kennedy scoring system.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Nasal Endoscopy Score following 6 weeks of antibiotics</measure>
    <time_frame>7-8 weeks after starting antibiotics</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Nasal endoscopy is a routine standard of care procedure to assess the sinuses. It will be performed at the initial clinic visit and again at the follow up visit. Nasal endoscopies will be scored with the Lund-Kennedy scoring system.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in CT Score after 3 weeks of antibiotics</measure>
    <time_frame>4-5 weeks after starting antibiotics</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A sinus CT within 3 months of study initiation will be graded and compared with a standard of care post-treatment CT scan using the Lund-Mackay CT scoring system.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in CT Score after 6 weeks of antibiotics</measure>
    <time_frame>7-8 weeks after starting antibiotics</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A sinus CT within 3 months of study initiation will be graded and compared with a standard of care post-treatment CT scan using the Lund-Mackay CT scoring system.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with antibiotic side effects after a 3 week course of antibiotics</measure>
    <time_frame>4-5 weeks after starting antibiotics</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The most frequent side effect of antibiotics is GI upset. At the follow up visit, subjects will be asked about their medication compliance and what, if any, side effects they experienced.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with antibiotic side effects after a 6 week course of antibiotics</measure>
    <time_frame>4-5 weeks and 7-8 weeks after initiating antibiotics</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The most frequent side effect of antibiotics is GI upset. 4-5 weeks after starting antibiotics, subjects in the 6-week of antibiotic group will be contacted by the study coordinators and medication compliance and side effects will be assessed. Any adverse outcomes will be reported to the primary investigator. At the follow up visit, subjects will be asked about their medication compliance and what, if any, side effects they experienced.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Sinusitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Doxycycline, 3 weeks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects with chronic rhinosinusitis with nasal polyps (CRSwNP) will receive Doxycycline 100mg BID or if allergic to doxycycline, then Augmentin 875mg BID for 3 weeks duration. These patients will also receive a course of Prednisone (30mg x 3d, 20mg x 3d, 10mg x3d, 10mg every other day for 6 days (3 doses)) which is standard of care treatment for patients with chronic sinusitis with nasal polyps.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Doxycycline, 6 weeks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects with Chronic Rhinosinusitis with Nasal Polyps (CRSwNP)will receive Doxycycline 100mg BID or if allergic to doxycycline, then Augmentin 875mg BID for 6 weeks duration. These patients will also receive a course of Prednisone (30mg x 3d, 20mg x 3d, 10mg x3d, 10mg every other day for 6 days (3 doses)) which is standard of care treatment for patients with chronic sinusitis with nasal polyps.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Azithromycin, 3 weeks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects with Chronic Rhinosinusitis without Nasal Polyps will receive Azithromycin 250mg daily, or if allergic to azithromycin, then Augmentin 875mg BID for 3 weeks duration.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Azithromycin, 6 weeks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects with chronic Rhinosinusitis without Nasal Polyps will receive Azithromycin 250mg daily, or if allergic to azithromycin, then Augmentin 875mg BID for 6 weeks duration.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Doxycycline</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects with CRSwNP who are not allergic to doxycycline will receive Doxycycline 100mg BID for either 3 or 6 weeks duration.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Doxycycline, 3 weeks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Doxycycline, 6 weeks</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Azithromycin</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects with CRS without Nasal Polyposis (CRSwNP)who are not allergic to azithromycin will be given Azithromycin 250mg daily for either 3 or 6 weeks duration.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Azithromycin, 3 weeks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Azithromycin, 6 weeks</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Augmentin</intervention_name>
    <description>If a subject in any of the study arms is allergic to the medication he/she is supposed to receive, he/she will be given Augmentin 875mg BID for either 3 or 6 weeks duration</description>
    <arm_group_label>Doxycycline, 3 weeks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Doxycycline, 6 weeks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Azithromycin, 3 weeks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Azithromycin, 6 weeks</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of chronic rhinosinusitis

          -  18 years of age or older

          -  English speaking

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding women

          -  vasculitis

          -  cystic fibrosis

          -  primary ciliary dyskinesia

          -  allergic fungal sinusitis

          -  gross immunodeficiency

          -  current use of chemotherapy

          -  insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus

          -  recent trial of maximal medical therapy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Adam Zanation, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Emily Cohn, BSPH</last_name>
    <phone>9193570977</phone>
    <email>emily_cohn@med.unc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Robert Taylor</last_name>
    <phone>7169035050</phone>
    <email>rjtaylor@email.unc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery clinics at UNC Hospitals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27514</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Adam Zanation, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Charles Ebert, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Brent Senior, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 2, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Adam Zanation, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Otolaryngology/Head and Neck Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Sinusitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anti-Bacterial Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Doxycycline</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Doxycycline hyclate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Azithromycin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Amoxicillin-Potassium Clavulanate Combination</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibiotics, Antitubercular</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
