<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="120874">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01715571</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NA_00052709</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01715571</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of Penile Vibratory Stimulation Using the Viberect in Men With Mild-Moderate and No Erectile Dysfunction</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical and Physiological Assessment of Noninvasive Penile Afferent Vibratory Stimulation of Both Surfaces of the Penis Using the Viberect® Device in Men With Mild to Moderate and No Erectile Dysfunction.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of this study is to assess the safety, acceptability, and satisfaction
      of penile vibratory stimulation. The secondary purpose is to demonstrate subjective
      physiological response (erection, rigidity, orgasm) after four weeks of frequent device use
      and the satisfaction of penile erection and sexual intercourse with partner.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Erectile dysfunction (ED) is the inability to develop and maintain an erection for
      satisfactory sexual intercourse or activity. ED is a highly prevalent medical condition
      often associated with multiple causes. It is estimated that more than 50 million American
      men suffer from mild/moderate to severe erectile dysfunction. Roughly 50% of men in their
      50's, 60% of men in their 60's, and 70% of men in their 70's suffer from ED. The economic
      impact of ED is in the billions of dollars. More than 5 billion dollars a year are spent on
      the three pro-erectile medications currently in the market.

      Penile vibratory stimulation mimics rapid and repetitive manual/hand stimulation of the
      penis, which is a natural aspect of human sexual behavior. For more than a century, tens of
      millions of women use vibratory devices on daily/regular basis for purpose of sexual
      pleasure/orgasm. Vibratory stimulation of genitalia is considered safe by the medical
      community with important benefits, such as treatment of orgasmic dysfunction, stress urinary
      incontinence, ejaculation, and erection. No significant physical or emotional side-effects
      have been reported in the medical literature, or the popular media. A recent epidemiological
      study of the use of vibrators by American women and men has shown no complaints, and
      generally high satisfaction and improvement in sexual response.

      Penile erection is controlled by spinal autonomic centers, the activity of which is
      dependent on input from supraspinal centers and genitalia. From a neurophysiological
      viewpoint, scientists believe that penile erection is a culmination of multiple successful
      nerve reflexes that initiate a vascular event. Simultaneous vibratory stimulation of both
      surfaces of the penis at high frequency (70-110 Hz) for 7-10 minutes can lead to
      reflexogenic gradual filling of the penis (minutes) with arterial blood by activating the
      pudendo-cavernosal reflex. Additional physiological effects include progressive rhythmic
      contraction of the perineal muscles via activation of bulbocavernosus reflex, which helps in
      strengthening rigidity of erection. This will prepare the user for successful sexual
      intercourse. Subsequent orgasm and ejaculation can be very strong and amplified due to
      stronger contraction of the bulbospongiosus muscle and activation of higher ejaculatory
      centers.

      The purpose of this multicenter study is to assess daily or on-demand ease of use, safety,
      satisfaction, and efficacy of the home use of the Viberect device  (FDA cleared)  by men
      with mild to moderate and no erectile dysfunction.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess daily or on-demand ease of use, and efficacy of the home use of the Viberect device by men with mild to moderate and no erectile dysfunction</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks after initiation of intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>After obtaining informed consent, the subjects will be instructed in the use of the Viberect device, and will be asked to perform vibratory stimulation of the penis in the privacy of their home, while focused on sexual/erotic thoughts for approximately 7-10 minutes (depending on erectile response) for 3 times a week, one day apart, throughout the four week period. Men can perform the stimulation once daily, as long as each session is more than 24 hours apart. Men will record device use and intercourse attempts after device use in a diary. They will fill out several validated questionnaires on week 4: Erection Hardness Scale (EHS), EDITS (Erectile Dysfunction Inventory of Treatment Satisfaction), TSS questionnaire</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess safety of using Viberect penile stiumulation for the treatment of mild-moderate ED</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks after initiation of intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>After obtaining informed consent, the subjects will be instructed in the use of the Viberect device, and will be asked to perform vibratory stimulation of the penis in the privacy of their home, while focused on sexual/erotic thoughts for approximately 7-10 minutes (depending on erectile response) for 3 times a week, one day apart, throughout the four week period. Men can perform the stimulation once daily, as long as each session is more than 24 hours apart. Men will record device use and intercourse attempts after device use in a diary. They will fill out several validated questionnaires on week 4: Erection Hardness Scale (EHS), EDITS (Erectile Dysfunction Inventory of Treatment Satisfaction), TSS questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Organic Erectile Dysfunction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>men with mild-mod. erectile dysfunction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Expected duration of subject participation: 4 weeks Initial visit: to perform history and physical,  to discuss the clinical study and obtain informed consent. Study subjects will fill out the International Index of erectile Function (IIEF) questionnaire, the Erection hardness Score (EHS), the Erectile Dysfunction Inventory of Treatment Satisfaction (EDITS) questionnaire and the Treatment Satisfaction Survey (TSS) to fill out after 4 weeks, and receive instructions on the use of the Viberect device, including the User manual.
Follow up visit four weeks later: To return the Viberect device and collect the completed forms.  The patient will have a penile examination to document any sores, lesions, or irritation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>men with no erectile dysfunction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Expected duration of subject participation: 4 weeks Initial visit: to perform history and physical,  to discuss the clinical study and obtain informed consent. Study subjects will fill out the International Index of erectile Function (IIEF) questionnaire, the Erection hardness Score (EHS), the Erectile Dysfunction Inventory of Treatment Satisfaction (EDITS) questionnaire and the Treatment Satisfaction Survey (TSS) to fill out after 4 weeks, and receive instructions on the use of the Viberect device, including the User manual.
Follow up visit four weeks later: To return the Viberect device and collect the completed forms.  The patient will have a penile examination to document any sores, lesions, or irritation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Viberect</intervention_name>
    <description>Men will be asked to perform vibratory stimulation of the penis in the privacy of their home, while focused on sexual/erotic thoughts for approximately 7-10 minutes (depending on erectile response) for 3 times a week, one day apart, throughout the four week period. Men can perform the stimulation once daily, as long as each session is more than 24 hours apart.
Men will record device use and intercourse attempts after device use in a diary.</description>
    <arm_group_label>men with mild-mod. erectile dysfunction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>men with no erectile dysfunction</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          -  mild-moderate erectile dysfunction-IIEF-EF score 13-25

          -  no erectile dysfunction-IIEF-EF score equal or greater than 25

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Men with neurological disease

          -  IIEF score less than 13

          -  Spinal cord injury

          -  History of priapism

          -  Pelvic neuropathy

          -  Post-prostatectomy

          -  Penile skin lesions or ulcers

          -  Inability to understand and demonstrate device use instructions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Arthur L Burnett, MD, MBA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kambiz Tajkarimi, MD</last_name>
    <phone>1-202-321-8162</phone>
    <email>Kambiz123@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jordan Dimitrakoff, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(410) 502-5384</phone>
    <email>jdimitr1@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jordan Dimitrakoff, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>410-502-5384</phone>
      <email>jdimitr1@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Brian Le, M.D.</last_name>
      <email>ble6@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Arthur L Burnett, MD, MBA</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Frederick Urology Specialists</name>
      <address>
        <city>Frederick</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21701</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <email>ble6@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kambiz Tajkarimi, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 20, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 21, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Arthur L. Burnett, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Patrick C. Walsh Professor of Urology, Cellular and Molecular Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Erectile Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
