<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="102668">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02103660</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDC-NCCDPHP-6512</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1K01TW009657-01</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U48-DP-001944</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>SIP 09-022</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02103660</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Trial on the Effects of Progestin-based Contraception in the Genital Tract of HIV-infected and Uninfected Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Clinical Trial on the Effects of Progestin-based Contraception in the Genital Tract of HIV-infected and Uninfected Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>John E. Fogarty International Center (FIC)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <authority>Malawi: National Health Sciences Research Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the acceptability of randomization to
      contraceptive options and estimate the effect of progestin contraception on HIV genital
      shedding and inflammatory/immune perturbations in women who may or may not be on
      antiretroviral therapy, as well as in HIV-uninfected women controls. It is hypothesized that
      progestin-containing contraception will lead to inflammatory changes that may affect the
      local immune activity, influencing HIV acquisition or transmissibility risk.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hormonal contraception is a central component in the prevention of unintended pregnancy;
      however there are concerns that certain methods may increase the risk of heterosexual HIV
      acquisition and transmission. Some studies, but not others, have suggested a link between
      hormonal contraceptive use and enhanced HIV-susceptibility, more rapid HIV disease
      progression, and increased transmissibility to partners. Hormonal contraception modifies the
      genital mucosa in several ways, and the interactions of the endocrine and immune system are
      complex but incompletely understood. In some cross-sectional studies, hormonal
      contraceptives appear to be associated with increased shedding of HIV DNA, but not RNA, in
      the genital tract, and the significance of these findings for HIV transmissibility are
      unclear. Very few studies have examined genital HIV shedding prospectively before and after
      initiation of contraception. The effects of hormonal contraception in the setting of
      antiretroviral therapy (ART) are also unknown.

      Hormonal contraception, particularly injectable DMPA, is widely used in many parts of the
      world, including settings with high HIV prevalence. It is important that the effects of
      hormonal contraception on HIV acquisition and HIV shedding and subsequent transmissibility
      be determined. The effect of progestin contraceptive implants, such as the levonorgestrel
      rod implant (LNG implant), on HIV shedding is unknown, and it will be of interest to
      evaluate it compared with the injectable progestin (DMPA), given their different kinetics of
      hormone release, differences in progestin type, and the high efficacy of both methods.

      We propose a pilot study among 100 HIV-infected women and 30 uninfected women in Lilongwe,
      Malawi randomized to either DMPA or LNG implant to: 1) assess the effect and compare the
      impact of type of progestin-containing contraception (injectable versus implant) on HIV
      viral shedding in the genital tract of HIV+ women, 2) assess the effect and compare the
      impact of type of progestin-containing contraception (injectable versus implant) on
      inflammatory/immune markers in the genital tract of both HIV+ and HIV- women, and 3) assess
      the interaction of progestin-based hormonal contraception and ART by examining: i.
      contraceptive efficacy (measured by systemic hormone levels and pregnancy rate during
      follow-up), and ii. ART efficacy (by drug concentrations in blood and genital tract and HIV
      viral load response in the plasma in women on ART).

      An overall study aim is to determine the feasibility and need for a larger study of
      determinants of HIV transmissibility and acquisition in this population.

      The study would take place at Bwaila Maternity Hospital, which was the site of the
      CDC-sponsored Breastfeeding, Antiretrovirals, and Nutrition (BAN) clinical trial, a partner
      project with this study. Women attending the clinics at Bwaila (a large proportion of whom
      participated in the BAN study) who desire to start hormonal contraception will be informed
      of the new study and counseled on the progestin-based contraceptives that are available
      within the study. BAN women will be specifically targeted for recruitment through radio
      messages. Eligible women who provide informed consent and agree to randomization to either
      DMPA or the LNG implant will be enrolled. HIV-infected women may be on ART or they may be
      pre-ART.

      To address the primary outcomes of HIV shedding and mucosal immune activation, we will
      quantify genital tract HIV RNA and inflammatory/immune markers at two time points before and
      four time points after randomization of the 100 HIV-infected and 30 HIV-uninfected women to
      DMPA or LNG-implant. The two time points prior to randomization will occur within the prior
      menstrual cycle, so that one visit occurs in the follicular phase and the other occurs in
      the luteal phase of the cycle.  Assessments after initiation of contraception will occur on
      days 3, 30, 90, and 6 months. To analyze the effects of progestin contraception on HIV
      shedding, as well as the effect of each contraceptive type, HIV-infected women on
      progestin-based contraception will be compared within each study arm (before and after
      initiation of contraception), as well as between the two contraceptive arms. Antiretroviral
      use will be evaluated for an independent effect on HIV shedding and also to determine if it
      modifies the effect of menstrual cycle or progestin contraception on HIV shedding. To
      analyze the effects of progestin contraception on genital inflammatory/immune markers, both
      HIV-infected and HIV-uninfected women on progestin-based contraception will be compared
      separately and combined, with HIV status treated as a potential effect modifier, within each
      study arm (before and after initiation of contraception), as well as between the two
      contraceptive arms. This study will provide information on acceptability of randomization to
      contraceptive options, overall study retention, and estimates of the effect of progestin
      contraception on HIV genital shedding and inflammatory/immune perturbations in women who may
      or may not be on antiretroviral therapy, as well as in HIV-uninfected women controls. This
      information will be instrumental in determining the need for and feasibility of a larger
      study to address these outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HIV viral load in the genital tract of HIV-infected women before and after initiation of progestin-containing contraception</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Genital HIV viral load at each study visit will be modeled longitudinally as a continuous outcome using a generalized estimating equation (GEE) model. The model will include a covariate indicating whether the measurement was taken before or after receiving the contraceptive method, and the null hypothesis will be tested using a z-test on this covariate.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HIV viral load in the genital tract of HIV-infected women by contraceptive type</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Genital HIV viral load at each study visit will be modeled longitudinally as a continuous outcome using a generalized estimating equation (GEE) model. The model will include a covariate for contraception arm, and the null hypothesis will be tested using a z-test on this covariate.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of the type of progestin-containing contraception (injectable versus implant) on inflammatory/immune markers in the genital tract women.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>A series of paired t-tests or Wilcoxon signed-rank tests, with Bonferonni correction, will be used for the within-subject assessments of all the immune markers, before and after contraceptive initiation. The baseline value will be the mean of the follicular and luteal phase values, and it will be compared to the value for each study time point after contraceptive initiation. Comparisons will be performed between subjects in the LNG-implant and DMPA arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Contraceptive efficacy in HIV-infected women</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Contraceptive efficacy will be measured by the occurrence of any pregnancies and compared by antiretroviral status</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Interaction of progesting-based hormonal contraception and antiretroviral therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Plasma and female genital tract ARV drug concentrations will be expressed as geometric mean with corresponding 95% CI. Correlation between genital tract viral shedding, plasma and genital tract ARV concentrations and HC will be assessed with longitudinal models using GEE. Outcomes will be compared between the DMPA and the implant users evaluating the contraceptive method as an effect modifier for HIV shedding or ART concentrations within the longitudinal models.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">130</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <condition>Contraception</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Depo-Medroxyprogesterone Acetate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Half of women will be randomized to receive Depo-Medroxyprogesterone Acetate injections every 13 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Progestin Implant (Jadelle)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Half of women will be randomized to receive progestin implant.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Depo-Medroxyprogesterone Acetate</intervention_name>
    <description>150 mg Depo-Medroxyprogesterone Acetate administered every 13 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Depo-Medroxyprogesterone Acetate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Depo provera</other_name>
    <other_name>DMPA</other_name>
    <other_name>injectable contraception</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Progestin Contraceptive (Jadelle)</intervention_name>
    <description>2 implants containing 75 mg of levonorgestrel will be implanted and will last for up to 5 years</description>
    <arm_group_label>Progestin Implant (Jadelle)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Jadelle</other_name>
    <other_name>Contraceptive Implant</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Known HIV status, as documented by at least 2 positive rapid tests (Determine and
             Uni-Gold, respectively). If the 2 rapid tests are discordant, then a confirmatory
             test will be done via Western blot.

          -  Female, pre-menopausal, age 18 to 45 years

          -  At least 2 regular, monthly cycles (~21-35 days) in the 3 months preceding study
             enrollment.

          -  If on hormonal or intrauterine contraception in the past, they must have been off for
             at least 6 months. If they were previously using DMPA, their last -injection must
             have been ≥6 months ago.

          -  If recently pregnant, they must be at least 6 months postpartum

          -  Able and willing to provide informed consent

          -  Be otherwise a good candidate for study participation based on assessment  by
             investigator or designee

          -  Interested in initiating a family planning method, specifically depot
             medroxyprogesterone acetate (DMPA) or the LNG implant (Jadelle)

          -  Willing to be randomized to receive either DMPA or LNG implant (Jadelle)

          -  Willing to wait 4-6 weeks after enrollment to receive this method and to use
             non-hormonal and non-intrauterine methods (such as abstinence or condoms)
             consistently during this period

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy (by clinical history or a positive urine pregnancy test at screening)

          -  Women currently using any hormonal contraceptive method

          -  Desire pregnancy within next 12 months

          -  Untreated visible genital ulcers or lesions on initial pelvic examination

          -  Known or suspected genital tract cancer (by clinical history or noted during initial
             pelvic examination).

          -  Contraindications to DMPA or LNG implant per the WHO medical eligibility114 criteria
             or judgment of clinician (contraindications include lactation within first 6 weeks
             postpartum, acute deep venous thrombosis or pulmonary embolism, lupus, migraine with
             aura, unexplained vaginal bleeding, current or history of breast cancer, severe
             cirrhosis, liver tumors, history of stroke, current or history of ischemic heart
             disease).

          -  Acute HIV infection (as documented by a known negative HIV test 6 months or less
             prior to screening).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Charles M van der Horst, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jennifer Tang, MD, MSCR</last_name>
    <phone>+265-99-640-2662</phone>
    <email>jennifer_tang@med.unc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UNC-Project Lilongwe</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lilongwe</city>
        <country>Malawi</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lameck Chinula, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Malawi</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 22, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 1, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>contraceptive implant</keyword>
  <keyword>Depo-Medroxyprogesterone Acetate</keyword>
  <keyword>Hormonal Contraception</keyword>
  <keyword>progestin</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Contraceptive Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levonorgestrel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Medroxyprogesterone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Medroxyprogesterone Acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Progestins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
