<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="146365">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01997086</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PTED-MED</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01997086</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Percutaneous Transforaminal Endoscopic Discectomy vs Microendoscopic Discectomy for Treatment of Lumbar Disc Herniation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Percutaneous Transforaminal Endoscopic Discectomy (PTED) Versus Microendoscopic Discectomy (MED) for the Treatment of Lumbar Disc Herniation: A Prospective Randomized Controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Third Affiliated Hospital, Sun Yat-Sen University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Third Affiliated Hospital, Sun Yat-Sen University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>China: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the effectiveness of two minimal invasive
      endoscopic discectomy, PTED and MED, for the treatment of symptomatic lumbar disc
      herniation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Lumbar disc herniation (LDH) is a common pathological process leading to spinal surgery.
      Open discectomy used to be a widespread procedure for surgical treatment for symptomatic
      LDH. Currently, with rapid progress of endoscopic techniques, several minimal invasive
      endoscopic surgeries have been developed to perform discectomy. Percutaneous transforaminal
      endoscopic discectomy (PTED) and microendoscopic discectomy (MED) are two widely used
      minimal invasive surgical procedures, the effectiveness of which has been proved to be
      comparable to conventional open discectomy. As difference in operative approaches and
      iatrogenic injury, the clinical outcome might be dramatically different from each other.

      In this study, a multicenter randomized controlled trial will be performed to evaluate the
      effectiveness of two minimal invasive endoscopic discectomy, PTED and MED, for the treatment
      of symptomatic LDH. We will conduct the study at 3 affiliated hospitals of Sun Yat-Sen
      University.

      Two groups of patients will be investigated; 1) patients diagnosed with lumbar disc
      herniation undergoing PTED, and 2) patients diagnosed with lumbar disc herniation undergoing
      MED.

      The primary endpoints of the study will be changes in Oswestry Disability Index (ODI) as
      measured at pre- and post-operation, 1 month, 3 months, 6 months, and annually thereafter.
      Secondary outcomes include Visual Analog Scale (VAS), the SF-36 Health Survey, as well as
      post-operative radiological assessment. Treatment effect is defined as the difference in the
      mean change from baseline between the two groups.

      On the basis of the results of this trial we will, for the first time, have scientific
      evidence as to the relative effectiveness of PTED versus MED for minimal invasive surgical
      treatment for symptomatic lumbar disc herniation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline in pain and functional status as measured by  Oswestry Low Back Disability Questionnaire (Oswestry Disability Index,ODI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, post-operation, 1 month, 3 months, 6 months, and annually thereafter</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in health-related quality of life as measured by the Visual Analog Scale (VAS) and the SF-36 health status questionnaire, and the radiological changes in spine as measured by x-ray, CT or MRI.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, post-op 1 month, 3 months, 6 months, and annually thereafter.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">345</enrollment>
  <condition>Lumbar Herniated Disc</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Transforaminal discectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>patients diagnosed as lumbar disc herniation undergoing percutaneous transforaminal endoscopic discectomy (PTED).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Microendoscopic discectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients diagnosed as lumbar disc herniation undergoing microendoscopic discectomy (MED).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Percutaneous transforaminal endoscopic discectomy (PTED)</intervention_name>
    <description>Percutaneous transforaminal endoscopic discectomy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Transforaminal discectomy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Microendoscopic discectomy (MED)</intervention_name>
    <description>Microendoscopic discectomy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Microendoscopic discectomy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Duration of symptoms: 6 or more weeks.

          -  Treatments tried: Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory medical therapy and physical
             therapy.

          -  Surgical screening: Persistent radicular pain provoked by moderate exercise, sitting,
             increased abdominal pressure, decreased mobility, straight leg raising.

          -  Tests: MRI, CT or CTM to confirm diagnosis and level(s).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous lumbar spine surgery.

          -  Not a surgical candidate for any of these reasons: Overall health which makes spinal
             surgery too life-threatening to be an appropriate alternative, dramatic improvement
             with conservative care, or inability (for any reason) to undergo surgery within 6
             months.

          -  Possible pregnancy.

          -  Active malignancy: A patient with a history of any invasive malignancy (except
             non-melanoma skin cancer) is ineligible unless he or she has been treated with a
             curative intent AND there has been no clinical signs or symptoms of the malignancy
             for at least 5 years.

          -  Current fracture, infection, and/or deformity (greater than 15 degrees of lumbar
             scoliosis, using Cobb measure technique) of the spine.

          -  Age less than 18 years.

          -  Cauda Equina Syndrome or progressive neurological deficit (usually requiring urgent
             surgery).

          -  Unavailability for follow-up (planning to move, no telephone, etc.) or inability to
             complete data surveys.

          -  Symptoms less than 6 weeks.

          -  Patient currently enrolled in any experimental &quot;spine related&quot; study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Limin Rong, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Third Affiliated Hospital, Sun Yat-Sen University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Limin Rong, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>862085252900</phone>
    <email>ronglimin@21cn.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>the Third Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-Sen University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guangzhou</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <zip>510630</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Limin Rong, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>862085252900</phone>
      <email>ronglimin@21cn.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 21, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 14, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Third Affiliated Hospital, Sun Yat-Sen University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Limin Rong</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof., M.D.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hernia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Intervertebral Disk Displacement</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
