<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="127721">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01849575</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VIPVIZA version 20121204</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01849575</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Visualization of Asymptomatic Atherosclerotic Disease for Optimum Cardiovascular Prevention</brief_title>
  <acronym>VIPVIZA</acronym>
  <official_title>Direct VIsualiZAtion of Asymptomatic Atherosclerotic Disease for Optimum Cardiovascular Prevention. A Population Based Pragmatic Randomised Controlled Trial Within Västerbotten Intervention Programme (VIP) and Ordinary Care.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Umeå University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Västerbotten County Council, Sweden</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Umeå University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Sweden: Regional Ethical Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This population based pragmatic randomized controlled trial (RCT) aims at optimizing
      cardiovascular disease (CVD) prevention through accurate identification of individuals at
      high risk of CVD and accurate perception of the risk, and better compliance to preventive
      treatments and reduced premature CV morbidity and mortality Increased carotid artery
      intima-media thickness (CIMT) and carotid plaques, assessed by ultrasonography, are early
      signs of atherosclerosis and associated with myocardial infarction and stroke. Few studies
      have systematically evaluated image-based risk stratification and its effect on clinical
      outcomes and results are conflicting.

      The Västerbotten Intervention Programme (VIP), Northern Sweden, is integrated in primary
      care services with assessment of traditional CV risk factors and individual health promoting
      counseling for all 40-, 50- and 60-year olds (n=6500/yr). Those with diabetes, hypertension,
      family history of premature CVD and/or hypercholesterolemia are referred to treatment.

      VIP participants with at least one conventional CV risk factor (60% of participants) are
      eligible for inclusion in VIPVIZA. During 2013-2015, 3200 participants will be enrolled.
      Portable carotid ultrasound machines will be used for ultrasound examinations, whereby CIMT
      and plaque formation will be visualized and measured.

      Subjects will be randomly assigned to one of two groups; 1/ Intervention: Written
      information to patient and physician, including graphic presentation in color of CIMT and of
      plaque, vascular age, an ultrasound image, general information about atherosclerosis as a
      dynamic process, and recommendation to follow clinical guidelines for risk factor control.
      2/ Control: No information from the baseline ultrasonography.

      We will explore determinants of behavioral change using psychometric questionnaires and
      level of health literacy. Deep interviews at the time point for the ultrasound examinations
      will explore how the screening relates to risk perception, quality of life, coping
      strategies, attitudes to and skills of self-care.

      Both groups will be managed according to clinical guidelines within the usual health care.
      After three years (2015-2017), the ultrasonography is repeated and information given to all
      participants and their physicians.

      CV risk factors, life style and pharmacological treatments will be assessed after one and
      three years. CV morbidity and mortality and all-cause mortality will be followed during five
      years, i.e. until 2020.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This population based pragmatic randomized controlled trial (RCT) aims at optimizing
      cardiovascular disease (CVD) prevention through accurate identification of individuals at
      high risk of CVD and accurate perception of the risk, and better compliance to preventive
      treatments and reduced premature CV morbidity and mortality

      Background: Myocardial infarction and stroke are the primary causes of deaths. Around 50%
      present with potentially life-threatening symptoms or unexpected death. The majority
      (90-95%) are caused by modifiable factors. Statistical screening models for risk assessment
      to identify individuals at high CVD risk are widely used clinically and basis for
      pharmacological prevention and life style modification. However, the life time risk of CVD
      is underestimated, the accuracy in differentiating between high and intermediate risk is
      only modest, the majority of events (that occur in individuals at only intermediate risk)
      are not predicted by such models, and randomized trials which show improved results of
      prevention of CVD are lacking

      Generally, the association between CVD risk factors and perceived risk is weak. Adherence to
      preventive medications and risk factor control are poor. Health care providers are unaware
      of this problem, and their compliance with guidelines for prevention suboptimal. The
      perception of risk depends on psychological and cultural factors and level of health
      literacy. Risk communication is increasingly recognized as important for CVD management.
      Visual risk messages might be more effective than verbal information

      Increased carotid artery intima-media thickness (CIMT) and carotid plaques, assessed by
      ultrasonography, are early signs of atherosclerosis and associated with myocardial
      infarction and stroke. Their contributory role for risk stratification is unclear, and also
      if imaging-based identification of at-risk subjects improves the compliance to life-style
      modification and pharmacotherapy. Few studies have systematically evaluated image-based risk
      stratification and its effect on clinical outcomes and results are conflicting. Therefore
      large-scale RCTs targeting low or intermediate-risk adults and focus on the impact of
      imaging results are needed

      Project description: The Västerbotten Intervention Programme (VIP), Northern Sweden, is
      integrated in primary care services with assessment of traditional CV risk factors and
      individual health promoting counselling for all 40-, 50- and 60-year olds (n=6500/year).
      Those with diabetes, hypertension, family history of premature CVD and/or
      hypercholesterolemia are referred to treatment according to clinical guidelines

      VIP participants with at least one conventional CV risk factor (60% of participants) are
      eligible for inclusion in VIPVIZA. During 2013-2015, 3200 participants will be enrolled.
      Portable carotid ultrasound machines will be used for ultrasound examinations at rural
      health centres and in hospitals in the towns. CIMT and plaque formation will be visualized
      and measured. Individuals with a stenosis ≥50% of the carotid lumen will be excluded. In a
      pilot study October 2012 (95 participants) 47% were classified as &quot;high risk&quot; of CVD based
      on CIMT ≥75th percentile for age and sex, or &quot;very high risk&quot; based on the presence of
      plaque

      Subjects will be randomly assigned to one of two groups; 1/ Intervention: Written
      information to patient and physician, including graphic presentation in colour of CIMT
      (1-100 percentile by age and sex) and of plaque, vascular age, an ultrasound image, general
      information about atherosclerosis as a dynamic process, and recommendation to follow
      clinical guidelines for risk factor control. 2/ Control: No information from the baseline
      ultrasonography

      Determinants of behavioural change will be explored using psychometric questionnaires and
      level of health literacy. Deep interviews at the time point for the ultrasound examinations
      will explore how the screening relates to risk perception, quality of life, coping
      strategies, attitudes to and skills of self-care

      Both groups will be managed according to clinical guidelines within the usual health care.
      CV risk factors and life style will be monitored after one and three years. After three
      years (2015-2017), the ultrasonography will be repeated and information given to all
      participants and their physicians. Total follow-up will be five years, i.e. until 2020.

      Primary outcome variables: After 1 and 3 years: CVD risk factors and lifestyle. Secondary
      outcome variables: 1/ After 1, 3 and 5 years:  pharmacological treatments for CVD
      prevention. 2/ After 3 years: quality of life, CIMT and  plaque parameters 3/ Within 5
      years: Myocardial infarctions, stroke, revascularizing surgery, and deaths (all-cause and
      CVD specific). Data will be collected from all computerized medical records in the county,
      the national Pharmaceutical, the In-patient, and Causes of Deaths registers.

      An International Advisory Board is established
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>S-LDL-cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>12 and 36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HbA1c</measure>
    <time_frame>12 and 36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>12 and 36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>SCORE evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>12 and 36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Risk of death in myocardial infarction within 10 years expressed as statistical assessment based on smoking, systolic blood-pressure, S-cholesterol, age and sex. The SCORE risk model.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Life style</measure>
    <time_frame>12 month and three years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient questionnaire. Composite measure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospitalizations due to stroke</measure>
    <time_frame>Five years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Data will be collected from computerized medical records from hospital care in the county, regional quality registry on stroke and from the In-patient registry at the National Board of Health and Welfare.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospitalizations due to revascularizations</measure>
    <time_frame>Five years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Data will be collected from computerized medical records from hospital care in the county and from the In-patient registry at the National Board of Health and Welfare.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cause-specific mortality due to myocardial infarctions and stroke</measure>
    <time_frame>Five years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Data will be collected from the Causes of Deaths registry at the National Board of Health and Welfare.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>Five years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Data will be collected the Causes of Deaths registry at the National Board of Health and Welfare.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospitalizations due to myocardial infarctions</measure>
    <time_frame>Five years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Data will be collected from computerized medical records from hospital care in the county, regional quality registry on myocardial infarctions and from the In-patient registry at the National Board of Health and Welfare.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Carotid ultrasonography results</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Compound measure. Carotid Intima Media Thickness Carotid plaques: Total plaque area, Grey scale median (GSM)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacological treatment, composite outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3 and 5 years after baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Prescriptions of medications for hypertension, diabetes and dyslipidemia. Data collected from computerized medical records in primary and hospital care in the county.
Purchases of medications for hypertension, diabetes and dyslipidemia followed through data from the Pharmaceutical registry, National Board of Health and Wellfare</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3200</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Info about carotid ultrasound results</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Information about carotid ultrasound results to patient and physician</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No info about carotid ultrasound results</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No information about carotid ultrasound results to patient and physician.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Information about carotid ultrasound results</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Info about carotid ultrasound results</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        - Participant in the Västerbotten Intervention Programme

        and

          -  40 years old and a history of CVD at age &lt; 60 years among first-degree relative

        or

          -  50 years old and at least one of the following six criteria:

          -  a history of CVD at age &lt; 60 years among first-degree relative,

          -  smoking,

          -  diabetes,

          -  hypertension,

          -  S-LDL-cholesterol ≥4.5 mmol/L,

          -  abdominal obesity

        or

          -  60 years old

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Stenosis ≥50% of the carotid lumen
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Margareta Norberg, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Umeå University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ulf Näslund, Professor,MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Umeå University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Reseach Center Umeå University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Umeå</city>
        <zip>Se-90185</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Margareta Norberg, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+46 90 785</phone>
      <phone_ext>3343</phone_ext>
      <email>margareta.norberg@umu.se</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ulf Näslund, Professor,MD</last_name>
      <phone>+46 90 785</phone>
      <phone_ext>3600</phone_ext>
      <email>ulf.naslund@vll.se</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Margareta Norberg, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Norberg M, Wall S, Boman K, Weinehall L. The Västerbotten Intervention Programme: background, design and implications. Glob Health Action. 2010 Mar 22;3. doi: 10.3402/gha.v3i0.4643.</citation>
    <PMID>20339479</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Norberg M, Blomstedt Y, Lönnberg G, Nyström L, Stenlund H, Wall S, Weinehall L. Community participation and sustainability--evidence over 25 years in the Västerbotten Intervention Programme. Glob Health Action. 2012 Dec 17;5:1-9. doi: 10.3402/gha.v5i0.19166.</citation>
    <PMID>23528041</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vanoli D, Lindqvist P, Wiklund U, Henein M, Näslund U. Fully automated on-screen carotid intima-media thickness measurement: A screening tool for subclinical atherosclerosis. J Clin Ultrasound. 2013 Mar 28. doi: 10.1002/jcu.22041. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>23553729</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yusuf S, Hawken S, Ounpuu S, Dans T, Avezum A, Lanas F, McQueen M, Budaj A, Pais P, Varigos J, Lisheng L; INTERHEART Study Investigators. Effect of potentially modifiable risk factors associated with myocardial infarction in 52 countries (the INTERHEART study): case-control study. Lancet. 2004 Sep 11-17;364(9438):937-52.</citation>
    <PMID>15364185</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Donnell MJ, Xavier D, Liu L, Zhang H, Chin SL, Rao-Melacini P, Rangarajan S, Islam S, Pais P, McQueen MJ, Mondo C, Damasceno A, Lopez-Jaramillo P, Hankey GJ, Dans AL, Yusoff K, Truelsen T, Diener HC, Sacco RL, Ryglewicz D, Czlonkowska A, Weimar C, Wang X, Yusuf S; INTERSTROKE investigators. Risk factors for ischaemic and intracerebral haemorrhagic stroke in 22 countries (the INTERSTROKE study): a case-control study. Lancet. 2010 Jul 10;376(9735):112-23. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(10)60834-3. Epub 2010 Jun 17.</citation>
    <PMID>20561675</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Claassen L, Henneman L, Nijpels G, Dekker J, Marteau T, Timmermans D. Causal beliefs and perceptions of risk for diabetes and cardiovascular disease, The Netherlands, 2007. Prev Chronic Dis. 2011 Nov;8(6):A130. Epub 2011 Oct 17.</citation>
    <PMID>22005623</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Garner JB. Problems of nonadherence in cardiology and proposals to improve outcomes. Am J Cardiol. 2010 May 15;105(10):1495-501. doi: 10.1016/j.amjcard.2009.12.077. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20451702</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kotseva K, Wood D, De Backer G, De Bacquer D, Pyörälä K, Reiner Z, Keil U; EUROASPIRE Study Group. EUROASPIRE III. Management of cardiovascular risk factors in asymptomatic high-risk patients in general practice: cross-sectional survey in 12 European countries. Eur J Cardiovasc Prev Rehabil. 2010 Oct;17(5):530-40. doi: 10.1097/HJR.0b013e3283383f30.</citation>
    <PMID>20577089</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Safeer RS, Cooke CE, Keenan J. The impact of health literacy on cardiovascular disease. Vasc Health Risk Manag. 2006;2(4):457-64. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17323600</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Karbach U, Schubert I, Hagemeister J, Ernstmann N, Pfaff H, Höpp HW. Physicians' knowledge of and compliance with guidelines: an exploratory study in cardiovascular diseases. Dtsch Arztebl Int. 2011 Feb;108(5):61-9. doi: 10.3238/arztebl.2011.0061. Epub 2011 Feb 4.</citation>
    <PMID>21311711</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fagerlin A, Ubel PA, Smith DM, Zikmund-Fisher BJ. Making numbers matter: present and future research in risk communication. Am J Health Behav. 2007 Sep-Oct;31 Suppl 1:S47-56.</citation>
    <PMID>17931136</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Webster R, Heeley E. Perceptions of risk: understanding cardiovascular disease. Risk Manag Healthc Policy. 2010;3:49-60. doi: 10.2147/RMHP.S8288. Epub 2010 Sep 6.</citation>
    <PMID>22312218</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lorenz MW, Markus HS, Bots ML, Rosvall M, Sitzer M. Prediction of clinical cardiovascular events with carotid intima-media thickness: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Circulation. 2007 Jan 30;115(4):459-67. Epub 2007 Jan 22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17242284</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peters SA, den Ruijter HM, Bots ML, Moons KG. Improvements in risk stratification for the occurrence of cardiovascular disease by imaging subclinical atherosclerosis: a systematic review. Heart. 2012 Feb;98(3):177-84. doi: 10.1136/heartjnl-2011-300747. Epub 2011 Nov 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22095617</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Den Ruijter HM, Peters SA, Anderson TJ, Britton AR, Dekker JM, Eijkemans MJ, Engström G, Evans GW, de Graaf J, Grobbee DE, Hedblad B, Hofman A, Holewijn S, Ikeda A, Kavousi M, Kitagawa K, Kitamura A, Koffijberg H, Lonn EM, Lorenz MW, Mathiesen EB, Nijpels G, Okazaki S, O'Leary DH, Polak JF, Price JF, Robertson C, Rembold CM, Rosvall M, Rundek T, Salonen JT, Sitzer M, Stehouwer CD, Witteman JC, Moons KG, Bots ML. Common carotid intima-media thickness measurements in cardiovascular risk prediction: a meta-analysis. JAMA. 2012 Aug 22;308(8):796-803. doi: 10.1001/jama.2012.9630.</citation>
    <PMID>22910757</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rodondi N, Collet TH, Nanchen D, Locatelli I, Depairon M, Aujesky D, Bovet P, Cornuz J. Impact of carotid plaque screening on smoking cessation and other cardiovascular risk factors: a randomized controlled trial. Arch Intern Med. 2012 Feb 27;172(4):344-52. doi: 10.1001/archinternmed.2011.1326. Epub 2012 Jan 23.</citation>
    <PMID>22269590</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalia NK, Miller LG, Nasir K, Blumenthal RS, Agrawal N, Budoff MJ. Visualizing coronary calcium is associated with improvements in adherence to statin therapy. Atherosclerosis. 2006 Apr;185(2):394-9. Epub 2005 Jul 26.</citation>
    <PMID>16051253</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Emberson J, Whincup P, Morris R, Walker M, Ebrahim S. Evaluating the impact of population and high-risk strategies for the primary prevention of cardiovascular disease. Eur Heart J. 2004 Mar;25(6):484-91.</citation>
    <PMID>15039128</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Polonsky TS, Greenland P. CVD screening in low-risk, asymptomatic adults: clinical trials needed. Nat Rev Cardiol. 2012 Oct;9(10):599-604. doi: 10.1038/nrcardio.2012.114. Epub 2012 Aug 14.</citation>
    <PMID>22889949</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rodondi N, Auer R, de Bosset Sulzer V, Ghali WA, Cornuz J. Atherosclerosis screening by noninvasive imaging for cardiovascular prevention: a systematic review. J Gen Intern Med. 2012 Feb;27(2):220-31. doi: 10.1007/s11606-011-1833-3. Epub 2011 Sep 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21882076</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shaw LJ, Blumenthal RS, Raggi P. Screening asymptomatic low-risk individuals for coronary heart disease: issues and controversies. J Nucl Cardiol. 2004 Jul-Aug;11(4):382-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15295406</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sørensen MH, Gerke O, Lambrechtsen J, Sand NP, Mols R, Thomassen A, Larsen ML, Mickley H, Diederichsen AC. Changes in medical treatment six months after risk stratification with HeartScore and coronary artery calcification scanning of healthy middle-aged subjects. Eur J Prev Cardiol. 2012 Dec;19(6):1496-502. doi: 10.1177/1741826711428063. Epub 2011 Oct 21.</citation>
    <PMID>22019909</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perk J, De Backer G, Gohlke H, Graham I, Reiner Z, Verschuren M, Albus C, Benlian P, Boysen G, Cifkova R, Deaton C, Ebrahim S, Fisher M, Germano G, Hobbs R, Hoes A, Karadeniz S, Mezzani A, Prescott E, Ryden L, Scherer M, Syvänne M, Scholte op Reimer WJ, Vrints C, Wood D, Zamorano JL, Zannad F; European Association for Cardiovascular Prevention &amp; Rehabilitation (EACPR); ESC Committee for Practice Guidelines (CPG). European Guidelines on cardiovascular disease prevention in clinical practice (version 2012). The Fifth Joint Task Force of the European Society of Cardiology and Other Societies on Cardiovascular Disease Prevention in Clinical Practice (constituted by representatives of nine societies and by invited experts). Eur Heart J. 2012 Jul;33(13):1635-701. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehs092. Epub 2012 May 3. Erratum in: Eur Heart J. 2012 Sep;33(17):2126.</citation>
    <PMID>22555213</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 11, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 3, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ultrasonography</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiovascular diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Risk communication</keyword>
  <keyword>Risk assessment</keyword>
  <keyword>Behavioral change</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
