<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="10106">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02148705</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MW 2010-03-02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02148705</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of NexoBrid in Subjects With Thermal Burns</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multicenter, Multinational, Randomized, Controlled, Blinded Study, Performed in Subjects With Thermal Burns, to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of NexoBrid as Compared to Standard of Care Treatment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>MediWound Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>MediWound Ltd</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will be a three-arms study intending to demonstrate superiority of NexoBrid
      treatment over SOC and over the Gel Vehicle placebo control treatment in thermal burn
      subjects. The study objective is to evaluate the efficacy and safety of NexoBrid in removing
      burn eschar earlier and reducing surgical needs in hospitalized subjects with large burns (
      4-15% of Total Body Surface Area).

      physicians will define one or more Target Wounds (TWs) per subject according to TWs
      definition. All subjects' deep  (DPT and FT) burns that comply with the specified entrance
      criteria are intended to receive study treatment per the randomized study arm.

      The randomization procedure will be initiated only after all Target wounds of a subject have
      been defined.  Patients  will be assigned to the treatment arm in a 3:3:1 ratio (NexoBrid:
      SOC (Collagenase): Gel Vehicle).

      Prior to eschar removal treatment with NexoBrid, Collagenase (SOC) or Gel Vehicle, patients
      will be medicated with appropriate analgesia and undergo wound cleansing and dressing of all
      wounds with antibacterial solutions. Following wound cleansing and antibacterial treatments,
      subjects will undergo the eschar removal process as per treatment assignment. Eschar Removal
      with NexoBrid, Gel Vehicle and Collagenase will be performed will be performed by two
      different health care professionals. First, a health care professional will prepare and
      apply the topical treatment. Wound assessment will be performed by a different health care
      professional, masked to the application process and the applied product, after the topical
      agent has been removed and the wound has been soaked for 2 hours (eliminating all traces of
      the debriding agent). If medically judged, the same product may be applied for a second time
      to the same burn area however, not more than twice to the same burn wound area. Additional
      surgical and/or non surgical procedures, pre defined in the protocol, might be performed, if
      medically warranted.

      Subsequent to eschar removal, all wounds will be assessed and treated in the same manner, in
      accordance with post-eschar removal wound care strategy. Further, patients will undergo
      daily assessments of VS and pain assessments until HD and weekly assessments thereafter,
      until wounds closure. Following wounds closure, patients will be followed up on a monthly
      basis for 3 months and after that, at 6, 9, 12, 18 and 24 months post complete wound closure
      for long term outcomes evaluation (including cosmesis, function and QoL evaluation).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Factorial Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of complete eschar removal: Demonstrate superiority over SOC for eschar removal as measured by incidence of complete eschar removal</measure>
    <time_frame>post application (post 2 h soaking)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">175</enrollment>
  <condition>Thermal Burns</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NexoBrid Gel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>NexoBrid Gel is applied to the burn wound at a dose of 2 g NexoBrid sterile powder mixed with 20g sterile Gel Vehicle per 1% of TBSA (~ surface of an adult palm) for four hours.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gel Vehicle</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Gel Vehicle is applied to the burn wound at a dose of 20 g sterile Gel per 1% of TBSA (~ surface of an adult palm) for four hours.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SOC - Santyl</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Collagenase Santyl ointment should be applied for 4 hours. Forty (40) g should be applied on 1% TBSA burn.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NexoBrid</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>NexoBrid Gel</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Santyl</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>SOC - Santyl</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Males and females; ≥ 18  and ≤ 70 years of age,

          2. Thermal burns caused by fire/flame, scalds or contact,

          3. Patient total burns area should be between 4% to 15% TBSA (≥ 4%  and ≤  15% ; SPT,
             DPT and/or FT in depth),

          4. Informed consent can be obtained within 48 hours of the burn injury.

          5. Patients who are willing and able to sign a written consent form. Inclusion Criteria
             - Wound level

        At least one wound (a continuous burn area which can be treated in one session; might
        include several anatomical areas) in a patient should meet all following criteria:

          1. Wound that is ≥ 1% TBSA  (not including face, perineal or genital),

          2. Wound is composed of DPT and/or FT in depth. Superficial partial thickness areas may
             be included in the wound area only if cannot be separated from deeper areas (e.g.
             surrounded by or mixed with DPT areas) and might interfere with the treatment of the
             deeper areas,

          3. Wound that is intended for surgical eschar removal,

          4. Wound's blisters can be unroofed, as judged by the investigator.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who are unable to follow study procedures and follow up period,

          2. Modified Baux index  ≥ 80,

          3. Patients with burned, charred fingers, 3rd degree in depth, possibly devoid of
             circulation,

          4. Patients with &gt; 15% TBSA burns,

          5. Patients with abraded wound/s that cannot be treated by an enzymatic debrider
             application (NexoBrid or Collagenase) will be excluded from the study,

          6. Patients with electrical or chemical burns,

          7. Patients with DPT and/or FT facial burn wounds from flame, flash, explosion &gt;0.5%
             TBSA (scald and contact burns are allowed),

          8. Patients with circumferential DPT and/or FT burns defined as Extremities at Risk
             (EAR) ,

          9. The following pre-enrollment dressings: a. Flammacerium, b. Silver Nitrate (AgNO3),

         10. Patients with pre-enrolment wounds which are covered by eschar heavily saturated with
             iodine or by SSD pseudoeschar (e.g. pseudoeschar as a result of SSD treatment),

         11. Patients with pre-enrollment escharotomy,

         12. Patients with diagnosed infections as described in Section 11.2.3 of study protocol,

         13. Any signs or history that may indicate smoke inhalation (e.g. flame burn to the upper
             body, flames in enclosed space, smoke and fumes on the patient and in mouth and
             nostrils, deep flame burns &gt;0.5 %TBSA to the face, cough, hoarseness, stridor or
             breathing difficulty including tachypnea possibly related to smoke inhalation, etc.),

         14. Pregnant women (positive pregnancy test) or nursing mothers,

         15. Poorly controlled diabetes mellitus (HbA1c&gt;9%) in patients with known diabetes as
             captured in the medical history,

         16. Patients with BMI greater than 34.0 kg/m2,

         17. ASA greater than 2 (see Appendix 15 in study protocol)

         18. Cardio-pulmonary disease (MI within 6 months prior to injury, pulmonary hypertension,
             COPD or pre-existing oxygen-dependent pulmonary diseases, broncho-pneumonia, steroid
             dependent asthma or uncontrolled asthma),

         19. Pre-existing diseases which interfere with circulation (peripheral vascular disease,
             edema, lymphedema, surgery to regional lymph nodes, obesity, varicose veins),

         20. Any conditions that would preclude safe participation in the study or adding further
             risk to the basic acute burn trauma (such as immuno-compromising diseases, life
             threatening trauma, severe pre-existing coagulation disorder, cardiovascular
             disorder, pulmonary disorder, liver disorder including post alcoholic abuse impaired
             function or neoplastic disease),

         21. Chronic systemic steroid intake,

         22. History of allergy and/or known sensitivity to pineapples, papaya, Bromelain or
             papain,

         23. Current (within 12 months prior to screening) suicide attempt,

         24. Mentally incapacitated adults who are incapable of giving legal consent (e.g.
             dementia, psychiatric patients, etc),

         25. Enrollment in any investigational drug trial within 4 weeks prior to screening,

         26. Current (within 12 months prior to screening) alcohol (daily consumption &gt; 3 units
             for males and &gt;2 units for females) or drug abuse ,

         27. Prisoners and incarcerated.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>17 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stony Brook University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stony Brook,</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Adam Singer, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 27, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 22, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>fire/flame</keyword>
  <keyword>scalds</keyword>
  <keyword>contact</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Burns</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
