<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="129368">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01808976</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R34MH100466</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01808976</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Can Mental Health Apps Work in the Real World? A Feasibility Pilot Study.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Can Mental Health Apps Work in the Real World? A Feasibility Pilot Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Over two million people in the US download health apps onto their smartphones and tablets,
      with the intent of improving their quality of life. Despite widespread use of these apps,
      there is relatively little information regarding app user access (do users download health
      apps and use them more than once), app user engagement (do users follow the app protocols)
      and app impact on mood, cognition and daily functioning. Our long-term goal is to conduct a
      future randomized controlled trial investigating access, engagement and impact of two types
      of mental health apps, apps based on evidence-based therapeutic principles (i.e.: Problem
      Solving Therapy) and apps based on cognitive neuroscience principles of depression (i.e.: a
      cognitive training game called Evolution) and compare both to an information only app. Our
      intent is to conduct this study entirely on mobile devices, in order to investigate access,
      engagement, and impact in an ecologically valid manner. The purpose of this pilot study is
      to test the feasibility of conducting our future randomized controlled trial comparing three
      mobile mental health apps for the management of depressed mood, improvement of cognitive
      control, and improvement in activities of daily living in people aged 18 and older.
      Recruitment, consent, randomization, app use and outcome assessment will be conducted
      entirely on mobile devices. We will recruit 150 people through four different recruitment
      avenues to determine which avenue results in the most representative sample of our target
      population (people 18 and older who have symptoms of depression that are interfering with
      their quality of life). We will also determine the number we need to recruit to have a final
      sample of 150 people willing to be randomized between the 3 apps and complete an 12-week
      study of app impact on mood, cognition and function. This pilot will provide information on
      the completeness of data from a study conducted in this manner, and uncover any other
      challenges we may face by using mobile devices for data collection, and if we will find
      differential drop out between app type (e.g.: will more people stop using of the information
      only app prematurely?). Although we will not have sufficient statistical power to answer
      questions about comparative effectiveness between the apps, we plan to explore relationships
      between sample demographics, app use, and improvement in cognitive control on improvements
      in mood and function.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sheehan Disability Assessment Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assesses functional impairment in three inter-related domains; work/school, social and family life.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Global Improvement Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A 7 point scale that requires the clinician to assess how much the patient's illness has improved or worsened relative to a baseline state at the beginning of the intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Health Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The PHQ-9 is the nine item depression scale of the Patient Health Questionnaire. The PHQ-9 is a powerful tool for assisting primary care clinicians in diagnosing depression as well as selecting and monitoring treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sheehan Disability Assessment Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assesses functional impairment in three inter-related domains; work/school, social and family life.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Global Improvement Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A 7 point scale that requires the clinician to assess how much the patient's illness has improved or worsened relative to a baseline state at the beginning of the intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Health Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The PHQ-9 is the nine item depression scale of the Patient Health Questionnaire. The PHQ-9 is a powerful tool for assisting primary care clinicians in diagnosing depression as well as selecting and monitoring treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sheehan Disability Assessment Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assesses functional impairment in three inter-related domains; work/school, social and family life.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Global Improvement Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A 7 point scale that requires the clinician to assess how much the patient's illness has improved or worsened relative to a baseline state at the beginning of the intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Health Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The PHQ-9 is the nine item depression scale of the Patient Health Questionnaire. The PHQ-9 is a powerful tool for assisting primary care clinicians in diagnosing depression as well as selecting and monitoring treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>MDD</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Evolution</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This app is designed to be a cognitive training game that conditions the CCN. This is done by having participants play a multitasking game that targets their perceptual discrimination abilities, selective attention, and visuomotor tracking skills. At the first session, participants will be directed to an initial assessment of each of these cognitive control skills in a single task and dual-task setting (a total of 3 different diagnostics, described below). Each week, this diagnostic phase will reflect the training paradigm they will encounter for that week, as each week the perceptual and tracking challenges will increase.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PST app</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This app is based on the social problem solving protocol developed by Nezu and D'Zurilla . The app begins with explaining the PST steps. Participants are informed that they can learn each step one session at a time, or they can chose to learn all the steps at once. After each step completed, participants are asked if they want to continue onto the next step or save it for the next session, thus the app tailors itself to the users ability to absorb new information.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Basic health push app</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This app provides daily suggestions for overcoming depressed mood and allows users to track their mood, using the 0-9 scale available for all three apps. In the first app session, participants are given a general education about depression and its known causes and consequences. Participants are told that to overcome mood problems, they must engage in one mood improvement strategy a day and that the app will suggest one to try each day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Problem Solving Therapy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>PST app</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Evolution</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Evolution</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Baisc health push</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Basic health push app</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years or older

          -  must own smart device

          -  a total score of 5 or greater on the PHQ-9; OR a score of 2 or greater on at least
             one of the first two PHQ-9 items AND a score of 2 or greater on the 10th PHQ-9 item

          -  must be English speaking

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  below 18 years or older

          -  does not own a smart device

          -  non-English speaking

          -  a total score of less than 5 on the PHQ-9

          -  less than a score of 2 on the first two PHQ-9 items and less than 2 on the 10th PHQ-9
             item
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patricia Arean, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 8, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 7, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
