<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="143071">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02082184</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ADC-CI-APO-12018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02082184</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Evaluation of a Novel Glucose Sensing Technology in Type 2 Diabetes</brief_title>
  <acronym>REPLACE</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomised Controlled Study to Evaluate the Impact of Novel Glucose Sensing Technology on HbA1c in Type 2 Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Abbott Diabetes Care</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Abbott Diabetes Care</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>France: Agence Nationale de Sécurité du Médicament et des produits de santé</authority>
    <authority>France: Conseil National de l'Ordre des Médecins</authority>
    <authority>France: Institutional Ethical Committee</authority>
    <authority>France: National Consultative Ethics Committee for Health and Life Sciences</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Ethics Commission</authority>
    <authority>Germany: German Institute of Medical Documentation and Information</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: National Institute for Health Research</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the impact of the Abbott Sensor Based Glucose Monitoring System on glycaemic
      control (HbA1c) compared to Self Monitoring Blood Glucose (SMBG) testing using a randomised
      controlled study design in adults with Type 2 diabetes  using  insulin.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HbA1c at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 194 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Difference in HbA1c between intervention and control group at day 194 adjusting for baseline HbA1c at day 1</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time in Range</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Days 194 to 208</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Difference in time in range 70 -180 mg/dL between intervention and control group assessed in days 194 to 208 adjusting for baseline (days 1 to 15 time in range).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Time in Range at Day 45</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Days 31 to 45</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change is defined as time in range 70 - 180 mg/dL in days 31 -45 minus time in range at baseline (days 1- 15) in the intervention group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease in HbA1c by greater than or equal to 0.5%</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Day 194</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Difference in the proportion of subjects with a greater than or equal to 0.5% reduction in HbA1c from baseline at day 194 between intervention and control group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6 Month HbA1c Level ≤7.5%</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 194</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Difference in the proportion of subjects that achieve HbA1c level ≤7.5% at day 194 between intervention and control group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HbA1c at 3 Months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 105 Days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Difference in HbA1c between intervention and control group at day 105 adjusting for baseline HbA1c at day 1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Days 194 to 208</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Difference in mean glucose between intervention and control group assessed in days 194 to 208 adjusting for baseline (days 1 to 15). mean glucose</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Glucose variability</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Days 194 to 208</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Difference in continuous overall net glycaemic action (CONGA) (1, 2 &amp; 4 hour), standard deviation (SD) rate of change, (mean amplitude of glycaemic excursions) MAGE, mean of daily differences (MODD) , hign blood glucose index (HBGI) ,  low blood glucose index (LBGI) post prandial glucose peak, time to peak, excursion and area under the curve (AUC) &gt;180mg/dL between intervention and control group assessed in days 194 to 208 adjusting for baseline (days 1 to 15). Post prandial glucose peak, time to peak, excursion and AUC&gt;180mg/dL will be calculated during the 3 hours after each logged meal, for each subject and timeframe. Glucose excursion is change from meal time to peak glucose.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time spent and frequency &lt; 70 mg/dL and &lt;55mg/dL</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Days 194 to 208</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Difference in time and frequency &lt; 70 mg/dL and &lt;55mg/dL(hours per day) between intervention and control group assessed in days 194 to 208 adjusting for baseline (days 1 to 15).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time spent and frequency &gt; 180 mg/dL and &gt; 240mg/dL</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Days 194 to 208</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Difference in time &gt; 180 mg/dL and &gt; 240mg/dL(hours per day) between intervention and control group assessed in days 194 to 208 adjusting for baseline (days 1 to 15).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of episodes of diabetic ketoacidosis (DKA), Hyperosmolar hyperglycaemic state (HHS), and severe hypoglycaemia.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Days 15 to 208</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of episodes of DKA, HHS and severe hypoglycaemia.will be summarised in the intervention and control group in each timeframe.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total daily dose of insulin (TDD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Days 194 to 208</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Difference in TDD between intervention and control group assessed in days 194 to 208 adjusting for baseline (days 1 to 15) TDD. TDD calculated from Reader uploads.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body weight, BMI, blood pressure and lipids at 6 Months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (day 1) and Day 194</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Difference in body weight, BMI blood pressure and lipids between intervention and control group assessed at day 194 adjusting for baseline (day 1).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>User Questionnaire (Subject &amp; HCP) at 6 Months</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 208</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>User questionnaire responses will be tabulated as number and percentage of subjects with each response. HCP questionnaire responses will be tabulated as number and percentage of HCPs with each response</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Day 194</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Includes diabetes treatment satisfaction questionnaire (DTSQ), diabetes distress scale(DDS) &amp; diabetes quality of life (DQoL) Difference in each score between intervention and control group assessed at day 194 adjusting for the corresponding score at baseline (day 1).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinic time and medication usage</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (days 1 -15) and Days 15 to 208</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of emergency room visits, admissions, additional non protocol related clinic time and medication usage will be summarised in the intervention and control group in each timeframe (days 1-15 and days 15 -208).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of glucose measurements performed</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Days 194 to 208</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Difference in frequency (number per day) of blood glucose finger stick tests between intervention and control group assessed in days 194 to 208 adjusting for baseline (days 1 to 15) frequency of finger stick tests performed. The frequency of sensor scans performed will be summarised in the intervention group in days 194 to 208.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Days -30 to 208</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of adverse events in days -30 to 208 will be tabulated as the number and percentage of subjects experiencing adverse events in the intervention and control groups, classified by seriousness, severity, relationship to the device and relationship to the study.  Glycaemic adverse events will be classed separately.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events Open Access Phase</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 208 to 388</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of adverse events in days 208 to 388 will be tabulated as the number and percentage of subjects experiencing adverse events in the intervention and control groups, classified by seriousness, severity, relationship to the device and relationship to the study.  Glycaemic adverse events will be classed separately.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events at 1 Month</measure>
    <time_frame>Days -30 to 45</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of adverse events in days -30 to 45 will be tabulated as the number and percentage of subjects experiencing adverse events in the intervention groups, classified by seriousness, severity, relationship to the device and relation to the study, Glycaemic adverse events will be classed separately.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">210</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sensor Based Glucose Monitoring System</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard system use for 6 months. Followed by open access to the device for 6 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Blood Glucose Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects randomised to the control group will be given blood glucose meters for monitoring for the 6 months study duration.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sensor Based Glucose Monitoring System</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will wear the Abbott Sensor Based Glucose Monitoring System (unmasked) for 6 months to monitor their glucose levels. Post completion of the 6 month intervention, subjects participating in this arm of the study will be given a further 6 month period of open access to the device.
All subjects will wear a masked Abbott Sensor Based Glucose Monitoring System, for 14 days prior to randomisation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sensor Based Glucose Monitoring System</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Blood Glucose Monitoring</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will use an Abbott Blood Glucose Monitoring System (standard blood glucose meter) for 6 months to monitor their glucose levels. A 14-day masked wear of the Abbott Sensor Based Glucose Monitoring System is included for these subjects at the 6 month time point, to collect glycaemic variability data for comparison to the intervention group of the study.
All subjects will wear a masked Abbott Sensor Based Glucose Monitoring System, for 14 days prior to randomisation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Blood Glucose Monitoring</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Has Type 2 diabetes on insulin therapy for ≥ 6 months and on their current regimen
             for ≥3 months prior to study entry.

          2. Their insulin management must be one of the following;

               1. an injection regimen of  prandial insulin at least once daily,

               2. or, prandial insulin at least once daily plus basal insulin at least once daily,

               3. or, continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion (CSII) with no plans to change
                  during the study.

          3. HbA1c result ≥7.5% (58 mmol/mol) and ≤12.0% (108 mmol/mol) on entry to the study.

          4. Reports self-testing of blood glucose levels on a regular basis equivalent to a
             minimum of 10 tests per week, for at least 2 months prior to study entry.

          5. In the investigator's opinion the subject is considered technically capable of using
             the Abbott Sensor Based Glucose Monitoring System.

          6. In the Investigator's opinion the subject is proactive and therefore willing to
             modify their diabetes management

          7. Aged 18 years or over.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Insulin regimen consists entirely of basal or includes bi-phasic insulin.

          2. Subject is currently prescribed animal insulin.

          3. Subject is currently prescribed steroid therapy or is likely to require steroid
             therapy for any acute or chronic condition during the study.

          4. Has known allergy to medical grade adhesives.

          5. Currently participating in another device or drug study that could affect glucose
             measurements or glucose management.

          6. Currently using a Continuous Glucose Monitoring (CGM) device or has used one within
             the previous 4 months.

          7. Is planning to use a CGM device at any time during the study.

          8. Total daily dose of insulin (TDD) is &gt;1.75iu/kg at entry to the study.

          9. A female subject who is pregnant or planning to become pregnant within the study
             duration.

         10. Currently receiving dialysis treatment or planning to receive dialysis during the
             study.

         11. Has experienced an acute myocardial infarction within previous 6 months.

         12. Has a concomitant disease or condition that may compromise patient safety, including
             unstable coronary heart disease, cystic fibrosis, serious psychiatric disorder, or
             any other uncontrolled medical condition.

         13. Has a pacemaker or any other neuro stimulators.

         14. Has experienced any episode of severe hypoglycaemia, requiring third party assistance
             and/or admission to hospital, in the previous 6 months.

         15. Has experienced any episode of diabetic ketoacidosis (DKA) or hyperosmolar
             hyperglycaemic state (HHS) in the previous 6 months.

         16. In the investigator's opinion, the subject is considered as unsuitable for inclusion
             in the study for any other reason.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas Haak</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Research Institute of Diabetes Academy Mergentheim (FIDAM)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joe Bugler</last_name>
    <phone>+44 1993 863164</phone>
    <email>joe.bugler@abbott.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Haut Lévêque</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bordeaux</city>
        <zip>33604</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bogdan Catargi</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital sainte Marguerite</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille</city>
        <zip>13274</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pauline Bellicar - Schaepelynck</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Lapeyronie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montpellier</city>
        <zip>34295</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eric Renard</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU. Nancy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nancy</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bruno Guerci</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Guillaume et René Laennec</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nantes</city>
        <zip>44000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lucie Chaillous</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Cochin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75679</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Helen Mosnier-Pudar</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Lariboisere</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75475</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jean-Pierre Riveline</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Rangueil</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulouse</city>
        <zip>31059</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Helene Hanaire</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Diabetes Zentrum Mergentheim</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bad Mergentheim</city>
        <zip>97980</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Thomas Haak</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Praris Dr Karin Schlecht</name>
      <address>
        <city>Eisenach</city>
        <zip>99817</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karin Schlecht</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vorstandsmitglied Deutsche Diabetes-Hilfe</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jens Kroger</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gemeiusilaftsproxis Fur Junere,</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>22607</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ulrich Wendisch</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Diabetologische Schwenpunlet Praxis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>21073</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kai Paschen</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hohenzollernring</name>
      <address>
        <city>Münster</city>
        <zip>48145</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rose</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Diabetes Center Quakenbruck</name>
      <address>
        <city>Quakenbrück</city>
        <zip>49610</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephan Matthaei</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Diabetes Schwerpunktpraxis Loccum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rehburg-Loccum</city>
        <zip>31547</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jost Hilgenberg</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>An der Pforte</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rosenheim</city>
        <zip>55545</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maxenier</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Versdias GmbH</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sulzbach-Rosenberg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ulrich Aigner</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ayr Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ayr</city>
        <state>Ayrshire</state>
        <zip>KA6 6DX</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrew Collier</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Diabetes Research, Linda McCartney Centre, Royal Liverpool University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liverpool</city>
        <state>Cheshire</state>
        <zip>L7 8XP</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jiten Vora</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal United Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bath</city>
        <zip>BA1 3NG</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tony Robinson</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>FRCPath Life and Health Sciences, Aston University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <zip>B4 7ET</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Parth Narendran</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital of North Durham</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <zip>DH1 5TW</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kamal Abouglila</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Diabetes Centre, Ipswich Hospital NHS Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ipswich</city>
        <zip>IP4 5PD</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gerry Rayman</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. James University Hospital, Leeds Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leeds</city>
        <zip>LS9 7TF</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ramzi Ajjan</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rotherham General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rotherham</city>
        <zip>S60 2UD</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bernd Franke</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 20, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 6, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sensing Technology</keyword>
  <keyword>Type 2 Diabetes,</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
