<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="146433">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02072486</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>I 238913</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2014-00180</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>I 238913</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016056</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02072486</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sorafenib Tosylate in Treating Patients With Liver Cancer That Cannot Be Removed By Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Granzyme B Production as a Biomarker for the Immunomodulatory Activity of Sorafenib in HCC</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Comprehensive Cancer Network</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This clinical trial studies sorafenib tosylate in treating patients with liver cancer that
      cannot be removed by surgery. Sorafenib tosylate may block some of the enzymes needed for
      tumor cell growth. Blocking these enzymes may also help the immune system work better.
      Granzyme B is a biomarker that can be used to measure how well the immune system is working.
      A biomarker is a biological molecule found in blood, other body fluids, or tissues that is a
      sign of a normal or abnormal process, or of a condition or disease. Studying granzyme B
      levels in patients receiving sorafenib tosylate may help doctors learn more about the
      effects of sorafenib tosylate on the immune system and may help to predict how well
      sorafenib tosylate will work in treating patients with liver cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine whether the proportion of cytotoxic T lymphocytes that are producing
      granzyme B (denoted pGrzB) as measured ~28-35 days after initiation of sorafenib (sorafenib
      tosylate) therapy correlates with overall survival, defined as the number of months between
      the start of sorafenib treatment and death from any cause.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine whether higher pGrzB levels will correlate with better sorafenib tolerance,
      manifested by fewer dose reductions, dose interruptions and adverse events.

      II. To determine whether improved immune function may also result in greater recognition of
      hepatitis viral antigens.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive sorafenib tosylate orally (PO) twice daily (BID). Treatment continues in
      the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study, patients are followed up for 30 days and then periodically
      thereafter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Time between start of first treatment and death, assessed up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The hazard ratio and 95% confidence interval for the effect of day ~28-35 pGrzB (in 10 percentage point increments) on OS will be estimated using proportional hazards (PH) models. The pGrzB functional form will be assessed using generalized additive models. Possible confounding from sorafenib dose differences and baseline characteristics will be assessed by including other covariates (or perhaps frailty terms) in the model.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Granzyme B levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 35</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The pGrzB hazard ratio (per 10 percentage point increase) and the associated 95% confidence interval will be estimated using a Cox PH model. Whether pGrzB measurements vary by presence of grade 3+ adverse events (AEs) will be assessed using permutation independent sample t-tests. Descriptive statistics include the pGrzB mean, standard deviations and ranges within AE or patient characteristics.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Granzyme B level variations by presence of grade 3 or higher adverse events (AE), characterized using National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) severity grade</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>These differences will be assessed using permutation independent sample t-tests. For an AE observed in 15 (50%) of the patients and two-sided statistical significance threshold = 0.05, this test has 80% power to detect a 1.0 standard difference in mean pGrzB. 95% confidence limits for the difference in mean pGrzB will also be provided. Descriptive statistics include the pGrzB mean, standard deviations and ranges within AE or patient characteristics.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of cluster of differentiation (CD)8+ T cells expressing granzyme B</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 35</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in granzyme B levels after sorafenib tosylate treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 35 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The hypotheses of immediate (HI) and sustained improvement (HS) of immune function will be tested using a fixed-sequence procedure. Each hypothesis uses a permutation paired t-test with an upper 1-sided 0.05 significance threshold. HI considers a pGrzB increase between days 0 &amp; ~28-35. If the HI test finds no short-term pGrzB improvement, the HS test will not be done. If HI indicates a short-time pGrzB improvement, HS considers a pGrzB increase between days 0 and 24 weeks (± 1 week). If both tests indicate improvements it will be concluded improved &amp; sustained pGrzB response follows sorafenib.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Adult Primary Hepatocellular Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Adult Primary Undifferentiated Hepatocellular Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Advanced Adult Primary Liver Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Childhood Hepatocellular Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Localized Unresectable Adult Primary Liver Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Primary Liver Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Childhood Liver Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage C Adult Primary Liver Cancer (BCLC)</condition>
  <condition>Stage D Adult Primary Liver Cancer (BCLC)</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Childhood Liver Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Childhood Liver Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (sorafenib tosylate)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive sorafenib tosylate PO BID. Treatment continues in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>sorafenib tosylate</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (sorafenib tosylate)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BAY 43-9006</other_name>
    <other_name>BAY 43-9006 Tosylate Salt</other_name>
    <other_name>BAY 54-9085</other_name>
    <other_name>Nexavar</other_name>
    <other_name>SFN</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (sorafenib tosylate)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject or legal representative must understand the investigational nature of this
             study and sign an Independent Ethics Committee/Institutional Review Board approved
             written informed consent form prior to receiving any study related procedure

          -  Outpatients with histologically/cytologically documented or radiographically
             diagnosed unresectable hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) who are candidates for systemic
             therapy and for whom a decision to treat with sorafenib has been made; radiographic
             diagnosis needs typical findings of HCC by a radiographic method, i.e. on
             multi-dimensional dynamic computed tomography (CT), CT hepatic arteriography
             (CTHA)/CT arterial portography (CTAP) or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)

          -  Patients must have a life expectancy of at least 8 weeks

          -  Patients must not have any evidence of bleeding diathesis or active gastrointestinal
             bleeding

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements

          -  Pregnant or nursing female subjects

          -  Unwilling or unable to follow protocol requirements

          -  Any condition which in the investigator's opinion deems the subject an unsuitable
             candidate to receive study drug

          -  Patients who have had prior anti-angiogenic therapy, including but not limited to
             sorafenib, brivanib, bevacizumab, or sunitinib, as this may confound the baseline
             values; prior treatment with liver directed, ablative or surgical therapies will be
             permitted as long as there is documented progression justifying the need for starting
             sorafenib therapy

          -  No known contraindications to anti-angiogenics such as severe coronary artery
             disease, recent myocardial infarction or stroke within 6 months, bleeding peptic
             ulcer or varices within last 3 months, and any other major illness that may
             jeopardize study treatment or follow up
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Renuka Iyer</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14263</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Roswell Park</last_name>
      <phone>877-275-7724</phone>
      <email>ASKRPCI@roswellpark.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Renuka V. Iyer</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 24, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Sorafenib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
