<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="126186">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02065674</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ABROAGUS01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02065674</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Therapeutic Efficacy of &quot;Abroma Agusta&quot; in HbA1c % in NIDDM</brief_title>
  <acronym>ABOMNIDDM</acronym>
  <official_title>Therapeutic Efficacy of Homoeopathic Mother Tincture of &quot;Abroma Agusta&quot; in Changing the Level of Glycated Hb (HbA1c %) in Diabetes Mellitus Type II (NIDDM</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fr Muller Homoeopathic Medical College</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fr Muller Homoeopathic Medical College</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>India: Indian Council of Medical Research</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objective:  To ascertain whether homoeopathic medicine ABROMA AUGUSTA has a clinical role in
      changing the Glycated Hb Level in Diabetes mellitus Type II.

      Introduction:

      Diabetes mellitus is classed as a metabolism disorder. It is often simply referred to as
      diabetes—is a group of metabolic diseases in which a person has high blood sugar, either
      because the body does not produce enough insulin, or because cells do not respond to the
      insulin that is produced.

      Blood sugar level is not only the criteria to diagnose the Dabeties Mellitus ,  Glycated
      hemoglobin (glycosylated hemoglobin, hemoglobin A1c, HbA1c, A1C, or Hb1; sometimes also
      HbA1c) is a form of hemoglobin used primarily to identify the average  plasma glucose
      concentration over prolonged periods of time.

      Diabetes is the single most important metabolic disease which can affect nearly every organ
      system in the body. According to the World Health Organization estimates, India had 32
      million diabetic subjects in the year 2000 and this number would increase to 80 million by
      the year 2030 (1). The 2010 American Diabetes Association Standards of Medical Care in
      Diabetes added the A1c ≥ 6.5% as another criterion for the diagnosis of diabetes.It is
      noticed that the blood sugar(HbA1c) is not controlled by other system of medicine, the
      patients come for Homoeopathic treatment and afc.ter homoeopathic treatment, it is seen that
      there is a remarkable improvements on HbA1c along with the general improvement of health
      like tiredness, lethargy numbness, polyurea, polydypsia and polyphagia et. But there is no
      scientific validation for that. So this study is conducted for achieving the optimal
      ugglycosuria, homoeopathic hypoglycemics is investigated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      According to recent survey reports about 5% of the total world population is suffering from
      Diabetes Mellitus. The incidence rate is also reasonably high in India. Currently about 20%
      of Indian Population is at High risk to develop Diabetes Mellitus in future i.e. they are
      having abnormal glucose Tolerance test. Studies have revealed that diabetic women suffer
      more than men. A male who is diabetic has double the chances of a heart failure. In case of
      women it grows to almost 5 times and it is 8 times more if the patient is a young female.

      Homeopathic treatment: When we talk about diseases like diabetes, we talk in terms of
      management rather than cure. Homoeopathy can be a major player in the management of
      Diabetes. Timely-administered homoeopathy medicines not only assist in maintaining levels of
      sugar, protein and fat metabolism, but also helps in preventing further progress and hence
      complications of the disease. The precipitating factors of diabetes like BP, Obesity etc.
      can be helped by homoeopathic medication. The complications of Diabetes also can be helped
      tremendously with homoeopathy. If homoeopathic treatment is opted earlier far less number of
      cases would go to the stage of Amputation etc. Even the cases of Non Healing Diabetic Ulcers
      have been cured with homoeopathy in Clinic. We have been able to help the patients of long
      standing Diabetes to whom their Anti-diabetic medicines stopped affecting anymore and needed
      the change in group of medication with persistent symptoms and threatening complications,
      after the proper Constitutional Homoeopathic medicines, the same medicines started affecting
      them once again with no persistence of symptoms and over all relief and comfort in their
      quality of life. Homoeopathy does help the person in regaining his health.There are
      different groups of medicines. As homoeopathic treatment is a holistic approach so it varies
      according to the individuals. Diabetic remedies can be - Acet-Ac, Adren, Arg-M, Arg-N, Ars,
      Ars-I,  Aur,  Aur-M,  Bar-C,  Bov, Calc, Calc-P, Carc,  Chel,  Chim, Chin,  Fl-Ac, Helon,
      Hep,  Iod,   Kali-P,  Lach,  Lyc,  Med,  Nat-M,  Nat-P,Nat-S, Nit-Ac,  Nux-V, Op,  Petr,
      Ph-Ac,  Phos, Plb, Sep, Sil, Sulph, Sul-Ac, Syzyg,  Tarent, Ter,  Thuj, 3 Uran-N,

      Specifics: Abroma Augusta, Cephalandra indica, Syzygium jambolanum, Gymnama
      sylvestre,Chimaphilla.

      Above all the medicines are having very good result in controlling blood glucose levels.
      When they have very good therapeutic value so we would like to investigate the effect on
      HbA1c. this is a pilot study.

      Abroma augusta (Olat Kambal, Devil's Cotton).The plant of Abroma augusta grows wild
      throughout the hotter part of India. In ancient times, it was used therapeutically as an
      emmenagogue in menstrual disorders. Late Dr. D.N.Roy of Calcutta proved this drug. A
      tincture of the drug is prepared from its leaves according to class III of American
      Homeopathic Pharmacopoeia. It is used in diabetes insipidus with very gratifying results.
      Clinically it is indicated in Diabetes, albuminuria, enuresis, debility, vertigo,
      sleeplessness, carbuncle, amenorrhoea and dysmenorrhoea. In brief, it has its action on all
      the systems of human body, which are similar to Camphor, Acid-phos, Uranium nitricum,
      Syzygium and Lactic acid but it is an excellent remedy for amenorrhoea, dysmenorrhoea and
      diabetes. It is indicated in irregular catamenia where there is tendency to appear before
      proper time and lasts for a short or for a long period.

      Several cases of Diabetes Mellitus even with complications - diabetic foot treated with
      homoeopathic medicines and seen very good results clinically.

      Potency used - mother tincure, 6c, 12c, 30 etc in frequent interval.

      Materials and methods:

      Research plan:

      Sampling Details: Patients attending the OPD of Fr Muller Homoeopathic Medical College
      Hospital, St Antonyn's Hospital, Prasanth Nivas Hospital, and NMPT's Mobile centre will be
      taken up for study. This study will be done on 30 diagnosed cases with high HbA1c level. But
      approximately 40-50 patients will be screened to ensure enrollment of 30 patients in trial.

      Inclusion Criteria     Exclusion Criteria Age 30 Years above  Patient with major
      complications like diabetic retinopathy and cardiomyopathy.

      Both Sexes NIDDM IDDM FBS - 110-300mg/dl HbA1c above ≤ 6.5   HbA1c above 11%

      Research protocol:

      Sampling: purposive sampling will be followed in this study. Patients who belong to the
      above category of inclusions criteria will be taken up and those will be willing to take
      homoeopathic medicines for T2DM.

      Screening:  the patients having the Random Blood Suger (RBS) - 150mg/dl above will be
      sending for the following tests listed below:

      Fasting (FBS) - above 111mg/dl Post Prandial blood Suger (PPBS) -150mg/dl above. HbA1c% -
      above 6.5 Those will fulfill the above criteria, will be included in this study. Cases will
      be recorded in a prescribed format which is given in Anexure 4 along with patients consent
      form and patient's information sheet.

      Medicines: Abroma Augusta Q (Mother tincture form) Dose: 30 drops TDS Visits:   Follow up -
      every 15 days FBS &amp; PPBS - Monthly HbA1c% - end of 3 months Each patient will be treated
      minimum 3 months with Abroma Augusta Ɵ and FBS, and PPBS will be checked in every month and
      HbA1c once in 3 months as the life span of RBC is 120 days.

      .Research Methodology &amp; statistics:

      Criteria for deciding the efficacy of Homoeopathic drugs will be based on parameters follow:

        1. . Change FBS, and PPBS

        2. Change in HbA1c level

      Statistical analysis:

      Data from the sample will be collected and it will be analysed based on Paired't' test to
      determine the efficacy of homoeopathic medicines.

      Null Hypothesis: No Significant variation in HbA1c before and after treatment. Alternate
      Hypothesis:  Significant Variation in HbA1c before and after treatment.

      Tabulation will be done based on SPS package.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the level of Glycated Hb (HbA1c %) in Diabetes Mellitus Type II (NIDDM</measure>
    <time_frame>Each patient will be treated minimum 3 months with Abroma Augusta Ɵ and FBS, and PPBS will be checked in every month and HbA1c once in 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>evaluation of glycated haemoglobin level</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Type II Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Abroma Augusta Q</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Abroma Augusta Q 30 drops in 1 cup of water 3 times daily for 3 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Abroma Augusta Q (mother tincture)</intervention_name>
    <description>30 drops in 1 cup of water three times a day for 3 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Abroma Augusta Q</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Abroma Augustum,</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Inclusion Criteria Age 30 Years above Both Sexes NIDDM FBS - 110-300mg/dl HbA1c above ≤
        6.5

        -

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient with major complications like diabetic retinopathy and cardiomyopathy. IDDM
             HbA1c above 11%
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>dr rita chakraborty, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fr Muller Homoeopathic Medical College</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>,Father Muller Homoeopathic Medical College, Prasanth Nivas Ashram Nmpt Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mangalore</city>
        <state>Karnataka</state>
        <zip>575002</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 15, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 13, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Fr Muller Homoeopathic Medical College</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>dr rita chakraborty</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PROFESSOR</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>type II Diabetes mellitus</keyword>
  <keyword>FBS</keyword>
  <keyword>PPBS</keyword>
  <keyword>HbA1c%</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
