<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="127710">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01853475</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MMV_OZ439_13_002</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-000983-28</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01853475</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Healthy Volunteer Study of the Pharmacokinetics of Oral Piperaquine With OZ439 + TPGS Formulation in the Fasted State</brief_title>
  <official_title>Open Label, Parallel Group Study to Investigate the Pharmacokinetics Following Oral Co-administration of Piperaquine Phosphate Tablets With a Prototype OZ439 + TPGS Formulation in the Fasted State in Healthy Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medicines for Malaria Venture</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Richmond Pharmacology Limited</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medicines for Malaria Venture</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Piperaquine tablets (coated) + OZ439 granules + TPGS granules will be co-administered in
      Phase IIb (adults).  However, safety data (for OZ439 plus piperaquine) and efficacy data
      (for OZ439) were obtained using piperaquine tablets plus OZ439 as Powder in Bottle with
      milk. Piperaquine has not yet been administered together with TPGS. Co-administration of
      piperaquine plus OZ439 as Powder in Bottle with milk results in an increase in OZ439
      exposure (current estimate ~ 70% due to a small drug drug interaction).

      This study investigates the exposure of piperaquine and OZ439 when co-administered as
      piperaquine phosphate tablets and OZ439 + TPGS prototype (a formulation close to that of
      Phase IIb, but not identical), in order to select the appropriate doses for Phase IIb. The
      reference treatment is piperaquine phosphate tablets + OZ439 Powder in Bottle + full fat
      milk
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives:

        1. To evaluate the piperaquine and OZ439 pharmacokinetics when administered as a
           combination of piperaquine phosphate tablets with OZ439 / TPGS formulation in the
           fasted state

        2. To evaluate the piperaquine and OZ439 pharmacokinetics of a reference free combination
           formulation: piperaquine phosphate tablets with OZ439 powder in bottle given with full
           fat milk

        3. To determine safety and tolerability of OZ439 and piperaquine phosphate when
           co-administered.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>maximum concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96 and 168 hours post-dose and on Days 11, 15, 29 and 43</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration time curve from time zero to the time of the time of last measurable concentration post-dose</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96 and 168 hours post-dose and on Days 11, 15, 29 and 43</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration time curve from time zero to infinity</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96 and 168 hours post-dose and on Days 11, 15, 29 and 43</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to reach maximum plasma concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96 and 168 hours post-dose and on Days 11, 15, 29 and 43</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the terminal elimination half-life</measure>
    <time_frame>up to Day 43 post-dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Terminal elimination rate constant</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96 and 168 hours post-dose and on Days 11, 15, 29 and 43</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Piperaquine phosphate tablets 1440mg and OZ439+TPGS prototype formulation 800mg co-administered as a single oral dose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Piperaquine phosphate tablets 960mg and OZ439+TPGS prototype formulation 800mg co-administered as a single oral dose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Piperaquine phosphate tablets 1440mg and OZ439 Powder in Bottle aqueous solution 800mg co-administered as a single dose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Piperaquine phosphate tablets 960mg</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Piperaquine phosphate tablets 1440mg</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment C</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>OZ439+TPGS prototype formulation 800mg</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>OZ439 Powder in Bottle Aqueous Solution 800mg</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment C</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Healthy male/female of any race aged 18-55 years at screening

          2. Body Mass Index 18-30kg/m2; body weight &gt;50kg but no more than 100kg at screening

          3. Females with negative pregnancy test at screening and admission, non-lactating and of
             non-child bearing potential confirmed by:

               -  natural (spontaneous) post-menopause (amenorrheic for 12 months without an
                  alternative medical cause with a screening FSH level &gt;25IU/L)

               -  irreversible surgical sterilisation by bilateral oophorectomy or bilateral
                  salpingectomy but not tubal ligation (with or without hysterectomy) at least six
                  months ago

          4. Agree to use acceptable methods of contraception:

               -  Condom and occlusive cap (diaphragm or cervical/vault caps) with spermicidal
                  foam/gel/film/cream/suppository;

               -  Surgical sterilisation (vasectomy with documentation of azoospermia) and a
                  barrier method {condom or occlusive cap used with spermicidal
                  foam/gel/film/cream/suppository};

               -  female partner uses oral contraceptives (combination oestrogen/progesterone
                  pills), injectable progesterone or subdermal implants and a barrier method
                  {condom or occlusive cap used with spermicidal foam/gel/film/cream/suppository};

               -  female partner uses medically prescribed topically-applied transdermal
                  contraceptive patch and a barrier method used with spermicidal
                  foam/gel/film/cream/suppository};

               -  female partner has undergone documented tubal ligation (female sterilisation).
                  In addition, a barrier method used with spermicidal
                  foam/gel/film/cream/suppository};

               -  female partner has undergone documented placement of an Intrauterine Device or
                  Intrauterine System and the use of a barrier method used with spermicidal
                  foam/gel/film/cream/suppository};

               -  True abstinence: When this is in line with the preferred and usual lifestyle of
                  the subject. [Periodic abstinence (e.g., calendar, ovulation, symptothermal,
                  postovulation methods) and withdrawal are not acceptable methods of
                  contraception]. Abstinent subjects have to agree use one of the above-mentioned
                  contraceptive methods, if they start sexual relationships during the study and
                  for up to 90 days after dose of study drug.

          5. Should not donate egg and sperm from the time of administration of treatment or study
             medication until 3 months following dose of study medication

          6. Must be capable of understanding and complying with the requirements of the protocol
             and must have signed the informed consent form prior to undergoing any study-related
             procedures

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Male subjects with a female partner(s) who is (are) pregnant or lactating from the
             time of the administration of study medication

          2. Has a clinically significant disease or any condition or disease that might affect
             drug absorption, distribution or excretion, e.g. gastrectomy, diarrhoea.

          3. History of allergic reactions to artemisinin-based compounds, 4-aminoquinolines such
             as piperaquine or any other clinically relevant allergy to drugs or food.

          4. Any clinically relevant history of cow's milk intolerance/allergy.

          5. Any clinically significant abnormal laboratory, vital signs or other safety findings
             as determined by medical history, physical examination or other evaluations conducted
             at screening or on admission. Exception is PR, QTcB, QTcF, cardiac rhythm, liver
             function tests and haemoglobin that must be within the normal reference range at
             screening and on admission.

          6. History or current evidence of any clinically relevant cardiovascular, pulmonary,
             hepatic, renal, gastrointestinal (excluding appendectomy and cholecystectomy),
             haematological, endocrinological, immunological, metabolic, neurological,
             oncological, psychiatric, urological or other disease, or current infection

          7. History of post-antibiotic colitis

          8. Electrocardiogram abnormalities in the standard 12-lead (at screening) and/or 24-hour
             5 lead Holter (at screening) which in the opinion of the Investigator is clinically
             relevant or will interfere with the analysis

          9. A history of clinically significant electrocardiogram abnormalities, or any of the
             following abnormalities at screening or admission:

               -  PR &gt;200 msec

               -  QRS complex &gt;120 msec

               -  QTcB or QTcF &gt;450 msec or shortened QTcB or QTcF less than 340 msec for males
                  and females or family history of long QT syndrome or sudden death

               -  Any degree of heart block (such as first, second or third degree
                  atrioventricular block, incomplete, full or intermittent bundle branch block)

               -  Abnormal T wave morphology / prominent U waves

               -  Potassium levels out of the normal range at  screening and prior to dosing

         10. Positive results in any of the serology tests for Hepatitis B Surface Antigen, anti
             Hepatitis core antibody, Hepatitis C antibodies, and Human Immunodeficiency Virus 1
             and 2 antibodies

         11. Confirmed positive results from urine drug screen (amphetamines, benzodiazepines,
             cocaine, cannabinoids, opiates, barbiturates, and methadone) or from the alcohol
             breath test at screening and admission

         12. History or clinical evidence of alcohol abuse, or any recreational drug abuse within
             the 2 years prior to screening

         13. Mentally handicapped

         14. Participation in a drug trial within 90 days prior to drug administration

         15. Use of ANY prescription or over the counter medications, within 3 weeks of study drug
             administration, or vitamins or herbal supplements within 2 week of administration of
             the drug administration of study drug (or at least 5 half-lives of the compound
             whichever period is the longer), unless prior approval is granted by both the
             Investigator and Sponsor. Excluded from this list is intermittent use of paracetamol
             at up to 2g/day.

         16. Use moderate or strong inhibitors and/or inducers of cytochrome CYP450 within 4 weeks
             prior to the planned drug administration (or at least 5 half-lives of the compound
             whichever period is the longer)

         17. Subjects have veins unsuitable for intravenous puncture or cannulation on either arm
             (e.g. veins that are difficult to locate, access or puncture veins with a tendency to
             rupture during or after puncture)

         18. Blood liver function tests not in the normal range at screening and on admission

         19. Haemoglobin is less than the lower limit of the reference range at screening and on
             admission.

         20. Donation of more than 500mL blood within 90 days prior to drug administration

         21. Subjects must be non-smokers for at least 3 months prior to screening Note: &quot;Tobacco
             use&quot; includes smoking and the use of snuff and chewing tobacco, and other nicotine or
             nicotine containing products

         22. Any consumption of grapefruit, Seville oranges, wild grapes, black mulberries,
             pomegranates in the form of fruit juice, marmalade or as a raw fruit within 7 days
             prior to dosing of study drug and throughout the study.  Any circumstances or
             conditions, which, in the opinion of the investigator may affect full participation
             in the trial or compliance with the protocol

         23. Legal incapacity or limited legal capacity at screening

         24. Vegetarians, vegans or any dietary restrictions conflicting with the study
             standardised menus
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ulrike Lorch, MD FRCA FFPM</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Richmond Pharmacology Limited</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Richmond Pharmacology Limited</name>
      <address>
        <city>Croyden</city>
        <state>London</state>
        <zip>CR7 7YE</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 25, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 10, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <keyword>safety</keyword>
  <keyword>tolerability</keyword>
  <keyword>bioavailability</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Piperaquine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
