<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="161387">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01826695</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DF0040UG</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01826695</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neurodynamic Intervention in Fibromyalgia</brief_title>
  <acronym>FM</acronym>
  <official_title>Study of the Effectiveness of a Neurodynamic Intervention in Women With Fibromyalgia.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidad de Granada</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidad de Granada</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Spain: Comité Ético de Investigación Clínica</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Fibromyalgia is a chronic illness characterised by persistent,widespread muscle pain with
      generalised hyperalgesia and allodynia. It can be accompanied by other concomitant symptoms
      like fatigue, sleep disturbances, musculoskeletal disorders, distress and psychological
      disorders. This condition is very prevalent. It has been reported to be about 2-5% of the
      general global population.

      Fibromyalgia have been reported to have neurodynamic disorders. The purpose of this
      prospective study was to examine the combined effects of soft tissue mobilization and nerve
      slider neurodynamic technique on pain and pressure sensitivity in women with fibromyalgia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Fibromyalgia affects women nine times more than men.The pathophysiology of fibromyalgia is
      being studied nowadays in order to understand the mechanisms implicated in it.

      The treatment propose in this study is a neurodynamic intervention. Neurodynamics is the
      term used to describe the integration of the morphology, biomechanics and physiology of the
      nervous system.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Nervous assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes from baseline to postintervention measured with neurodynamic tests This is to test upper extremities. It moves most of the nerves between the neck and hand, including the median nerve, radial and ulnar, brachial plexus, spinal nerves and cervical nerve roots.
The patient is placed supine position. It is measured with a goniometer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Manual dexterity</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes from baseline to postintervention in dexterity. This is assessed using the Purdue Pegboard Test.
The Purdue pegboard test is a timed physical test used to measure manual dexterity. Test subjects are asked to place small pins into holes in the pegboard using a specific hand and following a specific process.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Grip strength</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes from baseline to postintervention in grip strength. This is measured using a Jamar dynamometer with a standard protocol allowing three attempts on each side. During each measurement, patients were sitting with their shoulder adducted and elbow flexed to 90°. The maximum value achieved from all six attempts was used in analyses.
Kg/cm2</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pressure pain measure</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in pain pressure threshold from baseline to 8-weeks intervention. This is going to be measured in three points in upper extremities using the pressure algometer. All assessments were made by the same investigator. All the subjects were trained to familiarize the subjects with the pressure algometry procedure before the measures in an anatomical site different from the chosen sites for this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety and depression</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes from baseline to postintervention in anxiety and depression in the participants. Participants completed the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale in order to assess these parameters.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Fibromyalgia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>35 women are recruited in order to the inclusion criteria for the study. Placebo controlled. They received only standard treatment without neurodynamic intervention. They are diagnosed with Fibromyalgia attending to the Fibromyalgia Association of Granada. The study include subjects who can complete the assessment battery of tests at the beginning and end.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neurodynamic technique group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>35 women are recruited, diagnosed with Fibromyalgia attending to the Fibromyalgia Association of Granada. The study include subjects who can complete the assessment battery of tests at the beginning and at the end.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neurodynamic technique group</intervention_name>
    <description>Neurodynamic techniques are used in order to move most of the nerves between the neck and hand, including the median nerve, radial and ulnar, brachial plexus, spinal nerves and cervical nerve roots.
The patient is placed supine position. The treatment will be carry out 3 times per week during 8 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Neurodynamic technique group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Neurodynamic sliding technique</other_name>
    <other_name>Nerve mobilization</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo group</intervention_name>
    <description>Women in this group realized standard treatment in the Fibromyalgia Association without neurodynamic techniques.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Standard treatment.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women diagnosed with Fibromyalgia attending to the Fibromyalgia Association of
             Granada.

          -  Women who can complete the assessment battery of tests at the beginning and at the
             end of the study

          -  Female sex.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Male sex.

          -  Auditive and visual disturbances.

          -  Cognitive problems.

          -  Psychiatric pathology.

          -  Traumatic pathology of the hand.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marie Carmen Valenza, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>958 248035</phone>
    <email>cvalenza@ugr.es</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Faculty of Health Sciences. University of Granada.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Granada.</city>
        <state>Granada</state>
        <zip>18071</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marie Carmen Valenza, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>958 248035</phone>
      <email>cvalenza@ugr.es</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marie Carmen Valenza, PT, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 17, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 29, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidad de Granada</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marie Carmen Valenza</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Fibromyalgia, neurodynamic, dexterity</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fibromyalgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myofascial Pain Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
