<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="95830">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01985256</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Tg 511-13-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01985256</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of a Retroviral Replicating Vector Given Intravenously to Patients Undergoing Surgery for Recurrent Brain Tumor</brief_title>
  <official_title>A P1 Ascending Dose Trial of the Safety and Tolerability of Toca 511, a Retroviral Replicating Vector, Administered Intravenously Prior to, and Intracranially at the Time of, Subsequent Resection for Recurrent HGG &amp; Followed by Treatment With Extended-Release 5-FC</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tocagen Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tocagen Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multicenter study evaluating the safety and tolerability of Toca 511 administered
      intravenously to patients with recurrent or progressive Grade III or Grade IV Gliomas who
      have elected to undergo surgical removal of their tumor.  Patients will receive ½ of the
      Toca 511 intravenously, followed approximately 11 days later by removal of the tumor and
      injection of the remaining ½ of the Toca 511 into the resection cavity.  The tumor specimen
      will be tested for the presence of Toca 511.  Approximately 4 weeks later, the patient will
      take an oral 10-day course of Toca FC, an antifungal antibiotic. These 10-day courses of
      Toca FC will be repeated approximately every 5 weeks until study completion.  MRI scans will
      be performed approximately every 2 months. One subject each will be evaluated at 3 dose
      levels of Toca 511. Three subjects each will be evaluated in the 4th and 5th dosing cohorts.
      These cohorts will evaluate multiday intravenous administration of Toca 511: 3 consecutive
      days for the 4th cohort and 5 consecutive days for the 5th cohort. The dose of Toca 511 a
      patient receives will depend upon the number of previous study participants and how well
      they have tolerated the study drugs. All patients enrolled in this study will be encouraged
      to participate in a continuation protocol that enables additional 5-FC administration and
      the collection of long-term safety and response data.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Limiting Toxicities</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Excluding nausea, vomiting, weakness, and fatigue, any Grade 3 or higher non-hematologic toxicity or any Grade 4 or higher hematologic toxicity, felt to be related to Toca 511 or the Toca 511/5-FC combination.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PFS-6</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The percentage of subjects who have not progressed or died at 6 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Glioblastoma Multiforme</condition>
  <condition>Anaplastic Astrocytoma</condition>
  <condition>Anaplastic Oligodendroglioma</condition>
  <condition>Anaplastic Oligoastrocytoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Toca 511 vector</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Toca 511 a retroviral replicating vector expressing the cytosine deaminase enzyme</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Toca 511</intervention_name>
    <description>All subjects will receive Toca 511, a retroviral replicating vector that expresses the cytosine deaminase (CD) gene, intravenously and then intracranially. CD converts the antibiotic 5-fluorocytosine (5-FC) to the anti-cancer drug 5-fluorouracil (5-FU) in cells that have been infected by the Toca 511 vector. Beginning approximately 4 weeks after second administration of Toca 511, subjects will take an 10-day course of oral 5-FC. These 10-day courses of 5-FC are repeated every 5 weeks for the duration of the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Toca 511 vector</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>vocimagene amiretrorepvec</other_name>
    <other_name>retroviral replicating vector</other_name>
    <other_name>5-FC, flucytosine, 5-fluorocytosine</other_name>
    <other_name>Toca FC</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Has the subject given written informed consent?

          2. Is the subject between 18 years old and 80 years old inclusive?

          3. Has the subject undergone at least one prior surgical gross-total or subtotal tumor
             resection with histologic confirmation of Grade III or IV glioma and a course of
             postoperative radiation therapy with concurrent temozolomide?

          4. Does the subject have a single, enhancing tumor recurrence/progression that is ≤ 8 cm
             in its greatest dimension?

          5. Based on the pre-operative evaluation, is the tumor recurrence/progression a
             candidate for ≥ 80% resection?

          6. Has the subject elected not to undergo treatment with the Gliadel® wafer?

          7. Does the subject have a Karnofsky performance status ≥ 70?

          8. Does the subject have an absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1500/mm3?

          9. Does the subject have an absolute lymphocyte count ≥ 500/mm3?

         10. Does the subject have a platelet count ≥ 100,000/mm3?

         11. Does the subject have a Hgb ≥ 10 g/dL?

         12. Does the subject have a coagulation profile that would allow for the safe performance
             of surgery under general anesthesia?

         13. Does the subject have an estimated glomerular filtration rate of at least 50 mL/min
             (inclusive) by the Cockcroft-Gault formula?

         14. Does the subject have an ALT/AST &lt; 3 times the upper limit of the laboratory
             reference range and total bilirubin &lt; 1.5 mg/dL?

         15. If the subject is a female of childbearing potential, has she had a negative serum
             pregnancy test within the past 21 days?

         16. Is the subject willing to use condoms for contraception for 6 months after receiving
             Toca 511 or until there is no evidence of the virus in his/her blood, whichever is
             longer. If the subject is a fertile female, is she willing to use contraception for
             at least 12 months?

         17. Is the subject willing and able to abide by the protocol?

         18. Does the subject have adequate venous access?

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Has the subject received cytotoxic chemotherapy within the past 3 weeks (6 weeks for
             nitrosoureas) of the planned date of vector injection?

          2. Does the subject have, or has the subject had, within the past 4 weeks any infection
             requiring antibiotic, antifungal or antiviral therapy?

          3. Has the subject received Avastin® (bevacizumab) for this recurrence/progression, or
             within the 4 weeks prior to planned Visit 1?

          4. Does the subject require corticosteroids prior to surgery to control cerebral edema?

          5. Does the subject have any bleeding diathesis, or must the subject take any
             anticoagulants, or antiplatelet agents, including NSAIDs that cannot be stopped for
             surgery?

          6. Does the subject have a history of allergy or intolerance to flucytosine?

          7. Is the subject HIV positive?

          8. Does the subject have any gastrointestinal disease that would prevent him or her from
             being able to ingest or absorb flucytosine?

          9. Has the subject received any investigational treatment within the past 30 days?

         10. Is the subject breast feeding?
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Daniel Pertschuk, MD</last_name>
    <phone>858-412-8409</phone>
    <email>dpertschuk@tocagen.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tammy Boyce, MEd</last_name>
    <phone>858-412-8416</phone>
    <email>tboyce@tocagen.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Henry Ford Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John Gaggin, RN, BSN</last_name>
      <phone>313-916-3731</phone>
      <email>jgaggin1@hfhs.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Tiffany Pearce</last_name>
      <phone>313-916-1784</phone>
      <email>tpearce1@hfhs.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steven N Kalkanis, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 8, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Astrocytoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oligodendroglioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Flucytosine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
