<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="111037">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02009865</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OM-EPA-011</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>EVOLVE II</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02009865</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Epanova® for Lowering Very High Triglycerides II (EVOLVE II)</brief_title>
  <acronym>EVOLVE II</acronym>
  <official_title>A 12-Week, Randomized, Double-Blind, Olive Oil-Controlled Phase 3 Study to Assess the Efficacy and Safety of EPANOVA™ in Subjects With Severe Hypertriglyceridemia (EVOLVE II)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Omthera Pharmaceuticals, Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Omthera Pharmaceuticals, Inc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a double-blind, randomized, olive oil-controlled study to investigate the efficacy
      and safety of Epanova as an adjunct therapy to diet for reduction of TG levels in subjects
      with severe hypertriglyceridemia. The study consists of an approximately 8-week screening
      period that includes a diet and lifestyle stabilization and washout period and a 12-week
      treatment period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      [During the screening period and treatment period, all visits are to be within ±3 days of
      the scheduled time.]

      Screening Period:

      Visit 1 will occur at Week -8 for subjects requiring washout and/or statin,
      cholesterol-absorption inhibitor (CAI), or statin-CAI stabilization. This includes subjects
      who:

        -  Were previously on omega-3 drugs/supplements;

        -  Require adjustment to or addition of permitted statins, CAI, or statin-CAI combination;

        -  Have not been on a permitted stable dose of statin, CAI, or statin-CAI combination for
           at least 4 weeks prior to Visit 1; and/or

        -  Need to washout of bile acid sequestrants, fibrates, niacin, and other supplements
           known to alter lipid metabolism.

      For these subjects who require washout and/or statin, CAI, or statin-CAI stabilization, at
      Visit 1 (Week -8) screening procedures will be performed. Subjects will return at Visit 1a
      (Week -2) for their first qualifying lipid measurement.

      For subjects not requiring washout, Visit 1 will occur at Week -2. All screening procedures
      will be performed at this visit including the first qualifying lipid measurement.

      At Visit 2 (Week -1), all subjects will return for their second lipid qualifying
      measurement. If at Visit 2 the subject does not have an average TG ≥500 mg/dL (6 mmol/L) and
      &lt;2500 mg/dL (28 mmol/L), the TG measurement may be repeated one additional time after Visit
      2 (Visit 2a). The subject's qualifying measurement would be the average of Visit 1 or 1a +
      Visit 2 + Visit 2a (repeat measurement).

      To be eligible for randomization, the subject must have a qualifying TG ≥500 mg/dL (6
      mmol/L) and &lt;2500 mg/dL (28 mmol/L). Of the total number of subjects, approximately 50% will
      have a qualifying TG &gt;885 mg/dL (10 mmol/L) and &lt;2500 mg/dL (28 mmol/L). Once approximately
      50% of the total subjects has been reached for each TG group, enrollment of subjects with
      that specific TG criterion will stop. Subjects will be equally allocated to each treatment
      group.

      [At the screening visit, all subjects will receive counseling regarding the National
      Cholesterol Education Program (NCEP) Therapeutic Lifestyle Changes (TLC) diet and will
      receive basic instructions on how to follow this diet. See Appendix C.]

      Treatment Period:

      At Visit 3 (Week 0), approximately 116 subjects will be randomized in a 1:1 ratio to receive
      daily olive oil 2 g or Epanova 2 g. Subjects will be stratified by lipid-altering drugs to
      ensure a balanced allocation of subjects who are users and non-users of the following
      permitted lipid-altering drugs in each treatment group: statin, CAI, or statin-CAI
      combination. During the treatment period, subjects will return to the site at Visit 4 (Week
      6), Visit 5 (Week 10), and Visit 6 (Week 12) for efficacy and safety evaluations.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Triglyceride (TG)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the efficacy of Epanova 2 g daily compared to olive oil 2 g daily for 12 weeks in lowering serum TG levels in subjects with severe hypertriglyceridemia (TG levels ≥500 mg/dL [6 mMol/L] and &lt;2500 mg/dL [28 mMol/L]).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TG lowering in subgroup of subjects with high baseline levels</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the effect of Epanova 2 g daily compared to olive oil 2 g daily for 12 weeks in lowering serum TG levels in subjects with at least 1 qualifying TG &gt;885 mg/dL (10 mMol/L) and &lt;2500 mg/dL (28 mMol/L).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TG lowering in subgroup of subjects with Fredrickson Type V hyperlipidemia</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the effects of Epanova 2 g daily compared to olive oil 2 g daily for 12 weeks in lowering TG levels in subjects with Fredrickson Type V hyperlipidemia (TG/VLDL-C ≥6).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Non-high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (non-HDL-C)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The percent change in non-HDL-C from baseline to Week 12 endpoint.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>High-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The percent change in HDL-C from baseline to Week 12 endpoint.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">104</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertriglyceridemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Epanova 2 g/day</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm 1</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Olive Oil 2 g/day</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm 2</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Epanova</intervention_name>
    <description>Epanova will be provided in 1 g polyacrylate-coated soft gel capsules. Two capsules will be taken once per day, without regard to meals, for 12 weeks. At clinic visits, study drug will be administered at the clinic after fasting blood draws are complete.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Epanova 2 g/day</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>omega-3 free fatty acids</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Olive Oil</intervention_name>
    <description>Olive oil will be provided in 1 g polyacrylate-coated soft gel capsules. Two capsules will be taken once per day, without regard to meals, for 12 weeks. At clinic visits, study drug will be administered at the clinic after fasting blood draws are complete.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Olive Oil 2 g/day</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>placebo comparator</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Understanding of the study procedures, willingness to adhere to the study schedule,
             and agreement to participate in the study by giving written informed consent prior to
             screening;

          2. Willing to use an appropriate and effective method of contraception;

          3. Qualifying (average of Visit 1 or 1a + Visit 2 + Visit 2a [repeat measurement]) serum
             TG ≥500 mg/dL (6 mMol/L) and &lt;2500 mg/dL (28 mMol/L);

          4. Body mass index ≥20 kg/m2;

          5. Untreated dyslipidemia or dyslipidemia treated with a statin, CAI, or statin-CAI
             combination that has been stable for 6 weeks prior to randomization; and

          6. Willingness to maintain current physical activity level and follow the TLC diet
             throughout the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Allergy or intolerance to omega-3 fatty acids, omega-3-acid ethyl esters, or fish;

          2. Known lipoprotein lipase impairment;

          3. Known non-responder to omega-3 or fenofibrate therapy;

          4. Use of any prescription medications containing EPA and/or DHA (eg, Lovaza® or
             Vascepa®) within 8 weeks prior to randomization. Up to 1 g capsule/day of an omega-3
             dietary supplement will be permitted;

          5. Unable to discontinue use of bile acid sequestrants, fibrates or niacin (other than
             niacin-containing vitamins &lt;200 mg), or any supplement used to alter lipid metabolism
             including but not limited to dietary fiber supplements, red rice yeast supplements,
             garlic supplements, soy isoflavone supplements, sterol/stanol products, or
             policosanols at screening;

          6. Use of tamoxifen, estrogens, or progestins that has not been stable for &gt;4 weeks at
             screening or is unstable prior to randomization;

          7. Use of oral or injected corticosteroids or anabolic steroids prior to randomization;

          8. History of hospitalization for pancreatitis in the last 5 years;

          9. Uncontrolled diabetes (hemoglobin A1c [HbA1c] &gt;10%);

         10. Uncontrolled hypothyroidism or thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH) &gt;5 mIU/L;

         11. History of cancer (other than basal cell carcinoma) in the past 2 years;

         12. Cardiovascular event (ie, myocardial infarction, acute coronary syndrome, new onset
             angina, stroke, transient heart attack, unstable congestive heart failure requiring a
             change in treatment), revascularization procedure or vascular surgery within 6 months
             of randomization;

         13. Use of simvastatin 80 mg or Vytorin 10/80 mg;

         14. Recent history (within 6 months of randomization) of significant nephrotic syndrome,
             pulmonary, hepatic, biliary, gastrointestinal, or immunologic disease;

         15. Poorly controlled hypertension (systolic blood pressure ≥180 mmHg and/or diastolic
             blood pressure ≥110 mmHg);

         16. Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &gt;3 × the upper
             limit of normal (ULN); if ALT/AST is &gt;3 × ULN, the levels have been stable for 3
             months and are &lt;5 × ULN;

         17. Exposure to any investigational product within 4 weeks of randomization; or

         18. Any condition or therapy which, in the opinion of the Investigator, might pose a risk
             to the subject or make participation in the study not in the subject's best interest.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael H Davidson, MD, FACC</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Omthera Pharmaceuticals, Inc</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Douglas Kling</last_name>
    <phone>(908) 741-4193</phone>
    <email>dkling@omthera.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Judith Johnson</last_name>
    <phone>(908) 741-4194</phone>
    <email>jjohnson@omthera.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>COR Clinical Research, LLC.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinton N Corder, MD</last_name>
      <phone>405-272-8481</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Clinton N Corder, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 17, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 9, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hypertriglyceridemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Dyslipidemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Eicosapentaenoic acid</keyword>
  <keyword>EPA</keyword>
  <keyword>Docosahexaenoic acid</keyword>
  <keyword>DHA</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertriglyceridemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
