<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="168178">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01919099</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130177</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-I-0177</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01919099</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of the Complications Associated With Certain Stem Cell Transplants</brief_title>
  <official_title>Natural History Study of the Complications Associated With Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantations</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - The National Institutes of Health (NIH) performs up to 100 allogenic stem cell transplants
      (allo-HSCT) each year.  Many studies already look at different problems that can follow a
      transplant. But there are many types of transplants, diseases, responses, and treatments. An
      organized study of this information could help researchers learn more about how often
      transplant complications occur and what problems they cause. It could also lead to ideas for
      future research. This study will focus on complications thought to be the most significant.

      Objectives:

      - To gather information on the complications that may occur after an allo-HSCT.

      Eligibility:

      - People over 2 years of age currently enrolled in an allo-HSCT study at NIH.

      Design:

        -  Visits for this study will be scheduled along with primary study visits. The number of
           visits will depend on the primary study schedule.

        -  At each visit, participants will answer questions and take physical exams.

        -  The same questions and physical exams will continue for as long as they are in the
           primary study.

        -  In between visits, researchers might call participants to discuss their health. They
           may also discuss the cases with the primary study doctors and other doctors. Primary
           transplant study doctors will make treatment decisions.

        -  When participation in the primary transplant study ends, participation in this study
           will also end.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Between 80 and 100 allogeneic stem cell transplants (allo-HSCT) are performed every year at
      the NIH to treat a variety of malignant and nonmalignant conditions. The current transplant
      protocols at the NIH focus on research regarding the response of the underlying disease, the
      development of graft versus host disease (GVHD) as well as the feasibility and safety of a
      variety of transplant strategies. Many clinically significant complications are considered
      to be part of the transplant process and are not studied systematically. Even when they are
      studied, the diverse institute-based protocols differ on the range of complications captured
      and the amount of information collected on them. This leads to knowledge gaps regarding the
      incidence and risk factors for complications in the various protocols.

      This exploratory natural history study involves a prospective review of the medical records
      of patients actively enrolled in allo-HSCT protocols at the NIH. The study will focus on
      infections and a subset of noninfectious complications identified by the transplant
      community as significant causes of morbidity, mortality and cost. The cost data captured in
      this study will be the cost consumed by the Clinical Center. This study does not require any
      sample collection and will consist merely of data collection and periodic patient
      examinations that will be performed in conjunction with those already scheduled by the
      original transplant protocol. The prospective collection of clinical data and information
      available in the medical record will allow us to determine the rates of a number of
      complications in different protocols. At the completion of the study, it is expected the
      investigators will be able to generate preliminary hypotheses regarding risk factors for
      infection and noninfectious complications, the impact of complications on transplant costs
      and the correlation between laboratory immune reconstitution (usually determined by each
      transplant protocol in a variety of ways and functional immune reconstitution (frequency of
      infections).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2028</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2028</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>N/A</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Infections</measure>
    <time_frame>before day 100 and yearly thereafter</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulmonary complications</measure>
    <time_frame>before day 100 and yearly thereafter</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Renal complications</measure>
    <time_frame>before day 100 and yearly thereafter</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hepatic complications</measure>
    <time_frame>before day 100 and yearly thereafter</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiac complications</measure>
    <time_frame>before day 100 and yearly thereafter</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Stem Cell Transplantation, Hematopoietic</condition>
  <condition>Complications</condition>
  <condition>Infection</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Subjects over the age of 2 that are actively enrolled in an allo-HSCT protocol (and before
        they have allo-HSCT) at any NIH institute will be eligible to participate in this study
        regardless of gender or medical condition.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Subjects with any condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, contraindicates
        participation in the study will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Juan C Gea-Banacloche, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Theresa D Jerussi, P.A.-C</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-8993</phone>
    <email>jerussitd@cc.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Juan C Gea-Banacloche, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 435-2326</phone>
    <email>banacloj@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-I-0177.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>De Pauw B, Walsh TJ, Donnelly JP, Stevens DA, Edwards JE, Calandra T, Pappas PG, Maertens J, Lortholary O, Kauffman CA, Denning DW, Patterson TF, Maschmeyer G, Bille J, Dismukes WE, Herbrecht R, Hope WW, Kibbler CC, Kullberg BJ, Marr KA, Muñoz P, Odds FC, Perfect JR, Restrepo A, Ruhnke M, Segal BH, Sobel JD, Sorrell TC, Viscoli C, Wingard JR, Zaoutis T, Bennett JE; European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer/Invasive Fungal Infections Cooperative Group; National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases Mycoses Study Group (EORTC/MSG) Consensus Group. Revised definitions of invasive fungal disease from the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer/Invasive Fungal Infections Cooperative Group and the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases Mycoses Study Group (EORTC/MSG) Consensus Group. Clin Infect Dis. 2008 Jun 15;46(12):1813-21.</citation>
    <PMID>18462102</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seo S, Campbell AP, Xie H, Chien JW, Leisenring WM, Englund JA, Boeckh M. Outcome of respiratory syncytial virus lower respiratory tract disease in hematopoietic cell transplant recipients receiving aerosolized ribavirin: significance of stem cell source and oxygen requirement. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant. 2013 Apr;19(4):589-96. doi: 10.1016/j.bbmt.2012.12.019. Epub 2013 Jan 5.</citation>
    <PMID>23298855</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mandell LA, Wunderink RG, Anzueto A, Bartlett JG, Campbell GD, Dean NC, Dowell SF, File TM Jr, Musher DM, Niederman MS, Torres A, Whitney CG; Infectious Diseases Society of America; American Thoracic Society. Infectious Diseases Society of America/American Thoracic Society consensus guidelines on the management of community-acquired pneumonia in adults. Clin Infect Dis. 2007 Mar 1;44 Suppl 2:S27-72. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>17278083</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 7, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Transplantation Costs</keyword>
  <keyword>Risk Factors</keyword>
  <keyword>Transplant Infections</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
