<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="159724">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01862094</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130139</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-CH-0139</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01862094</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Kisspeptin Doses in Postmenopausal Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Blockade of Kisspeptin Signaling in Postmenopausal Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Kisspeptin is a chemical made by the body that affects human reproduction. Small doses of
      kisspeptin can help raise reproductive hormone levels. However, giving kisspeptin for a
      longer period (at least 1 day) can temporarily lower these hormone levels. Researchers want
      to study how kisspeptin controls the reproductive system in women. They also want to see
      what effect it has on reproductive hormones. They want to look at the effect of giving
      kisspeptin for 24 hours to healthy postmenopausal women.

      Objectives:

      - To see how kisspeptin affects hormone levels in postmenopausal women.

      Eligibility:

      - Healthy postmenopausal woman between 50 and 60 years of age.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. Blood samples
           will be collected.

        -  Participants will have a study visit for the kisspeptin test. They will stay in the
           hospital for about 38 hours.

        -  During the study visit, hormone levels will be monitored for 6 hours. Then, for the
           next 24 hours, participants will receive kisspeptin intravenously. After the 24 hours
           of kisspeptin, there will be 6 more hours of blood monitoring. Small amounts of blood
           will be drawn throughout the study.

        -  Participants will have a final followup visit within a month of the study visit.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The neuropeptide hormone kisspeptin sits at the top of the reproductive endocrine cascade.
      Kisspeptin potently stimulates secretion of gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) from
      neurons in the hypothalamus, which in turn stimulates secretion of the gonadotropins,
      follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) and luteinizing hormone (LH), from the pituitary gland,
      which then in turn stimulate the ovaries to produce estrogen and to mature an egg for
      ovulation in women and the testes to produce testosterone and generate sperm in men. While
      single doses of kisspeptin stimulate the reproductive endocrine axis, continuous
      administration of kisspeptin paradoxically suppresses the reproductive endocrine axis
      temporarily through desensitization of the kisspeptin receptor in monkeys. It remains
      controversial as to whether or not continuous kisspeptin will suppress GnRHinduced LH
      pulsatility in humans. By administering 24-hour infusions of kisspeptin to healthy
      postmenopausal women, we hope to learn more about the role of kisspeptin in normal
      reproductive physiology.

      The goal of this protocol is to explore the use of continuous kisspeptin as an antagonist of
      the reproductive cascade in healthy female volunteers. The protocol will focus on healthy
      postmenopausal women to determine the safety and effectiveness of continuous kisspeptin
      administration in women. Each enrolled subject will be admitted to the CRC for a frequent
      blood sampling study to determine the effect of continuous kisspeptin administration on GnRH
      pulsatility during this phase. These samples will be assayed for LH to assess the subject's
      baseline hormone secretion pattern, response to a 24-hour infusion of kisspeptin, and
      recovery after the infusion. Subjects will be closely monitored throughout and following the
      study for adverse reaction to the kisspeptin infusion or to the frequent blood sampling,
      though no significant adverse reactions have been reported in previous studies of kisspeptin
      administration to humans.

      In summary, this proposal will utilize a cutting-edge physiologic tool to answer key
      questions about the neuroendocrine control of reproduction in the human female. The
      information gained from this proposal has the potential to significantly broaden our
      knowledge of the neuroendocrine control of human reproduction, as well as to catalyze new
      diagnostic and therapeutic approaches to female reproductive disorders.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in mean LH level as a result of continuous kisspeptin infusion.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Volunteers</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Kisspeptin 112-121</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION &amp;  EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        History:

          -  age between 50 and 60 years

          -  prior history of normal puberty with respect to onset and pace,

          -  prior history of menstrual cycles between 25 and 35 days in duration, with no more
             than 5 days variability in cycle duration prior to the peri-menopausal period,

          -  amenorrhea, defined as absence of menstruation for the previous 12 months,

          -  no prescription medications (including hormonal replacement) for at least 2 months
             except for seasonal allergy medications,

          -  no symptoms associated with or known hypothalamic or pituitary disease, as a result
             of intracranial mass, history of irradiation, head trauma, etc,

          -  no history of a drug reaction that required emergency medical attention,

          -  no illicit drug use,

          -  no excessive alcohol consumption (&lt;  10 drinks/week),

          -  no history of chronic disease,

          -  no difficulty with blood draws,

        Physical Examination:

          -  BMI greater than or equal to 18.5 and &lt; 30 kg/m(2),

          -  systolic BP &lt; 140 mm Hg, diastolic &lt; 90 mm Hg)

          -  no evidence for androgen excess (hirsutism or acne),

        Laboratory Studies: (per NIH reference ranges unless noted otherwise)

          -  negative serum hCG pregnancy test at the time of screening (additional urine
             pregnancy test will be conducted prior to drug administration),

          -  white blood cell and platelet counts, prolactin, TSH, between 90% of the lower limit
             and 110% of the upper limit of the reference range,

          -  hemoglobin greater than or equal to 12 g/dL,

          -  BUN and creatinine not elevated,

          -  AST, ALT &lt;  2 times upper limit of the reference range,

          -  FSH &gt;  40 U/L,

          -  Estradiol &lt;  30 pg/mL.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Angela Delaney, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Angela Delaney, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-3025</phone>
    <email>delaneya@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-CH-0139.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kotani M, Detheux M, Vandenbogaerde A, Communi D, Vanderwinden JM, Le Poul E, Brézillon S, Tyldesley R, Suarez-Huerta N, Vandeput F, Blanpain C, Schiffmann SN, Vassart G, Parmentier M. The metastasis suppressor gene KiSS-1 encodes kisspeptins, the natural ligands of the orphan G protein-coupled receptor GPR54. J Biol Chem. 2001 Sep 14;276(37):34631-6. Epub 2001 Jul 16.</citation>
    <PMID>11457843</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gottsch ML, Cunningham MJ, Smith JT, Popa SM, Acohido BV, Crowley WF, Seminara S, Clifton DK, Steiner RA. A role for kisspeptins in the regulation of gonadotropin secretion in the mouse. Endocrinology. 2004 Sep;145(9):4073-7. Epub 2004 Jun 24.</citation>
    <PMID>15217982</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Irwig MS, Fraley GS, Smith JT, Acohido BV, Popa SM, Cunningham MJ, Gottsch ML, Clifton DK, Steiner RA. Kisspeptin activation of gonadotropin releasing hormone neurons and regulation of KiSS-1 mRNA in the male rat. Neuroendocrinology. 2004;80(4):264-72. Epub 2005 Jan 5.</citation>
    <PMID>15665556</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 22, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 22, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Postmenopausal Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>Hormones</keyword>
  <keyword>Phase I</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteers</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
