<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="29979">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01743417</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R01HD064416-01A1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01743417</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Computerized Cognitive Rehabilitation in Children After Severe Malaria</brief_title>
  <acronym>CM_CCRT</acronym>
  <official_title>Computerized Cognitive Rehabilitation in Children After Severe Malaria</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Makerere University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Michigan State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Makerere University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Uganda: National Council for Science and Technology</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Brain training exercises will be provided to children who survived an episode of severe
      malaria. These children will be given assessments for cognition, behaviour and executive
      functions before and after the brain training exercises.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Our Fogarty &quot;Brain Disorders&quot; R21 study findings demonstrated that attention and working
      memory deficits persist in one out of four children with cerebral malaria (CM) (Boivin et
      al., 2007; John, Bangirana et al., 2008).  Uganda has one of the highest incidences of
      malaria worldwide (~480/1000) with about 10% of these incidents becoming severe and over 90%
      of such cases occurring in children (Snow, Guerra, Noor, Myint, &amp; Hay, 2005).  This results
      in an estimated 80 thousand new cases each year of Ugandan children with mild to severe
      neurocognitive impairment from this disease.  Such impairment will likely compromise their
      school performance, impede their activities of daily living, and lessen their future
      economic opportunities.

      There is no known treatment intervention during acute illness to prevent CM brain-injury
      effects (Abubakar et al., 2007).  Nor are neurocognitive rehabilitative treatment programs
      available in low-resource settings for affected children.  However, we have successfully
      piloted a computerized cognitive rehabilitation therapy (CCRT) intervention to specifically
      improve attention, visual-spatial learning, and psychosocial adjustment (domains shown most
      affected by CM in our previous studies) with school-age Ugandan CM survivors (Bangirana,
      Giordani et al., 2009).  This evidence justifies an R01 for further study.

      The present application proposes a randomized control trial (RCT) to further establish that
      CCRT can improve attention, working memory, aspects of executive functioning, and
      psychosocial adjustment in pediatric CM survivors.  Such programs are already being used
      extensively with children with developmental disabilities (e.g., Attention Deficit
      Hyperactivity Disorder, learning disorders) and brain injury in high-income countries.  The
      evidence from RCT studies for these interventions is strong enough to warrant the evaluation
      of CCRT for at-risk African children (Bangirana, Idro, John, &amp; Boivin, 2006; Boivin &amp;
      Giordani, 2009).  CCRT could also then be extended to a variety of other infectious diseases
      causing brain injury and persisting neurocognitive deficits to children in this setting
      (e.g., HIV, schistosomiasis, meningitis, encephalitis, and neurocysticercosis).

      Objectives:

        1. To evaluate the effectiveness of CCRT in improving neuropsychological performance and
           psychiatric outcomes in Ugandan children who survive severe malaria.

        2. To evaluate whether severity of malaria illness (e.g., immunological brain
           inflammation, EEG abnormalities) is predictive of neuropsychological benefit from CCRT.

        3. METHODS

      Study design:

      Randomized controlled trial

      Study Population:

      Our proposed study groups of children aged 5 to 12 years will consist of 150 children with
      severe malaria (either cerebral malaria or severe malaria anemia). From the homes of these
      severe malaria children, we will also recruit 1 sibling (or neighbor child) 5 to 12 years of
      age without a history of cerebral malaria or other known infectious disease that could cause
      brain injury (Community Controls from Home: CC children N = 150).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Executive attention</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at 12 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Executive attention will be measured by the Test of Variables of Attention</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Working memory</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at 12 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Working memory will be measured by the Kaufman Assessment Battery for Children second edition</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cogntive intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Children in this arm will receive computerised cognitive rehabilitation training for 24 sessions lasting 45 minutes. The Captain's log brain training software is programmed to increase in difficulty as child progresses through the training levels.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Children in this arm will receive 24 sessions of computerised cognitive rehabilitation training. Captain's log, the brain training software will not be programmed to increase in difficulty with each successive level in this arm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Passive control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No computer training or games will be provided to this group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Computerised cognitive rehabilitation training</intervention_name>
    <description>24 sessions of computerised bran training will be provided for 8 weeks (+/-2) with about 3 sessions per week to the intervention arm and active control arms. The program will be programmed to increases in difficulty for the intervention arm. In the active control arms, the difficulty level will not change.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cogntive intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Active control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Captain's Log</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Aged 5 to 12 years of age;

          2. Signed consent from the parent/guardian, assent from children aged 7 years and older;

          3. Completion of their 24 months testing in the parent study (MUREC no 2008-033).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. CM: elevated cerebrospinal fluid protein, white blood cells or red blood cells

          2. Severe malarial anemia: history of coma, impaired consciousness, repeated seizures,
             other brain disorder, and developmental delay.  Additional exclusion criteria for CC
             group:

               -  any active illness; recent illness or recovery from illness;

               -  chronic illness requiring medical care; -) medical abnormalities on screening
                  history or physical exam.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael J Boivin, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Michigan State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Noeline Nakasujja, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Makerere University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paul Bangirana, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>256-772-673831</phone>
    <email>pbangirana@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Noeline Nakasujja, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>256-772-419700</phone>
    <email>drnoeline@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Makerere University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kampala</city>
        <country>Uganda</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paul Bangirana, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+256772673831</phone>
      <email>pbangirana@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Noeline Nakasujja, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+256772419700</phone>
      <email>drnoeline@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Noeline Nakasujja, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Uganda</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://globalhealthuganda.org/ccrt.html</url>
    <description>Webpage of the research collaboration managing the study</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bangirana P, Allebeck P, Boivin MJ, John CC, Page C, Ehnvall A, Musisi S. Cognition, behaviour and academic skills after cognitive rehabilitation in Ugandan children surviving severe malaria: a randomised trial. BMC Neurol. 2011 Aug 4;11:96.</citation>
    <PMID>21816079</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bangirana P, Giordani B, John CC, Page C, Opoka RO, Boivin MJ. Immediate neuropsychological and behavioral benefits of computerized cognitive rehabilitation in Ugandan pediatric cerebral malaria survivors. J Dev Behav Pediatr. 2009 Aug;30(4):310-8.</citation>
    <PMID>19668094</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>John CC, Bangirana P, Byarugaba J, Opoka RO, Idro R, Jurek AM, Wu B, Boivin MJ. Cerebral malaria in children is associated with long-term cognitive impairment. Pediatrics. 2008 Jul;122(1):e92-9. Epub 2008 Jun 9.</citation>
    <PMID>18541616</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 31, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 5, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cognitive rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>malaria</keyword>
  <keyword>neuropsychology</keyword>
  <keyword>attention</keyword>
  <keyword>working memory</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
