<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="60438">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01968135</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-1702</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01968135</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Does Concomitant Use of Combined Oral Hormonal Steroids Stop Bleeding in Women Using Etonogestrel Implants (Implanon/Nexplanon®)?: A Randomized Controlled Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Does Concomitant Use of Combined Oral Hormonal Steroids Stop Bleeding in Women Using Etonogestrel Implants (Implanon/Nexplanon®)?: A Randomized Controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators' specific aims are to determine if more women using ENG contraceptive
      implants who report a bleeding-spotting episode of at least seven days will stop bleeding
      within 3 days of beginning a 14-day course of combined oral hormonal steroids, as compared
      to women receiving 14 days of placebo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The etonogestrel (ENG) contraceptive implant (Implanon/Nexplanon®), is a silicone- free,
      single rod subdermal contraceptive implant that contains 68 mg of etonogestrel, is approved
      for use for three years, and is one of the most effective  forms of contraception available
      (1).  ENG contraceptive implants are easily inserted and removed (1,2), offer quick return
      to fertility (2), are cost-effective and cost-saving (3,4) and offer non-contraceptive
      benefits such as improvement in pain for patients with complaints of dysmenorrhea (5).

      Hypothesis:  Women using ENG contraceptive implants who report a bleeding-spotting episode
      of at least seven days will be more likely to stop bleeding within 3 days of beginning a
      14-day course of combined oral hormonal steroids compared to women receiving 14 days of
      placebo.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cessation of vaginal bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>At day 3 of 14 day course of study drug</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of cessation of vaginal bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Uterine Hemorrhage</condition>
  <condition>Contraception</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar Pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo Sugar Pill</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Combined Oral Contraceptive Pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>150 mcg levonorgestrel and 30 mcg ethinyl estradiol combined oral contraceptive pill</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Combined Oral Contraceptive Pill</intervention_name>
    <description>150 mcg levonorgestrel and 30 mcg ethinyl estradiol combined oral contraceptive pill</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combined Oral Contraceptive Pill</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Sugar Pill</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo Sugar Pill</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar Pill</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All female

          -  English or Spanish speaking women

          -  between the ages of 18-44

          -  using an ENG contraceptive implant who complain of bothersome bleeding and have a
             current bleeding episode of at least seven days will be invited to participate.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Category 3 or 4 contraindications to estrogen therapy according to the Centers for
             Disease Control 2010 Medical Eligibility Criteria.

          -  Category 3 contraindications: less than 1 month postpartum if breastfeeding, less
             than 21 days postpartum if not breastfeeding, history of Deep Vein Thrombosis (DVT)
             /Pulmonary Embolism (PE) not on anticoagulant therapy and no risk factors, Deep
             venous thrombosis/Pulmonary Embolus on established anticoagulant therapy and no risk
             factors, history of malabsorptive bariatric surgery, greater than or equal to  months
             post peripartum cardiomyopathy with normal to mildly impaired cardiac function,
             greater than or equal to 35 years old with less than 15 cigarettes smoked per day,
             multiple risk factors for arterial cardiovascular disease, adequately controlled
             hypertension, blood pressure 140-159/90-99 mm Hg, migraines without aura less than 35
             years old, past breast cancer and no evidence of recurrent disease for 5 years,
             diabetes with retinopathy, neuropathy, nephropathy (category 3 or 4 depending on
             severity), diabetes greater than 20 years duration or associated with other vascular
             disease, medically treated symptomatic gallbladder disease or current symptomatic
             gallbladder disease, past combined oral contraceptive pill related cholestasis, acute
             viral hepatitis, hepatocellular adenoma, hepatoma, use of ritonavir-boosted protease
             inhibitors, anticonvulsant therapy use including phenytoin, carbamazepine,
             barbiturates, primidone, topiramate, oxcarbazepine, and lamotrigine, use of
             Rifampicin,

          -  Category 4 contraindications: less than 6 months post peripartum cardiomyopathy with
             normal to mildly impaired cardiac function, any time following peripartum
             cardiomyopathy with moderately to severely impaired cardiac function, greater than or
             equal to 35 years old with greater than 15 cigarettes smoked per day, multiple risk
             factors for arterial cardiovascular disease, blood pressure greater than or equal to
             160/100 mm Hg, high risk for recurrent DVT/PE, acute DVT/PE, DVT/PE and on
             established anticoagulant therapy with greater than or equal to 1 risk factor for
             recurrent DVT/PE, major surgery/prolonged immobilization, known thrombogenic
             mutations, current and history of ischemic heart disease, history of stroke,
             complicated valvular heart disease,  systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) with positive
             or unknown antiphospholipid antibodies, migraines without aura greater than or equal
             to 35 years old, migraines with aura at any age, current breast cancer, complicated
             solid organ transplantation

          -  Body mass index (BMI) greater than 35.

          -  A systolic blood pressure greater than 135 on more than 2 occasions. assuring the
             measurements are separated by an interval of at least 15 minutes.

          -  A diastolic blood pressure greater than 85 on more than 2 occasions. assuring the
             measurement are separated by an interval of at least 15 minutes.

          -  A positive pregnancy test.

          -  A positive chlamydia test.

          -  Unable or unwilling to swallow pills.

          -  A medical condition deemed severed by a physician investigator.

          -  A participant taking a liver enzyme inducing drug.

          -  A known allergy to levonorgestrel or ethinyl estradiol.

          -  An abnormal speculum exam (i.e. bleeding ectropion or cervical mass).

          -  Does not meet appropriate cervical cytology screening guidelines.

          -  Cervical procedure done in the past 3 months.

          -  On a concurrent hormonal contraceptive and unwilling to discontinue.

          -  Breast lesions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>44 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maryam Guiahi, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Denver</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Maryke Swartz, MS</last_name>
    <phone>303-724-8482</phone>
    <email>maryke.swartz@ucdenver.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sandra Cano, MA</last_name>
    <phone>303-724-2013</phone>
    <email>sandra.cano@ucdenver.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maryke Swartz, MS</last_name>
      <phone>303-724-8482</phone>
      <email>maryke.swartz@ucdenver.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maryam Guiahi, MD, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uterine Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Contraceptive Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>3-keto-desogestrel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Contraceptives, Oral</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Contraceptives, Oral, Combined</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ethinyl Estradiol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
