<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="100811">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01881659</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IEC 12-27</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01881659</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cervical Cancer Screening With Human Papillomavirus Testing</brief_title>
  <acronym>ESTAMPA</acronym>
  <official_title>Multicentric Study of Cervical Cancer Screening and Triage With Human Papillomavirus (HPV) Testing</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>International Agency for Research on Cancer</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>International Agency for Research on Cancer</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Colombia: Ministry of Health and Social Protection</authority>
    <authority>Mexico: National Institute of Public Health, Health Secretariat</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      HPV testing for primary cervical cancer screening of women over 30 years of age is likely to
      become the standard of care in the near future in many areas of the world. Its high
      sensitivity can significantly improve the effectiveness of screening programs and its
      prolonged negative predictive value can allow extension of screening intervals. However, a
      single HPV test has low positive predictive value and can lead to unnecessary workup and
      over-treatment and generate unnecessary distress. This multi-centric study will screen
      50,000 women with HPV testing and compare several triage approaches that can follow HPV
      testing in order to make an HPV-based screening programme efficient, affordable and
      sustainable.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will be conducted in several Latin American countries. Currently, the study has
      started in one site in Colombia and soon another site in Mexico will start. In each
      participating center, at least 5,000 women ages 30-64 years who are attending clinics for
      cervical screening will be invited to participate in the study. Women who agree to
      participate and sign the corresponding Institutional Review Board (IRB) approved consent
      forms will undergo a pelvic examination, and cervical cells for primary screening and triage
      will be collected. Recruitment specimens will be used for primary screening with an
      established HPV DNA test (Food and Drug Administration FDA approved). All women who are
      HPV-positive by the recruitment test, and a 2% sample of the HPV-negative women, will be
      referred for a standardized colposcopy examination for diagnosis. At the colposcopy visit,
      but before colposcopy is performed, a risk factor interview will be administered and
      participants will undergo visual inspection of the cervix with acetic acid (VIA) and
      collection of additional cervical cells and a blood specimen. The results of VIA will not be
      disclosed to the colposcopist. During colposcopy, the colposcopists will obtain (2-4)
      biopsies from any abnormally-appearing areas to ascertain neoplastic outcomes (CIN 3+) and
      to direct treatment as required. All women who attend colposcopy will have a second round of
      HPV testing approximately 18 months after recruitment and those who are HPV-positive will be
      referred to colposcopy for final diagnosis. Data management and study supervision will be
      the responsibility of the International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC) and the local
      Principal Investigators, most of whom are experienced HPV researchers.

      The combined number of histologically-confirmed diagnoses of CIN 3+ (estimated n=500) will
      be the outcome of primary interest for evaluation of the performance of the various triage
      modalities. Our initial analyses will focus on comparisons of triage strategies that employ
      a single method: VIA, conventional/liquid-based cytology, HPV DNA genotyping, HPV RNA
      detection, detection of E6 proteins of high risk HPV types, or markers of HPV-induced
      cell-cycle alterations (e.g., p16, ki67, etc). To the extent possible, molecular testing for
      HPV triage will be carried out on the recruitment specimens to simulate a 'reflex testing'
      approach wherein screening and triage are done on the same specimen without additional
      visits. Subsequent analyses will consider various alternative strategies that employ more
      than one triage methodology; e.g., HPV DNA genotyping followed by cytology. The
      effectiveness and costs of each alternative strategy will be assessed under various
      scenarios of feasibility, cost, and effectiveness.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with histologically confirmed cervical intraepithelial neoplasia grade 3 or cancer (CIN3+) on reviewed histology</measure>
    <time_frame>Detected after initial HPV screening or at second screening round 18 months since entry</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>There will be two HPV screening rounds. Women who test negative for HPV at initial screening will finish their participation, except a 2% random sample who will be followed as if HPV positive. HPV positive women will be: 1) referred to colposcopy, 2) invited for a second HPV screening round if not yet treated, and 3) referred to final colposcopy if HPV positive at second screening. Clinical management will be based on local histology.
Histology specimens will be externally reviewed by one highly experience international pathologist. If the local and external results are the same, this will become the final histology. If there is disagreement, the specimen will be sent to a third pathologist (be blinded to previous readings). The final diagnosis will then be that agreed by two pathologists (local and either external or both external). Remaining discrepancies will be solved by adjudication at a multi-headed microscope. Worst histology on review will be used to define outcome measures.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with histologically confirmed CIN2, CIN3 or cancer (CIN2+) on reviewed histology</measure>
    <time_frame>Detected after initial HPV screening or at second screening round 18 months since entry</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>There will be two HPV screening rounds. Women who test negative for HPV at initial screening will finish their participation, except a 2% random sample who will be followed as if HPV positive. HPV positive women will be: 1) referred to colposcopy, 2) invited for a second HPV screening round if not yet treated, and 3) referred to final colposcopy if HPV positive at second screening. Clinical management will be based on local histology.
Histology specimens will be externally reviewed by one highly experience international pathologist. If the local and external results are the same, this will become the final histology. If there is disagreement, the specimen will be sent to a third pathologist (be blinded to previous readings). The final diagnosis will then be that agreed by two pathologists (local and either external or both external). Remaining discrepancies will be solved by adjudication at a multi-headed microscope. Worst histology on review will be used to define outcome measures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50000</enrollment>
  <condition>CIN3</condition>
  <condition>CIN2</condition>
  <condition>Cervical Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Women attending cervical screening</arm_group_label>
    <description>Women aged 30-64 years who signed informed consent and comply with inclusion and exclusion criteria.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HPV screening</intervention_name>
    <description>Women who signed informed consent will be screened with HPV testing.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Women attending cervical screening</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Three cervical samples will be collected at entry (one dry and two liquid-based). Sample
      retaining or discharge will depend on HPV test (done in first liquid sample) results. If HPV
      positive (and 2% of HPV negatives): 1) the dry sample will be used for the E6 protein strip
      test, 2) the first liquid sample remains will be used for liquid-based cytology and the
      p16/ki67 test and, 3) 10 aliquots from the second liquid sample will be stored. If HPV
      negative: 1) the dry sample will be stored for the E6 strip test until the end of the study.
      Testing will be done based on evidence towards usefulness in primary screening, 2) two
      aliquots from the first liquid sample will be stored and, 3) the second liquid sample will
      be discharged. At initial colposcopy, a cervical sample (6 aliquots) and a 10mL blood sample
      (serum, plasma and buffy-coat) will be collected and stored. All stored samples will be used
      for testing of triage techniques, either currently available or develop in the near future.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        This is a multicentric study to be carried out in countries across the Latin American
        region. At each site, a census of all women 28-64 years of age residents of the selected
        area will be done previously to the start of the study. All women will then be invited
        using different approaches to the local health centers where screening is to happen.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged 30-64 years

          -  Mentally competent to be able to understand the consent form

          -  Able to communicate with study staff

          -  Physically able to have a pelvic exam

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Reporting no previous sexual activity

          -  History of cervical cancer

          -  Previous treatment for cervical pre-cancer in the last six months

          -  Hysterectomy

          -  Plans to move out of the study area in the next 12 months

          -  Screened for cervical cancer in the last 12 months (depending on local regulations)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rolando Herrero, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rolando Herrero, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+33472738683</phone>
    <email>herreror@iarc.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Maribel Almonte, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+33472738492</phone>
    <email>almontem@iarc.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cancer Institute of Colombia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bogota</city>
        <country>Colombia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Raul Murillo, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+5713341111</phone>
      <phone_ext>4001</phone_ext>
      <email>rmurillo@cancer.gov.co</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Carolina Wiesner, MD</last_name>
      <email>cwiesner@cancer.gov.co</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Raul Murillo, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carolina Wiesner, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Instituto Nacional de Salud Publica de Mexico</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cuernavaca</city>
        <state>Morelos</state>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Aurelio Cruz, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+527773293020</phone>
      <phone_ext>3108</phone_ext>
      <email>acruz@insp.mx</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Aurelio Cruz, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eduardo Lazcano Ponce, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Colombia</country>
    <country>Mexico</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 26, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 17, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cervical cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>cancer prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>cervical screening</keyword>
  <keyword>HPV testing</keyword>
  <keyword>triage techniques</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Uterine Cervical Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
