<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="99139">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01900158</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PCI A202/12</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01900158</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase I/II Study Safety and Efficacy Study of PCI of Gemcitabine and Chemotherapy in Patients With Cholangiocarcinomas</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Dose Escalation Study to Assess the Safety, Tolerability and Efficacy of PCI of Gemcitabine Followed by Gemcitabine/Cisplatin Chemotherapy in Patients With Locally Advanced Inoperable Cholangiocarcinomas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>PCI Biotech AS</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>PCI Biotech AS</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase I/II Dose Escalation Study in which the safety, tolerability and efficacy of
      Amphinex-induced Photochemical Internalisation (PCI) of Gemcitabine followed by
      Gemcitabine/Cisplatin Chemotherapy will be assessed in patients with locally advanced
      inoperable cholangiocarcinomas.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cholangiocarcinoma (CCA) is an uncommon adenocarcinoma arising from the neoplastic
      transformation of cholangiocytes, the epithelial cells lining the intra-hepatic and
      extra-hepatic bile ducts. CCA accounts for about 3% of all digestive tumours and 10-15% of
      the hepatobiliary tumours. It has an annual incidence of 1-2 cases per 100,000 in the
      Western World, but rates of CCA have been steadily rising worldwide over the past several
      decades. On a global scale, CCA is the second most common primary hepatic malignancy These
      tumours have a poor overall survival with a 5-year survival of about 5%. Over 50% of
      patients present with advanced-stage disease, and the prognosis is poor with the survival of
      between 6-12 months for unresected patients, even after biliary decompression. CCA may arise
      anywhere in the biliary tree, from the small, peripheral hepatic ducts to the distal common
      bile duct. Commonly used classification systems utilise anatomical location to group tumours
      into three main categories: intra-hepatic (20-25%), hilar (also known as Klatskin tumour -
      50%) and extra-hepatic (20-25%).

      Hilar CCA is an adenocarcinoma of the extrahepatic biliary tree arising from the main left
      or right hepatic ducts or their confluence. There has a been a growing recognition that
      hilar CCA disease actually has a distinct biological behaviour and natural history compared
      to that of (distal) extra-hepatic CCA, and increasing acknowledgment that different
      therapeutic strategies are required (10). At initial presentation of patients with
      extra-hepatic CCA, 30-50% will have local lymph node involvement and 10-20% metastatic
      spread typically to the liver and peritoneum.  With hilar CCA due to the long asymptomatic
      course, only 20% are resectable at time of diagnosis (23).

      Standard treatment options for CCA include surgery, radiotherapy and chemotherapy, dependent
      upon if the CCA is intra- or extra-hepatic. Tumour resection is the only potential cure for
      CCA. Recent advances in transplantation using stringent selection criteria and utilization
      of neoadjuvant chemoradiation have demonstrated encouraging results with 5 year survival
      rates of over 70%, with even one series from The Mayo Clinic yielding a 5-year survival rate
      of 82%. For the 80% who present with unresectable disease, the utility of these modalities
      combined with biliary decompression interventions only provided a median survival time of
      3-6 months from the time of diagnosis.

      For these patients with inoperable locally advanced CCA the main treatment aim is palliative
      to relieve local symptoms such as pain and jaundice. Surgery for these patients is primarily
      for creating a bypass in patients who cannot be stented.  CCA is remarkably resistant to
      pharmacological therapy, but activity has been seen using chemotherapy; mainly gemcitabine
      given either as monotherapy or paired with either a platin derivative or a fluoropyrimidine
      as a doublet treatment and more recently docetaxel, these give partial response rates of
      0-9% and an average survival advantage of 2-12 months. Concerning biological therapy, the
      ongoing studies using sorafenib, lapatinib or bevacizumab have yielded some promising
      results, with sorafenib demonstrating therapeutic benefit in a single arm PhII study.  For
      patients who are unsuitable for curative resection, the current systemic combination
      chemotherapy is with cisplatin plus gemcitabine. This was established in the largest
      randomized phase III study to date in non-operable biliary tract cancer which demonstrated a
      response rate of 81.4% and a median overall survival of 11.7 months; notably there was no
      statistically significant increase in toxicity when compared to gemcitabine monotherapy. The
      recent advances in interventional and endoscopic technology have seen a rise in highly
      specialized centres that are able to deliver very precise local control treatments aimed at
      gaining local control; these include local ablation and embolization, brachytherapy,
      radio-frequency ablation and, most significantly, photodynamic therapy which, with its
      favourable adverse-event profile, is recommended by most recent review articles for
      non-resectable patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose limiting Toxicity - Phase I (safety)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 9 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Dose-limiting toxicities (DLT) and the safety profile</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy- Phase II (efficacy)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 17 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Progression Free Survival (PFS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Best Overall Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number and proportion of patients with CR, PR, SD PD and NE</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Pharmacokinetics profine of Amphinex and Gemcitabine in Plasma</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Control Rate (DC)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of patients with best overall response of CR, PR or SD</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of patients with best overall response rate of CR and PR</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety Profile (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Time to re-intervention (Exploratory Endpoint)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Skin photosensitivity (Exploratory Endpoint)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">61</enrollment>
  <condition>Cholangiocarcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Amphinex and Gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm A: Amphinex administration on day 0, followed by gemcitabine administration (1000 mg/m2) intravenously over 30 minutes and laser light application (652 nm) on day 4 followed by systemic gemcitabine (1000 mg/m2) and cisplatin (25 mg/m2) given on Day 1 and Day 8 of each 21-day cycle, commencing between 7 and 21 days after the laser light application</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gemcitabine and Cisplatin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>No PCI treatment (stenting only) followed by systemic gemcitabine (1000 mg/m2) intravenously over 30 minutes and cisplatin intravenously over a period of 1 hour (25 mg/m2) given on Day 1 and Day 8 of each 21-day cycle, commencing within 21 days after randomization.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Amphinex and Gemcitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Amphinex administration on day 0, followed by gemcitabine administration (1000 mg/m2) intravenously over 30 minutes and laser light application (652 nm) on day 4 followed by systemic gemcitabine (1000 mg/m2) and cisplatin (25 mg/m2) given on Day 1 and Day 8 of each 21-day cycle, commencing between 7 and 21 days after the laser light application.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Amphinex and Gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Gemzar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gemcitabine and Cisplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>No PCI treatment (stenting only) followed by systemic gemcitabine (1000 mg/m2) intravenously over 30 minutes and cisplatin intravenously over a period of 1 hour (25 mg/m2) given on Day 1 and Day 8 of each 21-day cycle, commencing within 21 days after randomization.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gemcitabine and Cisplatin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Gemzar</other_name>
    <other_name>Cisplatin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histopathologically/cytologically (C5) verified adenocarcinoma           consistent
             with locally advanced inoperable

          2. Cholangiocarcinoma that is limited to:

             Nodal enlargement ≤ to N1 as per CT/MRI assessment Less than 4cm in longest diameter
             Perihilar and extrahilar biliary duct region.

          3. Adequate biliary drainage (either at least 50% of the liver volume, or at least two
             sectors), with no evidence of active uncontrolled infection (patients on antibiotics
             are eligible).

          4. Age ≥ 18 years.

          5. Performance status ECOG ≤ 2

          6. Estimated life expectancy of at least 12 weeks.

          7. Written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis and main criteria for inclusion:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histopathologically/cytologically (C5) verified adenocarcinoma consistent with
             locally advanced inoperable

          2. Cholangiocarcinoma that is limited to:

             Nodal enlargement ≤ to N1 as per CT/MRI assessment Less than 4cm in longest diameter
             Perihilar and extrahilar biliary duct region.

          3. Adequate biliary drainage (either at least 50% of the liver volume, or at least two
             sectors), with no evidence of active uncontrolled infection (patients on antibiotics
             are eligible).

          4. Age ≥ 18 years.

          5. Performance status ECOG ≤ 2

          6. Estimated life expectancy of at least 12 weeks.

          7. Written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any prior anti-cancer (either local or systemic) treatment for cholangiocarcinoma.

          2. Patients with a severe visceral disease other than cholangiocarcinoma.

          3. Patients with primary sclerosing cholangitis.

          4. Patients with porphyria or hypersensibility to porphyrins.

          5. Concomitant or prior malignant disease, with exception of adequately treated basal
             cell carcinoma, squamous cell carcinoma or other non-melanomatous skin cancer, or
             in-situ carcinoma of the uterine cervix.

          6. Inability to undergo CT or MRI.

          7. Current participation in any other interventional clinical trial.

          8. Male patients not willing to use adequate contraception or female patients of
             childbearing potential not willing to use an effective form of contraception such as
             hormonal birth control, intrauterine device or double barrier method during PCI
             treatment and subsequent chemotherapy and for at least 6 months thereafter.

          9. Breast feeding women or women with a positive pregnancy test at baseline.

         10. Inadequate bone marrow function:

               -  Absolute Neutrophil Count (ANC): &lt;1.5 x 109/L, or platelet count &lt;100 x 109/L or
                  haemoglobin &lt;6 mmol/L (transfusion allowed).

         11. Inadequate liver function, defined as:

               -  Serum (total) bilirubin &gt;1.5 x the Upper Limit of Normal (ULN) for the
                  institution.

               -  Aspartate Amino Transferase (AST) or Alanine Amino Transferase (ALT) &gt;3.0 x ULN.

               -  Alkaline phosphatase levels &gt;5.0 x ULN.

         12. Inadequate renal function, defined as:

               -  Creatinine clearance &lt;60ml/min)

         13. Planned surgery, endoscopic examination or dental treatment in the first 30 days
             after PCI treatment.

         14. Co-existing ophthalmic disease likely to require slit-lamp examination within the
             first 90 days after PCI treatment.

         15. Clinically significant and uncontrolled cardiac disease including unstable angina,
             acute myocardial infarction within six months prior to baseline, congestive heart
             failure, and arrhythmia requiring therapy, with the exception of extra systoles or
             minor conduction abnormalities and controlled and well treated chronic atrial
             fibrillation.

         16. Known allergy or sensitivity to photosensitisers.

         17. Ataxia telangiectasia.

         18. Evidence of any other medical conditions (such as psychiatric illness, infectious
             diseases, physical examination or laboratory findings) that may interfere with the
             planned PCI treatment, affect patient compliance or place the patient at high risk
             from treatment-related complications.

         19. Significant hearing impairment.

         20. Patients concurrently receiving phenytoin.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dr Richard Sturgess, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital Aintree</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dr. Richard Sturgess, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0044(0)151 529 8157</phone>
    <email>RICHARD.STURGESS@aintree.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Dr Dan Palmer, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0044 (0)151 706 4177</phone>
    <email>Daniel.Palmer@liverpool.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Center for Tumor Diseases</name>
      <address>
        <city>Heidelberg</city>
        <state>Baden-Württemberg</state>
        <zip>D-69120</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dr Jürgen Krauss, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0049 6221 56 38696</phone>
      <email>juergen.krauss@nct-heidelberg.de</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Klinikum rechts der Isar</name>
      <address>
        <city>Munich</city>
        <state>Bayern</state>
        <zip>81675</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dr. Bruno Neu, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0049 89 4140-2902</phone>
      <email>Bruno.Neu@lrz.tu-muenchen.de</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Klinikum Ludwigshafen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ludwigshafen</city>
        <state>Rheinland-Pfalz</state>
        <zip>D-67063</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Prof. Ralf Jakobs, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0049 621 503 4100</phone>
      <email>JAKOBSR@klilu.de</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Charité, Campus Mitte</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>D-10117</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dr. med. Robert Wentrup, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0049 30 450 614 055</phone>
      <email>robert.wentrup@charite.de</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Aintree</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aintree</city>
        <state>Liverpool</state>
        <zip>L9 7AL</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dr Richard Sturgess, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0044 (0) 151 529 8157</phone>
      <email>RICHARD.STURGESS@aintree.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Dr Dan Palmer, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0044 (0)151 706 4177</phone>
      <email>Daniel.Palmer@liverpool.ac.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 22, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 15, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Phase I, Phase II, Dose Escalation, Safety, Tolerability,</keyword>
  <keyword>Efficacy, AmphinexTM-induced Photochemical Internalisation</keyword>
  <keyword>(PCI), Gemcitabine, Gemcitabine/Cisplatin Chemotherapy,</keyword>
  <keyword>Locally Advanced Inoperable Cholangiocarcinomas.</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cholangiocarcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Gemcitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
