<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="122876">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02124772</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>116540</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02124772</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Investigate Safety, Pharmacokinetic (PK), Pharmacodynamic (PD) and Clinical Activity of Trametinib in Subjects With Cancer or Plexiform Neurofibromas and Trametinib in Combination With Dabrafenib in Subjects With Cancers Harboring V600 Mutations</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label, Dose-Escalation, Phase I/II Study to Investigate the Safety, Pharmacokinetics, Pharmacodynamics and Clinical Activity of the MEK Inhibitor Trametinib in Children and Adolescents Subjects With Cancer or Plexiform Neurofibromas and Trametinib in Combination With Dabrafenib in Children and Adolescents With Cancers Harboring V600 Mutations</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a 3-part (Part A, Part B, Part C), Phase I/IIa, multi-center, open label, study in
      pediatric subjects with refractory or recurrent tumors.  Part A is a repeat dose, dose
      escalation monotherapy study that will identify the recommended phase II dose (RP2D) on the
      continuous dosing schedule using a 3 + 3 dose-escalation procedure. Part B will evaluate the
      preliminary activity of trametinib monotherapy in 4 disease-specific cohorts of subjects.
      Each cohort will enroll at least 10 response-evaluable subjects (evaluable for response is
      defined as a subject with a pre-dose and at least 1 post-dose disease assessment or clinical
      assessment of progression of disease).  The specifics around the Part C will determined
      after completion of enrollment into Part A.  The overall goal of this trial is to
      efficiently establish safe, pharmacologically relevant dose of trametinib in infants,
      children and adolescents and determine preliminary activity of trametinib monotherapy in
      selected recurrent, refractory or unresectable childhood tumors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety Assessment of trametinib as assessed by Adverse Events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>From screening up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety Assessment of trametinib as assessed by electrocardiogram (ECG)</measure>
    <time_frame>From screening up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Single 12-lead ECGs will be obtained to assess safety</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety Assessment of trametinib as assessed by echocardiogram (ECHO)</measure>
    <time_frame>From screening up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>ECHOs will be performed to assess cardiac ejection fraction and cardiac valve morphology</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety Assessment of trametinib as assessed by changes in laboratory values</measure>
    <time_frame>From screening up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Laboratory assessments will include Hematology, Clinical Chemistry, Routine Urinalysis and Other screening tests</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety Assessment of  trametinib assessed by changes in vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>From screening up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Vital sign measurements will include systolic and diastolic blood pressure, temperature, respiration rate and pulse rate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the dose of trametinib that achieves similar exposures (Ctau) to the recommended adult dose</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 15 and 22</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Steady state Ctau of trametinib</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK Assessment of trametinib</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 15 and Day 22</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PK parameters including Ctau (trough concentration), area under the concentration-time curve over a period of time (AUC [0-t]), area under the concentration-time curve over the dosing interval (AUC [0-tau]), apparent clearance following oral dosing (CL/F), maximum observed concentration (Cmax), Time of occurrence of Cmax (tmax) (tmax) and half-life (t1/2) of trametinib will be assessed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability assessments for trametinib for AEs</measure>
    <time_frame>From screening up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability assessments for trametinib for ECG</measure>
    <time_frame>From screening up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>12-lead ECGs will be performed to assess safety and tolerability</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability assessments for trametinib for changes in laboratory values</measure>
    <time_frame>From screening up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Laboratory parameter including chemistry and hematology</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability assessments for trametinib for vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>From screening up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Vital sign measurements will include systolic and diastolic blood pressure, temperature, respiration rate and pulse rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor response for trametinib</measure>
    <time_frame>From screening up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Disease assessments will be conducted and utilize disease specific response criteria (e.g. RECIST, RANO)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of age and weight on the PK of trametinib</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 15 and Day 22</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PK parameter will include CL/F, volume of distribution (V/F), absorption rate (ka), and coefficients for significant covariates</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">94</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Trametinib Dose-Escalation: Trametinib is administered orally once daily (OD) under fasting conditions.  The starting dose of trametinib (0.0125 milligram per kilogram per dose [mg/kg/dose]) is 50% of the recommended fixed dose in adults (2 mg OD). The second dose level (0.025 mg/kg) is equivalent to the recommended dose in adults (2 mg PO daily). The third dose level (0.040 mg/kg) is equivalent to the maximum tolerated dose [MTD] in adults (3 mg PO daily).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tumor-Specific Expansion: Trametinib is administered orally once daily under fasting conditions in 4 disease-specific cohorts of subjects Trametinib will be continued until disease progression.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The trametinib dose administered in Part C will be the trametinib monotherapy RP2D from Part A.  The monotherapy RP2D of dabrafenib in children will be established on a separate trial (BRF116013). The specifics for Part C will be determined following completion of enrollment into Part A.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trametinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Trametinib is available in tablet (0.125mg, 0.5mg, 2mg dose) as well as in powder form for Oral Solution (0.05mg/mL dose). It is recommended that subjects drink 4 to 6 mL of water/kg body weight following dosing.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dabrafenib</intervention_name>
    <description>Dabrafenib will be administered in combination with trametinib in Part C once the RP2D of dabrafenib and trametinib monotherapy is established in children.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part C</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  General Eligibility Criteria (All Parts)

          -  Written informed consent - a signed informed consent and/or assent (as age
             appropriate) for study participation including PK sampling will be obtained according
             to institutional guidelines.

          -  Male or female between one month and &lt;18 years of age (inclusive) at the time of
             signing the informed consent form (Part C between 12 months and &lt;18 years of age,
             inclusive).

          -  Part A subjects &lt;2 years of age will not be included in the initial dose escalation.

          -  Prior therapy: The subject's cancer (not neurofibromatosis type-1 [NF-1] with
             plexiform neurofibroma [PN] must have relapsed after or failed to respond to
             frontline curative therapy or there must not be other potentially curative treatment
             options available.  Curative therapy may include surgery, radiation therapy,
             chemotherapy, or any combination of these modalities.  All subjects (including NF-1
             with PN) must have recovered to grade &lt;=1 from the acute toxic effects of all prior
             chemotherapy, immunotherapy, or radiotherapy prior to enrollment. Prior therapy
             includes; myelosuppressive chemotherapy, differentiating agents/ biologic response
             modifiers (small molecules, antibodies, viral therapies) (anti-cancer agent),
             non-myelosuppressive anticancer agents, investigational agent, radiation therapy,
             stem cell transplantation or infusion, number of prior treatment regimens, colony
             stimulating factors, corticosteroids.

          -  Performance score of &gt;=50% according to the Karnofsky/Lansky performance status
             scale.

          -  Females of child-bearing potential must be willing to practice acceptable methods of
             birth control.  Additionally, females of childbearing potential must have a negative
             serum pregnancy test within 14 days prior to enrollment.

          -  Must have adequate organ function as defined by the following values: renal function
             - 24 hr creatinine clearance (revised Schwartz formula), or radioisotope glomerular
             filtration rate (GFR) &gt;=60 milliliter (mL)  per minute per 1.73 meter square
             (mL/min/1.73m^2); or a serum creatinine  &lt;=upper limit of normal (ULN) for age and
             gender; liver functions as bilirubin (sum of conjugated + unconjugated) &lt;=1.5 x ULN
             for age, alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &lt;=2.5 x ULN; for the purposes of enrollment
             and toxicity monitoring the ULN for ALT will be 45 unit per liter (U/L); cardiac
             function - corrected QT (QTcB) interval &lt;480 milliseconds (msec), left ventricular
             ejection fraction (LVEF) &gt;=lower limit of normal (LLN) by ECHO.

          -  Able to swallow and retain enterally (per oral [PO] or nasogastric or gastric tube)
             administered medication and does not have any clinically significant gastrointestinal
             abnormalities that may alter absorption such as malabsorption syndrome or major
             resection of the stomach or bowels.

          -  French subjects: In France, a subject will be eligible for inclusion in this study
             only if either affiliated to or a beneficiary of a social security category.

          -  Specific Eligibility Criteria, Part A

          -  Subjects must meet general eligibility criteria.

          -  Histologically confirmed solid tumors, which may include but are not limited to
             rhabdomyosarcoma and other soft tissue sarcomas, Ewing sarcoma family of tumors,
             osteosarcoma, neuroblastoma, Wilms' tumor, hepatic tumors, germ cell tumors, and
             primary brain tumors.  In subjects with brain stem gliomas the requirement for
             histological confirmation can be waived if a biopsy was not performed.

          -  Measurable or evaluable tumors.  Subjects with neuroblastoma that is only detectable
             by MIBG scan are eligible and considered to have measurable disease using the Curie
             scale.  Subjects with neuroblastoma that is only detected by bone marrow
             aspirate/biopsy or elevated homovanillic acid / vanillylmandelic acid (HVA/VMA) are
             not eligible.

          -  Adequate bone marrow function defined as absolute neutrophil count (ANC)
             &gt;=1000/microliter, hemoglobin &gt;=8.0 gram per deciliter (g/dL) (may receive red blood
             cell transfusions), platelets &gt;=75,000/ microliter (transfusion independent, defined
             as not receiving platelet transfusions within a 7 day period prior to enrollment).

          -  Specific Eligibility Criteria, Part B

          -  Subjects must meet general eligibility criteria. The specific eligibility criteria
             listed here will apply to subjects enrolling to different cohorts of Part B.

          -  Tumor tissue (archived or fresh) is required and must be available to be shipped to
             GSK.

          -  Solid tumor cohort (B1) specific criteria

          -  B1:  Refractory or relapsed neuroblastoma

          -  B2:  Recurrent or unresectable low grade gliomas with BRAF tandem duplication with
             fusion

          -  B3:  Neurofibromatosis Type -1 associated plexiform neurofibromas (NF-1 with PN) that
             are unresectable and medically significant.

          -  B4:  BRAF V600 mutant tumors.

          -  Specific Eligibility Criteria, Part C - to be determined after completion of
             enrollment into Part A

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Lactating or pregnant female.

          -  History of another malignancy including resected non-melanomatous skin cancer.

          -  Subjects with NF-1 associated optic pathway tumors are excluded if they are actively
             receiving therapy for the optic pathway tumor or do not meet criteria for PN or
             malignant solid tumor or relapsed leukemia (Subjects with NF-1 and isolated optic
             pathway tumors as only site of evaluable tumor are not eligible for enrollment).

          -  Subjects with a history of NF-1 related cerebral vascular anomaly are excluded.

          -  Subjects with NF-1 and active optic glioma are excluded.

          -  Subjects with NF-1 and PN that cannot be evaluated by volumetric analysis.

          -  Any serious and/or unstable pre-existing medical, psychiatric disorder or other
             conditions that could interfere with subject's safety, obtaining informed consent or
             compliance to the study procedures.

          -  Any prohibited medication(s), currently used or expected to be required.

          -  Any medications for treatment of left ventricular systolic dysfunction.

          -  Part B only: Previous treatment with trametinib or another MEK inhibitor.

          -  Administration of an investigational study treatment within 30 days preceding the
             first dose of study treatment(s) in this study.

          -  Have a known immediate or delayed hypersensitivity reaction or idiosyncrasy to drugs
             chemically related to study treatment or excipients that contraindicate their
             participation.

          -  Current active liver or biliary disease (with the exception of Gilbert's syndrome or
             asymptomatic gallstones, or liver metastases).

          -  History of hepatic sinusoid obstructive syndrome (venoocculsive disease) within the
             prior 3 months.

          -  History of sensitivity to heparin or heparin-induced thrombocytopenia.

          -  History of interstitial lung disease or pneumonitis.

          -  History of or current evidence of retinal vein occlusion (RVO) or retinal pigment
             epithelium detachment (RPED).

          -  For subjects with solid tumors that are not primary central nervous system (CNS)
             tumors, subjects with symptomatic or untreated leptomeningeal or brain metastases or
             spinal cord compression are excluded. NOTE: Subjects previously treated for these
             conditions that have had stable CNS disease (verified with consecutive imaging
             studies) for &gt;3 months, are asymptomatic and are not currently taking
             corticosteroids, or are on stable dose or decreasing of corticosteroids for at least
             7 days prior to enrolment are permitted.

          -  A history of known Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV), Hepatitis B Virus (HBV), or
             Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) infection.

          -  Unresolved toxicity of National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for
             Adverse Events, version 4.0 (NCI CTCAE v4.0) Grade 2 or higher from previous
             anti-cancer therapy, except alopecia.

          -  Presence of active gastrointestinal (GI) disease or other condition that will
             interfere significantly with the absorption of drugs.  If clarification is needed as
             to whether a condition will significantly affect absorption of drugs, contact the
             GlaxoSmithKline (GSK) medical monitor for guidance to enrol the subject.

          -  A history or evidence of cardiovascular disease: abnormal cardiac valve morphology
             (&gt;=Grade 2) documented by echocardiogram.  Subjects with moderate valvular thickening
             should not be entered on study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Month</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
    <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 8, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 24, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>v600-mutation</keyword>
  <keyword>neuroblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Trametinib</keyword>
  <keyword>pediatrics</keyword>
  <keyword>low grade glioma plexiform neurofibromas</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neurofibroma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neurofibroma, Plexiform</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
