<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="53668">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01938131</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1346/2012</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01938131</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Effectiveness of rMV (Repeated Muscle Vibration) in Knee Osteoarthritis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of Treatment With rMV (Repeated Muscle Vibration) in Patients Affected by Knee Osteoarthritis: a Prospective Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Catholic University of the Sacred Heart</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Catholic University of the Sacred Heart</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Italy: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The rehabilitation protocols in knee osteoarthritis are often difficult to be applied in
      elderly patients because they are long lasting and need the constant participation of
      patients. To rapidly improve the motor performances of patients it is possible to use the
      mechanical vibration applied to individual muscles using a protocol called &quot;repeated muscle
      vibration&quot; (rMV). The purpose of this single-blind randomized placebo-controlled study is to
      evaluate the effectiveness of the repeated muscle vibration (rMV) in terms of increasing the
      ability of the patients affected by knee osteoarthritis, compared to an ineffective
      treatment, considered as a placebo. Each subject, randomly assigned to either the group 1
      (study group) or placebo-treatment (group 2)is administered 3 daily applications of rMV of
      10 minutes each, for 3 consecutive days. Between two successive applications it's observed a
      break of at least 15 seconds. The probe of the specific instrument (Cro 速 System) is placed
      near the supero-medial margin of the patella, on both quadriceps. Patients in group 2
      (control group) are subjected to a treatment with muscle released in which the probe of the
      same instrument is approached to the quadriceps, without making contact. The instrument in
      these conditions emits a buzz but not provokes muscle vibration. The primary outcome of the
      study is to determine the changing in patients' ability (as measured by WOMAC scale =
      Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index) . The secondary outcomes of
      the study are the assessment of changing of patients' balance and risk of falling (as
      measured by the Tinetti scale) and assessment of changing of patients' quality of life (as
      measured by EQ-VAS= EuroQuality of Life-VAS scale).Outcome measures are administered at
      baseline (T0), at the end of the treatment protocol (T1), at 1 month (T2), 3 months (T3)
      after the end of treatment and 6 months (T4) after the end of the treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>changing in patients' ability (as measured by WOMAC scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (T0), at the end of the treatment protocol (T1), at 1 month (T2), 3 months (T3) after the end of treatment, 6 months (T4) after the end of the treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>administration of WOMAC scale for patient's ability evaluation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>assessment of changing of patients' balance and risk of falling (as measured by the Tinetti scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (T0), at the end of the treatment protocol (T1), at 1 month (T2), 3 months (T3) after the end of treatment, 6 months (T4) after the end of the treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>administration of Tinetti scale for patient's balance and risk of falling evaluation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>assessment of changing of patients' quality of life (as measured by EQ-VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (T0), at the end of the treatment protocol (T1), at 1 month (T2), 3 months (T3) after the end of treatment, 6 months (T4) after the end of the treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>administration of EQ-VAS scale for patient's pain evaluation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Knee Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this group will be subjected to a treatment with muscle released in which the probe of CroSystem instrument will be approached to the quadriceps, without making contact. The instrument in these conditions emits a buzz but not provokes muscle vibration</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>repeated Muscle Vibration</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patients will be subjected to 3 daily applications of rMV of 10 minutes each, for 3 consecutive days. Between two successive applications will be observed a break of at least 15 seconds. The probe of the specific instrument (Cro 速 System) will be placed near the supero-medial margin of the patella, on both quadriceps</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>repeated Muscle Vibration (rMV) (Cro 速 System)</intervention_name>
    <description>The patients will be subjected to 3 daily applications of rMV of 10 minutes each, for 3 consecutive days. Between two successive applications will be observed a break of at least 15 seconds. The probe of the specific instrument (Cro 速 System) will be placed near the supero-medial margin of the patella, on both quadriceps</description>
    <arm_group_label>repeated Muscle Vibration</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Knee Osteoarthritis

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Neurologic disease involving the lower limbs or causing balance problems

          -  Systemic inflammatory diseases

          -  Diabetic Neuropathy

          -  Severe heart disease.

          -  Acute infections or bone Tuberculosis

          -  Prosthetic lower limbs

          -  History of surgery on the affected knee in the last year

          -  History of cancer

          -  Cognitive impairment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital &quot;A. Gemelli&quot;, Catholic University of the Sacred Heart</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rome</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 9, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 5, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Catholic University of the Sacred Heart</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carlo Bertolini</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>knee, osteoarthritis, muscle vibration</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
