<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="82243">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01822548</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012-005399-32</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01822548</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Vildagliptin vs. Glibenclamide on Circulating Endothelial Progenitor Cell Number Type 2 Diabetes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized, Open Label, Two Parallel Arms, Intervention Trial Comparing the Effect of DPP-IV Inhibitor Vildagliptin vs. Glibenclamide on Circulating Endothelial Progenitor Cell Number in Patients With Type 2 Diabetes in Metformin Failure</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria di Parma</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria di Parma</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Italy: The Italian Medicines Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the effect of DPP-IV inhibitor Vildagliptin vs.
      Glibenclamide on circulating endothelial progenitor cells (EPCs) number in type 2 diabetes
      patients in metformin failure. Subjects will be followed for 12 months after randomization.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Diabetic patients show a higher cardiovascular risk compared with non-diabetic patients. It
      is therefore crucial that blood glucose lowering drugs reveal a favorable cardiovascular
      risk profile independently of metabolic control.

      EPCs are a subset of circulating mononuclear cells derived from the bone marrow. EPCs play a
      fundamental role in the formation of new blood vessels (neo-endothelization) and repairing
      of existing blood vessels (re-endothelization) in order to maintain endothelial homeostasis
      and integrity. Endothelial damage and tissue ischemia, through the release of growth factors
      and cytokines, represent a strong stimulus for the mobilization of EPCs from the bone
      marrow. Reduced EPC number has been related to the presence of traditional risk factors for
      cardiovascular disease and to the development of atherosclerosis and has been shown to
      predict cardiovascular (CV)risk. Type 2 diabetes is known to be associated with an increased
      CV risk and a reduced EPC number. Recent data suggest that DDP-IV inhibitors might be
      involved in the mechanisms promoting bone-marrow EPC mobilization. This putative ancillary
      effect of DPP-IV might have a favorable impact on type 2 diabetes, a condition
      characterized by an increased CV risk.

      This is a randomized, open-label, active-treatment-controlled, two parallel arm (2:1),
      intervention trial comparing DPP-IV inhibitor Vildagliptin (100 mg daily) with Glibenclamide
      (maximum daily dose of 10 mg). Treatment allocation and titration regimens are not blinded.

      Primary end-point:Absolute and relative change in the EPC number at visit: V0
      (randomization), V2 (month 4), V3 (month 8) and V4 (month 12).

      Secondary end-point: Absolute and relative change in HbA1C compared to baseline.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Absolute and relative change in the EPC number</measure>
    <time_frame>V0 (randomization) , V2 (month 4), V3 (month 8), V4 (month 12).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Absolute and relative change in HbA1C compared to baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>V0 (randomization), V2 (month4), V3 (month8), V4 (month 12).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">94</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vildagliptin &amp; metformin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Vildagliptin 100 mg tablet and metformin (max dose=2500 mg) tablet daily oral administration</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Glibenclamide &amp; metformin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Glibenclamide maximum dose of 10 mg tablet and metformin (max dose=2500 mg) tablet daily oral administration</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vildagliptin</intervention_name>
    <description>100 mg daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vildagliptin &amp; metformin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LAF237A</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Glibenclamide</intervention_name>
    <description>2.5 mg (total daily), progressively increased up to a maximum dose of 5 mg x 2/ day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Glibenclamide &amp; metformin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age equal or above 35 years;

          -  Diagnosis of type 2 diabetes mellitus as defined by the American Diabetes Association
             , with at least one year of disease duration at the time of the screening visit;

          -  Blood glucose lowering treatment with Metformin alone (monotherapy) at a stable dose
             of at least 1.5 g/day (or maximum tolerated dose) in the 3 months prior to the
             screening visit;

          -  Insufficient metabolic control as defined by recent (last six months) HbA1c ≥ 7% in
             any peripheral laboratory and confirmed at the time of the screening;

          -  Absence of a recent clinically-relevant progression of micro- and macro-vascular
             complications (see exclusion criteria);

          -  Written informed consent to participate to the study.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Age below 35 years

          -  Type 1 diabetes or other causes of diabetes (pancreatectomy, gestational diabetes,
             etc.)

          -  HbA1c &lt; 7% or ≥ 9% at the screening visit

          -  Treatment with any blood glucose lowering treatment other than Metformin in the six
             months before screening visit

          -  BMI &lt; 20 or ≥ 40 kg/m2, or current/ past history of clinically-relevant eating
             disorders (including -but no limited to- nervous anorexia, bulimia, binge-eating
             disorders, etc.)

          -  Significant progression of diabetic macro-angiopathy or cardiovascular disease in the
             six months prior to study visit

          -  Significant progression of diabetic micro-angiopathy in the six months prior to study
             visit

          -  Organ failure or other severe diseases limiting life expectancy;

          -  Beginning, in the three months before screening visit, of any kind of drug which can
             modify glycemic levels (beta-blockers, diuretics…), or acute disease (acute
             infection, urinary tract infection…) in three months before screening visit

          -  History of inflammatory/infective/autoimmune chronic disease

          -  History of unexplained pancreatitis, chronic pancreatitis, pancreatectomy, gastric
             surgery, inflammatory bowel disease;

          -  Any clinically significant abnormality identified on physical examination, laboratory
             tests, ECG or vital signs at screening that in the judgment of the investigator would
             preclude safe completion of the study;

          -  Uncontrolled or inadequately controlled hypertension at screening (SBP&gt;190 or DBP
             &gt;100 mmHg)

          -  Ongoing pregnancy or absence of effective contraception in women with childbearing
             potential

          -  Contraindications to the maintenance of the background therapy (Metformin), including
             -but not limited to- chronic kidney failure or plasma creatinine concentrations &gt; 1.5
             mg/dL, severe respiratory failure, etc.;

          -  Contraindications to the use of a Sulfonylurea;

          -  Contraindications to the use of a DPP-IV Inhibitor;

          -  Laboratory findings, or other disease conditions, at the screening visit that might
             interfere with study measurements:

               1. Hemoglobinopathy known to affect HbA1c assays;

               2. Known chronic liver diseases, including HBV and HCV infection;

               3. Liver makers (AST, ALT, ALP, GGT, bilirubin) above 2 times the upper normal
                  limit;

               4. Amylase and/or lipase above 2 times the upper normal limit;

          -  Chronic use of systemic and/or inhaled corticosteroids (only topical corticosteroids
             are allowed);

          -  History of low compliance, clinically-relevant psychiatric disorders or any current/
             historical finding suggesting the patient as inappropriate to follow the study
             procedures.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ivana Zavaroni, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Azienda Ospedaliera-Universitaria di Parma</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ivana Zavaroni, MD</last_name>
    <email>ivana.zavaroni@unipr.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alessandra Dei Cas, MD PhD</last_name>
    <email>alessandra.deicas@unipr.it</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera-Universitaria</name>
      <address>
        <city>Parma</city>
        <zip>43126</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Opedaliera-Universitaria</name>
      <address>
        <city>Parma</city>
        <zip>43126</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ivana Zavaroni, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0521033295</phone>
      <phone_ext>0039</phone_ext>
      <email>ivana.zavaroni@unipr.it</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>ivana zavaroni, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 28, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 28, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria di Parma</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ivana Zavaroni</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>EPC</keyword>
  <keyword>diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>DPP IV inhibitors</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Vildagliptin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glyburide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
