<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="80789">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02128347</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>eportal 2014-316</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02128347</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of an Online Portal for Delivery of Care to Home Dialysis Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of an Online Portal for Delivery of Care to Home Dialysis Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Karthik Tennankore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Capital District Health Authority, Canada</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Home dialysis has many potential benefits compared to in-center hemodialysis including
      improved quality of life, reduced hospital admission and reduced cost. However, some
      patients perceive that home modalities are associated with increased isolation from the
      healthcare system, substandard care or higher risk of catastrophic events. Providing better
      support for home dialysis patients may enhance their ability to maintain at home, improve
      their health outcomes, increase quality of life and improve satisfaction with care. In other
      chronic disease populations a secure, online communication portal between physicians and
      patients has proven useful in enhancing care for patients. Thus far, the utility of an
      online portal communication system has not been tested in a cohort of home dialysis
      patients. The investigators hypothesize that this novel form of communication will improve
      care and outcomes for home dialysis patients. Therefore, in a cohort of home dialysis
      patients, the purposes of this study are as follows: 1) Does an online patient-portal
      improve quality of life? 2) Does an online patient-portal improve patient satisfaction with
      home dialysis care?  3) Does an online patient-portal reduce hospitalization and health
      service utilization? 4) Does an online portal improve patient self-efficacy?
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Home dialysis (including peritoneal dialysis and home hemodialysis) has a number of
      potential benefits over in-center hemodialysis (including lower healthcare costs and
      improved quality of life for patients). However, overall quality of life remains low
      compared to the general population. Furthermore, home dialysis patients (primarily those on
      peritoneal dialysis) continue to experience a high rate of hospitalization. Finally, there
      can be improvement in patient satisfaction with home dialysis, particularly in the areas of
      shared decision making and handling of patient requests.

      Regarding satisfaction with care, peritoneal dialysis patients have identified that
      &quot;attentiveness to concerns&quot;, and clarity of recommendations is important. Improved
      satisfaction in turn, may be associated with improvements in quality of life. Therefore,
      identifying novel communication systems for home dialysis patients is crucial. The use of
      eHealth online portals that support online communication between patients and healthcare
      workers is increasing. An interface that allows patients to discuss treatment plans and
      address clinical problems while obviating the need for telephone communication has been
      shown to be beneficial in some studies. Such a system may improve patient satisfaction,
      reduce health service utilization, and potentially improve health outcomes.

      Thus far, the feasibility and potential benefit of an eHealth online portal to facilitate
      communication has not been evaluated in home dialysis. Therefore, in a cohort of home
      dialysis patients, the purpose of this study is to identify the following: 1) Does an online
      portal improve quality of life? 2) Does an online portal improve patient satisfaction with
      home dialysis care? 3) Does an online portal reduce hospitalization and health service
      utilization? 4) Does an online portal improve patient self-efficacy? Overall, we hope that
      this pilot study will inform the need to pursue a larger, multicenter trial to more
      rigorously evaluate the utility of this novel form of communication for home dialysis
      patients.

      We will conduct a prospective study of prevalent (receiving home dialysis for at least three
      months) home dialysis patients (including both peritoneal dialysis and home hemodialysis) at
      Capital Health. Consecutive patients that are evaluated in the home dialysis clinic over a
      4-month period (September to December 2014) will be enrolled in the study if they provide
      consent. We anticipate that this time frame will ensure that we can accrue our minimum
      target sample of patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient quality of life will be measured in all patients at 0, 6 and 12 months after initiating the study. Specifically, change from baseline in components of the Kidney Disease Quality of Life (KDQOL) will be evaluated at 6 and 12 months after initiation of the patient portal. While all aspects of the KDQOL will be examined, the patient satisfaction item will be of primary interest (acknowledging that this is intuitively most responsive to changes in process of care).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Patient Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient satisfaction will be examined in all patients at 0,6 and 12 months using the Consumer Quality index (CQI)  instrument. This Dutch-language tool will be translated to English using a validated translation procedure. In addition, Satisfaction with the technology itself will be evaluated by assessing change in the acceptability E scale, a validated tool to accept usability of computerized health programs</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospitalization and Health-Care Utilization Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Healthcare service utilization will consist of number and duration of hospitalizations, number of emergency room visits (for both dialysis and non-dialysis related complaints), number of non-advised drop-in visits to the home dialysis unit and number of telephone contacts with the home dialysis unit. All utilization measures will be retrospectively assessed over the preceding three to twelve months (depending on available data) to get a baseline rate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dialysis Self-Efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Self-efficacy will be evaluated using a specific self-efficacy scale developed for dialysis patients (BMC Nephrol. 2011 Jan 28;12:4. doi: 10.1186/1471-2369-12-4). Once again, scales will be completed at baseline and at 6 and 12 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Hemodialysis, Home</condition>
  <condition>Peritoneal Dialysis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Electronic Patient Portal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>RelayHealth is a web-based application that allows patients and healthcare workers to communicate through a secure, password protected online portal with data transfer capabilities. Effectiveness of the portal in improving several health outcomes from baseline-12 months will be assessed in this study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Electronic Patient Portal</intervention_name>
    <description>RelayHealth is a web-based application that allows patients and clinicians to communicate through a secure, password protected online electronic portal with data transfer capabilities. The system allows physicians and nurses to view patient questions, patient data and transmit messages to patients in response to questions or after clinic visits in an electronic message. In addition, patients can be made aware of upcoming investigations or clinic visits. Patients can also use the interface to identify any proposed changes (which would minimize recall mistakes after clinic visits) and submit queries pertaining to dialysis. Both patients and clinicians are made aware of new messages through email prompt, which moderates the asynchronous nature of electronic communication. Telephone communication can be maintained, but reserved for more urgent issues that require immediate assistance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Electronic Patient Portal</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Prevalent home dialysis (peritoneal dialysis or home hemodialysis) patients (on
             dialysis for at least 3 months)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Does not provide consent

          -  On home dialysis for less than 3 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karthik K Tennankore, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Capital District Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karthik K Tennankore, MD</last_name>
    <phone>902-473-2099</phone>
    <email>KarthikK.Tennankore@cdha.nshealth.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Capital Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Halifax</city>
        <state>Nova Scotia</state>
        <zip>B3H 1V8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karthik K Tennankore, MD</last_name>
      <phone>902-473-2099</phone>
      <email>KarthikK.Tennankore@cdha.nshealth.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karthik K Tennankore, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 30, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 29, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Capital District Health Authority, Canada</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Karthik Tennankore</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor, Division of Nephrology, Department of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hemodialysis, Home</keyword>
  <keyword>Peritoneal Dialysis</keyword>
  <keyword>Telemedicine</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
