<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="116001">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01899768</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>117270</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01899768</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>GSK2339345 Hypertussive Challenge Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomised, Double-Blind (Sponsor-Unblind), Placebo Controlled, Cross-Over Study to Investigate the Efficacy, Effect on Cough Reflex Sensitivity, Safety, Tolerability and Pharmacokinetics of Inhaled GSK2339345 in Patients With Chronic Idiopathic Cough Using an Aqueous Droplet Inhaler</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>North West Lung Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed to evaluate the effect of GSK2339345 relative to placebo on the
      number of coughs in patients with Chronic Idiopathic Cough (CIC) administered by an Aqueous
      Droplet Inhaler (ADI). The primary aim is to investigate the efficacy of GSK2339345 on
      reducing objective cough frequency in CIC patients. The secondary aim of this study is to
      investigate the efficacy of GSK2339345 in inhibiting a hypertussive cough response elicited
      by capsaicin and citric acid in CIC patients which have a hyperresponsive cough reflex.

      Following the screening visit, all eligible subjects will attend the unit for dosing at
      Visits 1-7. At Visits 1, 2 and 3 (Part A of the study), subjects will receive two doses of
      either GSK2339345 or placebo, 4 hours apart and will undergo 8 hours of cough monitoring. At
      Visits 4 and 5 (Part B of the study) and Visits 6 and 7 (Part C of the study), subjects will
      be administered a single dose of either GSK2339345 or placebo. Subjects will then undergo
      capsaicin (Part B) or citric acid (Part C) tussive challenge and will undergo cough
      monitoring for 1 hour post dose.

      The maximum study duration will be approximately 11 weeks, including 3 weeks screening and 2
      weeks follow-up. Approximately 30 patients will be randomised into the study, such that
      approximately 24 patients complete dosing and critical assessments.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total cough counts in Part A.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Total cough counts (8 hours of recording) at Visits 1, 2 and 3 (4 hours of post-dose recording for each of the two doses administered) will be done to evaluate the effect of a single dose of GSK2339345 versus placebo  on objective cough counts in patients with chronic idiopathic cough. Coughs will be counted by a cough monitor fitted to subjects for 8 hours post Dose 1.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of coughs following each dose of capsaicin, following a single dose of GSK2339345 or placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The cough count will be performed by a cough monitor fitted to subjects for 1 hour post dose</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of coughs following each dose of citric acid, following a single dose of GSK2339345 or placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The cough count will be performed by a cough monitor fitted to subjects for 1 hour post dose</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cough counts following GSK2339345 or placebo at Visits 1, 2 and 3 over shorter epochs (e.g. 1 hour or 15 minute intervals)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The cough count will be performed by a cough monitor fitted to subjects for 8 hours post dose</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urge to cough visual analogue scale (VAS) 1 hour post-last dose at Visits 1, 2 and 3</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subjects will be asked to subjectively assess their urge to cough using a VAS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cough severity VAS 1 hour post-last dose at Visits 1, 2 and 3</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subjects will be asked to subjectively assess their cough severity using a VAS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the safety profile of GSK2339345 versus placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety parameters include: Adverse events, vital signs (including systolic and diastolic blood pressure and heart rate.), electrocardiograms (ECG), body temperature, laboratory assessments (including haematology, clinical chemistry and cardiac troponin), and forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1) as a measure of lung function, and oropharyngeal sensate changes (four point scale).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The systemic pharmacokinetics (PK) profile of GSK2339345.</measure>
    <time_frame>PK samples will be collected at pre-dose, 2 minutes (mins), 5 mins, 10 mins, 30 mins, 1 hour, and 2 hours post dose 1 at visits 1, 2 and 3.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PK parameters include: Area under concentration-time curve from time zero to 1 hour (AUC [0 to 1]), AUC from time zero to 4 hours (AUC [0 to 4]), AUC from time zero to 24 hours (AUC [0 to 24]), maximum observed concentration (Cmax), and time of occurrence of Cmax (Tmax).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Cough</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive treatment A (placebo) or treatment B (GSK2339345) in 3 visits of part A (one treatment per visit) in one of the following four sequences: ABA, ABB, BAA, and BAB.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive treatment A or treatment B in 2 visits of part B (one treatment per visit) in one of the following two sequences: AB and BA. Subjects will then orally inhale 10 microliter (mcL) of a capsaicin solution of strength ranging from 0.49 micromolar (mcM) to 1000 mcM, which will be administered using a breath activated dosimeter approximately 5 minutes post-dosing with treatment A or B at Visits 4 and 5.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive treatment A or treatment B in 2 visits of part C (one treatment per visit) in one of the following two sequences: AB and BA. Subjects will then orally inhale 10 mcL of a citric acid solution of strength ranging from 0.03 to 4.0 M, which will be administered using a breath activated dosimeter approximately 5 minutes post-dosing with treatment A or B at Visits 6 and 7.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GSK2339345</intervention_name>
    <description>Clear colorless solution in clear glass vial for oral inhalation via aqueous droplet inhaler with unit dose strength of 1000 microgram (mcg) inhaled in two actuations.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part C</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Clear colorless solution of 0.9% sodium chloride for oral inhalation via aqueous droplet inhaler inhaled in two actuations.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part C</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          -  Chronic Idiopathic Cough patients according to the criteria listed below, determined
             by a responsible and experienced physician, based on a medical evaluation: Idiopathic
             cough defined as chronic cough resistant to treatment targeted at potential triggers.
             Chronic cough defined as cough lasting for more than 8 weeks.

          -  A patient with a clinical abnormality or laboratory parameters outside the reference
             range for the population being studied may be included only if the Investigator and
             the GSK Medical Monitor agree that the finding is unlikely to introduce additional
             risk factors and will not interfere with the study procedures.

          -  Male/females aged &gt;=18 years old, at the time of signing the informed consent.

          -  Non-smoker for at least 6 months with a cumulative history of &lt;= 10 pack years. Pack
             years = (No. of cigarettes smoked/day/20) x (No. of years smoked).

          -  Body weight &gt;= 50 kilograms.

          -  A female subject is eligible to participate if she is of; Non-childbearing potential
             defined as pre-menopausal females with a documented tubal ligation or hysterectomy
             [for this definition, &quot;documented&quot; refers to the outcome of the
             investigator's/designee's review of the subject's medical history for study
             eligibility, as obtained via a verbal interview with the subject or from the
             subject's medical records]; or postmenopausal defined as 12 months of spontaneous
             amenorrhea [in questionable cases a blood sample with simultaneous follicle
             stimulating hormone  &gt; 40 milli international unit/milliliter (mL) and estradiol &lt; 40
             picogram/ml (&lt;147 picomoles/Liter [L]) is confirmatory].  Females on hormone
             replacement therapy (HRT) and whose menopausal status is in doubt will be required to
             use one of the contraception methods if they wish to continue their HRT during the
             study.  Otherwise, they must discontinue HRT to allow confirmation of post-menopausal
             status prior to study enrollment.  For most forms of HRT, at least 2 to4 weeks will
             elapse between the cessation of therapy and the blood draw; this interval depends on
             the type and dosage of HRT. Following confirmation of their post-menopausal status,
             they can resume use of HRT during the study without use of a contraceptive method.

        Child-bearing potential with negative pregnancy test as determined by serum human
        chorionic gonadotropin test at screening or prior to dosing and Agrees to use one of the
        contraception methods for an appropriate period of time (as determined by the product
        label or investigator) prior to the start of dosing to sufficiently minimize the risk of
        pregnancy at that point.  Female subjects must agree to use contraception until the follow
        up visit or has only same-sex partners, when this is her preferred and usual lifestyle.

          -  Male subjects with female partners of child-bearing potential must agree to use one
             of the contraception methods.  This criterion must be followed from the time of the
             first dose of study medication until the follow up visit.

          -  Capable of giving written informed consent, which includes compliance with the
             requirements and restrictions listed in the consent form.

          -  Aspartate amino transferase and alanine amino transferase  &lt; 2xupper limit of normal
             (ULN); alkaline phosphatase and bilirubin &lt;= 1.5xULN (isolated bilirubin &gt;1.5xULN is
             acceptable if bilirubin is fractionated and direct bilirubin &lt;35%).

          -  Based on averaged QT interval corrected (QTc) values of triplicate electrocardiograms
             (ECGs) obtained over a brief recording period: QTc using Fridericia's formula (QTcF)
             &lt; 450 millisecond.

          -  A 24 hour Holter ECG at screening that demonstrates no clinically significant
             abnormalities or finding that could interfere with interpretation of the study
             results, when assessed by an appropriately trained and experienced reviewer.

        Exclusion Criteria Based Upon Medical Histories

          -  Subjects who have evidence of current asthma, as confirmed by the Investigator or
             designee.

          -  Subjects with any clinically significant respiratory condition or lung pathology that
             could cause cough (apart from chronic idiopathic cough).

          -  Known lung cancer or other active malignancy, or history of.

          -  Subjects with current or a chronic history of cardiovascular disease (including
             uncontrolled hypertension, ischemic heart disease, angina, myocardial infarct,
             congestive heart failure, and stroke).

          -  Subjects with current central nervous system / peripheral nervous system conditions
             e.g. epilepsy and myasthenia gravis.

          -  Current or chronic history of liver disease, or known hepatic or biliary
             abnormalities (with the exception of Gilbert's syndrome or asymptomatic gallstones).

          -  Any subject with a respiratory tract infection within 4 weeks of screening.

          -  Radiological imaging prior to the study, including chest X-rays, that have shown any
             evidence of clinically significant lung disease, as judged by the Investigator or
             designee.

          -  History of regular alcohol consumption within 6 months of the study defined as an
             average weekly intake of &gt;21 units for males or &gt;14 units for females. One unit is
             equivalent to 8 grams of alcohol: a half-pint (approximately 240 mL) of beer, 1 glass
             (125 mL) of wine or 1 (25 mL) measure of spirits.

          -  Any subject who has a history of an allergic reaction to a local anesthetic. History
             of sensitivity to any of the study medications, or components thereof or a history of
             drug or other allergy that, in the opinion of the investigator or GlaxoSmithKline
             (GSK) Medical Monitor, contraindicates their participation.

          -  Any subject who has a known hypersensitivity to capsaicin or citric acid. Exclusion
             Criteria Based Upon Diagnostic Assessment

          -  A positive pre-study Hepatitis B surface antigen or positive Hepatitis C antibody
             result within 3 months of screening.

          -  Any subject who, upon oropharyngeal examination, is deemed by the Investigator to be
             unsuitable for oropharyngeal sensation assessments. This includes any injuries to the
             mucosa of the mouth or pharynx that could potentially increase systemic absorption
             e.g. oropharyngeal candidiasis.

          -  FEV1 less than 80% of the predicted normal value prior to first dosing of the study

          -  Any subject who does not reach C5 following an oral inhalation of capsaicin at a dose
             level of 250 micromolar at screening.

          -  Urinary cotinine levels indicative of smoking or history or regular use of tobacco-
             or nicotine-containing products within 6 months prior to screening.

          -  A positive pre-study drug/alcohol screen. Other Exclusion Criteria

          -  Subjects who are unable to use the inhaler satisfactorily.

          -  Where participation in the study would result in donation of blood or blood products
             in excess of 500 mL within a 56 day period.

          -  Lactating females.

          -  The subject has participated in a clinical trial and has received an investigational
             product within the following time period prior to the first dosing day in the current
             study: 30 days, 5 half-lives or twice the duration of the biological effect of the
             investigational product (whichever is longer).

          -  Exposure to more than four new chemical entities within 12 months prior to the first
             dosing day.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
    <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manchester</city>
        <state>Lancashire</state>
        <zip>M23 9LT</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Belfast</city>
        <zip>BT9 7AB</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 11, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>efficacy</keyword>
  <keyword>hypertussive challenge</keyword>
  <keyword>voltage gated sodium channels (VGSC)</keyword>
  <keyword>anaesthesia</keyword>
  <keyword>Safety and tolerability</keyword>
  <keyword>capsaicin challenge</keyword>
  <keyword>cough</keyword>
  <keyword>citric acid challenge</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cough</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
