<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="23248">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01740713</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DEEP-1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01740713</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pharmacokinetic Study of Deferiprone in Paediatric Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>DEEP-1</acronym>
  <official_title>Multi-centre, Oral Single Dose Experimental and Modelling Study to Evaluate the Pharmacokinetics of Deferiprone in Patients Aged From 1 Month to Less Than 6 Years of Age Affected by Transfusion-dependent Haemoglobinopathies.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Consorzio per Valutazioni Biologiche e Farmacologiche</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>European Commission</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Consorzio per Valutazioni Biologiche e Farmacologiche</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>European Union: European Medicines Agency</authority>
    <authority>Italy: The Italian Medicines Agency</authority>
    <authority>Egypt: Ministry of Health, Drug Policy and Planning Center</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Deferiprone (DFP) is the most extensively studied oral iron chelator to date. It has been
      authorised in Europe in 1999 for the treatment of iron overload in patients with
      beta-thalassaemia major when DFO is contraindicated or inadequate. Despite a wide experience
      of DFP there are limited experimental data available on DFP in children and no
      pharmacokinetic data in children under 6 years of age. On the basis of the existing data in
      adults and adolescent, in the DEEP-1 trial a pharmacokinetic bridging model will be
      developed to support the dose selection in children aged less than 6 years. The study will
      consist of two phases, namely an experimental phase, during which patients will receive a
      single dose and a modeling phase, during which PK data obtained after single dose in
      patients &lt; 6 years of age will be analysed in conjunction with historical PK data in adults
      and older children and adolescents. The model-based analysis of the data obtained after
      single dose will enable the assessment of the dosing regimen required for the purpose of
      accurate pharmacokinetic bridging. The ratio between the predicted systemic exposure
      parameters (AUC and Cmax) in the target population and reference group will be used as basis
      for recommendation of the dose in the target population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, day 6</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>CL/F, Vd/F, Ka, AUC, Cmax, Tmax, Css and Cmin</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, day 6</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Clinical safety and tolerability data including ferritin levels, spontaneous AE reporting, ECGs, vital signs, nursing/physician observation and clinical laboratory values (haematology and biochemistry).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Iron Overload</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>deferiprone liquid formulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Deferiprone will be administered as single dose at 3 dose levels:
25 mg/kg/day
50 mg/kg/day
100 mg/kg/day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Deferiprone</intervention_name>
    <description>deferiprone liquid oral solution (80 mg/ml)</description>
    <arm_group_label>deferiprone liquid formulation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients in a chronic transfusional program who have received at least 150 ml/kg/year
             of packed red blood cells (corresponding approximately to 12 transfusions) and on
             current treatment with DFO, DFX, DFP; aged from 1 month to less than 6 years; or

          -  Patients naïve to any chelation treatment who have received not less than 150 ml/kg
             of packed red blood cells (corresponding to approximately 12 transfusions) and have
             ferritin levels &gt; 800 ng/mL, aged from 1 month to less than 6 years; or

          -  Patients who meet the transfusion criteria (150 ml/kg/year corresponding
             approximately to 12 transfusions) and have known intolerance or contraindication to
             DFO

        And if all of the following criteria apply:

          -  Patients affected by any hereditary haemoglobinopathies requiring chronic transfusion
             therapy including but not limited to thalassaemia and sickle cell disease

          -  Written informed consent obtained from their legal guardian on the patient's behalf
             in accordance with the national legislations. According to his/her capability,
             patient's informed assent will be collected

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient with known intolerance or contraindication to the trial treatment

          -  Patient with Hb levels less than 8g/dl (entry may be delayed until values return to
             normal)

          -  Patient with platelet count &lt;100.000/mm3 or absolute neutrophil count &lt;1.500/mm3
             (entry may be delayed until values return to normal)

          -  Patient with evidence of abnormal liver function (ALT level &gt;5 times the upper normal
             limit during six months preceding enrolment; entry may be delayed until values return
             to normal)

          -  iron overload from causes other than transfusional haemosiderosis

          -  severe heart dysfunction secondary to iron overload defined as the occurrence of
             heart failure or severe arrhythmia or as indicated by cardiac T2* lower than 10 ms,
             if recent MRI data is available,

          -  Patient with serum creatinine level above the upper normal limit at screening; entry
             may be delayed until values return to normal.

          -  Serological evidence of chronic hepatitis B (presence of HBe Ag, HBsAg, HBcAb-IgM, in
             the absence of HBsAb).

          -  History of significant medical or psychiatric disorder that may impair compliance
             with the requirements of the protocol.

          -  The patient has received another investigational drug within 30 days prior to this
             study.

          -  Patient with a pre-existing condition or any other surgical or medical condition
             which might significantly interfere with normal gastrointestinal and hepatic function
             that could alter the absorption, metabolism, and/or excretion of the study drug.

          -  Patient with a known history of HIV seropositivity.

          -  Fever and other signs/symptoms of infection in the 10 days before drug
             administration(treatment day)

          -  Concomitant use of other iron chelators or trivalent cation-dependent medicinal
             products such as aluminium-based antacids.

          -  Patient with a chronic condition that does not allow suspension of related treatment
             from starting of washout until drug is administered.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Month</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>6 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Oscar Della Pasqua</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Universiteit Leiden, The Netherlands</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Giovanni Carlo Del Vecchio</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria Consorziale Policlinico di Bari, Italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Laura Mangiarini</last_name>
    <phone>+39.327.7749666</phone>
    <email>lmangiarini@cvbf.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Nicosia</city>
        <country>Cyprus</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Cairo</city>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Bari</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Napoli</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Padova</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Palermo</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Sassari</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Cyprus</country>
    <country>Egypt</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 26, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 28, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>chronic iron overload</keyword>
  <keyword>hereditary haemoglobinopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>beta thalassaemia major</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hemoglobinopathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Iron Overload</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Deferiprone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
