<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="114142">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01688167</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20110290</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01MH095539</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01688167</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Increasing Availability and Acceptability of Circumcision in Zambia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Increasing Availability and Acceptability of Circumcision in Zambia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Miami</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Miami</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <authority>Zambia: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study proposes to balance supply and demand of male circumcision through a systematic
      scale-up of coordinated biomedical surgical and behavioral counseling services. The study
      will compare the combined biobehavioral sexual risk reduction intervention to the standard
      of care, which focuses exclusively on the provision of circumcision services alone, with the
      goal of optimizing both local and national HIV prevention efforts.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Investigator), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in likelihood of undergoing male circumcision across the study using stages of change model</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Average of 1 month post-baseline, 6 month and 12 month follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Readiness to undergo male circumcision will be assessed using the stages of change model (pre-contemplation, contemplation, preparation, action, maintenance). Intervention and attention control conditions will be compared at baseline, immediately following intervention, and 6 and 12 months post-intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Uptake of male circumcision</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of study enrollment to the date male circumcision is performed or study completion.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine if participants in the sexual risk reduction/MC promotion intervention (experimental condition) will be more likely to shift to the &quot;Action&quot; stage (undergo circumcision), in comparison with participants having identical MC services available plus usual care (attention control condition).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Male and female condom use post male circumcision</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after undergoing male circumcision</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine whether MC will significantly affect the maintenance of safer sexual practices (&quot;risk compensation&quot;) in the experimental group as compared to the attention control group</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1468</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Experimental condition clinics offer the MC and sexual risk reduction intervention: four group counseling sessions focused on male circumcision and sexual risk reduction.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Male participants in the standard of care control condition CHCs will receive counseling per the VCT protocol guidelines. Participants will attend four video-based time-equivalent &quot;attention-control&quot; group sessions on endemic disease prevention strategies (e.g., TB, malaria, cholera, waterborne diseases). Female partners will be invited to participate in a similar four session program devoted to endemic disease risk reduction.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Observational</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>3 CHC sites will be randomly assigned as &quot;observation only;&quot; only aggregated clinic VCT and circumcision data will be collected.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MC and sexual risk reduction</intervention_name>
    <description>Four group counselling sessions focused on male circumcision and sexual risk reduction</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV negative

          -  Uncircumcised male

          -  18+ years of age

          -  Able to understand and sign informed consent in English, Bemba, or Nyanja

          -  Have not requested male circumcision services at the time of or following VCT

          -  Female partners of enrolled males are invited to participate

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Men seeking circumcision services are not eligible for this study

          -  Men with genital abnormalities requiring MC, e.g. balanitis (inflammation of the
             preputial skin), posthitis (inflammation of the glans penis; common in patients with
             diabetes), phimosis (scarring of the distal margins of the foreskin) resulting from
             chronic balanitis, paraphimosis (the inability to pull the retracted foreskin back
             over the glans) or diseases of the foreskin, including localized carcinoma are not
             eligible for this study

          -  Men with congenital or acquired penile abnormalities that require the preputial skin
             for generative repair, such as hypospadias (urethra exits from underside of penis)
             are not eligible to participate

          -  Participants unable to provide informed consent will not be eligible.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen M Weiss, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Miami</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Zambia Teaching Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lusaka</city>
        <country>Zambia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Zambia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 17, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 11, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Miami</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Stephen Weiss</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Research Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>Male circumcision</keyword>
  <keyword>Sexual risk reduction</keyword>
  <keyword>Stages of change</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
