<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="168030">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01704599</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Dermatology 1104009591</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01704599</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Addition of Modulators of Homocysteine to Adalimumab Therapy in the Treatment of Moderate to Severe Plaque Psoriasis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-Center, Open-Label Study to Assess the Effects of the Addition of Modulators of Homocysteine to Adalimumab Therapy in the Treatment of Moderate to Severe Plaque Psoriasis Evaluated With the PASI, PGA and DLQI</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wayne State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Abbott</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wayne State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Vitamins modulating homocysteine affect both TNF-alpha, vascular endothelial growth factor,
      and  theoretically enhance the anti-inflammatory  version of NOS thus hopefully  increasing
      the efficacy and reducing  the chance of some toxicities of adalimumab as determined by
      blood testing and EKGs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a pilot study designed to evaluate whether  addition of oral vitamin B12, vitamin
      B6, and folic acid to the use of adalimumab for psoriasis leads to further  improvement of a
      patient's psoriasis and quality of life.

      Adalimumab is indicated by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for the treatment of
      adults with moderate to severe long standing (chronic) plaque psoriasis.  Adalimumab is a
      medicine called a TNF-alpha (tumor necrosis factor alpha) blocker.  The extra TNF-alpha in
      the body can attack normal healthy body tissues and cause inflammation. The purposes of this
      study are to investigate the effects of the addition of 12 weeks of modulators of
      homocysteine (oral vitamin B12, oral vitamin B6 or pyridoxine, and oral folic acid) plus
      adalimumab after  16 weeks adalimumab therapy on the clinical appearance of psoriasis and on
      laboratory values correlated with the use and disuse of said modulators. Given that near
      maximum clinical improvement on adalimumab is expected after 16 weeks of adalimumab, if
      further clearcut improvement was seen  in most subjects at the 28 week visit, it would be
      attributed to the addition of the vitamins.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Two of 7 subjects' psoriasis worsened on B vitmains and one who improved developed Left axis
    deviation on EKG
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>January 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PASI</measure>
    <time_frame>Change between week 16  on Humira and  then after another 12 weeks  on Humira  plus vitamins</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The investigators will measure patients' Psoriasis Area and Severity Index (PASI). The PASI assessment includes grading psoriatic involvement (6 point scale), and severity of lesions on the head, trunk, and, upper and lower extremities.  PASI scores range from 0.0 to 72.0 (0.1 increments), with a score of 72.0 representing complete erythroderma of the severest possible degree, and a PASI score of 0.0 indicating no psoriatic lesions at all.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PGA</measure>
    <time_frame>Change between week 16 on Humira and  after another 12 weeks on Humira plus vitamins</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Physician Global Assessment of Psoriasis (PGA): PGA is a numeric scale which is completed by the physician and is designed to evaluate the physician's overall assessment of the subject's psoriasis based on severity of symptoms.  The BSA numerical score will be used to measure the physician's assessment of the proportion of the subject's total BSA involved with psoriasis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>DLQI</measure>
    <time_frame>Change between week 16 on Humira and then after another 12 weeks on Humira plus vitamins</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI):  DLQI is a self-administered 10-question validated questionnaire that examines the impact of skin disease on quality of life.42  There are 10 questions focusing on the following domains: (1) symptoms &amp; feelings (2) daily activities (3) leisure (4) work &amp; school (5) personal relationship (6) treatment.42  The DLQI, although meant to examine overall skin-related QoL, primarily focuses on social interaction (i.e. shopping, sport, work).  Only 2 questions, one regarding physical discomfort and the other regarding treatment, do not directly pertain to social activities.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Event</measure>
    <time_frame>From Week 0 through day 70 post Week 28 of therapy with first Humira then Humira plus B Vitamins</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>An adverse event (AE) is any reaction, side effect, or other untoward medical occurrence, regardless of the relationship to study drug, which occurs at any time during this  study after the subject has taken the first dose of study drug.  Clinically significant adverse changes in clinical status, x-rays, physical examinations, etc. are considered adverse events.  A laboratory abnormality that is associated with signs/symptoms or a diagnosis, or that requires a therapeutic intervention (including dose reduction or discontinuation of the study drug) will be considered as an adverse event.
Reporting
All adverse events, whether ascertained through subject interviews, physical examination, laboratory findings, or other means will be recorded separately on an adverse event report form and be conveyed all investigators and sub-investigators  via Quartely Data Safety Report and as soon as possible to Abbott.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Serious Adverse Event (SAE)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Week 0 through day 70 post Week 28 of therapy with first Humira then Humira plus B Vitamins</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>A SAE is any adverse event occurring at any dose that results in:
Death
Life-threatening
In-patient hospitalization or prolongation of existing hospitalization
Persistent or significant disability or incapacity
Congenital abnormality or birth defect Any other event thought by the Investigator to be serious should also be reported.
All encounters are to be copied and sent to the ENTIRE investigating team within one week or sooner (Abbott within 48 hours).  In addition, Quarterly reports of all encounters will be summarized and sent to the Wayne State HIC and including Abbott Medical Affairs for Discussion if any aberrant or abnormal results are found that quarter.
Expedited safety reports (IND Safety Reports)will be sent to the FDA and other regulatory agencies as necessary, and will inform the Investigators of such regulatory reports.  Investigators must submit safety reports as required by the Wayne State IRB.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Electrocardiogram (EKG)</measure>
    <time_frame>At Screening, Week 16 on Humira, Week 28 after another 12 weeks on Humira plus vitamins and if early termination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>A 12 lead electrocardiogram will be taken</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma VEGF (vascular endothelial growth factor level)</measure>
    <time_frame>At Screening visit, Week 16 on Humira, after anotehr 12 weeks on Humira plus vitamins and if early termination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood test requiring venipuncture (if 140 pg/ml or more  at screening candidate will not be enrolled)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Complete blood count with differential</measure>
    <time_frame>At Week 0 just before Humira, Week 16 on Humira, Week 28 after another 12 weeks on Humira plus vitamins and if early termination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood test requiring venipuncture.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Serum Magnesium</measure>
    <time_frame>At Week 0 just before Humira, Week 16 on Humira, Week 28 after another 12 weeks on Humira plus vitamins and if early termination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood test requiring venipuncture.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>serum phosphorus</measure>
    <time_frame>At Week 0 just before Humira, Week 16 on Humira, Week 28 after another 12 weeks on Humira plus vitamins and if early termination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood test requiring venipuncture.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>serum homocysteine</measure>
    <time_frame>At Week 0 just before Humira, Week 16 on Humira, Week 28 after another 12 weeks on Humira plus vitamins and if early termination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood test requiring venipuncture.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Vitamin B12 blood level</measure>
    <time_frame>At Week 0 just before Humira, Week 16 on Humira, Week 28 after another 12 weeks on Humira plus vitamins and if early termination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood test requiring venipuncture</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Vitamin B6 level</measure>
    <time_frame>At Week 0 just before Humira, Week 16 on Humira, Week 28 after another 12 weeks on Humira plus vitamins and if early termination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood test requiring venipuncture</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Serum folic acid level</measure>
    <time_frame>At Week 0 just before Humira, Week 16 on Humira, Week 28 after another 12 weeks on Humira plus vitamins and if early termination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood test requiring venipuncture</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Helicobacter pylori antibody</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 justbefore Humira, Week 28 after 16 weeks of Humira then 12 of Humir-Vitamins</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood test requiring venipuncture.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Urine Pregnancy</measure>
    <time_frame>At screening, Week 28 after 16 weeks Humira and anotehr 12 of Humira-vitamins</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Urine test (if positive at screening candidae will  not be enrolled).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Blood Pressure and pulse</measure>
    <time_frame>At Week 0, week 16 on Humira, anotehr 12 weeks on Humira plus vitamins and if early termination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Measaurement using blood pressure cuff with pulse reader</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Temperature</measure>
    <time_frame>At Week 0, week 16 on Humira, anotehr 12 weeks on Humira plus vitamins and if early termination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Using a thermometer</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Height</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 at Start of Humira</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Using ruler</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Weight</measure>
    <time_frame>At Week 0 at start of Humira</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Using scale</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">8</enrollment>
  <condition>Psoriasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Humira  then   Humira plus  3 B vitamins</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Humira then Humira plus 3 B vitamins
The only arm: After 16 weeks on adalimumab, modulators of homocysteine (oral vitamin B12, oral vitamin B6 or pyridoxine, and oral folic acid) will be added to adalimumab therapy for an additional 12 weeks.  At end of this therapy can stop or continue . Telephone call day 70 after formal end of in person study the investigators will assess general health of each subject.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Humira Then Humira plus 3 B vitamins</intervention_name>
    <description>Humira alone for 16 weeks then Humira plus 100 mg daily pyridoxine, 5 mg daily folic acid and 1000 mcg daily cycnocobalamin</description>
    <arm_group_label>Humira  then   Humira plus  3 B vitamins</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Humira</other_name>
    <other_name>Adalimumab</other_name>
    <other_name>Vitamin B6</other_name>
    <other_name>Pyridoxine</other_name>
    <other_name>Vitamin B9</other_name>
    <other_name>Folic Acid</other_name>
    <other_name>Vitamin B12</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyanocobalamin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  adults 18 or older

          -  moderate to severe plaque psoriasis (&gt;10% BSA)

          -  Negative pregnancy test within 7 days before first dose of adalimumab in all women
             (except surgically sterile or 5 years postmenopausal)

          -  subject must sign/date appropriate written informed consent&amp;HIPAA authorization

          -  Sexually active subjects of childbearing potential must agree to use medically
             acceptable contraception during screening and throughout the study

          -  no evidence of active or latent tuberculosis based on a negative PPD skin test
             performed at screening, or within one year of starting this study. Patients with
             documentation of adequately treated TB may be enrolled

          -  Patients PPD positive and CXR negative can be enrolled if they finish appropriate INH
             prophylaxis prior to enrollment

          -  be willing and able to self-administer subcutaneous injections or to have a qualified
             person available to administer these injections

          -  agrees to comply with protocol requirements, attend all regularly study visits and is
             considered to be a good study subject

          -  meets concomitant medication washout requirements

          -  willing to use only allowed psoriasis medications and treatments and agree not to
             start any topical, systemic, or phototherapy for psoriasis during the study period

          -  adalimumab naïve

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  erythrodermic, pustular, or guttate psoriasis

          -  skin conditions other than psoriasis that would interfere with study-related
             psoriasis evaluations

          -  known sensitivity to any component of the study medications

          -  Evidence of active infections such as fevers, chills, sweats, or history of untreated
             Lyme disease and active severe infections within 4 weeks before screening visit, or
             between the screening and Week 0 visits

          -  history of listeriosis, untreated TB, persistent or active infections requiring
             hospitalization or treatment with IV antibiotics, IV antiretrovirals, or IV
             antifungals within 30 days of baseline, OR oral antibiotics, antivirals, or
             antifungals for purpose of treating infection, within 14 days of baseline

          -  positive PPD and positive chest x-ray for latent or active tuberculosis

          -  positive PPD and negative chest x-ray that have not completed appropriate INH
             prophylaxis

          -  On immune compromising drug or history of immune compromising disorder or
             immunodeficiency

          -  poorly controlled medical condition including, not limited to, unstable
             cardiovascular disease, poorly controlled diabetes, recent stroke, history of
             recurrent infections, or any condition for which, in the opinion of the
             investigators, participation in the study would place the subject at risk

          -  hx. congestive heart failure

          -  hx. demyelinating CNS disease

          -  History of malignancy (other than previously treated localized carcinoma in situ of
             the cervix or previously treated nonmelanoma skin cancer)

          -  history of or ongoing drug or alcohol abuse

          -  past or present psychiatric morbidity which may compromise the study

          -  Pregnant women, nursing mothers, or planning to become pregnant during study or
             within 150 days after last dose of study medication. Males planning pregnancy with
             spouse/partner while in study are to be excluded

          -  plans to receive any live vaccines during study

          -  history of liver disease

          -  Current enrollment in another clinical study/treatment with other experimental drug
             or approved therapy for experimental use within 30 days prior to Week 0

          -  previous enrollment in this study

          -  cannot commit to all assessments required by the protocol

          -  disorder that compromises the subject to give written informed consent and/or comply
             with study procedures

          -  considered by the investigators to be unsuitable candidate

          -  cannot comply with the protocol washout requirements

          -  on folic acid in doses over than the minimal daily requirements

          -  on vitamins higher than minimal daily requirements (multivitamins are allowed)

          -  colon polyps or cancer

          -  prior adalimumab therapy

          -  on screening plasma Vascular Endothelial Growth Factor level is 140 pg/ml or more
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter J Aronson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department Dermatology Wayne State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wayne State University Physician Group Dermatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dearborn</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48124</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.accessdata.fda.gov/scripts/cder/drugsatfda/index.cfm?fuseaction=Search.DrugDetails</url>
    <description>Search for Humira</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.fda.gov/downloads/Drugs/DrugSafety/ucm088611.pdf</url>
    <description>Humira</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.emedicine.com/med/topic3383.htm</url>
    <description>hypermagnesemia</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aronson PJ, Malick F. Towards rational treatment of severe psoriasis in alcoholics: report of two cases. J Drugs Dermatol. 2010 Apr;9(4):405-8.</citation>
    <PMID>20514802</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moat SJ, Madhavan A, Taylor SY, Payne N, Allen RH, Stabler SP, Goodfellow J, McDowell IF, Lewis MJ, Lang D. High- but not low-dose folic acid improves endothelial function in coronary artery disease. Eur J Clin Invest. 2006 Dec;36(12):850-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17087779</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Li W, Zheng T, Wang J, Altura BT, Altura BM. Extracellular magnesium regulates effects of vitamin B6, B12 and folate on homocysteinemia-induced depletion of intracellular free magnesium ions in canine cerebral vascular smooth muscle cells: possible relationship to [Ca2+]i, atherogenesis and stroke. Neurosci Lett. 1999 Oct 22;274(2):83-6.</citation>
    <PMID>10553943</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lewis V, Finlay AY. 10 years experience of the Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI). J Investig Dermatol Symp Proc. 2004 Mar;9(2):169-80. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15083785</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gordon KB, Langley RG, Leonardi C, Toth D, Menter MA, Kang S, Heffernan M, Miller B, Hamlin R, Lim L, Zhong J, Hoffman R, Okun MM. Clinical response to adalimumab treatment in patients with moderate to severe psoriasis: double-blind, randomized controlled trial and open-label extension study. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2006 Oct;55(4):598-606. Epub 2006 Aug 10.</citation>
    <PMID>17010738</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Genovese MC, Mease PJ, Thomson GT, Kivitz AJ, Perdok RJ, Weinberg MA, Medich J, Sasso EH; M02-570 Study Group. Safety and efficacy of adalimumab in treatment of patients with psoriatic arthritis who had failed disease modifying antirheumatic drug therapy. J Rheumatol. 2007 May;34(5):1040-50. Epub 2007 Apr 15. Erratum in: J Rheumatol. 2007 Jun;34(6):1439.</citation>
    <PMID>17444593</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pitarch G, Sanchez-Carazo JL, Mahiques L, Perez-Ferriols MA, Fortea JM. Treatment of psoriasis with adalimumab. Clin Exp Dermatol. 2007 Jan;32(1):18-22.</citation>
    <PMID>17305904</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leonardi C, Langley RG, Papp K, Tyring SK, Wasel N, Vender R, Unnebrink K, Gupta SR, Valdecantos WC, Bagel J. Adalimumab for treatment of moderate to severe chronic plaque psoriasis of the hands and feet: efficacy and safety results from REACH, a randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind trial. Arch Dermatol. 2011 Apr;147(4):429-36. doi: 10.1001/archdermatol.2010.384. Epub 2010 Dec 20.</citation>
    <PMID>21173304</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stuart PE, Nair RP, Ellinghaus E, Ding J, Tejasvi T, Gudjonsson JE, Li Y, Weidinger S, Eberlein B, Gieger C, Wichmann HE, Kunz M, Ike R, Krueger GG, Bowcock AM, Mrowietz U, Lim HW, Voorhees JJ, Abecasis GR, Weichenthal M, Franke A, Rahman P, Gladman DD, Elder JT. Genome-wide association analysis identifies three psoriasis susceptibility loci. Nat Genet. 2010 Nov;42(11):1000-4. Epub 2010 Oct 17.</citation>
    <PMID>20953189</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Suárez-Fariñas M, Fuentes-Duculan J, Lowes MA, Krueger JG. Resolved psoriasis lesions retain expression of a subset of disease-related genes. J Invest Dermatol. 2011 Feb;131(2):391-400. Epub 2010 Sep 23.</citation>
    <PMID>20861854</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 11, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 3, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Wayne State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Peter J. Aronson, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor Department of Dermatology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Psoriasis</keyword>
  <keyword>Adalimumab</keyword>
  <keyword>B vitamins</keyword>
  <keyword>Homocysteine</keyword>
  <keyword>Folic acid</keyword>
  <keyword>Cyanocobalamin</keyword>
  <keyword>Pyridoxine</keyword>
  <keyword>Vitamin B6</keyword>
  <keyword>Vitamin B9</keyword>
  <keyword>Vitamin B12</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Psoriasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Folic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin B Complex</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydroxocobalamin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin B 12</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pyridoxine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin B 6</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pyridoxal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adalimumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
