<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="56891">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01725633</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00025906</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01725633</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Aerobic Training in Metastatic Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>Breast Mets</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase II Trial of Aerobic Training in Metastatic Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the safety and feasibility of supervised aerobic
      training in women undergoing hormone therapy, chemotherapy, and/or radiation therapy for
      metastatic breast cancer. Previous research among persons with breast cancer has shown that
      breast cancer therapy is associated with side-effects that affect fitness and quality of
      life. Therefore, the investigators want to determine if aerobic training is appropriate for
      this population. To date, no study has tested this question and this is the reason for the
      study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary To determine the feasibility and safety of supervised aerobic training in women
      receiving endocrine therapy, chemotherapy, and/or radiotherapy for metastatic breast cancer

      Secondary

        -  To explore the potential effect (means and variation) on treatment toxicity, patient
           symptoms, and functional capacity, relative to attention control (i.e., mock exercise)

        -  To explore the potential effect (means and variation) on biomarkers associated with
           metastatic breast cancer prognosis (i.e., inflammatory cytokines and growth factors),
           relative to attention control

      Primary: Safety and feasibility evaluated by assessing the rates of study eligibility,
      overall accrual, attrition, and exercise adherence. Safety will be evaluated by the type and
      prevalence of adverse events during study-related assessments and aerobic training sessions.
      Tracking and monitoring of exercise-related adverse events will be assessed using the
      following methods: (1) stringent monitoring and recording (in the patient case report form;
      case report form, this will include a detailed past medical history, complete blood count
      panel history from first line chemotherapy, and detailed medication information) of
      physiologic outcomes and vital signs (e.g., heart rate, blood pressure, etc.) prior to,
      during, and following every intervention session, and (2) at the beginning of each week, the
      exercise physiologist will spend the first 10 minutes of every session discussing any
      potential negative side-effects of the intervention assignment and any injuries that may
      have occurred. Discussions will include topics such as sleep, depression, diet, exercise,
      and any other related topics that should come up.  All events will be recorded in the
      patient CRF, (3) every two weeks all patients will complete the Common Terminology Criteria
      for Adverse Events (CTCAE) v4.0 questionnaire. The CTCAE, developed by the NCI, tracks
      treatment toxicity and adverse events applicable to all oncology clinical trials regardless
      of chronicity or modality, (4) every three months a meeting of all investigators will be
      scheduled to review and discuss all reported non-serious and serious adverse events for
      early identification of negative issues and development of solutions. All serious adverse
      events will be immediately reported to Duke Institutional Review Board and immediately
      circulated to all study investigators for appropriate discussion, and (5) early stopping
      rules in response to a differential higher frequency of adverse events in a particular study
      group (Risk outweighs benefit as determined by primary investigator and oncologist).

      Secondary:

        1. Treatment toxicity and complete blood count panel will be assessed after every
           chemotherapy cycle or every month if on hormone or radiation therapy according to the
           CTCAE v.4.0 as described above.

        2. Insulin sensitivity as assessed by an oral glucose tolerance test,

        3. Exercise capacity as measured by a symptom-limited cardiopulmonary exercise test,

        4. Pulmonary function as assessed by hand held spirometry,

        5. Cardiac function as assessed by echocardiography at rest and exercise,

        6. Neurocognitive function (a computerized neurocognitive test battery called Central
           Nervous System Vital Signs including verbal memory test, visual memory test, finger
           tapping test, symbol digit coding, Stroop test, shifting attention test, continuous
           performance test, four part continuous performance test).

        7. Autonomic function as assessed by beat-to-beat heart, blood pressure, and
           cerebrovascular blood flow velocity via transcranial Doppler.

        8. Patient-reported outcomes will be determined using standardized and validated
           questionnaires to assess quality of life, fatigue, and other common patient symptoms.

        9. Systemic Cytokines / Angiogenic Factors assessed in fasted blood and prepared for
           multiplex assay analysis using Luminex 100/200 System (Luminex Corp, Austin, Tx;
           http://www.luminexcorp.com/products/luminex_200.html).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Aerobic Training</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the feasibility and safety of supervised aerobic training in women receiving endocrine therapy, chemotherapy, and/or radiotherapy for metastatic breast cancer.  Safety and feasibility evaluated by assessing the rates of study eligibility, overall accrual, attrition, and exercise adherence. Safety will be evaluated by the type and prevalence of adverse events during study-related assessments and aerobic training sessions. Tracking and monitoring of exercise-related adverse events will be assessed using the following methods: (1) stringent monitoring and recording (in the patient case report form; case report form, this will include a detailed past medical history, complete blood count panel history from first line chemotherapy, and detailed medication information) of physiologic outcomes and vital signs (e.g., heart rate, blood pressure, etc.) prior to, during, and following every intervention session</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment toxicities and Patient Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To explore the potential effect (means and variation) on treatment toxicity, patient symptoms, and functional capacity, relative to attention control (i.e., mock exercise)
To explore the potential effect (means and variation) on biomarkers associated with metastatic breast cancer prognosis (i.e., inflammatory cytokines and growth factors), relative to attention control</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stretching</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The progressive stretching program will be prescribed according the American College of Sports Medicine guidelines for older adults and aimed at increasing whole-body flexibility.98 The ultimate goal for the progressive stretching program is 3 stretching sessions/week for 30-45 minutes/session.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Aerobic Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Aerobic training will be prescribed according to American College of Sports Medicine guidelines.97 The ultimate goal for the aerobic training group is 3 supervised exercise sessions per week at 50% to 70% of the individually determined VO2peak for 30-45 minutes/session for 12 weeks. Participants will be able to choose between either cycling or treadmill walking to achieve the prescribed aerobic prescription.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>Study interventions are aerobic training or attention-control progressive stretching. Both interventions will be matched in terms of social interaction (participants will receive one-on-one instruction), duration (30-45 mins/session), and program length (12 weeks). All intervention sessions, including attention-control stretching, will be performed in a supervised setting with one-on-one supervision by an American College of Sports Medicine (ACSM)-certified exercise physiologist</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stretching</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Aerobic Exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Consecutive women with histologically confirmed or cytologically confirmed metastatic
        breast cancer (MBC) presenting at Duke University Medical Center (DUMC), Durham Regional
        Hospital, or Duke Raleigh will be potentially eligible. Other major specific inclusion
        criteria are as follows:

          1. Candidates receiving hormone therapy, chemotherapy, and/or radiotherapy for MBC

          2. Complete radiology and tumor measurement within a maximum of 4 weeks prior to study
             entry,

          3. ≥21 years of age,

          4. Life expectancy &gt;3 months to ensure recruited patients can complete the 3-month
             intervention,

          5. Performance status ≥70%, as assessed by the Karnofsky performance status (KPS)
             scoring system. KPS involves the subjective evaluation of patients' global physical
             functioning and capability of independent living and self-care as determined by
             oncology professionals,

          6. Sedentary (i.e., women not performing regular exercise on at least 5 days a week, for
             at least 30 minutes each session, at a moderate or vigorous intensity for the past
             month). This definition is consistent with the national exercise recommendations
             guidelines and will ensure that only women not currently engaging in regular exercise
             (i.e., those who are the most likely to benefit) are recruited,

          7. Normal cardiac function (left ventricular ejection fraction ≥50%), and

          8. Medical clearance from attending oncologist to undergo supervised exercise training.

        Previous treatment with an anthracycline, taxane, angiogenesis inhibition, or hormonal
        therapy in the neoadjuvant or adjuvant setting is allowed.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Radiographic evidence of central nervous system disease, and

          2. Contraindications to aerobic training (e.g., extensive skeletal metastases, coronary
             artery disease, severe anemia, etc.) as recommended for cancer patients.43  Extensive
             skeletal metastases will be defined for purposes of this study as greater than five
             (5) sites of bony disease, or any symptomatic site of disease in the spine, hip, or
             femur.  As above, all patients must additionally receive medical clearance to undergo
             a trial of supervised exercise for MBC from their primary attending oncologist.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 25, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 28, 2011</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
