<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="161389">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01833195</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SN-C-00003</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01833195</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Outcomes AlloMap Registry: the Long-term Management and Outcomes of Heart Transplant Recipients With AlloMap Testing</brief_title>
  <acronym>OAR</acronym>
  <official_title>Outcomes AlloMap Registry Study: the Clinical Long-term Management and Outcomes of Heart Transplant Recipients With Regular Rejection Surveillance Including Use of AlloMap Gene-expression Profiling Testing</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>XDx</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>XDx</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this registry is to observe short and long term clinical outcomes in heart
      transplant recipients who receive regular AlloMap testing as part of allograft rejection
      surveillance.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The standard of care in adult heart transplant recipients has been to perform periodic
      endomyocardial biopsies for surveillance for rejection.  Because of the risks and
      discomforts associated with the biopsy procedure, a non-invasive test (AlloMap) based on
      gene-expression profiling of peripheral blood was developed and introduced in 2005 to
      identify heart transplant recipients who have a low probability of rejection at the time of
      protocol surveillance testing. The schedule of AlloMap surveillance testing has been derived
      from the customary timing of surveillance biopsies: e.g.  at 1 to 2 month intervals for
      patients who are 6 and 12 post-transplantation, and at 3, 4 or 6 months after the first year
      post-transplantation.

      In the large multicenter IMAGE (Invasive Monitoring Attenuation by Gene Expression
      Profiling) 602 patients in the United States who had undergone cardiac transplantation at
      least 6 months prior were randomized 1:1  to either surveillance with routine biopsy or
      AlloMap testing.  Patients in both groups were also monitored with echocardiography.  A
      primary outcome event was defined as an episode of rejection with hemodynamic compromise,
      graft dysfunction due to other causes, death or retransplantation.  Over a median follow-up
      period of 19 months, 297 patients who were monitored with AlloMap  and 305 patients who
      underwent routine biopsies had similar  2-year cumulative rates of events (14.5% and 15.3%,
      respectively; hazard ratio with gene-expression profiling, 1.04; 95% confidence interval,
      0.67 to 1.68).

      This Outcomes AlloMap Registry (OAR) study is designed to collect similar clinical  outcomes
      information as studied  in IMAGE, in  a larger cohort of patients (approximately 2000)
      followed for up to 5 years.  At each routine  clinic visit, key clinical features such as
      rejection surveillance management schedules, testing results (e.g.  blood levels of
      immunosuppressive agents), and AlloMap scores will be collected.  This  larger  and longer
      term follow-up dataset  is intended to  enable  further elucidation, through analyses
      techniques such as multivariate  Cox proportional hazards models, of the surveillance
      management features which may be associated or contribute to the most favorable long term
      outcomes of the heart recipients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <target_duration>5 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vital status of heart  transplant  recipient</measure>
    <time_frame>5 Years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Hospitalizations and causes (i.e. infections or graft dysfunction (classified as: acute cellular rejection, antibody mediated rejection , cardiac allograft vasculopathy or non specific etiology of  graft dysfunction
Cancers (newly diagnosed and/or recurrent): onset and classification of types of cancers</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Surveillance  visit  schedules and patient management parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>5 Years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Endomyocardial biopsy and histology grades of rejection; left ventricular echocardiograms and ejection fractions; maintenance immunosuppressive drugs categories and doses/ blood levels; AlloMap scores and score patterns</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiac Transplant Failure</condition>
  <condition>Cardiac Transplant Rejection</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Heart transplant recipients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Heart transplant rejection surveillance including AlloMap testing</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      RNA isolated from peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC)
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Heart transplant patients
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  New and existing heart transplant recipients ≥ 2 months (≥ 55 days) post-transplant
             receiving post-transplant care at the enrolling centers for interim surveillance
             monitoring that includes AlloMap testing
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James P Yee, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>XDx, Inc., Brisbane, CA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ellyn P Shocron</last_name>
    <phone>415-287-2558</phone>
    <email>eshocron@xdx.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Allegheny General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15212</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Manreet Kanwar, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aurora St. Luke's Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nasir Sulemanjee, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.allomap.com/</url>
    <description>Click here for more information about AlloMap testing</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shah MR, Starling RC, Schwartz Longacre L, Mehra MR; Working Group Participants. Heart transplantation research in the next decade--a goal to achieving evidence-based outcomes: National Heart, Lung, And Blood Institute Working Group. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2012 Apr 3;59(14):1263-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2011.11.050. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22464255</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pham MX, Teuteberg JJ, Kfoury AG, Starling RC, Deng MC, Cappola TP, Kao A, Anderson AS, Cotts WG, Ewald GA, Baran DA, Bogaev RC, Elashoff B, Baron H, Yee J, Valantine HA; IMAGE Study Group. Gene-expression profiling for rejection surveillance after cardiac transplantation. N Engl J Med. 2010 May 20;362(20):1890-900. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0912965. Epub 2010 Apr 22.</citation>
    <PMID>20413602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 15, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 11, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>molecular diagnostics</keyword>
  <keyword>heart transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>risk factors</keyword>
  <keyword>prognosis</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
