<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="60560">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02117635</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RN01-CP-0002</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-003482-18</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02117635</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Investigation of Stem Cells in Stroke Phase II Efficacy</brief_title>
  <acronym>PISCES-II</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase II Simon Two-Stage Efficacy Study of Intracerebral CTX0E03 DP in Patients With Stable Paresis of the Arm Following an Ischaemic Stroke.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>ReNeuron Limited</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>ReNeuron Limited</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary aim of this Phase II trial is to determine whether it is sufficiently likely
      that CTX DP treatment at a dose level of 20 million cells improves the recovery in the use
      of the paretic arm in acute stroke patients to justify a subsequent larger prospectively
      controlled study.

      This study will evaluate the safety and efficacy of intracerebral CTX DP at a dose level of
      20 million cells in patients with paresis of an arm following an ischaemic middle cerebral
      artery (MCA) stoke. Eligible patients will have no useful function of the paretic arm a
      minimum of 28 days after the ischaemic stroke (a modified NIH Stroke Scale (NIHSS) Motor Arm
      Score of 2 or 3 for the affected arm).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Design: This Phase II efficacy trial is a multi-centre, open label, single arm,
      non-comparative two stage design,  administering a single dose of CTX cells 2 to 3 months
      post-ischaemic stroke with follow-up over 12 months. The trial will be overseen by an
      independent DSMB. The DSMB will adjudicate whether a patient has satisfied the primary
      response criterion and whether the ongoing safety profile justifies continuation or
      modification of the study.

      In stage 1, up to 21 patients will be enrolled to receive CTX DP (20 million cells) by
      stereotaxic intra-striatal injection ipsilateral to the location of the MCA ischaemic
      stroke. If 2 or more patients satisfy the primary response criterion 6 months after
      treatment with CTX DP, the study will progress to Stage 2 and, subject to the agreement of
      the DSMB, enrolment will be increased to a maximum total of 41 patients.

      Pre-treatment selection of patients:  Men and women, aged 40 to 89 inclusive, subcortical or
      cortical ischaemic stroke or a stroke with elements of both in an area perfused by the MCA
      (i.e. stroke due to ischaemia resulting in infarct located in the basal ganglia, internal
      capsule, or corona radiata or a stroke due to ischaemia resulting in infarction of part of
      the cerebral cortex). Treatment will be offered to eligible women with a history of surgical
      sterilisation or who are greater than 2 years but less than 4 years since their last
      menstrual period.

      Patients with a first stroke within the past 4 weeks (at time of consent) satisfying the
      following criteria: Modified NIHSS Motor Arm Score of 2 (some effort against gravity) or 3
      for affected arm (no movement against gravity) on day 28 and day 56 post-stroke; Clinical
      diagnosis of stroke confirmed by physician using neuro-imaging (computerised tomography or
      magnetic resonance imaging).  A Score of 0 or 1 for test 2 of the ARAT on day 28 and day 56
      post-stroke using the affected arm.

      Treatment: One patient will be treated at one time. A single dose (20 million) of CTX cells
      will be administered intracranially via stereotaxic neurosurgery.

      Post-treatment follow-up:  Patients will be followed for 12 months post-implantation.

      End-points:  The primary endpoint of the trial is efficacy, using ARAT.  Secondary endpoints
      are efficacy and safety.  Outcome measures for efficacy include NIHSS, BI and RFA.  Safety
      will be assessed by incidence of relevant adverse events monitoring patient's general
      physical condition and clinical measures (temperature, pulse rate and rhythm, ECG, blood
      pressure, full blood count, liver function tests, serum urea and electrolytes),
      immunological response and concomitant medications at the 7 follow-up visits to the clinic
      in the first year after treatment.

      Post-trial follow-up:  Annual correspondence with family practitioners;  Life-long follow-up
      for new diagnosis of cancer, site of primary tumour, and survival via National Cancer
      Registry.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Action  Research Arm Test (ARAT)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary outcome measure is a minimum 2 point improvement in the ARAT test number 2 (Yozbatiran et al., 2008).
Response will be defined as a minimum improvement of 2 points in test number 2 of the ARAT (Grasp a 2.5 cm3 block and move it from the starting position to the target end position) in the affected arm 6 months after injection of CTX DP. This would represent an improvement from a pre-treatment state in which the patient was unable to grasp and reposition the block as required to a post-treatment state in which the patient could accomplish the task as specified within 60 seconds.
If 2 or more patients satisfy the primary response criterion 6 months after treatment with CTX DP in 1st stage, the study will progress to the 2nd stage and enrolment will be increased to 41 patients.  If after 21 patients, fewer than 2 patients satisfy the primary response 6 months after CTX DP treatment, no further patients will be enrolled and the trial will be concluded.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the efficacy of intracranial CTX DP in restoring upper limb function following an ischaemic stroke using the ARAT</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the efficacy of intracranial CTX DP in restoring function following an ischaemic stroke using the Modified National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale (NIHSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the efficacy of intracranial CTX DP in restoring patient's functional independence following an ischaemic stroke using the Rankin Focused Assessment (RFA) version of the modified Rankin Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the efficacy of CTX DP in improving patient's ability to execute activities of daily living following an ischaemic stroke using the Barthel Index (BI)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the safety and tolerability of intracranial CTX DP in patients following an ischaemic stroke</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Incidence of adverse events: monitoring of vital signs, temperature, pulse rate and rhythm, ECG, blood pressure, full blood count, liver function test, serum urea and electrolytes, CTX antibody screen</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">41</enrollment>
  <condition>Ischaemic Stroke</condition>
  <condition>Cerebral Infarction</condition>
  <condition>Hemiparesis</condition>
  <condition>Arm Paralysis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>allogeneic human neural stem cell</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CTX DP
human neural stem cell product, single dose once only injection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CTX DP</intervention_name>
    <description>20 million cell dose administered by surgery to the damaged area of the brain</description>
    <arm_group_label>allogeneic human neural stem cell</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CTX0E03 DP</other_name>
    <other_name>allogeneic human neural stem cell therapy product</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Written informed consent or witnessed informed consent in the event that the patient
             is unable to sign informed consent due to paresis of the affected arm.

          -  Subcortical or cortical ischaemic stroke or a stroke with elements of both in an area
             perfused by the middle cerebral artery (i.e. stroke due to ischaemia resulting in
             infarct located in the basal ganglia, internal capsule, or corona radiata or a stroke
             due to ischaemia resulting in infarction of part of the cerebral cortex).

          -  Male or female.

          -  Age 40 to 89 years old inclusive.

          -  First stroke within the past 4 weeks (at time of consent) satisfying the following
             criteria:

          -  Modified NIHSS Motor Arm Score of 2 or 3 for affected arm on day 28+7 and day 56+7
             post-stroke.

          -  Clinical diagnosis of stroke confirmed by physician using neuro-imaging (CT or MRI).

          -  A Score of 0 or 1 for test 2 of the ARAT on day 28+7 and day 56+7 post-stroke using
             the affected arm.

          -  Ability to comprehend verbal commands.

          -  Eligible for neurosurgery. No medical conditions which would preclude neurosurgery
             with appropriate preparation and management.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Prior history of stroke resulting in permanent moderate to severe disability (i.e.
             Rankin Scale greater than 2) (other than the presenting ischaemic stroke).

          -  NIHSS upper limb = 4.

          -  Stroke due to haemorrhage.

          -  History of neurological or other disease resulting in significant functional
             impairment of the paretic arm impairing potential ability to pick up, lift and place
             a 2.5 cm3 block (e.g. Parkinson's disease, motor neuron disease, arthritis,
             Dupuytren's contracture or fixed anatomical abnormality).

          -  Any contraindications to MRI including presence of a cardiac pacemaker, metal
             fragments in eye etc.

          -  Uncontrolled blood pressure defined as systolic blood pressure ≥180 mm Hg or
             diastolic blood pressure ≥110 mm Hg (patients are only to be excluded if an initial
             value exceeding these limits is repeated on retesting over several days).

          -  Patient with a severe comorbid disorder, not expected to survive more than 12 months.

          -  Acute cardiovascular events other than the presenting ischaemic stroke (e.g.
             myocardial infarction, recent coronary intervention for symptomatic cardiac disease)
             3 months prior to planned injection of CTX DP.

          -  History of malignant disease, other than basal-cell carcinoma, cervical carcinoma in
             situ, superficial bladder cancer or successfully treated adolescent leukaemias or
             cancers.

          -  Current treatment with tamoxifen.

          -  Patients taking sodium valproate for any indication in whom it is not considered
             appropriate to discontinue the valproate for a period of 1 week prior and 4 weeks
             post neurosurgery. Patients in whom valproate is switched to an alternative agent
             during this period may be included.

          -  Documented fever within 7 days of the planned surgical procedure.

          -  HbA1c &lt;8.0%; (&lt;64mmol/mol).

          -  Women less than 2 years of post last menstrual period unless with a history of
             surgical sterilisation. (Women greater than 2 years but less than 4 years since their
             last menstrual period must have a negative pregnancy test).

          -  Considered unlikely to be able to attend for all follow-up visits.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>89 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Keith W Muir</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Glasgow</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NHS Southern General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glasgow</city>
        <zip>G51 4TF</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Keith W Muir, MD, FRCP</last_name>
      <email>Keith.Muir@glasgow.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Keith W Muir, MD, FRCP</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT01151124?term=stem+cells+and+stroke&amp;rank=6</url>
    <description>The PISCES safety trial is designed to test the safety of a manufactured neural stem cell line (CTX cells) delivered by injection into the damaged brains of male patients 60 years or over who are moderately to severely disabled 6-60 months post-stroke.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/results?term=OSIS&amp;Search=Search</url>
    <description>The OSIS trial is designed as a non-interventional observational study to document the clinical course of patients following ischaemic stroke and to establish a pool of patients for future trials.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yozbatiran N, Der-Yeghiaian L, Cramer SC. A standardized approach to performing the action research arm test. Neurorehabil Neural Repair. 2008 Jan-Feb;22(1):78-90. Epub 2007 Aug 17.</citation>
    <PMID>17704352</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 16, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Efficacy</keyword>
  <keyword>Non comparative</keyword>
  <keyword>Neural stem cells</keyword>
  <keyword>Intracranial administration</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paresis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paralysis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
