<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="8295">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01994304</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SCC--P2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01994304</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment and Evaluation of the Safe Childbirth Checklist --Phase II</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessment and Evaluation of the Safe Childbirth Checklist --Phase II Rajasthan, India</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Public Health Foundation of India</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>St. John's Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>UBS Optimus Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Children's Investment Fund Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Public Health Foundation of India</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>India: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      PHFI and SJRI will independently evaluate the effectiveness of the Safe Childbirth Checklist
      in preventing perinatal deaths and its impact on maternal and newborn complications.
      Evaluation (a quasi-experimental design) will include data collection from the seven
      intervention districts and six control districts. The estimated sample size is 200,000
      births, required to demonstrate a 15% reduction in perinatal mortality. Data on this will
      collected over a period of 17 months (November 2013 to April 2015).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Safe Childbirth Checklist (SCC), a tool that provides reminders and is a job aid to
      health care providers is a new maternal and newborn care intervention that is being
      implemented by the Government of Rajasthan with technical support from Jhpeigo.  SCC is thus
      expected to improve the quality of delivery care practices and is currently being
      implemented in Community Health Centres (CHCs) and District Hospitals (DHs) across seven
      districts in Rajasthan over a two-year time period (2013 to 2015). PHFI and SJRI will
      independently evaluate the effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of the SCC in preventing
      perinatal deaths and its impact on maternal and newborn complications. Evaluation will
      include data collection from the seven intervention districts and six control districts for
      a total of 13 districts in Rajasthan. The estimated sample size of 200,000 births is
      required to demonstrate a 15% reduction in perinatal mortality in the intervention districts
      compared to the control districts. Data on this will collected over a period of 17 months
      (November 2013 to April 2015).

      To estimate perinatal mortality (the main outcome of this study), information on newborn
      outcomes (stillbirths and early neonatal mortality) will be collected from various records
      at the study facilities.  Data collection will be done electronically using a mobile phone
      through software specifically developed for this purpose. The data sources include record
      registers from labor room; facility based newborn centres (FBNC) at DH and CHCs; and Monthly
      Death Records at the district.

      For a better understanding on how maternal and neonatal complications are diagnosed and
      managed at the facility, in-depth interviews will also be conducted biannually with the
      service providers (specialists, physicians, labor room staff nurses, and pharmacists) from
      the District hospitals and CHCs. In addition, interviews will also focus on understanding
      the use, acceptability and feasibility of the SCC among various types of providers.

      Cost of this intervention will be estimated and cost effectiveness in terms of cost per
      perinatal death prevented will be calculated.

      Permission for this study and data collection has been obtained from the Department of
      Health and Family Welfare, Government of Rajasthan.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perinatal mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>20 months (Aug-2013 to Mar-2015)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This evaluation will independently estimate the effectiveness of the Safe Childbirth Checklist in reduce perinatal mortality by 15% in the intervention areas</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Morbidity rates for infants and mothers</measure>
    <time_frame>20 months (Aug-2013 to Mar-2015)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We determine checklist-related morbidity rates for infants and mothers at the intervention facilities by observing the following:
Level of Practices -use of partograph or recording of events; active management of third stage labor (AMTSL); early initiation of breast feeding; use of antihypertensives/magnesium sulphate for mothers and use of antibiotics for mother and neonate
Levels of neonatal morbidity (low birth weight/prematurity, asphyxia, sepsis), maternal morbidity (Post partum haemorrhage, sepsis, eclampsia etc)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">200000</enrollment>
  <condition>Perinatal Mortality</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No safe childbirth checklist</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The selected control districts include Bharatpur, Pali, Jhunjhunu, Jaipur II, Nagaur, and Jodhpur.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Safe Childbirth Checklist</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The selected districts for SCC intervention include Alwar, Jalore, Sirohi, Sikar, Dausa, Churu, and Bikaner - a total of 7 districts.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SCC</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention involves introducing and orienting health providers on the SCC, facilitating availability of a specific set of commodities and regular targeted supervision.  These are expected to improve adherence to life saving interventions immediately before, during and after birth, and reduce perinatal mortality (still births and early neonatal mortality).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Safe Childbirth Checklist</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All women who deliver at the District Hospitals (DHs), Sub-District Hospitals (SDHs)
             and Community Health Centres (CHCs)

        Exclusion Criteria:

        -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Beena Varghese, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Public Health Foundation of India</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Public Health Foundation of India</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Delhi</city>
        <zip>110070</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.phfi.org/</url>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.sjri.res.in/projectdetail/1265</url>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ubs.com/global/en/wealth_management/optimusfoundation.html</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 19, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 13, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Public Health Foundation of India</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Beena Varghese</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Sr. Health Economist and Additional Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Safe Childbirth Checklist</keyword>
  <keyword>Maternal &amp; neonatal mortality</keyword>
  <keyword>Maternal &amp; neonatal complications</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
