<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="127848">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02026375</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>117259</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>SMOKERS3</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02026375</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Airway and Pulmonary Vascular Endothelial Function in Healthy Smokers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Airway and Pulmonary Vascular Endothelial Function in Healthy Smokers: Effect of Inhaled Glucocorticosteroid Treatment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Miami</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Miami</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Human Subject Research Office at University of Miami</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purposes of the present proposal are to 1) compare inhaled albuterolinduced changes in
      Qaw, and in CO and Ppas in healthy current smokers and lifetime nonsmokers as an index of
      endothelial function in the airway and pulmonary circulations, 2) compare the results
      between smokers and nonsmokers, and 3) determine the effect of a 4week treatment with an ICS
      on albuterol responsiveness of Qaw and the echocardiographic parameters. With this protocol
      we will test the hypotheses that a) there is a correlation between airway and pulmonary
      vascular endothelial function within the current smoker and nonsmoker groups, and b) ICS
      treatment improves airway and pulmonary vascular endothelial function in the current smoker
      group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Endothelial dysfunction has been defined as disturbed endothelium-dependent relaxation of
      resistance vessels, and breakdown of the vascular endothelial barrier, anti-adhesive and
      anti-thrombotic functions. As the latter two features are difficult to assess in intact
      human subjects, endothelium-dependent vasodilation has emerged as the principle test with
      which to demonstrate the presence of endothelial dysfunction in experimental and clinical
      settings. In previous studies we have shown that healthy current cigarette smokers with
      normal spirometry have a blunted endothelium-dependent vasodilation (endothelial function)
      in the systemic circulation to the airway (1-4). In the same studies, we also showed that a
      4-week treatment with an inhaled glucocorticosteroid (ICS) restored normal endothelial
      function in the airway of these subjects. While the exact mechanism of the ICS effect on
      airway vascular function remains unknown, these findings suggested that cigarette smoking
      causes steroid-sensitive vascular inflammation in the airway, possibly as a precursor of
      global vascular disease (4). Thus, there seems to be an abnormal regulation of vascular
      function in the absence of detectable abnormalities in airway function as assessed by
      spirometry in healthy smokers, possibly as an early sign of cigarette smoke-induced airway
      injury.

      Is it possible that cigarette smoking causes endothelial dysfunction in the pulmonary
      circulation as well, as an early manifestation of cigarette-smoke induced lung parenchymal
      damage before it is detectable by pulmonary function abnormalities? To our knowledge, no in
      vivo studies of endothelial function in the pulmonary circulation have been conducted in
      healthy smokers to date. However, investigators have reported endothelium-dependent
      relaxation responses of pulmonary arterial rings obtained from humans during resectional
      lung surgery, especially in patients with COPD and pulmonary hypertension, and found
      attenuated relaxation responses in them when compared to individuals without lung disease
      (5-8). A decreased expression of endothelial NOS seems to have a major role in the blunted
      pulmonary endothelium-dependent vasodilator responses in these patients. Similar changes
      have been reported in smokers without lung disease (9). This suggests that healthy smokers
      could have pulmonary vascular endothelial dysfunction similarly to airway vascular
      endothelial dysfunction, and that treatment with an ICS could restore normal endothelial
      function in the pulmonary circulation as well.

      Endothelial function can be assessed by the vasodilator response to pharmacologic agents
      known to cause endothelium-dependent vascular smooth muscle relaxation. β2-adrenergic
      agonists relax vascular smooth muscle through this mechanism. We have previously
      investigated endothelial function in the airway by measuring airway blood flow (Qaw)
      responses to inhaled albuterol (1). Similarly, pulmonary vascular endothelial function could
      be studied by measuring pulmonary hemodynamic responses to inhaled albuterol using
      echocardiography. Echocardiographic responses to β2-adrenergic agonists have been carried in
      patients with COPD,  showing an increase in cardiac output and a decrease in systolic
      pulmonary arterial pressure (Ppas) after terbutaline, formoterol and salmeterol
      administration (10,11).

      Previous comparative cardiac function studies have shown no differences between healthy
      smokers and non-smokers using echocardiography (12), but pulmonary vascular endothelial
      function thus far has not been investigated.

      Hemodynamic responses to β2-adrenergic agonists are mediated primarily by effects on
      vascular tone, not through direct effects on the heart (13). We therefore believe that
      inhaled albuterol-induced changes in echocardiographically measured CO and Ppas would
      reflect pulmonary vascular endothelial function.

      The purposes of the present proposal are to 1) compare inhaled albuterol-induced changes in
      Qaw, and in CO and Ppas in healthy current smokers and lifetime non-smokers as an index of
      endothelial function in the airway and pulmonary circulations, 2) compare the results
      between smokers and non-smokers, and 3) determine the effect of a 4-week treatment with an
      ICS on albuterol responsiveness of Qaw and the echocardiographic parameters. With this
      protocol we will test the hypotheses that a) there is a correlation between airway and
      pulmonary vascular endothelial function within the current smoker and non-smoker groups, and
      b) ICS treatment improves airway and pulmonary vascular endothelial function in the current
      smoker group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator)</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>albuterol-induced changes in Qaw</measure>
    <time_frame>before and 5 min after albuterol administration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>compare inhaled albuterol-induced changes in Qaw in healthy current smokers and lifetime non-smokers as an index of endothelial function in the airway and pulmonary circulations, 2) compare the results between smokers and non-smokers</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>albuterol-induced changes in CO and Ppas</measure>
    <time_frame>before and 5 minutes after albuterol inhalation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>compare inhaled albuterol-induced changes in CO and Ppas in healthy current smokers and lifetime non-smokers as an index of endothelial function in the airway and pulmonary circulations, 2) compare the results between smokers and non-smoker</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>determine the effect of a 4-week treatment with fluticasone propionate on albuterol responsiveness of Qaw</measure>
    <time_frame>4-week treatment with fluticasone propionate</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>after 4 weeks of inhaled fluticasone (220 μg fluticasone twice a day administered as a MDI using a spacer, albuterol responsiveness of Qaw will be measured</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>effect of a 4-week treatment with an ICS on the echocardiographic parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>4-week of treatment with an ICS</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>after 4 weeks of inhaled fluticasone (220 μg fluticasone twice a day administered as a MDI using a spacer, echocardiographic parameters ( Co and Ppas) will be measured</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Current Smokers and Healthy Non-smokers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>fluticasone propionate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>the current smokers will be started on a 4-week course of inhaled fluticasone (220 μg fluticasone twice a day administered as a MDI using a spacer).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>the current smokers will be started on a 4-week course of identically appearing placebo (2 puffs twice a day via spacer).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fluticasone propionate</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>fluticasone propionate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>fluticasone propionate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:Fifteen healthy current smokers with a &gt;10 pack-year history of smoking
        and 15 healthy never-smokers will be enrolled. Males and females between 25 and 75 years
        of age will be recruited.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women of childbearing potential who do not use accepted birth control measures;
             pregnant and       breast feeding women

          -  Cardiovascular disease and/or use of cardiovascular medications

          -  Subjects with known beta-adrenergic agonist intolerance

          -  A physician diagnosis of chronic airway disease (asthma, COPD, bronchiectasis, cystic
             fibrosis)

          -  Acute respiratory infection within four weeks prior to the study

          -  Use of any airway medication

          -  Abnormal pulmonary function (vide infra)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Adam Wanner, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(305)243-2568</phone>
    <email>awanner@med.miami.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Eliana Mendes</last_name>
    <phone>(305)243-2568</phone>
    <email>emendes@med.miami.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Human Research Laboratory University of Miami</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Adam Wanner, MD</last_name>
      <phone>305-243-2568</phone>
      <email>awanner@med.miami.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Eliana Mendes</last_name>
      <phone>(305)243-2568</phone>
      <email>emendes@med.miami.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Adam Wanner, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eliana Mendes</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andreas Schmid, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 30, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Miami</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Adam Wanner</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>endothelial dysfunction, smokers, airway blood flow, echocardiogram</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fluticasone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
