<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="70542">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01948141</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>I 225512</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-01618</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>I 225512</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016056</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01948141</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nintedanib in Treating Patients With Advanced Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer Who Have Failed Up to Two Previous Chemotherapy Regimens</brief_title>
  <official_title>FGFR1 Amplification as A Predictor of Efficacy in A Biomarker-Driven Phase II Study of BIBF 1120 in Advanced Squamous Cell Lung Cancer Patients Who Have Failed Up to Two Prior Chemotherapeutic Regimens</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Boehringer Ingelheim</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well nintedanib works in treating patients with advanced
      non-small cell lung cancer who have failed up to two previous chemotherapy regimens.
      Nintedanib may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed for
      cell growth.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the 6-month progression-free survival (PFS) rate of fibroblast growth factor
      receptor 1 (FGFRI) amplified squamous cell lung cancer patients treated with BIBF 1120
      (nintedanib).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Compare the 6-month PFS rate for the entire FGFRI amplified group versus the FGFRI
      wild-type patients.

      II. Compare the 6-month PFS rate for each FGFRI amplified group (low, intermediate, and
      high) versus historical controls and FGFRI wild-type patients.

      III. To assess the following endpoints overall and by FGFRI group: PFS, overall survival
      (OS), confirmed tumor response rate, and adverse events.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. The relation of FGFRI gene copy number with PFS, OS, confirmed response rate, and adverse
      events.

      II. The relationship fibroblast growth factor receptor (FGFR) polymorphisms with toxicity
      and efficacy.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive nintedanib orally (PO) twice daily (BID) on days 1-28. Courses repeat every
      28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 8 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PFS rate within the entire FGFRI amplified group defined as the proportion of patients who are alive and progression-free</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Tested at the 1-sided 0.10 significance level with all eligible, treated patients. Distributions of PFS will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PFS rate for the entire FGFR1 amplified group vs. the FGFRI wild-type patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from study entry to the first of either disease progression or death, assessed at 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Distributions of PFS will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method. Any comparisons between FGFRI groups will be done via the log-rank test for OS, along with the chi-square (or Fisher's exact test) for categorical data like tumor response and adverse events.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PFS rate between each of the FGFR1 amplified groups (low, intermediate, and high) vs. the FGFR1 wild-type patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from study entry to the first of either disease progression or death, assessed at 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Distributions of PFS will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method. Any comparisons between FGFRI groups will be done via the log-rank test for OS, along with the chi-square (or Fisher's exact test) for categorical data like tumor response and adverse events.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PFS rate for each of the FGFRI amplified groups (low, intermediate, high) in comparison to historical controls</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from study entry to the first of either disease progression or death, assessed at 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Distributions of PFS will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method. Any comparisons between FGFRI groups will be done via the log-rank test for OS, along with the chi-square (or Fisher's exact test) for categorical data like tumor response and adverse events.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>OS</measure>
    <time_frame>From study entry to death from any cause, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Distributions of OS will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method. Any comparisons between FGFRI groups will be done via the log-rank test for OS, along with the chi-square (or Fisher's exact test) for categorical data like tumor response and adverse events.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor response defined as complete response (CR) or partial response by RECIST 1.1 criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events (AEs) accessed by the National Cancer Institute (NCI) CTCAE version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days post-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Frequency tables will be reviewed to determine AE and toxicity patterns by FGFR1 groups. The frequency of AEs will be tabulated by grade across all dose levels and courses.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">67</enrollment>
  <condition>Recurrent Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Squamous Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (nintedanib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive nintedanib PO BID on days 1-28. Courses repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>nintedanib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (nintedanib)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BIBF 1120</other_name>
    <other_name>multitargeted tyrosine kinase inhibitor BIBF 1120</other_name>
    <other_name>Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor BIBF 1120</other_name>
    <other_name>Vargatef</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (nintedanib)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with advanced histologically proven squamous cell carcinoma of the lung

          -  Patients who have failed at least 1 systemic chemotherapy regimen for metastatic
             disease, but not more than 2 regimens

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of =&lt; 1

          -  The pathologic tissue is available to determine FGFR1 amplification status

          -  Presence of either evaluable disease or measurable disease as defined by Response
             Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1500/uL

          -  Hemoglobin (HgB) &gt;= 9 g/dL

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100,000/uL

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) =&lt; 1.5 x ULN (ALT
             and AST =&lt; 2.5 x ULN is acceptable if there is liver metastasis)

          -  Calculated or measured creatinine clearance &gt;= 45 mL/min

          -  Patients of child-bearing potential must agree to use acceptable contraceptive
             methods (e.g., double barrier) during treatment and have a negative serum or urine
             pregnancy test done =&lt; 7 days prior to registration (for women of childbearing
             potential only)

          -  Life expectancy &gt;= 12 weeks

          -  Willingness to provide the blood specimens as required by the protocol; please note
             that the willingness to participate pertains only to the patient and does not factor
             in the institution's ability to participate in any part of the translational
             component

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with any known endothelial growth factor receptor (EGFR) mutation and/or
             anaplastic lymphoma receptor tyrosine kinase (ALK) translocation

          -  Symptomatic, untreated, or uncontrolled central nervous system (CNS) metastases or
             seizure disorder; patients with asymptomatic CNS metastases treated with whole brain
             radiation (WBRT) or gamma knife radiosurgery (GKR) may be enrolled &gt;= 1 week after
             completion of WBRT/GKR provided toxicities are =&lt; Common Toxicity Criteria (CTC)
             grade I at the time of registration and/or controlled with dexamethasone 2 mg once
             daily for at least 5 days at the time of study treatment; patients with symptomatic
             CNS metastases treated with WBRT/GKR may be enrolled &gt;= 2 weeks after completion of
             WBRT/GKR provided toxicities are =&lt; CTC grade 1 at the time of registration and
             neurologic symptoms controlled with dexamethasone =&lt; 2 mg once daily for at least 1
             week at the time of study treatment

          -  Patients receiving palliative radiation to skeletal metastases may be registered as
             early as 1 week after completion of radiation therapy provided toxicities are =&lt; CTC
             grade I at the time of registration

          -  Any of the following prior therapies for malignancy:

               -  Systemic chemotherapy =&lt; 4 weeks prior to registration

               -  Radiation therapy =&lt; 4 weeks prior to registration (exceptions noted in the
                  prior bullet); the site of previous radiotherapy should have evidence of
                  progressive disease if this is the only site of disease

               -  Major surgery (i.e., laparotomy), open biopsy, or significant traumatic injury
                  =&lt; 4 weeks prior to registration; minor surgery =&lt; 2 weeks prior to
                  registration; insertion of a vascular access device is not considered major or
                  minor surgery in this regard

               -  Other investigational agent =&lt; 30 days prior to study treatment

          -  The following patients will be excluded from this study:

               -  Pregnant women

               -  Breastfeeding women

               -  Men or women who are sexually active and unwilling to use a medically acceptable
                  method of contraception (e.g., such as implants, injectables, combined oral
                  contraceptives, some intrauterine devices or vasectomized partner for
                  participating females, condoms for participating males) during the trial and for
                  at least three months after end of active therapy; a highly effective method of
                  birth control is defined as one which results in a low failure rate (i.e., less
                  than 1% per year) when used consistently and correctly; patients will be
                  considered to be of childbearing potential unless surgically sterilized by
                  hysterectomy or bilateral tubal ligation/salpingectomy, or post-menopausal for
                  at least 2 years

          -  Second primary malignancy with the following exceptions which are allowed:

               -  Carcinoma in situ of the cervix

               -  Non-melanoma skin cancer

               -  History of low-grade (Gleason score =&lt; 6) localized prostate cancer even if
                  diagnosed &lt; 5 years prior to registration

               -  Treated stage I breast cancer even if diagnosed =&lt; 5 years prior to registration

               -  Other prior malignancy (including melanoma) allowed if it was diagnosed and
                  definitively treated at least 5 years previously with no subsequent evidence of
                  recurrence

          -  Impairment of gastrointestinal function or gastrointestinal disease that may
             significantly alter the absorption of BIBF 1120 (e.g., ulcerative disease,
             uncontrolled nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, malabsorption syndrome or extensive small
             bowel resection)

          -  Leptomeningeal disease

          -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-positive patients receiving combination
             anti-retroviral therapy are excluded because of possible pharmacokinetic interactions
             with oral investigational agents

          -  Unwilling to, or unable to, comply with the protocol

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to ongoing or active
             infection requiring systemic antimicrobial therapy (including history of active or
             chronic hepatitis C and/or hepatitis B infection), significant pulmonary symptoms at
             baseline due to disease, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina
             pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would
             limit compliance with study requirements

          -  Centrally located tumors with radiographic evidence (computed tomography [CT] or
             magnetic resonance imaging [MRI]) of local invasion of major blood vessels

          -  Significant weight loss (&gt; 10% of baseline body mass) within past 6 months prior to
             inclusion into the study

          -  Coagulation parameters: International normalized ratio (INR) &gt; 2, prothrombin time
             (PT) and partial thromboplastin time (PTT) &gt; 50% of deviation of institutional ULN

          -  Proteinuria by Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) grade 2 or
             greater

          -  Known inherited predisposition to bleeding or thrombosis

          -  Therapeutic anticoagulation (except for low-dose heparin and/or heparin flush as
             needed for maintenance of an in-dwelling intravenous device) or anti-platelet therapy
             (except for low-dose therapy with acetylsalicylic acid &lt; 325 mg per day)

          -  Baseline hemoptysis, per clinician/investigator evaluation

          -  Active alcohol or drug abuse

          -  History of arterial or venous thrombotic/embolic events =&lt; 12 months prior to
             registration

          -  Prior history with BIBF 1120 or any other vascular endothelial growth factor
             (VEGF)/VEGF receptor (R) inhibitor

          -  New York Heart Association (NYHA) class III or IV; NOTE: patients classified as NYHA
             class II controlled with treatment may participate, with increased monitoring
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alex Adjei</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14263</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Roswell Park</last_name>
      <phone>877-275-7724</phone>
      <email>ASKRPCI@roswellpark.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alex A. Adjei</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 31, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
