<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="8320">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02013804</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AMP-514-01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>MEDI0680</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02013804</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase 1 Study to Evaluate AMP-514</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Multi-Center, Open-label, Multi-Dose Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, and Pharmacokinetics of AMP-514 in Subjects With Advanced Solid Malignancies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Amplimmune</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>MedImmune LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Amplimmune</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center, open-label, multi-dose, first-time-in-human study with a standard
      3+3 dose-escalation phase in subjects with advanced solid malignancies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects experiencing  dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs), adverse events (AEs), serious adverse events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 90 days after last dose of AMP-514</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) or optimal biological dose (OBD) will be determined by the number of subjects experiencing DLTs.  Safety profile will be assessed through the number of subjects experiencing AEs, SAEs, abnormal laboratory evaluations, vital signs, and physical examinations.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic profile of AMP-514</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 90 days after the last dose of AMP-514</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>AMP-514 concentrations in serum and PK parameters including peak concentration, area under the concentration-time curve, clearance, and half-life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess preliminary antitumor activity of AMP-514</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately every 3 months through 12 months following last cycle of AMP-514</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Disease status evaluated via RECIST 1.1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate pharmacodynamic effects of AMP-514 on its target receptor, PD-1, as well as effects on immune system function</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately every 3 months through 12 months following last cycle of AMP-514</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Includes assessment of receptor occupancy, reduction in PD-1 expression levels, and increase in T cells producing effector cytokines and lytic markers</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Solid Malignancies</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AMP-514</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Escalating doses of AMP-514</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AMP-514</intervention_name>
    <description>AMP-514 will be administered by IV infusion every 21 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>AMP-514</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MEDI0680</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ≥18 years of age at time of study entry

          -  Written informed consent and any locally required authorization (eg, Health Insurance
             Portability and Accountability Act [HIPAA]) obtained from the subject/legal
             representative prior to performing any protocol-related procedures, including
             screening evaluations

          -  Life Expectancy of ≥ 12 weeks

          -  Histologically- or cytologically-confirmed advanced solid tumor that is refractory to
             standard therapy or for which no standard therapy exists

          -  At least 1 measurable lesion per RECIST 1.1; subjects whose only measurable lesion is
             a lymph node will be excluded

          -  ECOG Performance Score of 0 or 1

          -  Adequate organ and marrow function

          -  Prior treatment toxicities must be ≤ Grade 1

          -  Willingness to provide consent for biopsy samples

          -  Females of childbearing and unsterilized males must use 2 methods of effective
             contraception from screening, and must agree to continue using such precautions for
             90 days after the final dose of AMP-514

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Concurrent enrollment in another clinical study, unless it is an observational (non
             interventional) clinical study or the follow-up period of an interventional study

          -  Receipt of any immunotherapy, BRAF inhibitor (in metastatic melanoma), or
             investigational anticancer therapy within 4 weeks prior to the first dose of AMP-514;
             in the case of monoclonal antibodies, 6 weeks prior to the first dose of AMP-514

          -  Prior exposure to any anti-PD-1 or anti-PD-L1 antibody

          -  Any prior Grade ≥3 immune-related adverse event (irAE) while receiving immunotherapy
             or any unresolved irAE &gt; Grade 1

          -  Major surgery (as defined by the investigator) within 4 weeks prior to first dose of
             AMP-514 or still recovering from prior surgery

          -  Other invasive malignancy within 2 years except for noninvasive malignancies such as
             cervical carcinoma in situ, non-melanomatous carcinoma of the skin or ductal
             carcinoma in situ of the breast that has/have been surgically cured

          -  Prior allogeneic or autologous bone marrow or organ transplantation that requires use
             of immunosuppressives

          -  Unresolved toxicities from prior anticancer therapy, defined as having not resolved
             to National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events
             (CTCAE) (NCI CTCAE v4.03) Grade 0 or 1, or to levels dictated in the
             inclusion/exclusion criteria with the exception of alopecia. Subjects with
             irreversible toxicity that is not reasonably expected to be exacerbated by AMP-514
             may be included (eg, hearing loss) after consultation with the MedImmune medical
             monitor.

          -  Active or prior documented autoimmune disease within the past 2 years NOTE: Subjects
             with vitiligo, Grave's disease, or psoriasis not requiring systemic treatment (within
             the past 2 years) are not excluded

          -  History of primary immunodeficiency

          -  Any concurrent chemotherapy, immunotherapy, biologic or hormonal therapy for cancer
             treatment. Concurrent use of hormones for non-cancer-related conditions (eg, insulin
             for diabetes and hormone replacement therapy) is acceptable.        NOTE: Local
             treatment of isolated lesions for palliative intent is acceptable (eg, by local
             surgery or radiotherapy)

          -  Current or prior use of immunosuppressive medication within 28 days before the first
             dose of AMP-514, with the exception of intranasal and inhaled corticosteroids or
             systemic corticosteroids at physiologic doses not to exceed 10 mg/day of prednisone
             or equivalent

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness

          -  Symptomatic or untreated central nervous system metastases requiring concurrent
             treatment

          -  Known history of tuberculosis

          -  Subjects who are known to be human immunodeficiency virus positive

          -  Subjects who are known to be hepatitis B or C positive

          -  Receipt of live attenuated vaccination within 30 days prior to study entry or within
             30 days of receiving AMP-514

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding women
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Solomon Langermann, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Amplimmune</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sarah Cannon Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amanda Mundy</last_name>
      <phone>615-329-7274</phone>
      <email>amanda.mundy@scresearch.net</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jeffrey Infante, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 18, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Non-small cell lung cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Renal cell cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Colorectal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Advanced malignant melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Advanced cutaneous melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatocellular cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck</keyword>
  <keyword>Gastroesophageal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Triple negative breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Pancreatic adenocarcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>AMP-514</keyword>
  <keyword>MEDI0680</keyword>
  <keyword>Advanced solid tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>PD-1</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti PD-1</keyword>
  <keyword>PD-L1</keyword>
  <keyword>PD-L2</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
