<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="19968">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01829711</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130106</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-C-0106</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01829711</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Moxetumomab Pasudotox for Advanced Hairy Cell Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pivotal Multicenter Trial of Moxetumomab Pasudotox in Relapsed/ Refractory Hairy Cell Leukemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Moxetumomab pasudotox is an experimental non-chemotherapy cancer treatment drug. It
      targets CD22, a molecule on the surface of essentially all hairy cell leukemia cells.
      Moxetumomab pasudotox binds to CD22, goes into the cell, and releases a toxin which kills
      the cell. In a phase I trial it had activity in relapsed/refractory hairy cell leukemia with
      safety profile supporting further clinical study (http://ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22355053).
      This is a phase III multicenter trial designed to confirm these results.

      Objectives:

      - To see how effective moxetumomab pasudotox is at destroying hairy cell leukemia tumor
      cells and producing lasting complete remissions.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals at least 18 years of age who have hairy cell leukemia that has not responded
      to or relapsed at least twice after standard therapy.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. Blood and urine
           samples will be collected. Imaging studies and heart and lung function tests will also
           be performed.

        -  Participants will have 28-day cycles of treatment. They will receive the study drug on
           days 1, 3, and 5 of every cycle. Each dose will take about 30 minutes.

        -  Treatment will be monitored with frequent blood and urine tests and imaging studies.

        -  The study will focus on the results from the first 6 months of treatment. However,
           participants will continue to take the study drug for as long as it is effective and
           the side effects are not severe.

        -  After stopping the study drug, participants will have frequent follow-up visits to
           monitor the outcome of the treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Hairy cell leukemia is an indolent B-cell leukemia comprising 2% of all leukemias, or
           approximately 900 of the 44,000 new cases of leukemia/year in the US

        -  Over the last two decades, immunotoxin research has accumulated to support a role for
           CD22-targeted therapy in the treatment of HCL.

        -  Moxetumomab pasudotox is a recombinant immunotoxin containing an Fv fragment of an
           anti-CD22 monoclonal antibody and truncated Pseudomonas exotoxin.

        -  Moxetumomab pasudotox has demonstrated a high complete remission (CR) rate in patients
           with chemoresistant hairy cell leukemia (HCL) and has shown activity in pediatric acute
           lymphoblastic leukemia as well.

        -  Modification of the structure of moxetumomab pasudotox has greatly improved binding and
           cytotoxicity toward CD22 expressing malignant cells compared to the precursor molecule.
           Preclinical and clinical studies have demonstrated that this increase in binding
           affinity results in improved antitumor activity and tolerability

        -  114 patients have been treated with moxetumomab pasudotox, including 48 with HCL.
           Moxetumomab pasudotox was generally well tolerated in HCL patients with no MTD defined
           and some patients treated for over a year.

        -  Currently there are no approved agents with significant efficacy for HCL patients after
           failure of standard therapy

      Objectives:

        -  The primary objective of this study is to determine the rate of durable complete
           response (CR) in multiply relapsed HCL with moxetumomab pasudotox. To meet the primary
           endpoint, patients will need to meet standard criteria for CR by analysis of blood,
           bone marrow and imaging, and maintain a hematologic remission (HR), namely the blood
           counts needed for CR, for &gt; 180 days.

        -  Secondary objectives include determining the overall response rate (ORR),
           progressionfree survival (PFS), time t otreatment failure (TIF), duration of responses
           (CR and PR), confirming safety, and evaluating immunogenicity and pharmacokinetics.

      Eligibility:

      - Histologically confirmed, immunotoxin-na(SqrRoot) ve hairy cell leukemia with a need for
      therapy based on at least one of the following criteria:

      neutrophils &lt;  1000/mm(3)

      platelets &lt;  100,000/mm(3)

      hemoglobin &lt;  10 g/dL)

      symptomatic splenomegaly.

        -  Have had at least 2 prior systemic therapies, including at least 2 prior courses of
           purine analog, or 1 if the response to this course lasted &lt;  1 year, or if the patient
           had unacceptable toxicity to purine analog.

        -  Age greater than or equal to 18 years

      Design:

        -  This is a multicenter, single-arm study of moxetumomab pasudotox in patients with
           relapsed/refractory hairy cell leukemia

        -  77 patients will be enrolled to receive 40 mcg/kg moxetumomab pasudotox IV on days 1, 3
           and 5 of each 28 day cycle until the subject progresses, toxicity occurs, the subject
           begins alternate therapy, or 2 cycles beyond CR (for subjects who have no assessable
           minimal residual disease). If less than or equal to 2 of the first 25 patients do not
           achieve durable CR, no additional patients will be accrued

        -  The primary endpoint is to determine the durable complete response (CR) rate of
           moxetumomab pasudotox with a minimum duration of &gt; 180 days. A durable CR will be
           defined as one in which hematologic remission (HR), namely the blood counts required
           for CR, are maintained for &gt; 180 days from the time CR was first confirmed by tests of
           marrow, imaging and blood. Recurrent sustained (nontransient) cytopenias, particularly
           during the first 6 months of CR, will prompt a repeat bone marrow study to confirm
           relapse. The durable CR rate and its 95% CI will be constructed using the exact
           probability method (Clopper-Pearson exact interval) in the Intent-to-Treat population.
           With 77 patients enrolled, there will be 90% power to detect a difference between 28%
           and 13% (expected CR rate from best alternative non-chemotherapy treatment, rituximab)
           durable CR rates using 2- sided significance level of 0.05.

      The overall IRB accrual ceiling is currently set at 80 to allow for a small number of
      patients that cannot be assessed for response.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of CR in patients treated with study drug</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>every 4 weeks.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relapse free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Once patients have a Complete Response (CR), they will be followed with  monthly blood work for 6 months then every 3 months for 2 years, then every 6 months.  Bone marrow examinations at 6 months then yearly for 2 years, then every 2 years.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Once patients have a Complete Response (CR), Patients will be followed with  monthly blood work for 6 months then every 3 months for 2 years, then every 6 months.  Bone marrow examinations at 6 months then yearly for 2 years, then every 2 years.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Leukemia, Hairy Cell</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive 40mcg/kg Moxetumomab Pasudotox IV over 30 minutes on days 1, 3, 5 of each 28 day cycle until CR, PD, initiation of alternate therapy or unacceptable toxicity.  There is no maximum duration of therapy on this protocol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>moxetumomab pasudotox</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IV Bag Protectant for Moxetumomab pasudotox</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Patients must have histologically confirmed hairy cell leukemia with a need for
             therapy based on at least one of the following criteria:

        neutrophils less than 1000/mm(3)

        platelets less than 100,000/mm(3)

        hemoglobin less than 10 g/dL)

        symptomatic splenomegaly.

          -  Patients must be Pseudomonas-immunotoxin na(SqrRoot) ve

          -  Patients must have had at least 2 prior systemic therapies, including at least 2
             prior courses of purine analog, or 1 if the response to this course lasted less than
             1 year, or if the patient had unacceptable toxicity to purine analog.

          -  Men or women age greater than or equal to 18 years. Because this disease does not
             generally occur in children, children are excluded from this study, but will be
             eligible for future pediatric trials in other indications.

          -  ECOG performance status less than or equal to 2.

          -  The effects of moxetumomab pasudotox on the developing human fetus are unknown. For
             this reason, women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate
             contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to
             study entry and for the duration of study participation, and 4 months after
             completion of moxetumomab pasudotox administration. Should a woman become pregnant or
             suspect she is pregnant while she or her partner is participating in this study, she
             should inform her treating physician immediately.

          -  Patients must have adequate organ function as defined below:

          -  total bilirubin less than or equal to 1.5 mg/dL, unless consistent with Gilbert   s
             (ratio between total and direct bilirubin greater than 5)

          -  AST and ALT less than or equal to 3 times upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  alkaline phosphatase less than or equal to 2.5 ULN

          -  serum creatinine less than or equal to 1.5 mg/dL or creatinine clearance greater than
             or equal to 60 mL/min as estimated by the Cockcroft-Gault equation

          -  Prothrombin time/INR or partial thromboplastin time less 2.5 ULN, fibrinogen greater
             than or equal to 0.5 LLN; if on warfarin, INR less than 3.5, if on any other
             anticoagulation, PT less than 2.5 times baseline

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent
             document.

          -  Life expectancy greater than or equal to 6 months

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA

          -  Patients who have had chemotherapy, immunotherapy or radiotherapy within 4 weeks
             prior to entering the study.

          -  Patients who are receiving any other investigational agents.

          -  Patients with known brain metastases should be excluded from this clinical trial
             because of their poor prognosis and because they often develop progressive neurologic
             dysfunction that would confound the evaluation of neurologic and other adverse
             events.

          -  Patients with clinically significant eye findings during screening

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding females. The effects of moxetumomab pasudotox on the
             developing fetus are unknown. Because there is an unknown but potential risk for
             adverse events in nursing infants secondary to treatment of the mother with
             moxetumomab pasudotox breastfeeding should be discontinued if the mother is treated
             with moxetumomab pasudotox

          -  Positive for Hepatitis B surface antigen unless the patient is on Lamivudine or
             Entecavir and Hepatitis B Viral DNA load is less than 2000 IU/mL.

          -  Lymph nodes greater than 4cm or prior splenectomy

          -  Active second malignancy requiring treatment other than minor resection of indolent
             cancers like basal cell and dquamous skin cancers

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, malaria infection or psychiatric illness/social situations that would
             limit compliance with study requirements.

          -  HIV-positive patients unless taking appropriate anti-HIV medications with a CD4 count
             of greater than 200. Otherwise, there may be increased risk of lethal infections when
             temporarily suppressing normal B-cells.

          -  History of allogeneic bone marrow transplant

          -  Patients with history of both thromboembolism and known congenital hypercoagulable
             conditions

          -  Uncontrolled pulmonary infection, pulmonary edema

          -  Oxygen saturation at rest less than 88% measured by pulse oximetry or PaO (2) less
             than or equal to  55 mm Hg

          -  Serum albumin less than 2 g/dL

          -  Radioimmunotherapy within 2 years prior to enrollment in study

          -  ANC less than 1000/mm(3), or platelet count less than 50,000/mm(3), if these
             cytopenias are not judged by the investigator to be due to underlying disease (ie,
             potentially reversible with antineoplastic therapy). A patient will not be excluded
             because of pancytopenia greater than or equal to Grade 3, or erythropoietin
             dependence, if it is due to disease, based on the results of bone marrow studies

          -  Patients with less than 50% of predicted forced expiratory volume (FEV1) or less than
             50% of predicted diffusing capacity for carbon monoxide (DLCO), corrected for
             hemoglobin concentration and alveolar volume. Note: Patients with no prior history of
             pulmonary illness are not required to have PFTs. FEV1 will be assessed after
             bronchodilator therapy.

          -  Patients with history of thrombotic microangiopathy or TTP-HUS.

          -  Patients with QTc elevation &gt;  grade 1

          -  Patient on high dose estrogen

          -  Patients with clinical evidence of disseminated intravascular coagulation

        Inclusion of Women and Minorities:

        Both men and women of all races and ethnic groups are eligible for this trial. No
        clinically important sex/gender and/or race ethnicity differences are expected from the
        intervention effect
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert J Kreitman, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Elizabeth J Maestri, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-5633</phone>
    <email>maestrie@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Robert J Kreitman, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 648-7375</phone>
    <email>kreitmar@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact National Cancer Institute Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>888-624-1937</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210-1240</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030-4096</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-C-0106.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bouroncle BA. Thirty-five years in the progress of hairy cell leukemia. Leuk Lymphoma. 1994;14 Suppl 1:1-12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>7820038</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jemal A, Siegel R, Ward E, Murray T, Xu J, Thun MJ. Cancer statistics, 2007. CA Cancer J Clin. 2007 Jan-Feb;57(1):43-66.</citation>
    <PMID>17237035</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sharpe RW, Bethel KJ. Hairy cell leukemia: diagnostic pathology. Hematol Oncol Clin North Am. 2006 Oct;20(5):1023-49. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16990105</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kreitman RJ, Tallman MS, Robak T, Coutre S, Wilson WH, Stetler-Stevenson M, Fitzgerald DJ, Lechleider R, Pastan I. Phase I trial of anti-CD22 recombinant immunotoxin moxetumomab pasudotox (CAT-8015 or HA22) in patients with hairy cell leukemia. J Clin Oncol. 2012 May 20;30(15):1822-8. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2011.38.1756. Epub 2012 Feb 21.</citation>
    <PMID>22355053</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 26, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 9, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Biologic Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Recombinant Immunotoxin</keyword>
  <keyword>Monoclonal Antibody</keyword>
  <keyword>Pseudomonas Exotoxin</keyword>
  <keyword>Targeted Therapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Hairy Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Protective Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
