<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="122678">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01879072</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BMTCTN1202</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U10HL069294-11</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01879072</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prospective Cohort for the Evaluation of Biomarkers Following HCT</brief_title>
  <acronym>BMTCTN1202</acronym>
  <official_title>Prospective Multi-Center Cohort for the Evaluation of Biomarkers Predicting Risk of Complications and Mortality Following Allogeneic HCT (BMT Clinical Trials Network (CTN)#1202)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical College of Wisconsin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Blood and Marrow Transplant Clinical Trials Network</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical College of Wisconsin</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this protocol is to establish a cohort of biologic samples collected
      prospectively from patients treated in BMT CTN centers that will be a shared biospecimen
      resource for conducting future allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HCT)
      correlative studies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this protocol is to establish a cohort of biologic samples collected
      prospectively from patients treated in BMT CTN centers that will be a shared biospecimen
      resource for conducting future allogeneic HCT correlative studies.  This resource is
      designed to allow genomic, proteomic and transcriptional data to be integrated with high
      quality clinical phenotype and outcomes data to identify risk factors for development and
      severity of acute GVHD, chronic GVHD, organ toxicity, relapse, mortality, infection and
      other clinically significant complications occurring after allogeneic HCT.

      To achieve this goal, patients and donors will be recruited and consent obtained at the time
      that they enroll on BMT CTN protocols where enrollment occurs at or before transplantation
      or prior to start of conditioning for patients enrolled on non-BMT CTN studies or treated as
      standard of care.  Samples will be collected: (1) from patients and donors pre-transplant;
      and, (2) from patients post-transplant on a calendar schedule through the first 3 months
      post-HCT.  For patients co-enrolled on BMT CTN studies, clinical data will be collected in
      the context of the primary transplant protocols.  For patients not enrolled on BMT CTN
      protocols, clinical data on early post-transplant events will be collected using the same
      data collection forms and systems that are used on BMT CTN trials.  Additional clinical data
      for both BMT CTN and non-BMT CTN patients will be available from data submitted to the
      Center for International Blood and Marrow Transplant Research (CIBMTR) using the CIBMTR
      Comprehensive Report Forms.  This protocol also leverages ongoing pre-transplant
      donor-recipient sample collection performed by the CIBMTR and National Marrow Donor Program
      (NMDP).  Success in establishing this shared resource will inspire future investigator
      initiated research proposals and will allow investigators to take advantage of National
      Institutes of Health (NIH) funding initiatives.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <target_duration>2 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Establish a cohort of biologic samples</measure>
    <time_frame>Two years from hematopoietic stem cell transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To describe patterns of disease among patients undergoing allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell.  The primary outcome will be measured by the number of participants who supply biologic samples.  The prospectively collected samples will be a shared biospecimen resource for conducting future correlative studies.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute Graft-versus-host disease (aGVHD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 100</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To describe patterns of aGVHD using The date of onset, severity, target organ involvement, treatment, and evolution over time, including response to treatment of acute GVHD is the main outcome of interest for future testing of the collected samples.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Chronic Graft-versus-host disease (cGVHD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Two years post-transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To describe patterns of cGVHD including the date of onset, severity, target organ involvement and evolution of chronic graft-versus-host disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Infections</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 100</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To describe patterns of infections through day 100.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relapse/Progression</measure>
    <time_frame>Two years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To describe patterns of relapse/progression post-transplant.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute liver injury</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 100</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To describe patterns of acute liver injury.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lung Injury</measure>
    <time_frame>Two years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To describe patterns of lung injury post-transplant.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Transplant-related mortality (TRM)</measure>
    <time_frame>Two years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To describe patterns of TRM post-transplant.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1500</enrollment>
  <condition>Recipients of Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      10mL serum for Proteomic studies for all 1500 patients at the following time points:
      pre-transplant, days 7, 14, 21, 28, 42, 56 and 90.

      Gene Expression studies will include the following:

        -  PAXgene Lysates-source whole blood RNA (15 ml blood) for 240 patients collected on days
           21 and 90.

        -  CytoChex tube for Immunophenotyping (4-5 mL blood) collected on days 21 and 90.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All U.S. Allogeneic Transplant Donors and Recipients weighing 20 or more kg may
        participate in the collection of samples.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Recipients of first allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplants that are transplanted
             in U.S. centers that participate in the NMDP/CIBMTR's &quot;Protocol for a Research Sample
             Repository for Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation and Marrow Toxic
             Injuries&quot; and receive a cord blood graft or receive a bone marrow or peripheral blood
             graft from a related donor or from an unrelated donor in an NMDP-affiliated Donor
             Center or Registry participating in that same protocol.

             This transplant and donor center restriction is to allow linkage with pretransplant
             donor specimens collected under the NMDP/CIBMTR protocol.  Current data indicate that
             &gt;90% of donors approached under this protocol agree to provide samples

          2. Patients with any malignant or non-malignant hematologic disorder will be eligible
             for enrollment on this protocol. A subset of 240 sequential patients with acute
             leukemia in first or second remission will also provide research samples for gene
             expression studies.

          3. Children may participate in this study but must weigh at least 20 kilograms given the
             volume (100ml) and number of blood draws during this study. Subjects must weigh at
             least 30 kg to provide research samples for gene expression studies (additional 40
             ml).

          4. All participants or parent/legal guardian must sign an informed consent for this
             study.

        Because studies using this resource will require linking with clinical data collected by
        CIBMTR, all participants or parent/legal guardian must also consent to participate in
        &quot;Protocol for a Research Database for Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation and Marrow Toxic
        Injuries&quot;.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  N/A
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mary Horowitz, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Center for International Blood and Marrow Transplant Research (CIBMTR), Medical College of Wisconsin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Linda Johnson</last_name>
    <phone>301-251-1161</phone>
    <phone_ext>2834</phone_ext>
    <email>ljohnson@emmes.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford Hospitals and Clinics</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Miklos, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>650-725-4626</phone>
      <email>dmiklos@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nemours Childrens Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32207</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anders Kolb, MD</last_name>
      <phone>302-651-5567</phone>
      <email>eakolb@nemours.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48105-2967</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John Levine, MD</last_name>
      <phone>734-247-2518</phone>
      <email>jelevine@med.umich.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas/MD Anderson CRC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amin Alousi, MD</last_name>
      <phone>713-745-3055</phone>
      <email>aalousi@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.bmtctn.net</url>
    <description>Blood and Marrow Transplant Clinical Trials Network Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 22, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 11, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Biomarkers</keyword>
  <keyword>Hematopoietic stem cell transplant</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
