<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="141081">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01693783</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2012-02877</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-02877</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>PHL-085</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>9209</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>N01CM00071</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>N01CM00038</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>N01CM00032</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01693783</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ipilimumab in Treating Patients With Metastatic or Recurrent Human Papilloma Virus-Related Cervical Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2 Study of Ipilimumab in Women With Metastatic or Recurrent HPV-Related Cervical Carcinoma of Either Squamous Cell or Adenocarcinoma Histologies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well giving ipilimumab works in treating patients with human
      papilloma virus (HPV)-related cervical cancer that has come back or that has spread to other
      areas of the body. Monoclonal antibodies, such as ipilimumab, can find tumor cells and help
      kill them or carry tumor-killing substances to them.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess the safety of ipilimumab in eligible patients with recurrent or metastatic
      cervical cancer.

      II. To assess the antitumor activity of ipilimumab in eligible patients with recurrent or
      metastatic cervical cancer via assessment of objective response rates (ORR).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess the antitumor activity of ipilimumab through secondary endpoints including of
      disease stabilization and progression free survival (PFS).

      II. Assessment of antitumor activity of ipilimumab using immune-related response criteria
      (irRC) III. Assessment of the predictive value of baseline C-reactive protein. IV. Assess
      the biologic responses of exposure to ipilimumab via correlative studies involving analysis
      of lymphocyte subsets and assessment of cervical cancer-antigen specific T cells anti-tumor
      response.

      V. Evaluation of archival tissue with regard to markers of immune population in correlation
      with clinical stage and response to treatment.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive ipilimumab intravenously (IV) over 90 minutes. Treatment repeats every 21
      days for 4 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients
      achieving objective response or stable disease continue to receive maintenance therapy
      comprising ipilimumab IV over 90 minutes once every 12 weeks. Maintenance treatment repeats
      every 21 days for 4 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for 1 year.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency and severity of adverse events, graded according to the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE) v4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Tabulated using counts and proportions detailing frequently occurring, serious and severe events of interest.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from start of treatment to time of progression or death, whichever occurs first, assessed up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Computed using the Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Antitumor activity (partial response [PR], complete response [CR], and stable disease [SD]) using immune-related response criteria (irRC) and Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) v1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Summary statistics, such as mean, median, counts and proportion, will be used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Predictive value of baseline C-reactive protein</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to week 3 of course 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">44</enrollment>
  <condition>Cervical Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Cervical Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Human Papilloma Virus Infection</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Cervical Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Cervical Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Cervical Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ipilimumab)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive ipilimumab IV over 90 minutes. Treatment repeats every 21 days for 4 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients achieving objective response or stable disease continue to receive maintenance therapy comprising ipilimumab IV over 90 minutes once every 12 weeks. Maintenance treatment repeats every 21 days for 4 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ipilimumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ipilimumab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>anti-cytotoxic T-lymphocyte-associated antigen-4 monoclonal antibody</other_name>
    <other_name>MDX-010</other_name>
    <other_name>MDX-CTLA-4</other_name>
    <other_name>monoclonal antibody CTLA-4</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ipilimumab)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histologically or cytologically confirmed metastatic or recurrent
             HPV-related cervical cancer of squamous, adenocarcinoma or mixed histology type not
             suited to definitive localized therapy

          -  Patients must have measurable disease, defined as at least one lesion that can be
             accurately measured in at least one dimension (longest diameter to be recorded for
             non-nodal lesions and short axis for nodal lesions) as &gt; 20 mm with conventional
             techniques or as &gt; 10 mm with spiral computed tomography (CT) scan, magnetic
             resonance imaging (MRI), or calipers by clinical exam

          -  Previous therapy:

               -  Patients may have undergone surgery and/or received definitive radiation or
                  chemo-radiation for localized disease in the past

               -  Radiation treatment must have been completed &gt;= 3 months prior to enrollment

               -  Patients must have been exposed to platinum chemotherapy either as part of
                  definitive chemo-radiation OR as first line systemic treatment for metastatic
                  disease

               -  Patients MAY have received up to two prior lines of systemic chemotherapy for
                  metastatic or recurrent disease; patients with metastatic disease at first
                  presentation MUST have received one platinum based line of chemotherapy

               -  All chemotherapy must have been completed &gt;= 4 weeks prior to enrollment with
                  radiologic evidence of radiological disease progression

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0-1

          -  Life expectancy of greater than 3 months

          -  Leukocytes &gt;= 3.0 x 10^9/L

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1.5 x 10^9/L

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100 x 10^9/L

          -  Total bilirubin within normal institutional limits (except in Gilbert's syndrome)

          -  Thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH) within normal institutional limits

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase
             [SGOT])/alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT])
             =&lt; 2.5 X institutional upper limit of normal

          -  Creatinine &lt; 1.25 x upper limit of normal (ULN) OR creatinine clearance &gt;=
             50mL/min/1.73 m^2 as calculated by the Cockroft and Gault formula

          -  All radiology studies must be performed =&lt; 3 weeks prior to the start of therapy

          -  Subjects with treated and asymptomatic brain metastases are eligible; patients that
             received palliative radiation (for brain metastases) are eligible if they do not
             require maintenance steroid treatment, have been asymptomatic for at least 2 weeks
             following cessation of steroid therapy, and last received radiation at least 4 weeks
             prior to start of therapy

          -  Ability to understand and willing to sign a written informed consent document

          -  Ongoing prior toxicities related to previous treatments must be recovered to &lt; grade
             1 at the time of registration (with the exception of alopecia or skin depigmentation)

          -  Patients are willing to undergo tumor biopsy pre-treatment (7 days prior to
             registration) and post-treatment (within the first week of cycle 2 onset); patients
             who consent but have tumor that is not amenable to safe biopsy will be allowed to
             enter the trial/continue therapy as per protocol if this has been addressed and
             permission is granted from the lead consortium principal investigator (PI) prior to
             registration continuation of treatment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have had chemotherapy &lt; 4 weeks prior to enrollment (&lt; 6 weeks for
             nitrosoureas or mitomycin C) or who had radiation &lt; 3 months prior to enrollment or
             those who have not recovered (&lt; grade 1) from adverse events related to previous
             treatments are excluded

          -  Patients with a history of prior treatment with Ipilimumab or other cytotoxic
             T-lymphocyte antigen 4 (CTLA4) agonists or antagonists, anti-programmed death 1 (PD
             1) antibody, cluster of differentiation (CD)137 agonist or other immune activating
             therapy such as anti-CD 40 antibody are excluded

          -  Patients who are receiving any other investigational agents

          -  Autoimmune disease: Patients with a history of inflammatory bowel disease, including
             ulcerative colitis and Crohn's disease, are excluded from this study, as are patients
             with a history of symptomatic disease (e.g., rheumatoid arthritis, systemic
             progressive sclerosis [scleroderma], systemic lupus erythematosus, autoimmune
             vasculitis [e.g., Wegener's granulomatosis]); central nervous system (CNS) or motor
             neuropathy considered of autoimmune origin (e.g. Guillain-Barre syndrome and
             Myasthenia Gravis, multiple sclerosis

          -  Patients requiring immunosuppressive agents, unless required for treating potential
             immune related adverse effects; steroids at their lowest effective dose in patients
             with radiated brain metastases is permitted

          -  Patients with known immune impairment who may be unable to respond to anti-CTLA 4
             antibody

          -  Any other prior malignancy from which the patient has been disease free for less than
             3 years, with the exception of adequately treated and cured basal or squamous cell
             skin cancer, superficial bladder cancer, carcinoma in situ of any site or any other
             cancer

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to ipilimumab

          -  Patients requiring systemic steroids are excluded, as these drugs may interfere with
             the activity of ipilimumab if administered at the time of the first ipilimumab dose;
             narcotics should be used with caution as they may mask the signs and symptoms of
             serious gastrointestinal immune-related adverse events (irAEs) including intestinal
             perforation

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements; patients with chronic hepatitis B or hepatitis C infections
             should be excluded because of potential effects on immune function and/ or drug
             interactions

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study because ipilimumab is an agent with the
             potential for teratogenic or abortifacient effects; because there is an unknown but
             potential risk for adverse events in nursing infants secondary to treatment of the
             mother with ipilimumab, breastfeeding should be discontinued if the mother is treated
             with ipilimumab

          -  Patients with active or chronic infection with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) who
             have raised viral loads or uncontrolled disease are ineligible because of the
             potential for anticipated and unknown adverse immune related effects secondary to
             treatment with ipilimumab; those patients however who exhibit minimal viral loads
             with good control whilst on stable anti-viral regimen may be considered if they meet
             all other eligibility criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amit Oza</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Princess Margaret Hospital Phase 2 Consortium</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City of Hope</name>
      <address>
        <city>Duarte</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mihaela C. Cristea</last_name>
      <phone>626-256-4673</phone>
      <email>mcristea@coh.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mihaela C. Cristea</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Southern California/Norris Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lynda D. Roman</last_name>
      <phone>323-865-0451</phone>
      <email>lroman@usc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lynda D. Roman</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California at Davis Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sacramento</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95817</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Edwin A. Alvarez</last_name>
      <phone>916-734-6900</phone>
      <email>edwin.alvarez@ucdmc.ucdavis.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Edwin A. Alvarez</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City of Hope South Pasadena</name>
      <address>
        <city>South Pasadena</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stephen C. Koehler</last_name>
      <phone>626-396-2900</phone>
      <email>Skoehler@cohmg.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephen C. Koehler</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gini F. Fleming</last_name>
      <phone>773-702-6712</phone>
      <email>gfleming@medicine.bsd.uchicago.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gini F. Fleming</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fox Chase Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lainie P. Martin</last_name>
      <phone>215-728-3889</phone>
      <email>lainie.Martin@fccc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lainie P. Martin</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tom Baker Cancer Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T2N 4N2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Prafull Ghatage</last_name>
      <phone>403-521-3721</phone>
      <email>Prafull.Ghatage@albertahealthservices.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Prafull Ghatage</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cross Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6G 1Z2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Katia S. Tonkin</last_name>
      <phone>780-432-8514</phone>
      <email>katia.tonkin@albertahealthservices.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Katia S. Tonkin</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>BC Cancer Research Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V5Z 1L3</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anna Tinker</last_name>
      <phone>604-877-6000</phone>
      <email>atinker@bccancer.bc.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anna Tinker</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Juravinski Cancer Centre at Hamilton Health Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L8V 5C2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Holger W. Hirte</last_name>
      <phone>905-387-9495</phone>
      <email>hal.hirte@jcc.hhsc.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Holger W. Hirte</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cancer Centre of Southeastern Ontario at Kingston General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kingston</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K7L 5P9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>James J. Biagi</last_name>
      <phone>613-544-2630</phone>
      <email>jim.biagi@krcc.on.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James J. Biagi</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>London Regional Cancer Program</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N6A 4L6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stephen A. Welch</last_name>
      <phone>519-685-8640</phone>
      <email>stephen.welch@lhsc.on.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephen A. Welch</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ottawa General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1H 8L6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Johanne I. Weberpals</last_name>
      <phone>613-737-8899ext76462</phone>
      <email>jweberpals@ottawahospital.on.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Johanne I. Weberpals</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Health Network-Princess Margaret Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 2M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amit M. Oza</last_name>
      <phone>416-946-2818</phone>
      <email>amit.oza@uhn.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amit M. Oza</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 30, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 21, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uterine Cervical Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Papilloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Virus Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Warts</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Papillomavirus Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cytotoxic T-lymphocyte antigen 4</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
