<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="45309">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02008526</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01DA035092</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02008526</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Theory-based Text Messaging to Reduce Methamphetamine Use and HIV Risks Among MSM</brief_title>
  <official_title>Theory-based Text Messaging to Reduce Methamphetamine Use and HIV Risks Among MSM</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Friends Research Institute, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Friends Research Institute, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Data and Safety Monitoring Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Participants receive culturally relevant and specifically tailored text messages based on
      the behavioral change theoretical constructs of Social Support Theory, Health Belief Model,
      and Social Cognitive Theory. Participants are randomized into one of three conditions for an
      8-week intervention period: Group 1: culturally relevant theory-based text messages
      interactively transmitted by peer health educators (TXT-PHE); or, Group 2: the same
      culturally relevant theory-based text messages transmitted by automation (TXT-Auto); or,
      Group 3: assessment-only (AO) control with no theoretically based text messages.
      Participants in all three conditions receive brief weekly text-message assessments on their
      methamphetamine use and HIV sexual behaviors in the previous seven days. Data related to
      intervention costs as well as relative exposure to each theoretical construct will be
      examined to determine cost- and mechanism-effectiveness, respectively.  The randomized
      three-group design uses repeated assessments at baseline, at the end of the 8-week
      intervention period, and at 3-, 6-, and 9-month post randomization follow-up.  This study
      will determine the differential immediate and sustained effects of transmitting theory-based
      text messages by PHE (TXT-PHE) versus by automation (TXT-Auto), compared to an
      assessment-only (AO) control condition among out-of-treatment, methamphetamine-using MSM for
      reductions of methamphetamine use and HIV sexual risk behaviors.  It is hypothesized that
      there will be significantly greater reductions in methamphetamine use and HIV sexual risk
      behaviors from text messages transmitted by PHE than by text messages transmitted by
      automation, which in turn will produce significantly greater reductions than the AO
      condition (PHE &gt; TXT &gt; AO).  In addition, this study will determine the cost-effectiveness
      of TXT-PHE vs. TXT-Auto compared to AO for reducing methamphetamine use and HIV sexual risk
      behaviors. The investigators hypothesize that the TXT-PHE intervention will prove more
      cost-effective than TXT-Auto in reducing methamphetamine use and HIV sexual risk behaviors,
      while the TXT-Auto condition will prove more cost effective than the AO condition in
      reducing these same outcomes (PHE &gt; TXT &gt; AO).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Methamphetamine Use</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 9-months post randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Self-reported and/or biomarker-confirmed methamphetamine use is assessed at baseline, weekly throughout the 8-week intervention, and at 3-, 6-, and 9-month follow-up assessments.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HIV Sexual Risk Behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 9-months post randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Self-reported HIV sexual risk behaviors and/or biomarkers for HIV and STIs  are assessed at baseline, weekly throughout the 8-week intervention, and at 3-, 6-, and 9-month post-randomization follow-up.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost Effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Cost-effectiveness data is collected quarterly throughout the course of the study using the UNAIDS template.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HIV Primary Care</measure>
    <time_frame>8-weeks post randomization, 3-/6-/9-months post randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>HIV-positive participants will be assessed according to their linkage/retention in HIV primary care and adherence to ART medication at 8-weeks, 3-, 6-, and 9-months post-randomization.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">285</enrollment>
  <condition>Methamphetamine Abuse</condition>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TXT-PHE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group 1: Gay-specific, Theory-based Text Messages Transmitted by Peer Health Educators (TXT-PHE) with &quot;Push and Pull&quot; Interactions.
Participants assigned to this group receive text-messaging from PHEs. This condition is interactive and tailored to the needs of the individual participant. PHEs initiate (i.e., &quot;push&quot;) text messages to participants and also respond to participant-initiated queries and participant responses to the PHE messages (i.e., &quot;pull&quot;).
Following the initial welcome message, participants receive five pre-written messages per day sent on a predetermined schedule. Participants who respond to the pre-written text messages or initiate queries or requests for support (&quot;pull&quot;) are sent additional real-time messages back from the PHE.
During the 8-week intervention, participants receive a brief weekly text-based assessment on their methamphetamine use and HIV sexual behaviors in the previous seven days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TXT-Auto</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group 2: Gay-specific, Theory-based Text Messages Transmitted by Automation (TXT-Auto) with &quot;Push Only&quot; interactions
Participants assigned to this group receive automatic text-messages.
Following the initial welcome message, participants receive five pre-written messages per day sent on a predetermined schedule.
During the 8-week intervention, participants receive a brief weekly text-based assessment on their methamphetamine use and HIV sexual behaviors in the previous seven days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Assessment Only (AO)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>During the 8-week intervention, participants receive a brief weekly text-based assessment on their methamphetamine use and HIV sexual behaviors in the previous seven days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gay-specific, Theory-based Text Messages Transmitted by Peer Health Educators (TXT-PHE)</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants receive five gay-specific, theory-based pre-written messages per day sent on a predetermined schedule. Participants who respond to the pre-written text messages or initiate queries or requests for support (&quot;pull&quot;) are sent additional real-time messages back from the PHE. Text messages are transmitted and responded to in real time, at the peak hours of high-risk activities. During the 8-week intervention, participants receive a brief weekly text-based assessment on their methamphetamine use and HIV sexual behaviors in the previous seven days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TXT-PHE</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gay-specific, Theory-based Text Messages Transmitted by Automation (TXT-Auto)</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants receive five gay-specific, theory-based pre-written messages per day sent on a predetermined schedule. During the 8-week intervention, participants receive a brief weekly text-based assessment on their methamphetamine use and HIV sexual behaviors in the previous seven days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TXT-Auto</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Self-identified MSM

          -  Between the ages of 18 and 65 years

          -  Methamphetamine use within the previous 3 months

          -  Unprotected anal intercourse (insertive or receptive) with a non-primary male partner
             in the previous 6 months

          -  Not currently in treatment or seeking methamphetamine abuse treatment

          -  Able and willing to fully charge a cellular phone daily

          -  Able and willing to provide informed consent

          -  Able and willing to comply with study requirements

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Does not identify as a MSM

          -  Not between the ages of 18 and 65 years

          -  Has not used methamphetamine in the previous 3 months

          -  Has not had unprotected anal intercourse (insertive or receptive) with a non-primary
             male partner in the previous 6 months

          -  Currently in treatment or seeking methamphetamine abuse treatment

          -  Unable or unwilling to fully charge a cellular phone daily

          -  Unable or unwilling to provide informed consent

          -  Unable or unwilling to comply with study requirements

          -  Unable to understand the Informed Consent Form

          -  Determined to have a more serious psychiatric condition (SCID verified) that is
             beyond the safe enrollment of study procedures
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cathy J Reback, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Friends Research Institute, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mitch Metzner, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(323) 463-1601</phone>
    <email>mmetzner@friendsresearch.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jesse B Fletcher, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(323) 463-1601</phone>
    <email>jfletcher@friendsresearch.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Friends Community Center, a division of Friends Research Institute, Inc., Los Angeles, CA 90028</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90028</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mitch Metzner, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>323-463-1601</phone>
      <email>mmetzner@friendsresearch.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reback CJ, Ling D, Shoptaw S, Rohde J. Developing a Text Messaging Risk Reduction Intervention for Methamphetamine-Using MSM: Research Note. Open AIDS J. 2010 May 14;4:116-22. doi: 10.2174/1874613601004030116.</citation>
    <PMID>20657827</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reback CJ, Grant DL, Fletcher JB, Branson CM, Shoptaw S, Bowers JR, Charania M, Mansergh G. Text messaging reduces HIV risk behaviors among methamphetamine-using men who have sex with men. AIDS Behav. 2012 Oct;16(7):1993-2002. Erratum in: AIDS Behav. 2012 Oct;16(7):2003.</citation>
    <PMID>22610370</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 27, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 3, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Friends Research Institute, Inc.</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Cathy Reback</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Text Messaging</keyword>
  <keyword>mHealth</keyword>
  <keyword>Methamphetamine</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>AIDS</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Methamphetamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
