<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="51840">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01755130</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012-0210</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-00149</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01755130</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>LOUIS-3D Breast Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Multimode Laser Optoacoustic Ultrasonic Tomography System for Breast Cancer Care</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>TomoWave Laboratories, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn if an imaging device called the Laser
      Optoacoustic Ultrasonic Imaging System (LOUIS-3D) is effective in detecting and monitoring
      changes in breast tumors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      If you agree to take part in this study, you will have the LOUIS-3D imaging procedure either
      on the same day or within 10 days of a regular scheduled visit for a mammogram, ultrasound,
      magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan, or any other breast imaging procedure, between 1 and
      7 days before your scheduled biopsy. The results of the LOUIS-3D imaging scans will be
      compared with the results of your other imaging scan(s).

      For the LOUIS-3D procedure, you will lay down on a specially-designed breast exam table and
      you will place your breast in a bowl-like imaging cup. The imaging cup will be filled with a
      gel that will help send signals to the imaging machine.

      The procedure will produce 2 types of images. For the first type, the imaging cup will
      deliver light from a laser that will travel into your breast and tumor. The light is
      designed to detect acoustic waves which produce an image. Even though all light will be
      contained in the imaging cup, you will wear laser safety goggles during the procedure.

      For the second type of image, the imaging cup will deliver an ultrasound to your breast
      which will produce an ultrasound image.

      During the scans, the imaging cup will rotate around the breast to create      3-dimensional
      pictures. The scans may be repeated several times. The entire LOUIS-3D procedure should take
      about 30 minutes to complete.

      Length of Study:

      You will be off study after the LOUIS-3D imaging procedure is complete.

      This is an investigational study.  The LOUIS-3D device is not FDA approved or commercially
      available. The use of the LOUIS-3D device to detect and monitor changes in breast tumors is
      investigational.

      Up to 96 participants will be enrolled in this study. All will be enrolled at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>LOUIS 3D Capability to Detect and Differentiate Breast Tumors</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary aim of this study is to successfully obtain images from LOUIS 3D and assess pathology in order to guide image calibration and gain knowledge about LOUIS 3D capabilities. Pathology will provide useful information including but not limited to type of malignancy, tissue type, and other qualitative information that is necessary for image calibration.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of False Positive Rate of LOUIS-3D Compared to Ultrasound for Breast Cancer Detection</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Secondary objective is to determine optimal scanning parameters by assessing certain machine parameters (e.g. illumination and detection conditions, laser pulse repetition rate, ultrasound emission characteristics, detection probe, coupling medium characteristics, software and firmware, etc.), anatomical information (speed of sound image, acoustic attenuation image, acoustic scattering image), and functional information (total hemoglobin distribution [THb] / image of angiogenesis density, image of blood oxygen saturation [SO2], and image of water distribution). Continuous variables summarized using descriptive statistics such as mean, standard deviation, median and range. Categorical variables tabulated by frequencies and the corresponding percentages.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">96</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LOUIS-3D Imaging Procedure</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Part I Years 1-4: Years 1-4 to develop and calibrate the LOUIS-3D machine. The subject of this project is to successfully obtain diagnostic imaging of breast tumors with new imaging technology, laser Optoacoustic Tomography system.
Part 2 Year 5:  Goal of part 2 to estimate and compare the false positive rate of LOUIS-3D compared to standard of care ultrasound.  Patients will have had a positive standard of care ultrasound requiring a biopsy (gold standard).  The LOUIS-3D images will be obtained within 7 days of the standard of care ultrasound.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LOUIS-3D Imaging Procedure</intervention_name>
    <description>LOUIS-3D imaging procedure either on the same day or within 10 days of a regular scheduled visit for a mammogram, ultrasound, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan, or any other breast imaging procedure, between 1 and 7 days before scheduled biopsy. Results of the LOUIS-3D imaging scans compared with results of other imaging scan(s). Entire LOUIS-3D procedure should take about 30 minutes to complete.</description>
    <arm_group_label>LOUIS-3D Imaging Procedure</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>x-ray</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Mass palpable or nonpalpable

          2. Tissue density - all tissue types

          3. Menses - any stage of cycle

          4. Age between 20-70 inclusive

          5. Breast size within specified size (e.g. B, C or D cup as appropriate per a fitting
             device)

          6. BIRADS category 4 or 5 as defined based on mammography and breast ultrasound
             indicating need for biopsy

          7. Tumor location - not in close proximity of chest wall (must be at least 10 mm from
             the chest wall)

          8. Index tumor size is no more than 2 centimeters

          9. Any tumor type (patients with inflammatory breast cancer may be included).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient is unable or unwilling to give informed consent for any reason

          2. Disability (psychiatric, neurological or physical, which precludes examination)

          3. Patient has tattoos on the region of interest.

          4. Patient has body piercing jewelry through the nipple that cannot be removed.

          5. Patient has had a core or excisional biopsy in the ipsilateral breast within 3 months
             (patients with previous fine needle aspirations but no US evidence of hematoma or
             post bx change may be included).

          6. Patient has inflammatory skin disease (i.e., psoriasis, eczema) affecting the breast.

          7. Currently taking hormonal replacement therapy

          8. Non-ambulatory or unable to comply with exam

          9. Weight in excess of exam table limits of 230 LB

         10. Prior biopsy clips present

         11. Implants present

         12. Pregnancy at 6 weeks or later when position on the stomach is not recommended or
             difficult (pregnancy test till not be required).

         13. Breastfeeding

         14. Previous breast radiation or surgery
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wei Yang, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Wei Yang, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-563-0127</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 18, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>LOUIS-3D</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast Study</keyword>
  <keyword>x-ray</keyword>
  <keyword>Multimode Laser Optoacoustic Ultrasonic Tomography System</keyword>
  <keyword>Mass palpable or nonpalpable</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast lesions</keyword>
  <keyword>Ductal carcinomas</keyword>
  <keyword>Lobular carcinomas</keyword>
  <keyword>Fibroadenomas</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
