<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="15043">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02006108</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>94027</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02006108</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Imaging Kidney Transplant Rejection Using Ferumoxytol-Enhanced Magnetic Resonance</brief_title>
  <official_title>Non-invasive MR Imaging Diagnosis of Transplant Rejection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Lucile Packard Children's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to develop a non-invasive imaging test for in vivo detection of
      kidney transplant rejection. The hypotheses are that 1) Ferumoxytol-MRI can generate
      accurate estimates of tissue iron concentrations and tissue macrophages. 2) The signal given
      by a renal allograft on Ferumoxytol-MRI demonstrates significant differences between
      rejected and non-rejected transplants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In children with kidney transplants, immunologically mediated rejection is the major cause
      of allograft failure. Thus, the therapeutic success of kidney transplants is highly
      dependent on the ability to avoid rejection during both the acute and chronic phase after
      transplantation. Children with kidney transplants currently undergo at least three routine
      (protocol) biopsies during the first two years after the transplantation in addition to
      biopsies required to investigate deterioration of kidney function. These biopsies are
      invasive and nearly always require general anesthesia, causing anxiety and distress of the
      patients and their parents, as well as significant costs to our health care system. There is
      currently no non-invasive diagnostic tool capable of detecting rejection in vivo. Thus, the
      goal of this study is to develop a non-invasive imaging test for in vivo detection of kidney
      transplant rejection. The investigators propose to accomplish this goal by detecting
      macrophage infiltration in kidney transplants with iron oxide nanoparticle-enhanced MR
      imaging. Macrophages play a major role in transplant rejection. CD68-positive macrophages
      comprise approximately 50% of the infiltrating leukocyte population in renal allograft
      rejection, they co-localize with areas of tissue-damage and fibrosis, and are preponderant
      in more severe forms of rejection. The investigators hypothesize that iron oxide
      nanoparticle-enhanced MR imaging can detect differences in macrophage infiltrations in renal
      allografts undergoing rejection as opposed to allografts without significant rejection. This
      hypothesis is based on the bio-physical properties of intravenously injected
      superparamagnetic iron oxide nanoparticles, which are phagocytosed by tissue macrophages and
      cause strong signal effects on MR images.

      The specific aims of the study are the following:

      Aim #1. Technical Development of a Quantitative Susceptibility Mapping (QSM)-Sequence for in
      vivo MRI detection and quantification of iron oxide nanoparticle-labeled macrophages.This
      aim will focus on the technical development of Quantitative Susceptibility Mapping (QSM), a
      novel MR imaging pulse sequence that will be used to accurately quantify the tissue
      concentration of free ferumoxytol and ferumoxytol in macrophages in renal allografts. Based
      on pulse sequence optimizations of phantoms with known concentrations of free and cell-bound
      iron, we expect to generate accurate estimates of tissue iron concentrations and macrophages
      with the QSM-MRI method.

      Aim #2. Detect rejection in kidney allografts with ferumoxytol-enhanced QSM-MRI. The
      investigators hypothesize that ferumoxytol can detect and quantify macrophages in kidney
      allografts, based upon the observation that iron oxide nanoparticles can be taken up by
      macrophages in malignant tumors. The investigators will evaluate the ability of ferumoxytol
      to map macrophage quantities in renal allografts, with histopathological correlation. We
      expect significantly higher ferumoxytol-MRI enhancement and macrophage quantities in
      rejected allografts compared to non-rejected allografts.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiologically detectable differences in signal intensity between healthy and rejected kidneys, measured using T2*/R2* maps</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours to 7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>According to the study hypothesis, macrophage infiltration into rejected kidneys will be significantly greater than in healthy kidneys; since macrophages are expected to phagocytose injected iron, there should be a detectable difference in signal intensity between healthy and rejected organs. This can be evaluated using semiquantitative T2* map and R2* maps.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of cell-bound iron quantities on QSM sequences with macrophage and iron stains on histopathology</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate our ability to quantify cell-bound iron using the novel QSM sequence, we use histopathological data showing 1) the iron content of renal tissue sampled, and 2) the level of macrophage infiltration of the renal tissue. We will perform iron and macrophage stains in biopsy tissues in order to determine this.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Kidney Transplant</condition>
  <condition>Transplant Rejection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Feraheme</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intravenous injection of Feraheme, 5 mg Fe/kg
Interventions:
Drug: Feraheme Procedure: MR Scan</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Feraheme</intervention_name>
    <description>Therapeutic classification: iron preparations. Use: Off-label use of ultrasmall paramagnetic iron nanoparticle as contrast agent for magnetic resonance imaging</description>
    <arm_group_label>Feraheme</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ferumoxytol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MRI-GE Healthcare 3 Tesla magnet</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients will undergo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Feraheme</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</other_name>
    <other_name>MR Imaging</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Completed solid organ transplant with referral for transplant follow-up

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Exclusion criteria comprise MR-incompatible metal implants, need of sedation (since
             an anesthesia is not supported by this), claustrophobia or
             hemosiderosis/hemochromatosis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Heike E Daldrup-Link, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Danielle Beecham, BA</last_name>
    <phone>(650)723-8406</phone>
    <email>dbecham@stanford.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jessica Donig, BA</last_name>
    <phone>(650)281-4534</phone>
    <email>Jdonig@stanford.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lucile Packard Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anne Sawyer</last_name>
      <phone>650-302-2846</phone>
      <email>amsawyer@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Heike E Daldrup-Link, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 4, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 28, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>kidney</keyword>
  <keyword>transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>rejection</keyword>
  <keyword>Feraheme</keyword>
  <keyword>ferumoxytol</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ferumoxytol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
