<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="23272">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01766713</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EZE</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01766713</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ezetimibe Versus Placebo in the Treatment of Non-alcoholic Steatohepatitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Ezetimibe Versus Placebo in the Treatment of Non-alcoholic Steatohepatitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Diego</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Diego</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) represents a spectrum of diseases ranging from
      simple steatosis to nonalcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH), the progressive form of liver
      disease that can lead to cirrhosis and liver-related mortality in persons who drink little
      or no alcohol.   Nonalcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH) represents the more severe end of this
      spectrum and is characterized by steatosis, ballooning degeneration and lobular inflammation
      with or without fibrosis. The etiology of NASH is not completely understood, but it is often
      associated with obesity, type 2 diabetes, hyperlipidemia and insulin resistance.
      Lipotoxicity, insulin resistance and oxidative stress appear to be central to the
      pathogenesis of NASH. Currently, there is no FDA approved treatment for NAFLD/NASH. Weight
      loss and exercise are the recommended but often difficult maintain these lifestyle changes
      in the long term and therefore therapeutic agents have been investigated. Ezetimibe is an
      LDL lowering agent that works through inhibition of the fat absorption from the small
      intestine. In this study, we propose to treat 50 patients with NASH with either Ezetimibe or
      placebo for 24 weeks. After an initial evaluation for insulin sensitivity, MRI liver fat
      distribution and liver biopsy, patients will receive either 10 mg/day of Ezetimibe or
      placebo. Patients will be monitored at regular intervals for symptoms of liver disease, side
      effects of Ezetimibe and serum biochemical and metabolic indices. At the end of 24-weeks,
      patients will have a repeat medical evaluation, liver MRI and liver biopsy. Pre and post
      treatment MRI-derived liver fat content, liver histology and insulin sensitivity will be
      compared. The primary end point of successful therapy will be improvement in hepatic
      steatosis measured by MRI. Secondary end points will be improvement in insulin sensitivity,
      liver histology and liver biochemistry.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Liver Biopsy</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Non Alcoholic Steatohepatitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ezetimibe</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>10 mg/day of Ezetimibe</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ezetimibe</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Ezetimibe</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age at entry at least 18 years.

          2. Serum alanine (ALT) or aspartate (AST) aminotransferase activities that are above the
             upper limits of normal. 19 or more in women and 30 or more in men.

          3. Evidence of hepatic steatosis or liver fat (&gt;5%) by MRI.

          4. Evidence of definite or suspected NASH

               1. Evidence of (definite) steatohepatitis on liver biopsy done within the previous
                  12 months with a NASH activity score of at least 4 (of a total possible score of
                  8) including a score of at least 1 each for steatosis, hepatocellular injury and
                  parenchymal inflammation. Histological criteria of steatohepatitis include: (1)
                  macrovesicular steatosis, (2) acinar zone 3 hepatocellular injury (ballooning
                  degeneration), (3) parenchymal and (4) portal inflammation. Additionally
                  helpful, but not required, features include the presence of (5) Mallory's
                  hyaline and (6) pericellular and/or sinusoidal fibrosis that predominantly
                  involves zone 3. If a liver biopsy is available within the last 12 months, then
                  a repeat biopsy may not be conducted unless there has been a considerable change
                  in body weight that may change liver histologic parameters associated with NASH

               2. Those who are suspected of having NASH and have not undergone a liver biopsy
                  within the last 12 months may undergo a liver biopsy as a screening liver biopsy
                  but would qualify for randomization into either ezetimibe or placebo arms only
                  if they meet histologic criteria of NASH.

          5. Written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Evidence of another form of liver disease.

               1. Hepatitis B as defined as presence of hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg).

               2. Hepatitis C as defined by presence of hepatitis C virus (HCV) RNA in serum.

               3. Autoimmune hepatitis as defined by anti-nuclear antibody (ANA) of 1:160 or
                  greater and liver histology consistent with autoimmune hepatitis or previous
                  response to immunosuppressive therapy.

               4. Autoimmune cholestatic liver disorders as defined by elevation of alkaline
                  phosphatase and anti-mitochondrial antibody of greater than 1:80 or liver
                  histology consistent with primary biliary cirrhosis or elevation of alkaline
                  phosphatase and liver histology consistent with sclerosing cholangitis.

               5. Wilson disease as defined by ceruloplasmin below the limits of normal and liver
                  histology consistent with Wilson disease.

               6. Alpha-1-antitrypsin deficiency as defined by alpha-1-antitrypsin level less than
                  normal and liver histology consistent with alpha-1-antitrypsin deficiency.

               7. Hemochromatosis as defined by presence of 3+ or 4+ stainable iron on liver
                  biopsy and homozygosity for C282Y or compound heterozygosity for C282Y/H63D.

               8. Drug-induced liver disease as defined on the basis of typical exposure and
                  history.

               9. Bile duct obstruction as shown by imaging studies.

          2. History of excess alcohol ingestion, averaging more than 30 gm/day (3 drinks per day)
             in the previous 10 years, or history of alcohol intake averaging greater than 10
             gm/day (1 drink per day: 7 drinks per week) in the previous one year.

          3. Contraindications to liver biopsy: platelet counts &lt; 75,000/mm3 or prothrombin time
             &gt;16 seconds or history of bleeding disorders

          4. Decompensated liver disease, Child-Pugh score greater than or equal to 7 points

          5. History of gastrointestinal bypass surgery or ingestion of drugs known to produce
             hepatic steatosis including corticosteroids, high-dose estrogens, methotrexate,
             tetracycline or amiodarone in the previous 6 months.

          6. Recent initiation or change of anti-diabetic drugs, including insulin, sulfonylureas,
             or thiazolidinediones in the previous 90 days.

          7. Use of ezetimibe or other agents in the same class within the 90 days prior to
             randomization and/or liver biopsy.

          8. Significant systemic or major illnesses other than liver disease, including
             congestive heart failure, coronary artery disease, cerebrovascular disease, pulmonary
             disease with hypoxia, renal failure, organ transplantation, serious psychiatric
             disease, malignancy that, in the opinion of the investigator would preclude treatment
             with ezetimibe and adequate follow up.

          9. Positive test for anti-HIV.

         10. Active substance abuse, such as alcohol, inhaled or injection drugs within the
             previous one year.

         11. Pregnancy or inability to practice adequate contraception in women of childbearing
             potential.

         12. Evidence of hepatocellular carcinoma: alpha-fetoprotein levels greater than 200 ng/ml
             and/or liver mass on imaging study that is suggestive of liver cancer.

         13. Any other condition, which, in the opinion of the investigators would impede
             competence or compliance or possibility hinder completion of the study.

         14. Serum creatinine &gt;1.5 mg/dl.

         15. Contraindications to ezetimibe use :

               1. History of allergic reaction to ezetimibe

               2. patients with acute liver injury or unexplained persistent elevations in ALT &gt;
                  500 U/L

               3. Women who are pregnant or may become pregnant

               4. Nursing mothers

         16. Contraindications to MRI:

               1. The subject has any contraindication to MR imaging, such as patients with
                  pacemakers, metallic cardiac valves, magnetic material such as surgical clips,
                  implanted electronic infusion pumps or other conditions that would preclude
                  proximity to a strong magnetic field.

               2. The subject has a history of extreme claustrophobia

               3. The subject cannot fit inside the MR scanner cavity
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Archana Bhatt</last_name>
    <phone>619-471-3915</phone>
    <email>abhatt@ucsd.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, San Diego</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Archana Bhatt</last_name>
      <phone>619-471-3915</phone>
      <email>abhatt@ucsd.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 18, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 9, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Diego</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rohit Loomba</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Clinical Medicine, Division of Gastroenterology, Department of Medicine and</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fatty Liver</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ezetimibe</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
