<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="8117">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01752504</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ATN 095</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01752504</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Connect to Protect (C2P): Building a Community-Based Infrastructure for HIV Prevention</brief_title>
  <official_title>Connect to Protect (C2P): Building a Community-Based Infrastructure for HIV Prevention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study seeks to implement Connect to Protect® (C2P), a community mobilization
      intervention, which entails developing coalitions to plan for and bring about structural
      changes for purposes of reducing HIV incidence and prevalence among youth in targeted
      communities at five ATN sites.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The C2P community mobilization model entails: determining a geographic area and population
      of focus for the coalitions to prioritize their planning and action; developing coalitions
      that have a shared vision and mission; developing a strategic plan focused on structural
      changes to reduce risks associated with HIV; documenting processes; providing feedback as
      technical assistance to the coalitions; hosting regular working group meetings; and on-going
      capacity building. The National Coordinating Center (NCC), operating under the direction of
      the Protocol Chair, provides guidance, training, technical assistance and feedback to
      coalitions.

      The evaluation of C2P includes both process evaluation (i.e., documentation of coalition
      actions and achievements of structural changes; interviews with Key Informants (KI) and
      assessments of structural changes to assess impacts of coalitions accomplishments) of the
      mobilization efforts and outcome evaluation of the changes in individual risk factors
      associated with HIV transmission and acquisition.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Increase in protective partner selection behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>Year 5</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>According to the Adolescent Trials Network (ATN)/C2P model, partner selection is highly related to HIV risk. Specific behaviors such as the proportion of youth reporting age-discordant relationships, sex with HIV-positive partners, and sex with intravenous drug user (IDU) will be evaluated over time and in relation to structural changes enacted within intervention communities. Data is derived from anonymized ACASI surveys of adolescents and young adults at elevated risk for HIV.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Increase in condom use with main and casual partners among adolescents and young adults at elevated risk for HIV</measure>
    <time_frame>Year 5</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>According to the ATN/C2P model, condom use is an important mediator of HIV risk. Proportions of youth reporting condom use at last sex, and consistent condom use, with both main and casual partners will be evaluated over time and in relation to structural changes enacted within intervention communities. Data is derived from anonymized ACASI surveys of adolescents and young adults at elevated risk for HIV.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease in number of sex partners reported over the preceding 3 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Year 5</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Youth with multiple sex partners are at increased risk of contracting HIV. The number of reported sexual partners over the last 3 months will be evaluated over time and in relation to structural changes enacted within intervention communities. Data is derived from anonymized ACASI surveys of adolescents and young adults at elevated risk for HIV.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease in the proportion of youth reporting risky injection drug use practices</measure>
    <time_frame>Year 5</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Needle sharing among youth who inject drugs increases risk for HIV. The proportion of youth reporting injection drug use, sharing needles, and cleaning needles will be evaluated over time and in relation to structural changes enacted within intervention communities. Data is derived from anonymized ACASI surveys of adolescents and young adults at elevated risk for HIV.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease in the proportion of youth reporting sexually transmitted infections in the last year</measure>
    <time_frame>Year 5</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Incident sexually transmitted infections both increase an individual's vulnerability to HIV infection and indicate that an individual is engaging in behaviors that may also put them at risk for HIV. The proportion of youth reporting having a sexually transmitted infection in the last year will be evaluated over time and in relation to structural changes enacted within intervention communities. Data is derived from anonymized ACASI surveys of adolescents and young adults at elevated risk for HIV.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Increase in the proportion of youth seeking testing for HIV</measure>
    <time_frame>Year 5</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>HIV counseling and testing services are an important component of prevention programs. The proportion of youth reporting that they have been tested for HIV will be evaluated over time and in relation to structural changes enacted within intervention communities. Data is derived from anonymized ACASI surveys of adolescents and young adults at elevated risk for HIV.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine whether intervention communities have a greater reduction in public health surveillance indicators of HIV risk</measure>
    <time_frame>Year 5</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine whether intervention communities have a greater reduction in public health surveillance indicators of HIV risk, including number of new cases of HIV and other sexually transmitted infections (STIs), compared to non-intervention demographically similar communities within all ATN 095 cities at the end of the study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine factors associated with successful completion of structural change objectives (SCOs) at sites</measure>
    <time_frame>Close of Year 5 (using 5 year data)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Where there has been a decreased risk for HIV (i.e., individual level change), examine attributes of the SCOs in order to provide guidance and recommendations to policy makers. Attributes that will be analyzed include:
Change strategy (e.g., information provision, policy change, relationship formation, program creation)
Sector(s) where change occurs
Community vs. individual risk conditions
Distal vs. proximal causes targeted</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine factors associated with coalition health and success.</measure>
    <time_frame>Close of Year 5 (using 5 year data)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This process evaluation will analyze how the intervention worked, including:
Determining which strategies (e.g., creating linkages, honest brokering, strategic partnering, etc.) are associated with successful SCOs.
Determining whether coalitions with greater measures of health and functioning have had greater success in achieving SCOs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1550</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Evaluation group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Consists of three sub-groups of youth:
VT participants: Each youth will participate in a single session visit to complete an anonymous Audio Computer-Assisted Self-Administered Interview (ACASI) lasting approximately 30 minutes.  Youth may participate up to a maximum of two times over the course of the study; once each per years one and five.
BVI participants: Each youth will participate in a single, five- minute survey.
HIV-Related Risk (RR) participants: Each youth will participate in a single session visit to complete an anonymous ACASI lasting approximately 60 minutes and anonymous HIV-Ab specimen collection in years one and five.  This will be followed by a 10-15 question, self-administered paper and pen survey containing questions developed by the site and its coalition.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Community members who become engaged in the coalitions and in the broader mobilization effort. A subset of community members, (i.e., Key Informants) will be interviewed to assess the potential impact of coalition work and achievements.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Community Mobilization</intervention_name>
    <description>The C2P community mobilization intervention begins, as described in this protocol, with a series of approximately four capacity building meetings with community partners to establish the coalitions and to build their capacity for strategic planning around structural change. This will be followed by launching the coalition's strategic planning with the identification of SCOs that the coalitions work to achieve. SCOs are new or modified policies, programs, practices, laws or changes to the built environment. The mobilization effort will include continual development of the coalitions' infrastructure and capacity for identifying and achieving relevant SCOs to influence risk, regular review of strategic plans and SCOs, and the development of new SCOs to achieve. Our primary study objective is to determine if the achievement of community-identified SCOs result in reduced individual risk as indicated by venue-based anonymous surveys with at-risk youth.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Evaluation group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria Three sub-groups of participants make up the evaluation group: (1) VT;
        (2) BVI; and (3) HIV-RR.

        Inclusion Criteria (VT and HIV-RR Participants)

        To be considered eligible for enrollment, an individual must meet the following criteria:

          1. Provides verbal confirmation that his or her age falls within the range of the site's
             population of focus (which must be within 12 through 24 years, inclusive);

          2. Provides verbal confirmation of demographic and sexual orientation/experience profile
             reflective of the site's population of focus;

          3. Reports engaging in any voluntary sexual activity (vaginal, anal and/or oral sex)
             within the past 12 months, regardless of sexual abuse history; and

          4. Has the ability to understand and is willing to provide verbal informed
             consent/assent in English or Spanish.

        Inclusion Criteria (BVI Participants)

        1. All adolescents and young adults encountered at the venue that appear to be 12-24 years
        old inclusive, and of the gender of the site's population of focus.

        Exclusion Criteria (VT and HIV-RR Participants)

        1. Verbal confirmation of participation in the same survey-type within the past six
        months.

        Exclusion Criteria (BVI Participants)

        1. Verbal confirmation of prior participation in the BVI.

        Exclusion Criteria (VT, BVI and HIV-RR Participants)

        To be considered eligible for enrollment, an individual must not meet the following
        criteria, which is based on ATN/C2P staff assessment:

        Visibly distraught and/or visibly emotionally unstable (e.g., depressive mood; exhibiting
        manic, suicidal, or violent behavior);* Presents as acutely ill; and/or Visibly
        intoxicated or under the influence of psychoactive agents.**
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>25 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jonathan Ellen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dina Monte, BSN, CCRC</last_name>
    <phone>(914) 591-6170</phone>
    <email>dinamonte@westat.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado - The Children's Hospital of Denver</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Emily A Barr, CPNP,CNM,MSN</last_name>
      <phone>720-777-6752</phone>
      <email>betsy.mcfarland@ucdenver.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Amy Witte, FNP</last_name>
      <phone>720-777-4495</phone>
      <email>witte.amy@tchden.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elizabeth J McFarland, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thuy C Anderson, BSN</last_name>
      <phone>443-287-8888</phone>
      <email>tander34@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jennifer Chang, BA</last_name>
      <phone>443-287-8888</phone>
      <email>jchang46@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jonathan Ellen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Allison Agwu, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fenway Community Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marcy S Gelman, CRNP</last_name>
      <phone>617-927-6021</phone>
      <email>mgelman@fenwayhealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Emily George, RN</last_name>
      <phone>617-927-6246</phone>
      <email>egeorge@fenwayhealth.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kenneth Mayer, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wayne State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Monique L Green-Jones, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>313-966-9763</phone>
      <email>mogreen@med.wayne.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Charnell Cromer, MSN</last_name>
      <phone>313-966-0622</phone>
      <email>ccromer@med.wayne.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elizabeth Secord, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor College of Medicine/Texas Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Norma Cooper, RN</last_name>
      <phone>832-824-1319</phone>
      <email>njcooper@texaschildrenshospital.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Nancy Calles, MSN</last_name>
      <phone>832-822-1038 (receptionist)</phone>
      <email>ncalles@bcm.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mary Paul, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.atnonline.org</url>
    <description>ATN Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 8, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 8, 2011</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV positive communities</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
