<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="63790">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01941537</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>JKR-0766</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01941537</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Randomized Placebo-controlled Study to Determine the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacodynamics and Clinical Efficacy of ILV-094 (an IL-22 Antibody) Administered Intravenously to Subjects With Atopic Dermatitis (AD)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study to Determine the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacodynamics and Clinical Efficacy of ILV-094 (an IL-22 Antibody) in Subjects With Atopic Dermatitis (AD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rockefeller University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rockefeller University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Atopic dermatitis (AD) is a common inflammatory skin disorder that adversely affects most
      aspects of everyday life in majority of patients.  It has a prevalence of up to 3-4% of
      adults and up to 25% among children.  AD has a complex pathogenesis, characterized by: 1)
      immune activation with increased numbers of T-cells, dendritic cells (DCs), and increased
      expression of inflammatory molecules 2) marked epidermal hyperplasia in chronic diseased
      skin, and 3) defective barrier function with increased trans-epidermal water loss (TEWL) and
      decreased lipids, reflecting underlying alterations in keratinocyte differentiation.  AD is
      predominantly a Th2 (IL-4, IL-13, and IL-31) disease, and recently was also found to be a
      &quot;T22&quot; (IL-22) polarized disease.

      ILV-094 is an anti IL-22 antibody and therefore should reverse the immune activation of AD.
      This study is being done to assess the safety, tolerability, clinical efficacy, and
      mechanism of action of ILV-094 in patients with AD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, study of six IV infusions of ILV-094
      administered to subjects with atopic dermatitis. Sixty subjects will be randomly assigned in
      a 2:1 ratio to one of the two treatments arms (ILV-094 vs placebo). Forty patients will be
      enrolled in the ILV-094 treatment arm and 20 in the placebo-treatment arm, accordingly. A
      loading IV dose of 600 mg of ILV-094 or placebo will be given at baseline (Day 0), followed
      by five additional IV doses of 300 mg of ILV-094 or placebo every two weeks (Weeks 2, 4, 6,
      8, and 10). We will continue to follow the patients every two weeks for an additional 10
      weeks after the last IV dose (20 weeks post baseline).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the clinical benefit as measured by SCORAD (Scoring of AD) of intravenous (IV) administration of ILV-094 administered to subjects with atopic dermatitis (AD).</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess the clinical benefit, safety and tolerability of intravenous (IV) administration of ILV-094 administered to subjects with atopic dermatitis (AD). The clinical effects on AD disease activity will be evaluated by the change in the Scoring of AD  (SCORAD) index and investigator's global assessment (IGA) index of AD at week 12.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the clinical benefit, safety and tolerability as measured by IGA (Investigator's Global Assessment of intravenous (IV) administration of ILV-094 administered to subjects with atopic dermatitis (AD).</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess the safety and tolerability of intravenous (IV) administration of ILV-094 administered to subjects with atopic dermatitis (AD) as measured by IGA at week 12.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reversal of the pathological epidermal phenotype during ILV-094 therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Reversal of the pathological epidermal phenotype during ILV-094 therapy, and which immune pathways are suppressed during treatment with the drug.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Atopic Dermatitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ILV-094</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Forty patients will be enrolled in the ILV-094 treatment arm. A loading IV dose of 600 mg of ILV-094 will be given at baseline (Day 0), followed by five additional IV doses of 300 mg of ILV-094 every two weeks (Weeks 2, 4, 6, 8, and 10).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Twenty patients will be enrolled in the ILV-094 placebo arm. A loading IV dose of placebo will be given at baseline (Day 0), followed by five additional IV doses of placebo every two weeks (Weeks 2, 4, 6, 8, and 10).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ILV-094</intervention_name>
    <description>IV infusion of ILV-094</description>
    <arm_group_label>ILV-094</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ILV-094</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Comparator</intervention_name>
    <description>Twenty patients will be enrolled in the ILV-094 placebo arm. A loading IV dose of placebo will be given at baseline (Day 0), followed by five additional IV doses of placebo every two weeks (Weeks 2, 4, 6, 8, and 10).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Signed and dated an IRB/IEC-approved ICF before any study-specific screening
             procedures were performed.

          -  Men or women of nonchildbearing potential (WONCBP), aged ≥18 years inclusive at
             screening. WONCBP could be included if they were either surgically sterile
             (hysterectomy and/or bilateral oophorectomy) or postmenopausal for ≥1 year (with
             follicle-stimulating hormone [FSH] ≥38 IU/mL) and had a negative pregnancy test
             result within 48 hours before administration of test article.

        Women who were surgically sterile must have provided documentation of the procedure by an
        operative report or by ultrasound.

        Sexually active men must have had agreed to use a medically acceptable form of
        contraception during the study and continued for 12 weeks after test article
        administration.

        -Body mass index (BMI) ≥18 kg/m2 and body weight ≥50 kg. BMI was calculated by taking the
        subject's weight, in kilograms, divided by the square of the subject's height, in meters,
        at screening (BMI = weight (kg)/ (height [m]) 2).

        Must have met the following criteria for disease activity, at screening and/or at study
        entry (subjects who washout from prior therapy may not meet this level of disease activity
        at screening but must before being entered into the study):

          -  Must have had stable moderate to severe chronic plaque psoriasis covering ≥15% of
             body surface area, and be a candidate for systemic therapy or phototherapy.

          -  PASI score &gt;11.

          -  PGA Psoriasis score ≥3.

          -  Target lesion score ≥6 based on the physician rating of selected sites for erythema,
             plaque elevation and scaling, with a minimal of 2 on the plaque elevation score. A
             12-point score was used with a 1-4 scale for each domain. Target lesions should not
             have been on the scalp, axillae, face or groin.

          -  Subjects with psoriasis must have been generally healthy, but might have been
             enrolled with stable, chronic illness, if the disease was well controlled, and did
             not interfere with the primary objectives of the study.

          -  Had a high probability for compliance with and completion of the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of active or latent serious infections (TB, or other granulomatous disorders
             such as histoplasmosis, coccidioidomycosis, etc). Skin colonization by Staph. aureus
             is expected in a high percentage of atopic patients with active disease and will not
             be considered as an exclusion criteria.

          -  Have a known malignancy or history of malignancy (except for basal or squamous cell
             carcinoma completely excised without evidence of recurrence and treated carcinoma in
             situ of the cervix) or lymphoproliferative diseases such as including lymphoma, or
             signs and symptoms suggestive of possible lymphoproliferative disease, such as
             lymphadenopathy of unusual size or location (e.g. nodes in the posterior triangle of
             the neck, intraclavicular, epitrochlear or periaortic areas) or splenomegaly.

          -  Have a nontuberculous mycobacterial infection or opportunistic systemic infection
             (e.g., Pneumocystis carinii, and aspergillosis) within 6 months prior to screening.

          -  Have positive HIV by history or POCT on the screening visit.

          -  Have documented current active hepatitis B (surface antigen positive or asymptomatic
             chronic carriers) or a history of hepatitis C infection (anti-HCV positive), by
             history and/or screening test.

          -  Have a history of substance abuse (drug or alcohol) within the past year before
             screening.

          -  Have a serious concomitant illness that could require the use of systemic
             corticosteroids or otherwise interfere with the patient's participation in the trial.

          -  Pregnant women or women that are breast feeding or plan to breast feed.

          -  Evidence of acute or unstable clinically significant disease (eg, unstable
             cardiovascular, cerebrovascular, respiratory, renal, or psychiatric disease or any
             unstable serious disorder requiring active frequent monitoring.

          -  Evidence of other concomitant skin conditions (eg, psoriasis, or lupus erythematosus)
             other than atopic dermatitis that would interfere with evaluations of the effect of
             study medication on atopic dermatitis.

          -  Have shown a previous immediate hypersensitivity response, including anaphylaxis, to
             an immunoglobulin product (plasma-derived, recombinant, e.g. monoclonal antibody).

          -  Use of any investigational small molecule drug within 90 days before the first dose
             of test article administration.

          -  Have a transplanted organ (with the exception of a corneal transplant performed &gt;3
             months prior to screening).

          -  Have concomitant autoimmune disease (such as lupus, rheumatoid arthritis, multiple
             sclerosis, Crohn's Disease, etc).

          -  Clinically important deviation from normal limits in physical examination, vital sign
             measurements, 12-lead electrocardiograms (ECGs), or clinical laboratory tests
             results, not associated with a chronic, well-controlled medical condition. Examples
             of these deviations include following:

               1. Undiagnosed hypertension.

               2. Evidence of undiagnosed ischemic heart disease or potentially clinically
                  significant arrhythmia on ECG.

               3. Hemoglobin  &lt;9 g/dl

               4. WBC count  &lt; 3.5 x 109 cells/L

               5. Neutrophils  &lt;1 x 109 cells/L

               6. Platelets  &lt; 100 x 109 cells/L

               7. AST/SGOT and ALT/SGPT levels above 2 times the upper limit of normal for the
                  laboratory conducting the test.

               8. Alkaline phosphatase levels above 2 times the upper limit of normal for the
                  laboratory conducting the test.

          -  Live vaccines within 3 months before test article administration or during the study.

          -  Any medical, psychological or social condition that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, would jeopardize the health or well-being of the participant during any
             study procedures or the integrity of the data.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Emma Guttman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Rockefeller University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lauren Corregano</last_name>
    <phone>1-800-RU-CARES</phone>
    <email>rucares@rockefeller.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Saakshi Khattri</last_name>
    <phone>212-327-8354</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Rockefeller University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lauren Corregano</last_name>
      <phone>800-782-2737</phone>
      <email>rucares@rockefeller.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 11, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 29, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Atopic Dermatitis</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis, Atopic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
