<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="156578">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02135692</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201312</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02135692</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase 3a, Repeat Dose, Open-label, Long-term Safety Study of Mepolizumab in Asthmatic Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>Study 201312: A Multi-Centre, Open-Label, Study of Mepolizumab in a Subset of Subjects With a History of Life Threatening/Seriously Debilitating Asthma Who Participated in the MEA115661 Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center, open-label, long-term study of subcutaneously (SC) administered
      mepolizumab 100mg in addition to standard of care (SOC), in subjects with severe
      eosinophilic asthma. This study will enroll a subset of subjects from Study MEA115661 who
      have demonstrated clear benefit from therapy and who without continuation of mepolizumab
      therapy are individuals at greatest risk of serious deterioration of their health status. In
      order to target individuals at greatest risk for serious deterioration of their health
      status, only subjects from the MEA115661 study with a history of life-threatening or
      seriously debilitating asthma, will be allowed to participate. Subjects meeting all of the
      eligibility criteria for the study will be offered the opportunity to consent for this study
      of up to 128 weeks in length (including the Follow-Up Visit). This study will give
      opportunity to extend the collection of clinical data for long-term use and further assess
      the sustainability of efficacy in a population likely to experience significant loss of
      asthma control and the need for higher doses of systemic steroids if returned to SOC only.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Annualized rate of exacerbations</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Weeks 128</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Exacerbations will be defined as worsening of asthma which requires use of systemic corticosteroids (CS) and/or hospitalisation and/or emergency department (ED) visits.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of all adverse events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Weeks 128</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Descriptive analysis of the safety profile of mepolizumab.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of positive anti-mepolizumab binding antibodies/neutralizing antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Weeks 128</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected for the determination of anti-mepolizumab antibodies, just prior to administration of mepolizumab. Samples testing positive for anti-mepolizumab antibodies will be further tested for neutralising antibody.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Asthma Control Questionnaire-5 score</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Weeks 128</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Asthma Control Questionnaire-5 (ACQ-5) is a five-item questionnaire used to measures a subject's asthma control.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Weeks 128</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>FEV1 is a measure of lung function.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of withdrawals due to lack of efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Weeks 128</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of subject withdrawals due to lack of efficacy will be summarized.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of withdrawals due to AEs</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Weeks 128</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of subject withdrawals due to adverse events will be summarized.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of hospitalizations due to AEs including asthma exacerbations</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Weeks 128</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of subject hospitalizations due to adverse events or exacerbations will be summarized.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of both systemic (i.e., allergic and non-allergic) and local site reactions</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Weeks 128</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A summary of AEs of special interest.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>12 lead ECG parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Weeks 128</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A summary of the mean changes in specific safety ECG parameters from baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety as assessed by vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Weeks 128</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Vital signs including sitting pulse rate and blood pressure measurements.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety as assessed by clinical laboratory parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Weeks 128</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Clinical laboratory tests as measured by parameters for hematology and clinical chemistry.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">375</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mepolizumab 100 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All subjects will receive mepolizumab 100mg administered SC into the upper arm or thigh approximately every 4 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mepolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Mepolizumab is a fully humanised IgG antibody (IgG1, kappa) with human heavy and light chain frameworks. Mepolizumab will be supplied as a lyophilised cake in sterile vials for individual use.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mepolizumab 100 mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SOC</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard of Care (SOC) will differ by participant, however it will generally include oral corticosteroids and an inhaled controller medicine (an inhaled corticosteroid plus a long acting beta agonist) and/or short acting beta agonists</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mepolizumab 100 mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Informed Consent: Prior to commencing any study related activities, subjects must be
             able and willing to provide written informed consent.

          -  Male or Eligible Female Subjects: To be eligible for the study, females of
             child-bearing potential must commit to consistent and correct use of an acceptable
             method of birth control and for 4 months after the last study drug administration. A
             urine pregnancy test is required of all females of childbearing potential at the
             initial Baseline Visit (Visit 1).

          -  French Subjects Only: In France, a subject will be eligible for inclusion in this
             study only if either affiliated to or a beneficiary of a social security category.

          -  MEA115661 Participation: Subjects must have completed Visit 14 of MEA115661.

          -  Current Anti-Asthma Therapy: The subject's asthma has been treated with an ICS
             controller medication for the last 8 months with fluticasone propionate (FP) &gt;=500
             mcg/day (or equivalent).

          -  Disease Severity: Subjects must be assessed as having life-threatening /serious
             debilitating asthma in order to enroll, as defined by the following: Subjects
             enrolled in MEA115588 must meet one of the following criteria: a) Subject has a
             history of at least one intubation during their lifetime; b) &gt;=3 asthma exacerbations
             in the 12 months prior to screening for MEA115588; c) &gt;=1 or more hospitalization for
             asthma exacerbation in the 12 months prior to screening for MEA115588. Subjects
             enrolled in MEA115575 must meet one of the following criteria: d) Subject has a
             history of at least one intubation during their lifetime; e) Their optimized dose at
             randomization in MEA115575 was &gt;=10mg of prednisone; f) &gt;=1 or more hospitalization
             for asthma exacerbation in the 12 months prior to screening for MEA115575.

          -  Clinical Benefit: Subjects must have experienced documented clinical benefit to
             enroll. Subjects must meet the following criteria demonstrating clinical benefit:
             Subjects enrolled in MEA115588 who received mepolizumab must meet all of the
             following criteria: a) Subject must have had a reduction in their exacerbation
             frequency by &gt;=50% during MEA115588. The baseline for comparison is the total number
             of exacerbations reported in the 12 months prior to screening for MEA115588. b) The
             investigator response on the &quot;Clinician-Rated Response to Therapy&quot; questionnaire at
             Visit 10 was either: mildly improved, moderately improved or significantly improved.
             Subjects enrolled in MEA115588 who received placebo must meet all of the following
             criteria: c) Subject must have had a reduction in their exacerbation frequency by
             &gt;=50% during the first 8 months of MEA115661. The baseline for comparison is the
             total number of exacerbations reported in the 12 months prior to screening for
             MEA115588; d) The investigator confirms that the subject demonstrated improvement
             during MEA115661. Subjects enrolled in MEA115575 who received mepolizumab must meet
             all of the following criteria: e) Subject must have reduced their oral corticosteroid
             dose by &gt;=50% during MEA115575. The baseline for comparison is the subject's
             optimized oral corticosteroid (OCS) dose at randomization in MEA115575; f) The
             investigator response on the &quot;Clinician-Rated Response to Therapy&quot; questionnaire at
             Visit 9 was either: mildly improved, moderately improved or significantly improved.
             Subjects enrolled in MEA115575 who received placebo must meet all of the following
             criteria: g) Subject must have reduced their oral corticosteroid dose at
             randomization by &gt;=50% in the first 6 months of MEA115661. The baseline for
             comparison is the subject's optimized OCS dose at randomization in MEA115575; h) The
             investigator confirms that the subject demonstrated improvement during MEA115661.

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Health Status: Clinically significant change in health status during MEA115661 which
             in the opinion of the investigator would make the subject unsuitable for
             participation in this long-term study.

          -  Pregnancy: Subjects who are pregnant or breastfeeding. Subjects should not be
             enrolled if they plan to become pregnanDeart during the time of study participation.

          -  Exacerbation History: Subjects who received placebo in MEA115588 and had NO
             exacerbations during the study.

          -  Oral Corticosteroid Use: Subjects who received placebo in MEA115575 and were able to
             discontinue oral corticosteroid therapy by the end of the study.

          -  Smoking Status: Current smokers

          -  Previous Significant Protocol Deviation: Subjects who were excluded from the per
             protocol analysis due to significant protocol deviations in either study MEA115575 or
             MEA115588.

          -  Electrocardiogram (ECG) Assessment: A clinically significant ECG abnormality at the
             exit visit of MEA115661, as determined by the investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
    <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 22, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 8, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Severe eosinophilic asthma</keyword>
  <keyword>Extension study</keyword>
  <keyword>Expanded access</keyword>
  <keyword>Safety</keyword>
  <keyword>Mepolizumab</keyword>
  <keyword>Eosinophils</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
