<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1327">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01693900</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2011-285</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01693900</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Compare the Ultrasound-guided Fascia Iliaca Compartment Block (FICB) to Surgeon-placed Fascia Iliaca Compartment Block for Post-operative Pain Control in Patients Undergoing an Anterior Hip Replacement Surgery.</brief_title>
  <official_title>EFFICACY OF FASCIA ILIACA BLOCK VERSUS INTRAOPERATIVE NERVE INFILTRATION DURING ANTERIOR HIP REPLACEMENT SURGERY</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Randy Fayne, DO</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>William Beaumont Hospitals</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Surgical trauma causes nerve sensitization leading to amplification and prolongation of
      postoperative pain. In experimental studies, pre-injury neural blockade using local
      anesthetics has been shown to reduce post-injury sensitization of the central nervous
      system, while similar techniques applied after the injury had less or no effect (FILOS).
      Investigators have therefore designed this study to examine the timing of FICB
      (pre-operatively versus intra-operatively) on postoperative pain in patients undergoing
      anterior hip replacement surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Though still uncommonly used in the United States, the popularity of the anterior approach
      for total hip replacement is rapidly growing because of its clinical advantages.
      Rehabilitation is simplified and accelerated, dislocation risk is reduced, leg length is
      more accurately controlled, and incision is smaller than with traditional approaches
      (GOEBEL).  Nevertheless, although pain is lessened, it is still considerable, and new
      techniques have been developed to improve postoperative pain control for this procedure.

      Surgical incision and tissue trauma result in postoperative pain.  Regional pain blocks,
      especially when done under ultrasound guidance, have proven to be extremely effective at
      reducing postoperative pain and improving patient satisfaction.  One such block, the fascia
      iliaca compartment block (FICB), has been shown to be effective in controlling pain
      associated with surgery involving the hip and femur.

      Although possible without ultrasound guidance, using this technique allows for
      identification of specific tissue planes and precise placement of medication near the nerves
      responsible for postoperative pain.  Using ultrasound, the superficial fascial layer of the
      iliopsoas muscle is identified at the anterior edge of the ilium, and a needle is placed
      just beneath that fascia.  A high volume of local anesthetic is then injected under
      ultrasound guidance, ensuring cephalad spread of medication, in an attempt to provide
      anesthesia of the lateral femoral cutaneous, femoral and obturator nerves.

      Unlike other approaches to hip replacement, anterior repair allows for direct visualization
      of the fascial layers described above.  This allows for direct injection of local anesthetic
      beneath this fascia, potentially obviating the need for preoperatively performed, ultrasound
      guided, FICB.  The primary differences in approach (ultrasound guided preop versus direct
      visualization intraop) is the timing of injection, and it is unclear if nerve block prior to
      or after tissue damage affects postoperative pain in these patients.

      Surgical trauma causes nerve sensitization leading to amplification and prolongation of
      postoperative pain. In experimental studies, pre-injury neural blockade using local
      anesthetics has been shown to reduce post-injury sensitization of the central nervous
      system, while similar techniques applied after the injury had less or no effect (FILOS).
      Investigators have therefore designed this study to examine the timing of FICB
      (pre-operatively versus intra-operatively) on postoperative pain in patients undergoing
      anterior hip replacement surgery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>to determine if timing of FICB affects postoperative pain</measure>
    <time_frame>From time of PACU admission until 3 week post-op appointment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Pain assessments will be made by the subject using a 10.0 mm VAS and a standard 10 point Likert scale (see attached) as follows at each time point:
Baseline assessment in Preoperative area
Upon arrival to the post-anesthesia care unit (PACU)
Every 15 min (+/- 2 minutes) thereafter and prior to any request for pain medication until PACU discharge
Prior to every request for pain medication
A global assessment of postoperative pain and a Post-operative patient satisfaction, using a 10 point Likert scale, will be assessed at the 3 week routine outpatient surgical visit by the study surgeon.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>measurement of incidence of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Adverse events will be reported by the patient (or when appropriate, staff personnel) from the signature on the informed consent document for the duration of the hospital stay, an expected average of 2 - 3 days.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>comparison of patient satisfaction between the 2 groups</measure>
    <time_frame>At the 3 week post-op visit</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Post-operative patient satisfaction, using a 10 point Likert scale, will be assessed at the 3 week routine outpatient surgical visit by the study surgeon.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Anterior Hip Replacement</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-operative Ultrasound FICB Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>25 subjects will receive FICB with 50cc of 0.3% ropivacaine. Blocks  will be performed under an ultrasound guidance device with an in-plane technique by a single study investigator, in the preoperative area.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intra-operative FICB Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>25 subjects will receive FICB with 50cc of 0.3% ropivacaine. Blocks will be performed intra-operatively under direct surgeon visualization, in the operating room.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pre-operative Ultrasound FICB Group</intervention_name>
    <description>25 subjects will receive FICB with 50cc of 0.3% ropivacaine. Blocks will be performed under an ultrasound guidance device with an in-plane technique by a single study investigator, in the preoperative area. Although possible without ultrasound guidance, using this technique allows for identification of specific tissue planes and precise placement of medication near the nerves responsible for postoperative pain.  Using ultrasound, the superficial fascial layer of the iliopsoas muscle is identified at the anterior edge of the ilium, and a needle is placed just beneath that fascia.  A high volume of local anesthetic is then injected under ultrasound guidance, ensuring cephalad spread of medication, in an attempt to provide anesthesia of the lateral femoral cutaneous, femoral and obturator nerves</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-operative Ultrasound FICB Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intra-operative FICB Group</intervention_name>
    <description>25 subjects will receive FICB with 50cc of 0.3% ropivacaine. Blocks will be performed intra-operatively under direct surgeon visualization, in the operating room. Unlike other approaches to hip replacement, anterior repair allows for direct visualization of the fascial layers described above.  This allows for direct injection of local anesthetic beneath this fascia, potentially obviating the need for preoperatively performed, ultrasound guided, FICB.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intra-operative FICB Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults 18-65 years of age

          -  Female patients must be surgically sterile, postmenopausal or have a negative
             pregnancy test on the day of surgery

          -  Willing and able to sign the informed consent approved by the IRB (Institutional
             Review Board)

          -  Willing and able to complete the study procedures and pain scales, and to communicate
             meaningfully in English with study personnel

          -  Elective anterior hip replacement to be performed at Beaumont Hospital, Royal Oak

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists physical status classification 1, 2, and 3
             (patients that have either no systemic illness, or mild to moderate systemic disease,
             eg. asthma, diabetes or hypertension)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of allergy to study medications including ropivacaine and other local
             anesthetic agents of the amide-type

          -  Enrollment in concurrent research study

          -  Female patients who are pregnant or lactating, or who have a positive urine pregnancy
             test

          -  Opioid tolerant, ie, A patient taking a narcotic &gt; 30mg per day morphine equivalent.
             (Source: www.globalrph.com/narcotic.cgi) for pain in the 2 months prior to surgery

          -  A medical condition that in the investigator's opinion could adversely impact the
             patient's participation or safety, conducts of the study, or interferes with the pain
             assessments

          -  Previous hip arthroplasty (partial or total) of the index hip

          -  History of illicit drug use, or prescription medicine or alcohol abuse within the
             past 2 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Randy Fayne, DO</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Beaumont Health System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cynthia Turzewski, RN, BSN</last_name>
    <phone>248-898-1907</phone>
    <email>Cynthia.Turzewski@beaumont.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beaumont Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Royal Oak</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48073</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cynthia Turzewski,RN, BSN</last_name>
      <phone>248-898-1907</phone>
      <email>Cynthia.Turzewksi@beaumont.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 9, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 23, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>William Beaumont Hospitals</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Randy Fayne, DO</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principle Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
