<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="70514">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01926041</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201303041RINB</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01926041</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effectiveness of Smoking Cessation in Prediabetic Smokers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Community-based Pilot Study of the Effectiveness of Smoking Cessation for Prediabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Taiwan University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Science Council, Taiwan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Taiwan University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Taiwan: Department of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Smoking is one of major risk factor for incident type 2 diabetes mellitus (DM), and smoking
      cessation can improve insulin resistance. Nowadays, the second-generation cessation program
      in Taiwan brings higher accessibility. However, there is little evidence on the long-term
      health outcomes of smoking cessation for the prediabetics in the community.

      This project is of five-year design. The investigators plan to recruit at least 596
      prediabetic smokers and 600 prediabetic non-smokers from communities. Initially, a
      cross-sectional analysis will be performed to investigate the physiological and
      psychological characteristics in prediabetic smokers. All participants are provided with
      standardized diet, lifestyle education, and skills of body weight self-management, with
      prospective follow-up every 3-6 months. Individuals may voluntarily attend smoking cessation
      program. Cox regression models and Kaplan-Meier methods will be used to investigate the
      effectiveness of the smoking cessation and body weight self-management in prediabetics
      regarding new-onset DM risk, glucose control, cardiovascular events, chronic kidney
      diseases, chronic hepatitis or cirrhosis, malignancy, and the relevant physiological and
      psychological parameters of interest.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators plan to recruit the study participants from 1) individuals who had
      abnormal glucose data at employment health examination or adult preventive care service in
      about 20 communities, including Yunlin, Changhua, Chiayi, and Taipei; 2) patients who has
      past history of metabolic syndrome and has been regularly followed-up at National Taiwan
      University Hospital and its Yun-Lin branch. All participants should give informed consent
      for this project and medical record review, with personal data protected.

      A history of diabetes, hypertension, FTND, alcohol consumption, physical activity,
      depression, sleep quality, and current medications is collected through standardized
      personal interview. Prediabetics are those repeatedly having either of the following: 1)
      plasma glucose 100 to 125 mg/dL (5.6 to 6.9 mmol/L) in the fasting state; 2) plasma glucose
      140 to 199 mg/dL (7.8 to 11.0 mmol/L) two hours after a 75-g oral glucose load; 3)
      glycosylated hemoglobin (A1C) 5.7% to 6.4%, in the absence of diabetic medications.
      Prediabetics who smoke ≥10 CPD for at least 6 months are classified as prediabetic smokers.
      Prediabetic non-smokers are also recruited.

      According an online sample size calculator (www.openepi.com), the investigators estimate to
      recruit at least 596 prediabetic smokers, in case 33% (199) of them joining the smoking
      cessation program, to reach a 90% power and two-sided confidence interval 95% for the
      detection of a 50% reduction from a risk for incident DM at 3-year follow-up.17 Besides, the
      investigators intend to recruit a total of 600 prediabetic non-smokers, including past
      smokers, for baseline analysis.

      Body height and weight are measured using a single stadiometer, and body mass index (BMI)
      was calculated. The participants are classified as either normal or underweight (BMI &lt;23
      kg/m2), overweight (BMI 23 to 24.9 kg/m2), or obese (BMI ≥25 kg/m2), according to the World
      Health Organization criteria for Asian populations. Waist circumference is taken at the end
      of exhalation in the horizontal plane at the midway point between the inferior margin of the
      lowest rib and the iliac crest. Central obesity is defined as a waist circumference ≥90 cm
      for men or ≥80 cm for women, according to the criteria for metabolic syndrome used in Taiwan
      (www.hpa.gov.tw). Blood pressure (BP) is measured with an electronic sphygmomanometer with
      the patient seated after resting for at least ten minutes. Each participant undergoes
      laboratory testing after fasting for at least ten hours. Serological tests include serum
      hepatitis B surface antigen, serum antibody to hepatitis C virus, and hepatitis B e antigen,
      determined via a microparticle enzyme immunoassay (Abbott Laboratories, Illinois, USA).
      Hepatitis B viral load for hepatitis B carriers is measured with a COBAS TaqMan real-time
      polymerase chain reaction assay (Roche Diagnostics, Basel, Switzerland), detecting an upper
      limit of 640,200,000 copies/mL and a lower limit of 35 copies/mL (1 copies/mL = 0.1718
      IU/mL). Serum adiponectin levels (in μg/mL) are determined by using the Procarta Cytokine
      Assay Kit (Affymetrix, Inc., California, USA) as in our recent report.

      Plasma glucose levels are determined through the hexokinase method (1 mg/dL = 0.0555
      mmol/L). Serum fasting insulin levels are measured using the COBAS electrochemiluminescence
      immunoassay (Roche Diagnostics, Basel, Switzerland) (1 μIU/mL = 6.945 pmol/L). Insulin
      resistance scores are determined by the homeostasis model assessment of insulin resistance
      (HOMA-IR),23 as calculated by the following formula: HOMA-IR score = fasting insulin
      (μIU/mL) × fasting glucose (mg/dL)/405. Participants will be categorized as insulin
      resistant if the HOMA-IR is 2.5 or higher. Plasma lipid, alanine aminotransferase (ALT), and
      creatinine levels are measured using a Hitachi 7150 Automated analyzer (Hitachi, Tokyo,
      Japan). Estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) is calculated using the four-variable
      version of the Modification of Diet in Renal Disease Study equation for Chinese Patients.25
      Briefly, eGFR (ml/min per 1.73 m2) = 175 × (serum creatinine -1.234) × (age -0.179) × 0.79
      (if female). The hypertriglyceridemia is defined as a plasma triglycerides level ≥150 mg/dL
      (1.70 mmol/L); and the hypercholesterolemia is defined as a plasma total cholesterol level
      ≥200 mg/dL (5.18 mmol/L). The low high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C) is defined as
      a serum HDL level &lt;40 mg/dL (1.04 mmol/L) in men and &lt;50 mg/dL (1.29 mmol/L) in women.

      Metabolic syndrome is defined clinically, based on the presence of three or more of the
      American Heart Association/National Heart Lung Blood Institute (AHA/NHLBI) criteria: (i)
      central obesity; (ii) hypertriglyceridemia or on drugs for elevated triglycerides; (iii) a
      low HDL-C level or on drugs for reduced HDL-C; (iv) high BP (≥130/85 mm Hg) or on
      antihypertensive drugs; and (v) a high fasting plasma glucose or taking anti-diabetic drugs
      for hyperglycemia. The International Diabetes Federation (IDF) criteria are also applied
      when defining metabolic syndrome, if participants have central obesity plus any two of the
      other four components.

      For descriptive analyses, values are presented as either a number (percent) or mean ±
      standard deviation (SD). For univariate analyses, categorical data are compared by means of
      the χ2 test or Fisher exact test. Continuous variables are compared using the two-sample
      Student's t-test. Statistical significance levels are determined by two-tailed tests (P
      value &lt; 0.05). In the end of enrollment (July of 2015), we will compare baseline
      characteristics among prediabetic smokers and prediabetic non-smokers, stratified by gender
      and BMI groups. Subgroup analysis will explore the association between adipocytokines, BMI,
      metabolic factors and viral load for prediabetic hepatitis B carriers.

      Changes in smoking habit for prediabetic smokers are recorded every 3 to 6 months. In the
      end of follow-up, hazard ratios (HRs) and 95% confidence intervals (95% CIs) of smoking
      cessation for incident DM risk or other outcome parameters during a 3 to 5-year follow-up
      period are estimated by multivariate Cox regression models after controlling age, gender,
      BMI (time-varying covariate) or body weight change (gainer, reducer, maintainer), BP,
      lipids, current medications, plasma ALT level, eGFR, daily coffee consumption, alcohol
      consumption, physical activity, depression, and sleep quality. Both intention-to-treat
      analysis and per-protocol analysis will be performed (Figure 1a, 1b). The former is based on
      the initial group assignment and not on the treatment eventually received. In the latter
      analysis, only participants who complete the entire clinical trial according to the protocol
      are counted towards the final results. That is, the independent variable &quot;smoking cessation&quot;
      reserves only for prediabetic smokers who succeed in quitting and keeping no relapse. For
      those who fail in quitting or keeping no relapse, they are still classified as
      self-management group and the individual follow-up period is from the study enrollment.

      We assume missing values over time as missing at random and do listwise deletion. We will
      test the assumption of proportional hazards by Kaplan-Meier curves for time fixed
      covariates, and by creating selected time dependent variables inside PROC PHREG with
      PROPORTIONALITY_TEST statement. Stratification analysis by baseline BMI group may be done.
      Additive and multiplicative interaction between change in smoking status and body weight on
      DM risk will also be estimated. Subgroup follow-up analysis will explore the association
      between change in adipocytokines, BMI, metabolic factors and viral load in prediabetic
      hepatitis B carriers. Unadjusted Kaplan-Meier survival curves of liver cancer for quitters
      versus non-quitters will be drawn. All of the abovementioned statistical analyses are
      performed with SAS software version 9.3 (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC, USA).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Diagnosis of diabetes mellitus by ADA criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>at least 3 years (from Aug 1, 2013)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary outcome is DM, defined as having repeatedly at least one of the following criteria: 1) plasma glucose ≥126 mg/dL (7.0 mmol/L) in the fasting state; 2) plasma glucose ≥200 mg/dL (11.1 mmol/L) randomly with hyperglycemic symptoms or two hours after a 75-g oral glucose load; 3) A1C ≥6.5%;20 or under medications for physician-diagnosed DM.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>A1C Change and Regression to Normoglycemia</measure>
    <time_frame>at least 3 years (from Aug 1, 2013)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Normoglycemia is defined as having all the following for over 3 months: 1) plasma glucose &lt;100 mg/dL (5.6 mmol/L) in the fasting state; 2) plasma glucose &lt;140 mg/dL (7.8 mmol/L) two hours after a 75-g oral glucose load; 3) A1C &lt;5.7%, in the absence of diabetic medications.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diagnoses of cardiovascular events</measure>
    <time_frame>at least 3 years (from Aug 1, 2013)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>by specialists</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Chronic kidney disease progression</measure>
    <time_frame>at least 3 years (from Aug 1, 2013)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>including change in eGFR and microalbuminuria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Chronic hepatitis or cirrhosis progression</measure>
    <time_frame>at least 3 years (from Aug 1, 2013)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>confirmed by ultrasonography or advanced image or pathology studies</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Malignancy incidence</measure>
    <time_frame>at least 3 years (from Aug 1, 2013)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>confirmed by national cancer registry system</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>All-cause mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>at least 3 years (from Aug 1, 2013)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Deaths are ascertained by computer linkage to the national death registry (death certificates were created by the Department of Health, Taiwan) using ID numbers and these death certificates have been validated.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1200</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <condition>Cigarette Smoking</condition>
  <condition>Prediabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Smoking cessation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in smoking cessation program will receive counseling from a physician and a nurse, educational materials explaining smoking cessation techniques, and prescriptions. Drugs are administered according to the manufacturer's directions, and a 1- to 4-week supply of medicine is prescribed at every clinic visit. Users can receive their medications for a course of 8 weeks in the following 90 days, with a maximum of two courses within one year (www.hpa.gov.tw). During the therapy course, physicians are allowed to adjust varenicline dosages according to tolerability.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Self-management</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants who decide not to attend the smoking cessation program will be classified as self-management group. They are still provided with standardized diet and lifestyle education, with prospective follow-up of Fagerström Test for Nicotine Dependence (FTND) scores, breath carbon monoxide (CO) levels, anthropometric indices and blood tests every 3-6 months. The skills of body weight self-management (with the goals of at least a 7 percent weight loss and at least 150 minutes of physical activity per week) are delivered through individualized counseling and educational materials.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Smoking cessation</intervention_name>
    <description>Each participant also receives counseling for individualized smoking cessation techniques at each visit. We do not prescribe the nicotine replacement therapy because it may induce insulin resistance and confound our study outcome. Bupropion is not available in our institutions and not prescribed. Varenicline users are encouraged to set either a fixed quit date or a flexible quit date. Varenicline is administered according to the manufacturer's directions, and a 1- to 4-week supply of medicine is prescribed at every clinic visit. At the end of the program, smoking status is assessed by self-reported 7-day point-prevalence abstinence, confirmed by a breath CO level of less than 3 ppm. We provide incentives to help minimize the relapse rate.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Smoking cessation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Smoking cessation program</other_name>
    <other_name>Body weight control</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Self-management</intervention_name>
    <description>The skills of body weight self-management (with the goals of at least a 7 percent weight loss and at least 150 minutes of physical activity per week)are delivered through individualized counseling and educational materials. Both the smoking cessation group and self-management group are provided with individualized counseling and incentives to help reach the goals of at least a 7 percent weight loss.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Smoking cessation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Self-management</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>lifestyle change</other_name>
    <other_name>body weight control</other_name>
    <other_name>diet modifications</other_name>
    <other_name>exercise</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals aged from 30 to 75 years

          -  Prediabetics (ADA criteria): including prediabetic smokers and non-smokers

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Acute cardiac conditions within 3months

          -  Acute renal failure

          -  Chronic glomerulonephritis

          -  Polycystic kidney disease

          -  Use of diabetic medications, steroids, lithium or antipsychotics

          -  Pregnancy or breast-feeding

          -  Malignancy.

          -  The elderly adults visiting two or more hospitals due to multiple diseases
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chien-Hsieh Chiang, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Taiwan Univeristy Hospital Yun-Lin Branch &amp; College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Chien-Hsieh Chiang, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>+886-920511256</phone>
    <email>jiansie@ntu.edu.tw</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Taiwan University Hospital Yun-Lin branch</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yunlin</city>
        <zip>640</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chien-Hsieh Chiang, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>+886-9-20511256</phone>
      <email>jiansie@ntu.edu.tw</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kuo-Chin Huang, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chien-Hsieh Chiang, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kuo-Chin Huang, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ylh.ntuh.gov.tw/ylh/department/15/index.php</url>
    <description>recruiting website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clair C, Rigotti NA, Porneala B, Fox CS, D'Agostino RB, Pencina MJ, Meigs JB. Association of smoking cessation and weight change with cardiovascular disease among adults with and without diabetes. JAMA. 2013 Mar 13;309(10):1014-21. doi: 10.1001/jama.2013.1644.</citation>
    <PMID>23483176</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bergman BC, Perreault L, Hunerdosse D, Kerege A, Playdon M, Samek AM, Eckel RH. Novel and reversible mechanisms of smoking-induced insulin resistance in humans. Diabetes. 2012 Dec;61(12):3156-66. doi: 10.2337/db12-0418. Epub 2012 Sep 10.</citation>
    <PMID>22966072</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heatherton TF, Kozlowski LT, Frecker RC, Fagerström KO. The Fagerström Test for Nicotine Dependence: a revision of the Fagerström Tolerance Questionnaire. Br J Addict. 1991 Sep;86(9):1119-27.</citation>
    <PMID>1932883</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cropsey KL, Eldridge GD, Weaver MF, Villalobos GC, Stitzer ML. Expired carbon monoxide levels in self-reported smokers and nonsmokers in prison. Nicotine Tob Res. 2006 Oct;8(5):653-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17008192</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rennard S, Hughes J, Cinciripini PM, Kralikova E, Raupach T, Arteaga C, St Aubin LB, Russ C; Flexible Quit Date Study Group. A randomized placebo-controlled trial of varenicline for smoking cessation allowing flexible quit dates. Nicotine Tob Res. 2012 Mar;14(3):343-50. doi: 10.1093/ntr/ntr220. Epub 2011 Nov 11.</citation>
    <PMID>22080588</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chiang CH, Yang HI, Jen CL, Lu SN, Wang LY, You SL, Su J, Iloeje UH, Chen CJ; REVEAL-HBV Study Group. Association between obesity, hypertriglyceridemia and low hepatitis B viral load. Int J Obes (Lond). 2013 Mar;37(3):410-5. doi: 10.1038/ijo.2012.63. Epub 2012 Apr 24.</citation>
    <PMID>22531094</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chiang CH, Lai JS, Hung SH, Lee LT, Sheu JC, Huang KC. Serum adiponectin levels are associated with hepatitis B viral load in overweight to obese hepatitis B virus carriers. Obesity (Silver Spring). 2013 Feb;21(2):291-6. doi: 10.1002/oby.20000.</citation>
    <PMID>23404868</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chiang CH, Lee LT, Hung SH, Lin WY, Hung HF, Yang WS, Sung PK, Huang KC. Opposite association between diabetes, dyslipidemia, and hepatocellular carcinoma mortality in the middle-aged and elderly. Hepatology. 2014 Jan 15. doi: 10.1002/hep.27014. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>24425422</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 6, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>community</keyword>
  <keyword>preventive medicine</keyword>
  <keyword>prediabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>smoking cessation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Smoking</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glucose Intolerance</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prediabetic State</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
