<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="48742">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02100228</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>B0661025</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CV185-267</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02100228</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study Of The Blood Thinner, Apixaban, For Patients Who Have An Abnormal Heart Rhythm (Atrial Fibrillation) And Expected To Have Treatment To Put Them Back Into A Normal Heart Rhythm (Cardioversion)</brief_title>
  <acronym>EMANATE</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase IV Trial To Assess The Effectiveness Of Apixaban Compared With Usual Care Anticoagulation In Subjects With Non-Valvular Atrial Fibrillation Undergoing Cardioversion</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bristol-Myers Squibb</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pfizer</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Some people can develop an abnormal heart beat known as &quot;Atrial fibrillation&quot; or &quot;AF&quot; that
      puts them at risk of developing clots in the heart.  Those clots can travel in the blood
      circulation to the brain and cause a brain attack (&quot;a stroke&quot;).  To prevent those clots
      forming, blood thinners (anti-coagulants) are used.  Apixaban is a blood thinner that works
      by stopping one of the blood substances required for clotting (&quot;Factor Xa&quot;).  It is approved
      and used to prevent clots forming in people with &quot;AF&quot;.  Other established blood thinners
      work by stopping clotting substances being made, known as &quot;Vitamin K antagonists&quot; or &quot;VKAs&quot;.
       An example of this type is Warfarin (Coumadin).  The good effects of all blood thinners are
      preventing clots, and they may also have bad effects of increasing the chance of bleeding.
      People with &quot;AF&quot;, abnormal heart beat, may benefit from changing it back to a normal regular
      rhythm, known medically as &quot;cardioversion&quot;.  When this is done, people are currently most
      commonly treated with a &quot;VKA&quot; blood thinner (e.g. warfarin).  The purpose of this study is
      to assess the good and bad effects (&quot;efficacy&quot; and &quot;safety&quot;) of apixaban compared with
      warfarin in people with &quot;AF&quot; in whom an early cardioversion is planned.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute stroke</measure>
    <time_frame>Events will be collected up to 30 days post cardioversion</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>An acute stroke is defined as a new focal neurological deficit of sudden onset, lasting at least 24 hours, that is not due to a readily identifiable non-vascular cause.  This will be assessed by the Investigator.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Systemic embolism</measure>
    <time_frame>Events will be collected up to 30 days post cardioversion</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A clinical history consistent with an acute loss of blood flow to a peripheral artery (or arteries), which is supported by evidence of embolism from surgical specimens, autopsy, angiography, or other objective testing.  This will be assessed by the Investigator.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Major Bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>Events will be collected up to 30 days post cardioversion</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Defined as new onset, visible bleeding or signs or symptoms suggestive of bleeding with confirmatory imaging techniques which can detect the presence of blood. The definition of major bleeding is adapted from the International Society on Thrombosis and Hemostasis (ISTH) definition. This will be assessed by the Investigator.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinically Relevant Non-Major Bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>Events will be collected up to 30 days post cardioversion</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The definition is adapted from International Society on Thrombosis and Hemostasis (ISTH) definition. This will be assessed by the Investigator.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>All cause death</measure>
    <time_frame>Events will be collected up to 30 days post cardioversion</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Death</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardioversion Details</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 90 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The timing, type, and the attempts of cardioversion will be collected.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of in-hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Number of hours will be collected from admission for cardioversion to 30 days post cardioversion.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Length of in-hospital stay is defined as the number of hours from hospital admission to hospital discharge for cardioversion. Mean and median duration will be summarized.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rhythm status</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre &amp; post cardioversion and 30 days post cardioversion</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Rhythm status pre- and post cardioversion as recorded by ECG will be collected.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1500</enrollment>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Apixaban</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Parenteral heparin and/or oral Vitamin K antagonist</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Parenteral heparin and/or locally used oral Vitamin K antagonist e.g. warfarin (excludes other novel oral anticoagulants)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Apixaban</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral, 2.5 or 5 mg BID</description>
    <arm_group_label>Apixaban</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Parenteral heparin and/or oral Vitamin K antagonist</intervention_name>
    <description>Parenteral heparin and/or locally used oral Vitamin K antagonist e.g. warfarin (excludes other novel oral anticoagulants)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Parenteral heparin and/or oral Vitamin K antagonist</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with non-valvular atrial fibrillation indicated for cardioversion and
             initiation of anticoagulation in accordance with the approved local label.

          -  Age ≥18 years.

          -  Evidence of a personally signed and dated informed consent document indicating that
             the subject (or their legally-recognized representative) has been informed of all
             pertinent aspects of the study.

          -  The subject is willing to provide contact details for at least one alternate person
             for study staff to contact regarding their whereabouts, should the subject be
             lost-to-follow-up over the course of the study.

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential must agree to use a highly effective method
             of contraception throughout the study and for at least 28 days after the last dose of
             assigned treatment. A subject is of childbearing potential if, in the opinion of the
             investigator, she is biologically capable of having children and is sexually active.

          -  Subjects who are willing and able to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plan,
             and other study procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects currently taking an oral anticoagulant.

          -  Contraindications to apixaban or usual care (eg, VKA) in accordance with the approved
             local label.

          -  Severe haemodynamically compromised subjects requiring emergent cardioversion.

          -  Clinically significant (moderate or severe) mitral stenosis.

          -  Conditions other than atrial fibrillation that require chronic anticoagulation (eg. a
             prosthetic mechanical heart valve).

          -  Pregnant females; breastfeeding females; females of childbearing potential who are
             unwilling or unable to use a highly effective method of contraception as outlined in
             this protocol for the duration of the study and for at least 28 days after last dose
             of investigational product.

          -  Participation in other studies involving investigational drug(s) (Phases 1-  - within
             30 days before the current study begins and/or during study participation.

          -  Severe acute or chronic medical or psychiatric condition or laboratory abnormality
             that may increase the risk associated with study participation or investigational
             product administration or may interfere with the interpretation of study results and,
             in the judgment of the investigator, would make the subject inappropriate for entry
             into this study.

          -  Subjects who are investigational site staff members directly involved in the conduct
             of the trial and their family members, site staff members otherwise supervised by the
             Investigator, or subjects who are BMS/Pfizer employees directly involved in the
             conduct of the trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pfizer CT.gov Call Center</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Pfizer</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Pfizer CT.gov Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>1-800-718-1021</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <link>
    <url>https://trialinfoemail.pfizer.com/pages/landing.aspx?StudyID=B0661025&amp;StudyName=Study%20Of%20The%20Blood%20Thinner%2C%20Apixaban%2C%20For%20Patients%20Who%20Have%20An%20Abnormal%20Heart%20Rhythm%20%28Atrial%20Fibrillation%29%20And%20Expected%20To%20Have%</url>
    <description>To obtain contact information for a study center near you, click here.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 27, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 5, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>apixaban</keyword>
  <keyword>oral anticoagulant</keyword>
  <keyword>non-valvular atrial fibrillation</keyword>
  <keyword>cardioversion</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Arrhythmias, Cardiac</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Calcium heparin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anticoagulants</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heparin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin K</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
