<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="21867">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02108912</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AHA CV study</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>AHA Award #14CRP18500016</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02108912</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Metabolic Costs of Walking Post Stroke</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Impact of Gait Training on the Metabolic Costs of Walking and Cardiorespiratory Capacity in Persons Post Stroke</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This will be a randomized, 4-group repeated measures trial to compare the cardiopulmonary /
      metabolic benefits for persons post stroke that learn to walk utilizing Early Standardized
      Task-specific Training (ESTT) during the inpatient rehabilitation phase of recovery to
      persons post stroke that learn to walk utilizing traditional methods during the same time
      period. Participants (n=60) will be adults who have completed inpatient rehabilitation
      following a stroke. Random assignment will be to either the ESTT or traditional gait
      training protocol during the outpatient rehabilitation phase.

        1. Group A: Traditional inpatient rehabilitation and traditional outpatient therapy (n =
           15)

        2. Group B: Traditional inpatient rehabilitation and ESTT outpatient therapy (n = 15)

        3. Group C: ESTT inpatient rehabilitation and traditional outpatient therapy (n = 15)

        4. Group D: ESTT inpatient rehabilitation and ESTT outpatient (n = 15)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum exercise tolerance testing</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in exercise tolerance from enrollment to 9 weeks later and 25 weeks later</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Exercise tests will be performed with a treadmill with a static/dynamic body weight system. Measurements will be conducted with open circuit spirometry. Heart rate will be continuously monitored by electrocardiogram. Blood pressure will be monitored every 2 minutes. Participants will be allowed a 3-minute warm-up. Following the warm-up, participants will be allowed up to 10 minutes to rest or until they recovery to baseline heart rate, respiration rate and blood pressure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6-Minute Walk Test</measure>
    <time_frame>At enrollment, week 9, week 17 and week 25.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Each subject will be asked to complete a 6-Minute Walk test. They will be advised to walk at a pace they think they can maintain for the entire time. Resting is permitted provided they are not required to sit. Participants will not be given any verbal encouragement during the test. A stop watch will be used to time the test and the distance will be measured with a calibrated measuring wheel along a 150 foot corridor. Heart rate will be monitored during the test by means of a Polar chest strap and values will be recorded at each minute of the test. Perceived rate of exertion using the Borg scale of 6-20 will be recorded at rest and each minute of the test.34 Blood pressure using an automated arm cuff will be recorded before and after the test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Temporal spatial gait analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>At enrollment, week 9, week 17 and week 25.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Testing will be completed using a 14'x4', 16-level pressure sensing Zeno Walkway. This system utilizes a computerized gait system for data collection. Gait parameters that will be collected include center of pressure, center of mass, step/stride length, velocity, toe in/out, cadence, and left/right lower extremity ratios. Participants will be asked to walk at self-selected and safe fast walking paces for repeated straight direction walking trials to collect an average of 100 feet of straight distance. This testing will be done at T1, T2, T3 and T4. This test takes 15 minutes to complete.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Sub-acute Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Traditional inpatient/outpatient</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Traditional inpatient rehabilitation and traditional outpatient physical therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Traditional inpatient/ESTT outpatient</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Traditional inpatient rehabilitation and ESTT (early standardized task-specific training) in outpatient rehabilitation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ESTT inpatient/traditional outpatient</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ESTT inpatient rehabilitation and traditional outpatient physical therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ESTT inpatient/ESTT outpatient</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ESTT inpatient rehabilitation and ESTT outpatient physical therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ESTT</intervention_name>
    <description>ESTT is early-standardized task-specific training is a treadmill and over ground gait protocol for gait recovery after stroke</description>
    <arm_group_label>Traditional inpatient/ESTT outpatient</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ESTT inpatient/ESTT outpatient</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Traditional outpatient</intervention_name>
    <description>Traditional physical therapy includes standard of care for gait recovery after stroke such as pre-gait activities, standing balance activities, strengthening, walking with assistive devices.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Traditional inpatient/outpatient</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ESTT inpatient/traditional outpatient</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  confirmed diagnosis of recent cerebrovascular accident (CVA) (less than 6 weeks post
             at the time of admission to inpatient rehabilitation)

          -  able to give informed consent independently or have family member or other authorized
             surrogate available to give consent

          -  first time stroke OR complete gait recovery from prior stroke

          -  adequate insurance benefits for a maximum of 24 30-minute physical therapy sessions
             in outpatient rehabilitation

          -  sufficient support at home to participate in home-based fitness training program

          -  transportation to University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center Gait Disorders
             Clinic (UTSW GDC) for therapy and testing

          -  ability to follow one-part commands

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  non-ambulatory before onset of stroke (at time of admission to inpatient
             rehabilitation)

          -  bilateral stroke

          -  presence of severe cardiac problems (heart failure [New York Heart Association &gt;
             Class 2], unstable or exercise-induced angina)

          -  other co-morbidities which could affect gait training (i.e. amputation, spinal cord
             injury, traumatic brain injury, etc.)

          -  recent myocardial infarct (within 4 weeks of date of inpatient rehabilitation
             admission)

          -  any uncontrolled health condition for which exercise is contraindicated

          -  severe lower extremity joint disease/pathology that would interfere with gait
             training

          -  subjects -with body mass index (BMI) greater than 40

          -  significant cognitive impairment (less than 2 on the Functional Independence Measure
             [FIM] cognitive sub-scale)

          -  age greater than  80 years or less than  18 years

          -  able to complete 5 or more full heel raises with the affected ankle in standing with
             the knee extended with no more than one or two fingers on support surface for balance
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karen J McCain, PT, DPT, NCS</last_name>
    <phone>214-648-1559</phone>
    <email>karen.mccain@utsouthwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Staci M Shearin, MPT</last_name>
    <phone>214-648-6564</phone>
    <email>staci.macklin@utsouthwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT Southwestern School of Health Professions</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 28, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>gait</keyword>
  <keyword>cardiovascular</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
