<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="43581">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01950325</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130189</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-I-0189</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01950325</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>VRC 601: A Phase I, Open-Label, Dose-Escalation Study of the Safety and Pharmacokinetics of a Human Monoclonal Antibody, VRC HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRC01), With Broad HIV-1 Neutralizing Activity, Administered Intravenously or Subcutaneously to HIV-Infected...</brief_title>
  <official_title>VRC 601: A Phase I, Open-Label, Dose-Escalation Study of the Safety and Pharmacokinetics of a Human Monoclonal Antibody, VRC HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRC01), With Broad HIV-1 Neutralizing Activity, Administered Intravenously or Subcutaneously to HIV-Infected Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is the first clinical trial of the VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRC01) monoclonal antibody.
      VRC01 is a broadly neutralizing antibody directed against HIV. This is a dose-escalation
      study to examine safety, tolerability, dose and pharmacokinetics of VRC01. The hypothesis is
      that VRC01 will be safe for administration to HIV-1 infected adults by the intravenous (IV)
      and subcutaneous (SC) routes and will not elicit hypersensitivity reactions. Samples will be
      collected to learn if VRC01 is detectable in mucosal secretions and blood of participants
      and how long VRC01 can be detected in the blood after it is given.

      Between 15 and 25 HIV-1 infected adults, ages 18-50 years will be enrolled. There are 4 dose
      escalation groups for IV administration; the doses are 1 mg/kg, 5 mg/kg, 20 mg/kg and 40
      mg/kg. There is 1 group for SC administration at 5 mg/kg. Each group is expected to include
      at least 3 participants. Each participant will receive two infusions of VRC01 with about 1
      month between doses. Infusions are administered in an inpatient unit and an overnight stay
      at the NIH Clinical Center is required. No more than one subject per day per group will
      receive a first infusion of the VRC01 product by the IV route and no more than one subject
      per week will receive a first infusion of the product by the SC route. Study participation
      lasts for 24 weeks. Participant health and effect on CD4 count and HIV viral load will be
      monitored. Samples will be collected and stored for research purposes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is the first clinical trial of the VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRC01) monoclonal antibody.
      VRC01 is a broadly neutralizing antibody directed against HIV. This is a dose-escalation
      study to examine safety, tolerability, dose and pharmacokinetics of VRC01. The hypothesis is
      that VRC 01 will be safe for administration to HIV-1- infected adults by the intravenous
      (IV) and subcutaneous (SC) routes and will not elicit hypersensitivity reactions. Samples
      will be collected to learn if VRC 01 is detectable in mucosal secretions and blood of
      participants and how long VRC01 can be detected in the blood after it is given.

      Between15 and 25 HIV-1 infected adults, ages 18-50 years will be enrolled. There are 4 dose
      escalation groups for IV administration; the doses are 1 mg/kg, 5 mg/kg, 20 mg/kg and 40
      mg/kg. There is 1 group for SC administration at 5 mg/kg. Each group is expected to include
      at least 3 participants. Each participant will receive two infusions of VRC01 with about 1
      month between doses. Infusions are administered in an inpatient unit and an overnight stay
      at the NIH Clinical Center is required. No more than one subject per day per group will
      receive a first infusion of the VRC01 product by the IV route and no more than one subject
      per week will receive a first infusion of the product by the SC route. Study participation
      lasts for 24 weeks. Participant health and effect on CD4 count and HIV viral load will be
      monitored. Samples will be collected and stored for research purposes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB administered at 1 mg/kg IV, 5mg/kg IV, 5 mg/kg SC, 20 mg/kg IV and 40 mg/kg IV on Day 0 and Week 4 to HIV-infected adults.</measure>
    <time_frame>October 2014</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV-1 Infection</condition>
  <condition>Neutralizing Antibody</condition>
  <condition>Monoclonal Antibody</condition>
  <condition>Viral Load</condition>
  <condition>HIV Antibodies</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        A volunteer must meet all of the following criteria:

          1. Able and willing to complete the informed consent process.

          2. 18 to 50 years of age.

          3. HIV infected and clinically stable, without changes in ARV status (whether or not
             taking an ARV regimen) in the 24 weeks prior to enrollment.

          4. Plasma viral load (VL) and CD4 count that meet eligibility criteria on at least two
             measurements performed within the 24 weeks prior to enrollment. The two measurements
             used for eligibility must have at least 3 days between tests and at least one set of
             the tests must be performed at the NIH Clinical Center within the 84 days prior to
             enrollment.

             For volunteers who are not on ARV treatment the criteria are:

             -VL less than or equal to 50,000 copies/mL and a CD4 count greater than or equal to
             400/mcL.

             For volunteers on ARV treatment without a history of highly resistant virus the
             criteria are:

             -VL less than or equal to 50 copies/mL and a CD4 count greater than or equal to
             3500/mcL.

             [Note: A viral    blip    of &lt; 400 copies/mL during the 24 weeks prior to enrollment
             is permitted if preceded and followed by test results showing VL less than or equal
             to 50 copies/mL on the same ARV regimen.]

             For volunteers with highly drug resistant HIV who are on ARV therapy, the criteria
             are:

             -VL less than or equal to 20,000 copies/mL and a CD4 count greater than or equal to
             250/mcL.

             [Note:    Highly drug resistant HIV    is defined in this protocol as:

             --genotype test results showing the presence of HIV with resistance to at least one
             drug in the following ARV classes: a) nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor
             (NRTI); b) non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor (NNRTI); and c) protease
             inhibitor (PI) resistance defined as greater than or equal to 3 major PI-associated
             mutations.

             OR

             --phenotype test results reporting    resistance    to at least one drug from the
             NRTI, NNRTI and PI classes.]

          5. In general good health and with an identified primary health care provider for
             medical management of HIV infection and willing to maintain a relationship with a
             primary health care provider for medical management of HIV infection while
             participating in the study.

          6. Willing to have blood samples collected, stored indefinitely, and used for various
             research purposes.

          7. Able to provide proof of identity to the satisfaction of the study clinician
             completing the enrollment process.

          8. Screening laboratory values within 84 days prior to enrollment must meet the
             following criteria:

               -  absolute neutrophil count greater than or equal to 800/mcL

               -  platelets greater than or equal to 100,000/mcL

               -  hemoglobin greater than or equal to 10.0 gm/dL

               -  creatinine less than or equal to 1.31 mg/dL

               -  alanine aminotransferase (ALT) less than or equal to 2.0 times ULN

             Female-Specific Criteria:

          9. Agrees not to become pregnant from the time of study enrollment until the last study
             visit. If a woman is sexually active and has no history of hysterectomy or tubal
             ligation or menopause, she must agree to use a prescription birth control method or a
             barrier birth control method.

         10. Negative Beta-HCG (human chorionic gonadotropin) pregnancy test (urine or serum) on
             day of enrollment for any women unless she is post-menopause for 24 consecutive
             months or has undergone a surgical procedure that precludes pregnancy.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        A volunteer will be excluded if one or more of the following conditions apply:

          1. Previous receipt of humanized or human monoclonal antibody whether licensed or
             investigational.

          2. Weight &gt; 130 kg or &lt; 53 kg.

          3. Detectable hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) or hepatitis C viral load on tests
             performed within 84 days prior to enrollment.

          4. Ongoing AIDS-related opportunistic infection (including oral thrush)

          5. Active injection drug use within previous 12 months or active drug or alcohol use or
             dependence that, in the opinion of the site investigator, would interfere with
             adherence to study requirements.

          6. History of a severe allergic reaction with generalized urticaria, angioedema or
             anaphylaxis in the 2 years prior to enrollment.

          7. Physical finding on examination considered clinically significant such as murmur
             (other than functional), hepatosplenomegaly, lymphadenopathy or focal neurological
             deficit.

          8. Hypertension that is not well controlled by medication.

          9. Breast-feeding.

         10. Receipt of other investigational study agent within 28 days prior to enrollment.

         11. Any other chronic or clinically significant medical condition that in the opinion of
             investigator would jeopardize the safety or rights of the volunteer. Including, but
             not limited to: diabetes mellitus type I, chronic hepatitis; OR clinically
             significant forms of: drug or alcohol abuse, severe asthma, autoimmune disease,
             psychiatric disorders, heart disease, or cancer.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Julie E Ledgerwood, D.O.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Pamela Costner, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-8715</phone>
    <email>vaccines@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For additional information , please contact VRC Clinic</last_name>
      <phone>301-451-8715</phone>
      <email>vaccines@nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-I-0189.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu X, Yang ZY, Li Y, Hogerkorp CM, Schief WR, Seaman MS, Zhou T, Schmidt SD, Wu L, Xu L, Longo NS, McKee K, O'Dell S, Louder MK, Wycuff DL, Feng Y, Nason M, Doria-Rose N, Connors M, Kwong PD, Roederer M, Wyatt RT, Nabel GJ, Mascola JR. Rational design of envelope identifies broadly neutralizing human monoclonal antibodies to HIV-1. Science. 2010 Aug 13;329(5993):856-61. doi: 10.1126/science.1187659. Epub 2010 Jul 8.</citation>
    <PMID>20616233</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu X, Wang C, O'Dell S, Li Y, Keele BF, Yang Z, Imamichi H, Doria-Rose N, Hoxie JA, Connors M, Shaw GM, Wyatt RT, Mascola JR. Selection pressure on HIV-1 envelope by broadly neutralizing antibodies to the conserved CD4-binding site. J Virol. 2012 May;86(10):5844-56. doi: 10.1128/JVI.07139-11. Epub 2012 Mar 14.</citation>
    <PMID>22419808</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lynch RM, Tran L, Louder MK, Schmidt SD, Cohen M; CHAVI 001 Clinical Team Members, Dersimonian R, Euler Z, Gray ES, Abdool Karim S, Kirchherr J, Montefiori DC, Sibeko S, Soderberg K, Tomaras G, Yang ZY, Nabel GJ, Schuitemaker H, Morris L, Haynes BF, Mascola JR. The development of CD4 binding site antibodies during HIV-1 infection. J Virol. 2012 Jul;86(14):7588-95. doi: 10.1128/JVI.00734-12. Epub 2012 May 9.</citation>
    <PMID>22573869</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 15, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 21, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV-1 Viral Load</keyword>
  <keyword>CD4 Count</keyword>
  <keyword>Antiviral</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV-1 Infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Broadly Neutralizing Antibody</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
