<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="109225">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01856764</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ROF-DERM_203</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-003000-12</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1133-6455</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01856764</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Topical Roflumilast in Adults With Atopic Dermatitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2a, 15-Day, Randomized, Parallel Group, Double-Blind, Multi-Centre, Vehicle Controlled Trial to Assess the Efficacy and Local Safety of a Cream Containing 0.5% Roflumilast - a Phosphodiesterase Type 4 Inhibitor (PDE4i) Dermal Formulation - on Atopic Dermatitis Patients With Skin Lesions of Moderate Severity</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Takeda</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the effect of topical roflumilast on the reduction
      of atopic dermatitis lesions in adults with atopic dermatitis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The drug being tested in this study is called roflumilast. Roflumilast is being tested to
      treat people who have atopic dermatitis. This study will look at the skin lesions of people
      who take topical roflumilast compared with a cream with no active ingredient.

      The study will enroll approximately 40 patients. Participants will be randomly assigned (by
      chance, like flipping a coin) to one of the two treatment groups—which will remain
      undisclosed to the patient and study doctor during the study (unless there is an urgent
      medical need):

        -  Dermal 0.5% Roflumilast cream

        -  Placebo (dummy inactive cream) - this is a cream that looks like the study drug but has
           no active ingredient

      All participants will be asked to apply the cream twice a day throughout the study.

      This multi-center trial will be conducted at 3 sites in Germany. The overall time to
      participate in this study is 7 weeks. Participants will make 6 visits to the clinic.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline to Day 15 in modified local SCORing Atopic Dermatitis (SCORAD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Day 15</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The modified local SCORAD intensity scale represents one part of the SCORAD index, which is a severity scoring system for atopic dermatitis. The symptoms erythema, edema/papulation, oozing/crusts, excoriations, and lichenification of the target lesion will be assessed by the investigator and the intensity of each of the criteria will be graded according to the following 4-point scale: 0 = absent; 1 = mild; 2 = moderate; 3 = severe. Worst scores indicate greater level of severity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline to Day 15 in transepidermal water loss (TEWL) values</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Day 15</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Diffusion of water through the skin (the TEWL) will be measured using a Tewameter at Baseline and on Day 15.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline to Day 15 in participants' assessment of pruritus</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Day 15</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The severity of each symptom in the target lesion during the last 24 h will be assessed by the participants using a numeric scale with a range from 0 to 10, where 0 indicates the absence of the symptoms and 10 indicates the most severe symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Atopic Dermatitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Roflumilast</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dermal 0.5% Roflumilast cream, topically, twice daily for up to 15 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Roflumilast placebo-matching cream, topically, twice daily for up to 15 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Roflumilast</intervention_name>
    <description>Roflumilast cream</description>
    <arm_group_label>Roflumilast</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Roflumilast placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Roflumilast placebo-matching cream</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female between 18 to 65 years of age, inclusive, with atopic dermatitis (AD)
             meeting Hanifin and Rajka's criteria

          2. Presence of lesional skin areas of moderate severity characterized by modified local
             SCORing Atopic Dermatitis (SCORAD) of at least 4, with an erythema score ≥2, and
             confirmed by a qualified investigator

          3. Must have an index/target lesion of moderate in severity of approximately 20 cm^2,
             suitable for topical treatment

          4. Must be willing to wash out from AD current active therapy prior to entry in the
             study

          5. Is willing and able to apply the study medication as directed, comply with study
             instructions and commit to all follow-up visits for the duration of the study.

          6. A male who is nonsterilized and sexually active with a female partner of childbearing
             potential agrees to use adequate contraception from signing of informed consent
             throughout the duration of the study and for 12 weeks after last dose.

          7. A female of childbearing potential who is sexually active with a nonsterilized male
             partner agrees to use routinely adequate contraception from signing of informed
             consent throughout the duration of the study and for 12 weeks after last dose.

          8. In the opinion of the investigator, the participant is capable of understanding and
             complying with protocol requirements.

          9. The participant or, when applicable, the participant's legally acceptable
             representative signs and dates a written, informed consent form and any required
             privacy authorization prior to the initiation of any study procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Has received any investigational compound within 30 days, or within 5 half-lives of
             the compound (whichever is the longer) prior to the Screening visit.

          2. Have a history of AD unresponsive or poorly responsive to topical treatments.

          3. Has a history of hypersensitivity to phosphodiesterase (PDE)-4 inhibitors or to drugs
             of similar chemical classes or any inactive ingredients of the trial medication.

          4. Has, in the judgment of the investigator, clinically significant abnormal
             hematological parameters of hemoglobin, hematocrit, or erythrocytes at Screening.

          5. Has a history or current clinically relevant allergies or idiosyncrasy to drugs or
             food.

          6. Has extensive exposure to ultraviolet (UV) light in the 4 weeks prior to first
             application of study medication, including tanning and sun beds or is intending to
             have such exposure during the study treatment that may interfere with the study
             assessments as judged by the investigator.

          7. Evidence of oozing of target lesion.

          8. Has a current skin complication such as erythroderma or overt bacterial or viral
             infection for which treatment with anti-infectives are indicated.

          9. Has systemic treatment with corticosteroids or retinoids for studied condition within
             3 months prior to the first application of study medication.

         10. Had topical or transdermal treatments, such as but not limited to retinoids, nicotine
             or hormone replacement therapies, on or near the intended site of application within
             4 weeks prior to first application of study medication.

         11. Treatment with systemic/locally acting medications/procedures which might counter or
             influence the study aim within 4 weeks prior to first application of study medication
             and during the study (eg, anti-histamines) .

         12. Has used emollients/moisturizers on areas to be treated within 24 hours prior to the
             first application of study medication.

         13. Has used biologics at any time for treatment of AD.

         14. Is currently enrolled in an investigational drug or device study.

         15. Any clinically significant illness that may influence the outcome of the trial 4
             weeks before Day 1 and during the trial.

         16. Has alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and/or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) values
             greater than 2.0 × upper limit of normal (ULN), or other clinically significant
             abnormal laboratory test that, in the opinion of the Investigator, would compromise
             the participant's ability to safely complete the trial.

         17. Has a significant medical condition and/or conditions that, in the opinion of the
             Investigator, would interfere with the treatment, safety or compliance with the
             protocol.

         18. Has a history of infection with hepatitis B, hepatitis C, or human immunodeficiency
             virus.

         19. Has a history of alcoholism or illicit drug abuse within 5 years prior to the
             Screening Visit or is currently consuming &gt;14 alcoholic drinks per week.

         20. If female, is pregnant, nursing or planning a pregnancy during the study period.

         21. Has a history of cancer that has not been in remission for at least 5 years prior to
             the first dose of study medication. This criterion does not apply to those
             participants with successfully resected basal cell or stage I squamous cell carcinoma
             of the skin.

         22. Has chronic or clinically relevant acute infections.

         23. Has a history of depression associated with suicidal ideation and behavior.

         24. Has hemodynamically significant cardiac arrhythmias or heart valve deformations.

         25. Is an immediate family member, study site employee, or is in a dependent relationship
             with a study site employee who is involved in conduct of this study (eg, spouse,
             parent, child, sibling) or may consent under duress.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Takeda</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Gera</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Grosshansdorf</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Hannover</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Mainz</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Schwerin</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Budapest</city>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Nyiregyhaza</city>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Szarvas</city>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Torokbalint</city>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Bloemfontein</city>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Cape Town</city>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Pretoria</city>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Hungary</country>
    <country>South Africa</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 19, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 14, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Drug therapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis, Atopic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Phosphodiesterase 4 Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
