<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="62219">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02095236</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>The ESMERALDA Trial</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02095236</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Intrafractional Motion of Liver Tumors Using Markers</brief_title>
  <acronym>ESMERALDA</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Inter- and Intrafractional Motion of Liver Tumors Using Interstitial Markers and Implantable Electro-magnetic Radiotransmitters in the Context of Image-guided Radiotherapy (IGRT) - the ESMERALDA Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital Heidelberg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Heidelberg</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Ethics Commission</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Radioopaque fiducial markers or electro-magnetic transponders will be implanted into or in
      close proximity of the tumor. During a radiotherapy treatment session image and/or signal
      acquisition will be performed by ultrasound, computed tomography, magnetic resonance imaging
      or by specialized signal detectors The data will help to characterize tumor and organ motion
      during one treatment session which may in fact have impact on dose distribution
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      With the development of more conformal and precise radiation techniques such as
      Intensity-Modulated Radiotherapy (IMRT), Stereotactic Body Radiotherapy (SBRT) and
      Image-Guided Radiotherapy (IGRT), patients with hepatic tumors could be treated with high
      local doses by sparing normal liver tissue. However, frequently occurring large HCC tumors
      are still representing a dosimetric challenge in spite of modern high sophisticated RT
      modalities. This interventional clinical study has been set up to evaluate the value of
      different fiducial markers, and to use the modern imaging methods for further treatment
      optimization using physical and informatics approaches.Radioopaque fiducial markers or
      electro-magnetic transponders will be implanted into or in close proximity of the tumor.
      During a radiotherapy treatment session image and/or signal acquisition will be performed by
      ultrasound, computed tomography, magnetic resonance imaging or by specialized signal
      detectors The data will help to characterize tumor and organ motion during one treatment
      session which may in fact have impact on dose distribution
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Three-dimensional intra- and interfractional measurement of fiducial marker or transponder motion</measure>
    <time_frame>One treatment session for one dataset</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Three-dimensional intrafractional motion of a fiducial marker or a transponder will be recorded and analyzed during radiotherapy. Image and/or signal acquisition will be performed by ultrasound, computed tomography, magnetic resonance imaging or by specialized signal detectors. The data will help to characterize tumor and organ motion during one treatment session which may in fact have impact on dose distribution. Prediction of tumor motion is the prerequisite for innovative adaptive radiotherapy techniques.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Effects of; Movement</condition>
  <condition>Radiation; Lesion</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>experimental</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Radioopaque fiducial markers or electro-magnetic transponders will be implanted into or in close proximity of the tumor. During a radiotherapy treatment session image and/or signal acquisition will be performed by ultrasound, computed tomography, magnetic resonance imaging or by specialized signal detectors The data will help to characterize tumor and organ motion during one treatment session which may in fact have impact on dose distribution</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>organ motion</intervention_name>
    <description>Three-dimensional intrafractional motion of a fiducial marker or a transponder during a radiotherapy treatment session. Image and/or signal acquisition will be performed by ultrasound, computed tomography, magnetic resonance imaging or by specialized signal detectors.</description>
    <arm_group_label>experimental</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  indication for high precision radiotherapy of primary and secondary liver tumors
             using IGRT (image-guided radiotherapy)

          -  age ≥ 18 years of age

          -  ability of subject to understand character and individual consequences of the
             clinical trial

          -  written informed consent (must be available before enrolment in the trial)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  refusal of the patients to take part in the study

          -  medical reasons impeding marker implantation or IGRT for treatment of liver tumors.

          -  non-compliance of patients
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephanie E Combs, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Radiooncology, University Hospital of Heidelberg, INF 400, 69120 Heidelberg, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Heidelberg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stephanie E Combs, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 6221 568203</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Daniel Habermehl, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephanie E Combs, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jürgen Debus, M.D., PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rolf Bendl, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Uwe Oelfke, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Florian Sterzing, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Klaus Herfarth, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Beat Müller, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 20, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 4, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospital Heidelberg</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Stephanie Combs</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. Dr. med.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
