<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="4881">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01851902</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FKE20130012H</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01851902</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PREdicting Atrial Fibrillation or Flutter</brief_title>
  <acronym>PREDATE-AF</acronym>
  <official_title>PREdicting Determinants of Atrial Fibrillation or Flutter for Therapy Elucidation in Patients at Risk for Thromboembolic Events (PREDATE AF)&quot;</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Keesler Air Force Base Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Keesler Air Force Base Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine, through continuous monitoring with a cardiac
      monitoring device placed under the skin, the incidence of atrial fibrillation or flutter
      (AF).  The cardiac monitor will be placed in patients without symptoms but at risk for AF.
      It is hoped that this information may assist health care professionals in treatment
      decisions related to the early identification of patients at high risk for AF.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:  Atrial fibrillation and atrial flutter (AF) are common cardiac arrhythmias that
      confer a substantial stroke burden largely because the vast majority of AF is asymptomatic
      and identified after a stroke has occurred.  Until recently, only intermittent cardiac
      monitors were available, with most AF episodes remaining undetected due to poor sensitivity.
       Health care providers estimate the risk of stroke in AF patients using a patient's
      comorbidity profile to determine who should be treated with oral anticoagulant therapy for
      stroke prevention.  The incidence of AF in patients with high stroke risk comorbidities is
      not known. The Medtronic Reveal insertable cardiac monitor (ICM) is a continuous monitoring
      device with excellent AF detection.

      Purpose and Study Objectives:  The purpose of the PREDATE AF study is to determine the
      incidence of AF in asymptomatic patients at high risk for having AF in order to determine
      which patient characteristics are most predictive of the development of AF.  The primary
      objective is to determine the AF incidence rate; secondary objectives include identifying
      the most important predictors of AF onset and identifying how physicians respond once AF has
      been discovered.

      Study Design:  The trial is a prospective, single arm, open-label, single center clinical
      study which will enroll up to 360 patients at high risk of having AF based upon their
      comorbidity profile, who will then receive an ICM.  Enrolled subjects will be followed for a
      minimum of 18 months to monitor for the detection of AF.  Monthly ICM data transmissions
      will be the mechanism of AF detection, and this information will be utilized to determine
      the AF incidence rate
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Atrial Fibrillation</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Incidence rate of AF calculated in each arm as the number of participants with an initial episode of AF lasting greater than or equal to six minutes divided by the total number of participants in that arm.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">360</enrollment>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <condition>Atrial Flutter</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CHA2DS2-VASc Score 2 - 4</arm_group_label>
    <description>Physicians estimate the risk of stroke in AF patients using either the CHADS2 or CHA2DS2-VASc scoring; this is a low risk cohort.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CHA2DS2-VASc Score 5 - 7</arm_group_label>
    <description>Physicians estimate the risk of stroke in AF patients using either the CHADS2 or CHA2DS2-VASc scoring; this is a medium risk cohort.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CHA2DS2-VASc Score 8 - 10</arm_group_label>
    <description>Physicians estimate the risk of stroke in AF patients using either the CHADS2 or CHA2DS2-VASc scoring; this is a high risk cohort.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The PREDATE AF trial is a prospective, single arm, open-label, single center clinical
        study to evaluate the incidence of AF in patients that are suspected to be at high risk of
        having AF, as defined by a modified CHA2DS2-VASc score.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient meets the approved FDA indication to receive the ICM

          -  Patient is suspected, based on demographics, to be at high risk of having AF, as
             determined by the clinical investigator

          -  Patient has a CHA2DS2-VASc score ≥ 2 [Note: stroke/TIA criterion as part of the
             CHA2DS2-VASc score for this trial is limited to either an ischemic stroke or TIA,
             which occurred more than one year prior to enrollment.]

          -  Patient is 18 years of age or older

          -  Patient has a life expectancy of 18 months or more

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient has a documented history of AF or atrial flutter

          -  Patient has a symptom complex consistent with an arrhythmia (where an ICM may have an
             alternate indication for use)

          -  Patient had an ischemic stroke or TIA within past year prior to enrollment

          -  Patient has a history of a hemorrhagic stroke

          -  Patient is currently implanted with a permanent pacemaker, insertable loop recorder,
             implantable defibrillator, cardiac resynchronization therapy device (pacemaker or
             defibrillator)

          -  NYHA Class IV Heart Failure patient

          -  Patient had heart surgery within previous 90 days prior to enrollment

          -  Patient had an MI within the previous 90 days prior to enrollment

          -  Patient is taking chronic immunosuppressant therapy

          -  Patient is taking an anti-arrhythmic drug

          -  Patient is contraindicated for long term anticoagulation medication

          -  Patient is taking a long-term anticoagulation medication

          -  Any concomitant condition which, in the opinion of the investigator, would not allow
             safe participation in the study (e.g., drug addiction, alcohol abuse, emotional /
             psychological diagnosis)

          -  Patient is enrolled in another study that could confound the results of this study,
             without documented pre-approval from the principal investigator

          -  Patient has a creatinine clearance &lt;30 ml/min or is on dialysis

          -  Active pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Steven Kindsvater, MD</last_name>
    <phone>228-376-3500</phone>
    <email>steven.kindsvater@us.af.mil</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jay Nasir, MD</last_name>
    <phone>228-376-3500</phone>
    <email>jay.nasir@us.af.mil</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Keesler Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Keesler AFB</city>
        <state>Mississippi</state>
        <zip>39534</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven Kindsvater, MD</last_name>
      <phone>228-376-3500</phone>
      <email>steven.kindsvater@us.af.mil</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jay Nasir, MD</last_name>
      <phone>228-376-3500</phone>
      <email>jay.nasir@us.af.mil</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steven Kindsvater, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Matthew Hann, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jay Nasir, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jamie Shedden, NP</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jennifer Walker, NP</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rishawn Carriere</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Audrey D Greenwell</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 8, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 2, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Atrial Fibrillation</keyword>
  <keyword>Atrial Flutter</keyword>
  <keyword>Arrhythmia</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atrial Flutter</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
