<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="13437">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02113007</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SCRI CNS 20</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02113007</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of High-Dose Rituximab With Temozolomide as Treatment for Primary Central Nervous System (CNS) Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of High-Dose Rituximab Combined With Temozolomide as Treatment for Patients With Primary CNS Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>SCRI Development Innovations, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genentech</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>SCRI Development Innovations, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the safety and efficacy of high-dose rituximab combined with
      temozolomide in the treatment of patients with Primary Central Nervous System Lymphomas
      (PCNSL).  This novel combination will be evaluated in PCNSL patients who are 60 years of age
      or older, or in patients 18 years or older who refuse methotrexate-based treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase II, multi-centered, single-arm study. A brief patient lead-in portion will
      be included to assess safety and feasibility. The first six patients enrolled will be
      monitored weekly for safety during two treatment cycles (4 weeks) for adverse events to
      assure there are no unexpected or prohibitive toxicities. If safety signals emerge from this
      group of patients, the protocol may be discontinued or modified.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Response Rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 36 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Determine the overall response rate (ORR) of patients with primary central nervous system lymphoma (PCNSL) when treated with high-dose rituximab combined with temozolomide.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Six and twelve-month CNS progression-free survival rate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Serious and Non-serious Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluate toxicity of the high-dose rituximab/temozolomide combination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">33</enrollment>
  <condition>Primary Central Nervous System Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rituximab plus Temozolomide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Rituximab:  375 mg/m2 IV, days 1, 3, and 5 Temozolomide:  150 mg/m2 PO, days 1-5</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rituximab plus Temozolomide</intervention_name>
    <description>Treatment cycles will be repeated every 14 days (2 weeks) for the lead-in portion.  If no prohibitive toxicities are observed in the first 6 patients during the first 2 treatment cycles, the study will continue enrolling patients.  Treatment cycles for the Phase II portion will be repeated every 14 days (2 weeks) for a total of 12 cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rituximab plus Temozolomide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Rituximab:  Rituxin, MabThera</other_name>
    <other_name>Temozolomide:  Temodar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologically confirmed CD20 positive primary B-cell CNS lymphoma (PCNSL) confirmed
             by one of the following:

               -  Brain biopsy or resection;

               -  Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) cytology for lymphoma or monoclonal lymphocyte
                  population as defined by cell surface markers.

          2. No evidence of systemic non-Hodgkin's lymphoma.

          3. Male or female, and:

               -  60 years of age or older, or

               -  18 years of age or older and decline methotrexate-based treatment.

          4. Measurable contrast-enhancing disease by MRI of brain and or spine (with gadolinium
             contrast).

          5. ECOG PS equals 2 or less.

          6. No more than 2 prior chemotherapy regimens.

          7. Adequate hematologic, renal, and hepatic function.

          8. Ability to swallow oral medications.

          9. Female patients who are not of childbearing potential, and female patients of
             childbearing potential who agree to use adequate contraceptive measures, who are not
             breastfeeding, and who have a negative serum pregnancy test within 72 hours prior to
             start of treatment.

         10. Male patients willing to use adequate contraceptive measures.

         11. Life expectancy 8 weeks or greater.

         12. HIV negative.

         13. Archival tumor block (or 20 unstained slides) for biomarker testing. Patients without
             archived tumor block material will be allowed to participate in the study.

         14. Willingness and ability to comply with study and followup procedures.

         15. Ability to understand the nature of this study and give written informed consent.

         16. Bone marrow biopsy must be negative for lymphoma.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Previous treatment with rituximab or other monoclonal antibodies, or temozolomide.

          2. Prior bone marrow or organ transplantation.

          3. Chemotherapy or investigational drug therapy for cancer up to 21 days prior to day-1
             of study.

          4. T-cell primary CNS lymphoma.

          5. Known hypersensitivity to dacarbazine (DTIC).

          6. Active, clinically serious infection greater than CTCAE grade 2. Patients may be
             eligible upon resolution of the infection.

          7. Positive test results for chronic hepatitis BsAg infection.

          8. Chronic treatment with steroids or other immunosuppressive agents for medical
             conditions other than cancer. Patients who require steroids for treatment of
             tumor-associated cerebral edema are eligible.

          9. History of other malignancy up to 5 years prior to study entry which could affect
             compliance with the protocol or interpretation of results. History of curatively
             treated basal or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin or in situ carcinoma of the
             cervix, low grade, early stage, localized prostate cancer treated surgically with
             curative intent, ductal carcinoma in situ (DCIS) of the breast treated with
             lumpectomy alone with curative intent, are generally eligible.

         10. History of unstable or newly diagnosed angina pectoris, recent myocardial infarction
             (within 6 months of enrollment), New York Heart Association Classification III or IV.

         11. Vaccination with a live-virus vaccine up to 4 weeks prior to onset of study
             treatment.

         12. Impairment of gastrointestinal (GI) function or GI disease that, in the opinion of
             the investigator, may significantly alter the absorption of study drug (e.g., Crohn's
             disease, ulcerative disease, uncontrolled vomiting, diarrhea, or malabsorption
             syndrome).

         13. Significant, concurrent, uncontrolled medical condition which, in the opinion of the
             investigator, may interfere with patient participation in the study.

         14. Pregnant or lactating female.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kent Shih, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>SCRI Development Innovations, LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sarah Cannon Research Institute</last_name>
    <phone>877-691-7274</phone>
    <email>asksarah@scresearch.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tennessee Oncology PLLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 10, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Lymphoma; CNS; rituximab; temozolomide</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Temozolomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dacarbazine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
