<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="119336">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01895270</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R21DA035325</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01895270</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Improving Buprenorphine Detoxification Outcomes With Isradipine</brief_title>
  <official_title>Improving Buprenorphine Detoxification Outcomes With Isradipine</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Arkansas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Arkansas</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This application seeks to address the problem of opioid withdrawal by examining the utility
      of the L-type calcium channel blocker (CCB) isradipine as an adjunct to BUP detoxification.
      This project will address the need for improved detoxification strategies by assessing the
      tolerability and preliminary efficacy of adjunct isradipine during a BUP detoxification in
      opioid-dependent participants. This pilot clinical trial will determine the potential
      utility of the L-type CCB isradipine to improve treatment outcomes in up to 60
      opioid-dependent individuals undergoing a BUP detoxification procedure. Specifically, this
      study will determine the efficacy of isradipine to reduce withdrawal symptoms, craving, and
      illicit use of opioids in opioid-dependent individuals undergoing BUP detoxification and
      determine the tolerability and safety of controlled-release isradipine (10 mg/day) in
      opioid-dependent individuals undergoing BUP detoxification. Currently, the only FDA-approved
      medications for opioid withdrawal are the opioid agonists methadone and BUP, both of which
      have abuse liability. Our findings, if positive, will support a larger phase II clinical
      trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Opioid dependence continues to be a serious public health problem, particularly with the
      dramatic rise in prescription opioid abuse. Traditional methods of detoxification from
      opioids, including tapering off the opioid agonist methadone or buprenorphine (BUP) and
      supportive treatment of symptomatology with the alpha2-adrenergic receptor agonists, are
      limited by the high relapse rate and/or lack of efficacy in relieving subjective symptoms.
      In addition, transitioning individuals from methadone to BUP maintenance has been limited by
      the need to drastically taper the methadone maintenance dose of methadone-maintained
      individuals prior to switching to BUP maintenance, which can precipitate opiate withdrawal
      and relapse. This application takes a novel approach to address the problem of opioid
      withdrawal by examining the utility of the L-type calcium channel blocker (CCB) isradipine
      as an adjunct to BUP detoxification. L-type CCBs have been shown to alleviate opioid
      withdrawal in opioid-treated nonhumans, to be safe and effective in alleviating withdrawal
      symptoms in human detoxification trials, and to have low abuse potential. Moreover,
      isradipine was the most effective of several CCBs tested and was more effective than the
      alpha2-adrenergic agonist clonidine in blocking naloxone-induced behavioral effects without
      producing self-reported effects associated with high potential for abuse. Thus, this project
      will address the need for improved detoxification strategies by assessing the tolerability
      and preliminary efficacy of adjunct isradipine during a BUP detoxification in
      opioid-dependent participants. The aim of this 8-week randomized, placebo-controlled pilot
      clinical trial is to determine the potential utility of the L-type CCB isradipine to improve
      treatment outcomes in up to 60 opioid-dependent individuals undergoing a BUP detoxification
      procedure. The specific aims are to (Aim 1) determine the efficacy of isradipine to reduce
      withdrawal symptoms, craving, and illicit use of opioids in opioid-dependent individuals
      undergoing BUP detoxification and (Aim 2) determine the tolerability and safety of
      controlled-release isradipine (10 mg/day) in opioid-dependent individuals undergoing BUP
      detoxification. Currently, the only FDA-approved medications for opioid withdrawal are the
      opioid agonists methadone and BUP, both of which have abuse liability. Our findings, if
      positive, will support a larger phase II clinical trial. Ultimately, this work could impact
      the addiction field by providing another pharmacological tool that is efficacious for
      treating opioid withdrawal while having minimal abuse liability. This would shift clinical
      practice, establishing an effective adjunct regimen for BUP detoxification as well as having
      the potential to enhance transition to naltrexone therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change over time in Illicit Opioid Use via Urine Toxicology Screens</measure>
    <time_frame>thrice weekly for 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Illicit opioid use via urine toxicology screens for heroin and several opioids will be measured thrice weekly during the trial.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change over time in orthostatic vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>once weekly for 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>orthostatic vital signs will be done at least once weekly to determine the incidence of orthostatic hypotension</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Opioid Dependence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Isradipine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Isradipine controlled-release formulation, 10 mg/day maintenance dose, will be administered according to the following dose procedures: Isradipine ingestion will occur under supervision 6 days per week, and a take-home dose will be given on Saturday for participants to take on Sunday. The initial dose of isradipine or placebo will be given on Day 3 of Week 1. The initial dose of isradipine will be 5 mg/day; the dose will increase to 10 mg/day on Day 3 of Week 3 and will continue through Day 2 of Week 7. On Day 3 of Week 7, isradipine will be decreased to 5 mg/day for 7 days. On Days 3-5 of Week 8, all participants will receive placebo. If ISR side effects are too severe at the 10-mg dose, isradipine will be decreased to 5 mg/day. If ISR side effects are too severe at 5 mg/day, isradipine will be discontinued and the participant will be discharged from the study and referred to local treatment agencies.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo will consist of microcrystalline cellulose. Two placebo capsules will be administered per day starting week 1 day 3 through the end of the isradipine taper.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Isradipine</intervention_name>
    <description>Isradipine extended release formulation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Isradipine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo will consist of microcrystalline cellulose.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>microcrystalline cellulose</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Availability to attend clinic 6 days a week for approximately 30-60 minutes per day.

          2. Participants must fulfill DSM-IV criteria for opioid dependence. These criteria will
             be ascertained in the following manner:  the physician will determine whether the
             individual is appropriate based on several clinical assessments that are routinely
             employed by methadone program physicians, including history and severity of opioid
             use, presence of track marks, prior treatment history, self-reported and/or observed
             signs and symptoms of opioid withdrawal. If any individual's degree of opioid
             dependence is questionable, that person will be excluded from further consideration
             as a participant.

          3. Participants must submit a urine sample negative for drugs of abuse other than
             opioids or marijuana prior to starting the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Unstable medical condition or stable medical condition that would interact with study
             medications or participation.

          2. History of major psychiatric disorder (psychosis, schizophrenia, bipolar)

          3. Pregnancy or plans to become pregnant or inadequate birth control (adequate birth
             control includes abstinence, condoms, birth control pills, etc).

          4. Present or recent use of over-the-counter psychoactive drug, prescription
             psychoactive drug or any drug that would have major interaction with drugs to be
             tested.

          5. Liver function tests greater than 3 times normal; BUN and Creatinine outside normal
             range.

          6. EKG abnormalities including but not limited to: bradycardia (&lt;60 bpm); prolonged QTc
             interval (&gt;450 msec); Wolff-Parkinson White syndrome; wide complex tachycardia; 2nd
             degree, Mobitz type II heart block; 3rd degree heart block; left or right bundle
             branch block.

          7. Physical dependence on alcohol or drugs other than opioids, marijuana or tobacco (as
             determined by physician assessment).

          8. Pre-existing severe gastrointestinal narrowing.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alison Oliveto, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Arkansas</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Heidi Charton, BA</last_name>
    <phone>501-526-7969</phone>
    <email>ChartonHeidiN@uams.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UAMS Psychiatric Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Heidi Charton</last_name>
      <phone>501-526-7969</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alison Oliveto, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 25, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>opioid dependence</keyword>
  <keyword>buprenorphine</keyword>
  <keyword>isradipine</keyword>
  <keyword>opioid withdrawal</keyword>
  <keyword>opioid detoxification</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Opioid-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Buprenorphine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Isradipine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
