<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="77149">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01780545</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GU12-160</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01780545</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 2 Study of Docetaxel +/- OGX-427 in Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Metastatic Bladder Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Borealis-2 Clinical Trial: A Randomized Phase 2 Study Comparing Docetaxel Alone to Docetaxel in Combination With OGX-427 in Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Metastatic Urothelial Carcinoma After Receiving a Platinum-containing Regimen: Hoosier Oncology Group GU12-160</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hoosier Oncology Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>OncoGenex Technologies</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hoosier Oncology Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, open-label Phase 2 clinical trial to evaluate whether suppression of
      Hsp27 (Heat shock protein 27) production using OGX-427, a second-generation antisense
      oligonucleotide (ASO), in combination with docetaxel can prolong survival time compared to
      docetaxel alone in participants with locally advanced or metastatic urothelial carcinoma
      (UC) that are relapsed or refractory after receiving a platinum-containing regimen.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OUTLINE: This is a multi-center study.

      Eligible patients will be stratified based on time from prior systemic chemotherapy (&lt; 3 vs
      ≥ 3 months) and Bellmunt prognostic factors criteria, which include Eastern Cooperative
      Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status &gt;0, hemoglobin &lt;10g/dL, and presence of liver
      metastases (0 versus 1-3 risk factors). Within the strata, participants will be randomly
      assigned with equal probability to either the investigational arm (Arm A: docetaxel +
      OGX-427) or the control arm (Arm B: docetaxel alone).

      INVESTIGATIONAL ARM OGX-427 + DOCETAXEL (Arm A):

      LOADING DOSE PERIOD:

      Participants randomized onto the investigational arm (Arm A) will receive OGX-427 beginning
      with a loading dose period prior to the initiation of docetaxel treatment. The first dose of
      OGX-427 for the loading dose period must be administered within 5 working days of
      registration and randomization.

      During the loading dose period, participants will receive three separate administrations of
      600 mg OGX-427 intravenously (IV) (days -9 to -1). There must be at least one &quot;non-infusion&quot;
      day between each administration of OGX-427 (i.e., every other day) during the loading dose
      period and between the third loading dose of OGX-427 and day 1 of cycle 1. There should be
      no more than 7 days between the last loading dose and day 1 of cycle 1.

      TREATMENT PERIOD:

      During the treatment period, participants randomized to this arm will receive:

        -  OGX-427 600 mg IV weekly on days 1, 8, and 15 of each 21-day cycle. OGX-427 must be
           administered prior to docetaxel on day 1 of each cycle.

        -  Docetaxel (75 mg/M2) IV on day 1 of each 21-day cycle. Docetaxel should be administered
           immediately following the completion of the OGX-427 infusion.

      OGX-427 MAINTENANCE:

      Following completion of 10 cycles of docetaxel, 600 mg OGX-427 will continue to be
      administered by IV weekly as maintenance therapy for participants who do not have disease
      progression (i.e., stable disease or better). Participants without documented disease
      progression who have discontinued from study treatment not due to toxicity related to
      OGX-427 can also continue to receive OGX-427 maintenance as long as they have completed
      disease assessments following at least 2 cycles of chemotherapy.  Maintenance with OGX-427
      will continue until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      CONTROL ARM - DOCETAXEL ALONE (Arm B):

      TREATMENT PERIOD:

      During the treatment period, participants randomized to this arm will receive:

      - Docetaxel (75 mg/M2) IV on day 1 of each 21-day cycle. The first dose of docetaxel must be
      administered within 5 working days of registration and randomization.  Participants will
      continue to receive docetaxel on day 1 of each 21-day cycle until disease progression,
      unacceptable toxicity related to docetaxel, voluntary patient withdrawal, or a maximum of 10
      docetaxel cycles.

      FOLLOW-UP FOR BOTH ARMS:

      Imaging studies will be performed every 6 weeks (i.e., after completion of cycles 2, 4, 6, 8
      and 10) until disease progression and with any sign or symptom of new or worsening disease;
      computed tomography scan (CT) of chest/abdomen/pelvis is preferred but magnetic resonance
      imaging scan(MRI) is acceptable, especially for participants with increased risk of
      contrast-related nephropathy or other contraindications. For Arm A, scans will be performed
      every 2 cycles (6 weeks) +/1 week during the 21-day cycles of docetaxel administration and
      every 6 weeks during maintenance OGX-427 administration until disease progression; for Arm
      B, scans will be performed every 6 weeks during the 21-day cycles of docetaxel
      administration until disease progression. All scans should be completed before the
      subsequent cycle is scheduled to begin. Bone scans will be repeated, if positive at
      baseline, every 6 weeks during the first 4 cycles of treatment (i.e., at the end of cycles 2
      and 4) and then every 12 weeks thereafter until disease progression (i.e., at the end of
      cycle 8, at end of treatment, and during maintenance with OGX-427 [Arm A only]).

      All participants will have an End of Treatment (EOT) visit when they discontinue study
      treatment. All participants will be followed until documented disease progression.

      Once disease progression is documented, participants will enter a survival follow-up period.
      All participants must be followed for survival as the primary endpoint. During the survival
      follow-up period, data will be collected every three months regarding further cancer
      therapy, secondary malignancy, and survival status.

      Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1

      Life Expectancy: Greater than 3 months

      Hematopoietic:

        -  Absolute neutrophil count(ANC)≥ 1,500/mcL

        -  Hemoglobin ≥ 8 g/dL

        -  Platelets ≥ 100,000/mcL

      Hepatic:

        -  Bilirubin ≤ 1.1 x upper limit of normal (ULN) (≤ 2.0 x ULN if secondary to Gilbert's
           disease)

        -  Aspartate transaminase (AST), serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT)/alanine
           transaminase (ALT), serum glutamic pyruvic transaminase (SGPT) ≤ 1.5 X institutional
           ULN

      Renal:

        -  Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 x ULN

      Cardiac:

        -  Symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, or
           myocardial infarction within 3 months of randomization.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine whether docetaxel administered in combination with OGX-427 provides a survival benefit compared to docetaxel alone.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and Toxicity of Regimen</measure>
    <time_frame>Every week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To compare the safety and toxicity of OGX-427 in combination with docetaxel to that of docetaxel alone.  Treatment-related toxicity rates will be assessed by Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) v4.0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To compare overall response rate (ORR) between the treatment arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum Levels of Hsp27 and Other Proteins</measure>
    <time_frame>Each cycle</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the effect of therapy with docetaxel and OGX-427 on serum Hsp27 levels and other serum proteins and explore their relation with clinical outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hsp27 Expression in Archival Tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the association of urothelial carcinoma expression of Hsp27 measured by immunohistochemistry (IHC) in archival tissue with clinical outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of Therapy Regimen on Circulating Tumor Cells (CTCs)and Correlative Analysis of Telomerase Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to screening, prior to first loading dose, and prior to cycles 1, 2, 3 and 5</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the effect of therapy with docetaxel and OGX-427 on peripheral blood circulating tumor cells (CTCs) enumeration and expression of Hsp27 and other relevant proteins via immunoflourescence, and levels of telomerase by quantitative polymerase chain reaction (PCR), and explore their relation with clinical outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Bladder Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Urothelial Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Arm: Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Three doses of 600 mg OGX-427 will be administered IV during the loading dose period (days -9 to -1). Following completion of the loading dose period, 600 mg OGX-427 will be given IV weekly on days 1, 8, and 15 of each 21-day cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Arm: Arm B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Docetaxel (75 mg/M2) will be administered IV on day 1 of each 21 day cycle for a maximum of 10 cycles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>OGX-427</intervention_name>
    <description>Three doses of 600 mg OGX-427 will be administered IV during the loading dose period (days -9 to -1). Following completion of the loading dose period, 600 mg OGX-427 will be given IV weekly on days 1, 8, and 15 of each 21-day cycle. OGX-427 must be administered prior to docetaxel on day 1 of each cycle.
Following completion of 10 cycles of docetaxel, 600 mg OGX-427 will continue to be administered by IV weekly as maintenance therapy in Arm A participants who do not have disease progression (i.e., stable disease or better). Participants without documented disease progression who have discontinued from study treatment not due to toxicity related to OGX-427 can also continue to receive OGX-427 maintenance as long as they have completed disease assessments following at least 2 cycles of chemotherapy.  Maintenance with OGX-427 will continue until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Arm: Arm A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Docetaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>For Arm A Only: Docetaxel should be administered immediately following the completion of the OGX-427 infusion.
For Both Arms: Docetaxel (75 mg/M2) will be administered IV on Day 1 of each 21 day cycle for a maximum of 10 cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Arm: Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control Arm: Arm B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must have histologically documented metastatic or locally inoperable
             advanced urothelial carcinoma (bladder, urethra, ureter and renal pelvis) (T4b, N2,
             N3, or M1 disease. NOTE: Aberrant differentiation such as squamous, glandular
             (adenocarcinoma), and micropapillary are eligible unless the tumor is considered a
             pure histological variant according to the pathology report. Participants with small
             cell histology are not eligible.

          -  Participants must have measurable disease defined as at least one target lesion that
             has not been irradiated and can be accurately measured in at least one dimension by
             RECIST v1.1 criteria.

          -  Participants must have received prior systemic chemotherapy treatment for metastatic
             urothelial carcinoma.  NOTE: Up to 2 prior systemic chemotherapeutic regimens given
             in the metastatic disease setting for urothelial carcinoma are allowed.

          -  Specifically, subjects must meet one or more of the following criteria:

               1. Progression during or after treatment with a regimen that includes a platinum
                  salt (e.g., carboplatin or cisplatin) OR

               2. Disease recurrence within one year after neoadjuvant or adjuvant platinum-based
                  systemic chemotherapy, measured from the date of last dose of chemotherapy or
                  surgery until the day the informed consent is signed

          -  Participants must be ≥18 years since no dosing or adverse event data are currently
             available on the use of OGX-427 in participants &lt;18 years of age.

          -  Minimum of 21 days have elapsed since prior major surgery, with recovery from any
             adverse events.

          -  Minimum of 14 days have elapsed since any prior radiation therapy, with recovery from
             any adverse events.

          -  The effects of OGX-427 on the developing human fetus are unknown. For this reason,
             women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
             (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry and
             for the duration of study participation. Should a woman become pregnant or suspect
             she is pregnant while participating in this study, she should inform her treating
             physician immediately.

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent
             document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of treatment with docetaxel in any setting.  Participants treated with prior
             paclitaxel are eligible.

          -  Prior enrollment in the OncoGenex Phase 2 Study OGX-427-02.

          -  Participants may not be receiving other investigational agents.

          -  Participants with known brain or spinal cord metastases are excluded from this
             clinical trial because of their poor prognosis and because they often develop
             progressive neurologic dysfunction that would confound the evaluation of neurologic
             and other adverse events. NOTE: Brain imaging is not required unless the patient has
             symptoms or physical signs of central nervous system (CNS) disease.

          -  History of allergic reactions or severe hypersensitivity reactions to drugs
             formulated with polysorbate 80 or antisense oligonucleotides.

          -  Peripheral neuropathy ≥Grade 2.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to ongoing or active
             infection or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements.

          -  Cerebrovascular accident or pulmonary embolus within 3 months of randomization.

          -  Pregnant women and breast feeding women are excluded from this study because of the
             risk to a fetus due to docetaxel chemotherapy and OGX-427 systemic treatment
             (fertility toxicology studies have not been completed for OGX-427).

          -  Active second malignancy (except non-melanomatous skin cancer or incidental prostate
             cancer found on cystectomy): active secondary malignancy is defined as a current need
             for cancer therapy or a high possibility (&gt;30%) of recurrence during the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Noah Hahn, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Hoosier Oncology Group</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Costantine Albany, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>3179212050</phone>
    <email>gegould@iupui.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Cynthia Burkhardt, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>3179212050</phone>
    <email>gegould@iupui.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alabama Hematology Oncology Clinic at Medical West</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Guru Sonpavde, M.D.</last_name>
      <email>sonpavde@uab.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>J Lynn Merritt</last_name>
      <phone>205.975.2028</phone>
      <email>jlynnrn@uab.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City of Hope: Duarte</name>
      <address>
        <city>Duarte</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sumanta Pal, M.D.</last_name>
      <email>spal@coh.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Dorie Cook</last_name>
      <phone>626.256.4673</phone>
      <phone_ext>61578</phone_ext>
      <email>dcook@coh.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City of Hope: Antelope Valley</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lancaster</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>93534</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sumanta Pal, M.D.</last_name>
      <email>spal@coh.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Dorie Cook</last_name>
      <phone>626.256.4673</phone>
      <phone_ext>61578</phone_ext>
      <email>dcook@coh.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA: Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven Wong, M.D.</last_name>
      <email>sgwong@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ross Mar Divinagracia</last_name>
      <phone>310.794.3448</phone>
      <email>rossmar@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>USC: Norris Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90089</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Quinn, M.D.</last_name>
      <email>diquinn@usc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Zeno Ashai</last_name>
      <phone>323.865.0454</phone>
      <email>zeno.ashai@med.usc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IU Health Goshen Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Goshen</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46527</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alex Starodub, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>574-535-2886</phone>
      <email>astarodub@iuhealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Vanessa De Pue</last_name>
      <phone>574.364.2649</phone>
      <email>vdepue@iuhealth.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University Melvin &amp; Bren Simon Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Costantine Albany, M.D.</last_name>
      <email>calbany@iu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Rhoda Lohman</last_name>
      <phone>317-278-4840</phone>
      <email>rloman@iupui.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IU Health Central Indiana Cancer Centers</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46219</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bamidele Adensunloye, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>317-859-5500</phone>
      <email>badesunloye@IUHealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ahran Lee</last_name>
      <phone>317-678-2738</phone>
      <email>alee4@iuhealth.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IU Health at Ball Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Muncie</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>47303</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>William Fisher, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>765-281-2174</phone>
      <email>wfisher1@iuhealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Angie Patterson, R.N.</last_name>
      <phone>765-2751-5849</phone>
      <email>apatterson2@iuhealth.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Maryland: Greenebaum Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Arif Hussain, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>410-328-7226</phone>
      <email>ahussain@som.umaryland.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Michelle Besche</last_name>
      <phone>410.328.8610</phone>
      <email>mbesche@umm.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Toni Choueiri, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-632-4524</phone>
      <email>Toni_Choueiri@dfci.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Bon Lam</last_name>
      <phone>617-632-5261</phone>
      <email>BonM_Lam@dfci.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ajjai Alva, MB, BS</last_name>
      <phone>734-647-8903</phone>
      <email>ajjai@med.umich.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sabrina Hargrove</last_name>
      <phone>734-936-8587</phone>
      <email>sgomes@med.umich.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Siteman Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joel Picus, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>314-747-1367</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Christopher Grant</last_name>
      <phone>314-747-3575</phone>
      <email>cgrant@dom.wustl.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nebraska Cancer Specialists</name>
      <address>
        <city>Omaha</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ralph Hauke, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>402-354-8124</phone>
      <email>rhauke@nebraskacancer.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Gladys Pierce</last_name>
      <phone>402-354-5129</phone>
      <email>gladys.pierce@nmhs.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center: Norris Cotton Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manchester</city>
        <state>New Hampshire</state>
        <zip>03102</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sergey Devitskiy, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>603-650-5534</phone>
      <email>Sergey.Devitskiy@hitchcock.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Neal Wilson</last_name>
      <phone>(603) 653-9054</phone>
      <email>neal.a.wilson@hitchcock.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center: Basking Ridge</name>
      <address>
        <city>Basking Ridge</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07920</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jonathan Rosenberg, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-422-4461</phone>
      <email>rosenbj1@mskcc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mariel Boyd</last_name>
      <phone>646.227.7186</phone>
      <email>boydm@mskcc.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>John Theurer Cancer Center: Hackensack University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hackensack</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robert Alter, M</last_name>
      <phone>551-996-5072</phone>
      <email>ralter@hackensackumc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jane Hayes</last_name>
      <phone>551.996.5831</phone>
      <email>jhayes@hackensackumc.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rutgers Cancer Institute of New Jersey</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Brunswick</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08903</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mark Stein, M.D.</last_name>
      <email>steinmn@cinj.rutgers.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kaveri Mamania</last_name>
      <phone>732.235.9837</phone>
      <email>mamanikb@cinj.rutgers.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of New Mexico Cancer Center: Albuquerque</name>
      <address>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <state>New Mexico</state>
        <zip>87131</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard Laurer, M.D.</last_name>
      <email>rlaurer@salud.unm.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Rebecca Myers</last_name>
      <phone>575.556.6545</phone>
      <email>rmyers-brito@salud.umn.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of New Mexico Cancer Center: Las Cruces</name>
      <address>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <state>New Mexico</state>
        <zip>88011</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>William Adler, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>575-521-1554</phone>
      <email>William.Adler@lpnt.net</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kim Hoffman</last_name>
      <email>Kim.Hoffman@lpnt.net</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14263</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Roberto Pili, M.D.</last_name>
      <email>roberto.pili@roswellpark.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Eileen Healy, 0</last_name>
      <phone>716.845.8910</phone>
      <email>eileen.healy@roswellpark.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center: Commack</name>
      <address>
        <city>Commack</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11725</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jonathan Rosenberg, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-422-4461</phone>
      <email>rosenbj1@mskcc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mariel Boyd</last_name>
      <phone>646.227.7186</phone>
      <email>boydm@mskcc.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center: Main Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jonathan Rosenberg, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-422-4461</phone>
      <email>rosenbj1@mskcc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ilana Garcia-Grossman</last_name>
      <phone>646-227-7186</phone>
      <email>garciagi@mskcc.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York University Clinical Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Arjun Balar, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>212-731-5820</phone>
      <email>arjun.balar@nyumc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sarah Torneten</last_name>
      <phone>212.263.4424</phone>
      <email>sarah.torneten@nyumc.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Rochester Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elizabeth Guancial, M.D.</last_name>
      <email>Elizabeth_Guancial@urmc.rochester.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Melissa Worman</last_name>
      <phone>585.275.4583</phone>
      <email>melissa_worman@urmc.rochester.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center: Rockville Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rockville Centre</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11570</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jonathan Rosenberg, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-422-4461</phone>
      <email>rosenbj1@mskcc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mariel Boyd</last_name>
      <phone>646.227.7186</phone>
      <email>boydm@mskcc.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center: Sleepy Hollow</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sleepy Hollow</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10591</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jonathan Rosenberg, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-422-4661</phone>
      <email>rosenbj1@mskcc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mariel Boyd</last_name>
      <phone>646.227.7186</phone>
      <email>boydm@mskcc.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rob Dreicer, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>216-445-2360</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Krista Zaharewick</last_name>
      <phone>216-444-2748</phone>
      <email>zaharek@ccf.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospitals Seidman Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christopher Hoimes, D.O.</last_name>
      <phone>216-844-3951</phone>
      <email>cjh122@case.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Janette Gortz</last_name>
      <phone>216-844-1545</phone>
      <email>janette.gortz@uhhospitals.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Thomas Jefferson University: Kimmel Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jean Hoffman-Censits, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>215-955-8874</phone>
      <email>jean.hoffman-censits@jefferson.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Monica Byrnes</last_name>
      <phone>215.503.0552</phone>
      <email>monica.byrnes@jefferson.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MUSC Hollings Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29425</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Harry Drabkin, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>843-792-9007</phone>
      <email>drabkin@musc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Seth Price</last_name>
      <phone>843-792-8625</phone>
      <email>pricesr@musc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Froedtert &amp; Medical College of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John Burfeind, M.D.</last_name>
      <email>jburfeind@mcw.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kristen Lemke</last_name>
      <phone>414.805.4627</phone>
      <email>klemke@mcw.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.hoosieroncologygroup.org</url>
    <description>Hoosier Oncology Group Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 23, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 25, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>OGX-427</keyword>
  <keyword>Docetaxel</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Transitional Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
