<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="26828">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02009215</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ITCRAA6910</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02009215</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>School-Based Treatment With ACT to Reduce Transmission</brief_title>
  <acronym>START</acronym>
  <official_title>'SCHOOL-BASED TREATMENT WITH ACT TO REDUCE TRANSMISSION'(START): Evaluation of the Community Impact of Intermittent Preventive Treatment for Malaria in Ugandan Children: a Cluster Randomised Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Infectious Diseases Research Collaboration, Uganda</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Durham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Uganda: National Council for Science and Technology</authority>
    <authority>Uganda: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      We propose to evaluate the community-level impact of IPT for malaria in schoolchildren on
      clinical outcomes and malaria transmission, using a cluster-randomised design in Jinja,
      Uganda. Dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine (DP) will be administered to schoolchildren monthly
      for one school year. Outcomes will be measured using surveys of communities, schoolchildren,
      and mosquito vectors.  Our proposal also includes health service research to evaluate the
      potential feasibility of taking the programme to scale, which will guide future research and
      implementation of the intervention, and help shape policies in Uganda and elsewhere in
      Africa.

      The primary objective of the study is: To evaluate the impact of IPT for malaria in
      schoolchildren using monthly DP, as compared with the current standard of care (no IPT), on
      measures of malaria transmission in community members. We will test the hypothesis that
      malaria transmission, as measured by the prevalence of asexual parasitaemia, will be lower
      in communities surrounding the intervention schools, than those surrounding the standard
      care schools.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study overview:

      We are proposing to evaluate the community-level impact of intermittent preventive treatment
      (IPT) for malaria in schoolchildren on clinical outcomes and malaria transmission, using a
      cluster-randomised design. The intervention will involve the administration of
      dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine (DP) to schoolchildren monthly for one school year.

      Study site:

      The study will be conducted in Jinja district, an area with low to moderate malaria
      transmission.  The annual EIR in Jinja district was estimated to be 6 infective bites per
      person/year in 2001-02. There are 11 sub-counties in Jinja district. Of these, 5
      sub-counties are more densely populated. The 6 more rural and less populated sub-counties
      (Budondo, Butagaya, Buwenge, Buyendo, Busedde, and Kakira) will be included in the study
      population.

      Clusters:

      For this trial, a cluster will be defined as one (or more) primary schools plus the 100
      closest households surrounding the school. The clusters will be defined prior to
      randomisation using the digitally enumerated maps.We plan to include a total of 78 clusters
      in the study, 39 in each study arm, focusing on public or private day schools that are
      well-spaced geographically, and aiming to maximize the buffer zone between clusters to
      minimize contamination. To ensure that we identify at least 78 clusters, in some cases we
      may include more than one school per cluster, if multiple schools are in close proximity.

      Randomisation:

      The randomisation will be conducted by a member of the study personnel who is not directly
      involved in the field activities. Primary schools will be stratified by type of ownership
      (public vs private). Restricted randomisation will be employed to ensure balance on type of
      school and geographical location. Specifically, restrictions will be applied that exclude
      the allocation of all clusters originating from a single sub-county, or that are otherwise
      in close geographical proximity from being allocated to the same arm of the trial.

      Study population:

      The intervention will be delivered to children attending participating primary schools that
      are randomized to the intervention group.  Of the 78 clusters, 39 will be randomized to the
      intervention and 39 to the control.  We estimate that the average number of schools per
      cluster will be 1.25.  Thus, approximately 50 schools will participate in the intervention.
      The overall mean number of children enrolled in the primary schools is approximately 500;
      thus approximately 25,000 students will participate in the intervention.

      The intervention:

      IPT with DP will be delivered to all schools located in the 39 intervention clusters.
      Treatment will be administered to participating students each month for one school year
      (approximately 9 treatments), and will not be blinded. Schools within clusters randomised to
      the control arm will not receive IPT.

      Administration of dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine:

      All enrolled students will receive DP (Holley Cotec Pharmaceuticals) given once a day for 3
      consecutive days. DP will be dosed according to weight-based guidelines. DP will be
      administered orally by study personnel, and all treatments will be directly observed. All DP
      treatments given will be recorded.

      Evaluation procedures:

      Outcomes will be measured through surveys of communities, schoolchildren, and mosquito
      vectors. The potential feasibility of the IPT intervention will also be assessed.

        1. Community surveys. At baseline (prior to implementing the intervention) and one year
           later, 138 community members from randomly selected households will be surveyed from
           each of the 78 clusters (total 10,764).  The survey will include a household
           questionnaire and clinical &amp; laboratory evaluation.

        2. School surveys. At baseline and one year later, 80 randomly selected schoolchildren
           will be surveyed from each of the 78 clusters (total 6240).The survey will include a
           brief questionnaire and clinical &amp; laboratory evaluation.

        3. Entomology surveys. Mosquitoes will be collected using Centers for Disease Control
           (CDC) light traps from 5 randomly selected households in 20 purposively selected
           clusters per arm (100 households per arm; 200 total). Households will be sampled
           monthly for the duration of the intervention.

        4. Qualitative assessment. A historical review of published and unpublished literature on
           programmes that have integrated health interventions into the education sector;
           ethnographic observation of intervention activities; in-depth interviews with key
           stakeholders (12-15), and teachers and health workers (12-15).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of asexual parasitaemia (as measured by microscopy) in community members</measure>
    <time_frame>Endline survey, approximately 7-11 months after starting the intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Parasite prevalence will be measured in final cross-sectional community survey, which will be conducted after implementing the intervention. Parasite prevalence will be defined as the proportion of thick blood smears that are positive for asexual parasites. A baseline survey will be conducted prior to implementing the intervention. An adjusted analysis will be performed to adjust for outcomes collected in the baseline community survey, and to account for any baseline imbalances in factors likely to be prognostic for outcomes, using a two-stage process.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of asexual parasitaemia (as measured by microscopy) in schoolchildren</measure>
    <time_frame>Endline survey conducted at the end of the 2014 school year, approximately 6-7 months after starting the intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Parasite prevalence will be measured in final school survey, which will be conducted at the end of the 2014 school year. Parasite prevalence will be defined as the proportion of thick blood smears that are positive for asexual parasites. A baseline survey will be conducted prior to implementing the intervention. An adjusted analysis will be performed to adjust for outcomes collected in the baseline school survey, and to account for any baseline imbalances in factors likely to be prognostic for outcomes, using a two-stage process.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Entomologic inoculation rate (EIR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Over one year of follow-up (2014 school year)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of infectious bites per person per year (the human biting rate multiplied by the sporozoite rate). We will compare the EIR in communities surrounding the intervention schools to that of communities surrounding control schools.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of serious adverse events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Over one year of follow-up (2014 school year)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of children experiencing any SAEs out of the total number of children enrolled in intervention and control schools.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25000</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IPT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine (DP) dosed by weight x 3 days, monthly for approximately 9 rounds of treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No IPT with DP will be given</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine</intervention_name>
    <description>Schoolchildren enrolled in schools randomized to the intervention will receive monthly treatment with DP (dosed by weight x 3 days)</description>
    <arm_group_label>IPT</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Duo-Cotecxin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        FOR IPT INTERVENTION (MONTHLY TREATMENT WITH DP):

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Student enrolled in a participating intervention school.

          -  Willingness of parent/guardian to provide written informed consent.

          -  Provision of written assent by the student (aged 8 years or above).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known allergy or history of adverse reaction to DP.

          -  Menarche in female students.

        FOR COMMUNITY HOUSEHOLD SURVEY:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Usual resident who is present in the sampled household on the night before  the
             survey

          -  Adult aged 18 years or older.

          -  Agreement to provide informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No adult resident home on more than 3 occasions.

          -  Household vacant

          -  Dwelling destroyed or not found

        FOR COMMUNITY CLINICAL SURVEY:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Usual residents who are present in the sampled households on the night before the
             survey

          -  Agreement of parents or guardians of children to provide informed consent.

          -  Agreement of eligible adults to provide informed consent.

          -  Agreement of a child aged 8 years or older to provide assent.

        Exclusion criterion:

          -  Inability to locate eligible resident on more than 3 occasions.

        FOR SCHOOL SURVEYS:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Enrolled in a participating primary school

          -  Agreement of parents or guardians of children to provide informed consent.

          -  Agreement of a child aged 8 years or older to provide assent.

        The exclusion criterion:

          -  Inability to locate eligible students on more than 3 occasions.

        FOR ENTOMOLOGY SURVEY:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Resident in the sub-county for the last six months.

          -  Provision of informed consent from head of household (or designate).

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Inability to locate the household on 3 or more occasions.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sarah G Staedke, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sarah G Staedke, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+256 782 507 132</phone>
    <email>Sarah.Staedke@lshtm.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Catherine M Sebuguzi, MBChB, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>+ 256 752 900 219</phone>
    <email>cmaiteki@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Infectious Diseases Research Collaboration</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kampala</city>
        <zip>P.O.Box 7475</zip>
        <country>Uganda</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Moses Kamya, MBChB</last_name>
      <phone>+ 256 414 530 692</phone>
      <email>mkamya@infocom.co.ug</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Catherine Tugaineyo</last_name>
      <phone>+ 256 414 530 692</phone>
      <email>ctugaineyo@idrc-uganda.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sarah G Staedke, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Moses Kamya, MBChB PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Grant Dorsey, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chris Drakeley, MI Biol, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Clare Chandler, BA, MSc, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yeka Adoke, MPH, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jonaiter Nankabirwa, MBChB, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Uganda</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.muucsf.org</url>
    <description>Infectious Disease Research Collaboration (IDRC), Uganda Malaria Surveillance Project (UMSP), Makerere University - University of California, San Francisco (MU-UCSF)</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 6, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 23, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sarah Staedke</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Uganda</keyword>
  <keyword>intermittent preventive treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine</keyword>
  <keyword>schoolchildren</keyword>
  <keyword>malaria</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dihydroquinghaosu</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Artemisinins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Piperaquine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
