<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="82218">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01803048</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11040198</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01803048</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Predicting Cognitive and Emotional Health From Neurocircuitry Following TBI</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Model for Predicting Cognitive and Emotional Health From Structural and Functional Neurocircuitry Following Traumatic Brain Injury</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mclean Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mclean Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Abnormalities in structural and functional connectivity between brain regions have been
      suggested as putative biomarkers of mild traumatic brain injury (TBI) and significant
      contributors to neuropsychological functioning and injury outcome.  The purpose of this
      study is to use two advanced magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) techniques called
      diffusion-weighted imaging (DWI) and resting state functional MRI to compare structural and
      functional connectivity between individuals with documented mild TBI and healthy controls.
      To evaluate the significance of structural and functional connectivity for behavior, the
      brain imaging data will then be related to measures of cognition and emotion. Over a 4-year
      period, 150 adults with documented mild TBI and 30 healthy controls will participate in the
      study.

      The study will investigate the following questions and hypotheses:

        1. Evaluate the DWI metric fractional anisotropy (FA) as a measure of white matter
           integrity across multiple stages of recovery following mild TBI relative to healthy
           controls.  It is hypothesized that mild TBI will be associated with greater white
           matter abnormalities than healthy controls.

        2. It is hypothesized that there will be a relationship between FA, cognition and emotion
           as a function of the injury.

        3. It is hypothesized that functional connectivity will be related to FA.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case Control, Time Perspective: Cross-Sectional</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Diffusion Weighted Imaging Metric: fractional anisotropy (FA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured on the day of the MRI scan</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Traumatic Brain Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TBI</arm_group_label>
    <description>30 individuals who will be tested at two weeks post-TBI; 30 individuals who will be tested at one month post-TBI; 30 individuals who will be tested at three months post-TBI; 30 individuals who will be tested at six months post-TBI; 30 individuals who will be tested at 12 months post-TBI.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Control</arm_group_label>
    <description>30 healthy individuals with no history of TBI</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        One hundred eighty participants aged 20-45, including 150 adults with documented mild TBI
        and 30 healthy controls (HC) will participate in this study.  Participants in the TBI
        group will include 30 individuals who will be tested at two weeks post-TBI; 30 individuals
        who will be tested at one month post-TBI; 30 individuals who will be tested at three
        months post-TBI; 30 individuals who will be tested at six months post-TBI; and 30
        individuals who will be tested at 12 months post-TBI. Participants will be recruited from
        the local area of Boston, MA, via IRB-approved flyers and advertisements placed in
        newspapers, on the radio and within vehicles of the local public transport system (e.g.
        buses and subway cars).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  English as first language

          -  Ability to provide informed consent

          -  Right handedness

          -  For TBI group: documented TBI experienced within 12 months prior to testing.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Metal within the body, claustrophobia or other contraindications for MRI

          -  Complicating medical conditions that may influence the outcome of neuropsychological
             assessment or neuroimaging (e.g., HIV, brain tumor, etc.)

          -  Less than 9th grade education

          -  History of alcoholism or substance use disorder

          -  Excess current alcohol use or illicit substance use

          -  for Healthy Controls (HC): life-time history of TBI or Axis I disorder

          -  Pregnancy (ruled out by urine β-HCG)

          -  Left or mixed handedness

          -  Colorblindness

          -  for HC: Having participated in a sport with a high risk of concussive/subconcussive
             blows for a period of at least 1 month including but not limited to: football, rugby,
             boxing, ice hockey, wrestling, soccer, martial arts
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William D Killgore, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mclean Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Maia Kipman</last_name>
    <phone>617-855-2239</phone>
    <email>mkipman@mclean.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>McLean Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Belmont</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02478</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maia Kipman</last_name>
      <phone>617-855-2239</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>William D Killgore, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://concussionstudies.com/home/tbi-model/</url>
    <description>Study Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 23, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 27, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mclean Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>William Killgore</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Traumatic Brain Injury</keyword>
  <keyword>Diffusion Weighted Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Resting State Functional Connectivity</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognition</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
