<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="47094">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02138227</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>5R01DK081118</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>5R01DK081118</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02138227</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Randomized Trial of the Early Referral and Request Approach (ERRA) Intervention to Increase Consent to Organ Donation</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Trial of the Early Referral and Request Approach (ERRA) Intervention to Increase Consent to Organ Donation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Temple University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Temple University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the efficacy and generalizability of a
      communication intervention (Communication Effectively about Donation (CEaD)) for Organ
      Procurement Organization (OPO) staff requesters and to compare two conditions of delivering
      the CEaD.  The experimental design will test: (1) the overall efficacy of the intervention
      on timely referral and consent for organ donation and (2) whether a completely autonomous
      condition (no outside training assistance) is clinically equivalent to the assisted
      condition (training provided by outside consultants) in terms of the final outcome of
      consent to donation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Communicating Effectively about Donation (CEaD) is a communications training program
      specifically and uniquely tailored to the problem of making requests for organ donation to
      families of deceased patients. The CEaD trains Organ Procurement Organization (OPO) staff
      requesters to make effective requests to donor-eligible families by allowing requesters to
      learn and practice relational communication skills using a series of simulated scenarios.
      &quot;Simulated Patients&quot; or &quot;Standardized Patients&quot; (SPs) acting out the roles of families
      making donation decisions were created in consultation with our partner OPO for our single
      site test of the intervention.

      In a previous study, four training scenarios were developed: the first an uncomplicated
      scenario; the second a single parent, urban, African-American family; the third the divorced
      parents of a pediatric patient who are at odds; and the fourth a case of donation after
      cardiac death (DCD).  Each scenario allows the requester to use basic requester skills,
      including: framing donation positively, use of statistics to explain donation benefits,
      engaging the family in a discussion of their values, probing and responding to family fears
      or misinformation about donation, and attending to family's emotional needs. Because they
      are presented as a series, the scenarios allow requesters to work through increasingly more
      challenging donation simulations and to encounter family-specific issues such as unresolved
      family disputes, family dysfunction, cultural differences, and families who are divided
      about whether or not to donate.

      OPO requesters will be trained in the CEaD method of organ donation communication over a
      period of 4 months either using the DVD training material only (the autonomous condition) or
      they will be assisted by having the DVD supplemented through working the scenarios with live
      SPs who will be trained to act out the scenarios with the OPO requesters and provide
      feedback in the four OPOs in the assisted CEaD condition.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in authorization rates for solid organ donation from families of donor-eligible patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and continuously for 3 years post intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>OPO requesters completed a brief, web-based survey after every family approach, regardless of whether the family ultimately consented to donation.  Rates of baseline and post-intervention consent to donation were compared.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in requesters' aggregated relational communication skills</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and continuously for 3 years post intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Using a family interview, we will examine the family's experience with the donation process, specifically focusing on family self-report of comfort, satisfaction with the communication and decision-making process, content of the conversation, and measurement of the relational aspects of the communication. The instrument is based on a well-developed interview that was used in a seminal study of family experience and decision-making for organ donation in acute care hospital settings.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in request staffs' comfort answering donation-related questions during the approach to family decision makers</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and continuously for 3 years post intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Requester staff self-report assessment utilizing a seven-point scale to rate his/her own comfort and satisfaction with the overall request process following each family contact.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1680</enrollment>
  <condition>Tissue and Organ Procurement</condition>
  <condition>Communication</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Assisted CEaD Condition</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the assisted condition, participants use the CEaD training materials supplemented with simulators to practice the communication skills.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Autonomous CEaD Condition</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the autonomous condition, participants view the CEaD training materials on a DVD along with a self-training guide.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Assisted CEaD Condition</intervention_name>
    <description>In the assisted condition, participants use the CEaD training materials supplemented with simulators to practice the communication skills.  OPO requesters will be assisted by having the CEaD DVD supplemented through working the scenarios with live simulated patients who will be trained to act out the scenarios with the OPO requesters and provide feedback.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Assisted CEaD Condition</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Autonomous CEaD Condition</intervention_name>
    <description>In the autonomous condition, participants view the CEaD training materials on a DVD along with a self-training guide.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Autonomous CEaD Condition</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  OPO requester staff employed at a participating OPO

          -  Family decision makers (FDM) approached by a participating OPO requester about the
             option of donating the organs of their loved one

          -  16 years of age or older (16 and 17 year old FDM will require consent of custodial
             adult)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  OPO requester staff not employed at a participating OPO

          -  FDM not approached by a participating OPO requester

          -  FDM younger than 16 years of age
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Laura Siminoff, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alabama Organ Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35233</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Donor Network of Arizona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85013</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>TransLife of Orlando</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winter Park</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32789</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New England Organ Bank</name>
      <address>
        <city>Waltham</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02451</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mid-America Transplant Services</name>
      <address>
        <city>Springfield</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>65707</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York Organ Donor Network</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10001</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>LifeBanc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44128</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>LifeGift Organ Donation Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77005</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>LifeNet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23227</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Traino HM, Siminoff LA. Attitudes and acceptance of First Person Authorization: a national comparison of donor and nondonor families. J Trauma Acute Care Surg. 2013 Jan;74(1):294-300. doi: 10.1097/TA.0b013e318270dafc.</citation>
    <PMID>23147186</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 12, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 24, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Temple University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Laura Siminoff</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dean, College of Health Professions and Social Work</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Organ donation request</keyword>
  <keyword>Family decision makers</keyword>
  <keyword>Communication</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
