<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="18273">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01848210</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VN01/12</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1141-7277</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>15030313.0.1001.5470</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01848210</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety of Coumarin and Troxerutin in the Symptomatic Treatment of Chronic Venous Insufficiency</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Efficacy and Safety of the Fixed-dose Combination of Coumarin and Troxerutin (Venalot®) Versus Placebo in the Symptomatic Treatment of Chronic Venous Insufficiency - VENACT.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Takeda</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Brazil: National Health Surveillance Agency - ANVISA</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the efficacy and safety of the fixed-dose
      combination of coumarin and troxerutin versus placebo in the symptomatic treatment of
      chronic venous insufficiency.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The drug being tested in this study is the fixed-dose combination of coumarin and troxerutin
      called Venalot®. Venalot is being tested to treat the symptoms of chronic venous
      insufficiency. This study will look at symptom relief in people who take Venalot.

      The study will enroll approximately 336 patients. Participants will be randomly assigned (by
      chance, like flipping a coin) to one of the two treatment groups—which will remain
      undisclosed to the patient and study doctor during the study (unless there is an urgent
      medical need):

        -  Combination coumarin + troxerutin extended release tablets

        -  Placebo (dummy inactive pill) - this is a tablet that looks like the study drug but has
           no active ingredient.

      All participants will be asked to take two tablets three times a day throughout the study.

      This multi-centre trial will be conducted in Brazil. The overall time to participate in this
      study is up to 18 weeks. Participants will make 6 visits to the clinic.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change from Baseline in Volume of Reference Leg at Week 16</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in the partial volume of legs will be measured using a water plethysmometer. The volume of water (at 34 ± 0.2 °C) displaced after limb immersion is collected in an empty plastic Beaker which has been previously weighed (scale tare). The equilibrium/stability will be estimated using the absolute difference between measures of volume obtained at the Week 16 visit and Baseline.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Local Complaint Severity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Local Complaint Severity will be assessed using the Severity Score of Local Complaints that comprises 8 items: 1=tired legs, 2=heavy legs, 3= feeling of tension, 4=feeling of swelling, 5=aching legs, 6=tingling, 7=itching, 8=burning of soles of the feet.
Each item is classified with a Likert-type scale of 5 levels, where 0=absent, 1=low, 2=medium, 3=high, 4=very high.
A total score is calculated from the sum of the scores of all the 8 items and ranges from 0 (complaints absent) to 32 (very high severity).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Assessment by the Investigator</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The investigator will record their impression about the overall clinical picture at the end of the treatment period (Week 16) taking into account the clinical picture compared with the Baseline visit, according to the following 4-point scale: 1=Marked improvement, 2= Slight improvement, 3=Unchanged, 4=Worsening.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with adverse events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Adverse events are any unwanted medical occurrences in an individual taking part in a clinical study who is receiving a pharmaceutical product. The adverse event does not have necessarily a causal relationship with the treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">398</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Venous Insufficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Coumarin + troxerutin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Coumarin 30 mg, troxerutin 180 mg fixed-dose combination tablets, orally, three times daily for up to 16 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Coumarin + troxerutin placebo-matching tablets, orally, three times daily for up to 16 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Coumarin/troxerutin</intervention_name>
    <description>Coumarin + troxerutin fixed-dose combination tablets</description>
    <arm_group_label>Coumarin + troxerutin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Venalot®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Coumarin / troxerutin placebo-matching tablets</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        1. Consent of subject or legal representative2. Men or women of any ethnicity, aged
        between 18 and 75 years, and body mass index (BMI) equal or less than 40.

        3. Is able to use properly the medication according to protocol. 4. Has chronic venous
        insufficiency in the reference leg with the clinical classification C3, or C4a orC4b or
        C5, provided that in two last situations the present lipodermatosclerosis does not
        compromise more than 1/3 portion of the leg immersed or immersible in the plethysmometer.

        5. Has stable edema (in a steady state), equivalent to a variation lower than or equal to
        10% in partial volume of the reference leg between the screening visit and the
        randomization visit, and present for at least 6 months.

        6. Scoring in &quot;Severity Score of Local Complaints&quot; equal to or higher than 5 total points.

        7. Women who are using an effective (at the discretion of the investigator), but not
        hormonal, birth control method (not hormonal intrauterine device (IUD), surgical
        sterilization, among others), or who are postmenopausal, in addition to condom use
        (mandatory).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Has chronic venous insufficiency classified as C1, C2 in the reference leg or C6 in
             any leg.

          2. Has chronic venous insufficiency C4b or C5 in the reference leg, with
             lipodermatosclerosis present in more than 1/3 portion of the leg immersed in the
             plethysmometer.

          3. Has unstable edema, equivalent to variation of more than 10% of partial volume in the
             reference leg between the screening visit and randomization visit, prior to start of
             treatment.

          4. Has venous obstruction and/or deep vein thrombosis (DVT) and/or presence of phlebitis
             in lower limbs during the last 3 (three) months.

          5. Has developed deep vein insufficiency during the last 3 (three) months.

          6. Has other diseases that may interfere in the findings of the study such as:
             lymphedema, thrombosis, clotting disorders, edema of lower limbs due to right-sided
             heart failure, arterial obstruction of lower limbs and other conditions that, at
             medical discretion, are relevant to exclusion, particularly symptoms which are
             similar to the symptomatology of chronic venous insufficiency.

          7. Has a history of surgery at the venous system or sclerotherapy or who received any
             treatment for chronic venous insufficiency during the last 03 months, whether it was
             by drug, elastic stocking, laser, or surgery.

          8. Has used previously Venalot® and had no benefits with the treatment.

          9. Has a previous history of known or suspected allergy or intolerance to any of the
             ingredients of the medicinal product under investigation.

         10. Has any clinical finding (history and physical examination) that is interpreted by
             the physician-investigator as a risk to participant's participation in the study.

         11. Has known serious systemic disease, according to the medical and/or laboratory
             history.

         12. Has history of a known liver disease such as hepatitis A, hepatitis B, or C.

         13. Has changed at least one lab parameters: aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine
             aminotransferase (ALT), gamma-glutamyltransferase (gamma-GT), or alkaline phosphatase
             2.5 times above the upper limit of normal range; hemoglobin less than 10 g/dL;
             clearance of creatinine estimative equal or above 60mL/min/1.73 m^2; platelets below
             90,000/mL; and total bilirubin and fractions 1.5 times above the normal values.

         14. Has been using diuretics for a period less than or equal to 6 months due to any
             disease (hypertension, renal failure, or other).

         15. Has serious chronic liver or kidney disease, according to the medical and/or
             laboratory history.

         16. Has uncontrolled blood hypertension (systolic blood pressure &gt; 180 mmHg or diastolic
             blood pressure  &gt; 100 mmHg) at randomization or clinical hypertensive urgency.

         17. Has a previous history of diabetes mellitus on use of insulin.

         18. Has received treatment with immunosuppressive drugs, including systemic
             corticosteroids within 30 days before the start of study (randomization visit), or
             who are receiving immunosuppressive treatments, or who have known congenital or
             acquired immunodeficiency.

         19. Has malignant neoplasms, from any etiology, or who are receiving any type of
             anticancer treatment, unless when properly treated and with no evidence of recurrence
             during the last five years. Non-melanoma skin cancer is not an exclusion criterion.

         20. Is unable to understand the guidelines specified in this protocol or who cannot
             attend all the study visits.

         21. Has a previous history of alcoholism, drug abuse, psychological or emotional problems
             in the last 5 years that can invalidate the Informed Consent Form or restrain
             participant's ability to comply with the requirements of the protocol.

         22. Pregnant or breastfeeding women, or those who have the potential to become pregnant
             and are not using an appropriate contraceptive method.

         23. Women who are using hormonal contraceptives or hormone replacement treatment,
             including phytoestrogens, within the last 3 months.

         24. Took part in clinical trials during the last year.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Takeda</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 25, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 2, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Drug therapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Venous Insufficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Coumarin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Troxerutin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coumarins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
