<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="33575">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02018419</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ITL-014-TACT-MBC</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02018419</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Increased Frequency of AlloStim(TM) Dosing in Combination With Cryoablation in Metastatic Breast Cancer Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>MBC</acronym>
  <official_title>In-Situ Cancer Vaccine: Phase I/IIb, Open-Label Study to Assess Safety of AllostimTM in Combination With Cryoablation in Metastatic Breast Cancer Previously Treated With an Anthracycline, a Taxane and Capecitabine</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Immunovative Therapies, Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Immunovative Therapies, Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I/II study is designed to compare different treatment schedules of a personalized
      anti-cancer vaccine protocol which combines the cryoablation of a selected metastatic lesion
      with intra-tumor immunotherapy. The cryoablation causes the tumor to release tumor-specific
      antigens into the surrounding environment. The injection of bioengineered allogeneic immune
      cells, AlloStim(TM), into the lesion is designed to modulate the immune response and educate
      the immune system to kill other tumor cells.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will assess three different dosing schedules. A standard 3 plus 3 study design
      will be used. The starting dose for each dosing schedule will be escalated in subsequent
      groups of patients. The study will evaluate safety of increased frequency of AlloStim (TM)
      dosing and anti-tumor effect of the new proposed dose and frequency schedule.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the safety of increased frequency of dosing</measure>
    <time_frame>Window is defined as the time required receiving two doses of AlloStim IV push plus 28 days follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Three patients are enrolled at each frequency schedule in the absence of dose limiting toxicity (DLT). A DLT is defined as any allergic or autoimmune toxicity or other study drug related toxicity Grade 3 or higher during the DLT assessment window.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the anti-tumor effect of Allostim combined with cryoablation at the new proposed dose and frequency schedule.</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days after last dose administration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Each treatment schedule will be monitored for radiological, pathological, and immunological response. These assessments will be compared between three treatment schedules.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-Related Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>From enrollment to 90 days after last dose administration.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Health-Related Quality of life will be measured using the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Quality of Life Questionnaire (QLQ-C30) and its supplementary breast cancer questionnaire (QLQ-BR23).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Immunological Response</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days after last dose administration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood samples will be evaluated for immunological response and a determination made as to whether immunological response correlates with RECIST and pathology.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-Tumor Response</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days after last dose administration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The changes in tumor burden by RECIST and compare these changes with the pathological analysis of corresponding biopsies.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">31</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dosing Schedule A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>the priming step with ID injection of AlloStim on Days 0, 7, and 14;
the ablation step with cryoablation and intra-tumor injection of AlloStim on Day 21;
the activation step with an IV infusion of AlloStim on Day 28;
the booster step with intravenous booster infusion of AlloStim on Days 56 and 84;
Protocol follow-up procedures continue until day 168 and at investigator discretion thereafter.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dosing Schedule B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>the priming step with ID injection of AlloStim on Days 0 and 3 and an additional ID injection of AlloStim on Days 7 and 10;
the ablation step with cryoablation and intra-tumor injection of AlloStim on Day 14;
the activation step with an IV infusion of AlloStim on Day 21;
the booster step with intravenous booster infusion of AlloStim on Days 49 and 77.
Protocol follow-up procedures continue until day 168 and at investigator discretion thereafter.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dosing Schedule C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>the priming step with ID injection of AlloStim on Days 0 and 3 and an additional ID injection of AlloStim on Days 7 and 10;
the ablation step with cryoablation and intra-tumor injection of AlloStim on Day 14, and intra-tumor injection of AlloStim again into the same cryoablated lesion on Day 17;
the activation step with an IV infusion of AlloStim on Day 21;
the booster step with intravenous infusion of AlloStim on days 49 and 77.
Protocol follow-up procedures continue until day 168 and at investigator discretion thereafter.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AlloStim</intervention_name>
    <description>AlloStim is derived from the blood of normal blood donors and is intentionally mismatched to the recipient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dosing Schedule A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dosing Schedule B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dosing Schedule C</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>InSituVax</other_name>
    <other_name>Personalized anti-tumor vaccine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cryoablation</intervention_name>
    <description>Percutaneous ablation of a single metastatic tumor lesion usually in liver or bone. The procedure is conducted under CT or ultrasound image-guidance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dosing Schedule A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dosing Schedule B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dosing Schedule C</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Women with histologically or cytologically confirmed carcinoma of the breast.

          2. Documented progressive metastatic disease not amenable to curative surgery or
             radiotherapy.

          3. Age ≥18 and ≤70 years

          4. Patients must have prior treatments that have included capecitabine and both an
             anthracycline and a taxane drug and must be resistant to taxane therapy.

               1. Patients must have received a minimum cumulative dose of anthracycline (≥ 180
                  mg/m² of doxorubicin or ≥ 300 mg/m² of epirubicin) or be resistant to an
                  anthracycline and resistant to capecitabine and anti-hormonal therapy (ER+
                  patients).

               2. Resistance is defined as tumor progression while receiving treatment or
                  progression within 4 months of the last dose in the metastatic setting, or
                  recurrence within 12 months in the neoadjuvant or adjuvant setting.

          5. Post-menopausal ER+ and/or PR+ patients must have received at least two lines of
             prior anti-estrogen therapy, which includes an aromatase inhibitor.

          6. Her2+ patients must have received at least one Her2+ targeted regimen containing
             trastuzumab alone or with pertuzumab or with lapatinib. Patients who have been
             treated with trastuzumab or pertuzumab must have discontinued therapy at least 4
             weeks prior to study treatment.

          7. Prior radiation therapy must be completed at least 4 weeks before treatment.

          8. Measurable disease according to revised RECIST v.1.1 guidelines with at least one
             lesion deemed to be safely accessible for serial biopsy.

          9. ECOG &lt;2

         10. Adequate hematological function

               1. Absolute granulocyte count ≥ 1,500/mm3

               2. Platelet count ≥ 100,000/mm3

               3. PT/INR ≤ 1.5

               4. INR correctable to ≤ 1.5 or a PT/PTT correctable to normal limits. Patients
                  receiving anti-coagulation treatment with an agent such as warfarin or heparin
                  may be allowed to participate. For patients on warfarin, the INR should be
                  monitored weekly prior to any intervention to assure INR is stable. However,
                  heparin or warfarin must be withheld prior to biopsy such that the above
                  criteria are met.

               5. Hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dL (may be corrected by transfusion)

         11. Adequate organ function.

               1. Creatinine ≤ 1.5 mg/dL

               2. Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 times upper limit of normal (ULN)

               3. Alkaline phosphatase ≤ 2.5 times ULN (≤ 5 times normal if liver involvement)

               4. Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) or (SGOT) ≤ 5.0 times ULN

               5. Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or (SGPT) ≤ 5.0 times ULN

         12. EKG without clinically relevant abnormalities

         13. Pre-menopausal patients with child bearing potential must agree to use adequate
             contraception.

         14. Study specific informed consent in the native language of the subject.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Peritoneal carcinomatosis.

          2. Moderate to large ascites accumulation requiring or likely to require paracentesis.

          3. Clinical evidence or radiological evidence of brain metastasis or leptomeningeal
             involvement.

          4. Pulmonary lymphangitis or symptomatic pleural effusion (grade ≥ 2) that results in
             pulmonary dysfunction requiring active treatment.

          5. History of second primary malignancy, except: bilateral breast carcinoma, in situ
             carcinoma of the cervix, adequately treated non-melanomatous carcinoma of the skin,
             and other malignancy treated at least 5 years previously with no evidence of
             recurrence.

          6. Patients having received &gt; 3 regimens of prior chemotherapy for metastatic disease.

          7. History of severe hypersensitivity to monoclonal antibody drugs or any
             contraindication to any of the study drugs.

          8. Pregnant or breast feeding.

          9. Patients who have any serious, concurrent uncontrolled medical disorder.

         10. Prior hepatectomy, liver chemoembolization, liver cryoablation or radiofrequency
             ablated.

         11. Symptomatic pulmonary disease.

         12. Bevacizumab (Avastin®) within 3 weeks of accrual.

         13. Prior allogeneic bone marrow/stem cell or solid organ transplant.

         14. Chronic use (&gt; 2 weeks) of greater than physiologic doses of a corticosteroid agent
             (dose equivalent to &gt; 10 mg/day of prednisone) within 30 days of the first day of
             investigational product treatment.

             - Topical and inhaled corticosteroids are permitted

         15. Concomitant active autoimmune disease (e.g., rheumatoid arthritis, multiple
             sclerosis, autoimmune thyroid disease, uveitis).

         16. Prior experimental therapy or cancer vaccine treatment (e.g., dendritic cell therapy,
             heat shock vaccine).

         17. Current immunosuppressive therapy, including: cyclosporine, antithymocyte globulin,
             or tacrolimus within 1 month of study entry.

         18. History of blood transfusion reactions.

         19. Known allergy to bovine products.

         20. Know allergy to murine products.

         21. Progressive viral or bacterial infection

             - All infections must be resolved and the patient must remain afebrile for seven days
             without antibiotics prior to being placed into the study

         22. Cardiac disease of symptomatic nature or cardiac ejection fraction &lt; 45%.

         23. History of HIV positivity or AIDS.

         24. Psychiatric or addictive disorders or other condition that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, would preclude study participation.

         25. Concurrent medication known to interfere with platelet function or coagulation (e.g.,
             aspirin, ibuprofen, clopidogrel, or warfarin) unless such medications can be
             discontinued for an appropriate time period based on the drug half-life and known
             activity (e.g., aspirin for 7 days) prior to cryoablation procedure.

         26. Use of low molecular weight heparin preparations unless can be discontinued 8 hours
             prior to cryoablation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zivile Katiliene, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Immunovative Clinical Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Zivile Katiliene, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>1-760-444-9040</phone>
    <email>zivile@immunovative.co.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Thu Bui, B.S.</last_name>
    <phone>1-760-444-9040</phone>
    <email>thu@immunovative.co.il</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical Oncology Associates of San Diego</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92123</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kristen Rice, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>858-637-7888</phone>
      <email>krice@oncologysandiego.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kristen Rice, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James Lyon, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ara Klijian, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Har-Noy M, Slavin S. The anti-tumor effect of allogeneic bone marrow/stem cell transplant without graft vs. host disease toxicity and without a matched donor requirement? Med Hypotheses. 2007 Dec 1; [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>18054441</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Har-Noy M, Zeira M, Weiss L, Slavin S. Completely mismatched allogeneic CD3/CD28 cross-linked Th1 memory cells elicit anti-leukemia effects in unconditioned hosts without GVHD toxicity. Leuk Res. 2008 Jun 17; [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>18565579</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Har-Noy M, Zeira M, Weiss L, Fingerut E, Or R, Slavin S. Allogeneic CD3/CD28 cross-linked Th1 memory cells provide potent adjuvant effects for active immunotherapy of leukemia/lymphoma. Leuk Res. 2008 Sep 30; [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>18834631</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Janikashvili N, LaCasse CJ, Larmonier C, Trad M, Herrell A, Bustamante S, Bonnotte B, Har-Noy M, Larmonier N, Katsanis E. Allogeneic effector/memory Th-1 cells impair FoxP3+ regulatory T lymphocytes and synergize with chaperone-rich cell lysate vaccine to treat leukemia. Blood. 2011 Feb 3;117(5):1555-64. doi: 10.1182/blood-2010-06-288621. Epub 2010 Dec 1.</citation>
    <PMID>21123824</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>LaCasse CJ, Janikashvili N, Larmonier CB, Alizadeh D, Hanke N, Kartchner J, Situ E, Centuori S, Har-Noy M, Bonnotte B, Katsanis E, Larmonier N. Th-1 lymphocytes induce dendritic cell tumor killing activity by an IFN-γ-dependent mechanism. J Immunol. 2011 Dec 15;187(12):6310-7. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.1101812. Epub 2011 Nov 9.</citation>
    <PMID>22075702</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 17, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 17, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
