<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="104314">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02060461</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11-744</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02060461</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>LASIK Flap Thickness and Visual Outcomes Using the WaveLight FS200 Femtosecond Laser</brief_title>
  <acronym>FS200</acronym>
  <official_title>LASIK Flap Thickness and Visual Outcomes Using the WaveLight FS200 Femtosecond Laser: 3 Months Follow-up of Initial US Clinical Series</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Cleveland Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Cleveland Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Laser in situ keratomileusis (LASIK) is a safe and effective method for treating myopia,
      hyperopia and astigmatism. It is based on reshaping the cornea to focus the light closer to
      the macula. This method includes two steps:  a corneal flap creation, which can be performed
      by a mechanical microkeratome or a femtosecond laser, and the reshaping of the cornea by
      another laser (Excimer laser).

      The corneal flap creation is a crucial step. Indeed, creating a flap weakens a large part of
      the anterior stroma. The accuracy of the LASIK flap thickness is a key safety consideration
      to reduce the likelihood of ectasia following LASIK. Femtosecond laser technology has
      significantly improved the results of LASIK flaps, with increased predictability, lesser
      induction of optical aberrations, and a better healing profile compared to microkeratome
      flaps, with similar visual acuity results.

      Femtosecond Laser technology has been extensively investigated for the last ten years for
      use in refractive surgery. Actually, four femtosecond laser devices are available to perform
      LASIK flaps, each of them having clinical benefits and limitations. A fifth, designed by
      WaveLight AG/Alcon Laboratories, Inc. (Erlangen, Germany/Fort Worth, Texas), is approved for
      human use by the United States Food and Drug Administration and has been just released in
      the US market. Its unique technical aspects, optimized scanning algorithms, and
      user-friendly patient interface, have already provided a high reproducibility for cutting
      three-dimensional tissues structures in porcine corneas. Furthermore, the device has been
      shown to minimize opaque bubble layer (OBL) formation. This condition is very common and
      responsible for a delay in the treatment, since it can obstruct the eye tracker.

      The objective of this study is to evaluate the visual outcome, accuracy, predictability and
      complications of LASIK flap creation using the new Wavelight FS200 Femtosecond laser and
      compare these results to those obtained using current IntraLase FS60 Femtosecond laser. The
      primary outcome to be evaluated is the flap thickness accuracy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of visual outcome accuracy and LASIK Flap thickness</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Myopia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Femtosecond laser</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FS200 Laser</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Femtosecond laser</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients with ametropia (Spherical, spherocylindrical, presbyopic) suitable for
             treatment by LASIK, including different target refractions (Plano or Monovision).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients unsuitable for LASIK procedure because of an estimated residual stromal bed
             &lt; 300 microns after calculation of the ablation (Corneal thickness - flap thickness -
             simulated stromal ablation for the desired correction).

          -  Patients unsuitable for LASIK due suspicious topography for ectasia, form frust
             keratoconus or unstable ( more than 0.50 diopter change in sphere or cylinder in the
             last year) refraction.

          -  Patients with amblyopia or any eye disease that might limit the visual recovery.

          -  Patients younger than 18 years old.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William J Dupps, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Cleveland Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Laura Holody, COA</last_name>
    <phone>216 445-3762</phone>
    <email>holodyl@ccf.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>William J Dupps, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <phone>216-444-8396</phone>
      <email>duppsw@ccf.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Laura Holody, COA</last_name>
      <phone>216-445-3762</phone>
      <email>holodyl@ccf.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Wiliiam J Dupps, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 16, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Myopia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
