<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="68870">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01953640</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MC1351</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-01628</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>13-001296</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>MC1351</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01953640</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PROstate Cancer Medically Optimized Genome Enhanced ThErapy in Castrate Resistant Patients Receiving Abiraterone Acetate Therapy</brief_title>
  <acronym>PROMOTE</acronym>
  <official_title>MC1351: PROstate Cancer Medically Optimized Genome Enhanced ThErapy-I (PROMOTE-I)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research trial studies gene expression patterns in patients with metastatic prostate
      cancer receiving cytochrome P45017 (CYP-17) inhibition therapy with abiraterone acetate. Two
      biopsies will be performed from metastatic sites before and 12 weeks after initiating
      abiraterone acetate therapy. Metastatic tissue, blood, and urine will be analyzed at the
      deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) and RNA level to help doctors learn about changes that predict
      response/resistance tpo  treatments. An attempt will also be made to grow Xenografts from
      these biopsy tissues. The overall goal is to identify biomarkers related to therapy
      response/resistance and to study these biomarkers at a functional level in animal models for
      future drug development and patient care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine whether somatic tumor genome alterations identified in tumor tissue before
      or after the initiation of abiraterone acetate therapy are associated with a 12-week
      composite progression free survival (PFS) endpoint.

      II. To use tumor tissue obtained prior to the initiation of therapy and from the 12 week
      biopsy to develop tumor xenografts for mechanistic and functional studies which will
      determine whether mutations identified in the tumor genome are associated with response to
      drugs that target the observed mutated genes and/or associated pathways.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine whether somatic tumor genome alterations identified before or after
      initiating abiraterone acetate therapy are associated with overall survival.

      II. To determine whether somatic tumor genome alterations identified in tumor tissue before
      or after the initiation of abiraterone acetate therapy are associated with progression free
      survival (PFS).

      OUTLINE:

      Tissue, blood, and urine samples are collected at baseline and after 12-14 weeks of
      treatment and assessed for circulating tumor cells, genome-wide single-nucleotide
      polymorphism (SNP), and exome sequencing.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Gene association changes with progression free survival (PFS) at 12-14 weeks as defined by PCWG2 criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Upto 14 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS) after receiving abiraterone acetate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Kaplan-Meier curve and Cox proportional hazard regression model will be used to summarize overall survival until 5 years after initiating abiraterone acetate therapy in this trial.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PFS after receiving abiraterone acetate therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS) after receiving abiarterone acetate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Kaplan-Meier curve and Cox proportional hazard regression model will be used to summarize overall survival until 5 years after initiating abiraterone acetate therapy in this trial.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Novel somatic changes within gene and gene pathway that form the genomic signature</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 14 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor &quot;signatures&quot; by using immortalized xenograft models</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Descriptive statistics and graphical procedures will be used for summarizing &quot;tumor signature&quot; for xenograft model. The results of xenograft model will be correlated with PFS at 12-14 weeks.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating tumor cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Descriptive statistics and graphical procedures will be used for summarizing circulating tumor cells. The quantity of circulating tumor cells at baseline and after abiraterone therapy will be correlated with PFS at 12-14 weeks.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Adenocarcinoma of the Prostate</condition>
  <condition>Hormone Refractory Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Androgen Independent Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ancillary-correlative (gene expression with CYP-17 inhibition)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Tissue, blood,urine, CTC samples are collected at baseline and after 12-14 weeks of treatment and assessed for DNA/RNA sequencing.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ancillary-correlative (gene expression with CYP-17 inhibition)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>quality-of-life assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ancillary-correlative (gene expression with CYP-17 inhibition)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>quality of life assessment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Metastatic site tissue for DNA/RNA analysis; Germline (buffy coat) for DNA analysis; Tissue
      Immunohistochemistry; Serum and plasma for Proteomics;genomics and Metabolomics; Serum and
      plasma, Urine for proetin analysis Circulating Tumor Cell analysis
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Metastatic castrate resistant prostate cancer patients failing androgen deprivation
        therapy and prior to initiating any new form of treatments for castrate resitant stage.
        Medical Oncology and Urology clinics primarily deal with thsi population of patients
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histological diagnosis of adenocarcinoma of the prostate or documented history in
             medical records of having received treatment for prostate cancer diagnosis

          -  Metastatic disease on chest, abdominal, or pelvic computed tomography (CT) and/or
             bone scan amenable to biopsy

        The following laboratory values obtained 14 days prior to registration

          1. Hematology: HgB &gt;9.0 gm, ANC ≥ 1500 cells /L, and platelets ≥100,000µ/L

          2. Creatinine ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN).

          3. SGOT (AST) and SGPT (ALT) ≤ 1.5 x ULN.

          4. Castrate serum testosterone level (&lt; 50 ng/dL-or-&lt; 1.7 nmol/L).

        Progression while on or after androgen deprivation therapy defined as:

          1. Progressive measurable disease: at least a 20% increase in the sum of the longest
             diameters of measurable lesions over the smallest sum observed or the appearance of
             one or more new lesions as assessed by imaging  during hormone ablation treatment.
             Measurable lesions are nodal or visceral soft-tissue lesions with nodal lesions ≥ 20
             mm in diameter or visceral/soft-tissue lesions ≥ 10 mm in diameter (see Section
             11.0).

             OR

          2. Bone Scan Progression: appearance of 2 or more new lesions on bone scan during
             hormone ablation treatment.

             OR

          3. Increasing serum PSA level: Two consecutive increases in PSA levels documented over a
             previous reference value obtained at least one week apart are required. If the third
             PSA value is less than the second, an additional fourth test to confirm a rising PSA
             is acceptable. A minimum starting value of 2.0 ng/mL is required for study
             enrollment.

             NOTE: Androgen deprivation therapy may have included either medical or surgical
             castration.

               -  ≥14 days has passed since completing radiotherapy (exception for radiotherapy: ≥
                  7 days since completing a single fraction of ≤ 800 cGy to a restricted field or
                  limited-field radiotherapy to non-marrow bearing area such as an extremity or
                  orbit) at the time of registration.

               -  Patients who may have received systemic chemotherapy or any novel therapeutic
                  CYP-17 inhibitor and/or novel AR inhibitor agents previously for prostate cancer
                  should have received the last dose of the previously administered systemic
                  therapy  ≥12 months from the date of registration.

               -  Provide informed written consent.

               -  Has recovered from any other therapy-related toxicity to ≤ grade 2, (except
                  alopecia, anemia and any signs or symptoms of androgen deprivation therapy).

               -  Willing to provide tissue and blood samples for correlative research purposes
                  (see Section 6.2, 14.1, and 17.1 of the protocol)

               -  ECOG Performance Status (PS) 0, 1 or 2 (Appendix I).

               -  Patient is considered a candidate for initiating abiraterone acetate and
                  prednisone after failure of hormonal therapy and has no contra-indications to
                  starting this combination Abiraterone acetate and prednisone after failure of
                  hormonal therapy and has no contra-indication to starting this combination as
                  standard of care.

               -  Patients have stopped any antiandrogen therapy (including bicalutamide) ≤4 weeks
                  prior to first dose of study drug. In addition any other therapies for prostate
                  cancer, other than GnRH analogue therapy, such as progesterone,
                  medroxyprogesterone, progestins (megesterol), or 5-alpha reductase inhibitors
                  (eg, finasteride or dutasteride), must be discontinued ≤2 weeks before the first
                  dose of study drug.

             Exclusion Criteria:

               -  Use of any of these therapies =&lt; 12 months prior to registration:

                    -  Use of any of the standard therapies for castrate resistant prostate cancer
                       (CRPC) stage =&lt;12 months prior to registration; NOTE: See below for further
                       exclusion details of specific standard therapies

                         -  Initiation of full dose chemotherapy with docetaxel for CRPC stage
                            =&lt;12 months prior to registration is an exclusion criterion

                            *** Note: Docetaxel for hormone sensitive prostate cancer is not an
                            exclusion criterion

                         -  Use of radium-223 for CRPC stage is an exclusion criteria

                         -  Use of Provenge vaccine for CRPC =&lt; 2 months prior to registration is
                            an exclusion criterion

                            *** Note: less than 3 doses of Provenge vaccine =&lt; 12 months prior to
                            registration for CRPC is not an exclusion criterion

                         -  Initiation of full dose chemotherapy with mitoxantrone for CRPC stage
                            with-in the previous 12 months is an exclusion criterion

                         -  Use of cabazitaxel chemotherapy =&lt;12 months prior to registration is
                            an exclusion criterion

                            *** Note: initiation of full dose chemotherapy with cabazitaxel for
                            CRPC stage with-in the previous 12 months is an exclusion criterion

                         -  Use of ketoconazole with steroids =&lt;12 months prior to registration
                            for CRPC stage

                            *** Note: ketoconazole therapy taken for a time period of =&lt;12 weeks
                            in the 12 month period prior to registration is not an exclusion
                            criterion

                         -  Use of enzalutamide for CRPC stage =&lt;12 months prior to registration
                            is an exclusion criteria use of any experimental or standard of care
                            CYP-17 inhibitors =&lt;12 months prior to registration is an exclusion
                            criteria *** Note: standard of care CRPC therapy with a CYP-17
                            inhibitor =&lt; 7 days prior to registration is not an exclusion
                            criterion; if taken for 8 days or more it will be counted as an
                            exclusion criterion

               -  Receiving any intermittent hormonal treatment gonadotropin-releasing hormone
                  (GnRH) analogues and has not yet achieved sub-castrate levels of testosterone (&lt;
                  50 ng/dl or &lt; 1.7 mmol/L)

               -  History of or current documented brain metastasis or carcinomatous meningitis,
                  treated or untreated; Note: brain imaging for asymptomatic patients is not
                  required

               -  Current symptomatic cord compression requiring surgery or radiation therapy

                    -  Note: once successfully treated and there has been no progression, patients
                       are eligible for the study

               -  Active second malignancy (except non-melanomatous skin or superficial bladder
                  cancer) defined as requiring anticancer therapy or at high risk of recurrence
                  during the study

               -  Uncontrolled medical conditions such as heart failure, myocardial infarction,
                  uncontrolled hypertension, disseminated on-going coagulopathy, stroke or
                  treatment of a major active infection =&lt; 3 months of registration, as well as
                  any significant concurrent medical illness that in the opinion of the
                  Investigator would preclude protocol therapy

               -  Planned concomitant participation in another clinical trial of an experimental
                  agent, vaccine, or device

                    -  Note: concomitant participation in observational studies is acceptable

               -  Patients with a global or severe deterioration of health status such that it
                  requires discontinuation of standard of care treatments for CRPC stage without
                  evidence of disease progression =&lt; 12 weeks prior to registration
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Manish Kohli</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Arizona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85259</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alan H. Bryce</last_name>
      <phone>507-538-7623</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alan H. Bryce</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32224-9980</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Winston W. Tan</last_name>
      <phone>507-538-7623</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Winston W. Tan</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Manish Kohli</last_name>
      <phone>507-538-7623</phone>
      <email>kohli.manish@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Manish Kohli</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 13, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 26, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Manish Kohli, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
