<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="40071">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01754623</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MCC-16932</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01754623</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>GTX-RT in Borderline Resectable Pancreatic Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Validation of a Radiation Response Signature in Borderline Resectable Pancreatic Cancer Patients Treated With Induction Chemotherapy Followed by Stereotactic Body Radiation Therapy (SBRT)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to find out if a program of intensive chemotherapy with
      gemcitabine, docetaxel and capecitabine followed by an advanced form of focused radiation
      aimed at participant's tumor followed by more chemotherapy can increase the chances that the
      participant's pancreatic tumor can be removed completely.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Investigators plan to conduct a prospective pilot phase II trial of GTX-SBRT as neoadjuvant
      treatment of borderline resectable pancreatic cancer. After informed consent, pretreatment
      pancreatic tumor tissues will be collected and immediately frozen at the time of staging
      endoscopic ultrasound (EUS). Ribonucleic acid (RNA) will be extracted from tumor specimens
      and run on microarray analysis to determine radiosensitivity index score. Borderline
      resectable (BR) patients will be treated with 3 cycles of GTX chemotherapy followed by SBRT.
      They will be restaged and evaluated for resectability 3 to 4 weeks later. Non-metastatic
      patients who are deemed resectable after neoadjuvant therapy will be taken to surgery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Margin-negative (R0) Resection Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary endpoint is correlation of a radiosensitivity index score derived from the microarray analysis and pathologic response on surgical specimens. Tumor regression Rating: R0 (Complete Response); R1 (Moderate Response); R2 (Minimal Response); R3 (No Response).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS) Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>OS will be calculated from date of enrollment to date of death from any cause. Investigators will also compare OS between resected and non-resected patients. Comparative analysis will be performed by Kaplan-Meier analysis and 2-sided log-rank test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Progression-Free Survival (PFS) PFS is defined as the duration of time from enrollment to time of death or progression of disease, whichever occurs first. Investigators will also compare PFS between resected and non-resected patients. Comparative analysis will be performed by Kaplan-Meier analysis and 2-sided log-rank test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Chemotherapy Followed by Radiation Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Gemcitabine, Taxotere, Xeloda (GTX): 21 day cycle x 3 Gemcitabine 750mg/m^2 on days 4 and 11 Taxotere® (docetaxel) 30 mg/m^2 on days 4 and 11 Xeloda® (capecitabine) 750 mg/m^2 on days 1-14 Radiation: stereotactic body radiation therapy stereotactic body radiation therapy (SBRT).
After radiation, participants will be re-evaluated for surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>capecitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Treatment will begin with the first round of chemotherapy. Each round of chemotherapy will take 21 days. Each round or cycle will start with participants taking capecitabine pills. Participants will take tablets of capecitabine (Xeloda®) twice per day for 14 days followed by 7 days without capecitabine.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chemotherapy Followed by Radiation Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Xeloda®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>gemcitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>On the fourth day of the cycle, participants will be treated with gemcitabine and docetaxel. First, this will consist of placing gemcitabine (Gemzar®) in a bag of fluid and giving it by vein over 30 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chemotherapy Followed by Radiation Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Gemzar®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>docetaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>On the fourth day of the cycle, participants will be treated with gemcitabine and docetaxel. After the gemcitabine, participants will receive docetaxel (Taxotere®) in a bag of fluid over 1 hour.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chemotherapy Followed by Radiation Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Taxotere®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>stereotactic body radiation therapy (SBRT)</intervention_name>
    <description>30/40 Gy to pancreatic tumor/area of borderline resectability</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chemotherapy Followed by Radiation Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SBRT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>restaging review after radiation</intervention_name>
    <description>After radiation, participants will be re-evaluated for surgery. Patients who have Complete Response (CR), Partial Response (PR) or stable disease (SD) will proceed with surgical exploration and resection provided they are suitable fit for surgery in the judgment of the surgical oncologist. Patients who have local progression on imaging scan will be offered conventional 5-Fluorouracil based intensity-modulated radiation therapy (IMRT).  If no surgery: then chemotherapy.  If surgery: chemotherapy will be given based on response.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chemotherapy Followed by Radiation Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>Non-metastatic patients who are deemed resectable after neoadjuvant therapy will be taken to surgery. After surgery, chemotherapy will be given based on response.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chemotherapy Followed by Radiation Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>5-Fluorouracil</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients who have local progression on imaging scan will be offered conventional 5-Fluorouracil based intensity-modulated radiation therapy (IMRT).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chemotherapy Followed by Radiation Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histologically or cytologically confirmed pancreatic
             adenocarcinoma that is borderline resectable disease. Borderline resectable lesions
             are defined as:

               -  circumferential tumor abutment with the superior mesenteric vein (SMV) or portal
                  vein (PV) or SMV/PV confluence over &lt;/= 180°

               -  circumferential tumor abutment with the superior mesenteric artery (SMA) over
                  &lt;/= 180°

               -  Short segment encasement (360°) of the PV or SMV that is amenable to partial
                  vein resection and reconstruction

               -  encasement of the gastroduodenal artery up to the origin of the hepatic artery

          -  Patients must have measurable disease

          -  No previous chemotherapy or radiation to the pancreas

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status &lt;/= 2 (Karnofsky &gt;/=
             60%)

          -  Patients must have normal organ and marrow function as defined below:

               -  leukocytes &gt;/= 3,000/μL

               -  absolute neutrophil count &gt;/= 1,000/ μL

               -  platelets &gt;/= 100,000/ μL

               -  creatinine within normal institutional limits (ULN)

               -  total bilirubin will allow for 2x the upper limit of the institution. Patients
                  may have biliary stents or drains to lower total bilirubin to this range.

          -  Has a negative serum or urine pregnancy test within 7 days prior to initiation of
             therapy (female patients of childbearing potential). Postmenopausal women must have
             been amenorrheic for at least 12 months to be considered of non-childbearing
             potential. Patients will agree to continue contraception for 30 days from the date of
             the last study drug administration.

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with metastatic disease are ineligible.

          -  Patients who have had prior chemotherapy for pancreatic adenocarcinoma

          -  Patients who have received prior radiation to an abdominal site are not eligible.

          -  Patients with peripheral neuropathy &gt;/= grade 2

          -  Patients with a history of severe hypersensitivity reaction to Taxotere (docetaxel),
             other drugs formulated with polysorbate 80, gemcitabine, or capecitabine

          -  Patients may not be receiving any other investigational agents.

          -  ECOG Performance Status 3-4

          -  Pregnant or breast-feeding women are excluded from this study because
             gemcitabine,capecitabine, and docetaxel are Class D agents with the potential for
             teratogenic or abortifacient effects.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, symptomatic
             congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, or
             psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study
             requirements

          -  Patients must not have any comorbid inflammatory conditions of the bowel such as
             Crohn's Disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ravi Shridhar, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Helen Jump</last_name>
      <phone>813-745-4834</phone>
      <email>helen.jump@moffitt.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ravi Shridhar, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gregory Springett, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sarah Hoffe, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pamela Hodul, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jason Klapman, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Shivakumar Vignesh, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amit Mahipal, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.moffitt.org/research--clinical-trials/clinical-trials</url>
    <description>Moffitt Cancer Center Clinical Trials website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 18, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pancreas</keyword>
  <keyword>Pancreatic</keyword>
  <keyword>Neoplasms</keyword>
  <keyword>Stereotactic</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiosurgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Borderline</keyword>
  <keyword>Resectable</keyword>
  <keyword>Gastrointestinal</keyword>
  <keyword>Gemcitabine</keyword>
  <keyword>Capecitabine</keyword>
  <keyword>Fluorouracil</keyword>
  <keyword>Docetaxel</keyword>
  <keyword>SBRT</keyword>
  <keyword>GTX Chemotherapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fluorouracil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gemcitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Capecitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
