<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="125904">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01701674</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MCC-17057</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CA184-213</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01701674</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ipilimumab With Lymphodepletion Plus Adoptive Cell Transfer and High Dose IL-2 in Melanoma Mets Pts</brief_title>
  <official_title>Co-stimulation With Ipilimumab to Enhance Lymphodepletion Plus Adoptive Cell Transfer and High Dose IL-2 in Patients With Metastatic Melanoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bristol-Myers Squibb</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators want to study the safety, side effects, and benefits of TILs when they are
      given with the drug ipilimumab. Ipilimumab is a type of immunotherapy - a drug that is used
      to boost the ability of the immune system to fight cancer, infection, and other diseases.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and Feasibility of Administering Ipilimumab with adoptive cell transfer (ACT) Using TIL</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The data analysis will mainly be descriptive. All study results will be preliminary and of exploratory in nature due to the pilot status and small sample size of the trial. Feasibility is defined as the ability to deliver at least 50% (i.e., two out of four) of the planned doses of ipilimumab and successfully treat at least 60% (i.e., ≥6/10) of the patients with TIL. All patients will be evaluable for toxicity from the time of their first protocol treatment. Toxicity will be reported by type and severity according to the National Cancer Institute Common Toxicity Criteria (NCI CTC) version 4.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Response Rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall response (OR) is defined as the patient being alive at week 6, confirmed at week 12 and tumor size evaluated at both times using the Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1 criteria to be a complete response (CR) or partial response (PR). Evaluations will be made by computed tomography (CT) scan approximately 6 weeks after the cell infusion, then confirmed by CT scanning approximately 12 weeks after the cell infusion, and by clinical evaluation during the first 12 weeks. The overall response (CR+PR) rate will be summarized using both a point estimate and its exact confidence interval based on the binomial distribution.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Progression-free survival (PFS), defined as the time from study entry to disease progression, relapse or death due to any cause, whichever is earlier, will be summarized with the Kaplan-Meier curve. Confidence intervals for the median and survival rates at different time points will be constructed if needed and appropriate. This secondary endpoint will be reported descriptively.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Combination Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The combination of ipilimumab followed by lymphodepletion with chemotherapy, TIL infusion, and high dose IL-2.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ipilimumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Pre-treatment with ipilimumab (cycle 1): Before the participant's tumor sample is taken to send to the lab for growing the TILs, they will start their first cycle of ipilimumab. This drug is given as an intravenous infusion (through a vein) over a period of about 90 minutes (an hour and a half). Cycle 2 of ipilimumab: About a week after the sample of the participant's tumor was collected for TIL growth (and 3 weeks after their first cycle of ipilimumab), participant's will have their second cycle of ipilimumab. This will be another IV infusion, lasting about 90 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combination Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Yervoy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tumor Infiltrating Lymphocytes (TIL)</intervention_name>
    <description>Tumor sample for TIL growth in the lab: About 2 weeks after the participant's first cycle of ipilimumab, a sample of their tumor will be collected and sent to the lab for TIL growth. Growing the TILs takes about 6 weeks. If their sample has grown enough TIL cells, participants will continue with the next part of the study. Depending on how long the TILs take to grow in the lab, they may need to repeat some of their laboratory and imaging tests (blood draws, X-rays, and CT or magnetic resonance imaging [MRI] scans). TIL Infusion (inpatient): After completing lymphodepletion, participants will be admitted back into the hospital for IV infusion of the TIL cells.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combination Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Administration of Lymphodepletion</intervention_name>
    <description>Lymphodepletion (inpatient hospital stay for about 2 days plus outpatient drug dosing for 5 days): About 4 weeks after their second cycle of ipilimumab, participants will be admitted to the hospital for their first two days of receiving the chemotherapy drug, cyclophosphamide. This drug will be given as an intravenous (IV, meaning through the vein) infusion. After 2 days of receiving cyclophosphamide, if their study doctor thinks that they are well enough, you will be discharged from the hospital and will return for the next 5 days in a row for outpatient IV infusions of the second lymphodepletion chemotherapy, fludarabine.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combination Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide as Part of Lymphodepletion</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Combination Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cytoxan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine as Part of Lymphodepletion</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Combination Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fludara</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High Dose IL-2</intervention_name>
    <description>High dose IL-2 (continued inpatient): Participants will remain in the hospital following TIL infusion for receiving high dose IL-2 and recovery. The IL-2 will be given three times per day for about 3-5 days as an IV bolus (meaning through the vein, more quickly than other infusions - in about 15 minutes each dose). Participants will remain in the hospital for approximately 7-14 days until they have recovered from the IL-2 treatments.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combination Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Interleukin-2</other_name>
    <other_name>Aldesleukin</other_name>
    <other_name>Proleukin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Adoptive Cell Therapy with TIL</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Combination Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ACT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have unresectable metastatic stage IV melanoma or stage III intransit
             or regional nodal disease, and in the opinion of the institutional PI is an
             acceptable candidate for ACT with high dose IL-2

          -  Residual measurable disease after resection of target lesion(s) for TIL growth

          -  Tumor may have a B-RAF V600 mutation or be BRAF wild type, and patients must not have
             been previously treated with ipilimumab

          -  Clinical performance status of Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) 0 - 1. ECOG
             performance status of 0-1 will be inferred if the patient's level of energy is ≥ 50%
             of baseline.

          -  May have been previously treated for metastatic disease, or may have not had prior
             systemic treatment. Patients with a V600 BRAF mutated tumor may have previously
             received a prior BRAF inhibitor.

          -  Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) must have a negative serum pregnancy test
             within 7 days of screening.

          -  Adequate renal, hepatic and hematologic function, including creatinine of less than
             or equal to 1.7 gm/dL, total bilirubin less than or equal to 2.0 mg/dL, except in
             patients with Gilbert's Syndrome who must have a total bilirubin less than 3.0 mg/dL,
             aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine transaminase (ALT) of less than 3 X
             institutional upper limit of normal, hemoglobin of 8 gm/dL or more, white blood count
             (WBC) of 3000 per mcL and total granulocytes of 1000 per mcL or more, and platelets
             of 100,000 per mcL or more.

          -  Must have a positive screening Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) antibody titre on screening
             test

          -  Patients with antibiotic allergies per se are not excluded; although the production
             of TIL for adoptive transfer includes antibiotics, extensive washing after harvest
             will minimize systemic exposure to antibiotics.

          -  At screening, patients with ≤ 3 untreated CNS metastases may be included provided
             none of the untreated lesions are &gt; 1 cm in greatest dimension, and there is no
             peri-tumoral edema present on brain imaging (MRI or CT if MRI is contraindicated).

          -  At screening, patients with central nervous system (CNS) metastases treated with
             either surgical resection and/or radiation therapy may be included. Patients may be
             included if the largest lesion is ≤ 1 cm, and there is no evidence of progressive CNS
             disease on brain imaging at least 28 days after treatment.

          -  At screening, patients may be included if the largest lesion is &gt; 1 cm or &gt; 3 in
             number, and there is no evidence of progressive CNS disease on brain imaging at least
             90 days after treatment with surgery and/or radiation therapy.

          -  No evidence of ongoing cardiac dysrhythmia ≥ grade 2 (NCI Common Terminology Criteria
             for Adverse Events [CTCAE], v4.0)

          -  All laboratory and imaging studies must be completed and satisfactory within 30 days
             of signing the consent document, with the exceptions of: negative serum pregnancy
             test for women of child-bearing potential which must be negative within 7 days of
             screening, human leukocyte antigen (HLA) typing which will not be repeated if
             performed previously, and pulmonary function tests (PFTs)/cardiac stress tests whose
             results are valid for 6 months if performed previously.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with active systemic infections requiring intravenous antibiotics,
             coagulation disorders or other major medical illness of the cardiovascular,
             respiratory or immune system, which in the opinion of the principal investigator (PI)
             or treating coinvestigator is not acceptable risk for ACT, are excluded.

          -  Patients testing positive for HIV titre, Hepatitis B surface antigen, Hepatitis B
             core antibody, Hepatitis C antibody, Human T-Lymphotropic Virus (HTLV) I or II
             antibody, or both Rapid. Plasma Reagin (RPR) and fluorescent treponemal antibodies
             (FTA) positive are excluded.

          -  Pregnant or nursing

          -  Patients needing chronic, immunosuppressive systemic steroids are excluded

          -  History of autoimmune disease that require immunosuppressive medications at the time
             of screening

          -  Presence of a significant psychiatric disease, which in the opinion of the principal
             investigator or his designee, would prevent adequate informed consent or render
             immunotherapy unsafe or contraindicated

          -  Patients with &gt; 3 untreated CNS metastases or evidence of peri-tumoral edema

          -  Patients with ≤ 3 untreated CNS metastases but with at least one lesion &gt;1 cm or
             peri-tumoral edema

          -  Patients with invasive malignancy other than melanoma at the time of enrollment and
             within 2 years prior to the first TIL administration are excluded, except for
             adequately treated (with curative intent) basal or squamous cell carcinoma, in situ
             carcinoma of the cervix, in situ ductal adenocarcinoma of the breast, in situ
             prostate cancer, or limited stage bladder cancer or other cancers from which the
             patient has been disease-free for at least 2 years.

          -  Patients with treated CNS metastases &gt; 1 cm or &gt; 3 in number will be excluded if
             there is evidence of progressive CNS disease on brain imaging at least 90 days after
             treatment with surgery and/or radiation therapy.

          -  Unable to comprehend and give informed consent

          -  Male patients with WOCBP partners who do not agree to use two FDA-accepted forms of
             contraception during sexual intercourse with women of child-bearing potential from
             the start of ipilimumab and up to at least 6 months after ACT

          -  WOCBP who do not agree to use 2 FDA forms of contraception during sexual intercourse
             from the start of ipilimumab and up to at least 6 months after ACT

          -  Patients who have received ipilimumab in the past
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amod Sarnaik, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>H. Lee Moffit Cancer Center and Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Erica Royster</last_name>
      <phone>813-745-4279</phone>
      <email>erica.royster@moffitt.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amod Sarnaik, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Heather Bridge, PA-C</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ronald DeConti, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Geoffrey Gibney, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>William Janssen, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ragini Kudchadkar, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vernon Sondak, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Melissa Thebeau, ARNP</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jeffrey Weber, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jonathan Zager, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.moffitt.org/research--clinical-trials/clinical-trials</url>
    <description>Moffitt Cancer Center Clinical Trials website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 19, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 3, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>skin cancer</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine monophosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Interleukin-2</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
