<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="112573">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01832766</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>05-0359</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01832766</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of Cannabis Use in People With Schizophrenia on Clinical, Neuropsychological and Physiological Phenotypes</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effects of Cannabis Use in People With Schizophrenia on Clinical, Neuropsychological and Physiological Phenotypes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Alliance for Research on Schizophrenia and Depression</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Data and Safety Monitoring Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Approximately 25% of people with schizophrenia abuse marijuana.  These people may be using
      marijuana to self-medicate symptoms such as hallucinations (hearing or seeing things that
      are not heard or seen by others) or delusions (false beliefs i.e. people are harassing or
      persecuting them) or the depressed and anxious feelings brought on by these symptoms.
      Currently, it is unknown whether marijuana makes schizophrenia better or worse.  Marijuana
      intoxication in people without schizophrenia generally causes decreased recall of words, may
      decrease reaction time and decrease inhibition.  Additionally, marijuana may cause
      distractibility as demonstrated by difficulty keeping their eyes on a moving target and
      difficulty inhibiting their response to repetitive tones.  However, marijuana may have
      different effects in schizophrenia.  Receptors for cannabis (marijuana) are concentrated in
      the brain and maladjustment of the cannabinoid system may be associated with the difficulty
      in thinking found in schizophrenia.  The proposed research project examines if clinical
      symptoms, learning, memory, inhibition and distractibility are improved or made worse by the
      acute ingestion of tetrahydrocannabinol (THC).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The trial will be a double two period (visit) blind cross-over trial with one arm dronabinol
      10 mg one arm a placebo control.  The order of doses and placebo will be randomized with the
      restriction that half of the subjects will receive each order.    This counterbalances
      possible visit effects or learning effects associated with the visits.  The use of an oral
      cannabis analog is not equivalent to smoking as the onset of action is slower.  This is why
      people who use dronabinol for chronic pain prefer to smoke cannabis.  There is no &quot;high&quot;
      associated with dronabinol.  However, the active ingredients are the same, THC, which will
      have similar effects on the cannabinoid 1 receptor.  Ethically, we did not feel we could ask
      people to smoke cannabis on one day of study. Subjects will present to the GCRC at 5:00 p.m.
       They will abstain from use of cannabis overnight.  The following morning, at 8:00 a.m., the
      subject will provide a urine sample for a toxicology screen and a blood sample for
      quantitative THC levels.  They will then be administered either 10 mg of dronabinol or an
      identical placebo on an alternate day.  The subject will then have a baseline assessment of
      clinical positive and negative symptoms measured by the Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale
      (BPRS).  The majority (70-90%) of people with schizophrenia smoke cigarettes.  Thus, it is
      likely that in this population that smokes cannabis, 100% will also be cigarette smokers.
      The effects of nicotine via cigarette smoking on the endophenotypes studied is an acute
      effect, with a peak at about 5 minutes.  To preclude nicotine effects on endophenotypes, we
      have the patient not smoke for 20 minutes prior to and during testing.  Nicotine is quickly
      removed from the body when inhaled and its effects wear off within 20 minutes.  Two hours
      after administration, the subject will perform the following tests:  P50 auditory evoked
      potential- the recording will consist of the presentation of 5 sets of 16 click pairs with
      an intrapair interval of 500 ms heard through headphones with a 3-minute rest between sets.
      Brain wave responses will be recorded; neurocognitive assessment-the California Verbal
      Learning Test will measure verbal memory and the Stroop will measure inhibition; clinical
      symptom assessment- The BPRS will again be administered measure positive and negative
      symptoms; and a blood sample will be collected for quantitative THC levels.  They will then
      be escorted by a Clinical Research Center nurse over to a laboratory at Colorado Psychiatric
      Hospital to perform smooth pursuit eye movements  In performing smooth pursuit eye
      movements, they will watch a dot moving across a computer screen while infrared sensors that
      are placed just in front of their eyes record their eye movements.  Each subject performs 3
      trials of one minute each, with 2 minutes rest between each recording.  Subjects will be
      reassessed by the BPRS for drug exacerbation of symptoms, will have vitals, will be checked
      for adverse effects, will perform a sobriety test (the standard test used in roadside
      testing i.e. walking a straight line and finger to nose testing) which will be assessed by
      Dr. Olincy, who is experienced in assessing sobriety, to assure that the patient is not
      acutely intoxicated and able to perform normal functions that require coordination.  If they
      fail the sobriety test, they will be asked to remain in the (General Clinical Research
      Center (GCRC) until they can pass the sobriety test.  Otherwise, they will then will be
      discharged at 5:00 p.m.  Transportation to and from the GCRC will be by a provided cab
      service.  Subjects will be randomized in blocks of 4 or 6 to the order in which they receive
      placebo or dronabinol.  The interval between the two days of testing will be 1 week.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Unable to find subjects with schizophrenia that were using only cannabis
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>June 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>P50 auditory evoked potential</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours after drug administration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>electrophysiological measure of ability to filter extraneous stimuli</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>California Verbal Learning Test</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours after drug administration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>ability to remember al list of words</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>at 1 hour and 8 hours after drug administration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measures psychiatric symptoms and can be subdivided in to positive and negative subscales</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">13</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>dronabinol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>dronabinol 10 mg one capsule by mouth at 8:00 a.m.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>sugar pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>one capsule given by mouth at 8:00 a.m.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dronabinol</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>dronabinol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>sugar pill</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Marinol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and females

          -  18 and 50 years of age

          -  Diagnosis of schizophrenia

          -  Chronic cannabis users who have used for at least 1 year

          -  Using cannabis at least once weekly

          -  Currently being treated with antipsychotic medication

          -  Must be on a the same dose of antipsychotic medication for at least 3 months.

          -  Females of childbearing potential must use an adequate form of birth control while
             participating.

          -  Participants will be required to have blood pressures greater than 90/60 and less
             than 140/90.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Use of illicit drugs other than cannabis

          -  Any psychiatric hospitalizations within 3 months

          -  pregnancy in females

          -  taking clozapine
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lynn Johnson, Pharm D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Denver</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Denver</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 11, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 25, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>schizophrenia</keyword>
  <keyword>dronabinol</keyword>
  <keyword>P50</keyword>
  <keyword>cannabis</keyword>
  <keyword>memory</keyword>
  <keyword>symptoms</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Marijuana Abuse</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Tetrahydrocannabinol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
