<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="78809">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01751646</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ATN 109</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01751646</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Vitamin D Absorption in HIV Infected Young Adults Being Treated With Tenofovir Containing cART</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial of the Safety and Effectiveness of Vitamin D3 50,000 IU Every 4 Weeks to Increase Bone Mineral Density and Decrease Tenofovir-Induced Hyperparathyroidism in Youth With HIV Infection Being Treated With Tenofovir-Containing Combination Antiretroviral Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a 96 week randomized double-blind, placebo-controlled prospective cohort study of
      adolescents and young adults with HIV infection in the ATN who are currently being treated
      with cART  that includes TDF as one component of the regimen that includes at least three
      Food and Drug Administration (FDA)-approved ARVs for at least 180 days.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a 96 week randomized double-blind, placebo-controlled prospective cohort study of
      adolescents and young adults with HIV infection in the ATN who are currently being treated
      with cART  that includes TDF as one component of the regimen that includes at least three
      Food and Drug Administration (FDA)-approved ARVs for at least 180 days. Subjects must have
      at least one documented viral load that is below 200 copies/mL that is collected following
      initiation of TDF containing cART and greater than 90 days prior to screening; no viral load
      above 200 copies/mL if measured within the 90 days prior to screening; and a viral load
      obtained at screening that is below 200 copies/mL.

      Treatment assignments will be balanced by subject sex at birth, age (&lt;20 years vs. &gt;=20
      years), and race (African American vs. other). Enrolled subjects will be randomized to
      receive vitamin D3 50000 IU or matching placebo, given orally every four weeks by DOT. In
      addition to the randomized study agent, all subjects will receive a MVI to be taken orally
      once daily. This &quot;standard&quot; MVI will contain ingredients not to exceed 600 IU of vitamin D3
      and 200 mg Ca.

      DXA measurement of whole-body BMC, and BMD at spine and hip,   will be performed at baseline
      and study weeks 24, 48, and 96. Blood and urine sampling to assess the Ca-PO4 axis,
      PTH-FGF23-vitamin D signaling, bone turnover, and renal glomerular and tubular function will
      occur at baseline and study weeks 12, 24, 48, and 96. Blood samples to measure Gluc
      homeostasis will be drawn at baseline and weeks 48 and 96, and will be run by batch
      analysis.

      Safety, measured by SCa and SCr, will be monitored by subject's record review at study sites
      since these labs will generally be measured as a part of routine clinical care.  The ATN109
      study will use the SCa and SCr values obtained within 10 weeks at the time of the visit
      beginning at the baseline visit. If these evaluations were not performed within the prior 10
      weeks they will be drawn at the time of the visit. Viral load and CD4 cell count results
      will be recorded for the ATN109 study at screening, baseline and study weeks 12, 24, 48, and
      96 provided the evaluations were done within the protocol specified timeframe. If the
      evaluations are not performed within the protocol specified timeframes they will be drawn at
      the time of the visit (see section 7.0 for additional details).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the percent change from baseline to week 96 in DXA-measured BMD</measure>
    <time_frame>96 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To compare the percent change from baseline to week 96 in DXA-measured BMD at the spine for the randomized study groups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>BMC of whole body and BMD of spine, total hip, and femoral neck - compare at different timepoints</measure>
    <time_frame>96 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>For BMC of whole body and BMD of spine, total hip, and femoral neck, compare change from baseline to week 24, change from baseline to week 48, and change from baseline to week 96 by randomized study group, with analyses using measured BMC/BMD and Z-scores;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the time course of change in SCa, UCa / UCr, SPO4, TRP, 25-OHD, 1,25-OHD, free 1,25-OHD index, PTH, FGF23, BAP, OC, and CTX at various timepoints</measure>
    <time_frame>96 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To compare  the time course of change from baseline to weeks 12, 24  48, and 96, and the overall change from baseline to week 48 and baseline to week 96, in SCa, UCa / UCr, SPO4, TRP, 25-OHD, 1,25-OHD, free 1,25-OHD index, PTH, FGF23, BAP, OC, and CTX;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess renal glomerular safety by measuring change in SCr and estimated GFR at various timepoints</measure>
    <time_frame>96 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess renal glomerular safety by measuring change in SCr and estimated GFR from baseline to weeks 12, 24 48, and 96 by randomized study group;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess renal tubular function by measuring change in TRP, UGluc, URBP/UCr ratio, UB2MG, UProt/ UCr ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>96 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess renal tubular function by measuring change in TRP, UGluc, URBP/UCr ratio, UB2MG, UProt/ UCr ratio by randomized study group;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure change from baseline to week 48 and change from baseline to week 96 in Gluc homeostasis</measure>
    <time_frame>96 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To measure change from baseline to week 48 and change from baseline to week 96 in Gluc homeostasis (fasting insulin and Gluc and calculated HOMA-IR and their relationship to changes in 25-OHD, 1,25-OHD, and free 1,25-OHD index for the randomized study groups and for different attained vitamin D serum concentrations;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare 25-OHD serum concentrations by randomized study group at various timepoints</measure>
    <time_frame>96 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To compare 25-OHD serum concentrations by randomized study group at all-time points and change from baseline to week 48 and 96;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the mean 25-OHD serum concentration and to measure the effect of concurrent treatment with EFV or ritonavir on serum 25-OHD concentrations and changes during the study</measure>
    <time_frame>96 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To compare the mean 25-OHD serum concentration by randomized study group and to measure the effect of concurrent treatment with EFV or ritonavir on serum 25-OHD concentrations and changes during the study;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure the relationship of 25-OHD, 1,25-OHD, and free 1, 25-OHD serum concentrations BMD/BMC, markers of Ca-PO4-FGF23 activity, markers of bone turnover, renal glomerular and tubular toxicity, and Gluc homeostasis at various timepoints</measure>
    <time_frame>96 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To measure the relationship of 25-OHD, 1,25-OHD, and free 1, 25-OHD serum concentrations to baseline and change from baseline to week 24, baseline to week 48, and baseline to 96 in  BMD/BMC, markers of Ca-PO4-FGF23 activity, markers of bone turnover, renal glomerular and tubular toxicity, and Gluc homeostasis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A: Vitamin D3 50,000 IU</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B: Vitamin D3 placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vitamin D3 50,000 IU</intervention_name>
    <description>Group A: Vitamin D3 50,000 IU orally every four weeks by DOT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A: Vitamin D3 50,000 IU</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MVI Tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>A standard MVI will be supplied to all study subjects and will contain ingredients not to exceed 600 IU of vitamin D3 and 200 mg Ca. Subjects will take one MVI tablet orally once daily.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A: Vitamin D3 50,000 IU</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B: Vitamin D3 placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vitamin D3 placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Group B: Vitamin D3 placebo orally every four weeks by DOT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group B: Vitamin D3 placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 16 years and 0 days to 24 years and 364 days;

          -  Behaviorally infected with HIV (e.g., sexual contact, injection drug use; not
             infected by perinatal transmission, blood transfusion, or at age younger than 9
             years);

          -  HIV-1 infection as documented in subject's medical record by at least one  of the
             following criteria:

               -  reactive HIV screening test result with an antibody based FDA-licensed assay
                  followed by a positive supplemental assay (e.g., HIV-1 Western Blot, HIV-1
                  Indirect Immunofluorescence);  or

               -  positive HIV-1 DNA PCR  assay; or

               -  plasma HIV-1 quantitative RNA assay &gt;1,000 copies/mL; or

               -  positive plasma HIV-1 RNA qualitative assay

          -  Subjects must have at least one documented viral load that is below 200 copies/mL
             collected following initiation of TDF containing cART and greater than 90 days prior
             to screening; no viral load above 200 copies/mL if measured within the 90 days prior
             to screening; and a viral load obtained at screening that is below 200 copies/mL.

          -  Currently being treated for at least 180 days with a TDF containing cART with at
             least 2 other FDA approved ARVs (NOTE: This may include a TDF-containing fixed drug
             combination medication);

          -  Negative serum hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) at screening or by history within
             4 weeks prior to screening (see section 7.1.3);

          -  Willingness and ability to remain on the same cART regimen for the 96-week duration
             of the study;

          -  Willingness and ability to participate in the study, follow all study procedures for
             the 96-week duration, and provide written informed consent or assent with parental
             permission, if applicable; and

          -  For females of child-bearing potential, agreement to use a minimum of one
             proven-effective method of birth control and willingness to postpone pregnancy for
             the duration of study participation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior hypersensitivity to vitamin D;

          -  History of sarcoidosis, arteriosclerosis, renal stones, glomerulonephritis,
             interstitial kidney disease, nephrotic syndrome, hypercalcemia, osteoporosis and/or
             other bone diseases, clinical diagnosis of hypoparathyroidism or hyperparathyroidism;

          -  Lactation or pregnancy currently or within the past 24 weeks;

          -  Chemotherapy or radiation therapy for malignancy within the past 12 months;

          -  Known presence of GI disease that, in the opinion of the clinician, would interfere
             with study agent administration or absorption (e.g. Crohn's, Colitis);

          -  For subjects ≥ 18 years, confirmed creatinine clearance &lt; 70 ml/min (estimated GFR
             from SCr using CG equation) and for subjects &lt;18 years, confirmed creatinine
             clearance &lt; 70ml/min/1.73m2 (estimated GFR from SCr using Schwartz formula (see
             section 3.5). (Estimated GFR may be calculated using the formulae programmed on the
             ATN website);

          -  SCa &gt; Upper Limit Normal (ULN) for local laboratory values (see section 7.1.3);

          -  Active Grade 3 or higher clinical or laboratory toxicity except ATV associated
             indirect hyperbilirubinemia (see section 9.5.2.2);

          -  Weight is &gt; 350 pounds (lbs) or 159 kilograms (kgs);

          -  Positive hepatitis C antibody by history or at screening (see section 7.1.3); and

          -  Use of any medications as specified in sections 5.3.1, 5.3.3 and 5.4.

          -  Females Only: Use of certain hormonal contraceptives as specified in the protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>24 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter Havens, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>MACC Fund Research Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hopsital of Los Angeles</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90027</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Childrens National Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Miami School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of South Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33606</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stroger Hospital and the CORE Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tulane Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Orleans</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fenway Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wayne State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Montefiore Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10467</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Jude Childrens Research Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.atnonline.org</url>
    <description>ATN website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 8, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 14, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cholecalciferol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin D</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ergocalciferols</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tenofovir</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
