<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="154823">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02015091</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>140035</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>14-I-0035</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02015091</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Controlled Human Malaria Infections to Evaluate Protection After Intravenous or Intramuscular Administration of PfSPZ Vaccine in Malaria-Na(SqrRoot) ve Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>VRC 314: A Phase 1, Open-Label, Clinical Trial With Experimental Controlled Human Malaria Infections (CHMI) to Evaluate Safety and Durability of Protection Following Intravenous and Intramuscular Administration of PFSPZ Vaccine in Malaria-Naive Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - People bitten by mosquitoes carrying weakened malaria parasites could fight off the
      disease if later exposed to normal malaria parasites. Scientists have discovered how to make
      the weakened parasites, which can be injected by the PfSPZ vaccine. Researchers want to see
      if people who receive the vaccine get malaria after being bitten in a controlled setting (a
      controlled human malaria infection, CHMI).

      Objective:

      - To see if the PfSPZ malaria vaccine is safe and prevents malaria in a controlled setting.

      Eligibility:

      - Healthy adults 18   45 years old.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with medical history, physical exam, blood and lab tests,
           and EKG.

        -  Participants will be split into 8 groups, to be in the study for 3   12 months.

        -  Participants will receive 3   5 vaccinations, injected by a needle in an arm vein or
           muscle.

        -  Participants will keep a health diary and be contacted by phone.

        -  For CHMI, a cup with mosquitoes carrying malaria is applied to participants    arm for
           5 minutes. Five mosquitoes at a time are used, until 5 have bitten. Some groups will be
           exposed to malaria more than once.

        -  After CHMI, participants will visit the clinic very frequently (including daily visits
           for 12 days)  for 28 days.

        -  Blood will be drawn at most visits, from 1 to 20 tubes. Physical exam and medical
           history may also be repeated

        -  Participants who develop malaria will be treated immediately at the clinic. Standard
           treatment takes 72 hours. Malaria symptoms may last up to 3 days.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      VRC 314 is designed as an open-label evaluation of the safety, tolerability, immunogenicity
      and protective efficacy of the PfSPZ Vaccine. This vaccine administered at 1.35 x 10(5) SPZ
      per injection by the IV route on a schedule of 5 vaccinations was previously shown to confer
      protection in all vaccinated subjects against Controlled Human Malaria Infections (CHMI)
      performed shortly after last vaccination; however there was limited durability of protection
      in a small number of subjects. in this study, 1.35 x 10(5) SPZ per injection by the IV route
      will be given to substantiate the initial results with this dose for protection against
      CHMI. In addition, 2.7 x 10(5) SPZ IV per injection on schedules of 3 to 5 vaccinations will
      be evaluated for protection against CHMI conducted at 3 weeks and 24 weeks after completion
      of vaccinations. Also, one group will receive 2.2 x 10(6) SPZ IM, with half of the amount
      administered in each arm on a schedule with 4 vaccination time-points.

      The primary objectives of the study are related to the safety and tolerability of
      vaccinations by the IV and IM routes of administration and protection against Plasmodium
      falciparum (Pf) challenge performed via a well-established CHMI procedure early (2-4 weeks)
      after completing schedules of 3 to 5 vaccinations. The secondary objective is related to the
      durability of protection at 20-26 weeks after the last vaccination and exploratory
      objectives are related to the immunogenicity of the PfSPZ Vaccine and identifying potential
      immune correlates of protection.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary objectives of the study are related to the safety and tolerability of vaccinations by the IV and IM routes of administration and protection against the Plasmodium falciparum challenge.</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The secondary objective is related to the durability of protection at 20-26 weeks after the last vaccination.</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria</condition>
  <condition>Prevention and Control</condition>
  <condition>Acquired Immunity</condition>
  <condition>Parasitemia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PfSPZ</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        A volunteer must meet all of the following criteria to be included:

          1. 18 to 45 years old adults.

          2. Able and willing to participate for the duration of the study.

          3. Able to provide proof of identity to the satisfaction of the study clinician
             completing the enrollment process.

          4. Able and willing to complete the informed consent process.

          5. Willing to donate blood for sample storage to be used for future research.

          6. Willing to refrain from blood donation to blood banks for 3 years following P.
             falciparum CHMI.

          7. Agrees not to travel to a malaria endemic region during the entire course of study
             participation.

          8. Physical examination and laboratory results without clinically significant findings
             and a body mass index (BMI) less than or equal to 35 for vaccine groups or BMI less
             than or equal to 40 for control groups.

          9. If enrolling into a Group with an IV vaccination schedule, then the physical exam
             must include assessment that there is adequate bilateral antecubital fossa venous
             access.

             Laboratory Criteria within 56 days prior to enrollment:

         10. Hemoglobin greater than or equal to 11.2 g/dL for women; greater than or equal to
             12.6 g/dL for men.

         11. Differential and platelet count either within institutional normal range or
             accompanied by site physician approval.

         12. Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) less than or equal to 1.25 x upper limit of normal
             (ULN) for vaccine groups or less than or equal to 1.75 x ULN for CHMI control groups.

         13. Serum creatinine less than or equal to upper limit of normal.

         14. Negative for HIV infection.

             Laboratory Criterion documented any time prior to enrollment:

         15. Negative sickle cell screening test.

             Female-Specific Criteria:

         16. Negative Beta-HCG pregnancy test (urine or serum) on day of enrollment for women
             presumed to be of childbearing potential.

         17. A woman of childbearing potential must agree to use an effective means of birth
             control throughout the duration of study participation.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        A volunteer will be excluded if one or more of the following conditions apply:

          1. Woman who is breast-feeding or planning to become pregnant during the time interval
             needed to complete the study.

          2. Receipt of a malaria vaccine in a prior clinical trial.

          3. Any history of malaria infection.

          4. Evidence of increased cardiovascular disease risk; defined as &gt; 10% five year risk by
             the non-laboratory method.

          5. Current use of systemic immunosuppressant pharmacotherapy.

          6. History of a splenectomy, sickle cell disease or sickle cell trait.

          7. Plan for major surgery between enrollment and challenge.

          8. Known allergy to any component of the vaccine formulation; history of anaphylactic
             response to mosquito-bites; or known allergy to chloroquine phosphate, atovaquone or
             proguanil.

          9. Participation in any study involving another investigational vaccine or drug within
             12 weeks prior to enrollment, or plan to participate in another investigational
             vaccine/drug research during the study.

         10. Personal beliefs that prohibit the receiving of vaccine product containing human
             serum albumin within the diluent.

         11. Use or planned use of any drug with anti-malarial activity that would coincide with
             study vaccination or challenge.

         12. History of psoriasis or porphyria, which may be exacerbated after treatment with
             chloroquine.

         13. Anticipated use of medications known to cause drug reactions with chloroquine or
             atovaquone-proguanil (Malarone) such as cimetidine, metoclopramide, antacids, and
             kaolin.

         14. Psychiatric condition that precludes compliance with the protocol; past or present
             psychoses; disorder requiring lithium; or within five years prior to enrollment,
             history of a suicide plan or attempt.

         15. Any medical, psychiatric, social condition, occupational reason or other
             responsibility that, in the judgment of the investigator, is a contraindication to
             protocol participation or impairs a volunteer   s ability to give informed consent or
             to comply with the protocol schedule.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Julie E Ledgerwood, D.O.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Floreliz H Mendoza</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-8715</phone>
    <email>vaccines@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Maryland Center for Vaccine Dev, Baltimore</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201-1595</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kirsten Lyke, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>410-706-6156</phone>
      <email>klyke@medicine.umaryland.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>VRC Clinic</last_name>
      <phone>301-451-8715</phone>
      <email>vaccines@nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2014-I-0035.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nussenzweig RS, Vanderberg J, Most H, Orton C. Protective immunity produced by the injection of x-irradiated sporozoites of plasmodium berghei. Nature. 1967 Oct 14;216(5111):160-2. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>6057225</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seder RA, Chang LJ, Enama ME, Zephir KL, Sarwar UN, Gordon IJ, Holman LA, James ER, Billingsley PF, Gunasekera A, Richman A, Chakravarty S, Manoj A, Velmurugan S, Li M, Ruben AJ, Li T, Eappen AG, Stafford RE, Plummer SH, Hendel CS, Novik L, Costner PJ, Mendoza FH, Saunders JG, Nason MC, Richardson JH, Murphy J, Davidson SA, Richie TL, Sedegah M, Sutamihardja A, Fahle GA, Lyke KE, Laurens MB, Roederer M, Tewari K, Epstein JE, Sim BK, Ledgerwood JE, Graham BS, Hoffman SL; VRC 312 Study Team. Protection against malaria by intravenous immunization with a nonreplicating sporozoite vaccine. Science. 2013 Sep 20;341(6152):1359-65. doi: 10.1126/science.1241800. Epub 2013 Aug 8.</citation>
    <PMID>23929949</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Epstein JE, Tewari K, Lyke KE, Sim BK, Billingsley PF, Laurens MB, Gunasekera A, Chakravarty S, James ER, Sedegah M, Richman A, Velmurugan S, Reyes S, Li M, Tucker K, Ahumada A, Ruben AJ, Li T, Stafford R, Eappen AG, Tamminga C, Bennett JW, Ockenhouse CF, Murphy JR, Komisar J, Thomas N, Loyevsky M, Birkett A, Plowe CV, Loucq C, Edelman R, Richie TL, Seder RA, Hoffman SL. Live attenuated malaria vaccine designed to protect through hepatic CD8⁺ T cell immunity. Science. 2011 Oct 28;334(6055):475-80. doi: 10.1126/science.1211548. Epub 2011 Sep 8.</citation>
    <PMID>21903775</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 8, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Healthy Subjects</keyword>
  <keyword>Vaccine-Mediated Protection</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunogenicity</keyword>
  <keyword>Sporozoites</keyword>
  <keyword>Parasitemia</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Parasitemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
