<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="43405">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01726725</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>B2012:099</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01726725</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hemifacial Spasm and Desflurane</brief_title>
  <acronym>HFS</acronym>
  <official_title>Investigating the Etiology of Hemifacial Spasm (HFS): The Role of Desflurane</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Manitoba</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Manitoba</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Ethics Review Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients are chosen to participate in this study because they will undergo a particular type
      of brain surgery to treat their hemifacial spasm. This surgery is called microvascular
      decompression (MVD) and involves the facial nerve.  The facial nerve is being compressed by
      one or more blood vessels and this contact produces the facial twitches.  The investigators
      do not know why a blood vessel that touches the facial nerve produces facial twitches. The
      investigators are interested in investigating this during your surgery. A total of 25
      participants are expected to participate in this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      &quot;Intra Operative Monitoring&quot; (IOM) is a standard and routine medical practice for patients
      having MVD surgery. IOM is done to make sure that the hearing and face nerves are not
      accidentally bumped or damaged during surgery. After anesthetic induction, the
      neurophysiologist places electrodes for the nerves, on the scalp and muscles.  Stimulation
      and monitoring of muscle twitches are all common, safe and painless medical procedures.

      In this study, the investigators would like to measure the nerve and muscle function on the
      normal side and compare it to nerve and muscle function on the abnormal side during
      different levels of the anesthetic desflurane. In order to monitor the normal side of the
      face one additional set of electrodes will be placed in the facial muscles. The
      investigators will compare responses to three different levels of anesthetic. The technique
      used will be motor evoked potentials. The effect of the anesthesia on the lateral spread
      response will also be examined. This response is evident only on the symptomatic side. These
      observations will take approximately 10 to 15 minutes and will not delay or lengthen the
      surgery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case Control, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure EMG responses to peripheral nerve stimulation and motor cortex stimulation during changes in desflurane levels</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Hemifacial Spasm</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>hemifacial spasm, lateral spread, motor evoked potentials</arm_group_label>
    <description>EMG recordings from facial muscles of HFS patients during MVD surgery will be compared during total intravenous anesthesia (propofol), 0.5 MAC desflurane and 1.0 MAC desflurane</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>desflurane</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>hemifacial spasm, lateral spread, motor evoked potentials</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients diagnosed with hemifacial spasm who will be undergoing microvascular
        decompression surgery
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patients referred to the neurosurgical service for microvascular decompression
             surgery for HFS

          -  males and females 18 to 75 years of age

          -  otherwise normal neurological exam

          -  signed informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Botox treatment within the last three months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marshall Wilkinson, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Manitoba</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>November 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 15, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 7, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hemifacial spasm</keyword>
  <keyword>microvascular decompression surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>desflurane</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Spasm</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemifacial Spasm</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Desflurane</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
