<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="3347">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02122601</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LG-HACL013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02122601</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Open-label, Single Arm, Multi-center, Phase 3 Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of Retreatment With Intra-articular LBSA0103 Injections in the Patients With Osteoarthritis of the Knee</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>LG Life Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>LG Life Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>South Korea: Ministry of Food and Drug Safety</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To assess the safety and efficacy of LBSA0103 (BDDE cross-linked sodium hyaluronate gel)
      when it is administered for the second time 26 weeks after its first administration in
      patients with osteoarthritis of the knee.

      The Safety and efficacy of 26weeks after its first administration will be also evaluated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Adverse events for 13 weeks after the first administration and second administration</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and week 13</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Local reactions at injection site after the first administration and the re-administration</measure>
    <time_frame>13,39 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events of total clinical study period</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 13, 26, 39 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 13, 26, 39 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Laboratory exam</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 13, 26, 39 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Weight-bearing pain(100mm-VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 13, 26, 39 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in WOMAC-likert assessment: Pain, Function, stiffness, Total score</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 13, 26, 39 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Patient Global Assessment (100mm-VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 13, 26, 39 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Observed subject evaluations on Visual Analog Scale (VAS) of 100 mm; 0 mm meaning excellent feeling in knee joint; 100 mm meaning poor feeling in knee joint. Change in score from baseline to each time frame will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Investigator Global Assessment (100mm-VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 13, 26, 39 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Observed subject evaluations on Visual Analog Scale (VAS) of 100 mm; 0 mm meaning excellent feeling in knee joint; 100 mm meaning poor feeling in knee joint. Change in score from baseline to each time frame will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in rest pain(100mm-VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 13, 26, 39 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Observed subject evaluations on Visual Analog Scale (VAS) of 100 mm; 0 mm meaning excellent feeling in knee joint when the subject takes a rest; 100 mm meaning poor feeling in knee joint. Change in score from baseline will be calculated</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in night pain(100mm-VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 13, 26, 39 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Observed subject evaluations on Visual Analog Scale (VAS) of 100 mm; 0 mm meaning excellent feeling in knee joint at night; 100 mm meaning poor feeling in knee joint. Change in score from baseline will be calculated</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in motion pain(100mm-VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 13, 26, 39 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Observed subject evaluations on Visual Analog Scale (VAS) of 100 mm; 0 mm meaning excellent feeling in knee joint while walking; 100 mm meaning poor feeling in knee joint. Change in score from baseline will be calculated</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical assessment: Changes in swelling on knee joint, tenderness on pressure and the range of motion of knee joint</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 13, 26, 39 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate (%) of the subjects who were administered with rescue therapy and amount consumed</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 13, 26, 39 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of the subjects who showed a reduction by at least 20 mm or an improvement by at least 40% in the Weight-bearing pain (100 mmVAS) at Week 13 in comparison with the baseline value</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 13, 26, 39 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>OMERACT-OARSI responder rate</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 13, 26, 39 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Outcome Measures in Rheumatology Clinical Trials and Osteoarthritis Research Society International (OMERACT-OARSI) strict responses defined by changes from baseline in WOMAC pain or physical function subscore ≥50% with absolute changes ≥20 mm (termed strict responders), or ≥20% with absolute changes ≥10mm in 2 of 3 measures of WOMAC pain or physical function subscore or subject global evaluations (termed responders).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">162</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis of Knee</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LBSA0103</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>single arm , LBSA0103 only</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LBSA0103 (BDDE cross-linked sodium hyaluronate gel)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>LBSA0103</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. A patient diagnosed with one or both knee osteoarthritis based on the clinical
             diagnosis criteria of the American College of Rheumatology (ACR) (there should be
             knee pain and in addition, at least three of the following six conditions have to be
             satisfied: 1. Over 50 years of age 2. Less than 30 minutes of morning stiffness 3.
             Crepitus on active motion 4 Bony tenderness 5. Bony enlargement 6. No palpable warmth
             of synovium)

          2. Adult male and female patients of age 40 or above diagnosed with knee osteoarthritis
             with the Kellgren &amp; Lawrence Grade of I - III by x-ray within 6 months before the
             screening visit (based on -2 weeks) or by x-ray at the screening visit

          3. A patient who has at least one knee with a weight-bearing pain value of 40 mm or more
             when weight-bearing pain (100 mm-VAS) is measured

          4. A patient taking aspirin at a low dose (300 mg or less per day) who is willing to
             take aspirin constantly at the same dose until the clinical study is completed and
             can refrain from taking aspirin within 24 hours before each visit.

          5. A patient who can walk without depending on a walking aid such as walker, cane, etc.
             but if the patient has been using a walking aid on a daily basis from six months ago,
             the patient assessment can be conducted while including the walking aid and the
             walking aid must be used in the same way until the study is completed.

          6. A patient who can understand the meanings of an efficacy measurement questionnaire
             well and complete it

          7. A patient who heard an explanation about the purpose, method, effects, etc. of the
             clinical study and whose informed consent form has been signed by him/herself or
             subject's representative

          8. A patient who falls under one of the following four cases

               -  Patients who are surgically infertile

               -  Post-menopausal women who are above 45 years of age and 2 years after the last
                  menstruation

               -  Fertile premenopausal female patients or male patients without having a surgical
                  sterilization who have agreed to use at least two birth control methods
                  (including one of barrier methods) for at least 13 weeks after the
                  administration of the last investigational product to avoid pregnancy

                    -  Barrier methods: Condom, Diaphragm, Cervical cap(Pessary), Spermicide

                    -  Hormonal methods: Pills, Injection(Depot), Skin patch, Hormonal
                       implant(Implanon), Vaginal ring

                    -  Intrauterine Devices(IUDs): Cooper IUD(Loop), Hormonal IUD(Mirena)

                    -  Natural methods: Basic body temperature, Ovulation period, Coitus
                       interruptus, Abstinent

          9. A patient who discontinued analgesics, NSAIDs, condroichin sulfate/glucosamine and
             physical therapy or oriental medical treatment (acupuncture, cubbing therapy, moxa
             treatment) within 2 weeks before the administration (washout period) and has a will
             to discontinue them from the screening visit of the study to the end (however, 300 mg
             less per day of aspirin and acetaminophen, a rescue therapy, can be taken)

         10. A patient who didn't take any analgesic including aspirin and acetaminophen within 24
             hours before the administration

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Body mass index &gt; 32

          2. A patient with rheumatoid arthritis, or other inflammatory or metabolic arthritis

          3. A patient with infection or severe inflammation at the joint like septic arthritis

          4. A patient with infection or skin disease at the site of administration

          5. A patient with secondary knee osteoarthritis caused by ochronosis, hemochromatosis,
             systemic disease, etc.

          6. A patient with a very painful musculoskeletal disease such as Sudek's atrophy,
             Paget's disease, or spinal disc herniation

          7. A poly-artricular patient with a severe osteoarthritis symptom at other site (e.g.,
             hip joint, etc.) which can have an effect on the assessment of the pain for knee
             joint

          8. Patients diagnosed with knee osteoarthritis with the Kellgren &amp; Lawrence Grade of IV
             in X-ray within 6 months before the screening visit (based on -2 weeks) or X-ray at
             the screening visit

          9. A patient showing a clear loss in the joint space of patello-femoral joint (PFJ) in
             X-ray

         10. A patient who took following drug before the administration of investigational
             product (baseline visit):

               -  A patient who had HA at the target knee joint within the last 6 months

               -  A patient who was given an intra-articular knee joint injection with steroidal
                  agent within the last 3 months

               -  A patient who used steroidal agent systemically by oral administration within
                  the last 1 month (However, except for inhalant)

         11. A patient with moderate to severe joint effusion which was found to be positive
             through patella tap test, etc.

         12. A patient with alcoholism and alcoholic liver disease

         13. A patient with a serious heart disease or hepatic and renal dysfunction or a patient
             who showed the following laboratory test value:

               -  AST, ALT &gt; 3 times the upper limit of normal range

               -  Serum creatinine &gt; 2mg/dl

         14. A patient who had a surgical procedure including arthroscopy on the target knee
             within the last 1 year (In case of a patient who had a history of joint surgery on
             other knee or hip joint, the patient shall be excluded if the assessment of the
             target knee is likely to be affected by that. )

         15. A patient who has a history of knee replacement surgery on the target knee joint

         16. A patient who does highly intensive aerobic exercise or heavy anaerobic exercise such
             as running or weight training which can have an effect on knee joint.

         17. A patient who needs to use an anticoagulant agent concurrently (However, except for
             aspirin of 300 mg or less per day)

         18. A patient who is mentally ill or can't understand the purpose and method of this
             clinical study

         19. A patient who shows hypersensitivity reaction to the investigational product of this
             clinical study

         20. A patient who is participating in other clinical study after having enrolled in this
             study, or participated in other clinical study within 1 month before the enrollment
             in this clinical study

         21. A patient who is considered to have a difficulty undergoing the clinical study at the
             discretion of the Principal Investigator

         22. A patient who was given one of the following drugs based on the day of
             administration:

               -  A patient who was given anesthetic within the last 48 hours

               -  A patient who took analgesics including acetaminophen and aspirin within the
                  last 24 hour
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bogyeong Kim, MS</last_name>
    <phone>82-2-6924-3172</phone>
    <email>ibonobo@lgls.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seoul National University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>110-744</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kyung-In Won, Project Manager</last_name>
      <phone>82-2-2011-4778</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 23, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 16, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hyaluronic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
