<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="95810">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01922856</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>S-12-24</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NMRC.2013.0011</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CIR 289</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01922856</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Challenge Study of an ETEC Vaccine</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2b Controlled Efficacy Study of Intradermally Delivered ETEC Fimbrial Tip Adhesin Vaccine Against Experimental Challenge With ETEC H10407 in Healthy Adult Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>U.S. Army Medical Research and Materiel Command</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>U.S. Army Medical Research and Materiel Command</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to determine the efficacy of a vaccine against enterotoxigenic
      E. coli (ETEC)-caused diarrhea.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to establish preliminary efficacy of dscCfaE administered with
      LTR192G by intradermal (ID) immunization in prevention of disease caused by a challenge with
      a CFA/I expressing ETEC strain (H10407).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of adverse events associated with vaccine</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Day 0-365</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Occurrence of subjective fever, malaise, headache, rash, pain, diarrhea, abdominal pain, extremity pain or swelling reported by in-person symptom surveillance, symptom memory aid tool and clinical assessments.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of vaccine</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Day 70-75</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Prevention of moderate to severe diarrhea:
Severe diarrhea: ≥ 6 grade 3-5 stools in 24 hours, or &gt; 800 g of grade 3-5 stools in 24 hours
Moderate diarrhea: 4-5 grade 3-5 stools in 24 hours or 401-800 g of grade 3-5 stools in 24 hours.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Seroconversion to dscCfaE and LT</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Day 0, 21, 42, 69 &amp; 98</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Defined as a &gt; 4-fold increase in endpoint titer for anti-CfaE and Anti-LT IgG and IgA</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Positive Antibody Secreting Cell (ASC) response</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Day 0, 7, 28, 49, 69 &amp; 77</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Defined as a &gt;2-fold increase over the baseline value of the ASC per 10^6 PBMC</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">68</enrollment>
  <condition>Enteritis; Escherichia Coli, Enterotoxigenic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>25ug dscCfaE + 100ng LTR192G ID on study days 0, 21 &amp;42</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Challenge (Vaccinated Volunteers)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>2 x 10^7 CFU mixture of H10407, ST+, LT+ CFA/I suspended in bicarbonate buffer solution</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Challenge (Unvaccinated Volunteers)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>2 x 10^7 CFU mixture of H10407 ETEC suspended in bicarbonate buffer solution</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>dscCfaE + LTR192G</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Vaccine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>H10407 ETEC</intervention_name>
    <description>O78:H11 LT+ ST+ CFA/I+</description>
    <arm_group_label>Challenge (Vaccinated Volunteers)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Challenge (Unvaccinated Volunteers)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female age 18 through 50 years (inclusive).

          -  General good health, without clinically significant medical history, physical
             examination findings or clinical laboratory abnormalities per clinical judgment of
             PI.

          -  Negative pregnancy test. Pregnancy at any time will result in not receiving any or
             additional investigational product. Females of childbearing potential must agree to
             use an efficacious hormonal or barrier method of birth control during the study.
             Abstinence is acceptable. Female subjects unable to bear children must have this
             documented (eg, tubal ligation or hysterectomy) or must have negative pregnancy
             tests.

          -  Willingness to participate in the study after all aspects of the protocol have been
             explained and written informed consent obtained.

          -  Completion of a training session and demonstrated comprehension of the protocol
             procedures, knowledge of ETEC-associated illness, and by passing a written
             examination (70% passing score).

          -  Availability for the study duration, including all planned follow-up visits.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        General

          -  Presence of a significant medical or psychiatric condition which in the opinion of
             the investigator precludes participation in the study. Some medical conditions which
             are adequately treated and stable would not preclude entry into the study. These
             conditions might include stable asthma controlled with inhalers or mild hypertension
             stably controlled with a single agent.

          -  Significant abnormalities in screening hematology, or serum chemistry as determined
             by PI or PI in consultation with the research monitor and sponsor.

          -  Presence in the serum of HIV antibody, HBsAg, or HCV antibody.

          -  Evidence of IgA deficiency (serum IgA &lt; 7 mg/dL or below the limit of detection of
             assay).

          -  Evidence of current excessive alcohol consumption or drug dependence (a targeted drug
             screen may be used to evaluate at the clinician's discretion).

          -  Evidence of impaired immune function.

          -  Recent vaccination or receipt of an investigational product (within 30 days before
             vaccination).

          -  Any other criteria which, in the investigator's opinion, would compromise the ability
             of the subject to participate in the study, the safety of the study, or the results
             of the study

        Research Related Exclusions Applicable to Vaccination and Challenge Participation

          -  History of microbiologically confirmed ETEC or cholera infection in last 3 years.

          -  Occupation involving handling of ETEC or Vibrio cholerae currently, or in the past 3
             years.

          -  Symptoms consistent with Travelers' Diarrhea concurrent with travel to countries
             where ETEC infection is endemic (most of the developing world) within 3 years prior
             to dosing, OR planned travel to endemic countries during the length of the study.

          -  Vaccination for or ingestion of ETEC, cholera, or E coli heat labile toxin within 3
             years prior to dosing.

        Research Related Exclusions Not Applicable to Challenge-Only Participants

          -  Exclusionary skin history/findings that would confound assessment or prevent
             appropriate local monitoring of AEs, or possibly increase the risk of an AE.

          -  History of chronic skin disease (clinician judgment).- History of atopy such as
             active eczema.

          -  Acute skin infection/eruptions on the upper arms including fungal infections, severe
             acne, or active contact dermatitis.

          -  History of significant allergic reactions to any vaccines and allergies that may
             increase the risk of AEs (Well-controlled seasonal allergies responsive to
             antihistamine medication or intranasal steroids are not exclusionary per clinician
             determination).

        Study-specific Exclusion Criteria

          -  Abnormal stool pattern (fewer than 3 per week or more than 3 per day).

          -  Regular use of laxatives, antacids, or other agents to lower stomach acidity.

          -  Use of any medication known to affect the immune function (eg, systemic
             corticosteroids and others) within 30 days preceding the first vaccination or planned
             use during the active study period.

          -  Known allergy to two of the following antibiotics: ciprofloxacin,
             trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole, and penicillin.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Clayton Harro, MD, ScM</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins Center for Immunization Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Clayton Harro, MD, ScM</last_name>
    <phone>410-614-4937</phone>
    <email>charro@jhsph.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins Center for Immunization Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Clayton Harro, MD, ScM</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center for Immunization Research Isolation Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Clayton Harro, MD, ScM</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 12, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Enteritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
