<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="46782">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01748227</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RRP 12-438</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01748227</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>IMproving Pain Using Peer RE-inforced Self-management Skills</brief_title>
  <acronym>IMPPRESS</acronym>
  <official_title>Improving Pain Using Peer RE-inforced Self-management Skills (IMPPRESS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall purpose of this pilot study is to conduct a formative evaluation of
      (veteran)peer delivery of a chronic pain self-management program to veterans with chronic
      musculoskeletal pain.

      Our specific aims are as follows:

      Aim 1:  Evaluate the feasibility of identifying, recruiting, training, and retaining veteran
      peers to implement a self-management program for chronic pain.

      Aim 2:  Identify facilitators and barriers to peer-delivery of a chronic pain
      self-management program.

      Aim 3:  Convene an expert panel to review the results of Aims 1 and 2, help to interpret the
      results, and plan next steps.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Peer training will consist of 2 core components:  1) How to deliver the pain self-management
      curriculum; and 2) Peer-support competencies (i.e., &quot;how to be a peer&quot;).  After initial
      training, research personnel will remain in regular contact with peers to answer questions,
      troubleshoot problems, and facilitate mutual support among peers.  Peers will meet as a
      group with the psychologist for bi-weekly peer supervision either in-person or via
      teleconference.

      The self-management program will be delivered in two phases.  Phase 1 will be a 2-hour
      didactic session led by the study nurse and will parallel the content described for the
      peers.  The pain self-management manual developed for our earlier studies will be used and
      distributed to the patients.  Phase 2 will be additional sessions delivered by peers, over a
      4-month period.  At the end of the Phase 1 session, the peers will meet their assigned
      patients.  Peers will be assigned 2 patients, and pairings will be made with input from the
      study nurse and psychologist, with patients and peers being age- and gender-matched to the
      extent possible.

      After their initial face-to-face meeting, peers will be asked to keep in regular contact
      with patients over a 4-month period.  Specifically, peers will contact patients a minimum of
      bi-weekly via telephone or in-person.

      Peers will be asked to review each of the topic areas covered in the self-management manual.
       Peers will review a different topic each session, ask if the patient has questions, and
      discuss his or her personal experience with the topic being covered during that session.
      Modeling what the nurse care manager has done in prior studies, peers will work with
      patients to help them to set goals and to evaluate whether these goals are realistic.  A new
      goal will be set at each session, with the peer following up on the previous goals with the
      patient, whether they were accomplished, and if not, possible courses of action (e.g.,
      modifying the goal or offering other advice to accomplish the goal).  Throughout these
      sessions peers will be encouraged to draw on their own experiences and how they personally
      overcame obstacles and handled setbacks and frustrations.  Peers will not advise on or
      discuss medications or medical questions with patients.  If such questions come up, peers
      will instruct patients to contact their PCPs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain severity</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 4 month assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This will be measured by the Brief Pain Inventory (3 items)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain beliefs and coping measured by the Pain Catastrophizing Scale (10 items) and Centrality of Pain Scale (10 items)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 4 month assessment (final assessment)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Social Support and Relationships measured by the Multidimensional Scale of Perceived Social Support (12 items) and the Working Alliance Inventory (12 items)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 4 month for SPSS and only 4 month final interview for Working Alliance</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain interference</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 4 month assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This will be measured by the PROMIS pain measures (12 items)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationships</measure>
    <time_frame>4 month assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured by the Working Alliance measure (12 items)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pain Self-Management</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Training of (veteran) peers to deliver pain self-management materials to veterans with chronic pain</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pain Self-Management</intervention_name>
    <description>Training of veteran peers to deliver pain self-management material to veterans with chronic pain. Veteran peers will then be assigned 2 patients with chronic pain to work with over the next 4 months on pain self-management.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pain Self-Management</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Peers will be eligible if they have chronic musculoskeletal pain and have completed a
             pain self-management program from any of these chronic pain trials:

               -  Stepped Care for Depression and Musculoskeletal Pain (SCAMP)

               -  Evaluation of Stepped Care for Chronic Pain in Iraq and Afghanistan Veterans
                  (ESCAPE)

               -  CAre Management for the Effective use of Opioids (CAMEO)

               -  Or participants of the VA Pain School or VA Pain program

               -  Peers may also be recommended by their primary care providers at the VA

          -  Eligible patients must have musculoskeletal pain in the low back, cervical spine, or
             extremities (hip, knee, or shoulder) that has persisted for  3 months

          -  And have pain of at least moderate intensity as defined by a Brief Pain Inventory
             score 5

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients will be excluded if they have active suicidal ideation

          -  Have been hospitalized for psychiatric or substance abuse reasons in the last 6
             months pending back surgery

          -  Current substance dependence

          -  Severe medical conditions (e.g., New York Heart Association Class III or IV heart
             failure) that precludes participation

          -  Or severe hearing or speech impairment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marianne Sassi Matthias, PhD MS BA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Richard Roudebush VA Medical Center, Indianapolis</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Richard Roudebush VA Medical Center, Indianapolis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202-2884</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 12, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 21, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>self-management</keyword>
  <keyword>peer support</keyword>
  <keyword>social support</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
