<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="51766">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01658930</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CX5</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01658930</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Radical Versus Simple Hysterectomy and Pelvic Node Dissection in Patients With Early Stage Cervical Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Phase III Trial Comparing Radical Hysterectomy and Pelvic Node Dissection vs Simple Hysterectomy and Pelvic Node Dissection in Patients With Low-Risk Early Stage Cervical Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NCIC Clinical Trials Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Gynecologic Cancer Intergroup</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NCIC Clinical Trials Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The reason this study is being done is to see if a simple hysterectomy is as good as a
      radical hysterectomy in preventing cancer of the cervix from returning, and whether, because
      less tissue surrounding the uterus is removed during surgery, there are fewer side-effects
      after the surgery and in the long-term.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      At this time, it is not clear which of these approaches best balances the desire to prevent
      cancer of the cervix from returning with the risks of side effects after surgery and in the
      long-term.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pelvic relapse-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>7 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Pelvic relapse-free survival (PRFS), the primary endpoint of this study, is defined as the time from randomization to the time of documented evidence of recurrence within the pelvic field.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy comparison between treatment arms</measure>
    <time_frame>7 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>compare the two treatment arms with respect to:
Extrapelvic relapse-free survival
Relapse-free survival (any site)
Overall survival
Treatment-related toxicity
Patient Reported Outcomes including global quality of life and measures of sexual health
Cost-effectiveness and cost-utility
Sentinel node detection
Parametrial involvement
Involvement of surgical margins
Pelvic node involvement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">700</enrollment>
  <condition>Cervical Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Radical Hysterectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Simple Hysterectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radical Hysterectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>This procedure may be performed abdominally, laparoscopically, robotically or vaginally. The uterus, cervix, medial 1/3 of parametria, 2cm of the uterosacral ligaments and upper 1-2cm of the vagina are to be removed en bloc. The uterine artery is ligated laterally to the ureters and the ureters are unroofed to the ureterovesical junction.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Radical Hysterectomy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Simple hysterectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>This procedure may be performed abdominally, laparoscopically, robotically or vaginally. Extrafascial hysterectomy involves removal of the uterus with cervix without adjacent parametria. The uterine arteries are transected medial to the ureters at the level of the isthmus and the uterosacral ligaments are transected at the level of the cervix. Surgeons should pay special attention to make sure that the whole cervix is removed. As such, a maximum of 0.5 cm of vaginal cuff can be removed to ensure the complete removal of the cervix.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Simple Hysterectomy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed adenocarcinoma, squamous, or adenosquamous cancer of the
             cervix. Diagnosis has been made by LEEP, cone or cervical biopsy and has been
             reviewed and confirmed by the local reference gynecological pathologist.

          -  Patient has been classified as low-risk early-stage cervical cancer. These patients
             include:

               -  FIGO Stage IA2 [FIGO Annual Report, 2009], defined as:

                    -  evidence of disease by microscopy;

                         1. for patients who underwent a LEEP or cone.

                              -  histologic evidence of depth of stromal invasion between 3.0-5.0
                                 mm based on the local reference pathologist's measurement of the
                                 LEEP or cone specimen.

                              -  histologic evidence of lateral extension that is not greater than
                                 7.0 mm based on the local reference pathologist's measurement of
                                 the LEEP or cone specimen.

                              -  negative margins.

                         2. for patients who underwent a cervical biopsy only:

                              -  radiologic evidence of less than 50% stromal invasion based on
                                 pelvic MRI.

               -  FIGO Stage IB1 [FIGO Annual Report, 2009] with favorable (low risk) features,
                  defined as:

                    -  a clinically visible lesion or a microscopically diagnosed lesion measuring
                       &gt; 5 mm depth of invasion or &gt; 7 mm in lateral extension or a IA2 sized
                       lesion with positive margins.

                    -  histologic evidence of less than 10mm stromal invasion based on the local
                       reference pathologist's measurement of the LEEP or cone specimen Note: this
                       criterion will not apply to patients who underwent a cervical biopsy only;

                    -  Radiologic evidence of maximum dimension of ≤ 20 mm as seen by pelvic MRI;
                       and

                    -  Radiologic evidence of less than 50% stromal invasion based on pelvic MRI.
                       Note: Patients are eligible irrespective of the presence or absence of
                       lymph-vascular space involvement (LVSI).

          -  The histologic grade of cervical cancer must be 1, 2, 3 or not assessable [FIGO
             Annual Report, 2009].

          -  Physical examination, recto-vaginal examination and visualization of the cervix by
             speculum or colposcopic examination have been done after the initial diagnostic
             procedure (LEEP, cone or biopsy) and prior to randomization. Staging criteria
             described in 5.1.2 must be satisfied based on these examinations.

          -  Chest x-ray or CT scan of chest AND pelvic MRI* done after initial diagnostic
             procedure (LEEP, cone or biopsy) and prior to randomization.

        The CT should be a 16 slice (or higher) helical scanner. Oral and intravenous contrasts
        are required (unless there is a contraindication to the use of contrast) with scan
        obtained in the portal phase at a slice thickness of 5mm or lower Pelvic MRI should be
        performed on a 1.5 or 3 Tesla magnet with pelvic phased-array coils. The MR pulse
        sequences will consist of T1 gradient echo in the axial plane at 5 mm slice thickness and
        fast spin echo in the axial, sagittal, and coronal planes at 4 mm slice thickness. The
        short axis (perpendicular to the tumour's long axis) with a 3 mm slice thickness is
        required in the best plane to show the maximum thickness of stromal invasion. Use of an
        anti-peristaltic agent is mandatory while intravenous use of gadolinium or
        diffusion-weighted imaging (DWI) is optional.

        * Note: pelvic MRI is not required if the patient has stage IA2 disease and underwent a
        LEEP or cone.

          -  After consideration of a patient's medical history, physical examination and
             laboratory testing, patients must be suitable candidates for surgery as defined by
             the attending physician / investigator.

          -  Patients must have no desire to preserve fertility.

          -  Patients fluent in English, French or Spanish must be willing to complete the Quality
             of Life Questionnaire and the Sexual Health Questionnaire. The baseline assessments
             must be completed within 6 weeks prior to randomization. Inability (illiteracy in
             English, French or Spanish, loss of sight, or other equivalent reason) to complete
             the questionnaires will not make the patient ineligible for the study. However,
             ability but unwillingness to complete the questionnaires will make the patient
             ineligible. As additional GCIG groups join the study, more translations of some of
             the questionnaires may be added.

        Patients fluent in English or French who reside in Canada and the United Kingdom must
        agree to participate in the economic evaluation component of this trial and complete the
        Health Economics Questionnaire. Similarly, patients fluent in English or French accrued
        from other GCIG groups who are participating in the economic evaluation must be willing to
        complete the Health Economics Questionnaires.

          -  Patient consent must be appropriately obtained in accordance with applicable local
             and regulatory requirements. Each patient must sign a consent form prior to
             enrollment in the trial to document their willingness to participate

          -  Patients must be accessible for treatment and follow-up. Investigators must assure
             themselves the patients randomized on this trial will be available for complete
             documentation of the treatment, adverse events, and follow-up.

          -  Surgery is to be done within 20 weeks of initial diagnosis (NO EXCEPTIONS). The
             20-week period includes time required for diagnosis, referral, diagnostic staging,
             randomization and scheduling of the surgical procedure.

          -  Patients must be ≥ 18 years old.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with FIGO 1A1 disease [FIGO Annual Report, 2009].

          -  History of other malignancies, except: adequately treated non-melanoma skin cancer,
             curatively treated in-situ cancer of the cervix, or other solid tumours, Hodgkin's
             lymphoma or non-Hodgkin's lymphoma curatively treated with no evidence of disease for
             &gt; 5 years.

          -  Patients with evidence of lymph node metastasis on preoperative imaging or histology.

          -  Patients who have had or will receive neoadjuvant chemotherapy.

          -  Patients who are pregnant.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marie Plante</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>CHUQ - Hotel-Dieu de Quebec</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Elizabeth Eisenhauer</last_name>
    <phone>6135336430</phone>
    <email>eeisenhauer@ctg.queensu.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>McGill University Dept of Oncology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H2W 1S6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHUQ-Pavillon Hotel-Dieu de Quebec</name>
      <address>
        <city>Quebec City</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>G1R 2J6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 3, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Uterine Cervical Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
