<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="117489">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01675869</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R34MH095911</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01675869</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Executive Function/Metacognitive Training for At-Risk Preschoolers</brief_title>
  <acronym>ETAM</acronym>
  <official_title>Executive Function/Metacognitive Training for At-Risk Preschoolers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to see if an intervention training executive functions like
      attention, working memory, and self-regulation for preschoolers at risk for
      Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder is feasible, acceptable to families, and improves
      attention, behavior, and functioning.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Disruptive behavior disorders, particularly Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD),
      constitute one of the most common diagnoses in preschool children. Disruptive behaviors are
      a major public health problem including causing significant emotional distress for
      caregivers and children, expulsion from daycare or early education settings, demands on
      caregiver's time, accident proneness and other safety concerns. However, few evidence-based
      early interventions exist for preschoolers with attention and behavior problems, which is
      critical because they are strongly suggested as the first line of treatment for preschoolers
      with ADHD. Because executive functioning (EF) has been consistently been proposed as a
      putative factor in the development of disruptive behavior disorders an intervention
      targeting EF (e.g., inhibition, working memory), attention, and metacognition during early
      childhood could likely affect the development of disruptive behavior disorders in
      preschoolers. Indeed, EF skills are identified by kindergarten teachers as primary
      prerequisites for school success. EF deficits independently contribute to poorer outcomes in
      ADHD, and have been linked directly to academic and social functioning deficits. Given that
      EF and brain development are rapidly developing during the preschool years, preschoolers may
      benefit most from an early intervention targeting EF skills. Investigators have developed a
      promising intervention, Executive Training of Attention and Metacognition (ETAM), for
      preschoolers, and have conducted a small preliminary open trial demonstrating the initial
      acceptability of the intervention. Investigators also found significant moderate effect
      sizes on objective measures of EF and moderate to large effect size reductions in ratings of
      inattention and behavioral symptoms by parents, clinicians, and teachers. A randomized
      clinical trial (RCT) is needed to investigate if these positive effects on executive
      functioning, attention, and behavior are due to ETAM or to the effect of parental attention
      and/or a placebo effect. Investigators propose to assess the feasibility of a design for a
      future RCT. Investigators will develop an attention control (AC) comparison group and assess
      the feasibility of: identifying, enrolling and retaining preschoolers at-risk for ADHD,
      randomization choices, the measurement of EF and functional outcomes, and delivery protocol
      for both AC and ETAM by conducting a pilot RCT with 60 children at-risk for ADHD.
      Exploratory aims include assessing whether children in the ETAM group show gains compared to
      those in AC on targeted (trained) outcomes (i.e., measures of EF) and untrained outcomes
      (i.e., ADHD symptoms, academic readiness, social competence). Investigators will also assess
      whether gains are maintained as well as investigate potential moderators/mediators.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Caregiver, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Executive Functioning</measure>
    <time_frame>2 month follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigators will compute an aggregated measure of EF deficits. For each EF measure investigators will define a threshold for adequate performance as a score obtained by 75% of the children. Performance will be dummy-coded according to this threshold as &quot;0&quot; for adequate performance and &quot;1&quot; for poor performance. We will then calculate a continuous measure of EF ranging from 0 (adequate performance on all) to 9 (poor performance on all), by summing the dummy coded scores of all EF measures.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ETAM group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Executive Function/Metacognitive Training Program: An 8-week program, which addresses major areas of deficit in ADHD; namely, attention (the ability to concentrate and focus), inhibition (the ability to control ones behaviors), and memory (the ability to remember information).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Attention Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Attention control group: An 8-week program which provides education regarding several topics relevant for preschool children including nutrition, sleep, temperament, etc.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Executive Training of Attention and Metacognition (ETAM)</intervention_name>
    <description>ETAM is an 8-week intervention involving weekly concurrent child (n=~6 per group) and parent intervention groups. The ETAM groups will be 1 hour in length (except for the first session which will be 2 hours).</description>
    <arm_group_label>ETAM group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Attention Control</intervention_name>
    <description>Attention Control is an 8-week intervention involving weekly concurrent child (n=~6 per group) and parent groups that control for the effects of attention. The groups will be 1 hour in length (except for the first session which will be 2 hours).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Attention Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female, ages 3.0-4.11 years

          -  Outpatients, enrolled in a structured educational setting

          -  At risk for ADHD

          -  Parent or teacher rated BRIEF T-score &gt; 60 on at least 1 subscale

          -  Not in other psychosocial interventions

          -  Medication free at time of the intervention

          -  English-speaking

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children with significant impairment will be referred for more intensive treatment.

          -  Pervasive developmental disorders

          -  Serious head injury or unstable medical or neurological conditions

          -  Judged by one of the investigators to be acutely suicidal or homicidal, or at
             imminent risk of injuring self or others or causing significant damage to property

          -  Children with an Intelligence Quotient (IQ) &lt;85 will be excluded to avoid confounds
             related to intellectual functioning
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>5 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leanne Tamm, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Leanne Tamm, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>513-803-3176</phone>
    <email>leanne.tamm@cchmc.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sarah Brenner, B.A.</last_name>
    <phone>513-803-1345</phone>
    <email>sarah.brenner@cchmc.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Leanne Tamm, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 18, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 10, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Executive function</keyword>
  <keyword>Preschooler</keyword>
  <keyword>Metacognition</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Attention Deficit Disorder with Hyperactivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperkinesis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
