<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="105853">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01837862</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CCMC1311</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01837862</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Study of Mebendazole to Treat Pediatric Low-Grade Gliomas</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I and II Pilot Study of Mebendazole in Combination With Vincristine, Carboplatin, and Temozolomide in Children With Low-Grade Gliomas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mark Atlas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>North Shore Long Island Jewish Health System</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a study to determine the safety and efficacy of the drug, mebendazole, when used in
      combination with three additional chemotherapy agents, vincristine, carboplatin, and
      temozolomide, for the treatment of pediatric brain tumors.  Mebendazole is a drug used to
      treat infections with intestinal parasites and has a long track record of safety in humans.
       Recently, it was discovered that mebendazole may be effective in treating cancer as well,
      in particular brain tumors. Studies using both cell cultures and mouse models demonstrated
      that mebendazole was effective in decreasing the growth of brain tumor cells.

      This study focuses on the treatment of a category of brain tumors called low-grade gliomas.
      Low-grade gliomas are tumors arising from the glial cells of the central nervous system and
      are characterized by slower, less aggressive growth than that of high-grade gliomas.  The
      category of low-grade glioma includes many subtypes.  One such subtype, pilomyxoid
      astrocytoma, is a grade II tumor which has an aggressive nature with an increased rate of
      recurrence and decreased survival rate compared to other low-grade gliomas.

      Low-grade gliomas are often able to be treated by observation alone if they receive a total
      surgical resection.  However, tumors which are only partially resected and continue to grow
      or cause symptoms, or those which recur following total resection require additional
      treatment, such as chemotherapy.  Due to their more aggressive nature, pilomyxoid
      astrocytomas, even when totally resected, will often be treated with chemotherapy.  The
      current first-line treatment at our institution for these low-grade gliomas involves a
      three-drug chemotherapy regimen of vincristine, carboplatin, and temozolomide.  However,
      based on our data from our own historical controls, over 50% of patients with pilomyxoid
      astrocytomas will continue to have disease progression while on this treatment.  We believe
      that mebendazole in combination with vincristine, carboplatin, and temozolomide may provide
      an additional therapeutic benefit with increased progression-free and overall survival for
      low-grade glioma patients, particularly for those with pilomyxoid astrocytomas.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pilomyxoid astrocytoma is a variant subtype of pilocytic astrocytoma, which follows a more
      variable and aggressive course than that of pilocytic astrocytomas with decreased duration
      of disease-free and overall survival. There is no current standard of care in treating
      patients with pilomyxoid astrocytoma. Surgery is often the primary treatment strategy if the
      tumor is amenable to resection.  However, gross total resection is often not possible due to
      the common locations of these lesions and the severe morbidity associated with aggressive
      resection. The long-term biological behavior of residual tumor often necessitates the use of
      adjuvant chemotherapy to improve disease progression and recurrence rates.  To date, there
      are no published clinical trials focused specifically on the treatment of pilomyxoid
      astrocytoma.

      In 2002, a Children's Oncology Group phase II pilot study was initiated to evaluate the
      combination of carboplatin, vincristine, and temozolomide in children with progressive or
      symptomatic low-grade gliomas. The full data from this study has yet to be released and the
      latest reports do not give outcome results specific to the group of patients with pilomyxoid
      astrocytomas. This regimen is the current first-line treatment used at our institution for
      children with pilomyxoid astrocytoma.  However, based on our own historical patient data,
      over 50% of patients with pilomyxoid astrocytoma will continue to progress while on this
      treatment.

      Mebendazole is a benzimidazole drug developed for the treatment of human parasitic
      infections. Recently, mebendazole has displayed efficacy in numerous cancer models including
      glioblastoma multiforme, an aggressive high-grade form of glioma. A mouse glioblastoma model
      demonstrated that mebendazole significantly inhibited tumor growth and extended mean
      survival by 63% compared to controls. The combination of mebendazole and temozolomide
      displayed a similar anti-tumor effect, prolonging survival by 72% over controls. The
      pre-clinical efficacy of mebendazole in glioblastoma multiforme, its ability to cross the
      blood brain barrier, and its track record of safety make mebendazole a strong candidate for
      the treatment of low-grade glioma.

      This is a phase I-II pilot study of mebendazole in combination with our current regimen of
      carboplatin, vincristine, and temozolomide for treatment of pediatric patients with
      pilomyxoid astrocytoma, and other progressive or symptomatic low-grade gliomas.  We believe
      that mebendazole in combination with our current regimen may provide an additional
      therapeutic benefit for low-grade glioma patients, particularly those with pilomyxoid
      astrocytoma.

      This pilot study includes both phase I and II portions.  The objective of the phase I
      portion is to determine if the standard dose of mebendazole 100 mg twice daily is
      &quot;well-tolerated&quot; when used in combination with the current three-drug regimen.  Mebendazole
      will be given in combination with carboplatin, vincristine, and temozolomide in cohorts of
      three patients in an effort to determine if this four-drug combination is &quot;well-tolerated&quot;.
      The four-drug regimen will be considered &quot;well-tolerated&quot; if none or one of the initial
      three-to-six enrolled patients has a severe adverse event related to therapy after one
      induction cycle (10 weeks) of treatment.

      In the phase II portion of the study, potential subjects will be offered the option to
      participate in the study, to receive mebendazole with the three other drugs (CVT+M). Those
      who do not wish to receive mebendazole will then be given the option to enroll as a control
      and receive the three current drugs alone (CVT). Treatment will take place over a period of
      70 weeks. After one cycle of induction chemotherapy (10 weeks duration), evaluation will be
      performed to assess response. Patients with stable disease or decreasing tumor size will
      continue maintenance therapy with an additional six 10-week maintenance cycles. Patients who
      demonstrate progression following the induction cycle will be taken off-study to continue
      treatment.  Following completion of therapy, patients will be monitored to assess event-free
      and overall survival.  Data will be compared between the CVT+M and CVT treatment arms.

      For the phase II portion of the study, the outcome variables of interest are
      progression-free and overall survival.  Survival will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier
      Product-Limit Method and compared using the log-rank test.  Patients who are lost to
      follow-up or who are alive at the end of the study will be considered 'censored' for the
      survival analysis.  Similarly, patients who have not progressed (or who have not died) as of
      their last known follow-up, will be considered 'censored' for the time-to-progression
      analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximally tolerated dose of Mebendazole in combination with Vincristine, Carboplatin, and Temozolomide</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed during the 10 week Induction cycle for each patient</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients enrolled on the phase I portion of the study will receive a standard dose of 100 mg of mebendazole twice daily in combination with vincristine, carboplatin and temozolomide. During a 10 week induction period, patients will be assessed for &quot;adverse events&quot; defined as grade III-IV non-hematologic toxicity that is beyond the expected toxicity from the standard regimen of vincristine, carboplatin, and temozolomide alone. If one or fewer of the patients experiences an adverse event during the 10 week trial period, then mebendazole 100 mg twice daily will be considered the maximally tolerated dose.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival of patients with pilomyxoid astrocytoma</measure>
    <time_frame>3-years post-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>3-year event-free survival (EFS) and overall survival (OS) of patients with pilomyxoid astrocytomas treated with carboplatin, vincristine, temozolomide, and mebendazole in combination following surgical resection, to the extent feasible.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival of patients with juvenile pilocytic astrocytomas</measure>
    <time_frame>3-years post-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>3-year event-free survival (EFS) and overall survival (OS) of patients with recurrent or progressive juvenile pilocytic astrocytomas treated with carboplatin, vincristine, temozolomide, and mebendazole in combination following surgical resection, to the extent feasible.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival of patients with optic pathway gliomas</measure>
    <time_frame>3-years post-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>3-year event-free survival (EFS) and overall survival (OS) of patients with symptomatic or progressive optic pathway gliomas (OPG) treated with carboplatin, vincristine, temozolomide, and mebendazole in combination following surgical resection, to the extent feasible.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) dissemination in pilomyxoid astrocytoma</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years post-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The frequency of tumor dissemination in the CSF of patients with pilomyxoid astrocytomas treated with carboplatin, vincristine, temozolomide, and mebendazole.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival of patients with pleomorphic xanthoastrocytomas</measure>
    <time_frame>3-years post-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>3-year event-free survival (EFS) and overall survival (OS) of patients with pleomorphic xanthoastrocytomas treated with carboplatin, vincristine, temozolomide, and mebendazole in combination following surgical resection, to the extent feasible.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Pilomyxoid Astrocytoma</condition>
  <condition>Pilocytic Astrocytoma</condition>
  <condition>Glioma, Astrocytic</condition>
  <condition>Optic Nerve Glioma</condition>
  <condition>Pleomorphic Xanthoastrocytoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients on the control arm will receive seven 10-week cycles will consisting of carboplatin, vincristine, and temozolomide.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mebendazole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients on the Mebendazole arm will receive seven 10-week cycles of carboplatin, vincristine, temozolomide, and mebendazole.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mebendazole</intervention_name>
    <description>Mebendazole will be given at a dose of 100mg orally twice daily for 70 weeks over the course of treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mebendazole</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vincristine</intervention_name>
    <description>Vincristine will be dosed as per the following: For patients &lt; 12kg: 0.05 mg/kg; for patient &gt; 12kg: 1.5mg/m2 (maximal dose 2.0 mg).  Vincristine will be administered on Day 1 of  weeks 0,1,2,3,4,5 during the 10-week induction cycle and on Day 1 of Weeks 0,1,2 of the six 10-week maintenance cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Mebendazole</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>oncovin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Carboplatin will be dosed at 175 mg/m2.  Carboplatin will be administered on Day 1 of Weeks 0,1,2,3 of the 10-week Induction cycle, and on Day 1 of Weeks 0,1,2,3 during the six 10-week maintenance cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Mebendazole</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Paraplatin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Temozolomide</intervention_name>
    <description>Temozolomide will be dosed at 200 mg/m2/day.  Temozolomide will be given for 5 days during Week 6 of the 10-week induction cycle and for 5 days during Week 6 of the six 10-week maintenance cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Mebendazole</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Temodar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≤ 21 years

          2. Timing of therapy

               1. Patients must be enrolled before treatment begins.  Treatment must start
                  within 14 days of study enrollment.

               2. Patients with pilomyxoid astrocytomas and pleomorphic xanthoastrocytoma must be
                  newly diagnosed and start therapy within 28 days of diagnostic biopsy.

               3. Patients pilocytic astrocytomas and optic pathway gliomas who are observed and
                  later noted to have:

                    -  progression on imaging studies, or

                    -  progression of symptoms, or

                    -  appearance of new symptoms are eligible, provided that the patients have
                       previous diagnostic biopsy of pilocytic astrocytoma or optic pathway
                       glioma, or MRI consistent with optic pathway glioma.  These patients do not
                       need another biopsy at the time of progression and therapy should start
                       within 4 weeks after progression.  These patients must have a baseline MRI
                       of the primary lesion not more than 30 days prior to initiation of therapy.

          3. Histological diagnosis:

               1. Pilomyxoid Astrocytomas

               2. Pleomorphic Xanthoastrocytomas, without anaplastic transformation

               3. Pilocytic Astrocytomas

               4. Optic Pathway Gliomas

                    -  Patients with optic pathway gliomas are eligible without biopsy, but must
                       have MRI consistent with OPG.

          4. Adequate hematologic, renal, liver function as demonstrated by laboratory values
             performed within 21 days, inclusive prior to administration to temozolomide:

               1. Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1,000/ul

               2. Hemoglobin ≥8.0 gm/dl

               3. Platelet count ≥ 100,000/ul

               4. Adequate Liver Function Defined As

                    -  Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) for age, and

                    -  Alanine Aminotransferase (ALT) &lt; 2.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) for age.

               5. Adequate Renal Function Defined As

                    -  Creatinine clearance or radioisotope glomerular filtration rate ≥
                       70ml/min/1.73m2

                    -  A normal serum creatinine based on age and gender

          5. Life expectancy ≥ 3 months

          6. Concurrent medications: It is recommended that patients are weaned off or are on a
             tapering dose of corticosteroids before starting therapy on study.

          7. Patient or legal guardian must give written, informed consent or assent (when
             applicable)

          8. Recent mothers must agree not to breast feed while receiving medications on study.
             All females of childbearing age must have a negative pregnancy test within two weeks
             of beginning study therapy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who received prior chemotherapy or radiotherapy for this tumor are excluded.

          2. Pregnant and Nursing Women are excluded as temozolomide is potentially mutagenic.

          3. Men &amp;Women who are sexually active and refuse birth control are excluded from
             participating in this study

          4. Patients who are unable to take oral medications because of significant vomiting will
             be excluded.

          5. Patients with Neurofibromatosis Type 1

          6. Patients who have known allergy to mebendazole or benzimidazole class drugs.

          7. Patients who have previously had a severe side effect, such as agranulocytosis and
             neutropenia, in conjunction with previous mebendazole or benzimidazole class drug for
             a parasitic infection .

          8. Patients who are taking metronidazole and cannot be safely moved to a different
             antibiotic greater than 7 days prior to starting mebendazole therapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark P Atlas, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>North Shore-LIJ</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mark P Atlas, MD</last_name>
    <phone>718-470-3460</phone>
    <email>matlas@nshs.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Derek R Hanson, MD</last_name>
    <phone>718-470-3460</phone>
    <email>dhanson3@nshs.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cohen Children's Medical Center of New York</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Hyde Park</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11040</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mark P Atlas, MD</last_name>
      <phone>718-470-3460</phone>
      <email>matlas@nshs.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Derek R Hanson, MD</last_name>
      <phone>7184703460</phone>
      <email>dhanson3@nshs.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark P Atlas, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Derek R Hanson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Arlene Redner, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alyssa Quinlan, PA</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tihan T, Fisher PG, Kepner JL, Godfraind C, McComb RD, Goldthwaite PT, Burger PC. Pediatric astrocytomas with monomorphous pilomyxoid features and a less favorable outcome. J Neuropathol Exp Neurol. 1999 Oct;58(10):1061-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10515229</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Komotar RJ, Mocco J, Jones JE, Zacharia BE, Tihan T, Feldstein NA, Anderson RC. Pilomyxoid astrocytoma: diagnosis, prognosis, and management. Neurosurg Focus. 2005 Jun 15;18(6A):E7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16048293</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paraskevopoulos D, Patsalas I, Karkavelas G, Foroglou N, Magras I, Selviaridis P. Pilomyxoid astrocytoma of the cervical spinal cord in a child with rapid progression into glioblastoma: case report and literature review. Childs Nerv Syst. 2011 Feb;27(2):313-21. doi: 10.1007/s00381-010-1171-5. Epub 2010 May 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20461521</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Komotar RJ, Carson BS, Rao C, Chaffee S, Goldthwaite PT, Tihan T. Pilomyxoid astrocytoma of the spinal cord: report of three cases. Neurosurgery. 2005;56(1):191.</citation>
    <PMID>15617606</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bauman G, Lote K, Larson D, Stalpers L, Leighton C, Fisher B, Wara W, MacDonald D, Stitt L, Cairncross JG. Pretreatment factors predict overall survival for patients with low-grade glioma: a recursive partitioning analysis. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 1999 Nov 1;45(4):923-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10571199</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Desai KI, Nadkarni TD, Muzumdar DP, Goel A. Prognostic factors for cerebellar astrocytomas in children: a study of 102 cases. Pediatr Neurosurg. 2001 Dec;35(6):311-7.</citation>
    <PMID>11786699</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gajjar A, Sanford RA, Heideman R, Jenkins JJ, Walter A, Li Y, Langston JW, Muhlbauer M, Boyett JM, Kun LE. Low-grade astrocytoma: a decade of experience at St. Jude Children's Research Hospital. J Clin Oncol. 1997 Aug;15(8):2792-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9256121</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wisoff JH, Boyett JM, Berger MS, Brant C, Li H, Yates AJ, McGuire-Cullen P, Turski PA, Sutton LN, Allen JC, Packer RJ, Finlay JL. Current neurosurgical management and the impact of the extent of resection in the treatment of malignant gliomas of childhood: a report of the Children's Cancer Group trial no. CCG-945. J Neurosurg. 1998 Jul;89(1):52-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9647172</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Finlay JL, Wisoff JH. The impact of extent of resection in the management of malignant gliomas of childhood. Childs Nerv Syst. 1999 Nov;15(11-12):786-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10603023</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pollack IF, Claassen D, al-Shboul Q, Janosky JE, Deutsch M. Low-grade gliomas of the cerebral hemispheres in children: an analysis of 71 cases. J Neurosurg. 1995 Apr;82(4):536-47.</citation>
    <PMID>7897512</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Packer RJ, Ater J, Allen J, Phillips P, Geyer R, Nicholson HS, Jakacki R, Kurczynski E, Needle M, Finlay J, Reaman G, Boyett JM. Carboplatin and vincristine chemotherapy for children with newly diagnosed progressive low-grade gliomas. J Neurosurg. 1997 May;86(5):747-54.</citation>
    <PMID>9126887</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Conway PD, Oechler HW, Kun LE, Murray KJ. Importance of histologic condition and treatment of pediatric cerebellar astrocytoma. Cancer. 1991 Jun 1;67(11):2772-5.</citation>
    <PMID>1851047</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fisher BJ, Leighton CC, Vujovic O, Macdonald DR, Stitt L. Results of a policy of surveillance alone after surgical management of pediatric low grade gliomas. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2001 Nov 1;51(3):704-10.</citation>
    <PMID>11597812</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Duffner PK, Horowitz ME, Krischer JP, Friedman HS, Burger PC, Cohen ME, Sanford RA, Mulhern RK, James HE, Freeman CR, et al. Postoperative chemotherapy and delayed radiation in children less than three years of age with malignant brain tumors. N Engl J Med. 1993 Jun 17;328(24):1725-31.</citation>
    <PMID>8388548</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brown MT, Friedman HS, Oakes WJ, Boyko OB, Hockenberger B, Schold SC Jr. Chemotherapy for pilocytic astrocytomas. Cancer. 1993 May 15;71(10):3165-72.</citation>
    <PMID>8490847</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gajjar A, Bhargava R, Jenkins JJ, Heideman R, Sanford RA, Langston JW, Walter AW, Kuttesch JF, Muhlbauer M, Kun LE. Low-grade astrocytoma with neuraxis dissemination at diagnosis. J Neurosurg. 1995 Jul;83(1):67-71.</citation>
    <PMID>7782852</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ceppa EP, Bouffet E, Griebel R, Robinson C, Tihan T. The pilomyxoid astrocytoma and its relationship to pilocytic astrocytoma: report of a case and a critical review of the entity. J Neurooncol. 2007 Jan;81(2):191-6. Epub 2006 Jul 19.</citation>
    <PMID>16850101</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tsugu H, Oshiro S, Yanai F, Komatsu F, Abe H, Fukushima T, Nomura Y, Matsumoto S, Nabeshima K, Takano K, Utsunomiya H. Management of pilomyxoid astrocytomas: our experience. Anticancer Res. 2009 Mar;29(3):919-26.</citation>
    <PMID>19414328</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lefkowitz IB, Packer RJ, Sutton LN, Siegel KR, Bruce DA, Evans AE, Schut L. Results of the treatment of children with recurrent gliomas with lomustine and vincristine. Cancer. 1988 Mar 1;61(5):896-902.</citation>
    <PMID>3338054</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Petronio J, Edwards MS, Prados M, Freyberger S, Rabbitt J, Silver P, Levin VA. Management of chiasmal and hypothalamic gliomas of infancy and childhood with chemotherapy. J Neurosurg. 1991 May;74(5):701-8.</citation>
    <PMID>1901597</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Friedman HS, Krischer JP, Burger P, Oakes WJ, Hockenberger B, Weiner MD, Falletta JM, Norris D, Ragab AH, Mahoney DH Jr, et al. Treatment of children with progressive or recurrent brain tumors with carboplatin or iproplatin: a Pediatric Oncology Group randomized phase II study. J Clin Oncol. 1992 Feb;10(2):249-56.</citation>
    <PMID>1732426</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Packer RJ, Sutton LN, Bilaniuk LT, Radcliffe J, Rosenstock JG, Siegel KR, Bunin GR, Savino PJ, Bruce DA, Schut L. Treatment of chiasmatic/hypothalamic gliomas of childhood with chemotherapy: an update. Ann Neurol. 1988 Jan;23(1):79-85.</citation>
    <PMID>3345069</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Janss AJ, Grundy R, Cnaan A, Savino PJ, Packer RJ, Zackai EH, Goldwein JW, Sutton LN, Radcliffe J, Molloy PT, et al. Optic pathway and hypothalamic/chiasmatic gliomas in children younger than age 5 years with a 6-year follow-up. Cancer. 1995 Feb 15;75(4):1051-9.</citation>
    <PMID>7842408</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sievert AJ, Fisher MJ. Pediatric low-grade gliomas. J Child Neurol. 2009 Nov;24(11):1397-408. doi: 10.1177/0883073809342005. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19841428</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burkhard C, Di Patre PL, Schüler D, Schüler G, Yaşargil MG, Yonekawa Y, Lütolf UM, Kleihues P, Ohgaki H. A population-based study of the incidence and survival rates in patients with pilocytic astrocytoma. J Neurosurg. 2003 Jun;98(6):1170-4.</citation>
    <PMID>12816259</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wallner KE, Gonzales MF, Edwards MS, Wara WM, Sheline GE. Treatment results of juvenile pilocytic astrocytoma. J Neurosurg. 1988 Aug;69(2):171-6.</citation>
    <PMID>3392563</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mamelak AN, Prados MD, Obana WG, Cogen PH, Edwards MS. Treatment options and prognosis for multicentric juvenile pilocytic astrocytoma. J Neurosurg. 1994 Jul;81(1):24-30.</citation>
    <PMID>8207524</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dutton JJ. Gliomas of the anterior visual pathway. Surv Ophthalmol. 1994 Mar-Apr;38(5):427-52. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8009427</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Opocher E, Kremer LC, Da Dalt L, van de Wetering MD, Viscardi E, Caron HN, Perilongo G. Prognostic factors for progression of childhood optic pathway glioma: a systematic review. Eur J Cancer. 2006 Aug;42(12):1807-16. Epub 2006 Jun 30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16809032</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cappelli C, Grill J, Raquin M, Pierre-Kahn A, Lellouch-Tubiana A, Terrier-Lacombe MJ, Habrand JL, Couanet D, Brauner R, Rodriguez D, Hartmann O, Kalifa C. Long-term follow up of 69 patients treated for optic pathway tumours before the chemotherapy era. Arch Dis Child. 1998 Oct;79(4):334-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9875044</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Silva MM, Goldman S, Keating G, Marymont MA, Kalapurakal J, Tomita T. Optic pathway hypothalamic gliomas in children under three years of age: the role of chemotherapy. Pediatr Neurosurg. 2000 Sep;33(3):151-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11096362</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nicholson HS, Kretschmar CS, Krailo M, Bernstein M, Kadota R, Fort D, Friedman H, Harris MB, Tedeschi-Blok N, Mazewski C, Sato J, Reaman GH. Phase 2 study of temozolomide in children and adolescents with recurrent central nervous system tumors: a report from the Children's Oncology Group. Cancer. 2007 Oct 1;110(7):1542-50.</citation>
    <PMID>17705175</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gil-Grande LA, Boixeda D, Garcia-Hoz F, Barcena R, Lledo A, Suarez E, Pascasio JM, Moreira V. Treatment of liver hydatid disease with mebendazole: a prospective study of thirteen cases. Am J Gastroenterol. 1983 Sep;78(9):584-8.</citation>
    <PMID>6613972</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bai RY, Staedtke V, Aprhys CM, Gallia GL, Riggins GJ. Antiparasitic mebendazole shows survival benefit in 2 preclinical models of glioblastoma multiforme. Neuro Oncol. 2011 Sep;13(9):974-82. doi: 10.1093/neuonc/nor077. Epub 2011 Jul 15.</citation>
    <PMID>21764822</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mukhopadhyay T, Sasaki J, Ramesh R, Roth JA. Mebendazole elicits a potent antitumor effect on human cancer cell lines both in vitro and in vivo. Clin Cancer Res. 2002 Sep;8(9):2963-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12231542</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sasaki J, Ramesh R, Chada S, Gomyo Y, Roth JA, Mukhopadhyay T. The anthelmintic drug mebendazole induces mitotic arrest and apoptosis by depolymerizing tubulin in non-small cell lung cancer cells. Mol Cancer Ther. 2002 Nov;1(13):1201-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12479701</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Doudican N, Rodriguez A, Osman I, Orlow SJ. Mebendazole induces apoptosis via Bcl-2 inactivation in chemoresistant melanoma cells. Mol Cancer Res. 2008 Aug;6(8):1308-15. doi: 10.1158/1541-7786.MCR-07-2159. Epub 2008 Jul 30.</citation>
    <PMID>18667591</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dobrosotskaya IY, Hammer GD, Schteingart DE, Maturen KE, Worden FP. Mebendazole monotherapy and long-term disease control in metastatic adrenocortical carcinoma. Endocr Pract. 2011 May-Jun;17(3):e59-62. doi: 10.4158/EP10390.CR.</citation>
    <PMID>21454232</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vutova K, Mechkov G, Vachkov P, Petkov R, Georgiev P, Handjiev S, Ivanov A, Todorov T. Effect of mebendazole on human cystic echinococcosis: the role of dosage and treatment duration. Ann Trop Med Parasitol. 1999 Jun;93(4):357-65.</citation>
    <PMID>10656037</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kepes JJ, Rubinstein LJ, Eng LF. Pleomorphic xanthoastrocytoma: a distinctive meningocerebral glioma of young subjects with relatively favorable prognosis. A study of 12 cases. Cancer. 1979 Nov;44(5):1839-52.</citation>
    <PMID>498051</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rao AA, Laack NN, Giannini C, Wetmore C. Pleomorphic xanthoastrocytoma in children and adolescents. Pediatr Blood Cancer. 2010 Aug;55(2):290-4. doi: 10.1002/pbc.22490.</citation>
    <PMID>20582976</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Giannini C, Scheithauer BW, Burger PC, Brat DJ, Wollan PC, Lach B, O'Neill BP. Pleomorphic xanthoastrocytoma: what do we really know about it? Cancer. 1999 May 1;85(9):2033-45.</citation>
    <PMID>10223246</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 22, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 16, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>North Shore Long Island Jewish Health System</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mark Atlas</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Childhood Brain and Spinal Cord Tumor Program, Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pilomyxoid astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Pilocytic Astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>Optic Nerve Glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>mebendazole</keyword>
  <keyword>Pleomorphic Xanthoastrocytoma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Astrocytoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Optic Nerve Glioma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Mebendazole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Piperazine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vincristine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Piperazine citrate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Temozolomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dacarbazine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
