<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="95631">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01717456</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11-1569</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HS018695</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01717456</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Educational-Medical-Behavioral Treatment of Fecal Incontinence</brief_title>
  <acronym>FIX</acronym>
  <official_title>Conservative Treatment of Fecal Incontinence: Community-Based Effectiveness Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In previous studies at a university referral center the investigators demonstrated that a
      multicomponent conservative treatment for fecal incontinence was effective. The treatment
      combines patient education with medical management of diarrhea and constipation plus
      behavioral training. The purpose of this study is to determine whether this treatment is
      effective when delivered by home health care nurses to frail elderly patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Fecal incontinence (FI) affects 9% of U.S. adults and occurs weekly or more often in 2.7%.
      Prevalence increases with age reaching 15% by 70 years. FI has a devastating impact on
      quality of life and substantially increases caregiver burden when patients have comorbid
      conditions requiring caregiver assistance. The investigators propose an effectiveness trial
      whose overall goal is to determine whether a conservative intervention which has been shown
      to be effective in single-site studies will sustain its efficacy when disseminated to a home
      bound population by home health care nurses. The treatment includes patient education about
      the physiology of how continence is maintained, pelvic floor exercises, behavioral
      strategies for preventing FI, and use of fiber or nonprescription medication to treat
      diarrhea or constipation. To minimize drift when the treatment is disseminated to a large
      group of providers, patient education and other basic components of treatment are included
      in a printed training manual and are available to nurse providers on a website; however,
      nurse supervision to individualize treatment remains important. The study will be carried
      out in 8 counties in central North Carolina which are served by the University of North
      Carolina Home Health Care and Rex Home Health Care agencies (partners in this study). Nurses
      in these agencies will be randomly assigned to two groups. For the first two years all
      patients of the nurses in one group will receive the active intervention while all patients
      of nurses in the other group will receive usual care plus a training manual and symptom
      monitoring to control for expectancy. After two years, all patients in these home health
      care agencies will receive the active intervention. After excluding patients with severe
      cognitive impairment and those with stomas, the investigators estimate 252 - 340 patients
      with FI who are over age 50 will receive treatment (at least 189 in active treatment and 63
      controls). Specific aims are (1) to show that the active treatment is more effective than
      the control treatment for improving FI severity, patient quality of life, and caregiver
      burden, and that improvements are maintained for at least 6 months; (2) to identify
      moderators of treatment effectiveness (candidate variables are cognitive status, mobility
      impairment, willingness of family caregiver to assist with treatment, anxiety, depression,
      age, and race); and (3) to explore whether successful treatment of FI reduces the risk of
      nursing home referral.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fecal Incontinence Severity Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 6 weeks after treatment onset</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The FISI requires the patient to report the frequency of occurrence of 4 types of fecal incontinence (solid, liquid, mucus, and gas incontinence) in the past month. These four responses are multiplied by empirically derived patient weights and the values are added together.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Zarit Caregiver Burden Interview</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 6 weeks after treatment onset</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Validated questionnaire developed to assess the psychosocial and health burden experienced by a family caregiver of the identified patient.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Manchester Health Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 6 weeks after treatment onset</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Quality of life scale specific to fecal incontinence. This scale was validated for interviewer administration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adequate relief of fecal incontinence</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks after treatment onset</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>&quot;Compared to before you started home health care, have you experienced adequate relief of your fecal incontinence symptoms? [Responses: yes or no]&quot;.
(This is the same secondary outcome measure that was used in a previous trial of conservative treatment of fecal incontinence.)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fecal incontinence frequency</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 6 weeks after treatment onset</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>OASIS question M1620: Bowel incontinence frequency. Response options are:
0 - Very rarely or never has bowel incontinence
- Less than once weekly
- One to three times weekly
- Four to six times weekly
- On a daily basis
- More often than once daily</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urinary incontinence</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 6 weeks after treatment onset</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>OASIS question M1610: Urinary incontinence or urinary catheter presence. Response options are:
0 - No incontinence or catheter (includes anuria or ostomy for urinary drainage)
- Patient is incontinent
- Patient requires a urinary catheter (i.e., external, indwelling, intermittent, suprapubic)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Admission to nursing home</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to  follow-up 7-8 months following treatment onset</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Was patient admitted to a nursing home for one or more days at any time between enrollment and follow-up 7-8 months after treatment onset.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospitalizations</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to follow up 7-8 months after treatment onset</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Extracted from medical record by research assistant</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Emergency department visits</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to follow up 7-8 months after treatment onset</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Extracted from medical record by research assistant.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Outpatient clinic visits</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to follow up 7-8 months after treatment onset</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Extracted from medical record by research assistant</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fecal Incontinence Severity Index (FISI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to follow-up 7-8 months after treatment.onset</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The FISI requires the patient to report the frequency of occurrence of 4 types of fecal incontinence (solid, liquid, mucus, and gas incontinence) in the past month. These four responses are multiplied by empirically derived patient weights and the values are added together.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Zarit Caregiver Burden Interview</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to follow up 7-8 months after treatment onset</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Validated questionnaire developed to assess the psychosocial and health burden experienced by a family caregiver of the identified patient.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Manchester Health Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to follow up 7-8 months following treatment onset</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Quality of life scale specific to fecal incontinence. This scale was validated for interviewer administration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fecal incontinence frequency</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to follow up 7-8 months after treatment onset</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>OASIS question M1620: Bowel incontinence frequency. Response options are:
0 - Very rarely or never has bowel incontinence
- Less than once weekly
- One to three times weekly
- Four to six times weekly
- On a daily basis
- More often than once daily</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive status</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>OASIS question M1700: Cognitive functioning: Patient's current (day of assessment) level of alertness, orientation, comprehension, concentration, and immediate memory for simple commands. Measure as treatment moderator. Response categories are:
0 - Alert/oriented, able to focus and shift attention, comprehends and recalls task directions independently.
- Requires prompting (cuing, repetition, reminders) only under stressful or unfamiliar conditions.
- Requires assistance and some direction in specific situations (e.g., on all tasks involving shifting of attention), or consistently requires low stimulus environment due to distractibility.
- Requires considerable assistance in routine situations. Is not alert and oriented or is unable to shift attention and recall directions more than half the time.
- Totally dependent due to disturbances uch as constant disorientation, coma, persistent vegetative stte, or delirium.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Ambulation/locomotion</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 6 weeks after treatment onset</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>OASIS question M1860: Ambulation/locomotion: Current ability t walk safely, once in a standing position, or use a wheelchair, once in a seated position, on a variety of surfaces. Measure as a moderator of treatment effects. Responses:
0 - Able to independently walk on even and uneven surfaces and negotiate stairs with or without railings (i.e., needs no human assistance or assistive device).
... 6 - Bedfast, unable to ambulate or be up in a chair.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Ability to reach toilet</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 6 weeks after treatment onset</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>OASIS question M1840: Toilet transferring: Current ability to get to and from the toilet or bedside commode safely and transfer on and off toilet/commode. Measure as moderator of treatment outcomes. Responses:
0 - Able to get to and from teh toilet and transfer independently with or without a device.
... 4 - Is totally dependent in toileting.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to end of 6 weeks after treatment onset</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>OASIS question M1720: When anxious (reported or observed within the last 14 days). Measure as moderator of treatment effects. Responses are:
0 - None of the time
- Less often than daily
- Daily, but not constantly
- All of the time</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 6 weeks after treatment onset</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>OASIS question M1730: Depression Screening. Measure as a moderator of treatment effectiveness.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Patient's living situation</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 6 weeks after treatment onset</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>OASIS question M1100: Patient living situation: This is a measure that combines who lives with the patient and the frequency that assistance is available to them throughout the day. Responses are coded on a 1-15 scale. Measure this as a moderator of treatment effectiveness.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Caregiver's ability and willingness to assist with ADLs</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 6 weeks after treatment onset</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>OASIS question M2100, item A: Types and sources of assistance for ADLs. Measure as moderator of treatment effectiveness. Responses range from &quot;No assistance needed in this area&quot; to &quot;Assistance needed, but no Caregivers available&quot;.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">252</enrollment>
  <condition>Fecal Incontinence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Educational-Medical-Behavioral</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Educational-Medical-Behavioral intervention includes education, fiber supplements [Metamucil 1-4 packets (3.4-13.6 g)/day], laxatives or anti-diarrheals [Miralax 1-2 packets (17-34 g)/day or Imodium 0.5-2 tablets (1-4 mg)/day], pelvic floor muscle exercises [100 10-second squeezes/day], tips on how to prevent fecal incontinence, daily diary, and protective pads or garments [as needed].</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard care includes fiber supplements 1-4 packets (3.4-13.6 g)/day], daily diary, and protective pads or garments [as needed].</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Education</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient and caregiver will be taught which muscles are used in continence and defecation through the use of a training manual and anatomical drawings.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Educational-Medical-Behavioral</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fiber supplements</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients and caregivers will be taught to use fiber supplements to normalize stool consistency if patient reports diarrhea or constipation. Fiber supplements will be in the form of Metamucil beginning with 3.4 grams per day and increasing up to 13.6 grams per day if needed to control stool consistency.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Educational-Medical-Behavioral</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laxatives or anti-diarrheals</intervention_name>
    <description>Miralax at a dose of one packet (17 grams) daily may be used for constipation if unresponsive to fiber. Dose may be titrated up to two packets (34 grams) daily if needed.
Imodium at a starting dose of 2 mg/day may be used for diarrhea if unresponsive to fiber. Dose of Imodium may be titrated down to 1 mg or up to 4 mg if needed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Educational-Medical-Behavioral</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Miralax (polyethylene glycol)</other_name>
    <other_name>Imodium (loperamide)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pelvic floor muscle exercises</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be taught how to perform pelvic floor muscle contractions during digital rectal examination by a nurse. They will be asked to squeeze 100 times daily.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Educational-Medical-Behavioral</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tips on how to prevent fecal incontinence</intervention_name>
    <description>Examples of behavioral tips are &quot;Walk, don't run to the toilet&quot; and &quot;Squeeze before you lift objects or sneeze&quot;.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Educational-Medical-Behavioral</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Daily diary</intervention_name>
    <description>Both groups will keep a daily diary, but amount of detail differs: Active comparator group records bowel accidents, bowel movements, Bristol Stool ratings of stool consistency, number of times they do pelvic floor exercises, study medications, and comments for the nurse to read. Placebo comparator group records only bowel accidents, bowel movements, and Bristol Stool scores.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Educational-Medical-Behavioral</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Protective pads or garments</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Educational-Medical-Behavioral</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Continence pads</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Self-reported fecal incontinence at least once a month

          -  Family caregiver available and willing to participate in treatment sessions and
             willing to assist patient with study procedures

          -  Patients and caregivers willing to be interviewed by a research assistant in their
             home on three occasions

          -  Onset of fecal incontinence more than 3 months previously (i.e., not transient fecal
             incontinence)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has a stoma or fecal incontinence status is unknown

          -  Has fecal incontinence less than monthly

          -  Severe cognitive impairment (response of 4 on OASIS question M1700)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William E Whitehead, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599-7080</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 8, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 15, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>William (Bill) Whitehead, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine and Adjunct Professor of OBGYN</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Fecal incontinence</keyword>
  <keyword>Frail elders</keyword>
  <keyword>Home health care</keyword>
  <keyword>Nurse</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient education</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fecal Incontinence</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antidiarrheals</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Loperamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Laxatives</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cathartics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
