<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="14797">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01691508</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>115575</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01691508</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mepolizumab Steroid-Sparing Study in Subjects With Severe Refractory Asthma</brief_title>
  <official_title>MEA115575: A Randomised, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Parallel-Group, Multicenter Study of Mepolizumab Adjunctive Therapy to Reduce Steroid Use in Subjects With Severe Refractory Asthma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <authority>France: Agence Nationale de Sécurité du Médicament et des produits de santé</authority>
    <authority>Poland: URZAD REJESTRACJI PRODUKTOW LECZNICZYCH, WYROBOW MEDYCZNYCH I PRODUKTOW BIOBOJCZYCH</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Mexico: Comision Federal para la Proteccion contra Riesgos Sanitarios (COFEPRIS)</authority>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <authority>Netherlands: De Centrale Commissie Mensgebonden Onderzoek</authority>
    <authority>Czech Republic: Statni ustav pro kontrolu leciv</authority>
    <authority>Australia: Therapeutic Goods Administration</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Pau-Ehrlich Institute</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled, parallel-group, multicenter study of
      mepolizumab in comparison with placebo in reducing Oral Corticosteroid (OCS) use in subjects
      with severe refractory asthma. The study consists of four phases, OCS Optimisation Phase
      (Week -8 to Week 0), and the double-blind treatment period divided into an Induction Phase
      (Week 0 to Week 4), OCS Reduction Phase (Week 5 upto Week 20) followed by Maintenance Phase
      (Week 20 to Week 24). During the Optimisation Phase the investigator will adjust the OCS
      (prednisone/prednisolone) dose according to the Optimisation titration schedule based on a
      review of Asthma Control Questionnaire (ACQ)-5 score and exacerbation. In the Induction
      Phase subjects will be randomized 1:1 (approximately 60 per arm) to receive either
      mepolizumab (100 mg) administered subcutaneously (SC) or placebo every 4 weeks in addition
      to their existing maintenance asthma therapy with the lowest dose of OCS from Optimisation
      Phase. The Induction Phase will allow sufficient time for those subjects randomised to the
      mepolizumab arm to achieve a decrease in the eosinophilic inflammation prior to the
      reduction in OCS. During the Reduction Phase, subjects will continue receiving 100 mg
      mepolizumab/placebo every 4 weeks and the OCS dose reduction will be done every 4 weeks
      using the reduction titration schedule based on a review of eDiary parameters recorded by
      the subject, the subjects' exacerbation history, and a review of the signs and symptoms of
      adrenal insufficiency. In the Maintenance Phase subjects will be maintained without any
      further OCS dose adjustment. Subjects who complete the 24 week double-blind period and meet
      the eligibility criteria, will be offered the opportunity to participate in an open label
      extension (OLE) study otherwise they will return for a Follow-up Visit 12 weeks after their
      last dose of double blind study treatment. At each clinic visit, adverse events, safety
      labs, spirometery parameters and exacerbations will be assessed. The pharmacokinetic samples
      will be collected in the beginning of the treatment, prior to last dose, at the end of study
      (exit visit) and the follow up.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent reduction of OCS dose during weeks 20 to 24 compared with the Baseline dose, while maintaining asthma control</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percent change from Baseline in OCS dose during weeks 20 to 24 will be calculated as the dose at Baseline minus the dose during weeks 20 to 24 divided by Baseline dose multiplied by 100.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with &gt;=50% reduction in daily OCS dose, compared with Baseline dose, during weeks 20 to 24, while maintaining asthma control</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of subjects who had &gt;=50% reduction in daily OCS dose during weeks 20 to 24 from Baseline will be considered.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with&lt;=5.0 mg reduction in daily OCS dose during weeks 20 to 24, while maintaining asthma control</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of subjects who had &lt;=5.0 mg reduction in daily OCS dose during weeks 20 to 24 as compared with Baseline dose will be considered.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with a total reduction of OCS dose during weeks 20 to 24, while maintaining asthma control</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of subjects who had total reduction in OCS dose during weeks 20 to 24 as compared with Baseline dose will be considered.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median percentage reduction from Baseline in daily OCS dose during weeks 20 to 24, while maintaining asthma control</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The median of percentage reduction in daily OCS dose during weeks 20 to 24 from Baseline will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of mepolizumab in subjects with severe refractory asthma with elevated eosinophils as evaluated by adverse events (AE)s including both systemic and local site reactions</measure>
    <time_frame>32 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety and tolerability parameters include AEs including both systemic (i.e., allergic/ Immunoglobulin E [IgE]-mediated and non-allergic) and local site reactions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of mepolizumab in subjects with severe refractory asthma with elevated eosinophils as evaluated by clinical chemistry, haematological parameters, blood glucose, body weight, glycosylated haemoglobin (HbA1c) and vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>32 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety and tolerability parameters include clinical chemistry, haematological parameters, blood glucose, body weight, HbA1c and vital signs (pulse rate and systolic and diastolic blood pressure).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events typical of and associated with the chronic use maintenance OCS</measure>
    <time_frame>32 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The AEs typical of and associated with the chronic use maintenance OCS were recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from Baseline in the QTc(F) of 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG)</measure>
    <time_frame>32 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>QTc(F) of ECG is QT interval corrected by Fridericia's method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from Baseline in QTc(B) of 12-lead ECG</measure>
    <time_frame>32 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>QTc(B) of ECG is QT interval corrected by Bazett's method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum change from Baseline for QTc(F) and QTc(B) of 12-lead ECG</measure>
    <time_frame>32 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The maximum change from Baseline for QTc(F) and QTc(B) of 12-lead ECG.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">135</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mepolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Mepolizumab 100 mg subcutaneous once every 4 weeks upto Week 20</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo subcutaneous once every 4 weeks upto Week 20</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mepolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Mepolizumab is a fully humanised Immunoglobulin G antibody (IgG1, kappa) with human heavy and light chain frameworks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mepolizumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Will be available as an equivalent volume of 0.9% sodium chloride.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Informed Consent and Study Compliance: Subjects must be able to give written informed
             consent prior to participation in the study, which will include the ability to comply
             with the requirements and restrictions listed in the consent form.

          -  Systemic Corticosteroids: Requirement for regular treatment with maintenance systemic
             corticosteroids in the 6 months prior to Visit 1 and using a stable oral
             corticosteroid dose for 4 weeks prior to Visit 1. Subjects must be taking 5.0 to 35
             mg/day of prednisone or equivalent at Visit 1 and must agree to switch to study
             required prednisone/prednisolone as their oral corticosteroid and use it per protocol
             for the duration of the study.

          -  Inhaled Corticosteroids: Requirement for regular treatment with high dose inhaled
             corticosteroid in the 6 months prior to Visit 1. For 18 years of age and older:
             inhaled corticosteroid (ICS) dose must be &gt;=880 microgram (µg)/day fluticasone
             propionate (FP) (ex-actuator) or equivalent daily. For ICS/ long acting beta2 agonist
             (LABA) combination preparations, the highest approved maintenance dose in the local
             country will meet this ICS criterion. For ages 12 to 17: ICS dose must be &gt;=440
             μg/day FP (ex-actuator) or equivalent daily.

          -  Controller Medication: Current treatment with an additional controller medication for
             at least 3 months OR documentation of having used and failed an additional controller
             medication for at least 3 successive months during the prior 12 months [e.g., LABA,
             leukotriene receptor antagonist (LTRA), or theophylline].

          -  Eosinophilic Asthma: Prior documentation of eosinophilic asthma or high likelihood of
             eosinophilic asthma.

          -  FEV1: Persistent airflow obstruction as indicated by a pre-bronchodilator FEV1 &lt;80%
             predicted.

          -  Asthma: Evidence of asthma indicated by airway reversibility, hyperresponsiveness or
             airway variability.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Smoking history: Current smokers or former smokers with a smoking history of &gt;=10
             pack years.

          -  Concurrent Respiratory Disease: Presence of a clinically important lung condition
             other than asthma.

          -  Malignancy: A current malignancy or previous history of cancer in remission for less
             than 12 months prior screening

          -  Liver Disease: Unstable liver disease

          -  Cardiovascular: Subjects who have severe or clinically significant cardiovascular
             disease uncontrolled with standard treatment.

          -  Other Concurrent Medical Conditions: Subjects who have known, pre-existing,
             clinically significant endocrine, autoimmune, metabolic, neurological, renal,
             gastrointestinal, hepatic, haematological or any other system abnormalities that are
             uncontrolled with standard treatment.

          -  Eosinophilic Diseases: Subjects with other conditions that could lead to elevated
             eosinophils such as Hypereosiniophilic Syndromes, including Churg-Strauss Syndrome,
             or Eosinophilic Esophaghitis. Subjects with a known, pre-existing parasitic
             infestation within 6 months prior to Visit 1 are also to be excluded.

          -  ECG: ECG assessment QTcF &gt;=450 milliseconds (msec) or QTcF &gt;= 480 msec for subjects
             with Bundle Branch Block.

          -  Immunodeficiency: A known immunodeficiency (e.g. human immunodeficiency virus - HIV),
             other than that explained by the use of corticosteroids taken as therapy for asthma.

          -  Omalizumab Use: Subjects who have received omalizumab [Xolair] within 130 days of
             Visit 1.

          -  Other Monoclonal Antibodies: Subjects who have received any monoclonal antibody
             (other than Xolair) to treat inflammatory disease within 5 half-lives of Visit 1.

          -  Investigational Medications: Subjects who have received treatment with an
             investigational drug within the past 30 days or five terminal phase half-lives of the
             drug whichever is longer, prior to Visit 1 (this also includes investigational
             formulations of marketed products).

          -  Hypersensitivity: Subjects with a known allergy or intolerance to a monoclonal
             antibody or biologic.

          -  Pregnancy: Subjects who are pregnant or breastfeeding. Patients should not be
             enrolled if they plan to become pregnant during the time of study participation.

          -  Alcohol/Substance Abuse: A history (or suspected history) of alcohol misuse or
             substance abuse within 2 years prior to Visit 1.

          -  Adherence: Subjects who have known evidence of lack of adherence to controller
             medications and/or ability to follow physician's recommendations.

          -  Previous participation: Subjects who have previously any study of mepolizumab and
             received Investigational Product.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Long Beach</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90808</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80206</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06520</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburg</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>PA 15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Spartanburg</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29303</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Lambton</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2305</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bedford Park</city>
        <state>South Australia</state>
        <zip>5042</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Parkville</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3050</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nedlands</city>
        <state>Western Australia</state>
        <zip>6009</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L8N 4A6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H2X 2P4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H4J 1C5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Quebec City</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>G1V 4G5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brno</city>
        <zip>625 00</zip>
        <country>Czech Republic</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Olomouc</city>
        <zip>775 20</zip>
        <country>Czech Republic</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Praha 4</city>
        <zip>140 59</zip>
        <country>Czech Republic</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Praha 8</city>
        <zip>180 01</zip>
        <country>Czech Republic</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gières</city>
        <zip>38610</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montpellier cedex 5</city>
        <zip>34295</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nantes cedex 1</city>
        <zip>44093</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris Cedex 18</city>
        <zip>75877</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Strasbourg</city>
        <zip>67091</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aschaffenburg</city>
        <state>Bayern</state>
        <zip>63739</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Potsdam</city>
        <state>Brandenburg</state>
        <zip>14478</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ruedersdorf</city>
        <state>Brandenburg</state>
        <zip>15562</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Frankfurt</city>
        <state>Hessen</state>
        <zip>60596</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gelnhausen</city>
        <state>Hessen</state>
        <zip>63571</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Neu isenburg</city>
        <state>Hessen</state>
        <zip>63263</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hannover</city>
        <state>Niedersachsen</state>
        <zip>30173</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mainz</city>
        <state>Rheinland-Pfalz</state>
        <zip>55131</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Luebeck</city>
        <state>Schleswig-Holstein</state>
        <zip>23552</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guadalajara</city>
        <state>Jalisco</state>
        <zip>44100</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zapopan</city>
        <state>Jalisco</state>
        <zip>45040</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <zip>1105 AZ</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leeuwarden</city>
        <zip>8934 AD</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rotterdam</city>
        <zip>3045 PM</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bialystok</city>
        <zip>15-044</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bialystok</city>
        <zip>15-010</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Krakow</city>
        <zip>31-024</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lodz</city>
        <zip>90-153</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leicester</city>
        <state>Leicestershire</state>
        <zip>LE3 9QP</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liverpool</city>
        <zip>L9 7AL</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newcastle upon Tyne</city>
        <zip>NE1 4LP</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Southampton</city>
        <zip>SO16 6YD</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>Czech Republic</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Mexico</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 22, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 20, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Safety</keyword>
  <keyword>Steroid Reduction</keyword>
  <keyword>Efficacy</keyword>
  <keyword>SB-240563</keyword>
  <keyword>Eosinophils</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of Life</keyword>
  <keyword>Mepolizumab</keyword>
  <keyword>Severe Refractory Asthma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
