<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="143091">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02125084</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SCRI GU 99</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02125084</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Enzalutamide Plus Everolimus in Men With Metastatic Castrate-Resistant Prostate Cancer and Previous Treatment With Docetaxel</brief_title>
  <official_title>Enzalutamide Plus Everolimus in Men With Metastatic Castrate-Resistant Prostate Cancer and Previous Treatment With Docetaxel: A Phase I Study With a Maximum Tolerated Dose Expansion Cohort</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>SCRI Development Innovations, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>SCRI Development Innovations, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the safety and efficacy of a novel combination of
      agents, enzalutamide and everolimus, for the treatment of patients with metastatic
      castrate-resistant prostate cancer who received prior therapy with docetaxel.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center, open-label, Phase I study with an expansion cohort, in patients with
      metastatic Castrate-Resistant Prostate Cancer (CRPC) who previously received docetaxel
      chemotherapy and have progressive disease at the time of study entry. The dose escalation
      phase of this study will establish the optimum daily dose of everolimus that can be
      delivered along with a standard daily dose of enzalutamide to patients with metastatic CRPC.
      Eligible patients must have evaluable (elevated PSA) or measurable disease (per RECIST
      v1.1). Following completion of the dose escalation phase, an additional cohort of patients
      will be treated at the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) to give preliminary information
      regarding the efficacy of this combination.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Escalating doses of everolimus will be tested with standard dose enzalutamide.</measure>
    <time_frame>6-8 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Establish the optimal daily dose of everolimus to be administered in conjunction with a standard daily dose of enzalutamide</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prostate-specific antigen (PSA) response rate decline of greater than 50 percent.</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Obtain preliminary information regarding the efficacy of the combination in the treatment of men with docetaxel-refractory metastatic prostate cancer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with serious and non-serious adverse events.</measure>
    <time_frame>every 4 weeks up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluate the safety of the combination  per CTCAE v4.0, every 4 weeks from date of first study treatment until the date of documented progression, up to 24 months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of everolimus in blood samples collected from patients at selected timepoints prior to everolimus dosing during the first 3 cycles of treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PSA response rate (decline of greater than 85 %)</measure>
    <time_frame>every 8 weeks up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to PSA progression</measure>
    <time_frame>every 8 weeks up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Restaging will occur every 8 weeks from date of first treatment until date of first PSA progression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Response Rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>every 8 weeks up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Soft tissue response rate [percentage of complete responders (CR) and partial responders (PR) per RECIST v1.1]</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>every 8 weeks up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Restaging will occur every 8 weeks from date of first treatment until date of first progression, or date of death from any cause, whichever comes first - up to 24 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">43</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer, Castrate-resistant</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Everolimus and Enzalutamide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose Escalation Phase (18 patients): 3-6 patients will be treated at each dose level until the Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD) is determined.
Everolimus: Orally (PO) once daily (dose to be determined;
Enzalutamide: 160mg (four 40mg capsules) PO continuous daily dosing.
Dose Expansion Phase (23 patients): Everolimus and Enzalutamide to be administered using the MTD determined in the dose escalation phase.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Everolimus</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Everolimus and Enzalutamide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>RAD001</other_name>
    <other_name>Afinitor</other_name>
    <other_name>Votubia</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Enzalutamide</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Everolimus and Enzalutamide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MDV3100</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        KEY POINTS:

          1. Adenocarcinoma of the prostate confirmed histologically.

          2. Metastatic disease confirmed by biopsy or imaging studies.

          3. Castrate-resistant prostate cancer (i.e., progression of prostate cancer while
             receiving standard androgen ablation therapy, orchiectomy or luteinizing
             hormone-releasing hormone [LHRH] antagonist). Castrate levels of serum testosterone
             must be documented at progression in patients who have not had an orchiectomy.

          4. Previous treatment with docetaxel for metastatic prostate cancer.

          5. ECOG of 0 to 2.

          6. Patients must have progressive metastatic prostate cancer by at least 1 of the
             following criteria:

               -  Progression of measurable lesions defined by Response Evaluation Criteria in
                  Solid Tumors (RECIST) version 1.1.

               -  Bone scan progression defined by 2 or more new lesions on bone scan.

               -  PSA progression is determined by a minimum of two rising PSA levels with an
                  interval of 1 week or greater between each determination. The screening PSA
                  measurement (documenting progression) must be greater than or equal to 2 ng/mL.

          7. Adequate hematologic, hepatic and renal function.

          8. Adequate coagulation parameters and serum chemistries.

          9. Ability to swallow and retain oral medication.

         10. Life expectancy of 6 months or greater.

         11. Ability to understand the nature of the study and give written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Treatment with more than 2 prior chemotherapy regimens.

          2. Previous treatment with enzalutamide or other investigational androgen receptor
             inhibitors.

          3. Previous treatment with PI3K/mTOR inhibitors.

          4. Known hypersensitivity to everolimus or other rapamycins (sirolimus, temsirolimus) or
             its excipients.

          5. Use of an investigational drug within 21 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is shorter)
             prior to the first dose of study drug.  For investigational drugs for which 5
             half-lives is less than 21 days, a minimum of 10 days between termination of the
             investigational drug and administration of study drug is required.

          6. All patients must be more than 21 days after their most recent chemotherapy and have
             recovered from side effects.

          7. CNS metastases.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John D. Hainsworth, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>SCRI Development Innovations, LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>John D. Hainsworth, MD</last_name>
    <phone>1-877-691-7274</phone>
    <email>askSarah@scresearch.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 6, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 17, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Metastatic Prostate Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Castrate-resistant</keyword>
  <keyword>Enzalutamide</keyword>
  <keyword>Everolimus</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sirolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
