<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="6536">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01893203</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R13073 / Q257</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-002108-15</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01893203</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treating Actinic Keratoses With Natural Daylight PDT: Comparing Two Light Sensitizers (ALA and MAL)</brief_title>
  <acronym>2013-002108-15</acronym>
  <official_title>Treating Actinic Keratoses With Natural Daylight PDT: Comparing Two Light Sensitizers (ALA and MAL)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Joint Authority for Päijät-Häme Social and Health Care</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Joint Authority for Päijät-Häme Social and Health Care</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Finland: Finnish Medical Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Actinic keratoses (AKs) are superficial premalignant skin lesions that can progress into an
      invasive or metasthatic squamous cell carcinoma. AKs can be treated with photodynamic
      therapy (PDT), of which cure rate compares to cryo surgery with an excellent cosmesis. In
      PDT the AK lesions are first curettaged, then a photosensitizer is applied on the skin and
      let to absorb for 3 hours. The skin is illuminated using a blue or red light source light
      source depending on the sensitizer, which induces activation of protoporphyrin IX (PpIX) and
      phototoxic reaction destroying the cancer cells.

      The approved photosensitizers in Europe are methylaminolevulenic acid cream, (MAL, Metvix™,
      Galderma), a patch containing 5-aminolevulenic acid (5-ALA, Alacare®, Spirig AG) and
      aminolevulenic acid gel (BF-200 ALA, Ameluz®, Biofrontera AG) to be used with a red LED
      light (630-635 nm). In North America a 5-aminolevulinic acid stick (5-ALA, Levulan®
      Kerastick) can also be used with a blue light source (417 nm).

      PpIX absorption peaks are within the visual spectrum of light, which allows PpIX daylight
      activation. During natural daylight PDT (NDL-PDT) protocol, PpIX is continuously activated
      during its development, whereas in conventional PDT (LED-PDT) using red LED lamps, large
      amounts of accumulated PpIX are momentarily activated.

      Since skin field cancerization refers to presence of different degrees of visible and
      invisible dysplastic changes, the whole area should be treated to prevent the development of
      non-melanoma skin cancers (NMSCs). NDL-PDT enables treatment of field cancerization in one
      sitting whereas LED-PDT may need repeated illuminations to cover the whole area. NDL-PDT
      results in enhanced cost-efficacy due to reduced staff expenses, since there's no need for
      policlinical sensitizer absorption and illumination.

      At the moment two photosensitizers have marketing authorization in Finland, ALA (Ameluz®)
      and MAL (Metvix™). Ameluz® holds a lower unit price and it's clearance rate compares to
      Metvix™ in LED-PDT. We are piloting a study comparing the cost-efficacy of these two light
      sensitizers in NDL-PDT. Our hypothesis is that there will be at least 0,30 difference in the
      histopathological curing of the lesions. Our other hypothesis is that Ameluz® with it's
      lower unit price results in reduced treatment costs and better cost-efficacy compared to
      Metvix™. The efficacy of the treatments will be assessed clinically, histopathologically,
      immunohistochemically and by hyper spectrum camera imaging.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Histopathological healing of actinic keratoses</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will take 3mm punch biopsies of similar looking AKs from both sides of the face or scalp before the treatment and 3 months after the treatment to assess the histopathological healing of actinic keratoses. We will also make immunohistochemical analyses of P53 chromosome mutations from the taken biopsies.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between pain experienced by the patient: comparing symmetrical areas of face or scalp</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients will be asked to fill visual analogue scales about pain experienced by the patients on each sides of the face or scalp. Pain is assessed after the treatment until the evening.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Primary treatment reaction</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary treatment reaction will be single-blindedly assessed one week after the treatment. A dermatologist will assess which side of the face or scalp presents a stronger reaction.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Dermatoecological analyses of the treatment costs</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Researchers will analyze the cost-efficacy of the treatments using decision tree, sensitivity analysis, ICER and QALY-analyses to decide with treatment modality is more preferrable. The differences in cost-efficacy will most likely depend on the light sensitizer costs and their efficacy on the treated lesions.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Hyper spectrum imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Hyper spectrum camera images will be taken before treatment and 3 months after the treatment to assess the healing of field cancerization and actinic keratoses areas.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Actinic Keratoses (gr I-III)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Actinic keratoses patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>First the anticipated treatment area will be degreased using ethanol. Then SPF20 sun protection cream will be applied on all sun-exposed areas of the skin. Then a 0,25mm layer application of Ameluz-light sensitizer on the field cancerized area on the other side of the face and Metvix-light sensitizer on the other. The sides will be randomized in blocks of two. After appropriate absorption time of 30 minutes, the patients will be taken to the hospital balcony or yard for 2 hour illumination with natural daylight to accomplish the phototoxic reaction. Maximum dosage of light sensitizer will be 2 grams. The treatment will be repeated after 2 weeks for thicker gr II-III lesions with the same protocol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ALA sensitizer</intervention_name>
    <description>First the anticipated treatment area will be degreased using ethanol. Then SPF20 sun protection cream will be applied on all sun-exposed areas of the skin. Then a 0,25mm layer application of Ameluz-light sensitizer on the field cancerized area. After appropriate absorption time of 30 minutes, the patients will be taken to the hospital balcony or yard for 2 hour illumination with natural daylight to accomplish the phototoxic reaction. Maximum dosage will be 2 grams. The treatment will be repeated after 2 weeks for thicker gr II-III lesions with the same protocol.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Actinic keratoses patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>aminolevulenic acid</other_name>
    <other_name>Ameluz</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MAL sensitizer</intervention_name>
    <description>First the anticipated treatment area will be degreased using ethanol. Then SPF20 sun protection cream will be applied on all sun-exposed areas of the skin. Then a 0,25mm layer application of Metvix-light sensitizer on the field cancerized area. After appropriate absorption time of 30 minutes, the patients will be taken to the hospital balcony or yard for 2 hour illumination with natural daylight to accomplish the phototoxic reaction. Maximum dosage will be 2 grams. The treatment will be repeated after 2 weeks for thicker gr II-III lesions with the same protocol.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Actinic keratoses patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>methylaminolevulenic acid</other_name>
    <other_name>Metvix</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  actinic keratoses on boths sides of the face or scalp

          -  age over 18 years

          -  there must be atleast one ak of over 6mm on both sides

          -  patients must be able to make the decision to attend independently

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  pregnancy

          -  lactation

          -  lack of compliance
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Noora E Neittaanmäki-Perttu, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Helsinki University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Toni T Karppinen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Päijät-Häme Central Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Taneli Tani, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Päijät-Häme Central Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ilkka Pölönen, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Jyväskylä University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mari Grönroos, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+358503708881</phone>
    <email>mari.gronroos@co.inet.fi</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Päijät-Häme Central Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lahti</city>
        <zip>15850</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mari Grönroos, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+358503708881</phone>
      <email>mari.gronroos@co.inet.fi</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Finland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 22, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 2, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Keratosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Keratosis, Actinic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Methyl 5-aminolevulinate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
