<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="80658">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01967147</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>M-13-027</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01967147</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Outcomes Following Treatment With Systane® Balance in Dry Eye Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Clinical Outcomes Following Treatment With Systane® Balance in Dry Eye Subjects With Lipid Deficiency</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Alcon Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Alcon Research</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>France: Institutional Ethical Committee</authority>
    <authority>France: Haute Autorité de Santé Transparency Commission</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Ethics Commission</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>Netherlands:  Independent Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>Italy: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>Poland: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to demonstrate the superior efficacy of Systane® Balance over
      Preservative-Free 0.9% Saline following 35 days of QID (4 times a day) dosing in treating
      dry eye subjects with lipid deficiency.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A 15-day Run-in phase will precede a 90-day Treatment period. The Treatment period will be
      conducted in 2 phases. In Phase 1, participants will be randomized to either Systane®
      Balance or Saline and dose 4 times a day for 35 days. In Phase II (Day 35-90) participants
      will continue to dose with their assigned product on an as-needed basis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in tear film break-up time (TFBUT) at Day 35</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Day 0), Day 35</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>TFBUT is defined as the time required for dry spots to appear on the corneal surface after blinking. TFBUT will be assessed by the investigator using ophthalmic dye and a biomicroscope and is measured in seconds. A shorter TFBUT indicates a higher likelihood of dry eye symptoms. Subjects must dose in the office 1 hour ±10 minutes prior to TFBUT assessment. A positive change indicates an improvement in TFBUT.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Total Ocular Surface Staining (TOSS) score at Day 35</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Day 0), Day 35</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The TOSS score is a cumulative cornea and conjunctival staining score. Staining will be assessed by the investigator using ophthalmic dye and a biomicroscope. Three areas of the ocular surface will be graded for dryness on a 0-5 scale (0=Absent, 5=Severe), with a resultant overall score of 0-15. A negative change indicates an improvement in dry eye-related staining.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in ocular surface disease index (OSDI) score at Day 35</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Day 0), Day 35</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The OSDI is a 12-item quality of life questionnaire designed to assess ocular surface symptoms, their severity, and their impact on the subject's ability to function.  Each item will be scored by the subject on a 0-4 Likert-type scale (0=None, 4=All of the Time), with a resultant overall score of 0-100 (0=no disability, 100=complete disability). A negative change number  represents a perceived improvement in ocular health.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Impact of Dry Eye on Everyday Life (IDEEL) Treatment Effectiveness score at Day 35</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Day 0), Day 35</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The IDEEL is a 10-item questionnaire designed to assess the subject's general satisfaction with treatment use.  The subject's responses regarding treatment effectiveness will be graded using a 0-4 Likert-type scale (0=None of the time, 4=All of the time).  A Treatment Effectiveness score is calculated, with higher scores indicating greater satisfaction. A positive change number represents perceived improvement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in IDEEL Treatment Inconvenience score at Day 35</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Day 0), Day 35</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The IDEEL is a 10-item questionnaire designed to assess the subject's general satisfaction with treatment use. The subject's responses regarding treatment inconvenience will be graded using a 0-4 Likert-type scale (0=All of the time, 4=None of the time). A Treatment Inconvenience score is calculated, with higher scores indicating greater satisfaction. A positive change number represents perceived improvement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">294</enrollment>
  <condition>Dry Eye</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Systane® Balance</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Propylene Glycol, 0.6% eye drops, 1 drop in each eye, 4 times per day, during Phase I (Day 0-35), followed by 1 drop in each eye as needed during Phase II (Day 35-90).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Saline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Preservative-Free 0.9% Saline solution, 1 drop in each eye, 4 times per day, during Phase I (Day 0-35), followed by 1 drop in each eye as needed during Phase II (Day 35-90).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Propylene Glycol, 0.6% eye drops</intervention_name>
    <description>Commercially available eye drops used during Treatment Phase</description>
    <arm_group_label>Systane® Balance</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Systane® Balance</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Preservative-free 0.9% Saline solution</intervention_name>
    <description>Commercially available solution used as Run-in (1 drop in each eye 4 times a day for 15 days) and during Treatment Phase</description>
    <arm_group_label>Saline</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must have all of the following in at least 1 eye at Screening:

               1. Meibomian Gland Dysfunction (MGD) grading for Expressibility ≤ 2 and Meibum
                  Quality ≤ 2,

               2. The average of 3 measures of TFBUT &lt; 5 seconds, and

               3. Unanesthetized Schirmer I test of ≥ 3 mm.

          -  Must have an Ocular Surface Disease Index (OSDI) Score ≥ 18 at Visit 1      prior to
             randomization (ie, after 2 weeks of run-in with Preservative-Free 0.9% Saline
             administered 4 times a day).

          -  Must have best-corrected visual acuity of 55 letters or better in each eye as
             assessed using an early treatment diabetic retinopathy study (ETDRS) chart (letter
             read method).

          -  Physician diagnosis of dry eye at least 6 months prior to Screening visit.

          -  Willing and able to attend all study visits.

          -  Must sign a written informed consent form.

          -  Other protocol-defined inclusion criteria may apply.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects on topical ocular treatments containing benzalkonium chloride (BAK), or
             other products with known toxicity to the corneal surface, within 30 days of
             Screening.

          -  Subjects who have started, stopped, or changed a lid hygiene regimen within 30 days
             of Screening.

          -  Use of any artificial tears/lubricants/gels/rewetting drops within 4 hours of
             Screening.

          -  Women of childbearing potential are excluded from participating in this study if they
             meet any of the following conditions:

               -  Currently pregnant, or

               -  Test positive for pregnancy at Screening visit, or

               -  Currently breast feeding, or

               -  Are not in agreement to use adequate birth control methods to prevent pregnancy
                  throughout the study.

          -  Hypersensitivity to the use of any of the study products or allergy to any ingredient
             in the study products.

          -  Has an active ocular allergy.

          -  Any ocular abnormalities that could adversely affect the safety or efficacy outcome,
             including eyelid anomalies, corneal disorders, history of herpes simplex, etc.

          -  Subjects taking any systemic medication known to cause dry eye unless they have been
             on stable therapy/dosage for at least 30 days prior to Screening and will remain on a
             stable dosage for the duration of the study.

          -  History of any ocular or intraocular surgery (including periocular Botox injections),
             eyelid surgery, keratorefractive procedure, corneal transplant and its variants, or
             serious ocular trauma within 1 year of Screening.

          -  Active ocular infection (bacterial, viral or fungal), active inflammation not
             associated with dry eye such as uveitis, iritis, active blepharitis, active allergic
             conjunctivitis, etc.

          -  Subjects with punctal plug insertion or diathermy procedure initiated within 30 days
             of Screening.

          -  Any significant illnesses that could be expected to interfere with the study
             parameters.

          -  Subjects with active oculodermal rosacea with meibomian gland dysfunction.

          -  Participation in an investigational drug or device trial within 30 days of Screening.

          -  Contact lens use within 30 days prior to Screening, or unwilling to avoid contact
             lens use during the course of the study.

          -  Unwilling to avoid the use of additional artificial tears/lubricants/gels/rewetting
             drops (other than the assigned study medication) throughout the course of the study.

          -  Other protocol-defined exclusion criteria may apply.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christine Rosko, Clinical Manager</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Alcon Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alcon Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>1-888-451-3937</phone>
    <email>alcon.medinfo@alcon.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Contact Alcon Call Center for Trial Locations</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Worth</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>76134</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 28, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dry eye</keyword>
  <keyword>Lipid deficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>Tear film break-up time</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Keratoconjunctivitis Sicca</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dry Eye Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Tetrahydrozoline</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
