<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="66992">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01723839</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00002262 RV-CLL-PI-0530</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01723839</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase II Protocol for CLL With Fludarabine and Cyclophosphamide With Rituximab (FCR) Plus Lenalidomide</brief_title>
  <acronym>FCR</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase II Clinical Protocol for the Treatment of Patients With Previously Untreated CLL With Four or Six Cycles of Fludarabine and Cyclophosphamide With Rituximab (FCR) Plus Lenalidomide Followed by Lenalidomide Consolidation/ Maintenance</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hackensack University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Celgene Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hackensack University Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In previously-untreated subjects with CLL, fludarabine and rituximab with or without
      cyclophosphamide (FR or FCR) produces complete responses (CR) of 40-80%. The major
      complication of FCR has been grade 3/4 neutropenia which was reduced using a lower dose of
      fludarabine and cyclophosphamide (FCR-Lite) The objective of this study is to evaluate the
      minimal residual disease (MRD) complete response rate (using the 2008 IWCLL guidelines)
      after 4 cycles of FCR-Lite plus lenalidomide in subjects with previously untreated CLL.
      Lenalidomide is active in frontline treatment of CLL as well as in patients with refractory
      disease. MRD has been demonstrated to be a sensitive surrogate marker for progression-free
      survival.  If patients are MRD negative complete responders (CR) they will stop at 4 cycles
      of FCR-Lite followed by the lenalidomide consolidation/maintenance arm of the study.  If
      they have a MRD positive CR or partial response (PR) they will continue with 2 additional
      cycles of FCR-Lite plus lenalidomide followed by lenalidomide consolidation/maintenance.
      They will be re-tested for MRD after the 6th cycle of FCR-Lite and after 6 and 12 months of
      lenalidomide monotherapy  If they have no response (NR) or progressive disease (PD)
      following 4 cycles of FCR-Lite plus lenalidomide they will be removed from the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      STUDY OBJECTIVES:

      Primary:

      The primary objective is to evaluate the complete response rate following 4 cycles of
      FCR-Lite plus lenalidomide in previously untreated patients with CLL.

      Secondary:

      The first secondary objective is to evaluate the toxicity of patients with previously
      untreated CLL treated with FCR-Lite plus lenalidomide, followed by lenalidomide.  The second
      is to evaluate the overall response rate and overall survival of patients with previously
      untreated CLL treated with FCR-Lite plus lenalidomide followed by lenalidomide.  The third
      is to determine whether adding lenalidomide as a consolidation/maintenance therapy will
      eliminate bone marrow minimal residual disease in CR patients and whether patients who have
      a PR after 6 cycles of FCR-Lite plus lenalidomide will respond to 12 months of lenalidomide.
       The final secondary objective is to determine whether the expression of ZAP-70, CD38, and
      chromosomes correlate with response rate, duration of response, and survival for previously
      untreated patients with CLL.

      STUDY DESIGN:

      2-stage phase 2 study-design.  19 subjects are treated in stage-1 with FCR-Lite plus 5mg
      lenalidomide increasing to 10mg and 15mg in subsequent cycles depending on toxicity.  If
      there are at least 5 CRs the study will accrue an additional 35 subjects (see statistical
      section).  A secondary objective of this study will be to determine if MRD positive patients
      will become MRD negative with  lenalidomide consolidation/maintenance and whether PR
      patients will convert to CRs  Lenalidomide will begin 2 months after the last dose of
      FCR-Lite in all subjects with CR.  It may begin as soon as 1 month after FCR-Lite plus
      lenalidomide in subjects with PR.  Lenalidomide is given in 28 d cycles increasing the dose
      from 5 mg/d to 10 mg/d in cycle 2 and to 15mg in cycles 3-6 if well- tolerated (no grade-3
      or -4 toxicity). Patients with creatinine clearance ≥30ml/min and &lt;60ml/min will start at
      2.5mg daily increasing to 5 and 10mg in subsequent cycles . Reduction to the prior dose is
      allowed for grade-3/-4 toxicity.   MRD will be studied by flow cytometry from bone marrow
      and peripheral blood samples following 4 and 6 cycles of FCR-Lite and after 6 and 12 months
      of lenalidomide in CR patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete Response</measure>
    <time_frame>28 day cycle</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Analysis of the Primary Endpoint: The complete responses will be estimated by the number of patients with CR divided by the total number of evaluable patients. Ninety-five percent confidence intervals for the true CR will be calculated</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>4-6 28 day cycles</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Analysis of the other Secondary Endpoints: The overall response rate will be estimated by the number of patients with complete and partial responses divided by the total number of evaluable patients. Ninety-five percent confidence intervals for the true success proportion will be calculated.  Responses will be evaluated after 4 and 6 cycles of FCR plus lenalidomide and after 6 and 12 cycles of lenalidomide consolidation/maintenance. The overall survival (OS) is defined as the time interval between the treatment starting date and the documented date of death. For a surviving patient, OS is censored at the last follow-up date when the patient is documented to be alive. Progression-free survival (PFS) is defined as the time interval between the treatment starting date and the documented date of disease progression or death, whichever occurs first. For an alive and progression free patient, PFS is censored at the last follow-up date when patient is documented to be progression free.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">54</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (CLL)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FCR with Lenalidomide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fludarabine, Cyclophosphamide, Rituximab, Lenalidomide - 19 subjects are treated in stage-1 with FCR plus 5mg lenalidomide increasing to 10mg and 15mg in subsequent cycles depending on toxicity. If there are at least 5 CRs after 4 cycles of FCR plus lenalidomide the study will accrue an additional 35 subjects.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine, Cyclophosphamide, Rituximab, Lenalidomide</intervention_name>
    <description>19 subjects are treated in stage-1 with FCR plus 5mg lenalidomide increasing to 10mg and 15mg in subsequent cycles depending on toxicity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>FCR with Lenalidomide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>FCR + Lenalidomide</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have diagnosis of CLL (as defined by the NCI Criteria below:

               -  Patients must have peripheral blood absolute lymphocyte count of &gt;5,000/mm3
                  obtained within 2 weeks prior to start of study.

               -  The lymphocytosis must consist of small, mature lymphocytes, with ≤55% (not
                  greater than 55%) prolymphocytes.

          -  Patients must have phenotypically characterized CLL as defined as:

               1. The predominant population of cells share B-cell antigens with CD5 in the
                  absence of other pan-T-cell markers (CD3, CD2, etc.);

               2. Surface immunoglobulin (slg) and CD20 with low-cell surface density expression.

               3. If surface immunoglobulin can be demonstrated, the leukemic cells are restricted
                  to expression of either kappa or lambda.

          -  Splenomegaly, hepatomegaly or lymphadenopathy are not required for the diagnosis of
             CLL

          -  Patients must require chemotherapy

          -  Patients must not have received prior treatment cytotoxic, immunotherapy or
             investigational therapy.

          -  Patients must not have history of corticosteroid treatment for CLL, Autoimmune
             thrombocytopenia, or autoimmune hemolytic anemia.

          -  Calculated creatinine clearance ≥30ml/min by Cockcroft-Gault formula

          -  Bilirubin must be ≤1.5mg/dl, unless secondary to tumor, obtained within 2 weeks prior
             to registration

          -  Platelets ≥75x109/L, unless due to CLL involvement of bone marrow

          -  Neutrophils ≥1.5x109/L, unless due to CLL involvement of bone marrow

          -  AST or ALT &lt; 2x upper limit of normal, unless related to CLL

          -  Age ≥18 years

          -  ECOG performance status 0-2

          -  Females of childbearing potential (FCBP) must have a negative serum or urine
             pregnancy test

          -  Men must agree to use a latex condom during sexual contact with a FCBP even if they
             have had a successful vasectomy

          -  Able to take aspirin (81mg or 325mg) daily as prophylactic anticoagulation

          -  Subject must provide written informed consent

          -  All study participants must be registered into the mandatory RevAssist® program, and
             be willing and able to comply with the requirements of RevAssist®

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with autoimmune hemolytic anemia or autoimmune thrombocytopenia are not
             eligible

          -  No prior immunotherapy, investigational or cytotoxic chemotherapy

          -  Patients with a history of steroid treatment for CLL/SLL autoimmune hemolytic anemia,
             or autoimmune thrombocytopenia are not eligible

          -  Patients with active infections requiring oral or intravenous (IV) antibiotics until
             resolution of the infection and completion of therapeutic antibiotics

          -  Women of childbearing potential and sexually active males who both refuse to use an
             accepted and effective method of contraception or women who are breastfeeding

          -  Patients with a second malignancy other than basal cell carcinoma or squamous cell
             carcinoma of the skin or in situ carcinoma of the cervix are not eligible unless the
             tumor was treated with curative intent at least two years previously

          -  History of known HIV

          -  History or presence CNS disease

          -  Evidence of laboratory TLS by Cairo-Bishop definition of Tumor Lysis Syndrome

          -  History of corticosteroid treatment for CLL, Autoimmune thrombocytopenia, or
             autoimmune hemolytic anemia.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anthony Mato, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>John Theurer Cancer Center at HackensackUMC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>John Theurer Cancer Center at HackensackUMC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hackensack</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anthony Mato, MD</last_name>
      <phone>201-996-5900</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Marisa Valentinetti, RN</last_name>
      <phone>201.996.5900</phone>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 6, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CLL</keyword>
  <keyword>FCR</keyword>
  <keyword>Rituximab</keyword>
  <keyword>Lenalidomide</keyword>
  <keyword>Cyclophosphamide</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine monophosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
