<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="10067">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02095405</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2009403-01H</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02095405</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Caffeine on Cardiac Arrhythmias</brief_title>
  <acronym>CACOA-HEART</acronym>
  <official_title>A Prospective Placebo Controlled Randomized Study of Caffeine in Patients With Supraventricular Tachycardia Undergoing Electrophysiologic Testing.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Ottawa Heart Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Ottawa Heart Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Stimulants and drugs are often associated with cardiac effects.  Caffeine, a therapeutic
      xanthine, has been described as a sympathomimetic and has shown to have stimulatory effects
      on the heart.  Patients with symptomatic cardiac arrhythmias are generally informed by their
      physician to stop or significantly reduce caffeine intake.  However, in spite of numerous
      reports that have reviewed the cardiac effects of caffeine, it remains unclear to what
      extent this stimulant may be detrimental, and what subgroups of patients may be most
      vulnerable. The investigators propose to evaluate the effects of caffeine in patients with
      previously diagnosed cardiac arrhythmias.  The results of our report will provide important
      new information for physicians and patients regarding the effects of caffeine on symptomatic
      cardiac arrhythmias.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Caffeine is one of the most frequently consumed pharmacologic active substances in the
      world.  The potential effects of caffeinated beverages and chocolate on human health remains
      of great interest.  The increased prevalence of cardiac arrhythmias in the general
      population has resulted in greater concern about the potential effects of caffeine on
      cardiac arrhythmias.  Patients diagnosed with a cardiac dysrhythmia are generally informed
      by their physician to restrict or even abstain from caffeine, despite a lack of evidence of
      this causal relationship.

      Although there have been numerous reports published on the effects of caffeine on human
      health, there have been few reports on the relation between caffeinated beverages and
      chocolate in different subgroups of patients with previously diagnosed cardiac arrhythmias,
      including supraventricular tachycardia (SVT), atrial fibrillation (AF), atrial flutter, and
      ventricular arrhythmias.  These patients frequently undergo interventional ablation
      procedures, and have a potential for a recurrence of their arrhythmia.  A greater knowledge
      of the effects of caffeine in different subgroups of patients with cardiac arrhythmias is
      thus essential to properly guide patients and physicians in their treatment.

      The objective of our study is to evaluate the effects of caffeine through noninvasive and/or
      invasive means on patients with documented symptomatic cardiac arrhythmias.

      One group will consist of 80 patients with Supraventricular Tachycardia (SVT): This group
      will undergo Invasive testing, which will be completed in the electrophysiology laboratory
      prior to their ablation procedure to evaluate the electrophysiologic effects of caffeine or
      placebo on the human heart. This testing will include a measure of the effective refractory
      periods, inducibility of tachyarrhythmias, and conduction intervals during programmed
      electrical stimulation.

      The other group will consist of up to 80 patients with Atrial Fibrillation: This group will
      undergo non-invasive testing, consisting of two consecutive 48-hr Ambulatory monitors while
      they consume caffeinated or noncaffeinated products.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Invasive group: Refractory period of the Right Ventricle (RV) and Right Atrium (RA),  Non-Invasive group: Ambulatory monitoring number of atrial and ventricular extrasystoles</measure>
    <time_frame>Invasive group: Admission to Hospital for the EP study until discharge the same day.  Non-Invasive group: From start of 2 consecutive 48 hour ambulatory monitors to their removal.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Invasive group: During programmed electrical stimulation, determination of the effective refractory period of the atrium and ventricle.
Non-Invasive group: During Ambulatory Monitoring, determination of atrial and ventricular extrasystoles.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Invasive group: Tachycardia inducibility</measure>
    <time_frame>Invasive group: Admission to Hospital for the EP study until discharge the same day.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Invasive group: During programmed electrical stimulation, was SVT induced, was isoproterenol required, and what was the rate of induced tachycardia.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Supraventricular Tachycardia (SVT)</condition>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Caffeine arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>SVT group: Caffeine tablets, 5 mg/kg.
AF group: Caffeinated substances and Dark Chocolate</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>SVT group: Placebo
AF group: Decaffeinated substances and White Chocolate</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Caffeine</intervention_name>
    <description>SVT group: Oral tablets of Caffeine prior to the electrophysiology study in patients with SVT.
AF group: Dark chocolate and Caffeinated substances in patients with AF at the time of Ambulatory monitoring.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Caffeine arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>SVT group: Oral tablets of placebo prior to the electrophysiology study in patients with SVT.
AF group: White chocolate and Decaffeinated substances in patients with AF at the time of Ambulatory monitoring.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18-80 years.

          -  Document cardiac arrhythmia, consisting of either:

             i. Patients with SVT:  Patients with documented narrow complex tachycardia on a
             twelve lead ECG or on ambulatory monitoring ii. Patients with AF, paroxysmal
             (self-terminating AF within 7 days), documented on a twelve lead ECG or on ambulatory
             monitoring

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Failure to provide informed consent

          -  Pregnancy as determined by a pre-procedure pregnancy test, or women who are
             breastfeeding

          -  Class III or IV congestive heart failure

          -  Myocardial infarction within the last 6 months

          -  Coronary stenting or cardiac surgery within the last 6 months

          -  History of unstable angina

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension

          -  Intolerance to caffeinated beverages or chocolate

          -  Dependency on medications that may severely react with caffeine: substrate for
             Cytochrome P450 1A2  (CYP1A2) (tizanidine), inhibit CYP1A2 (fluvoxamine,
             ketoconazole, and rofecoxib), induce CYP1A2 (aminoglutethimide, carbamazepine,
             phenobarbital, and rifampin)

          -  Enrolment in another study at University of Ottawa Heart Institute (UOHI), unless
             approved by the Human Ethics Review Board (HREB).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Lemery</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Ottawa Heart Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Robert Lemery, MD</last_name>
    <phone>613-761-4978</phone>
    <email>rlemery@ottawaheart.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Ottawa Heart Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1Y 4W7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robert Lemery, MD</last_name>
      <phone>613-761-4978</phone>
      <email>rlemery@ottawaheart.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert Lemery, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Ottawa Heart Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1Y 4W7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robert Lemery, MD</last_name>
      <phone>613-761-4978</phone>
      <email>rlemery@ottawaheart.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 20, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 18, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Ottawa Heart Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Robert Lemery</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Cardiac Electrophysiologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Supraventricular Tachycardia</keyword>
  <keyword>Atrial Fibrillation</keyword>
  <keyword>Electrophysiology Study</keyword>
  <keyword>Programmed Electrical Stimulation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Arrhythmias, Cardiac</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tachycardia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tachycardia, Supraventricular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Caffeine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
