<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="24990">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01813214</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MLN28305</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01813214</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of Vemurafenib on Immunity in Patients With Melanoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Analysis of the Kinetics and Effects of Vemurafenib on Intratumoral and Host Immunity in Patients With Advanced BRAFV600 Mutant Melanoma: Implications for Combination With Immunotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Georgetown University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genentech</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Melanoma Research Alliance</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Georgetown University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is for patients with malignant melanoma which has spread beyond the local area
      and cannot be surgically removed, and who have melanoma tumors that are accessible for
      repeat biopsies. This research study is a way of gaining new knowledge about treatment
      options for metastatic melanoma. This research study is evaluating the effects of a drug
      called vemurafenib on the immune system.

      Vemurafenib has been approved by the FDA for treatment of patients with advanced melanoma
      that harbors a B-RAF mutation. Vemurafenib works by blocking a protein called B-RAF.
      Researchers have found that a large number of melanomas have mutations (changes) in the BRAF
      gene. Genes are specific parts of your DNA that contain information on hereditary
      characteristics such as hair color and eye color. The BRAF gene codes for a protein called
      B-RAF, which is involved in sending signals in cells that can lead to cell growth. Research
      has determined that mutations in the BRAF gene at the V600 position cause a change in the
      B-RAF protein that can drive the growth and spread of melanoma cells.

      The purpose of this research study is to determine how vemurafenib may alter the immune
      system's reaction to melanoma, in order to learn how best to combine immune therapies with
      vemurafenib in the future.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-arm, multicenter study of vemurafenib in patients with biopsy-accessible
      advanced metastatic melanoma.

      The trial will consist of a screening period, a treatment phase, and one post-study
      follow-up visit occurring about 30 days after the last dose of vemurafenib. Day 1 of the
      study will be defined as the first day a subject receives vemurafenib. During the treatment
      phase, all study assessments will be conducted on Day 1 (± 3 days) of each cycle, with the
      exception of computed tomography (CT) and/or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), which should
      occur every 6 weeks (+/- 7 days).

      All subjects will have biopsies performed of safely accessible tumors before starting
      treatment and at 1, 2, and 4 weeks later (days 8, 15, 29). In addition, any patient with
      accessible tumor at the time of progression will have a tumor biopsy performed at that time.

      Mixed-effects models will be used to study the change in CD8 T cell counts per mm2 of
      tissue, changes in expression of immunoinhibitory proteins (B7-H1/PD-L1, IDO, arginase), and
      changes in endothelial homing receptor ligands and tumor associated chemokines at
      pre-treatment at pre-treatment and at weeks 1, 2, and 4 after vemurafenib therapy. Subjects
      will be treated as random effects to account for individual variability. Potential
      covariates are age, gender, and ECOG performance status.

      60 ml of blood for lymphocytes will be drawn on days 1, 8, 15, and 29.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Pharmacodynamics Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time course by which vemurafenib increases T cell infiltration</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>CD8 T cell count per mm2 of tumor</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Activation state tumor-infiltrating T cells</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Descriptive assessment of changes in activation state over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Expression of immunoinhibitory proteins</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Descriptive assessment of changes in B7-H1/PD-L1, IDO, Arginase</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lysis of tumor cells</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Determination of lysis of tumor cells in comparison to allogeneic tumor cells</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of tumor associated immune signatures</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Non-hierarchical clustering of gene expression signatures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in endothelial homing receptor ligands and tumor associated chemokines</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Descriptive assessment and changes in activation state over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of immune/inflammatory expression pattern</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Generalized linear mixed model will be used to study whether tumor expression patterns changes from non-immune (type 1) to an immune (type 2) over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of tissue-specific destruction and IFN-gamma upregulation</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Descriptive assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>IFN-gamma upregulation and TSD expression patterns relative to baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks, 4 weeks, 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes will be assessed using a mixed-effects model</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of grade 3, 4, and 5 toxicities</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Reporting of all grade 3 and 4 toxicities, all death, and any grade skin cancers</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vemurafenib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Vemurafenib 960 mg po BID until unacceptable toxicity or progression of disease</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vemurafenib</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Vemurafenib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Zelboraf</other_name>
    <other_name>R05185426 (PLX4032)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histological or cytological confirmed melanoma that is metastatic
             or unresectable stage IIIc and clearly progressive.

          -  Melanoma must be documented to contain a BRAFV600 mutation by a CLIA approved
             laboratory

          -  Age &gt;/= 18 years

          -  ECOG performance status 0, 1, or 2

          -  Participants must have measurable melanoma

          -  Women must not be pregnant

          -  Breastfeeding must be discontinued prior to treatment Day 1 of the study.

          -  Subjects may have received any number of prior systemic treatment regimens for
             distant metastatic disease or advanced regional disease. The following prior therapy
             is permitted in either the adjuvant or metastatic disease setting:

               -  No prior therapy

               -  Immunotherapy consisting of interferon-alpha, interleukin-2, GM-CSF, ipilimumab,
                  anti-PD1, cancer vaccines, or other experimental agent

               -  Cytotoxic chemotherapy consisting of dacarbazine, temozolomide, carboplatin, or
                  paclitaxel alone or in combination

               -  Targeted therapy with temsirolimus, bevacizumab, or sorafenib

          -  Subjects must have discontinued cytotoxic therapy agents at least 4 weeks, cytokine
             based immunotherapy at least 6 weeks and immunoregulatory antibody therapy at least
             12 weeks prior to entering the study and have recovered from adverse events due to
             those agents.

          -  Subjects must have completed radiation therapy at least 4 weeks previously

          -  Subjects must have the following baseline laboratory values:

               -  White blood count &gt;/= 3000/mm3

               -  Absolute granulocyte count &gt;/= 1500/mm3

               -  Platelet count &gt;/= 100,000/mm3

               -  Serum creatinine /= 40 ml/min

               -  AST/ALT

               -  Alkaline Phosphatase

               -  INR

               -  Total bilirubin

          -  Subjects must not receive any other investigational agents during the period on study
             or the four weeks prior to entry.

          -  Subjects must have no clinical evidence of active brain metastasis.

          -  Subjects who have had brain metastases will be eligible only if all of the following
             are true:

          -  The total number of brain metastases ever is - All are less than or equal to 2 cm

          -  They have been resected surgically or have been treated with gamma-knife or
             stereotactic radiosurgery

          -  The patient has not taken any steroids

          -  Subjects must not have a serious intercurrent illness including, but not limited to:

               -  Ongoing or active infection requiring parenteral antibiotics on Day 1

               -  History of congenital long QT syndrome or mean corrected QTc interval &gt; 450 msec
                  at baseline

               -  Clinically significant cardiovascular disease:

                  i. Myocardial infarction within 6 months ii. Unstable angina iii. New York heart
                  association grade II or greater congestive heart failure iv. Serious cardiac
                  arrhythmia requiring medication

               -  Serious non-healing wound, active ulcer, or untreated bone fracture

               -  Psychiatric illness/ social situations that would limit compliance with study
                  requirements.

          -  Subjects must be HIV negative

          -  Subjects must be Hepatitis C negative

          -  Subjects must have the ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written
             informed consent document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior therapy with a MEK inhibitor or an inhibitor of mutant BRAF

          -  Patients on warfarin therapy due to the requirement for multiple biopsies

          -  Subjects who have another cancer diagnosis, except that the following diagnoses will
             be allowed:

               -  Squamous cell cancer of the skin without known metastasis. Subjects with
                  suspected cuSCCs should have them excised prior to study registration

               -  Basal cell cancer of the skin without known metastasis

               -  Carcinoma in situ of the breast (DCIS or LCIS)

               -  Carcinoma in situ of the cervix

               -  Any cancer without distant metastasis that has been treated successfully,
                  without evidence of recurrence or metastasis over 3 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael B Atkins, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Georgetown Lombardi Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael B Atkins, MD</last_name>
    <phone>202-687-2795</phone>
    <email>mba41@georgetown.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Rose Hardesty, RN</last_name>
    <phone>202-687-2111</phone>
    <email>rk286@georgetown.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Georgetown Lombardi Comprehsnive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20007</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rose Hardesty, RN</last_name>
      <phone>202-687-2111</phone>
      <email>rk286@georgetown.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael B Arkins, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 19, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>vemurafenib</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
