<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="157925">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01707693</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>135603</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01707693</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Lifestyle Physical Activity Intervention for Older Sedentary Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Lifestyle Physical Activity Intervention for Older Sedentary Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Arkansas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Arkansas</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States:University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences, Center for Clinical and Translational Research, Data Safety and Monitoring Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Making physical activity an integral part of daily life is imperative to the health and
      well-being of our nation's older adults. However, no intervention strategy to encourage
      daily physical activity for older adults, especially older women, has been effective. This
      feasibility study will test a multi-tailored motivational intervention to increase usual
      lifestyle physical activity of older sedentary women to reduce their coronary heart disease
      risks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Over 98% of older women do not meet national guidelines for physical activity (PA). There is
      clear evidence that a physically active lifestyle reduces the human and economic cost of
      heart disease in a dose-response relationship; but current efforts to increase long-term PA
      in older women are inadequate. The aims of this proposed research are to: 1) determine the
      feasibility of using an individually tailored motivational counseling intervention method to
      promote lifestyle physical activity (LPA) in older sedentary women; 2) examine intervention
      effects by comparing baseline to outcome measures at 3 and 6 months in treatment and
      information/attention comparison groups; and 3) explore stage of behavior change and
      self-efficacy and their relationship to LPA, along with functional health.

      This will be a single blinded randomized controlled study of sedentary women aged 60 years
      and older. We will replace &quot;structured aerobic exercise&quot; with lifestyle physical activity
      (LPA), i.e., self-selected activities performed daily in a purposeful manner to meet the
      national PA guidelines. A total of 120 older women who are ambulatory and cognitively intact
      will be recruited from a senior health clinic and randomized to receive either the
      motivational LPA intervention or information/attention. Women will be assessed at baseline,
      3 and 6 months. The theoretically based behavioral intervention is derived from the
      Transtheoretical Model and other evidence-based physical activity research. We will use a
      Motivational Interviewing counseling technique delivered by a social worker to individually
      tailor the LPA intervention to participant preferences, taking into consideration their
      functional ability and need for information, readiness to change, and self-efficacy.
      Outcomes of the LPA intervention sessions will include tailored goals and an LPA plan.
      Intervention participants will also receive the newly developed NIA &quot;Exercise &amp; You&quot; LPA
      informational booklet with companion digital video disc (DVD) as well as motivational
      coaching via telephone calls, tapering in frequency for 6 months. The control group will
      receive the NIA LPA booklet with DVD and attention telephone calls. We will assess changes
      from baseline in LPA (primary outcome), readiness to change, self-efficacy and function
      (secondary outcomes) and examine the associations between primary and secondary outcomes in
      both groups. The allied disciplines of Nursing, Gerontology, Social Work, and Medicine will
      collaborate to promote PA and cardiovascular health of older women. Undergraduate and
      graduate student research assistants will contribute to this project. This research has the
      potential to increase PA of sedentary older women and reduce coronary heart disease risks.
      If we could increase physical activity in our rapidly growing older population —even
      modestly, we could make a significant impact to the health of our nation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Accelerometer (energy expenditure)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 month, six month and completion</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>This activity monitor uses a solid-state triaxial accelerometer to collect motion data on three axes for the highest level of analytic capabilities.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional health</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>SF-36</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Self-Efficacy for Exercise Scale</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Stage of Change</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Exercise Stage of Change</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">145</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Heart Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lifestyle Physical Activity Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>the women will be randomized to either the LPA Intervention (n=60) or Information/Attention Comparison (I/A, n=60) groups using a permuted block randomization scheme. Participants in both groups will be followed longitudinally with repeated assessments of LPA (accelerometer &amp; LPA diary), stage of change, and self-efficacy at baseline and 3 and 6 months; and functional health and well-being (SF36) at baseline and 6 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Information/Attention Comparison</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>the women will be randomized to either the LPA Intervention (n=60) or Information/Attention Comparison (I/A, n=60) groups using a permuted block randomization scheme. Participants in both groups will be followed longitudinally with repeated assessments of LPA (accelerometer &amp; LPA diary), stage of change, and self-efficacy at baseline and 3 and 6 months; and functional health and well-being (SF36) at baseline and 6 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lifestyle Physical Activity Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Behavioral counseling</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lifestyle Physical Activity Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Information / Attention Comparison</intervention_name>
    <description>Information and attention comparison</description>
    <arm_group_label>Information/Attention Comparison</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  women &gt; 60 years of age who are Senior Health clinic patients

          -  health care provider's approval to participate

          -  ability to speak/read English

          -  access to a telephone

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  report participation in a regular physical activity program

          -  report an unresolved acute illness, such as pneumonia or flu

          -  fail screening for capacity to provide informed consent

          -  fail a simple functional screen or are currently nonambulatory

          -  are unable to complete activities of daily living

          -  have uncorrectable severe hearing or vision deficits

          -  have a history of falls in the past 3 months

          -  have other unforeseen pathology that precludes safe participation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leanne L Lefler, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Arkansas</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Leanne L Lefler, PhD, RN</last_name>
      <phone>501-296-1939</phone>
      <email>LLefler@uams.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Leanne L Lefler, PhD, APN, RN</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jean C McSweeney, PhD, RN</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kimberly K Garner, MD, JD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 19, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 12, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>physical activity</keyword>
  <keyword>prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>coronary heart disease</keyword>
  <keyword>women</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
