<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="102571">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01963260</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>8723-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01963260</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Single Rising Dose Study of MK-8723 in Healthy Participants and Participants With Immune Thrombocytopenia Purpura (MK-8723-001)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Two-Part, Single Rising Dose Study to Assess the Safety, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of MK-8723 in Healthy Adults and Patients With Immune Thrombocytopenia Purpura</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Australia: National Health and Medical Research Council</authority>
    <authority>Israel: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objectives of this study are to assess the safety and tolerability of single
      rising doses of MK-8723 in healthy adult participants and adult participants with chronic
      immune thrombocytopenia purpura (ITP) and to assess pharmacodynamics of MK-8723 in
      participants with ITP.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In Part 1 of the trial, safety and pharmacokinetics of MK-8723 will be evaluated in healthy
      participants. In Part 2 of the trial, safety, pharmacokinetics, and pharmacodynamics will be
      evaluated among participants with ITP. In Part 1, dose escalation will occur in up to 5
      serial panels of partcipants (Panels A, B, C, D, and E); each participant will receive a
      single intravenous (IV) dose of MK-8723 (or placebo). In Part 2, dose escalation will occur
      in up to 3 serial panels of participants with ITP (Panels F, G and H); each participant will
      receive a single IV dose of MK-8723 (or placebo), once safety and tolerability of the
      corresponding dose is shown in Part 1.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics/Dynamics Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Experiencing an Adverse Event (AE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 84 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Discontinuing Study Due to An AE</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 84 Days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant Platelet Response Rate to MK-8723</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 14</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Curve (AUC[0-∞]) of MK-8723 Among Healthy Participants and Participants With ITP</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Serum Concentration (Cmax) of MK-8723 Among Healthy Participants and Participants With ITP</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>9</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">52</enrollment>
  <condition>Immune Thrombocytopenia Purpura</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Panel A: MK-8723 Very Low Dose in Healthy Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MK-8723 very low dose administered as a single intravenous (IV) infusion to healthy participants.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Panel B: MK-8723 Low Dose in Healthy Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MK-8723 low dose administered as a single IV infusion to healthy participants.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Panel C: MK-8723 Medium Dose in Healthy Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MK-8723 medium dose administered as a single IV infusion to healthy participants.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Panel D: MK-8723 Medium-High Dose in Healthy Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MK-8723 medium-high dose administered as a single IV infusion to healthy participants.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Panel E: MK-8723 High Dose in Healthy Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MK-8723 high dose administered as a single IV infusion to healthy participants.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Panel F: MK-8723 Medium Dose in ITP Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MK-8723 medium dose administered as a single IV infusion to participants with ITP.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Panel G: MK-8723 Medium-High Dose in ITP Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MK-8723 medium-high dose administered as a single IV infusion to participants with ITP.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Panel H: MK-8723 High Dose in ITP Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MK-8723 high dose administered as a single IV infusion to participants with ITP.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Matching Placebo to MK-8723</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Matching placebo to MK-8723 administered as a single IV infusion over approximately 4 hours on Day 1 of Study Part 1 and Study Part 2 in Panels A, B, C, D, E, F, G, H.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MK-8723</intervention_name>
    <description>MK-8723 administered as a single IV infusion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Panel A: MK-8723 Very Low Dose in Healthy Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Panel B: MK-8723 Low Dose in Healthy Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Panel C: MK-8723 Medium Dose in Healthy Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Panel D: MK-8723 Medium-High Dose in Healthy Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Panel E: MK-8723 High Dose in Healthy Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Panel F: MK-8723 Medium Dose in ITP Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Panel G: MK-8723 Medium-High Dose in ITP Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Panel H: MK-8723 High Dose in ITP Participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Matching Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo to MK-8723 administered as a single IV infusion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Matching Placebo to MK-8723</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria (Part 1):

          -  Female participants must be non-pregnant, non-breast feeding, and of non-childbearing
             potential;

          -  Has a Body Mass Index (BMI) &lt;=32 kg/m^2;

          -  Has a body weight &gt;= 50 kg and &lt;= 100 kg;

          -  Has been judged to be in good health based on medical history, physical examination,
             vital sign measurements, electrocardiogram (ECG), and laboratory safety tests;

          -  Non-smoker or has not used nicotine or nicotine-containing products for at least 3
             months;

        Inclusion Criteria (Part 2):

          -  Has been diagnosed with ITP at least 3 months prior;

          -  Female ITP participants must be non-pregnant, non-breast feeding, and either of 1)
             non-childbearing potential or 2) must have serum beta human chorionic gonadotropin
             (HGC) level consistent with a non-pregnant state, and agree to use acceptable
             contraception from pretrial period until 84 days postdose;

          -  Has a BMI &lt;=36 kg/m^2;

          -  Has been judged to be in good health, other than ITP diagnosis, based on medical
             history, physical examination, vital sign measurements, ECG, and laboratory safety
             tests;

        Exclusion Criteria (Part 1):

          -  Has a history or clinically significant endocrine, gastrointestinal, cardiovascular,
             hematological, hepatic, immunological, renal, respiratory, genitourinary, or major
             neurological abnormalities or diseases;

          -  Has a history of cancer (malignancy);

          -  Has a history of significant multiple and/or severe allergies or has had an
             anaphylactic reaction or significant intolerability to prescription or
             non-prescription drugs or food;

          -  Is positive for hepatitis B surface antigen, hepatitis C antibodies, or human
             immunodeficiency virus (HIV);

          -  Has had major surgery or donated or lost 1 unit of blood in the 4 weeks prior;

          -  Has participated in another investigational trial within 4 weeks (12 weeks for
             biologics);

          -  Has received a live virus vaccination within 42 days or plans to receive such while
             participating in the trial;

          -  Is unable to refrain from or anticipates the use of any medication, including
             prescription and non-prescription drugs and herbal remedies from 2 weeks prior and
             for the duration of the trial;

          -  Consumes greater than 3 glasses of alcoholic beverages per day;

          -  Consumes greater than 6 servings of caffeine-containing beverages per day;

          -  Is currently a regular user of any illicit drugs or has a history of drug and/or
             alcohol abuse within 3 months;

          -  Has a history of ITP or other autoimmune disease;

          -  Has an active infection that is clinically significant;

        Exclusion Criteria (Part 2):

          -  Has a comorbid and significant hematological or immunological disorder;

          -  Has a history of significant multiple and/or severe allergies or has had an
             anaphylactic reaction or significant intolerability to prescription or
             non-prescription drugs or food;

          -  Is positive for hepatitis B surface antigen, hepatitis C antibodies, or HIV;

          -  Has had major surgery or donated or lost 1 unit o f blood within 4 weeks;

          -  Has participated in another investigational trial within 4 weeks (12 weeks for
             biologics);

          -  Has a history of ITP unresponsive to intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG);

          -  Has had systemic corticosteroid use within 1month (with the exception of stable low
             dose oral corticosteroids);

          -  Has had systemic IVIG or other systemic immunomodulatory therapy within 3 months;

          -  Has received a thrombopoietin receptor antagonist within 3 months;

          -  Is unable to refrain from using thrombopoietin receptor agonists and/or systemic
             immune modulatory medications throughout the study;

          -  Has received a live virus vaccine within 42 days prior or plans to receive such
             during the trial;

          -  Consumes greater than 3 alcoholic beverages per day;

          -  Consumes greater than 6 servings of caffeine-containing beverages per day;

          -  Is currently a regular user of any illicit drugs or has a history of drug and/or
             alcohol abuse within 3 months;

          -  Has clinical evidence of bleeding or coagulopathy including petechial rash, easy
             bruising, or excessive gingival bleeding with routine dental hygiene;

          -  Has an active infection that is clinically significant.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Toll Free Number</last_name>
    <phone>1-888-577-8839</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme</name>
      <address>
        <city>North Ryde</city>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gary Jankelowitz</last_name>
      <phone>61 2 8988 8246</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Co. Ltd.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hod Hasharon</city>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ofer Sharon</last_name>
      <phone>972 9 9539310</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 11, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Purpura</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thrombocytopenia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Purpura, Thrombocytopenic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
