<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="74046">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02128243</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AIO-YMO-0111</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-002742-37</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02128243</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of S-1 Maintenance Therapy in Metastatic Esophagogastric Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>MATEO</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomized Controlled Trial of S-1 Maintenance Therapy in Metastatic Esophagogastric Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AIO-Studien-gGmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Taiho Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Nordic Pharma SAS</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AIO-Studien-gGmbH</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim is to assess the relative efficacy of S-1 de-escalation therapy vs. continuation of
      chemotherapy after induction therapy in patients with metastatic esophagogastric cancer in
      terms of overall survival.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Open-label, multi-center, controlled, randomized, parallel-group phase II trial in patients
      with metastatic esophagogastric cancer having received induction chemotherapy.

      Patients will be registered before the initiation of first-line chemotherapy regimen. This
      12-week induction therapy will consist of one of the following regimens: FLO/mod. FOLFOX-6,
      Cisplatin/S-1, FLOT or EOX/EOF (see interventions for specification of regimens). Regarding
      dose adjustments, Investigators should refer to Section 6.3 and to the summary of product
      characteristics of the chemotherapeutical agents. Patients having finished the preplanned
      induction therapy without tumor progression (i.e. with complete remission (CR), partial
      remission (PR) or stable disease (SD) according to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid
      Tumors (RECIST) Criteria Version 1.1) at week 12, being able to swallow capsules and having
      Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance score of 0-1 will be randomized in a
      2:1 ratio to receive Arm A or B.

      In Arm A patients will continue with S-1 de-escalation phase starting at week 13 until
      disease progression, toxicities requiring discontinuation, withdrawal of consent, pregnancy,
      death or lost to follow up whichever occurs first. In patients with drug-related severe
      toxicity S-1 dose will be adjusted or study treatment will be terminated.

      In Arm B patients will continue to receive the same polychemotherapy as during induction
      therapy until tumor progression, toxicities requiring discontinuation, withdrawal of
      consent, pregnancy, death or loss to follow up whichever occurs first.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>approx. 12 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>OS will be defined as the time length between randomization and the date of death from any cause or the date of last follow-up in case of no documentation of death.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>approx. 12 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PFS will be defined as the time length between the date of randomization and the date of first disease progression or death (whichever occurs first).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>approx. 12 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Quality of life will be evaluated using the validated European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Quality of Life Questionnaire (QLQ)-C30 questionnaire and the gastric module STO22.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Malnutrition</measure>
    <time_frame>approx. 12 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Explorative descriptive statistical methods will be applied to describe the results of the Nutritional Risk Screening stratified by visit and treatment arm.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival of non-randomized patients</measure>
    <time_frame>approx. 12 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>For exploratory purposes, the overall survival experience of non-randomized patients will be considered. The survival time is defined as the time length between start of induction therapy and the date of death from any cause or the date of last follow-up in case of no documentation of death.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>approx. 12 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>For descriptive analysis of toxicity/safety, summary tables will be presented showing the total number of patients reporting at least one specific event stratified by System Organ Class, Common terminology criteria for adverse events (CTCAE) term, CTCAE grade and causality.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Esophagogastric Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: De-escalation therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in Arm A will continue with S-1 de-escalation phase starting at week 13 until disease progression, toxicities requiring discontinuation, withdrawal of consent, pregnancy, death or lost to follow up whichever occurs first. In patients with drug-related severe toxicity S-1 dose will be adjusted or study treatment will be terminated.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: Chemotherapy by Investigator's choice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in Arm B will continue to receive the same polychemotherapy as during induction therapy until tumor progression, toxicities requiring discontinuation, withdrawal of consent, pregnancy, death or loss to follow up whichever occurs first.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>S-1 de-escalation</intervention_name>
    <description>S-1 30 mg/m² bid d1-14 q21d</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: De-escalation therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Teysuno</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chemotherapy by Investigator's choice</intervention_name>
    <description>Polychemotherapy administration as in induction therapy consists of a platinum and fluoropyrimidine compound as well as optional a taxane / an anthracycline compound.
Two-Drug combinations:
FLO / mod. FOLFOX-6 Cisplatin, S-1
Three-drug combinations:
EOX/EOF FLOT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: Chemotherapy by Investigator's choice</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>FLO regimen</other_name>
    <other_name>- Oxaliplatin 85 mg/m²</other_name>
    <other_name>- Leucovorin 200 mg/m²</other_name>
    <other_name>- 5-Fluorouracil 2600 mg/m²</other_name>
    <other_name>mod. FOLFOX-6 regimen</other_name>
    <other_name>- Leucovorin 400 mg/m²</other_name>
    <other_name>- 5-Fluorouracil 400 mg/m²</other_name>
    <other_name>- 5-Fluorouracil 2400 mg/m²</other_name>
    <other_name>Cisplatin / S-1</other_name>
    <other_name>- Cisplatin 75 mg/m²</other_name>
    <other_name>- S-1 25mg/m²</other_name>
    <other_name>EOX/EOF</other_name>
    <other_name>- Epirubicin 50 mg/m²</other_name>
    <other_name>- Oxaliplatin 130 mg/m²</other_name>
    <other_name>- Capecitabine 625 mg/m²</other_name>
    <other_name>FLOT</other_name>
    <other_name>- Docetaxel 50 mg/m²</other_name>
    <other_name>- Leucovorin 200 mg/mg²</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Signed written informed consent incl. participation in translational research

          2. Male or female patient 18 years or older

          3. Histologically confirmed metastatic or locally advanced unresectable gastric
             adenocarcinoma or adenocarcinoma of the esophagus or the esophagogastric junction
             (Her-2/neu negative or with unknown Her-2/neu status)

          4. Measurable disease as per RECIST 1.1 criteria

          5. Adjuvant/neoadjuvant or perioperative chemotherapy or (chemo-)radiotherapy must have
             been finished at least 6 months before study entry

          6. No previous systemic treatment (i.e.chemotherapy) for metastatic disease

          7. ECOG Performance Score 0-1 (Karnofsky Performance status &gt;= 80%)

          8. Ability for oral intake of the study drug, patients with tumor-related problems with
             oral intake might be registered if the symptom is expected to be improved during
             induction therapy (e.g. due to a tumor stenosis)

          9. Female patient of childbearing potential (i.e. did not undergo surgical sterilization
             - hysterectomy, bilateral tubal ligation, or bilateral oophorectomy - and is not
             post-menopausal for at least 24 consecutive months) with a negative pregnancy test

         10. Hematology and biochemistry laboratory results within the limits normally expected
             for the patient population, defined by the following:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1500/μl

               -  Platelet count ≥ 100000/μl

               -  Leukocyte count &gt; 3000/μl

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dL or 5.59 mmol/l, previous transfusions (&gt;3 days) of
                  erythrocytes are allowed

               -  Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 times the upper limit of normal (ULN), in patients with
                  known Meulengracht syndrome ≤ 3x ULN

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) ≤ 3x ULN in absence of liver metastases, or ≤
                  5x ULN in presence of liver metastases

               -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) ≤ 3x ULN in absence of liver metastases, or ≤ 5x
                  ULN in presence of liver metastases

               -  Creatinine clearance ≥30 mL/min according to Cockcroft-Gault formula

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Previous major surgery within the last 28 days before the start of the induction
             treatment. The implantation of a central venous access (e.g. port-a cath system) is
             allowed.

          2. History of other malignant tumors within the last 5 years, except basal cell
             carcinoma or curatively excised cervical carcinoma in situ

          3. Known brain metastases

          4. Concurrent radiotherapy involving target lesions used for this study. Concurrent
             palliative radiation for non-target lesions is allowed if other target lesions are
             available outside the involved field; previous radiotherapy including target lesions
             must have been finished at least 28 days before start of induction treatment.

          5. Previous systemic treatment (i.e. chemotherapy) for metastatic disease

          6. Known active Hepatitis B virus (HBV), Hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection or documented
             HIV infection

          7. Serious concomitant disease or medical condition that by judgment of the Investigator
             renders the patient at high risk of treatment complications

          8. Clinically relevant coronary artery disease (NYHA functional angina classification
             III/IV), congestive heart failure (NYHA III/IV), clinically relevant cardiomyopathy,
             history of myocardial infarction in the last 3 months, or high risk of uncontrolled
             arrhythmia

          9. Female patient pregnant or breast feeding

         10. Female patient of childbearing potential (i.e. did not undergo surgical sterilization
             - hysterectomy, bilateral tubal ligation, or bilateral oophorectomy - and is not
             post-menopausal for at least 24 consecutive months) not willing to use an adequate
             method of contraception to avoid pregnancy throughout the study and for up to 26
             weeks after the end of treatment. Male patient not willing to use an adequate method
             of contraception to avoid conception throughout the study and for up to 26 weeks
             after the end of treatment in such a manner that the risk of pregnancy is minimized.

         11. Concurrent treatment with other experimental drugs or participation in another
             clinical trial with any investigational drug within 60 days prior to start of
             induction

         12. Chronic diarrhea or short bowel syndrome

         13. Known hypersensitivity to S-1, other fluoropyrimidines or platinum compounds.
             Contraindication to receive S-1 as per current Summary of Product Characteristics.
             Known Dihydropyrimidine dehydrogenase (DPD) deficiency

         14. Grade ≥2 peripheral neuropathy

         15. Known drug abuse/alcohol abuse
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Georg Martin Haag, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NCT-Med. Onkologie</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Helge Schröder, Dipl.- Biol.</last_name>
    <phone>+49 - 30 - 8145 344</phone>
    <phone_ext>35</phone_ext>
    <email>helge.schroeder@aio-studien-ggmbh.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NCT-Med. Onkologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Heidelberg</city>
        <state>Baden-Württemberg</state>
        <zip>69120</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Georg Martin Haag, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+49-6221</phone>
      <phone_ext>5637630</phone_ext>
      <email>GeorgMartin.Haag@med.uni-heidelberg.de</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.aio-portal.de</url>
    <description>Working Group for Medical Oncology (AIO) from the German Cancer Society (DKG)</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 30, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 29, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Oxaliplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluorouracil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leucovorin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
