<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="129324">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01754376</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-343</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01754376</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Combined BRAF-Targeted Therapy &amp; Immunotherapy for Melanoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>COMBAT 1: A Phase II Trial of Combined BRAF-Targeted Therapy and Immunotherapy for Melanoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research study is a Phase II clinical trial of an investigational combination of drugs
      (vemurafenib and aldesleukin) to learn whether the combination works in treating a specific
      cancer. While both vemurafenib and aldesleukin are approved by the FDA for the treatment of
      metastatic melanoma, the FDA has not yet approved the combination of vemurafenib and
      aldesleukin.

      Researchers have found that a large number of melanoma cells have mutations in the BRAF
      gene. It has been shown that vemurafenib blocks the effects of these mutations in the BRAF
      gene, and, as a result, may help to prevent cancer growth.

      Aldesleukin, also referred to as IL-2, is an immunotherapy drug administered via IV infusion
      that increases the growth of key cells within the immune system that are responsible for
      targeting cancer cells. Activating more of these key cells, called T-lymphocytes and
      natural-killer cells, leads to increased cancer cell death.

      The BRAF gene is located on a larger pathway called the MAPK pathway. Studies have shown
      that when a BRAF inhibitor, like vemurafenib is used to block the MAPK pathway, melanocytes,
      or cancer cells express more proteins on their surfaces, making them easier for
      T-lymphocytes and natural killer cells to recognize and kill them. This suggests that
      combining BRAF-targeted therapy with aldesleukin, which activates more of these white blood
      cells, can lead to an increase in the death of cancer cells.

      In this research study, we are looking to see whether the combination of vemurafenib, a
      BRAF-inhibitor combined with aldesleukin, an immunotherapy drug, work together to produce a
      better health outcome in people with metastatic melanoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      You will take oral vemurafenib twice a day for 2 weeks. Following this lead-in period, you
      will receive aldesleukin via IV infusion on Day 15 of the study. One course of aldesleukin
      is 12 weeks long; you will receive aldesleukin via IV infusion every 8 hours for the first
      five days. Youi will be hospitalized for the 5 days that you are receiving aldesleukin. This
      week that you are hospitalized will be referred to as Week 1. Week 1 of aldesleukin will be
      days 15-19 (M-F) of the 12 week cycle. Following Week 1 of therapy, you will be discharged
      from the hospital and only take vemurafenib at home for the following week. You wil then
      come in for one more week of aldesleukin during days 29-33 of the 12 week cycle. This is
      referred to as Week 2 of aldesleukin.

      You will continue to take vemurafenib twice daily during the course of aldesleukin. Your
      cancer will be evaluated at screening and at Week 12 following the beginning of the first
      aldesleukin course with a CT scan. After the first cycle, your tumor will be evaluated every
      8 weeks for the first year, then every 12 weeks for years 2 and 3, every 6 months for year
      5, and annually thereafter.

      During the research study, you will come into the clinic weekly for various tests and
      procedures.

      If scans show that your cancer has improved after the first course of aldesleukin, your
      doctor may allow you to continue on the a second course. In the event of a second course of
      aldesleukin, you will remain on vemurafenib throughout the second course. If your doctor
      decides you will not receive a second course of aldesleukin, you may still remain on
      vemurafenib until one of the following events occurs: Your cancer becomes worse, you
      experience serious side effects that are from taking vemurafenib, you request to discontinue
      taking vemurafenib/withdraw from the study, you develop another illness that prevents you
      from being able to take vemurafenib, the study is terminated by the sponsor or your study
      doctor decides it is in your best interest to discontinue treatment with vemurafenib.

      In some cases if your cancer does get worse, but you and your study doctor believe you are
      still benefitting from vemurafenib in some way, you may continue receiving it after you
      consult with the study director.

      After the final dose of the study drug we would like to keep track of your medical condition
      for the rest of your life. We would like to do this by calling you on the telephone once a
      year to see how you are doing. Keeping in touch with you and checking your condition every
      year helps us look at the long-term effects of the research study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of Vemurafenib + Aldesleukin</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess the efficacy (as measured by progression-free survival (PFS)) of patients with metastatic melanoma with V600E mutation treated with the combination of vemurafenib and aldesleukin in comparison to an historic control of vemurafenib alone</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine Response Rates (Complete, Partial and Durable)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the complete response (CR), partial response (PR), and durable response (DR) rates (as defined as the rate of objective response (CR or PR) lasting continuously for 12 or more months, as compared to control therapy, and beginning at any point within 12 months of initiating therapy) in patients treated with aldesleukin and vemurafenib</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the overall survival in patients treated with aldesleukin and vemurafenib</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity and Safety of Aldesleukin and Vemurafenib</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the toxicity and safety of concurrent administration of aldesleukin and vemurafenib</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Confirm Pre-Clinical Data</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To confirm preclinical data indicating that pharmacologic inhibition of mutated BRAF enhances the immunogenicity of melanoma without adversely affecting the cellular immune response. To assess whether the number of doses of aldesleukin that can be safely administered is affected by the co-administration of vemurafenib</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exploration of Biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To explore biomarkers that may be relevant: to further predict responsiveness to vemurafenib and aldesleukin, to explain primary or acquired resistance to vemurafenib, to indicate pharmacodynamic effects of vemurafenib and to monitor the disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">49</enrollment>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oral vemurafenib twice a day IV infusion of aldesleukin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vemurafenib</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aldesleukin</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed metastatic or unresectable melanoma with V600E mutation

          -  Measurable disease

          -  May have received prior immunotherapy (excluding interleukin 2)

          -  Life expectancy greater than 3 months

          -  Recovered from effects of previous surgery and/or traumatic injury

          -  Must agree to use effective contraception

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding

          -  Psychological, familial or other conditions that could hamper compliance with
             protocol

          -  Receiving other study agents

          -  History of carcinomatous meningitis

          -  Known active brain metastases

          -  Have received a BRAF inhibitor

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness

          -  HIV positive on antiretroviral therapy

          -  History of a different malignancy within past 5 years (except cervical cancer in situ
             or basal/squamous cell carcinoma of the skin)

          -  Active hepatitis B or C

          -  Have received allogenic bone marrow transplant or organ transplant
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ryan J Sullivan, MD</last_name>
    <phone>617-724-4800</phone>
    <email>rsullivan7@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02113</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ryan J. Sullivan, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-724-4800</phone>
      <email>rsullivan7@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ryan J Sullivan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David McDermott, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-632-9270</phone>
      <email>dmcdermo@bidmc.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David McDermott, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 18, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 16, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ryan Sullivan, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Metastatic</keyword>
  <keyword>Unresectable</keyword>
  <keyword>V600E mutation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Aldesleukin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
