<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="24885">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01676714</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UCDCC#231</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CTKI258AUS21T</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01676714</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Dovitinib and Biomarkers in Advanced Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer or Advanced Colorectal Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of Dovitinib and Pilot Study of Fibroblast Growth Factor Receptor Biomarkers in Advanced Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer or Advanced Colorectal Cancer Previously Treated With Anti-Vascular Endothelial Growth Factor Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Davis</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Davis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to find out if dovitinib is an effective treatment for patients
      with advanced lung cancer or advanced colorectal cancer (CRC) who have progressed on
      anti-vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purposes of this study are 1) to evaluate the clinical efficacy of dovitinib and 2) to
      prospectively estimate the prevalence of fibroblast growth factor (FGF) signaling
      alterations in patients with advanced non-squamous non small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) or
      advanced CRC who have progressed on anti-VEGF treatment.  Additionally, the investigators
      will make exploratory initial observations of the relationship between FGF signaling
      alterations and the clinical activity of dovitinib.  This trial is expected to provide key
      biologic information that will inform the clinical development of dovitinib and provide
      initial evaluation of the analytic characteristics of these potential predictive biomarkers
      of its efficacy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Response</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of treatment until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 100 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured by an X-Ray and/or a CT and/or an MRI (RECIST criteria)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Control Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The total proportion of patients who demonstrate a response to treatment. Measured by RECIST criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of treatment until the date of death from any cause, assessed up to 100 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The length of time during and after the treatment of the cancer that a patient lives with the disease but it does not get worse.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>Starting at screening and then at every visit and then up to 30 days after the last dose of study treatment.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Toxicities will be summarized by the type, severity (by NCI CTCAE), time of onset, duration, and outcome.  Toxicity will be graded according to the NCI CTCAE version 4.0.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dovitinib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>500 mg of dovitinib (5 capsules) once a day for 5 continuous days and stop for 2 days. Continue to take dovitinib capsules in this manner until until progression or unacceptable toxicity develops.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dovitinib</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Dovitinib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TK1258</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed non-small cell lung cancer or colorectal cancer for which no
             potentially curative treatment options are available

          -  Any number of prior treatment regimens are allowed

          -  Immediate prior treatment regimen must have included an anti-VEGF agent.  Acceptable
             anti-VEGF therapy includes bevacizumab, sunitinib, or sorafenib.  For other anti-VEGF
             therapies, contact the principal investigator.

          -  Last dose administered of bevacizumab must be at least 21-days but not more than
             56-days from enrollment.

          -  Last dose of anti-VEGF tyrosine kinase inhibitor must be at least 7-days but not more
             than 56-days from enrollment.

          -  Willingness to consent to research biopsy

          -  Measurable disease by RECIST 1.1 criteria

          -  Available tumor site amenable to core needle biopsy as determined by the treating
             investigator.  Any questions regarding suitability of site for biopsy will be
             adjudicated by the principal investigator.

          -  Zubrod (ECOG) performance status 0 or 1

          -  Age ≥ 18 years old

          -  Patients who give a written informed consent

          -  Patients must have the following laboratory values:

               -  Platelets ≥ 100 x 109/L

               -  Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1.5 x 109/L Hemoglobin &gt; 9 g/dL

               -  Serum total bilirubin: ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of normal ULN

               -  ALT and AST ≤ 3.0 x ULN ( with or without liver metastases)

               -  Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 x ULN or serum creatinine &gt;1.5 - 3 x ULN

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with known brain metastases

          -  Patients with another primary malignancy within 3 years prior to starting study drug,
             with the exception of adequately treated in-situ carcinoma of the uterine cervix, or
             skin cancer

          -  Patients who have received the last administration of an anticancer therapy including
             chemotherapy, immunotherapy, hormonal therapy and monoclonal antibodies that have not
             resolved to NCI CTCAE grade 1 or less.

          -  Patients who have received the last administration of nitrosurea or mitomycin-C ≤ 6
             weeks prior to starting study drug, or who have side effects that have not resolved
             to NCI CTCAE grade 1 or less.

          -  Patients who have received targeted therapy  ≤ 1 week prior to starting study drug,
             or who have not recovered from the side effects of such therapy

          -  Patients who have had radiotherapy ≤ 4 weeks prior to starting study drug, or ≤ 2
             weeks prior to starting study drug in the case of localized radiotherapy or who have
             not recovered from radiotherapy toxicities

          -  Patients who have undergone major surgery, open biopsy or significant traumatic
             injury ≤ 4 weeks prior to starting study drug, or patients who have had minor
             procedures, percutaneous biopsies or placement of vascular access device ≤ 1 week
             prior to starting study drug,  or who have not recovered from side effects of such
             procedure or injury

          -  Patients with any of the following concurrent severe and/or uncontrolled medical
             conditions which could compromise participation in the study:

               -  Impaired cardiac function or clinically significant cardiac diseases

               -  Impairment of gastrointestinal (GI) function or GI disease that may
                  significantly alter the absorption of dovitinib

               -  Cirrhosis, chronic active hepatitis or chronic persistent hepatitis

               -  Known diagnosis of human immunodeficiency virus  infection

               -  Patients who are currently receiving anticoagulation treatment with therapeutic
                  doses of warfarin

               -  Other concurrent severe and/or uncontrolled concomitant medical conditions

          -  Pregnant or breast-feeding women

          -  Women of child-bearing potential, who are biologically able to conceive, not
             employing two forms of highly effective contraception.

          -  Fertile males not willing to use contraception, as stated above

          -  Patients unwilling or unable to comply with the protocol
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas Semrad, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Davis</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Clinical Trials Navigator</last_name>
    <phone>916-734-3089</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sacramento</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95817</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 10, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 27, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dovitinib</keyword>
  <keyword>Fibroblast Growth Factor Receptor Biomarkers</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti-Vascular Endothelial Growth Factor Therapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Mitogens</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endothelial Growth Factors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
