<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="25200">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02081014</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>XSMP-201</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R44DK096715-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02081014</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy Study of Mini-Dose Glucagon (G-Pen Mini) in Patients With Type 1 Diabetes</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Phase 2a, Blinded, 3-Way Crossover Dose-Ranging Study With G-Pen Mini™ (Glucagon Injection) to Evaluate Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics in Patients With Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus (T1DM)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Xeris Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Emissary International LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Xeris Pharmaceuticals</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to demonstrate that mini-doses of Xeris' stable liquid glucagon
      (G-Pen Mini) are safe and effective as a treatment for mild to moderate hypoglycemia, a
      complication of diabetes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of G-Pen Mini™ (glucagon injection) doses</measure>
    <time_frame>From first dose until follow-up call, ~ 4 weeks per subject</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Vital signs, body weight and laboratory tests, AEs as well as serious adverse events (SAEs)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the pharmacodynamics of G-Pen Mini™ (glucagon injection) doses</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 15 minutes before each injection until 3 hours post-injection</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>AUC(0-inf), Cmax, CL, Tmax, T½ el, and Vext</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the pharmacodynamics (efficacy) of G-Pen Mini™ (glucagon injection) doses</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 15 minutes before each injection until 3 hours post-injection</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>BGmax, TBGmax, AUC0-rtb, AUCex, MAE, and TBGex</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypoglycemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>G-Pen Mini™ (glucagon injection) 75 ug</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>G-Pen Mini™ (glucagon injection), single 75 microgram subcutaneous injection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>G-Pen Mini™ (glucagon injection) 150 ug</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>G-Pen Mini™ (glucagon injection), single 150 microgram subcutaneous injection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>G-Pen Mini™ (glucagon injection) 300 ug</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>G-Pen Mini™ (glucagon injection), single 300 microgram subcutaneous injection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>G-Pen Mini™ (glucagon injection)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>G-Pen Mini™ (glucagon injection) 75 ug</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>G-Pen Mini™ (glucagon injection) 150 ug</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>G-Pen Mini™ (glucagon injection) 300 ug</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male and female subjects who have documentation of or with laboratory evidence of GAD
             and/or ICA antibody positive type 1 diabetes (anti-insulin or anti-islet cell
             antibodies).

          2. Between the ages of 18 and 30 years of age, inclusive, at Screening.

          3. Well controlled/managed insulin-using patients without clinical evidence of chronic
             complications of diabetes or any other chronic disease except hypothyroidism.

          4. Females of childbearing potential with a negative serum pregnancy test prior at
             screening and negative urine pregnancy tests  prior to the  Treatment visits, using
             an approved forms of contraception for the duration of participation in the study
             (i.e. until after last dose).

          5. Male subjects are required to use a condom and another of the methods of
             contraception in #4 above starting at Randomization and for the duration of the
             study.

          6. HgA1c &lt; 9.0 %.

          7. All subjects must be on an insulin infusion pump

          8. No other medications other than thyroid replacement and insulin

          9. No other chronic illnesses other than well controlled hypothyroidism.

         10. Normal plasma concentrations of Hgb, AST and ALT.

         11. Evidence of a personally signed and dated informed consent document indicating that
             the subject has been informed of all pertinent aspects of the study.

         12. Subjects must be willing and able to comply with scheduled visits, treatment,
             laboratory tests and study procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Islet cell antibody negative

          2. Clinical evidence of microvascular complication(s)

          3. Any chronic diseases or illness, except for T1DM, or medications other than
             hypothyroidism on appropriate thyroid hormone replacement.

          4. A total bilirubin level above 1.5 mg/dl

          5. ALT or AST above the upper limit of normal

          6. BP readings at Screening where SBP &lt;90 or &gt;140 mm Hg, and DBP &lt;50 or &gt;90 mm Hg.

          7. Cardiovascular event within 6 months prior to screening such as unstable angina,
             acute coronary syndrome, myocardial infarction, therapeutic coronary procedure (e.g.,
             stent placement, Percutaneous Transluminal Coronary Angioplasty (PTCA), Coronary
             Artery By-pass Grafting (CABG)), stroke or transient ischemic attack.

          8. Study participants who are pregnant at Screening.

          9. Breast feeding must be discontinued if a subject wishes to participate in this study.

         10. Positive test for hepatitis B, hepatitis C, or HIV found at Screening.

         11. Positive urine drug test for illicit drugs at Screening.

         12. History of allergies to glucagon, glucagon-like products or to any of the excipients
             in the investigational formulation.

         13. Known presence of hereditary problems of glycogen storage disease, galactose and /or
             lactose intolerance

         14. Recent (i.e., within three (3) months prior to Screening) administration of glucagon.

         15. Subjects with any of the following abnormalities in clinical laboratory tests at
             Screening, confirmed by a single repeat, if necessary:

               -  Total bilirubin above the upper limits of normal for the laboratory

               -  AST/SGOT or ALT/SGPT above the upper limits of normal for the laboratory

               -  Creatinine above the upper limits of normal for the laboratory

         16. History of regular alcohol consumption as defined by alcohol intake in a quantity
             exceeding 7 drinks per week for females or 14 drinks per week for males, where 1
             drink = 5 ounces (150 mL) of wine or 12 ounces (360 mL) of beer or 1.5 ounces (45 mL)
             of hard liquor.

         17. Participation in other studies involving administration of an investigational drug or
             device within 30 days or 5 half-lives, whichever is longer, before screening for the
             current study and during participation in the current study.

         18. Whole blood donation of 1 pint (500 mL) within 8 weeks prior to Screening.  Donations
             of plasma, packed RBCs, platelets or quantities less than 500 mL are allowed at
             investigator discretion.

         19. Other severe acute or chronic medical or psychiatric condition or laboratory
             abnormality that may increase the risk associated with study participation or
             investigational product administration or may interfere with the interpretation of
             study results and, in the judgment of the investigator, would make the subject
             inappropriate for entry into this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Morey W Haymond, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor College of Medicine, Children's Nutritional Research Center, Texas Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Morey W. Haymond, MD</last_name>
      <phone>713-798-6776</phone>
      <email>mhaymond@bcm.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 4, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hypoglycemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Glucagon</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypoglycemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Glucagon</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glucagon-Like Peptide 1</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
