<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="82458">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02081248</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BMTCTN1205</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2U10HL069294-11</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02081248</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Easy-to-Read Informed Consent (ETRIC) for Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation Clinical Trials (BMT Clinical Trials Network 1205)</brief_title>
  <acronym>ETRIC</acronym>
  <official_title>Easy-to-Read Informed Consent (ETRIC) for Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation Clinical Trials (BMT CTN 1205)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical College of Wisconsin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Blood and Marrow Transplant Clinical Trials Network</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical College of Wisconsin</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study has two parts: (1) Randomized Study to evaluate the effectiveness of ETRIC, and
      (2) Evaluation Study to understand barriers to implementation of ETRIC.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A two-arm, randomized study will be conducted in patients about to undergo consent
      discussion for participation in two large, multicenter BMT CTN clinical trials. Once they
      agree to participate in this Easy-to-Read Informed Consent (ETRIC) study, they will go
      through the consent process for the parent trial (BMT CTN 0901 or 1101 trials) using either
      a standard or the ETRIC consent form. The content of both forms will be similar but the
      ETRIC form will incorporate a two-column format with specific attention towards enhanced
      readability and processability. Following the consent discussion for the BMT CTN 0901 or
      1101 trials, patients will complete assessments of health literacy, comprehension of the
      parent trial and satisfaction and anxiety related to the consent process. These assessments
      will be completed within 7 business days of the consent discussion of the parent trial.

      Enrollment on the BMT CTN 0901 trial (NCT01339910) was closed to further accrual on April
      18, 2014.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comprehension</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary objective of the trial is to compare objective comprehension scores on the Quality of Informed Consent (part A) instrument between subjects randomized to the ETRIC versus the standard consent arms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary Comprehension</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Quality of Informed Consent (part B) measures actual subjects understanding of cancer clinical trials to address 13 independent domains of informed consent.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary Comprehension</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Deaconess Informed Consent Comprehension Test (DICCT) uses semi-structured interviews to assess subject's understanding of 8 core elements of disclosure for the study they have agreed to participate in.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>State Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI) measures anxiety and distinguishes it from depressive syndromes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Short study specific questionnaire and selected questions from the Quality of Informed Consent (QuIC) supplement questionnaire will query participants about their overall satisfaction with the consent process, helpfulness of information provided, and comprehension of key study-specific elements of treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Information Location</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subjects are asked to identify select items within the consent document and the time taken to locate items is measured.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Literacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Rapid Estimate of Adult Literacy in Medicine (REALM) is a medical-word recognition and pronunciation test to determine subject's grade-equivalent reading level.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Literacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Newest Vital Sign (NVS) uses an ice cream container nutrition label to measure numeracy and reading comprehension.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>To Improve the Informed Consent Process.</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Consent</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will receive the Consent Form Specific Format 1 'standard consent'. The standard consents are already approved and used for the BMT CTN 0901 and 1101 trials.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Easy-to-Read Informed Consent</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will receive the Consent Form Specific Format 2 'Easy-to-Read Informed Consent'.The Easy-to-Read Informed Consent (ETRIC) is the newly approved consent.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Consent Form Specific Format 1 or 2</intervention_name>
    <description>The Consent Form Specific Format 1 is the 'Standard Consent' and the Consent Form Specific Format 2 is the 'Easy-to-Read Informed Consent'. The Easy-to-Read Informed Consent is two-columns with changes in layout readability, organization of content, typography and use of plain language. The standard consent does not have these formatting changes and are already used by sites for the BMT CTN 0901 and 1101 clinical trials.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Consent</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Easy-to-Read Informed Consent</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria and Exclusion Criteria for the ETRIC randomized study will be the same
        as the eligibility criteria for the BMT CTN 0901 and 1101 studies.

        Note: Enrollment on the BMT CTN 0901 trial (NCT01339910) was closed to further accrual on
        April 18, 2014.

        BMT CTN 0901 Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≤ 65 years and ≥ 18 years.

          -  Patients with the diagnosis of MDS or AML with fewer than 5% myeloblasts in the bone
             marrow and no leukemic myeloblasts in the peripheral blood on morphologic analysis
             performed within 30 days of enrollment.

          -  For patients receiving treatment of their MDS or AML prior to transplantation:

               -  Interval between the start of the most recent cycle of conventional cytotoxic
                  chemotherapy and enrollment must be at least 30 days.

               -  Interval between completing treatment with a hypomethylating agent or other
                  non-cytotoxic chemotherapy and enrollment must be at least 10 days.

          -  Patients must have a related or unrelated bone marrow or peripheral blood donor.

          -  Sibling donor must be a 6/6 match at HLA-A and - B (intermediate or higher
             resolution) and -DRB1 (at high resolution using DNA-based typing).

          -  Related donor other than sibling must be a 7/8 or 8/8 match at HLA-A, -B, -C (at
             intermediate or higher resolution) and -DRB1 (at high resolution using DNA-based
             typing).

          -  Unrelated donor must be a 7/8 or 8/8 match at HLA-A, -B, -C, and -DRB1 at high
             resolution using DNA-based typing.

          -  HCT-Specific Comorbidity Index Score (HCT-CI) ≤ 4.

          -  Organ function:

             o Cardiac function: Ejection fraction ≥ 40%.

          -  Hepatic function: total bilirubin ≤ 2x the upper limit of normal and ALT and AST
             ≤ 3x the upper limit of normal.

             o Pulmonary function: DLCO (corrected for hemoglobin) ≥ 40% and FEV1 ≥ 50%

          -  Estimated creatinine clearance ≥ 50mL/min/based on the Cockcroft-Gault formula.

          -  Signed informed consent.

        BMT CTN 0901 Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior allograft or prior autograft.

          -  Symptomatic coronary artery disease.

          -  Leukemia involvement in the CNS within 4 weeks of enrollment for patients with a
             history of prior CNS leukemia involvement (i.e., leukemic blasts previously detected
             in the cerebral spinal fluid).

          -  Karnofsky Performance Score &lt; 70.

          -  Patients receiving supplemental oxygen.

          -  Planned use of DLI therapy.

          -  Patients with uncontrolled bacterial, viral or fungal infections (undergoing
             appropriate treatment and with progression of clinical symptoms).

          -  Patients seropositive for the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).

          -  Patients with prior malignancies, except resected basal cell carcinoma or treated
             cervical carcinoma in situ.  Cancer treated with curative intent &gt; 5 years previously
             will be allowed.  Cancer treated with curative intent &lt; 5 years previously will not
             be allowed unless approved by the Protocol Officer or one of the Protocol Chairs.

          -  Females who are pregnant or breastfeeding.

          -  Fertile men and women unwilling to use contraceptive techniques during and for 12
             months following treatment.

        BMT CTN 1101 Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age: Subjects ≥ 18 and ≤ 70 years old

          -  Patients must have available both:

               -  One or more potential related mismatched donors (biologic parent (s) or siblings
                  (full or half) or children).  At least low resolution DNA based typing at HLA-A,
                  -B and -DRB1 for potential haplo-identical sibling donors is required
                  pre-randomization.  HLA typing of biological parents and children as potential
                  haplo-identical donors is not required pre-randomization.

               -  At least two potential umbilical cord blood units identified.

          -  Each unit must have a minimum of 1.5 x 107/kg pre-cryopreserved total nucleated cell
             dose. For non-red blood cell depleted units, the minimum pre-cryopreserved total
             nucleated cell dose of each unit must be at least 2.0 x 107/kg.

          -  Units must be HLA matched at a minimum of 4/6 to the recipient at HLA-A, HLA-B (at
             low resolution using DNA based typing) and HLA-DRB1 (at high resolution using DNA
             based typing). Confirmatory typing is not required for randomization.

          -  Patients must have received either

               -  At least one cycle of at least one of the following cytotoxic chemotherapy
                  regimens (or regimen of similar intensity) within 3 months of enrollment
                  (measured from the start date of chemotherapy) Multi-agent chemotherapy (e.g.
                  CVP±R, CHOP±R, ICE±R, DHAP±R, ESHAP±R, …) Chemotherapy regimens like those that
                  are given as induction or consolidation of acute leukemia (7+3, HiDAc,
                  mitoxantrone+etoposide, FLAG, FLIG, and others) Single drug alkylator agent
                  (cyclophosphamide ≥1.5 g/m2 or equivalent) Bendamustine Single agent alemtuzumab
                  or brentuximab vedotin

               -  Antineoplastic agents that are not considered adequate cytotoxic chemotherapy
                  include:

        Single agent steroids Single agent monoclonal antibody ± steroids with the exception of
        alemtuzumab Single agent hypomethylating agent (e.g. azacytidine) Single agent
        antimetabolite ± steroids (e.g. low dose methotrexate, low dose cytarabine) Single agent
        proteasome inhibitor ± monoclonal antibody (except for alemtuzumab or brentuximab vedotin)
        ± steroids Hydroxyurea Localized radiation therapy Interferon

          -  Autologous hematopoietic stem cell transplantation &lt; 2 years prior to enrollment.

               -  Please consult with the protocol chairs for any drugs or regimens not listed
                  above.

               -  . Acute Leukemias (includes T lymphoblastic lymphoma):

          -  Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL) in first complete remission (CR1) that is NOT
             considered favorable-risk as defined by the presence of at least one of the
             following:

        Adverse cytogenetics such as t(9;22), t(1;19), t(4;11), other MLL rearrangements, White
        blood cell counts of greater than 30,000/mcL (B-ALL) or greater than 100,000/mcL (T-ALL)
        at diagnosis, Recipient age older than 30 years at diagnosis, Time to CR greater than 4
        weeks

          -  Acute Myelogenous Leukemia (AML) in first complete remission (CR1) (see  remission
             definition in Chapter 3) that is NOT considered as favorable-risk.

          -  Favorable risk is defined as having one of the following:

               -  t(8,21) without CKIT mutation

               -  inv(16) without CKIT mutation or t(16;16)

               -  Normal karyotype with mutated NPM1 and not FLT3-ITD

               -  Normal karyotype with double mutated CEBPA

               -  APL in first molecular remission at end of consolidation

          -  Acute Leukemias in 2nd or subsequent CR (see remission definition in Chapter 3).

          -  Biphenotypic/Undifferentiated/Prolymphocytic Leukemias in first or subsequent CR,
             adult T-cell leukemia/lymphoma in first or subsequent CR

               -  Burkitt's lymphoma: second or subsequent CR.

               -  Lymphoma fulfilling the following criteria:

          -  Chemotherapy-sensitive (complete or partial response) lymphomas that have failed at
             least 1 prior regimen of multi-agent chemotherapy and are INELIGIBLE for an
             autologous transplant.

          -  Marginal zone B-cell lymphoma or follicular lymphoma that has progressed after at
             least  two prior therapies (excluding single agent Rituxan).

               -  Performance status: Karnofsky score ≥ 70%.

        BMT CTN 1101 Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with suitably matched related or unrelated donor, as defined per
             institutional practice.

             o An unrelated donor search is not required for a patient to be eligible for this
             protocol, or a search and donor mobilization may be abandoned, if the clinical
             situation dictates an urgent transplant.  Clinical urgency is defined as 6-8 weeks
             from referral to transplant or a low-likelihood of finding a matched, unrelated
             donor.

          -  Recipients of prior autologous hematopoietic stem cell transplantation are ineligible
             if disease recurrence occurred &lt; 6 months from their autologous hematopoietic stem
             cell transplant.

          -  Current uncontrolled bacterial, viral or fungal infection (currently taking
             medication with evidence of progression of clinical symptoms or radiologic findings).

          -  Prior allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant.

          -  Patients with history of primary idiopathic myelofibrosis or any severe marrow
             fibrosis.

          -  Planned use of prophylactic donor lymphocyte infusion (DLI) therapy.

          -  Anti-donor HLA antibodies.  Positive anti-donor HLA antibody is defined as a positive
             crossmatch test of any titer (by complement-dependent cytotoxicity or flow cytometric
             testing) or the presence of anti-donor HLA antibody to the high expression loci
             HLA-A, -B, -C, or -DRB1 with mean fluorescence intensity &gt;1000 by solid phase
             immunoassay.

          -  Fertile men or women unwilling to use 2 effective forms of birth control or
             abstinence.

          -  German centers only: Treatment with any known non-marketed drug substance or
             experimental therapy within 5 terminal half lives or 4 weeks prior to enrollment,
             whichever is longer, or participation in any other interventional clinical study.

        BMT CTN 1205 Additional Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Speaking and reading proficiency in English (as most of this study's instruments have
             not been translated and validated in languages other than English).

          -  Willing and able to provide informed consent.

          -  Stated willingness to comply with study procedures and reporting requirements.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Navneet S Majhail, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>The Cleveland Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ryan Spellecy, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mary Horowitz, MD, MS</last_name>
    <email>marymh@mcw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ellen Parker</last_name>
    <phone>301-251-1161</phone>
    <email>eparker@emmes.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City of Hope National Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Duarte</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida (Shands)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32610-0277</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Florida Hospital Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32804</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33624</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>BMT Program at Northside Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30342</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Kansas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lawrence</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21231</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Karmanos Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic (Rochester)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14263</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Jewish Hospital BMT Program</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45236</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospitals of Cleveland/Case Western</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104-3309</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virginia Commonwealth University MCV Hospitals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23298</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>West Virginia University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Morgantown</city>
        <state>West Virginia</state>
        <zip>26506-9162</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.bmtctnsp.net</url>
    <description>Link Text: Blood and Marrow Transplant Clinical Trials Network</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 25, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 30, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
