<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="168158">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01878799</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130159</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-I-0159</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01878799</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of A Combination Pill With GS-7977 and GS-5885 for Hepatitis C in People With HIV</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open Label Trial to Assess Safety, Tolerability, and Efficacy of the Fixed Dose Combination of GS-7977 and GS-5885 in HCV Genotype 1 Subjects Coinfected With HIV</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Present treatment for hepatitis C includes the use of a weekly injection and two different
      pills. This treatment is associated with serious side effects. Drugs that can be taken by
      mouth and cure HCV infection without serious side effects would be a great help to the large
      number of people infected with HCV. GS-7977 and GS-5885 are new medications being developed
      to treat the hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection. They are still being researched and are not
      approved by the Food and Drug Administration. They are being developed as treatment for
      hepatitis C as a single pill taken once a day.

      Objectives:

      - To determine whether a combination of the two study drugs can safely and effectively treat
      HCV infection in people with HIV infection and who do not have cirrhosis of the liver.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals who have HIV infection and have liver disease caused by infection with HCV.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. Blood samples
           will be collected. Urine samples will be collected from participants who might become
           pregnant. If a participant has not had a liver biopsy in the past 3 years, one will be
           required.

        -  Participants will take one pill daily for 12 weeks. This pill will be a combination of
           the two study drugs.

        -  Treatment will be monitored with frequent clinic visits and blood tests over a total of
           60 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection is a major public health problem with an estimated
      180 million people infected worldwide. In the US an estimated 4.1 million people are
      infected with HCV which is the principal cause of death from liver disease and leading
      indication for liver transplantation. Significant advances have been made with the approval
      of directly acting antivirals (DAA) namely the protease inhibitors, telaprevir (TVR) and
      boceprevir (BOC) which have been shown to significantly improve rates of sustained virologic
      response (SVR).  Response rates to these new combinations in HIV/HCV are also very
      promising, however treatment has been characterized with high rates of toxicities.

      Recently several trials have confirmed the efficacy of potent DAA therapy without
      concomitant IFN in the treatment of HCV monoinfected individuals. Given the improved
      response rates achieved with a combination of DAAs with fast HCV suppression and improved
      side-effect profiles; and the need for better therapy for HIV/HCV co-infected subjects, we
      propose a study to determine the safety, tolerability and efficacy of 12 weeks of treatment
      with a fixed dose combination of GS-7977 and GS-5885 in HIV/HCV Genotype 1 (GT-1) subjects.
      We hypothesize that anti-HCV therapy that does not rely on the host immune system will
      provide an enhanced rate of SVR among HIV/HCV GT-1 coinfected subjects. The findings from
      this study will aid in our understanding of determinants of response to an IFN-free regimen
      in HIV/HCV coinfected individuals.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the safety, tolerability and efficacy of a fixed dose combination (FDC) of GS-7977/GS-5885 tablets for 12 weeks in HIV/HCV GT-1 coinfected subjects who are IFN-treatment na(SqrRoot) ve.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0, Day 1, Day 3, Day 5, Day 7, Day 10,Week 2, Week 3, Week 4, Week 6, Week 8, Week 12, Week 14, Week 16, Week 20, Week 24, Week 36, Week 48, Week 60</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the fitness of NS5A/B viral mutants in vivo in the presence or absence of a fixed dose combination of GS-7977/ GS-5885 in vitro by performing NS5A/B site directed mutagenesis.</measure>
    <time_frame>At study completion</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare HCV quasispecies evolution from baseline and throughout 12 weeks of treatment (especially during relapse or viral breakthrough) and assess the influence on virologic response to treatment in HIV/HCV GT-1 coinfected patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>At study completion</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare the immunologic, virologic and host genetic/proteomic predictors of response to treatment with a fixed dose combination of GS-7977/GS-5885 in subjects treated for 12 weeks.</measure>
    <time_frame>At study completion</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">63</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatitis C</condition>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HIV</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects with HIV and HCV</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GS-7977/GS- 5885 FDC</intervention_name>
    <description>The GS-7977/GS-5885 FDC product combines a potent HCV nucleotide inhibitor and a potent HCV NS5A inhibitor and will be given for 12 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>HIV</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. Eighteen years of age or older at screening.

               2. HCV treatment-na(SqrRoot) ve, as defined as no prior exposure to any IFN, RBV,
                  or other approved or experimental HCV-specific direct-acting antiviral agent.

               3. Participants must be willing to practice either:

                    1. Abstinence from sexual intercourse or

                    2. At least 2 forms of contraception including one barrier method from 2 weeks
                       prior to Day 0 through 30 days after the last dose is received.

                  i. Female partners of male study subjects may rely upon hormonal contraception
                  as one of the 2 methods; however female study subjects may not.

               4. Chronic hepatitis C infection defined as one of the following:

                    1. Positive for anti-HCV antibody, HCV RNA, or an HCV genotype at least 6
                       months before screening, and positive for HCV RNA and anti-HCV antibody at
                       the time of screening or

                    2. Positive for anti-HCV antibody and HCV RNA at the time of screening with a
                       liver biopsy consistent with chronic HCV infection (or a liver biopsy
                       performed before enrollment with evidence of chronic hepatitis C disease,
                       such as the presence of fibrosis).

               5. HIV treatment status:

                    1. Documented HIV infection, ARV untreated for &gt; 8 weeks preceding dosing and
                       having either:

                         1. a CD4 T-cell count greater  than or equal to 500 cells/mm3 within 8
                            weeks of Day 0 or

                         2. an HIV viral load less than 500 copies/mL with a stable CD4 count for
                            at least 3 months.

                    2. Documented HIV infection on a stable, protocol-approved, ARV regimen for
                       greater than or equal to 8 weeks prior to dosing and is expected to
                       continue the current ARV regimen through the end of study with all of the
                       following:

                         1. a CD4 T-cell count &gt; 100 cells/mm3

                         2. a documented plasma HIV-1 RNA level less than the level of detection
                            for at least 8 weeks preceding dosing.

                            If the lower limit of detection of the local HIV-1 RNA assay is &lt; 50
                            copies/mL (e.g.,&lt; 20 copies/mL), the Screening plasma HIV-1 RNA level
                            cannot exceed 50 copies/mL.

                         3. HIV ARV agents including only combination regimens consisting of
                            medications from the following list: tenofovir (TDF), emtricitabine
                            (FTC), efavirenz, raltegravir, and rilpivirine administered according
                            to their manufacturer   s prescribing information. (reference Section
                            10.3 for additional information)

               6. Documentation of hepatitis C genotype 1a, 1b or mixed 1a/1b

               7. Absence of cirrhosis, defined as one of the following:

                    1. A liver biopsy performed within 36 calendar months of screening showing
                       absence of cirrhosis.

                    2. FibroTest   score of &lt; 0.48 AND APRI of &lt; 1 performed during the 8 weeks
                       preceding dosing (In the absence of a definitive diagnosis of presence or
                       absence of cirrhosis by the above criteria, a liver biopsy is required).

               8. Able to effectively communicate with the Investigator and other center
                  personnel.

               9. Willing to give written informed consent and comply with the study restrictions
                  and requirements.

              10. If opioid-dependent, subjects must be participating in a supervised treatment.

              11. Participants must have a primary medical provider outside of OP8 and the NIH for
                  medical management.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Subjects who meet any of the following exclusion criteria are not to be enrolled in this
        study:

          1. Current or prior history of any of the following:

               1. Clinically significant illness (other than HCV) or any other major medical
                  disorder that may interfere with subject treatment, assessment or compliance
                  with the protocol; subjects currently under evaluation for a potentially
                  clinically-significant illness (other than HCV) are also excluded.

               2. Gastrointestinal disorder or post-operative condition that could interfere with
                  the absorption of the study drug.

               3. Poor venous access interfering with required study blood collection.

               4. Clinical hepatic decompensation (i.e., ascites, encephalopathy or variceal
                  hemorrhage).

               5. Solid organ transplantation.

               6. Significant pulmonary disease, significant cardiac disease or porphyria.

               7. Unstable psychiatric disease (Subjects with psychiatric illness that is
                  well-controlled on a stable treatment regimen or currently not requiring
                  medication may be included).

               8. Any malignancy or its treatment that in the opinion of the PI may cause ongoing
                  interference with host immunity; subjects under evaluation for malignancy are
                  not eligible.

               9. Significant drug allergy (such as anaphylaxis or hepatotoxicity).

              10. Chronic liver disease of a non-HCV etiology (e.g., hemochromatosis, Wilson   s
                  disease, alfa-1 antitrypsin deficiency, cholangitis).

              11. Patients with renal impairment or uncontrolled medical problems that could place
                  them at high risk for developing renal impairment.

          2. Positive test at screening for either HBsAg or quantifiable HBV DNA (completed only
             if necessary to rule out chronic HBV)

          3. Current use of non-protocol approved ARVs.

          4. A new AIDS-defining condition diagnosed within 30 days prior to screening or active,
             serious infection (other than HIV or HCV) requiring parenteral antibiotics,
             antivirals or antifungals within 30 days prior to Day 0.

          5. Cirrhosis of the liver

          6. Screening or baseline ECG with clinically significant ECG findings.

          7. Abnormal hematological and biochemical parameters, including:

               1. Neutrophil count &lt; 750 cells/mm(3)

               2. Hemoglobin &lt;  9 g/dL. If Hgb is &lt;  11g/dL in women or &lt;  12 g/dL in men. Other
                  causes of anemia should be excluded as medically indicated.

               3. Platelet count less than or equal to 50,000 cells/mm(3)

               4. Estimated GFR (calculated by the CKD-EP(I) equation) &lt; 50 mL/min/per 1.73 m(2)
                  if not on ARV or &lt; 60 mL/min if on ARVs

               5. ALT or AST greater than or equal to 10 times ULN

               6. Serum lipase greater than or equal to 1.5 times ULN (at screening or during the
                  screening period)

               7. Direct bilirubin greater than or equal to 1.50 times ULN

               8. Albumin less than or equal to 3.0 g/dL

               9. INR greater than or equal to 1.5 times ULN unless subject has known hemophilia
                  or is stable on an anticoagulant regimen affecting INR.

          8. Donation or loss of more than 400 mL blood within 8 weeks prior to first dose
             administration.

          9. Poorly controlled diabetes mellitus indicated by hemoglobin A1C &gt;  10% at screening
             for known diabetics.

         10. Known hypersensitivity to, GS-5885, GS-7977, or formulation excipients.

         11. Pregnant/Breastfeeding women.

         12. Co-enrollment in other clinical trials is restricted, and requires approval of the
             Investigator.

             Study staff should be notified of co-enrollment status.

         13. Need for use of the following medications from 21 days prior to the start of study
             drugs through the end of treatment:

               1. Hematologic stimulating agents (e.g. erythropoiesis-stimulating agents (ESAs);
                  granulocyte colony stimulating factor (GCSF); thrombopoietin (TPO) mimetics)

               2. Chronic systemic immunosuppressants including, but not limited to,
                  corticosteroids (prednisone equivalent of &gt;  10 mg/day for &gt;  2 weeks),
                  azathioprine, or monoclonal antibodies (e.g., infliximab)

               3. Investigational agents or devices for any indication

               4. Medications for disease conditions excluded from the protocol (e.g., active
                  cancer, transplantation) are not listed under this Concomitant Medication
                  section and are disallowed in the study.

               5. Concomitant use of certain medications or herbal/natural supplements per PI
                  discretion expected to result in pharmacokinetic interactions resulting in
                  increases or decreases in exposure of study drug(s) as listed in Table of this
                  protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shyamasundaran Kottilil, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?B_2013-I-0159.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alter MJ, Kruszon-Moran D, Nainan OV, McQuillan GM, Gao F, Moyer LA, Kaslow RA, Margolis HS. The prevalence of hepatitis C virus infection in the United States, 1988 through 1994. N Engl J Med. 1999 Aug 19;341(8):556-62.</citation>
    <PMID>10451460</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Armstrong GL, Wasley A, Simard EP, McQuillan GM, Kuhnert WL, Alter MJ. The prevalence of hepatitis C virus infection in the United States, 1999 through 2002. Ann Intern Med. 2006 May 16;144(10):705-14. Summary for patients in: Ann Intern Med. 2006 May 16;144(10):I20.</citation>
    <PMID>16702586</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim WR. The burden of hepatitis C in the United States. Hepatology. 2002 Nov;36(5 Suppl 1):S30-4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12407574</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 15, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 14, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Direct Acting Antiviral</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment Naive</keyword>
  <keyword>Interferon Sparing</keyword>
  <keyword>Ribavarin Sparing</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
