<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="134614">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02071979</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ART-13-006</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CAG-00190R3</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02071979</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Registry Trial of the Effectiveness of Platelet Rich Plasma for Chronic Non-Healing Wounds</brief_title>
  <acronym>CMS</acronym>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of Autologous Platelet Rich Plasma in the Treatment of Chronic Skin Wounds</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Arteriocyte, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Arteriocyte, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine differences in the process of wound-healing in patients treated with
      a gel made from platelet rich plasma (a concentration of proteins derived from a patients
      own blood) compared to patients treated with usual medical treatment . This study seeks to
      enroll patients who are 18 or older with a non-healing skin wound that is at least 30 days
      old.  Only patients with Diabetic Foot Ulcers, Venous Ulcers, or Pressure Ulcers will be
      included in the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The proposed investigation is designed to solicit a large number of patients (N=1,500) with
      non-healing wounds (Diabetic Foot Ulcers, Venous Ulcers, or Pressure Ulcers) that have not
      responded to standard wound care in the previous 30 days or more. A prospective,
      observational, registry trial will be used. Data will be analyzed to compare patients who
      received PRP therapy and standard wound care (usual customary care) with patients who
      received standard wound care (usual customary care), only. Wound size, rate of healing,
      quality of life, and recurrence of wound will be measured during the 20-week period at usual
      office visits and at one-year post-enrollment, respectively.

      Hypotheses to be tested:

        -  Treatment of a chronic wound with standard wound care and autologous platelet rich
           plasma (PRP) will result in a reduction in wound size over a twenty-week period as
           compared to patients receiving standard wound care only (Case-matched cohort).

        -  Treatment of a chronic wound with standard medical care and autologous platelet rich
           plasma (PRP) will increase the velocity of healing (rate of wound closure) over a
           twenty-week period as compared to patients receiving standard wound care only
           (Case-matched cohort).

        -  Treatment of a chronic wound with standard medical care and autologous platelet rich
           plasma (PRP) will result in complete wound healing within twenty weeks, whereas
           complete wound healing will not be observed within twenty weeks in patients receiving
           standard wound care only (Case-matched cohort).

        -  Treatment of a chronic wound with standard medical care and autologous platelet rich
           plasma (PRP) will improve quality of life scores as compared to patients receiving
           standard wound care only (Case-matched cohort).  The Center for Disease Control (CDC)
           Health Related Quality of Life (HRQoL)-14 &quot;Healthy Days Measure&quot; will be administered
           to test this hypothesis.

        -  Treatment of a chronic wound with standard wound care and autologous platelet rich
           plasma (PRP) will reduce incidence of wound recurrence as compared to patients
           receiving standard wound care only (Case-matched cohort).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <target_duration>1 Year</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Wound Size</measure>
    <time_frame>20 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Wound size will be measured with ruler/probe for length, width and depth as well as with digital imaging. Wound size will be assessed in digital images taken of the wound.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of wound closure (change in wound size over time)</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The ratio of wound percent change over time will be used</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete wound healing</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Complete wound healing is determined when the wound shows no sign of drainage for two consecutive visits (over two weeks)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Related Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Center for Disease Control (CDC) Health Related Quality of Life (HRQoL)-14, &quot;Healthy Days Measure&quot; will be administered</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Wound recurrence</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Incidence of wound recurrence over the course of a year</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1500</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetic Foot Ulcers</condition>
  <condition>Venous Ulcers</condition>
  <condition>Pressure Ulcers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Autologous PRP Gel</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients whose physicians choose to treat their chronic wound with Autologous PRP Gel will receive standard of care plus autologous PRP gel applied to their wound according to treatment strategy: Baseline/Week 0, Week 1, Week 2, Week 3, Week 7, and Week 11. The Arteriocyte Magellan® System (510(k) cleared) will be used to prepare the autologous PRP gel. For data analysis, the data from these patients will be classified as PRP Treatment Group data.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Wound Care</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients whose physicians choose to treat their chronic wound according to accepted medical practice will receive standard wound care, only. For data analysis, the data from these patients will be classified as Standard Wound Care Group data.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Autologous PRP Gel</intervention_name>
    <description>Autologous PRP Gel is prepared using the Arteriocyte Magellan® System (510(k) approved), an Autologous Platelet Separator Instrument, which is a microprocessor-controlled centrifuge designed to be used in the clinical laboratory or intraoperatively at point of care for the safe and rapid preparation of platelet poor plasma and platelet concentrate (platelet rich plasma) from a small sample of blood.  The Arteriocyte Magellan® automatically and quickly separates PRP from anticoagulated blood and dispenses it into a separate sterile syringe.  The prepared PRP is then activated (by mixing with thrombin and calcium chloride) and sprayed directly on the area to be treated.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Autologous PRP Gel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Wound Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Participation will be offered to 1,500 male and female patients (N=1,500) over the age of
        18 presenting with a non-healing skin wound that has persisted for at least 30 days. Only
        patients with Diabetic Foot Ulcers (DFU), Venous Ulcers (VU), or Pressure Ulcers (PU) will
        be included in the study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Medicare Eligible

          -  Written informed consent obtained from either the patient or the patient's legally
             acceptable representative prior to screening activities

          -  Male or female ≥ 18 years of age

          -  Duration of Diabetic Foot Ulcers (DFU),Venous Ulcers (VU), or Pressure Ulcers (PU) is
             greater than 30 days at first visit/patient screening

          -  Classified as Wagner 1 -2 on the Wagner classification system

          -  If more than one non-healing wound is present, the largest of the wounds that is
             classified as a Wagner 1 - 2.

          -  If a patient has multiple eligible wounds, the largest wound will be selected. There
             must be at least 4 cm between the index wound and other wounds; if all wounds are
             closer than 4 cm, the patient should not be enrolled (screen failure).

          -  The ulcer must be clinically non-infected (culture assessment during patient
             eligibility screening)

          -  Able and willing to comply with the procedures required by the protocol. Patients may
             be managed as either inpatient or outpatient.

          -  If a female of childbearing potential, the patient must have a negative serum
             pregnancy test at screening.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with known sensitivity to components of the Arteriocyte PRP kit (calcium
             chloride, thrombin, acid citrate dextrose solution A (ACDA)).

          -  Current treatment of another chronic wound in the same limb.

          -  Wound is not of DFU, Pressure ulcer or venostasis ulcer pathophysiology.

          -  Presence of osteomyelitis, or if osteomyelitis is suspected.

          -  Received systemic corticosteroids or immunosuppressive agents, hyperbaric oxygen
             therapy (HBOT), electrostimulation, growth factors, or any cell or tissue-derived
             products for wounds during the 30 days preceding the screening visit.

          -  Received radiation therapy or chemotherapy within previous 6 months.

          -  Any malignancy other than non-melanoma skin cancer.

          -  Patient has radiographic evidence consistent with diagnosis of neuropathic
             osteoarthropathy (Charcot foot).

          -  Patients who are cognitively impaired and do not have a healthcare proxy.

          -  Serum albumin of less than 2.5 g/dL.

          -  Patient has inadequate venous access for repeated blood draw required for PRP
             preparation.

          -  Patient has sickle cell anemia.

          -  Patient is pregnant or plans to become pregnant during the duration of the trial.

          -  Any chronic condition requiring the use of systemic corticosteroids 30 days prior to
             study entry and anytime during the course of the study.

          -  Concurrent participation in a clinical trial in which an investigational agent is
             used.

          -  Females who are pregnant or nursing or intend to become pregnant during the duration
             of the study.

          -  Patients with Thrombocytopenia &lt; 100,000 platelets/µL.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maria L. Urso, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Arteriocyte Medical Systems, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Maria L. Urso, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>508-435-7422</phone>
    <email>murso@arteriocyte.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sunnyside Foot and Ankle</name>
      <address>
        <city>Idaho Falls</city>
        <state>Idaho</state>
        <zip>83404</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cameron Bryan</last_name>
      <phone>208-529-2230</phone>
      <email>eips@cableone.net</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tony Quentin, DPM</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lea Medical</name>
      <address>
        <city>Silver Spring</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20910</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dallas Lea, DPM</last_name>
      <phone>301-495-3742</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dallas Lea, DPM</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Total Foot Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rashelle Johnson</last_name>
      <phone>216-529-1800</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jerome Lamendola, DPM</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Heritage Valley Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beaver</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15009</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thomas Michael, MD</last_name>
      <phone>724-770-7998</phone>
      <email>tmichael@hvhs.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Thomas Michael, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mustoe TA, O'Shaughnessy K, Kloeters O. Chronic wound pathogenesis and current treatment strategies: a unifying hypothesis. Plast Reconstr Surg. 2006 Jun;117(7 Suppl):35S-41S. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16799373</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martinez-Zapata MJ, Martí-Carvajal AJ, Solà I, Expósito JA, Bolíbar I, Rodríguez L, Garcia J. Autologous platelet-rich plasma for treating chronic wounds. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2012 Oct 17;10:CD006899. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD006899.pub2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23076929</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lacci KM, Dardik A. Platelet-rich plasma: support for its use in wound healing. Yale J Biol Med. 2010 Mar;83(1):1-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20351977</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Crovetti G, Martinelli G, Issi M, Barone M, Guizzardi M, Campanati B, Moroni M, Carabelli A. Platelet gel for healing cutaneous chronic wounds. Transfus Apher Sci. 2004 Apr;30(2):145-51.</citation>
    <PMID>15062754</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mazzucco L, Medici D, Serra M, Panizza R, Rivara G, Orecchia S, Libener R, Cattana E, Levis A, Betta PG, Borzini P. The use of autologous platelet gel to treat difficult-to-heal wounds: a pilot study. Transfusion. 2004 Jul;44(7):1013-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15225241</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shan GQ, Zhang YN, Ma J, Li YH, Zuo DM, Qiu JL, Cheng B, Chen ZL. Evaluation of the effects of homologous platelet gel on healing lower extremity wounds in patients with diabetes. Int J Low Extrem Wounds. 2013 Mar;12(1):22-9. doi: 10.1177/1534734613477113.</citation>
    <PMID>23509083</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yang HS, Shin J, Bhang SH, Shin JY, Park J, Im GI, Kim CS, Kim BS. Enhanced skin wound healing by a sustained release of growth factors contained in platelet-rich plasma. Exp Mol Med. 2011 Nov 30;43(11):622-9. doi: 10.3858/emm.2011.43.11.070.</citation>
    <PMID>21847007</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Driver VR, Hanft J, Fylling CP, Beriou JM; Autologel Diabetic Foot Ulcer Study Group. A prospective, randomized, controlled trial of autologous platelet-rich plasma gel for the treatment of diabetic foot ulcers. Ostomy Wound Manage. 2006 Jun;52(6):68-70, 72, 74 passim.</citation>
    <PMID>16799184</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 23, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 20, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chronic</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-healing</keyword>
  <keyword>Wounds</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Pressure Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Varicose Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Foot Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Foot</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
