<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="38342">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01702922</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>120206</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>12-C-0206</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01702922</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Relationship Stressors in Parents of Children With Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Understanding the Perceived Influence of Childhood Cancer on the Parents' Marital/Partner Relationship: A Descriptive Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Serious illnesses like cancer can cause high levels of stress in a family. When a child is
      diagnosed with cancer, parents face numerous stressors, each of which can strain
      relationships. Many parents struggle to effectively cope with the changes in parenting roles
      that often accompany treatment of childhood cancer. How parents cope with this stress can
      influence whether the relationship is strengthened or weakened. Stress levels can also
      affect the care of the child who has cancer. Researchers want to better understand the
      critical time points and events during the child   s treatment when the relationship becomes
      most stressed and/or strengthened.

      Objectives:

      - To study how stress affects the relationship between parents who have a child with cancer.

      Eligibility:

        -  Parents of a child (between 1 and 24 years of age) who has been diagnosed with cancer.

        -  Participants must have been in a partnership at the time the child was diagnosed with
           cancer. At least one of the parents must be a biological or legal parent of the child.

      Design:

        -  Participants will fill out a questionnaire either online or by paper and pencil. It
           will take about 20 minutes to complete. The questions ask about the experience of
           dealing with a child   s cancer diagnosis and how it affects participants
           relationship with their spouse/partner.

        -  Some participants will also have an in-depth interview. It will last about an hour. It
           will ask further questions about the cancer diagnosis and treatment and its effect on
           the relationship.

        -  Treatment will not be provided as part of this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

        -  Parents face numerous stressors when their child is diagnosed with cancer, each of
           which can strain a marriage/partnership.

        -  Marital/partner relationship dynamics are often not assessed or addressed when
           providing health care for children with cancer. Many parents struggle to effectively
           cope with the changes in parenting roles that frequently accompany treatment of
           childhood cancer.

        -  How parents cope with these stressors can strengthen or weaken the relationship, and
           can impact the entire family, including the care to the child undergoing cancer
           treatments.

        -  Limited studies have examined relationship stress or satisfaction during a child   s
           treatment for cancer or the critical time points and events during the child   s
           treatment when the relationship becomes most stressed and/or strengthened.

      OBJECTIVES:

        -  To explore whether the stress associated with having a child with cancer is perceived
           to impact the communication between partners.

        -  To explore whether positive dyadic coping (joint decision making, joint problem
           solving, sharing responsibilities) is perceived to have strengthened the marital
           relationship/partnership following the child   s diagnosis with cancer.

        -  To describe the time points and events during the child   s treatment when the parents
             relationship becomes most stressed and/or strengthened.

        -  To compare the perceptions of various subgroups in the sample, (e.g. parents who score
           either high or low on a marital stress scale, mothers versus fathers) statistically or
           qualitatively as the distribution of the characteristics of the sample allow.

      ELIGIBILITY:

        -  Participants must have been in a partnership at the time the child was diagnosed with
           cancer. At least one of the participating parents must be a biological or legal parent
           of the child. If a divorce/separation occurred with a previous partner during/after the
           child   s cancer treatment, the other partner will be invited to participate.

        -  The participant   s child must be between 1-24 years of age.

        -  There are 2 groups of participants being recruited: 1) those who have a child who has
           been diagnosed with cancer at least 3 months prior to enrolling on this study and are
           currently undergoing cancer treatment and 2) those who have completed treatment at age
           21 or younger (without evidence of disease) within the previous 3 years.

        -  Participants must be fluent in the English language.

        -  The participant   s child must have been diagnosed with cancer at least 3 months prior
           to enrollment on this study.

        -  Participants must verbalize willingness to discuss the impact of their child   s cancer
           diagnosis on their relationship.

      DESIGN:

        -  Cross-sectional, multi-center, exploratory study utilizing a convenience sample to
           explore the parents    perception of how the child   s cancer diagnosis, treatment,
           decision-making and other aspects of care are addressed and impact the martial
           relationship/partnership.

        -  Subjects will complete a self-administered measure that addresses potential stresses
           experienced in the partnership since the child   s diagnosis and how each are either
           resolved or create a divide in the relationship.

        -  Subjects who experience a    high    or    low    degree of relationship stress on a
           standardized marital stress form (a score greater than one standard deviation from the
           norm) will be invited to participate in a qualitative interview, that further explores
           which components of parenting a child with cancer is most challenging on the
           relationship.

        -  Up to 240 participants will be enrolled onto the study (up to 120 couples), and we aim
           for qualitative interviews with approximately 26% of the sample.  Subjects will be
           offered a gift card ($20 Target gift card at NIH) upon completion of the questionnaire
           for their time and inconvenience, where available.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>N/A</study_design>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">240</enrollment>
  <condition>Parents of Children With Cancer</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Participants must have been in a partnership at the time the child was diagnosed with
             cancer. At least one participant must be the biological/legal parent of the child;
             the partner may or may not be a biological/legal parent. Divorced parents who
             separated or divorced during or after the child   s treatment can participate in this
             study.

          -  The participant   s child must be between 1-24 years of age.

          -  Participants must be 18 years of age or older.

          -  Participants must be fluent in the English language.

          -  The participant   s child must have been diagnosed with cancer at least 3 months
             prior to enrollment on this study and be currently receiving treatment or have
             completed treatment at age 21 or younger (without evidence of disease) within the
             previous 3 years..

          -  Participants must verbalize willingness to discuss the impact of their child   s
             cancer diagnosis on their relationship.

          -  Able to understand and willing to sign the informed consent document.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Parents of a child with cancer without a partner/spouse during the child   s
             treatment for cancer are excluded from this study.

          -  Parents who were not living with the child during his or her treatment and involved
             in the child   s care.

          -  Parents of children who are enrolled in hospice care.

          -  Presence of psychotic symptoms or severe psychological distress, which in the
             judgment of the Principal or Associate Investigator would compromise the participants
                ability to engage in the study procedures or results.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lori Wiener, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Candace M Anderson</last_name>
    <phone>Not Listed</phone>
    <email>menkecs@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Lori Wiener, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-9148</phone>
    <email>wienerl@pbmac.nci.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact National Cancer Institute Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>888-624-1937</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alberta's Children's Hospital Hematology/Oncology/Transplant Program</name>
      <address>
        <city>Alberta</city>
        <zip>T2L 2A6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2012-C-0206.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lannen PK, Wolfe J, Prigerson HG, Onelov E, Kreicbergs UC. Unresolved grief in a national sample of bereaved parents: impaired mental and physical health 4 to 9 years later. J Clin Oncol. 2008 Dec 20;26(36):5870-6. Epub 2008 Nov 24.</citation>
    <PMID>19029425</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Assari S, Moghani Lankarani M, Tavallaii SA. Revised dyadic adjustment scale as a reliable tool for assessment of quality of marital relationship in patients on long-term hemodialysis. Iran J Kidney Dis. 2009 Oct;3(4):242-5. Erratum in: Iran J Kidney Dis. 2010 Jan;4(1):88.</citation>
    <PMID>19841530</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coyne JC, Smith DA. Couples coping with a myocardial infarction: a contextual perspective on wives' distress. J Pers Soc Psychol. 1991 Sep;61(3):404-12.</citation>
    <PMID>1941511</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 6, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <keyword>Stress</keyword>
  <keyword>Marriage</keyword>
  <keyword>Dyadic Coping</keyword>
  <keyword>Mother</keyword>
  <keyword>Father</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
