<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="107512">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01816763</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CRE 12-030</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01816763</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effective Screening for Pain Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>ESP</acronym>
  <official_title>Effective Screening for Pain Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The ESP Study will evaluate the role of a novel pain measure and computer-based platform to
      screen for pain routinely in primary care settings at the VA Greater Los Angeles, Portland,
      and Minneapolis VAMCs. ESP will consider not only the effectiveness of the novel pain
      measures vs. usual care and the role of patient-reported versus clinician-documented pain
      but also evaluate how pain screening can be more effectively linked to pain management and
      consider how a technology platform can be implemented effectively in VA general practice
      settings.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The &quot;Pain as the Fifth Vital Sign&quot; Initiative is a prominent feature of the VA's pain
      strategy. It focuses on current pain intensity by querying patients about &quot;pain right now.&quot;
      In acute care settings (i.e, post-operative), assessment of current pain intensity allows
      clinicians to provide appropriate and timely analgesia and adjust treatment to achieve
      effective near-term pain control. In contrast, assessment of current pain intensity may have
      less relevance in primary care and other outpatient settings where many patients with pain
      have ongoing pain conditions and where functional impact may have greater clinical
      significance.

      Pain problems in primary care are diverse, but the chronic conditions, back and
      osteoarthritis pain, are responsible for most of the burden of pain in primary care and
      require a long-term management approach. Structured repeated assessment is needed to
      evaluate the effectiveness of chronic pain management strategies, the benefits of which may
      accrue over months or years. Discrepancy between the information provided by the current
      pain screening approach and type of pain assessment information needed in primary care may
      be an important reason for the limited benefits of pain screening in primary care to date.

      We previously found that pain screening often misses clinically important chronic pain in
      primary care. Several measures perform better than the 0-10 Numeric Rating Scale, or 'NRS
      now.' We have validated the three item PEG, derived from the Brief Pain Inventory, as an
      alternative to the 'NRS now'. A major advantage of the PEG is inclusion of emotional and
      physical function, as well as pain intensity. Furthermore, adherence to screening process is
      low, with informal approaches (e.g., &quot;are you hurting?&quot;) being used in 50% of encounters
      instead of elicitation of a numeric value. Finally, pain screening does not address
      dimensions of pain, such as emotional or physical interference, which clinicians often find
      relevant. These problems illuminate why clinicians don't act on pain, even when it's of
      moderate-severe intensity.

      Although screening may be improved by a more sensitive measure that includes functional
      aspects (e.g., the PEG), improving clinician adherence to screening processes is likely to
      be difficult. Direct patient reports of symptoms offer an alternative screening approach
      with momentum outside of VA due to the Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information
      System (PROMIS) effort; underscoring the need to compare PRO vs. clinician assessment
      directly. An empiric study can also consider clinicians' views of how to link a new
      screening approach to management and formatively evaluate other implementation challenges
      (e.g., kiosk throughput. Results can prospectively inform improvement to the VA's '5th vital
      sign'. The ESP Project will test a new, better measure of pain using a computer kiosk,
      evaluate that measure versus what is in use now (e.g. 5th Vital Sign) and consider the
      barrier to implementing and using the new measure widely.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Arm 1 (NRS now), to arm 2 (PEG), to arm 3 (usual care) pairwise difference scores in baseline and pain disability detection at one week, and satisfaction with pain management at one week</measure>
    <time_frame>one week after the encounter</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>pain (NRS and PEG measures)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Arm 1 (NRS now), to arm 2 (PEG), to arm 3 (usual care) pairwise differences in pain missingness and rating variability</measure>
    <time_frame>after 3 months of the recorded visits</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Arm 1 (NRS now), to arm 2 (PEG), to arm 3 (usual care) pairwise difference scores in baseline and pain disability detection at one week, and satisfaction with pain management at one week</measure>
    <time_frame>one week after the encounter</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>pain related disability (Roland Disability measure)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Arm 1 (NRS now), to arm 2 (PEG), to arm 3 (usual care) pairwise difference scores in baseline and pain disability detection at one week,</measure>
    <time_frame>one week after the encounter</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>pain satisfaction (CAHPS related patient experience of pain management)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Arm 1 (NRS now), to arm 2 (PEG), to arm 3 (usual care) pairwise differences in pain missingness and rating variability</measure>
    <time_frame>after 3 months of the recorded visits</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Siegel Tukey test coefficient of concordance to disability</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">4000</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <condition>Pain Management</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Kiosk based NRS pain now, followed by nurse pain screen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>kiosk-based patient self-report of the 'NRS pain now'</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Kiosk based PEG, followed by nurse pain screen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>kiosk-based enhanced pain screening with the PEG (pain intensity, emotional, and functional pain interference)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Kiosk based health reminder, followed by nurse pain screen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Unrelated health reminder on kiosk followed by usual nursing staff documented pain screening with NRS pain now</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NRS pain now</intervention_name>
    <description>Eligible patients will be randomly assigned to complete a patient-reported 'NRS now' on a kiosk prior to making contact with a nursing staff vital signs screener.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Kiosk based NRS pain now, followed by nurse pain screen</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PEG</intervention_name>
    <description>Eligible patients will be assigned to complete a patient-reported enhanced pain screening with the PEG on a kiosk prior to making contact with a nursing staff vital signs screener.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Kiosk based PEG, followed by nurse pain screen</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All Veterans are eligible to participate in the clinical trial when presenting for
             routine care in the primary care clinic at all sites (VA at Greater Los Angeles,
             Minneapolis, and Portland).

          -  All are eligible who do not opt out of participation.

          -  All participants in the baseline kiosk intervention will also be eligible for a one
             week follow up telephone interview - unless they are unable to complete a phone
             interview (see exclusions).

          -  For the qualitative Veteran component, all Veterans who can hear and respond in an
             interview are eligible.

          -  All primary care providers and staff in any of the three sites (GLA, Minneapolis,
             Portland) will be eligible to participate in provider interviews/focus groups.

          -  Providers/staff must be clinic and facility staff including administrative clerks,
             regular part time or full time employees in primary care who routinely participate in
             the care of Veterans who have painful conditions.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Veterans who meet either of the following exclusion criteria that may interfere with
             outcome assessment will be ineligible for the follow up telephone evaluation:

               -  a) no working telephone (home, office, or mobile)

               -  b) moderately severe cognitive impairment, defined as greater than or equal to 3
                  errors on a brief cognitive screener

               -  c) hearing impaired and unable to complete a phone survey
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karl A. Lorenz, MD MSHS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Greater Los Angeles Health Care System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karl A Lorenz, MD MSHS</last_name>
    <phone>(310) 478-3711</phone>
    <phone_ext>43523</phone_ext>
    <email>Karl.Lorenz@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Hannah Schreibeis-Baum, MPH</last_name>
    <email>hannah.schreibeis-baum@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Greater Los Angeles Health Care System</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90073</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karl A Lorenz, MD MSHS</last_name>
      <phone>310-478-3711</phone>
      <phone_ext>43523</phone_ext>
      <email>Karl.Lorenz@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Hannah Schreibeis-Baum, MPH</last_name>
      <email>hannah.schreibeis-baum@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karl A. Lorenz, MD MSHS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Richard L. Roudebush VA Medical Center, Indianapolis, IN</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202-2884</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alissa Russ, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>317-988-3132</phone>
      <email>alissa.russ@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Minneapolis VA Health Care System, Minneapolis, MN</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55417</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Erin Krebs, MD</last_name>
      <phone>612-725-2000</phone>
      <email>erin.krebs@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Portland VA Medical Center, Portland, OR</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven K Dobscha, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>503-220-8262</phone>
      <email>steven.dobscha@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 11, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Health Care Quality, Access, and Evaluation</keyword>
  <keyword>Primary Health Care</keyword>
  <keyword>Medical Informatics</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
