<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="38622">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02066922</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C-12-057</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02066922</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Comparative Study of Two Daily Disposable Contact Lenses in Higher Myopia Subjects</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Alcon Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Alcon Research</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Ethics Commission</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare the central corneal curvature in highly myopic
      participants wearing two different silicone hydrogel contact lenses, one in each eye, for
      one week.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Participants will be expected to attend 4 office visits. Visit 1 is the Screening/Enrollment
      visit. Between Visit 1 and Visit 2 (Baseline visit), participants will be allowed to wear
      their habitual contact lenses, except for the last two days prior to Visit 2. At Visit 2,
      participants will be randomized and the study lenses will be trial fit. Spectacle lenses
      will be ordered (if necessary) to ensure acceptable visual acuity during study lens wear.
      Between Visit 2 and Visit 3 (Dispensing visit) participants may wear their habitual contact
      lenses, except for the last two days prior to the Visit 3. At Visit 3, participants will
      receive study lenses and the spectacles, if needed, for 1 week of wear. Visit 4 (Follow
      up/Exit visit) will occur 1 week later. The expected duration of participation in the study
      is about 3 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in average central corneal curvature from Dispense at Week 1</measure>
    <time_frame>Dispense (Day 1), Week 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Corneal curvature is defined as the average between horizontal and vertical keratometry values on the same eye.  Corneal curvature will be measured prior to study lens dispense (Day 1) and approximately 15 minutes after study lens removal following 8 hours of wear (Week 1). Spectacle over-refraction, if required, will be performed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of eyes with change of &gt;1.00 diopter (D) in spherical equivalent of subjective refraction from Baseline at Week 1</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subjective manifest refraction will be assessed after a 2-day washout period (Baseline) and approximately 15 minutes after study lens removal following 8 hours of wear (Week 1).  Spectacle over-refraction, if required, will be performed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">19</enrollment>
  <condition>Refractive Error</condition>
  <condition>Myopia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DAILIES® TOTAL1®</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Delefilcon A contact lens randomly assigned to one eye, with narafilcon A contact lens in the fellow eye for contralateral wear. Both products worn in a daily wear, daily disposable mode approximately 8 hours a day for 1 week. Spectacles worn over contact lenses as needed to provide acceptable vision.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1-DAY ACUVUE TRUEYE™</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Narafilcon A contact lens randomly assigned to one eye, with delefilcon A contact lens in the fellow eye for contralateral wear. Both products worn in a daily wear, daily disposable mode approximately 8 hours a day for 1 week. Spectacles worn over contact lenses as needed to provide acceptable vision.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Delefilcon A contact lens</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>DAILIES® TOTAL1®</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>DAILIES® TOTAL1®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Narafilcon A contact lens</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>1-DAY ACUVUE TRUEYE™</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>1-DAY ACUVUE TRUEYE™</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Spectacles</intervention_name>
    <description>Incremental prescription worn over contact lenses to provide acceptable vision, if needed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>DAILIES® TOTAL1®</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>1-DAY ACUVUE TRUEYE™</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Sign Informed Consent document;

          -  Higher degree of myopia in both eyes, i.e. habitual contact lens power between -10.00
             diopters (D) and -17.00D;

          -  Best corrected distance visual acuity greater than or equal to 20/30 in each eye
             (measured with either spectacle refraction or habitual contact lenses plus over
             refraction);

          -  Manifest astigmatism less than or equal to -1.00D;

          -  Soft contact lens wear in both eyes at least 5 days per week and at least 8 hours per
             day;

          -  Other protocol-defined inclusion criteria may apply.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant or lactating;

          -  Eye injury or surgery within twelve weeks immediately prior to enrollment;

          -  Any ocular condition that contraindicates contact lens wear;

          -  History of herpetic keratitis;

          -  Any use of systemic or ocular medications for which contact lens wear could be
             contraindicated, including any use of topical ocular medications that would require
             instillation during contact lens wear, except for approved lubricating drops;

          -  Clinical significant dry eye not responding to treatment;

          -  Previous corneal or refractive surgery or irregular cornea;

          -  Requires reading glasses;

          -  Participation in a clinical trial (including contact lens or contact lens care
             product) within the previous 30 days;

          -  Wears habitual lenses in an extended wear modality (routinely sleeps in lenses
             overnight for 1 night per week or more) over the last 3 months prior to enrollment;

          -  Other protocol-defined exclusion criteria may apply.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joachim Nick, Dipl. Ing.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Alcon Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Contact Alcon Call Center for Trial Locations</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Worth</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>76134</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 27, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 8, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Contact lenses</keyword>
  <keyword>Nearsightedness</keyword>
  <keyword>Corneal curvature</keyword>
  <keyword>K-reading</keyword>
  <keyword>High minus</keyword>
  <keyword>Spectacle refraction</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Myopia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Refractive Errors</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
