<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="68885">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01980940</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0663-168</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01980940</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Single Dose Pharmacokinetics of Two and Proof of Efficacy of One New Etoricoxib Gel Formulation in Participants With Osteoarthritis (MK-0663-168)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study to Assess the Single Dose Pharmacokinetics of Two and Proof of Efficacy of One New Etoricoxib Gel Formulation in Osteoarthritis Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Study Part 1 is designed to assess the plasma pharmacokinetics of two different etoricoxib
      (4%) gel formulations, each at 2 different doses, upon single-dose topical administration on
      the knee of osteoarthritis participants. Study Part 2 is designed to evaluate the efficacy
      of topical etoricoxib vs. placebo in the treatment of osteoarthritis of the knee. The
      primary hypothesis is that at least one of the two gel formulations will be safe and
      tolerable.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Part I of the study will consist of a single-dose, open-label, randomized, four-way cross
      over study with topical administration of etoricoxib gel on the knee of osteoarthritis
      participants. The washout between successive dose administrations will be at least one week.
      Part 2 of the study will consist of double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled, parallel
      groups, multiple dose, twice daily topical administration of etoricoxib or placebo gel on
      the knee of osteoarthritis participants for a period of two weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Concentration-Time Curve from 0 to Last (AUC 0-last) of MK-0663 in Study Part 1</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 72 Hours Post-Application</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Plasma Concentration (Cmax) of MK-0663 in Study Part 1</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 72 Hours Post-Application</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Mean Participant Score on the Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Arthritis Index (WOMAC) Visiual Analog 3.0 Pain Scale in Study Part 2</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Day 14</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">68</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Sequence 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single-dose etoricoxib 75 mg (1.97 mL) 4% DMSO gel applied topically, followed by single-dose etoricoxib 75 mg (2.15 mL) 4% PG gel applied topically, followed by single-dose etoricoxib 150 mg (3.94 mL) 4% DMSO gel applied topically, followed by single-dose etoricoxib 150 mg (4.30 mL) 4% PG gel applied topically.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Sequence 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single-dose etoricoxib 75 mg (2.15 mL) 4% PG gel applied topically, followed by single-dose 75 mg (1.97 mL) 4% DMSO gel applied topically, followed by single-dose etoricoxib 150 mg (3.94 mL) 4% DMSO gel applied topically, followed by single-dose etoricoxib 150 mg (4.30 mL) 4% PG gel applied topically.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Sequence 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single-dose of etoricoxib 150 mg (3.94 mL) 4% DMSO gel applied topically, followed by single-dose etoricoxib 75 mg (2.15 mL) 4% PG gel applied topically, followed by single-dose etoricoxib 150 mg (4.30 mL) 4% PG gel applied topically, followed by single-dose etoricoxib 75 mg (1.97 mL) 4% DMSO gel applied topically.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Sequence 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single-dose etoricoxib 150 mg (4.30 mL) 4% gel applied topically, followed by single-dose etoricoxib 150 mg (3.94 mL) 4% DMSO gel applied topically, followed by single-dose etoricoxib 75 mg (1.97 mL) 4% DMSO gel applied topically, followed by single-dose etoricoxib 75 mg (2.15 mL) 4% PG gel applied topically.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Etoricoxib 50 mg (1.31 mL, 4% DMSO gel)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Etoricoxib 50 mg (1.31 mL, 4% DMSO gel) applied twice daily to the affected knee for a period of 2 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Matching Placebo to Etoricoxib 50 mg (1.31 mL, 4% DMSO gel)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Matching placebo to etoricoxib 50 mg 1.31 mL 4% DMSO gel applied topically twice daily to the affected knee for a period of 2 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Etoricoxib 75 mg 4% DMSO Gel</intervention_name>
    <description>Etoricoxib 75 mg 4% DMSO gel applied topically.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Sequence 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Etoricoxib 75 mg 4% PG Gel</intervention_name>
    <description>Etoricoxib 75 4% PG gel applied topically.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Sequence 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Etoricoxib 150 mg 4% DMSO Gel</intervention_name>
    <description>Etoricoxib 150 mg 4% DMSO gel applied topically.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Sequence 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Etoricoxib 50 mg (1.31 mL, 4% DMSO gel)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Etoricoxib 150 mg 4% PG Gel</intervention_name>
    <description>Etoricoxib 150 mg 4% PG gel applied topically.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Sequence 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Etoricoxib 50 mg (1.31 mL, 4% DMSO gel)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Matching Placebo to Etoricoxib 50 mg 4% DMSO Gel</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching Placebo to Etoricoxib 50 mg 4% DMSO gel applied topically.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Matching Placebo to Etoricoxib 50 mg (1.31 mL, 4% DMSO gel)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Etoricoxib 50 mg (1.31 mL) 4% DMSO</intervention_name>
    <description>Etoricoxib 50 mg (1.31 mL) 4% DMSO gel applied topically.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Etoricoxib 50 mg (1.31 mL, 4% DMSO gel)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          -  Has diagnosis of osteoarthritis of the knee (tibio-femoral joint) for &gt;6 months based
             on clinical and radiographic criteria;

          -  Has a diagnosis of American Rheumatology Association (ARA) functional Class I, II, or
             III;

          -  The knee designated as the &quot;study joint&quot; must be the participant's primary source of
             pain/disability in the lower extremity. If both knees are affected, the most painful
             joint will be selected for evaluation for inclusion and clinical response;

          -  Female participants of childbearing potential must demonstrate a serum beta human
             chorionic gonadatropin (β-hCG) level consistent with a non-gravid state at the
             screening visit and urine β-hCG at Day -1 prior to first dosing and agree to use
             adequate oral or barrier contraception or abstain from sexual contact at least 7 days
             prior to treatment and continuing through the treatment period or a discontinuation
             visit;

          -  Willing to limit alcohol intake (beer 8 ounces, wine 4 ounces, liquor 1 ounce) to no
             more than 14 drinks a week (no more than 2 in a day) and to avoid unaccustomed
             strenuous physical activity (e.g., unaccustomed weight lifting, initiation of
             physical therapy) for the duration of the study;

          -  Judged to be in general good health with the exception of osteoarthritis based on
             medical history, physical examination, and routine laboratory tests.

          -  For Part 2, if the participant is a regular user of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory
             drugs (NSAIDs) including coxibs he/she must report a history of positive therapeutic
             benefit in osteoarthritis of the knee with NSAID/coxibs in the past;

          -  For Part 2, participants must be taking a single NSAID on a regular basis and at a
             prescription strength for at least 30 days prior to study screening (&quot;regular basis&quot;
             is defined as at least 25 of the previous 30 days) for treatment of symptoms of
             osteoarthritis.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has a concurrent medical/arthritic disease;

          -  History of acute ligamentous or meniscal injury of the study joint within the
             previous 2 years or arthroscopy of the affected knee within 6 months prior to study
             entry;

          -  Is a candidate for imminent joint replacement;

          -  Has clinical or laboratory evidence of significant renal, gastrointestinal,
             pulmonary, hepatic, endocrine, neurological (apart from migraine), or other systemic
             disease that in the opinion of the investigator contraindicates the use of
             etoricoxib;

          -  Has congestive heart failure with symptoms that occur at rest or minimal activity;

          -  Has unstable angina that occurs at rest or with minimal activity;

          -  Has uncontrolled hypertension (sitting diastolic blood pressure &gt;95 mm Hg, or sitting
             systolic blood pressure &gt;165 mm Hg);

          -  Has a history of stroke or transient ischemic attack (TIA) within the previous 6
             months;

          -  Has a history of hepatitis/hepatic disease that has been active within the previous 2
             years;

          -  Has a history of neoplastic disease;

          -  Is currently a user (including &quot;recreational use&quot;) of any illicit drugs, or has a
             history of drug or alcohol abuse within the past 5 years;

          -  Is allergic of has hypersensitivity to aspirin, ibuprofen, rofecoxib, celecoxib,
             valdecoxib, other NSAIDs, acetaminophen, or sulfa drugs;

          -  Has used intravenous, intramuscular, or oral corticosteroids within 1 month of study
             entry;

          -  Has used glucosamine and/or chondroitin sulfate for &lt;6 months prior to study start;

          -  Has used intra-articular steroids, HYALGAN™ (sodium hyaluronate, Sanofi
             Pharmaceuticals), or SYNVISC™ (hylan G-F 20, Wyeth-Ayerst Pharmaceuticals) to the
             study joint within 3 months of entry into the study or intra-articular steroids,
             HYALGAN™, or SYNVISC™ to any other joint within 1 month of study entry;

          -  Has used topical, oral or systemic analgesic medications within 2 weeks of study
             entry and for the duration of the study;

          -  Requires treatment with warfarin, heparin, high-dose aspirin (&gt;325 mg), or digoxin;

          -  Has used Arcoxia® within 2 weeks of study entry.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Toll-Free Number</last_name>
    <phone>888-577-8839</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme IDEA, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chisinau</city>
        <country>Moldova, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tatyana Gots</last_name>
      <phone>38 044 393-7480</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Moldova, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 23, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 5, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dimethyl Sulfoxide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoricoxib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
