<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="20123">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02042911</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012003</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02042911</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety Study of SyB L-0501 for Patients With Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multicenter, Open-label Phase II Study of SyB L-0501 in Patients With Chronic Lymphocytic Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>SymBio Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>SymBio Pharmaceuticals</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Japan: Pharmaceuticals and Medical Devices Agency</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate safety and efficacy of SyB L-0501 after 2-day
      intravenous infusion at a dose of 100 mg/m2/day to patients with chronic lymphocytic
      leukemia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate [complete remission (CR) +complete remission / incomplete (CRi) + nodular partial remission (nPR) + partial remission (PR)] based on International Workshop on Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (IWCLL) guideline</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The criteria for CR, CRi, nPR and PR based on IWCLL guideline are shown below. For the criteria for nPR and PR, please refer to the description of NCI-WG response rate (CR+nPR+PR).
CR: Assessment should be made at least 8 weeks after completion of administration.
Absence of significant lymphadenopathy (lymph nodes greater than 1.5 cm in diameter)
No hepatomegaly or splenomegaly
Absence of B symptoms
Meet the following laboratory test values;
lymphocyte count in peripheral blood: ＜4.0×10^9/L
neutrophil count: ＞1.5×10^9/L
platelet count: 100×10^9/L
hemoglobin: 11.0 g/dL without transfusions
less than 30% of nucleated cells are lymphocytes (confirmed by bone marrow aspiration and no lymphoid nodules).
No new lesion emergence
CRi: Fulfills all of the following criteria
Delayed anemia, thrombocytopenia, or neutropenia is observed.
Fulfills all CR criteria other than 4).
Delayed symptoms are all judged to be caused by drug.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>National Cancer Institute-sponsored Working Group (NCI-WG) response rate (CR+nPR+PR) based on IWCLL guideline</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The criteria for nPR and PR based on IWCLL guideline are shown below.
nPR: Fulfills all CR criteria other than residual lymphoid nodules confirmed by bone marrow examination.
PR: Fulfills two or more items from Group A and one or more items from Group B for a minimal duration of 8 weeks.
Group A;
50% or greater reduction in lymphocyte count in peripheral blood from baseline
50% or greater reduction (size reduction) in Sum of the products of the greatest diameters (SPD) and no new lesion emergence or no new enlarged lymph node
A decrease in the size of the liver and/or spleen by 50% more
A decrease in marrow infiltration or lymphoid nodules by 50% more Group B;
1) Neutrophil count ＞1.5×10^9/L or 50% improvement from baseline 2) Platelet count ＞100×10^9/L or 50% improvement from baseline 3) Hemoglobin 11.0 g/dL or 50% improvement from baseline without transfusions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete remission rate (CR+CRi) based on IWCLL guideline</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The period from the first day of the study drug administration (Day1) to progressive disease (PD), recurrence/relapse, or death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of remission</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The period from the day of CR or PR confirmation to recurrence/relapse.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The period from the date of patient registration to the date of death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 32 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>All undesirable medical events experienced by the subject treated with the investigational product (including abnormal changes in laboratory values) are treated as adverse events and evaluated for safety.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with clinically significant laboratory test values</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and up to 32 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Analysis of hematology, clinical chemistry, urinalysis, immunology, and flow cytometry will be performed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with clinically significant physical examination values</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 32 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Analysis of vital signs, body weight, body surface area, and ECOG performance status will be performed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SyB L-0501</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SyB L-0501</intervention_name>
    <description>SyB L-0501 is administered at 100 mg/m2/day by intravenous infusion on Day 1 and Day 2 followed by 26 days of monitoring. This is considered to be one cycle and may be repeated up to 6 cycles. Dose administration can be delayed or discontinued  from the second cycle as necessary according to adverse events and the results of monitoring during the previous cycle, but dose reduction is permitted from the 3rd cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SyB L-0501</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

        Patients meeting all of the following criteria are to be included in the study:

          1. Patients aged between 20 and 80 years (at the time of registration)

          2. Patients who have provided written consent in person for participation in this study

          3. Patients with Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status (PS) of 0
             to 2

          4. Patients who are expected to survive for at least 3 months

          5. Patients who are naive to or not suitable for fludarabine therapy

          6. Patients who are documented with chronic lymphocytic leukemia on the basis of IWCLL
             guideline:

               -  The presence of ≥ 5000/mm3 monoclonal mature B-lymphocytes in the peripheral
                  blood

               -  ≤ 55 % atypical lymphocytes, prolymphocyte-like cells, and lymphoblasts with
                  prominent nucleoli

               -  For monoclonal mature B-lymphocytes, at least one of the B-cell specific
                  differentiation antigens (Cluster of differentiation (CD) 19, CD 20, and CD 23)
                  and CD 5 is positive by flow cytometry

          7. Patients in Stage C or stage B with active disease based on Binet staging system (at
             the time of registration)

               -  Decision to start treatment should be made upon IWCLL guideline criteria.

               -  Active disease is defined to meet at least one of the following criteria.

                    1. Progression and/or worsening of anemia and/or thrombocytopenia caused by
                       decreased bone marrow function.

                    2. Massive (6 cm below the left costal margin) or progressive or symptomatic
                       splenomegaly

                    3. Massive nodes (≥10 cm in longest diameter) or progressive or symptomatic
                       lymphadenopathy

                    4. Progressive lymphocytosis with an increase of &gt; 50% over a 2-month period,
                       or lymphocyte doubling time of less than 6 months

                    5. Autoimmune anemia and/or thrombocytopenia poorly responsive to
                       corticosteroids or other standard therapy

                    6. B symptoms Weight loss &gt; 10% within the previous 6 months Fevers of greater
                       than 38.0° C for 2 or more weeks without other evidence of infection Night
                       sweats

          8. Patients with 2 or less regimens of previous chemotherapy including antibody therapy.
             Corticosteroid monotherapy is not counted.

          9. Patients with adequately maintained organ functions (e.g., bone marrow, heart, lung,
             liver, and kidney functions)

               -  Neutrophil count: ≥ 1,000 /mm3

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase(AST) Glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase(GOT): ≤ 3.0
                  times the upper limit of normal range at each site

               -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) Glutamic pyruvic transaminase(GPT): ≤ 3.0 times
                  the upper limit of normal range  at each site

               -  Total bilirubin: ≤ 1.5 times the upper limit of normal range  at each site

               -  Serum creatinine: ≤ 1.5 times the upper limit of normal range  at each site

               -  Partial pressure of O2 (PaO2): ≥ 65 mmHg

               -  No abnormalities which require treatment are detected on ECG

               -  Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) (echocardiography): ≥ 55%

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patients who fall under any one of the following criteria are to be excluded

          1. Patients who have been without treatment for less than 4 weeks after prior treatment.
             For patients treated with antibody therapy or underwent hematopoietic stem cell
             transplantation, for 3 months after prior treatment

          2. Patients who enrolled other clinical studies within 4 weeks before registration for
             this study

          3. Patients who received allogeneic stem cell transplantation in the past

          4. Patients with defective p53 (17p-) confirmed by chromosome analysis (Fluorescence in
             situ hybridization (Fish) method)

          5. Patients who are clinically diagnosed with Richter's syndrome

          6. Patients with infiltration to the central nervous system (CNS) or patients with
             clinical symptoms of suspected infiltration to the CNS

          7. Patients with multiple primary cancers or patients with a history of other malignant
             tumors within past 5 years, except for basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer, or
             carcinoma in situ of the cervix or gastrointestinal tract

          8. Patients with serious bleeding tendencies (e.g., disseminated intravascular
             coagulation (DIC))

          9. Patients with, or confirmed in the past to have had, interstitial lung disease or
             pulmonary fibrosis

         10. Patients with, or confirmed in the past to have had, autoimmune hemolytic anemia
             responds to corticosteroid therapy

         11. Patients with any of the following complications

               -  serious cardiac disease (e.g., myocardial infarction, ischemic heart disease, or
                  arrhythmia requiring treatment)

               -  serious, active infections (requiring intravenous administration of antibiotics,
                  antifungal drugs, or antiviral drugs)

               -  hepatic or renal dysfunction

               -  accumulation of pleural effusion, pericardial effusion, or peritoneal effusion

               -  uncontrollable serious gastrointestinal disease, endocrine disorder, or mental
                  illness

         12. Patients who received SyB L-0501 in the past

         13. Patients with allergies to mannitol

         14. Patients who need cytokine preparations such as erythropoietin or granulocyte colony
             stimulating factor (G-CSF) or blood transfusions at registration for this study

         15. Patients positive for HIV antibody or Hepatitis C virus (HCV) antibody

         16. Patients positive for Hepatitis B surface (HBs) antigen. Patients with negative
             results will also be checked for Hepatitis B core (HBc) antibody and HBs antibody. If
             either of the test results is positive, measure Hepatitis B virus (HBV)-DNA and
             exclude the patients with results above sensitivity

         17. Patients with clinical symptom of cytomegalovirus (CMV) infection, except
             asymptomatic patients with CMV positive

         18. Patients who are pregnant, who may possibly be pregnant, or lactating

         19. Patients who do not agree to practice contraception. Male: During investigational
             product administration and until 6 months after final administration Female: During
             investigational product administration and until 4 months after final administration

         20. Patients with drug addiction, narcotics addiction, and/or alcohol dependency

         21. Patients otherwise judged by the investigator or sub-investigator to be unsuitable
             for inclusion in this study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Toshihiko Nagase</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>SymBio Pharmaceuticals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Seiji Kinoshita</last_name>
    <phone>+81-3-5472-1127</phone>
    <email>skinoshita.0709@symbiopharma.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nagoya</city>
        <state>Aichi</state>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fukuyama</city>
        <state>Hiroshima</state>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Isehara</city>
        <state>Kanagawa</state>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Izumo</city>
        <state>Shimane</state>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minato-ku</city>
        <state>Tokyo</state>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kagoshima</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 20, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 17, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
