<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="58779">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02000934</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C34001</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-002292-18</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02000934</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of TAK-659 in Adult Patients With Advanced Solid Tumor and Lymphoma Malignancies</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label, Dose Escalation, Phase 1, First-in-Human Study of TAK-659 in Adult Patients With Advanced Solid Tumor and Lymphoma Malignancies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is an open-label, multicenter, phase 1, dose escalation study of TAK-659 in adult
      patients with advanced solid tumor and lymphoma malignancies. This study will be the first
      to administer TAK-659 to humans. The patient population during dose escalation (Part A) will
      consist of adults previously diagnosed with any form of a solid tumor or lymphoma for which
      standard, curative, or life-prolonging treatment does not exist or is no longer effective.
      This first-in-human (FIH) study will include 2 dose expansion cohorts in refractory and/or
      relapsed CLL and DLBCL (Part B) following completion of dose escalation (Part A).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events (AEs), serious adverse events (SAEs), DLTs (Cycle 1), clinical laboratory values, and vital sign measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>From signing of the informed consent form through 28 days after the last dose of study drug</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma, and urine PK  of TAK-659 including maximum concentration (Cmax), end of dosing interval concentration (Ctrough), dosing interval area under the curve (AUC24), 8 hour urine recovery (Ae8), and renal clearance (CLr).</measure>
    <time_frame>Depending on whether the patient is in dose escalation/expansion, the maximum sampling schedule is days 1, 2, 8, 15, 16 of first cycle.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Single and Repeat Dose Pharmacokinetic Parameters.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic effects of TAK-659 in circulating tumor cells, including but not limited to drug-induced modulation of signaling molecules in the B-cell receptor (BCR) pathway.</measure>
    <time_frame>At screening and twice in cycle 1 for CLL patients in dose expansion.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate (ORR) in the CLL cohort</measure>
    <time_frame>Until disease progression, death, start of alternative therapies, or study closure up to 24 months.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ORR and progression-free survival (PFS) in the diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL) cohort</measure>
    <time_frame>Until disease progression, death, start of alternative therapies, or study closure up to 24 months.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Solid Tumor and Lymphoma Malignancies</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TAK-659</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Given orally in a once daily schedule.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TAK-659</intervention_name>
    <description>Dose escalation stage (Part A) Modified 3+3 dose escalation in patients with advanced solid tumor/lymphoma, with no effective treatment available projected.
Dose expansion stage (Part B) CLL Expansion Cohort and DLBCL Expansion Cohort in patients with relapsed or refractory diseases.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TAK-659</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

        Each patient must meet all of the following inclusion criteria to be enrolled in the
        study:

          1. Male or female patients 18 years or older

          2. To be enrolled to the dose escalation cohorts, (Part A), patients must have
             histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of metastatic and/or advanced
             solid tumor malignancy or lymphoma, for which no effective standard treatment is
             available.

          3. To be enrolled to the CLL expansion cohort (Part B) or DLBCL expansion cohort (Part
             B), patients must have relapsed or refractory diseases after ≥ 1 prior therapy that
             meet the criteria described in the protocol.

          4. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0 or 1.

          5. Patients must have adequate organ function, including the following:

             a) Bone marrow reserve, hepatic, and renal function as described in the protocol

          6. Male or female patient with reproductive potential who agrees to use effective
             method(s) of contraception during the study treatment period through 6 months after
             the last dose of study drug. The definition of &quot;effective method of contraception&quot;
             will be based on the investigator's judgment and local regulation.

          7. Patients must have recovered from the reversible effects of prior anticancer therapy
             (to Grade ≤ 1).

          8. Voluntary written consent must be given before performance of any study-related
             procedure not part of standard medical care, with the understanding that consent may
             be withdrawn by the patient at any time without prejudice to future medical care.

        Exclusion Criteria

        Patients meeting any of the following exclusion criteria are not to be enrolled in the
        study.

          1. Patients with brain metastasis, or patients with active secondary malignancy that
             requires treatment, with exceptions as described in the protocol

          2. Any serious medical or psychiatric illness, including drug or alcohol abuse, that
             could, in the investigator's opinion, potentially interfere with the completion of
             treatment according to this protocol.

          3. Life-threatening illness unrelated to cancer;  major surgery, systemic infection
             requiring intravenous (IV) antibiotic therapy or other serious infection within 14
             days before the first dose of study drug.

          4. Female patients who are pregnant or lactating.

          5. Any immunotherapy, chemotherapy, radiotherapy, or investigational therapy within 2-4
             weeks before the first dose of study treatment, as detailed in the protocol

          6. Autologous stem cell transplant within 6 months before Day 1 of Cycle 1, or prior
             allogeneic stem cell transplant at any time.

          7. Treatment with high dose corticosteroids (&gt; daily dose equivalent to 10 mg oral
             prednisone) for anticancer purposes within 7 days before the first dose of TAK-659.

          8. Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positive; known hepatitis B surface
             antigen-positive; or known or suspected active hepatitis C infection (testing not
             required).

          9. Evidence of currently uncontrolled cardiovascular conditions as listed in the
             protocol; acute myocardial infarction with 6 months before starting study drug;
             baseline QT interval (QTcF) &gt; 475 milliseconds (msec) (males) or &gt; 450 msec
             (females); or abnormalities on baseline 12-lead ECG that are considered clinically
             significant per investigator.

         10. Patients who are receiving treatment with prohibited medications (inhibitor or
             inducer of P-gp or strong inhibitors or inducers of CYP3A) as listed in the protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Monitor</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>For an updated listing of recruitment sites contact: Millennium Medical and Drug Information Center</last_name>
    <phone>1-877-674-3784</phone>
    <email>medical@mlnm.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Robert H. Lurie Comprehensive Cancer Center Northwestern University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sarah Cannon Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>TAK-659</keyword>
  <keyword>Solid Tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>CLL</keyword>
  <keyword>DLBCL</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
