<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="40349">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02114723</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DPC-MITR-01-1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02114723</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of Kinesio Tape in Primary Dysmenorrhea</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessment of Kinesio Tape Self-applied, in the Treatment of Primary Dysmenorrhea</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidad Miguel Hernandez de Elche</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidad Miguel Hernandez de Elche</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Spain: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Determine the effectiveness of a proceeding under kinesio tape on pain and systemic symptoms
      most frequently described in primary dysmenorrhea.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to assess the analgesic efficacy of self-applied Kinesio tape in
      the treatment of primary dysmenorrhea .

      To evaluate this effect, a total of 128 students from the University Miguel Hernández , with
      the following inclusion criteria, participated in this study: history of menstrual pain,
      aged between 18 and 39 years who have performed a gynecological check in the last 18 months
      and who have been diagnosed with any kind of primary dysmenorrhea.

      A preliminary survey to identify valid students was made. Thereafter the participants were
      separated into two different groups (intervention group and placebo group) in order to
      request the completion of three questionnaires about the characteristics of menstrual pain
      and other demographic data for the next two menstrual cycles before the intervention. One
      survey included a graphic scale so the students could mark the start and the end of the
      symptoms associated with the menstrual cycle.

      After that the principal researcher will interviewed with the participants to show them the
      correct auto-application of the menstrual bandage and placebo. Each students group will
      receive a triptych with information and pictures to the correct application of the adhesive
      strips.

      Finally, during two new menstrual cycles, the participants will answer the same
      questionnaires to assess symptoms and menstrual pain while being worn adhesive strips (3
      pieces of Kinesio tape - 20 cm x 5 cm Tape Cure ®-, applied to the abdominal and lower back,
      in the intervention group; 2 pieces of Cross Tape ® 2.5 cm x 2 cm -, in the hip joint, in
      the placebo group. Participants may do personal hygiene during the days of the menstrual
      cycle with their adhesives strips placed on oneself.

      The size sample will be 128 girls. Differences will be contrasted in comparison of means
      (quantitative improvement, with an ANOVA) to evaluate the intervention. 18 girls were
      randomly chosen to obtain an estimation of the contrast parameters considered (means and
      standard variations). With this size sample and a significance of 5%, the investigators will
      have a power for the total sample for the contrasts of 80%.

      To describe the variables, the investigators will use frequencies (absolute and relative)
      for the qualitative variables. For the quantitative variables, the investigators will use
      means plus standard variations.

      To verify the homogeneity of the randomization the investigators will use tests based on the
      X2 (Pearson or Fisher) and t-test. The same procedure will be used to verify that the
      participants who quit the study have similar characteristics as those who remain.

      The improvement will be analyzed quantitatively using ANOVA test. Dependent variable: pain
      after the intervention. Independent variables: pain before the intervention, changes in
      pharmacological therapy and intervention group. In the event of significant differences in
      the ANOVA models the investigators will use the Tukey post-hoc test, in order to determine
      where the differences exist between the two groups.

      Qualitatively, the investigators will assess the improvement by calculating indicators of
      clinical relevance: relative risk (RR), absolute risk reduction (ARR), relative risk
      reduction (RRR), and number needed to treat (NNT).

      All the analyses will be made at a significance of 5%. The confidence intervals (CI) will be
      calculated for the most relevant parameters. The analyses will be done using  IBM SPSS
      Statistics 19.0.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain NRS (numeric rating scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for  4 menstrual cycles, an expected average of 5 mounths</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluations will be performed before, just after, 2 hours, 4 hours, 8 hours, 12 hours, 24 hours, and 48 hours after treatment. It will be measured in abdominal area,  low back,  lower limb and head.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of analgesics requiring during menstruation</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for  4 menstrual cycles, an expected average of 5 mounths</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of live</measure>
    <time_frame>before/after intervention (5 mounths)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Quality of live Questionnaire Euroquol-5D (EQ-5D)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">128</enrollment>
  <condition>Primary Dysmenorrhea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Kinesio tape</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>3 band of a special and hypoallergenic tape, called Cure Tape ® (2 strips of 12 x 5 cm and 1 strip of 20 cm x 5 cm) are attached to the abdominal  and lower back. One piece of 12 cm in length is applied right from below the navel and reached to where the pubic hair below, and another piece of 12 cm in length is applied to make a cross shape with the first piece (inside 11-12 dermatomes area). The piece of 20cm in length is placed horizontally to the lower back.
The bandage is applied at the time that menstrual pain begins and is stuck to the skin for 4-5 days until menstrual pain disappears</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cross tape</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Two pieces of special and squared tape of 2.5 x 2 cm called Cross Tape ® are attached to the external side of the thigh at the hip joint area (outside 11-12 dermatomes area)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Kinesio tape</intervention_name>
    <description>The material used is a lengthways tape bandage of cotton with elastic properties,  provided with a layer of anti-allergic adhesive in one of its sides that does not contain latex. This layer of glue is applied according to a special pattern so as to allow adequate transpiration.
The bandage is applied at the time that menstrual pain begins and is stuck to the skin for 4-5 days until menstrual pain disappears</description>
    <arm_group_label>Kinesio tape</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cure Tape®</other_name>
    <other_name>Kinesio Tape®</other_name>
    <other_name>Kinesiotape Akraven</other_name>
    <other_name>Kinesio® Tex</other_name>
    <other_name>BB Tape (Bio balance tape)</other_name>
    <other_name>BB Lattice Tape</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women presenting menstrual pain grade 2-3 according to the classification of the
             severity of primary dysmenorrhea Andersch and Milsom.

          -  Have attended gynecological examination in the past 18 months and had ever diagnosed
             as having a gynecological disorder different from primary dysmenorrhea

          -  Not have been diagnosed with secondary dysmenorrhea

          -  Regular menstrual cycles (cycle typical range of 21 to 35 days)

          -  Do not use an intrauterine contraceptive device (IUD) or taking oral contraceptive
             pills

          -  Nulliparous

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women with mild dysmenorrhea (pain lower 4 in a numeric pain scale range 0-10);

          -  Women with irregular or infrequent menstrual cycles (outside the typical range of
             cycle 21 to 35 days);

          -  Women using an intrauterine contraceptive device (IUD) or taking oral contraceptive
             pills.

          -  Women who suffer from diseases diagnosed added

          -  Women to which it has undergone a surgical procedure for the treatment

          -  Provide skin lesions in the abdominal wall

          -  Use or abuse of drugs or alcohol

          -  Body mass index (BMI) between&gt; 15.99 kg/m2 (maximum value of underweight according to
             WHO) and &lt;25.00 kg m2 (maximum overweight according to WHO)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>María I Tomás-Rodríguez, PT, MSC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universidad Miguel Hernández de Elche</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>José V Toledo-Marhuenda, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Universidad Miguel Hernández de Elche</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vicente F Gil-Guillén, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Universidad Miguel Hernández de Elche</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Antonio Palazón-Bru, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Universidad Miguel Hernández de Elche</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>María I Tomás-Rodríguez, PT</last_name>
    <phone>+34 607326334</phone>
    <email>mitomas@umh.es</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>José V Toledo-Marhuenda, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+34 965919260</phone>
    <email>josetoledo@umh.es</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universidad Miguel Hernández de Elche</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sant Joan D'Alacant</city>
        <state>Alicante</state>
        <zip>03550</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.kinesiotaping.com/</url>
    <description>Kinesio Taping® Association International</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.aevnm.com/</url>
    <description>Spanish Association of Neuromuscular Bandage.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.medicaltaping.com/</url>
    <description>Medical Taping Concept</description>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lim C, Park Y, Bae Y. The effect of the kinesio taping and spiral taping on menstrual pain and premenstrual syndrome. J Phys Ther Sci. 2013 Jul;25(7):761-4. doi: 10.1589/jpts.25.761. Epub 2013 Aug 20.</citation>
    <PMID>24259847</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Akin M, Price W, Rodriguez G Jr, Erasala G, Hurley G, Smith RP. Continuous, low-level, topical heat wrap therapy as compared to acetaminophen for primary dysmenorrhea. J Reprod Med. 2004 Sep;49(9):739-45.</citation>
    <PMID>15493566</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Dawood MY, Ramos J. Transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation (TENS) for the treatment of primary dysmenorrhea: a randomized crossover comparison with placebo TENS and ibuprofen. Obstet Gynecol. 1990 Apr;75(4):656-60.</citation>
    <PMID>2179780</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 7, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidad Miguel Hernandez de Elche</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>María Isabel Tomás-Rodríguez, PT</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PT, MSC</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Kinesio tape</keyword>
  <keyword>Neuromuscular bandage</keyword>
  <keyword>Physiotherapy techniques</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dysmenorrhea</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
