<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="130994">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01744977</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>01642</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01744977</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cholesterol Medication Packaging Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>MWV_CAPS</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluate the Efficacy, Perceptions and Cost of an Innovative Cholesterol Packaging</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Durham VA Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Durham VA Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the overall study is to improve medication use rates among veterans by
      looking at the risk factors of low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL).  It will involve
      patients who have high LDL-C level (&lt;130mg/dl) and /or may have difficulty taking their
      medications based on how often they refilled their medications in the last 12 months.

      The investigators will test an innovative adherence packaging relative to usual care.  The
      primary hypothesis is that veterans who receive the intervention will have greater
      improvement in their medication adherence as measured by pill refill at 6 and 12 months of
      follow up as compared to the control group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A sample of participants with elevated LDL level &gt;130 mg/dl and/or &lt;80% medication position
      ratio in the last 12 months (n=250) will be consented. The study sample will consist of both
      male and female subjects. Research assistants (RA's) will complete a baseline assessment and
      then randomly allocated participants to one of the following two groups:

        -  MeadWestvaco (MWV) Packaging Intervention. Patients randomized to the intervention
           group will receive the MWV medication adherence packaging and adherence education
           (Packaging Education.) at baseline from a research pharmacist. The participant will
           then receive their prescribed cholesterol medication in the MWV packaging  over the
           next 12 months.

        -  The Education only Group - Patients randomized to the control group will receive
           educational material about LDL reduction at baseline.

      The study includes the following contacts with participants.

        -  Recruitment letter

        -  Telephone screening

        -  Baseline consent and interview - In person for all participants [Only Adherence
           Packaging Intervention participants will receive baseline discussion and education from
           the research pharmacist]

        -  6 month outcome assessment follow-up - In person for all participants

        -  12 month outcome assessment follow-up - In person for all participants

        -  12 month phone interview - Optional recorded qualitative interview for  intervention
           participants only.

      All participants enrolled in study will be followed for 12 months.

      The study includes the following contacts with providers

        -  Baseline consent and explanation of the adherence packaging - In person for all
           providers (group style visit)

        -  6 month phone interview - recorded qualitative interview for providers with
           intervention participants only.

        -  12 month phone interview - recorded qualitative interview for providers with
           intervention participants only.

      Participation in this aspect of the study by providers does not preclude them for
      participating in other research studies during the same time period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cholesterol medication adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PIll refill will be obtained at baseline, 6 and 12 months to review change in cholesterol medication adherence over the 12 month period</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in LDL cholesterol level</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>obtain non-fasting lipid panel at timepoints to review change in LDL cholesterol levels over the 12 month period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">250</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypercholesterolemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Adherence Packaging Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>[MeadWestvaco Packaging Intervention Arm] At baseline, the intervention arm will receive instructions from the RA on obtaining medication refills and the first fill of their statin medication from the VA pharmacy. At this time, the pharmacist will provide counseling including 1) use of adherence packaging, 2) to only use statin medications from the adherence packaging 3) purpose of LDL-related medications 4) how to take the medications.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Education Only Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control Arm patients will receive primary care and LDL management according to the discretion of their provider. At baseline, patients will receive similar written information on how to obtain medication refills and the importance of taking their cholesterol medications as prescribed. The 6-month interval was selected to maintain contact with patients.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>packaging</intervention_name>
    <description>Intervention provides usual statin medication dispensed in pre-prepared adherence packaging (blister packaging) rather than the previously received prescription bottles</description>
    <arm_group_label>Adherence Packaging Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Enrolled in one of three Durham VA Medical Center (DVAMC) Primary Care clinics for at
             least one year

          -  AT least one visit to a primary care provider at the Raleigh Community Based
             Outpatient Clinic (CBOC) or DVAMC associated primary care clinics in the previous 12
             months

          -  Outpatient diagnostic code for hypercholesterolemia

          -  uncontrolled LDL in the last 12 months and/or poor LDL refill defined as &lt;80%
             medication adherence in the last 12 months

          -  prescribed whole tablets of simvastatin, rosuvastatin or pravastatin

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of metastatic cancer.

          -  Active diagnosis of dementia documented in medical record.

          -  Active diagnosis of psychosis documented in medical record with admission with last
             30days.

          -  Treated with dialysis

          -  Hospitalized for a stroke, myocardial infarction, coronary artery revascularization
             in past month.

          -  Severely impaired hearing, speech or sight.  (Patients must be able to respond to
             phone calls and review adherence literature)

          -  Participating in another on-going cardio- vascular disease (CVD) risk management
             study (i.e., pharmaceutical trial or behavioral intervention)

          -  Does not have access to a telephone

          -  Resident in nursing facility that manages patients medications or

          -  Receiving home health care for extended period (home health service for limited time
             period will not exclude, i.e. scheduled surgical procedure not expected to require
             care for longer than 30 days)

          -  Planning to leave the area prior to the anticipated end of participation in the
             study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hayden B Bosworth, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University Medical Center/Durham VA Medical Center, Health Services and Development</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Durham VAMC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27701</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Raleigh Community-based Outpatient Clinic (CBOC- Raleigh)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Raleigh</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27701</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 6, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 5, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hypercholesterolemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
