<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="35227">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02001220</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>151113</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02001220</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Screening Frequency Trial to Identify Weaning Candidates</brief_title>
  <acronym>RELEASE</acronym>
  <official_title>LibeRation From MEchanicaL VEntilAtion and ScrEening Frequency Trial: The RELEASE Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Michael's Hospital, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Michael's Hospital, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Ethics Review Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      During weaning the work of breathing is transferred from the ventilator back to the patient.
      Approximately 40% of the time on ventilators is spent weaning. Studies support the use of
      screening protocols and tests of patient's ability to breathe spontaneously (SBTs) to
      identify weaning candidates. Once daily screening is the current standard of care. With
      respiratory therapists (RTs) in Canadian intensive care units (ICUs), a significant
      opportunity exists to screen patients more frequently, conduct more SBTs, and reduce the
      time spent on ventilators and in the ICU.

      The study is seeking to identify the optimal screening frequency to minimize patients'
      exposure to invasive ventilation. The RELEASE Trial will evaluate a simple a simple
      construct: more frequent screening will result In earlier identification of weaning
      candidates, more frequent SBT's, and less time spent on ventilators and in the ICU. More
      frequent screening is an appealing intervention because it is sensible, low risk, and
      represents a cost effective use of current resources. This simple intervention holds promise
      as a strategy that could change clinical practice, enhance the care delivered to critically
      ill adults, and improve clinically important outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Eligible patients will be randomly assigned 1:1 to either 'once daily' or 'at least twice
      daily' screening for weaning readiness.

      After randomization, RTs in participating ICUs will be informed of the allocated study arm
      and bedside nurses will complete a checklist that documents practices related to sedation,
      analgesia, delirium, and mobilization before each screening period in both study arms. RTs
      will conduct weaning readiness assessments either 'once daily' or 'at least twice daily' as
      per group assignment.

      In the 'once daily screening arm', RTs will screen invasively ventilated patients between
      approximately 06:00 - 08:00 hours daily. In the 'at least twice daily' screening arm
      patients will be screened at a minimum between approximately 06:00 - 08:00 hours and 13:00 -
      15:00 hours daily. Additional screening trials in the 'at least twice daily' screening arm
      will be permitted at the discretion of the clinical team (RTs and physicians). Regardless of
      group assignment, if the SBT screening assessment is passed, an SBT will be conducted.

      To pass the 'readiness to wean screen' and undergo an SBT, all of the following criteria
      must be met:

        1. The patient must be capable of initiating spontaneous breaths on Pressure Support (PS)
           or triggering breaths on volume or pressure Assist Control (AC), volume or pressure
           Synchronized Intermittent Mandatory Ventilation (SIMV) ± PS, Pressure Regulated Volume
           Control (PRVC) or Airway Pressure Release Ventilation (APRV),

        2. The ratio of partial pressure of arterial oxygen to the fractional concentration of
           inspired oxygen (PaO2/FiO2) greater than or equal to 200 mm Hg,

        3. Respiratory rate (RR) less than or equal to 35 breaths/min,

        4. Positive end-expiratory pressure (PEEP) less than or equal to 10 cm H2O,

        5. Heart rate (HR) less than or equal to 140 beats/min,

        6. The ratio of respiratory frequency to tidal volume (f/VT) &lt; 105 breaths/min/L during a
           2 minute assessment.

      The initial SBT will be 30 minutes in duration and may be conducted with any one of the
      following techniques: T-piece, continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) less than or equal
      to 5 cm H2O or PS less than or equal to 8 cm H2O with PEEP less than or equal to 5 - 10 cm
      H2O. In both groups, patients who pass an SBT will be assessed for extubation criteria.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Screening</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To demonstrate our ability to recruit the desired population (1-2 patients, per centre per month, on average)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>1-2 patients, on average, per centre per month</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate clinician compliance with 'once daily' versus 'at least twice daily' screening assessments and the potential for contamination in the 'once daily' arm</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In both arms, compliance rates of at least 80% will be considered acceptable in both arms.
A contamination rate of less than or equal to 10% in the once daily screening arm will be acceptable.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess current practices related to sedation, analgesia and delirium management and mobilization before conducting 'once daily' or 'at least twice daily screening' assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We expect that these practices will be recorded at least 80% of the time, when feasible. Strategies utilized in &lt; 60% of assessments (leading to the first SBT) in either arm will be considered potentially important.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Identify barriers (clinician and institutional) to recruitment</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Descriptive</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Classify trial participants as requiring (i) simple, (ii) difficult or (iii) prolonged weaning using the 'Task Force on Weaning' definitions.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Descriptive</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Obtain preliminary estimates of the impact of the alternative screening strategies ('once daily' vs. 'at least twice daily'') on clinically important outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Clinically important outcomes will include time to first Spontaneous Breathing Trial (SBT) and first successful SBT, time to first extubation and successful extubation, total duration of mechanical ventilation, intensive care unit (ICU) and hospital length of stay, ICU and hospital mortality, use of noninvasive ventilation (NIV) following extubation, complications (self-extubation, tracheostomy, reintubation, proportion requiring prolonged mechanical ventilation)] and adverse events.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Critically Ill</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Once daily screening</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will undergo assessments to determine readiness to undergo an SBT once daily.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>At least twice daily screening</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will undergo assessments to determine readiness to undergo an SBT at least twice daily.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Once daily screening</intervention_name>
    <description>In the 'once daily screening arm', RTs will screen invasively ventilated patients between approximately 06:00 - 08:00 hours daily. To pass the 'readiness to wean screen' and undergo an SBT, all of the following criteria must be met: (1)The patient must be capable of initiating spontaneous breaths on PS or triggering breaths on volume or pressure AC, volume or pressure SIMV ± PS, PRVC or APRV, (2) The ratio of partial pressure of oxygen to FiO2 (PaO2/FiO2) greater than or equal to 200 mm Hg, (3)RR less than or equal to 35 breaths/min, (4) PEEP less than or equal to 10 cm H2O, (5) HR less than or equal to 140 beats/min, (6) The ratio of respiratory frequency to tidal volume (f/VT) &lt; 105 breaths/min/L during a 2 minute assessment.
The initial SBT will be 30 minutes in duration and may be conducted with any one of the following techniques: T-piece, CPAP less than or equal to 5 cm H2O or PS less than or equal to 8 cm H2O with PEEP less than or equal to 5 - 10 cm H2O.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Once daily screening</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>At least twice daily screening</intervention_name>
    <description>In the 'at least twice daily' screening arm patients will be screened at a minimum between approximately 6:00-8:00 hours and 13:00-15:00 hours daily. To pass the 'readiness to wean screen' and undergo an SBT, all of the following criteria must be met: (1)the patient must be capable of initiating spontaneous breaths on PS or triggering breaths on volume or pressure AC, volume or pressure SIMV ± PS, PRVC or APRV, (2) The ratio of partial pressure of oxygen to FiO2 (PaO2/FiO2) greater than or equal to 200 mm Hg, (3)RR less than or equal to 35 breaths/min, (4) PEEP less than or equal to 10 cm H2O, (5) HR less than or equal to 140 beats/min, (6) The ratio of respiratory frequency to tidal volume (f/VT) &lt; 105 breaths/min/L during a 2 minute assessment.
SBT will be conducted in the same manner as once daily screening arm.</description>
    <arm_group_label>At least twice daily screening</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Receiving invasive mechanical ventilation for ≥ 24 hours.

          -  Capable of initiating spontaneous breaths on PS or triggering breaths on volume or
             pressure AC, volume or pressure SIMV ± PS, PRVC, or APRV.

          -  With an FiO2 ≤ 70%.

          -  With a PEEP ≤ 12 cm H₂O.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients admitted after cardiopulmonary arrest or with brain death or expected brain
             death.

          -  Patients who have evidence of myocardial ischemia in the 24 hour period before
             enrollment.

          -  Patients who have received continuous invasive mechanical ventilation for ≥ 2 weeks.

          -  Patients who have a tracheostomy in situ at the time of screening.

          -  Patients who are receiving sedative infusions for seizures or alcohol withdrawal.

          -  Patients who require escalating doses of sedative agents.

          -  Patients who are receiving neuromuscular blockers or who have known quadriplegia,
             paraplegia, or 4 limb weakness or paralysis preventing active mobilization (e.g.
             active range of motion, exercises in bed, sitting at edge of bed, transferring from
             bed to chair, standing, marching in place, ambulating).

          -  Patients who are moribund (e.g., at imminent risk for death) or who have limitations
             of treatment (e.g., withdrawal of support, do not reintubate order, however, do not
             resuscitate orders will be permitted).

          -  Patients who have profound neurologic deficits (e.g., large intracranial stroke or
             bleed) or Glasgow Coma Scale (GCS) ≤ 6.

          -  Patients who are using modes that automate SBT conduct.

          -  Patients who are currently enrolled in a confounding study that includes a weaning
             protocol.

          -  Patients who were previously enrolled in this trial.

          -  Patients who have already undergone an SBT.

          -  Patients who have already undergone extubation [planned, unplanned (e.g. self,
             accidental)] during the same ICU admission.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen EA Burns, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Michael's Hospital and the Li Ka Shing Knowledge Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karen EA Burns, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
    <phone>416-864-6060</phone>
    <phone_ext>3567</phone_ext>
    <email>burnsk@smh.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Leena Rizvi, BSc</last_name>
    <phone>416-864-6060</phone>
    <phone_ext>2938</phone_ext>
    <email>rizvil@smh.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St Paul's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Dodek, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hamilton General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Joseph's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Deborah J Cook, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ottawa General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrew Seely, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Toronto General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eddy Fan, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Michael's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5B 1W8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karen EA Burns, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karen EA Burns, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Sinai Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sangeeta Mehta, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universite de Sherbrooke</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sherbrooke</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Francois Lamontagne, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 3, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 26, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>screening</keyword>
  <keyword>invasive ventilation</keyword>
  <keyword>mechanical ventilation</keyword>
  <keyword>weaning</keyword>
  <keyword>spontaneous breathing trials</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Critical Illness</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
