<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="31753">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01873118</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ANCC2013-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01873118</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>READI (Readiness Evaluation And Discharge Interventions): Implementation as a Standard Nursing Practice for Hospital Discharge</brief_title>
  <acronym>READI</acronym>
  <official_title>READI (Readiness Evaluation And Discharge Interventions): Implementation as a Standard Nursing Practice for Hospital Discharge</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Marquette University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Marquette University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Preparation of patients for discharge is a primary function of hospital-based nursing care
      and readiness for discharge is an important outcome of hospital care.  Inadequacies in
      discharge preparation have been well-documented and linked to difficulty with
      self-management after hospital discharge and with increased likelihood of emergency
      department (ED) use and readmission. Prior studies by the research team have led to
      recommendations for implementation of discharge readiness assessment as a standard nursing
      practice for hospital discharge.

      The investigators will conduct a multi-site study to determine the impact on post-discharge
      utilization (readmission and ED visits) and costs of implementing  discharge readiness
      assessment as a standard nursing practice for adult medical-surgical patients discharged to
      home. The study tests, in a stepped approach, the impact of implementing discharge readiness
      assessment by the discharging nurse as standard nursing practice (RN-RHDS protocol), the
      incremental value of informing the nurse assessment with the patient's perspective
      (RN-RHDS+PT-RHDS protocol), and of requiring that the nurse initiates and documents
      risk-mitigating actions for patients with low readiness scores (RN-RHDS+PT-RHDS+NIAF
      protocol).

      HYPOTHESIS 1: Patients discharged using the RN-RHDS protocol will have fewer hospital
      readmissions and ED visits within 30 days post-discharge compared to patients discharged
      under usual care conditions.

      HYPOTHESIS 2: Patients discharged using the RN-RHDS+PT-RHDS protocol will have fewer
      hospital readmissions and ED visits within 30 days post-discharge compared to patients
      discharged using the RN-RHDS protocol.

      HYPOTHESIS 3: Patients discharged by nurses using the RN-RHDS+PT-RHDS protocol plus a
      Nurse-Initiated Action Form [NIAF] (RN-RHDS+PT-RHDS+NIAF protocol) will have fewer
      post-discharge readmissions and ED visits than patients discharged using the RN-RHDS+PT-RHDS
      protocol; the effect will be strongest for patients with low RHDS scores.

      Aim 4: Conduct cost-benefit analysis of implementing discharge readiness assessment as
      standard practice, by comparing cost-savings from reduced post-discharge utilization against
      implementation costs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Factorial Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-discharge Utilization within 30 days after hospital discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after hospital discharge</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Readmissions and Emergency Department Visits within 30 days after hospital discharge</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nurse Initiated Action Form</measure>
    <time_frame>measured on day of hospital discharge typically 1 to 30 days after hospital admission</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measures actions taken by the discharging nurse in response to discharge readiness assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Readiness for Hospital Discharge Scale - RN version</measure>
    <time_frame>measured on day of hospital discharge typically 1 to 30 days after hospital admission</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Nurses perceptions of patient readiness for hospital discharge</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Readiness for Hospital Discharge Scale - Patient version</measure>
    <time_frame>measured on day of hospital discharge typically 1 to 30 days after hospital admission</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient perception of discharge readiness</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24000</enrollment>
  <condition>Discharge Transition of Patients Discharged to Home</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care Control hospital unit</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>This study involves implementation of interventions across entire hospital units. This arm is a usual care control unit paired to the intervention unit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>implementation unit</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>3 implementation protocols implemented sequentially:
RN-RHDS: implementation of discharge readiness assessment by the discharging nurse
RN-RHDS+PT-RHDS: implementation of discharge readiness assessment by the discharging nurse which is informed by patient self-assessment of discharge readiness
RN-RHDS+PT-RHDS+NIAF: implementation of discharge readiness assessment by the discharging nurse which is informed by patient self-assessment of discharge readiness followed by documentation of nurse actions initiated in response to the assessment. Nurse are instructed that action must be taken if any assessment item scores less than 7 ( on a 10 point scale).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RN-RHDS protocol</intervention_name>
    <description>The discharging nurse assesses each patient being discharged home using the Readiness for Hospital Discharge Scale (RN version)</description>
    <arm_group_label>implementation unit</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RN-RHDS+PT-RHDS protocol</intervention_name>
    <description>The discharging nurse obtains and reviews patient self-report of discharge readiness using the Readiness for Hospital Discharge Scale - Patient version and then completes the Readiness for Hospital Discharge Scale (RN version)</description>
    <arm_group_label>implementation unit</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RN-RHDS + PT-RHDS + NIAF</intervention_name>
    <description>The discharging nurse assesses each patient being discharged home using the Readiness for Hospital Discharge Scale (RN version)after reviewing the patients self-perception of discharge readiness (PT-RHDS) and then records any actions taken in response to the discharge readiness assessment on the Nurse Initiated Action form (NIAF). When any item on the RN-RHDS is less than 7, an action is required.</description>
    <arm_group_label>implementation unit</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Medical, surgical, or medical-surgical nursing units of Magnet designated hospitals

          -  Patients 18 years of age or more, English speaking,able to read and understand
             consent who are being discharged to home as the discharge destination.

          -  Nursing personnel (Registered Nurses or Licensed Practical Nurses) who are performing
             discharge instructions and procedures on the day of hospital discharge.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients discharged to home with hospice care.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marianne Weiss, DNSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Marquette University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marianne Weiss, DNSc</last_name>
    <phone>414-288-3855</phone>
    <email>marianne.weiss@marquette.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 5, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 3, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Marquette University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marianne Weiss</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hospital discharge</keyword>
  <keyword>discharge readiness</keyword>
  <keyword>readmission</keyword>
  <keyword>Emergency Department visits</keyword>
  <keyword>Nurse assessment</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
