<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="168018">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01701999</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>rBV A/B-CL-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01701999</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety, Tolerability, and Immunogenicity Study of Investigational Recombinant Botulinum Vaccine A/B (rBV A/B) in Volunteers Previously Immunized With Investigational Pentavalent Botulinum Toxoid</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 2b, Two-part, Open-label, Uncontrolled Study to Evaluate Safety, Tolerability, and Immunogenicity of a Single 40-µg Dose of Recombinant Botulinum Vaccine A/B (rBV A/B) for the Production of BabyBIG® in Volunteers Previously Immunized With Pentavalent Botulinum Toxoid for Occupational Protection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>California Department of Public Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>California Department of Public Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Study rBV A/B-CL-001 is a Phase 2b, 2-part, open-label, uncontrolled study to evaluate
      safety, tolerability, and immunogenicity of a single dose of recombinant botulinum vaccine
      A/B (rBV A/B) for the production of BabyBIG in volunteers previously immunized with the
      pentavalent botulinum (PBT) toxoid.  This study is designed to determine neutralizing
      antibody levels for botulinum toxin types A and B in healthy subjects who were previously
      immunized with the PBT for occupational protection and who receive the rBV A/B.  Subjects
      with titers of the neutralizing antibodies against the toxins would be candidates for plasma
      donation for BabyBIG production.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunogenicity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary immunogenicity objective of this study is to evaluate the effects of a single dose of rBV A/B on the botulinum toxin types A and B neutralizing antibody concentration (NAC) over a 12-week period after receiving the rBV A/B vaccine in subjects who have previously been immunized with PBT for occupational protection.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency and Severity of Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary safety objective of this study is to obtain safety information over a 12 week period on the use of rBV A/B in a population of plasma donors previously immunized with PBT for occupational protection with a long-term safety assessment (phone call follow-up) at 6 months.  The frequency and severity of adverse events will be summarized by system organ class and preferred term.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in laboratory parameters from Baseline to 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in hematology, serum chemistry, and urinalysis parameters from baseline to the end of the study will be examined and summarized from baseline to week 12.  Laboratory abnormalities will be assessed for relatedness.  Treatment-emergent changes from normal to abnormal values in key laboratory parameters will be identified.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">83</enrollment>
  <condition>Botulism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>rBV A/B</intervention_name>
    <description>rBV A/B injections will consist of a single 40 µg injection of total antigen (20 µg of Antigen A and 20 µg of Antigen B) adsorbed to 0.2% (wt/vol) Alhydrogel™, in a total dose volume of 0.5 mL.  The vaccine will be administered by intramuscular injection in the deltoid muscle, preferably in the nondominant arm.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vaccine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The volunteer has received pentavalent botulinum toxoid for occupational protection
             under BB IND 0161, with the previous pentavalent botulinum toxoid dose at least 6
             months prior to the planned rBV A/B dose.

          -  The volunteer is between the ages of 18 and 69 years at the time of consent.

          -  The volunteer is healthy and has an acceptable medical history.

          -  The volunteer meets the subject suitability requirements and recommendations for
             source plasma donors (for Part 2 subjects only).

          -  The volunteer, if female and of childbearing potential, is not pregnant or lactating,
             and agrees to use an acceptable form of FDA-approved contraception for the duration
             of the study.

          -  The volunteer has the ability to understand the requirements of the study and provide
             informed consent.

          -  The volunteer agrees to complete the subject diary on a daily basis for 7 days
             post-vaccination and to report concomitant medication and adverse events during the
             study period.

          -  The volunteer provides written authorization for use and disclosure of protected
             health information.

          -  The volunteer agrees not to donate blood or blood products (outside of study
             procedures) during the course of the study.

          -  The volunteer has personal health insurance.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Be pregnant or nursing

          -  The volunteer has a history of laboratory evidence of syphilis, acquired
             immunodeficiency syndrome, Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease, or infection with human
             immunodeficiency viruses 1 or 2, human T cell lymphotropic virus 1, hepatitis B
             virus, or hepatitis C virus.

          -  The volunteer had prior severe local or severe systemic reaction to last immunization
             with pentavalent botulinum toxoid.

          -  The volunteer has a known allergy to aluminum compounds, yeast, or other components
             of the vaccine.

          -  The volunteer has donated one or more units of blood or undergone plasmapheresis
             within 28 days before screening.

          -  The volunteer has received a blood product or immunoglobulin within 6 months of
             screening or plans to receive such products during the study.

          -  The volunteer has received licensed nonliving vaccine within 14 days before study
             entry or licensed live vaccine within 60 days before study entry.

          -  The volunteer has received investigational products (drugs, biologics, vaccines, or
             implantable devices) 60 days prior to study entry or plans to receive experimental
             products at any time during the study.

          -  The volunteer has received prescription immunosuppressive or immunomodulatory agents,
             including parenteral, inhaled, or oral corticosteroids within 3 months before
             screening or plans on receiving such therapy at any time during the study with the
             exceptions (Subjects who have used prescription topical steroids may be enrolled 2
             weeks after the therapy is completed; Intra-articular, bursal, or tendon injectable
             steroids are permitted; Any over-the-counter topical steroid use is permitted;
             Ophthalmic and intranasal steroids are permitted).

          -  The volunteer has received cytotoxic therapy at any time in the previous 5 years to
             study entry.

          -  The volunteer has an active systemic or recurrent disease that would place the
             subject at unacceptable risk of injury, require hospitalization, or require surgical
             intervention.

          -  The volunteer has a history of alcohol or drug abuse within 12 months before
             screening.

          -  The volunteer has past, present, or suspected illicit injection drug use.

          -  The volunteer has inflammatory, vasculitic, or rheumatic disease, including systemic
             lupus erythematosus, polymyalgia rheumatica, rheumatoid arthritis, or scleroderma.

          -  The volunteer has clinically recognized hepatic or renal insufficiency.

          -  The volunteer has uncontrolled hypertension.

          -  The volunteer has moderate to severe asthma, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease,
             or other significant pulmonary disease.

          -  The volunteer has a seizure disorder.

          -  The volunteer has moderate or severe illness or oral temperature of 100.4°F or
             greater within 3 days prior to immunization.

          -  The volunteer is determined by the investigator to be unsuitable for participation in
             this trial for any reason.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>69 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen S. Arnon, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>California Department of Public Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>California Department of Public Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94804</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.infantbotulism.org/</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 3, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Botulism Vaccine</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Botulism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
