<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="112505">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01736566</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MedSeq™</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U01HG006500</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01736566</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pilot Project Exploring the Impact of Whole Genome Sequencing in Healthcare</brief_title>
  <official_title>The MedSeq Project Pilot Study: Integrating Whole Genome Sequencing Into the Practice of Clinical Medicine</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brigham and Women's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Baylor College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brigham and Women's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The MedSeq™ Project seeks to explore the impact of incorporating information from a
      patient's whole genome sequence into the practice of clinical medicine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Whole genome sequencing (WGS) and whole exome sequencing (WES) services are currently
      available to and are being utilized by physicians and their patients in both research and
      clinical settings. The widespread availability and use of WGS and WES in the practice of
      clinical medicine is imminent. In the very near future, sequencing of individual genomes
      will be inexpensive and ubiquitous, and patients will be looking to the medical
      establishment for interpretations, insight and advice to improve their health. Developing
      standards and procedures for the use of WGS information in clinical medicine is an urgent
      need, but there are numerous obstacles related to integrity and storage of WGS data,
      interpretation and responsible clinical integration. MedSeq™ seeks to develop a process to
      integrate WGS into clinical medicine and explore the impact of doing so.

      We believe that WGS will be used in many ways, including two distinct and complementary
      situations. In generally healthy patients, physicians will use the results of WGS to derive
      insight into future health risks and inform prevention and surveillance efforts, a category
      we refer to as General Genomic Medicine. In patients presenting with a family history or
      symptoms of a disease, physicians will use the results of WGS to interrogate particular sets
      of genes known to be associated with the disease in question, a category we refer to as
      Disease-Specific Genomic Medicine.

      Beginning in fall 2012, we will enroll 10 primary care physicians and 100 of their healthy
      middle-aged patients to evaluate the use of General Genomic Medicine, and 10 cardiologists
      and 100 of their patients presenting with hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (HCM) to evaluate the
      use of Disease-Specific Genomic Medicine. We will randomize physicians and their patients
      within each of the above models to receive clinically meaningful information derived from
      WGS versus current standard of care without the use of WGS.

      MedSeq™ is comprised of three distinct but highly collaborative projects. Project 1 will
      enroll physicians and patients into the protocol, educate the physicians on basic genomic
      principles and safely monitor the use of genomic information in clinical practice. Project 2
      will use a WGS analysis/interpretation pipeline to generate a genome report on each patient
      randomized to receive WGS in this protocol. Project 3 will examine preferences and
      motivations of physicians and patients enrolled, evaluate the flow and utilization of
      genomic information within the clinical interactions, and assess understanding, behavior,
      medical consequences and healthcare costs associated with the use of WGS in these models of
      medical practice.

      This initiative will significantly accelerate the use of genomics in clinical medicine by
      creating and safely testing novel methods for integrating information from WGS into
      physicians' care of patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Attitudes and Trust</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6-weeks post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Novel measures and adapted measures (Hall, MA, et al. 2006) will assess participants' attitudes toward genetic information and trust of their physicians and the medical system regarding interpretation and use of genetic information.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Self Efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6-months post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessed through a scale developed for the Multiplex Initiative (Kaphingst, K.A., et al. 2012)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Preferences for WGS information</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6-weeks post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Through novel survey items, participants will be asked about their preferences for the types of genetic testing results they would like to receive from their whole genome sequence and their preferences regarding their sequencing results in their medical record.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Risk Perception</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at the disclosure visit (about 1 hour after results disclosure) and 6-months post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Novel and adapted survey measures from the Multiplex Initiative will assess changes in how participants perceive their own health and risk of health conditions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Shared Decision Making</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in shared decision making will be assessed through the Control Preferences Scale, a validated survey measure designed to ascertain the degree of control an individual wants to assume when decisions are being made about medical treatment. The measure will assess how patients prefer to make healthcare decisions with their doctor. This will be measured one time as a stable trait.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Intolerance of Uncertainty</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6-months post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in participants' tolerance for uncertainty will be assessed through a short version of the Intolerance of Uncertainty Scale (Carleton, 2007).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in General Anxiety and Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and at the disclosure visit (about 1 hour after results disclosure), 6-weeks post-disclosure and 6-months post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) scale will be administered through a survey. This is a validated scale designed to assess the participants' level of depression and anxiety through Likert-type questions. Any participant scoring 11 or higher will be contacted by study staff for evaluation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Health Behaviors and Intentions</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and at the disclosure visit (about 1 hour after results disclosure), 6-weeks post-disclosure and 6-months post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in participants' health behaviors and intentions will be assessed through novel and adapted survey measures (from the Cancer Prevention Research Center, Stages of Change Measures, 1991)  asking about vitamin, supplement and medication use, insurance-purchasing behaviors, and diet, smoking and exercise practices.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Information Seeking and Sharing</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at the disclosure visit (about 1 hour after results disclosure), 6-weeks post-disclosure and 6-months post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in participants' information seeking and sharing behaviors will be assessed through measures adapted from the HINTS surveys on information seeking and information sharing.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Genetic Literacy and Numeracy</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessing Genomic Literacy at baseline and 6-months post-disclosure. Measuring Subjective Numeracy at baseline and Objective Numeracy at post-disclosure visit (about 1 hour after results disclosure)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in participants' numeracy will be assessed through validated measures of objective and subjective numeracy (Lipkus et al. 2007 and Fagerlin et al. 2007), and changes in genetic literacy will be measured by survey measures adapted from the ClinSeq Study (Kaphingst K.A. et al. 2012). We are only assessing changes in Genetic Literacy. Genetic Numeracy will be measured one time as a stable trait.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Health Care Utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at the disclosure visit (about 1 hour after results disclosure), 6-weeks post-disclosure, and 6-months post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in participants' health care utilization will be assessed through novel and adapted measures from the Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System (BRFSS).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Expectations/Perceived Utility</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, disclosure visit at the disclosure visit (about 1 hour after results disclosure), 6-weeks and 6-months post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Novel survey items will assess participants' expectations of the number of health conditions they will learn about through genome sequencing, and their interest in, their perceived usefulness of and their concerns about these results. Novel survey items will also assess affective forecasting. Additionally, novel survey items will assess participants' perceived utility of their results in terms of their own healthcare and planned behavior.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychological Impact</measure>
    <time_frame>6-weeks post-disclosure and 6-months post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Psychological impact will be assessed by a modified version of the Multidimensional Impact of Cancer Risk Assessment (MICRA) questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction and Decisional Regret</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessing Satisfaction with Clinician and Decisional Regret at post-disclosure visit (about 1 hour after results disclosure). Assessing Satisfaction with Information at 6-weeks post-disclosure.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants' satisfaction with their clinician will be measured via the RIAS scale (Roter and Larson, 2002). Participants' satisfaction with the information learned from genome sequencing will be assessed with novel measures. Decisional regret will be assessed through a validated scale (Brehaut 2003).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Understanding and Recall</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessing Understanding of Informed Consent at baseline. Assessing Understanding of Results at post-disclosure visit at the disclosure visit (about 1 hour after results disclosure), 6-weeks post-disclosure, and 6-months post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Novel items will assess participants' understanding of their genome sequencing results. Additionally, novel items will assess participants' objective understanding of the informed consent for whole genome sequencing and adapted items will assess participants' subjective understanding of the informed consent for genome sequencing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Motivations for Participation</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Novel survey items will ask participants about why they decided to participate in this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Adults</condition>
  <condition>Hypertrophic Cardiomyopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>&quot;Standard of Care&quot; + Whole Genome Sequencing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Doctors and their patients will receive a Genome Report and an Annotated Family History Report.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>&quot;Standard of Care&quot; Only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Doctors and their patients will receive an Annotated Family History Report only.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Experimental:   &quot;Standard of Care&quot; + Whole Genome Sequencing (Genome Report)</intervention_name>
    <description>Doctors and their patients will receive a Genome Report and a Family History Report.
There will be two sections of the Genome Report:
The General Genome Report, which will include highly penetrant disease mutations, carrier status for recessive disease, and pharmacogenetic associations.
The Cardiac Risk Report, which will contain genetic information found in the genome regarding cardiac diseases or a risk of cardiovascular diseases that can help with the care of the patient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>&quot;Standard of Care&quot; + Whole Genome Sequencing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Comparator:   &quot;Standard of Care&quot; Only</intervention_name>
    <description>Doctors and their patients will receive a Family History report only</description>
    <arm_group_label>&quot;Standard of Care&quot; Only</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Primary Care

          -  Generally healthy (as defined by the primary care provider) adult patients at Brigham
             and Women's Hospital ages 40-65. All patients must be fluent in English.

        Cardiology

          -  Patients in the Partners Healthcare System who are 18 years or older with a diagnosis
             of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (HCM) and a family history of HCM who previously had
             or who are candidates for targeted HCM genetic testing through routine clinical
             practice within Partners. All patients must be fluent in English.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Primary Care

          -  Patients who do not meet the above criteria. Patients with cardiac disease or a
             progressive debilitating illness. Patients who are pregnant or patients whose
             spouses/significant others are pregnant. Patients with untreated clinical anxiety or
             depression (as measured by a Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) score &gt; 11
             administered at the baseline study visit.)

        Cardiology

          -  Patients who do not meet the above criteria. Patients with a progressive debilitating
             illness. Patients who are pregnant or patients whose spouses/significant others are
             pregnant. Patients with untreated clinical anxiety or depression (as measured by a
             Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) score &gt; 11 administered at the baseline
             study visit.)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert C Green, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham and Women's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.genome.gov/</url>
    <description>NHGRI</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Biesecker LG. Opportunities and challenges for the integration of massively parallel genomic sequencing into clinical practice: lessons from the ClinSeq project. Genet Med. 2012 Apr;14(4):393-8. doi: 10.1038/gim.2011.78. Epub 2012 Feb 16.</citation>
    <PMID>22344227</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Green ED, Guyer MS; National Human Genome Research Institute. Charting a course for genomic medicine from base pairs to bedside. Nature. 2011 Feb 10;470(7333):204-13. doi: 10.1038/nature09764.</citation>
    <PMID>21307933</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kohane IS, Masys DR, Altman RB. The incidentalome: a threat to genomic medicine. JAMA. 2006 Jul 12;296(2):212-5. Erratum in: JAMA. 2006 Sep 27;296(12):1466.</citation>
    <PMID>16835427</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khoury MJ, Berg A, Coates R, Evans J, Teutsch SM, Bradley LA. The evidence dilemma in genomic medicine. Health Aff (Millwood). 2008 Nov-Dec;27(6):1600-11.</citation>
    <PMID>18997217</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Varmus H. Ten years on--the human genome and medicine. N Engl J Med. 2010 May 27;362(21):2028-9. doi: 10.1056/NEJMe0911933.</citation>
    <PMID>20505183</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Evans JP, Meslin EM, Marteau TM, Caulfield T. Genomics. Deflating the genomic bubble. Science. 2011 Feb 18;331(6019):861-2. doi: 10.1126/science.1198039.</citation>
    <PMID>21330519</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hall MA, Camacho F, Lawlor JS, Depuy V, Sugarman J, Weinfurt K. Measuring trust in medical researchers. Med Care. 2006 Nov;44(11):1048-53.</citation>
    <PMID>17063137</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaphingst KA, Facio FM, Cheng MR, Brooks S, Eidem H, Linn A, Biesecker BB, Biesecker LG. Effects of informed consent for individual genome sequencing on relevant knowledge. Clin Genet. 2012 Nov;82(5):408-15. doi: 10.1111/j.1399-0004.2012.01909.x. Epub 2012 Aug 7.</citation>
    <PMID>22694298</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carleton RN, Norton MA, Asmundson GJ. Fearing the unknown: a short version of the Intolerance of Uncertainty Scale. J Anxiety Disord. 2007;21(1):105-17. Epub 2006 May 2.</citation>
    <PMID>16647833</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lipkus IM. Numeric, verbal, and visual formats of conveying health risks: suggested best practices and future recommendations. Med Decis Making. 2007 Sep-Oct;27(5):696-713. Epub 2007 Sep 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17873259</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fagerlin A, Zikmund-Fisher BJ, Ubel PA, Jankovic A, Derry HA, Smith DM. Measuring numeracy without a math test: development of the Subjective Numeracy Scale. Med Decis Making. 2007 Sep-Oct;27(5):672-80. Epub 2007 Jul 19.</citation>
    <PMID>17641137</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roter D, Larson S. The Roter interaction analysis system (RIAS): utility and flexibility for analysis of medical interactions. Patient Educ Couns. 2002 Apr;46(4):243-51.</citation>
    <PMID>11932123</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brehaut JC, O'Connor AM, Wood TJ, Hack TF, Siminoff L, Gordon E, Feldman-Stewart D. Validation of a decision regret scale. Med Decis Making. 2003 Jul-Aug;23(4):281-92.</citation>
    <PMID>12926578</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 28, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 17, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Robert C. Green, MD, MPH</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator, The MedSeq Project</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Primary Care</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiology</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypertrophic Cardiomyopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Whole Genome Sequencing</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathy, Hypertrophic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
