<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="116109">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02057068</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>E7249-W</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02057068</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Improving Sleep in Veterans and Their CGs</brief_title>
  <acronym>SLEEP-E Dyads</acronym>
  <official_title>Improving Sleep In Veterans and Their Family Caregivers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study addresses the neglected topic of sleep disturbance in older caregiving dyads-a
      topic that has important implications for the safety, health, functioning and quality of
      life of older Veterans living at home and being cared for by a family caregiver (CG). The
      purpose of the first phase of this study is determine the relationship between CG and care
      recipient (CR) sleep and describe the impact of dyadic sleep to daytime functioning and
      well-being for Veterans and their caregivers. The information from phase 1 will inform the
      next study phase in which we develop and field test non-pharmacological, technology based,
      cognitive behavior therapy and compassion meditation interventions  to improve sleep in
      Veteran caregiving dyads.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective:  The primary objective of this study to develop and field test
      non-pharmacological, technology based, psycho-educational, cognitive behavior therapy and
      compassion meditation interventions to improve sleep in Veteran/caregiver dyads.

      Research Plan: The specific objectives will be accomplished through the execution of a three
      phase strategy: 1) an evaluation phase, 2) a development and preliminary intervention field
      testing phase, and 3) an intervention refinement, revision and re-testing phase.  All
      studies will use samples of Veteran care receivers (CR s) over the age of 60 who require
      assistance from a spousal or cohabitating caregiver (CG).  A sub-study will include the same
      collection of data, however using non-Veteran care receivers (CR) over the age of 60 who
      require assistance from a spousal or cohabitating caregiver (CG).

      Study 1 is a cross-sectional study which focuses on the Sleep Evaluation of 124 CG/CR Dyads.
       In SLEEP-E Dyads 1 actigraphy will be used to objectively and contemporaneously measure
      dyadic sleep.   Daily journals will be used to collect CG/CR self-reported sleep quality,
      daytime mood and behavior and to identify the nature and types of sleep disturbance.
      Electronic Tablets (E-Tabs) will be introduced, evaluated and validated with half the dyads.
       Pre and post journal video greetings will be tested and evaluated during this phase. Data
      from SLEEP-E Dyads 1 will be analyzed and inform the developmental tasks and activities for
      the next phase of the study. An additional sub-sample of caregiving dyads (non-Veterans)
      will be recruited to implement the same study design and to compare data to Veteran
      caregiving dyad data.

      The focus of SLEEP-E Dyads 2 is on Sleep Enhancement for CG/CR Dyads. This phase involves
      the adaptation, implementation and field testing of interventions with proven efficacy in
      other populations for use with Veteran dyads and the development of new interventions using
      selected components from evidence based sleep interventions. The intervention will be tested
      on 12 dyads stratified by dementia status. The tele-health device will be used to collect
      daily diary information during this phase and to deliver the sleep hygiene educational and
      cognitive behavior therapy components of the intervention.

      In SLEEP-E Dyads 3 feedback from the CGs regarding the acceptability of the intervention
      will be processed and analyzed in addition to preliminary outcome data. The intervention
      will be refined accordingly and the revised intervention will be tested with 44 dyads
      stratified by dementia status.

      Methods: All study phases involve comprehensive assessments of sleep and daytime
      functioning, mood and behavior using standardized validated instruments in addition to
      subjective data from the dyad as well as objective sleep evaluations with contemporaneous
      wrist actigraphy measured over seven days.

      Clinical Relevance:  This study addresses the neglected topic of sleep disturbance in older
      caregiving dyads-a topic that has important implications for the safety, health, functioning
      and QOL of older Veterans living at home and being cared for by a family caregiver. Because
      of the inter-related, bi-directional nature of sleep to stress, burden and depression, the
      most efficacious interventions should be ones which consider risk factors as they relate to
      the sleep of both members of a dyad. Yet, this study is the first to attempt to elucidate
      the dynamic relationship between CG and care recipient sleep and the impact of dyadic sleep
      to daytime functioning and well-being with Veterans and their caregivers.

      These activities will lead to the implementation and evaluation of a definitive randomized
      clinical trial for CG/CR dyads and make a significant and important contribution to
      complement the emergent program of caregiver research in the VA devoted to improving quality
      of life for Veterans and their families.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep Efficiency</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6 of 6 Week Intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Objective measures of sleep efficiency the wrist actigraphs</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective Sleep</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6 of 6 Week Intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subjective sleep quality from daily journals</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Daytime Mood</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6 of 6 week intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>daily measures of mood from journal</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep Hygiene Behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 5 and 6 of 6 Week Intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Daily sleep hygiene behaviors from e- journals composite of sleep hygiene indicators</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention Adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>Daily for 6 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participation in daily sessions; daily journals - modules viewed</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">260</enrollment>
  <condition>Sleep Quality</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>SLEEP-E Dyads Sleep Hygiene and Cognitively Based Compassion Training Intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>During the intervention period there is no data collection or contact with research staff other than for scheduling outcomes visits.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SLEEP-E Dyads Sleep Hygiene and Cognitively Based Compassion Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Adaptive prescriptions for the individualized components of the sleep intervention will be written for each dyad based upon dyad-specific risk factors, sources of sleep disturbance, nature of sleep problems and baseline sleep hygiene practices. In addition to the adaptive prescriptions, each dyad will receive a core intervention component consisting of a sleep hygiene psycho-education curriculum and compassion meditation training delivered by the E-Tablets.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Veterans 60 who require assistance from the identified caregiver with more than one
             Activity of Daily Living or three or more Instrumental Activity of Daily Living,

          -  have a life expectancy of greater than or equal to six (6) months,

          -  have no plans for transitioning out of home or into hospice in the next six months,

          -  and have approval from the primary care provider to participate in the research.

          -  Caregivers must live with the Veteran, provide care four (4) or more days out of the
             week for at least 6 months,

          -  and obtain a negative mini-cog assessment.  Caregivers can be any relation (spouse,
             child, sibling, friend, etc.) to the Veteran so long as the two are co-habitating.

          -  Caregiver can be any age.

          -  Approval for participation by PCP

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Parkinson's with tremor or other movement disorder that would invalidate actigraphy

          -  Untreated diagnosis of sleep apnea or restless leg syndrome

          -  Inability to tolerate actigraphy

          -  CG and CR sleep efficiency &gt; 85% and/or both members of dyad report sleeping well

          -  Caregivers must have a negative screen with the Mini-Cog to demonstrate cognitive
             capacity to provide informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patricia C Griffiths, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Atlanta VA Medical and Rehab Center, Decatur, GA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Patricia C Griffiths, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(404) 321-6111</phone>
    <phone_ext>7138</phone_ext>
    <email>pcgriff@emory.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Christine A Towler, MS</last_name>
    <phone>(404) 321-6111</phone>
    <phone_ext>7093</phone_ext>
    <email>christine.towler@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Atlanta VA Medical and Rehab Center, Decatur, GA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Decatur</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Patricia C Griffiths, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>404-321-6111</phone>
      <phone_ext>7138</phone_ext>
      <email>pcgriff@emory.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Christine A Towler, MS</last_name>
      <phone>(404) 321-6111</phone>
      <phone_ext>7093</phone_ext>
      <email>christine.towler@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Patricia C Griffiths, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 24, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Caregivers</keyword>
  <keyword>Telemedicine</keyword>
  <keyword>Sleep Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Compassion Meditation</keyword>
  <keyword>Dementia</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Meditation</keyword>
  <keyword>Technology</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
