<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="55282">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01841632</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MISOT-I</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2009-017795-25</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01841632</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety Study of Multipotent Progenitor Cells for Immunomodulation Therapy After Liver Transplantation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Safety and Feasibility of Multipotent Adult Progenitor Cells for Immunomodulation Therapy After Liver Transplantation: A Phase I Study of the MiSOT Study Consortium</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Prof. Dr. Marc-H. Dahlke, Ph. D.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital Regensburg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Athersys, Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Regensburg</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Paul-Ehrlich-Institut</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      MultiStem ® is a new biological product, manufactured from human stem cells obtained from
      adult bone marrow. Factors expressed by MultiStem cells are believed to regulate immune
      system function and augment tissue repair.

      Standard of care pharmacological immunosuppression after liver transplantation can achieve
      reasonable survival of liver grafts and patients. The side effects of this treatment,
      however, are clinically significant and diminish the overall success of organ
      transplantation as a curative therapy. It is therefore the objective of this study to
      implement cellular immunomodulation therapy with MultiStem as an adjunct to standard
      pharmacological immunosuppression with the ultimate goal of significantly reducing
      drug-based immunosuppression.

      As this is the first study with MultiStem in this subject population it has been designed as
      a safety and feasibility trial. However, first evidence of a potential benefit for this
      patient population will be explored cautiously.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Infusional and acute toxicity, using toxicity scoring mechanism</measure>
    <time_frame>up to day 30 (+10)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>For the description of intraportal toxicity a doppler ultrasound examination will be performed to assess various parameters that describe velocity of flow and flow pattern.
For pulmonary toxicity the assessment begins with an arterial blood gas. If this reveals pathological findings, a chest X-ray is required for clinical reasons independent of the study enrolment. In addition, clinical data describing the need for postoperative re-intubation will be recorded and the patient is assessed for the occurrence of a pulmonary embolism according to clinical guidelines.
For systemic toxicity, the occurrence of anaphylactic shock due to standard clinical guidelines is recorded.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first biopsy-proven acute rejection</measure>
    <time_frame>up to day 90 (+/-30)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Per protocol biopsies will be performed on days 1, 4, 10. Additional biopsies will be taken whenever clinically necessary.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evidence confirming that MultiStem does not promote malignant transformation or tumor growth</measure>
    <time_frame>up to day 365 (+/-30)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Four additional outpatient visits are planned to further evaluate the study patients (including screening for malignancies).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of data from routine examinations following last study visit for evidence of long term safety from MultiStem administration</measure>
    <time_frame>up to six years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The results of routine examinations, which are necessary for all transplant patients, will be used once a year and analyzed retrospectively.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Liver Transplantation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MultiStem</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose escalation
Cohort 1
Drug: MultiStem, Dose 1 of MultiStem; Route and time: Two infusions; First: intra portal at liver transplantation (day 1), second:  intra venous (day 3)
Cohort 2
Drug: MultiStem, Dose 2 of MultiStem; Route and time: Two infusions; First: intra portal at liver transplantation (day 1), second:  intra venous (day 3)
Cohort 3
Drug: MultiStem, Dose 3 of MultiStem; Route and time: Two infusions; First: intra portal at liver transplantation (day 1), second:  intra venous (day 3)
Cohort 4
Drug: MultiStem, Dose 4 of MultiStem; Route and time: Two infusions; First: intra portal at liver transplantation (day 1), second:  intra venous (day 3)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MultiStem</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>MultiStem</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients ≥18 years of age undergoing allogeneic liver transplantation

          -  Absence of any familial, sociological or geographical condition potentially hampering
             compliance with the study protocol and follow-up schedule

          -  Written informed consent prior to any study procedures

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known allergies to bovine or porcine products or any other ingredients of the product

          -  Patients older than 65 years of age

          -  Patients listed in a high-urgency status that would not allow proper preparation of
             the study interventions

          -  Patients receiving a secondary liver graft (Re-Transplantation)

          -  Double organ transplant recipients

          -  Pre-existing renal failure that requires or has required hemodialysis within the last
             year

          -  Pulmonary function: FEV1, FVC, DLCO ≤50% predicted

          -  Cardiac function: left ventricular ejection fraction ≤50%

          -  HIV seropositive, varicella virus active infection or any other clinically relevant
             infection

          -  History of any malignancy (including lymphoproliferative disease and hepatocellular
             carcinoma) except for squamous or basal cell carcinoma of the skin that has been
             treated with no evidence of recurrence

          -  Unstable myocardium (evolving myocardial infarction), cardiogenic shock

          -  Females of childbearing potential (hormonal status and gynecological consultation
             required)

          -  Patients with portal vein thrombosis

          -  Patients with a history of pulmonary embolism
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marc H Dahlke, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>0049 941 944 0</phone>
    <email>Marc.Dahlke@ukr.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Surgery, University Hospital Regensburg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Regensburg</city>
        <state>Bavaria</state>
        <zip>93053</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marc H Dahlke, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>00499419440</phone>
      <email>Marc.Dahlke@ukr.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marc H Dahlke, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.misot.eu</url>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Popp FC, Fillenberg B, Eggenhofer E, Renner P, Dillmann J, Benseler V, Schnitzbauer AA, Hutchinson J, Deans R, Ladenheim D, Graveen CA, Zeman F, Koller M, Hoogduijn MJ, Geissler EK, Schlitt HJ, Dahlke MH. Safety and feasibility of third-party multipotent adult progenitor cells for immunomodulation therapy after liver transplantation--a phase I study (MISOT-I). J Transl Med. 2011 Jul 28;9:124. doi: 10.1186/1479-5876-9-124.</citation>
    <PMID>21798013</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dillmann J, Popp FC, Fillenberg B, Zeman F, Eggenhofer E, Farkas S, Scherer MN, Koller M, Geissler EK, Deans R, Ladenheim D, Loss M, Schlitt HJ, Dahlke MH. Treatment-emergent adverse events after infusion of adherent stem cells: the MiSOT-I score for solid organ transplantation. Trials. 2012 Nov 15;13:211. doi: 10.1186/1745-6215-13-211.</citation>
    <PMID>23151227</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 19, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospital Regensburg</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Prof. Dr. Marc-H. Dahlke, Ph. D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Sponsor-Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Liver transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>Allogeneic liver transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>Solid organ transplantation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
