<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="6378">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01686503</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Doris Duke CF-2012061</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01686503</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intradermal Versus Intramuscular Polio Vaccine Booster in HIV-Infected Subjects</brief_title>
  <acronym>IDIPV</acronym>
  <official_title>Comparison of the Immunogenicity of Various Inactivated Polio Vaccine Booster Doses by Intradermal vs. Intramuscular Routes in HIV-Infected Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eastern Virginia Medical School</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>NanoPass Technologies Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eastern Virginia Medical School</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether a lower dose of inactivated polio vaccine
      (IPV) injected into the skin (intradermal administration) can work equally well or better
      than the standard dose injected into the muscle (intramuscular administration).  There are
      more immune cells in the skin than in the muscle, and other vaccines have been shown to
      require a lower dose when administered intradermally.  The study is being done in
      participants infected with HIV because HIV-infected people are known to respond less well to
      vaccines than other groups, so it is particularly important to know if IPV might work better
      in HIV-infected people if administered intradermally.

      If it is possible to lower the dose of IPV by intradermal administration, this would make
      inactivated polio vaccine more affordable in the developing countries where it is most
      needed
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Oral polio vaccine (OPV) will not be sufficient to eradicate polio.  OPV has failed to
      provide adequate polio immunity in certain immunocompromised populations, such as people
      with AIDS.  Also, OPV can mutate and form neurovirulent strains capable of causing polio
      outbreaks.  Inactivated polio vaccine (IPV), which cannot mutate into neurovirulent strains
      and which is more effective in populations that have failed to respond to OPV, will be
      needed globally to eradicate polio, but it is unaffordable for many developing countries.
      Because there are more immune cells in the skin than in the muscle, intradermal
      administration of IPV may be a way to increase the efficacy and reduce the dose (and thus
      the cost) of IPV.  We plan to conduct a clinical trial randomizing 231 HIV-infected adults
      to receive a booster of two-fifths dose intradermal IPV, one-fifth dose intradermal IPV,
      full dose intramuscular IPV, or two-fifths dose intramuscular IPV. We will measure polio
      immunity before and after vaccine administration.  Through this study, we will determine the
      optimal booster dose of intradermal IPV, whether intradermal works better than intramuscular
      IPV administration, and whether intradermal IPV is effective in an immunocompromised
      population.  The data from this trial could contribute to global polio eradication.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Increase in polio neutralizing antibody titers</measure>
    <time_frame>4-6 weeks after receiving the vaccine</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood will be drawn at baseline and 4-6 weeks after receiving the vaccine booster dose.  It will be spun down, and the serum frozen and stored at -80 degrees celsius.  After all the participants have completed the study, all of the serum will be tested for polio neutralizing antibody titers.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">231</enrollment>
  <condition>Polio Immunity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2/5 dose intradermal IPV</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this arm will receive 2/5 dose (0.2 mL) of inactivated polio vaccine (IPOL, Sanofi Pasteur) as a one-time dose intradermally using the NanoPass MicronJet 600 microneedle device</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1/5 dose intadermal IPV</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this study arm will receive 1/5 dose (0.1 mL) of inactivated polio vaccine (IPOL, Sanofi Pasteur) as a one time dose intradermally using the NanoPass MicronJet 600 microneedle device.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>full dose intramuscular IPV</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this study arm will receive the standard full dose (0.5 mL) of inactivated polio vaccine (IPOL, Sanofi Pasteur) as a one time dose intramuscularly.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2/5 dose intramuscular IPV</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this study arm will receive 2/5 dose (0.2 mL) inactivated polio vaccine (IPOL, Sanofi Pasteur) as a one time dose intramuscularly.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IPOL (Sanofi Pasteur) inactivated polio vaccine booster dose</intervention_name>
    <description>Depending on study arm, participants will receive 0.2 mL intradermally, 0.1 mL intradermally, 0.5 mL intramuscularly, or 0.2 mL intramuscularly.</description>
    <arm_group_label>2/5 dose intradermal IPV</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>1/5 dose intadermal IPV</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>full dose intramuscular IPV</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2/5 dose intramuscular IPV</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IPOL (Sanofi Pasteur)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  documented HIV infection

          -  age of at least 18 years old

          -  HIV viral load &lt;400 on the most recent test

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  current acute moderate to severe illness (demonstrated by fever over 100.4
             Fahrenheit, shortness of breath, altered mental status, or by judgment of the primary
             clinician)

          -  current pregnancy

          -  history of allergic reaction to a polio shot,

          -  history of a life-threatening allergic reaction to neomycin, streptomycin, or
             polymyxin B
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephanie B Troy, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Eastern Virginia Medical School</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>C3ID Clinic, Eastern Virginia Medical School</name>
      <address>
        <city>Norfolk</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23507</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 10, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 13, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Eastern Virginia Medical School</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Stephanie Troy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Poliomyelitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
