<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="13270">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01893307</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012-0825</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-01879</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01893307</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intensity-Modulated Proton Beam Therapy (IMPT) Versus Intensity-Modulated Photon Therapy (IMRT)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II/III Randomized Trial of Intensity-Modulated Proton Beam Therapy (IMPT) Versus Intensity-Modulated Photon Therapy (IMRT) for the Treatment of Oropharyngeal Cancer of the Head and Neck Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to compare the side effects of 2 radiation
      treatments for head and neck cancer.  The 2 treatments are intensity modulated photon
      therapy (IMRT) and intensity modulated proton therapy (IMPT).  Participants may also receive
      chemotherapy along with radiation therapy.

      IMPT is designed to use beams of proton particles to send radiation to the tumor.  IMRT is
      designed to use beams of photon therapy to send radiation to the tumor.  Both of these types
      of radiation treatment may give a full dose of radiation treatment to the tumor while not
      damaging as much of the healthy tissue around it.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Baseline Visit:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will have a baseline visit.
      The following tests and procedures will be performed:

        -  You will be asked about your diet and if you have had recent weight loss.

        -  You will have a hearing test.

        -  You will have a dental exam.

        -  Your swallowing function will be tested with a special type of x-ray called a modified
           barium swallow (MBS).  During the test, you will eat and drink foods and liquids mixed
           with a &quot;contrast&quot; chemical called barium that will make your throat more visible in the
           x-rays.  A special x-ray tube will be connected to a television screen to allow the
           doctor to watch the foods and liquids pass from your mouth and down your throat.  As
           part of this exam, each time you will fill out a questionnaire about swallowing that
           should take about 5 minutes to complete.  You will be asked to sign a separate consent
           form that describes the MBS procedure and its risks.

        -  You will fill out questionnaires about your quality of life, work status, medical
           history, smoking status, and any symptoms you may have.  Completing these
           questionnaires should take about 10-15 minutes.

      Study Groups:

      You will go through the standard radiation treatment planning procedure, called the marking
      session.  After the marking session, a standard IMRT plan and an IMPT plan will be made.  If
      the radiation doctor thinks that both the plans are acceptable, you will be randomly
      assigned (as a flip of a coin) to 1 of 2 study groups:

      If you are in Group 1, you will receive IMRT.

      If you are in Group 2, you will receive IMPT.

      Study Therapy Administration:

      You will receive radiation therapy 1 time each day, 5 days a week (Monday through Friday)
      for up to 33 treatments (about 6 ½ weeks).

      You will receive chemotherapy while you are receiving radiation therapy.  If this occurs,
      you will be asked to sign a separate consent form for these drugs with a full description of
      how they are given and the risks they may cause.  The drugs, schedule, and doses will be
      your doctor's decision.

      Study Visits:

      Every week while you are receiving radiation therapy:

        -  Any updates to your medical history will be recorded.

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your vital signs and weight.

        -  Your performance status will be recorded.

        -  Blood (about 1-2 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

        -  You will fill out the same questionnaires as before.

        -  At Week 6 only, photos of the inside of your mouth will be taken to check for mouth
           sores.

      Length of Treatment:

      You may continue receiving radiation therapy for up to 6 ½ weeks.  You will no longer be
      able to receive the study therapy if the disease gets worse, if intolerable side effects
      occur, or if you are unable to follow study directions.

      Your participation on the study will be over after the follow-up.

      You can decide to stop taking part in this study and the study doctor will tell you how to
      stop safely.  It is important to tell the study doctor if you are thinking about stopping so
      any side effects from the treatment can be looked at by your doctor.  Another reason to tell
      your doctor that you are thinking about stopping is to discuss what follow-up care and
      testing could be most helpful for you.

      End-of-Treatment Visit:

      After you finish radiation therapy:

        -  You will fill out the same questionnaires as before.

        -  You will have an MBS exam to test your swallowing function.

        -  You will have a dental exam.

      Follow-Up:

      At 10-12 weeks after finishing radiation therapy:

        -  You will fill out the same questionnaires as before.

        -  You will have a hearing test.

        -  You will have a dental exam.

        -  If the doctor thinks it is needed, you will have a CT scan and/or PET/CT scan to check
           the status of the disease.

      At 6, 12, and 24 months after you finish radiation therapy:

        -  You will have an MBS exam to test your swallowing function.

        -  You will fill out the same questionnaires as before.

      After you finish radiation therapy and during the 8-12 weeks while you are recovering from
      treatment, you will be called or emailed by an automated system.  This will be to remind you
      to fill out a web-based form that asks about any side effects you may have had.  You will
      fill out this form every 2 weeks during this time period.  Filling out the form should take
      about 10-15 minutes.

      Filling out these forms does not take the place of your regularly scheduled follow-up
      visits.  If you have side effects, you should also tell the study staff.

      If the doctor thinks it is needed during follow-up, you will have a tumor biopsy for tumor
      marker testing.

      This is an investigational study.  IMRT and IMPT are delivered using FDA-approved and
      commercially available methods.  Comparing them is investigational.

      Up to 360 participants will be enrolled in this study.  All will take part at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates and Severity of Late Grade 3-5 Toxicity Between Intensity-Modulated X-Ray Therapy (IMRT) and Intensity-Modulated Proton Beam Therapy (IMPT)</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days after radiation therapy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Primary outcome is the cumulative incidence of late onset grade 3+ toxicity anytime during the 2 years following completion of radiation therapy. Late onset toxicity occurs 90 days or more following completion of radiation therapy. Primary outcome assessed by a committee blinded to the treatment assignment for each patient.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">360</enrollment>
  <condition>Head And Neck Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intensity-Modulated X-Ray Therapy (IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Radiation therapy dosage 70 Gy (RBE) delivered 1 time each day, 5 days a week (Monday through Friday) for up to 33 treatments (about 6 ½ weeks).
Treating physician evaluate each patient for possible chemotherapy.
Modified barium swallow (MBS) performed at baseline, end of treatment visit, and at 6, 12, and 24 months after radiation therapy.
Questionnaires completed at baseline, each week while receiving radiation therapy, at end of treatment visit, at 10 - 12 weeks after radiation, and at 6, 12, and 24 months after radiation therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intensity-Modulated Proton Beam Therapy (IMPT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Radiation therapy dosage 70 Gy (RBE) delivered 1 time each day, 5 days a week (Monday through Friday) for up to 33 treatments (about 6 ½ weeks).
Treating physician evaluate each patient for possible chemotherapy.
Modified barium swallow (MBS) performed at baseline, end of treatment visit, and at 6, 12, and 24 months after radiation therapy.
Questionnaires completed at baseline, each week while receiving radiation therapy, at end of treatment visit, at 10 - 12 weeks after radiation, and at 6, 12, and 24 months after radiation therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intensity-Modulated X-Ray Therapy (IMRT)</intervention_name>
    <description>Radiation therapy dosage 70 Gy (RBE) delivered 1 time each day, 5 days a week (Monday through Friday) for up to 33 treatments (about 6 ½ weeks).
Treating physician evaluate each patient for possible chemotherapy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intensity-Modulated X-Ray Therapy (IMRT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intensity-Modulated Proton Beam Therapy (IMPT)</intervention_name>
    <description>Radiation therapy dosage 70 Gy (RBE) delivered 1 time each day, 5 days a week (Monday through Friday) for up to 33 treatments (about 6 ½ weeks).
Treating physician evaluate each patient for possible chemotherapy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intensity-Modulated Proton Beam Therapy (IMPT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Modified barium swallow (MBS)</intervention_name>
    <description>Modified barium swallow (MBS) performed at baseline, end of treatment visit, and at 6, 12, and 24 months after radiation therapy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intensity-Modulated X-Ray Therapy (IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intensity-Modulated Proton Beam Therapy (IMPT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaires</intervention_name>
    <description>Questionnaires completed at baseline, each week while receiving radiation therapy, at end of treatment visit, at 10 - 12 weeks after radiation, and at 6, 12, and 24 months after radiation therapy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intensity-Modulated X-Ray Therapy (IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intensity-Modulated Proton Beam Therapy (IMPT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Surveys</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age &gt;/= 18

          2. Histologically documented squamous cell carcinoma of the oropharynx (Stage III-IV
             A,B)

          3. Tumor tissue (primary or cervical metastasis) available for human papilloma virus
             (HPV) /p16 (in situ hybridization (ISH), immunohistochemistry (IHC) or genotyping
             testing)

          4. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance criteria = 0, 1, or 2

          5. Negative pregnancy test for women of child bearing potential

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Previous radiation treatment for head and neck mucosal primary cancers within the
             past 5 years (i.e. oropharynx, nasopharynx, hypopharynx, larynx, and oral cavity)

          2. Pregnant or breast-feeding females

          3. Clinically significant uncontrolled major cardiac, respiratory, renal, hepatic,
             gastrointestinal or hematologic disease but not limited to: a) Symptomatic congestive
             heart failure, unstable angina, or cardiac dysrrhythmia  not controlled by pacer
             device. b) No myocardial infarction within 3 months of registration.

          4. Distant Metastases (Stage IV C, any T, any N and M1)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven J. Frank, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Steven J. Frank, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-563-2300</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 15, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 2, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Head And Neck Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Oropharyngeal Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Squamous cell carcinoma of the oropharynx</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute and late toxicity</keyword>
  <keyword>Intensity modulated photon therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>IMRT</keyword>
  <keyword>Intensity modulated proton therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>IMPT</keyword>
  <keyword>Modified barium swallow</keyword>
  <keyword>MBS</keyword>
  <keyword>Questionnaires</keyword>
  <keyword>Surveys</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oropharyngeal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
