<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="109419">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02099864</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>10241</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2014-00417</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>10241</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA069533</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02099864</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Genetic and Molecular Mechanisms in Assessing Response in Patients With Prostate Cancer Receiving Enzalutamide Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Molecular Mechanisms Underlying Tumor Progression Despite Enzalutamide Treatment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This clinical trial studies genetic and molecular mechanisms in assessing response in
      patients with prostate cancer receiving enzalutamide therapy. Androgens can cause the growth
      of prostate cancer cells. Antihormone therapy, such as enzalutamide, may lessen the amount
      of androgens made by the body. Studying samples of tissue and blood in the laboratory from
      patients with prostate cancer may help doctors better understand hormone resistant prostate
      cancer. It may also help doctors make improvements in prostate cancer treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess the correlations between baseline molecular features and pathways and prostate
      specific antigen (PSA) change (&lt;/&gt;= 50% decline) at 12 weeks vs. baseline.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess the correlations between the baseline molecular features and pathways and
      progression-free survival, disease-specific survival, and overall survival.

      II. To assess the correlations between the baseline molecular features and pathways and time
      to PSA progression.

      III. To identify molecular features and cellular pathways present in tumors from men with
      metastatic castrate-resistant prostate cancer (CRPC) that are progressing despite
      Enzalutamide treatment.

      IV. To explore correlation between baseline molecular features and pathways and changes in
      circulating tumor cells (CTCs) counts.

      V. To explore correlation between baseline molecular features and pathways and objective
      response.

      VI. To assess the correlations between the baseline molecular features and pathways and
      degree of PSA decline at 12 weeks and maximal PSA decline observed while on study.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive enzalutamide orally (PO) once daily (QD) in the absence of disease
      progression.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 12 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Pharmacodynamics Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent PSA change</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The proportion of patients with or without a &gt;= 50% decline in PSA values will be reported with 95% exact confidence interval. Simple Logistic regression model will be used to evaluate the association between PSA response and each of the potential molecular biomarker predictors, including (gene expression signatures, copy number alterations, mutations, IPLs (integrated pathway levels and immunohistochemistry [IHC] measurements).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from day 1 of study drug treatment to date of first documented radiographic progression or clinical progression, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Correlations between baseline molecular features and pathways and progression-free survival will be assessed using cox regression model. In addition, Kaplan-Meier plots will be used to graphically illustrate the survival distributions across the strata of categorical molecular predictors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-specific survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from day 1 of study drug treatment to date of death from prostate cancer, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Correlations between baseline molecular features and pathways and disease-free survival will be assessed using cox regression model. In addition, Kaplan-Meier plots will be used to graphically illustrate the survival distributions across the strata of categorical molecular predictors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from day 1 of study drug treatment to date of death from any cause, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Correlations between baseline molecular features and pathways and overall survival will be assessed using cox regression model. In addition, Kaplan-Meier plots will be used to graphically illustrate the survival distributions across the strata of categorical molecular predictors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to PSA progression</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Correlations between baseline molecular features and pathways and time to PSA progression will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Molecular features and cellular pathways present in tumors that are progressing despite treatment with enzalutamide</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Random Forests classification will be used to identify molecular features and pathways present in patients with disease progression or who discontinue Enzalutamide treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in CTC counts</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Correlations between baseline molecular features and pathways and changes in CTC will be assessed. Linear regression model will be used to assess the association for changes in CTC counts from baseline and maximal PSA observed while on study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response defined using the new international criteria proposed by the RECIST version 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Logistic regression model will be used to assess the association between molecular predictors and response rate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Degree of PSA decline</measure>
    <time_frame>At 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Correlations between baseline molecular features and pathways and degree of PSA decline will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximal PSA decline observed</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Correlations between baseline molecular features and pathways and maximal PSA decline observed will be assessed. Linear regression model will be used to assess the association for changes in CTC counts from baseline and maximal PSA observed while on study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">46</enrollment>
  <condition>Adenocarcinoma of the Prostate</condition>
  <condition>Hormone-resistant Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Basic science (enzalutamide)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive enzalutamide PO QD in the absence of disease progression.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>enzalutamide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Basic science (enzalutamide)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MDV3100</other_name>
    <other_name>selective androgen receptor modulator MDV3100</other_name>
    <other_name>XTANDI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Basic science (enzalutamide)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically or cytologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of the prostate without
             neuroendocrine differentiation or small cell features

          -  Ongoing androgen deprivation therapy with a gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH)
             analogue or orchiectomy (i.e., surgical or medical castration); for patients who have
             not had an orchiectomy, there must be a plan to maintain effective GnRH-analogue
             therapy for the duration of the trial

          -  Radiographic evidence of regional or distant metastases with suspected tumor in an
             area that is safe to biopsy

          -  Willingness to undergo a tumor biopsy at baseline and at disease progression

          -  Serum testosterone level &lt; 50 ng/dL at the screening visit

          -  Progressive disease by PSA or imaging in the setting of medical or surgical
             castration; disease progression for study entry is defined as one or more of the
             following three criteria:

               -  PSA progression defined by a minimum of three rising PSA levels with an interval
                  of &gt;= 1 week between each determination; the PSA value at the screening visit
                  should be &gt;= 2 µg/L (2 ng/ml) if PSA is the only criterion for progression

               -  Soft tissue disease progression defined by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid
                  Tumors (RECIST) 1.1

               -  Bone disease progression defined by two or more new lesions on bone scan

          -  Patient's physician has already recommended enzalutamide for treatment of progression

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0-2

          -  Willing and able to give informed consent

          -  Estimated life expectancy &gt;= 6 months

          -  Subjects who have partners of childbearing potential must be willing to use a method
             of birth control with adequate barrier protection as determined to be acceptable by
             the principal investigator and sponsor during the study and for 1 week after last
             study drug administration

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Severe, concurrent disease, infection, or co-morbidity that, in the judgment of the
             investigator, would make the patient inappropriate for enrollment

          -  Previous treatment with docetaxel for metastatic prostate cancer

          -  Metastases in the brain or active epidural disease (NOTE: patients with treated
             epidural disease are allowed)

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &lt; 1,000/μL

          -  Platelet count &lt; 75,000/μL

          -  Hemoglobin &lt; 9 g/dL at the screening visit; (NOTE: subject may not have received any
             growth factors or blood transfusions within seven days of the hematologic laboratory
             values obtained at the screening visit)

          -  Total bilirubin (TBL) &gt; 2.5 times the upper limit of normal at the screening visit

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &gt; 2.5 times the
             upper limit of normal at the screening visit

          -  Creatinine (Cr) &gt; 2 mg/dL at the screening visit

          -  Prothrombin time (PT) or international normalized ratio (INR) and a partial
             thromboplastin time (PTT) &gt; 1.5 times the upper limit of normal

          -  Previous treatment with an agent that blocks androgen synthesis (e.g. abiraterone
             acetate, TAK-700) or blocks the androgen receptor (e.g., BMS 641988, ARN-509)

          -  Systemic corticosteroids (used in the management of cancer or non-cancer-related
             illnesses)

          -  Structurally unstable bone lesions suggesting impending fracture

          -  Previous treatment with Enzalutamide (MDV3100)

          -  Medical contraindications to stopping aspirin, Coumadin or other anticoagulants for 1
             week prior to image-guided tumor biopsies

          -  Plans to initiate treatment with an investigational agent during the study

          -  History of seizure or condition that may predispose to seizure; also, history of loss
             of consciousness or transient ischemic attack within 12 months of enrollment (day 1
             visit)

          -  Medications that may lower seizure threshold

          -  Concomitant use of strong cytochrome P450, family 2, subfamily C, polypeptide 8
             (CYP2C8) inhibitors (e.g. gemfibrozil)

          -  History of known malabsorption syndrome or prior surgery(ies) that may lead to
             malabsorption
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joshi Alumkal</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California at San Francisco - Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94143-0875</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eric J. Small</last_name>
      <phone>415-353-9865</phone>
      <email>esmall@medicine.ucsf.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eric J. Small</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joshi J. Alumkal</last_name>
      <phone>503-494-1091</phone>
      <email>alumkalj@ohsu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joshi J. Alumkal</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 26, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 26, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
