<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="79024">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02020746</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MW 2013-07-10</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02020746</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety Study of EscharEx to Treat (Debride) Hard to Heal Wounds</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multicenter, Prospective, Randomized, Vehicle Controlled, Blinded Study Performed in Subjects With Hard to Heal Wounds, to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Enzymatic Debridement With EscharEx</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>MediWound Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>MediWound Ltd</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Israel : Ministry of Health (MOH)</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main objective of this study is to assess the safety and the efficacy of EscharEx in
      preparing the wound's bed in patients with hard to heal venous leg ulcers, diabetic lower
      extremity ulcers and traumatic/post operative wounds.

      This study will be a multi-center, blinded, randomized, controlled study intended to
      demonstrate superiority of EscharEx debriding treatment over the Gel Vehicle control
      treatment in patients with hard to heal wounds.

      72 adults with &gt;50% necrotic/slough/fibrin non-viable tissue on a hard to heal wound (venous
      leg ulcer, diabetic lower extremity ulcer or traumatic/ post operative wound) between 5 cm2
      and 100 cm2 (surface area), will be enrolled into the study.

      Patients will undergo a 1 week screening period (2 visits) which will include: record of
      demographics, medical history and concomitant medications, vital signs, physical
      examination, clinical laboratory tests, wound photography and assessments and questionnaires
      (wound status and quality of life). During this period wounds will be cleansed with normal
      saline and the wound will be dressed with moist-to-moist saline gauze. During this screening
      period, subjects whose study wound size (surface area) decreases by a stated amount (i.e. &gt;
      20 percent) will be excluded. Following completion of the screening process, eligible
      patients will be randomized to either EscharEx or Gel vehicle debridement treatments.
      Treatment will be performed once daily up to 10 applications (up to 10 visits) or until
      complete debridement is achieved, whichever occurs first. The duration of each application
      is 4 hours.  Following each application the wound will be washed photographed and assessed
      for wound size, removal of nonviable tissue and change in granulation tissue (by digital
      planimetry software), wound status, and safety parameters.  Subsequent to each debridement
      treatment the wound will be dressed with moist-to-moist saline gauze.  Following completion
      of the debridement treatment period, patients will be treated according to standard
      procedures and evaluated (wound assessments) once a week until complete wound closure for up
      to 12 weeks from last application (up to 12 visits).  For patients who achieved wound
      closure, additional 3 months (3 visits) follow up of wound closure recurrence will be
      conducted. Quality of life (QoL) will be evaluated at the last wound closure follow-up visit
      and 3 months post wound closure follow-up period (for all patients).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of complete debridement (non-viable tissue removal) at the end of Incidence of complete debridement (non-viable tissue removal)</measure>
    <time_frame>10 treatment days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of complete wound closure</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks post debridement</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Hard to Heal Wounds</condition>
  <condition>Venous Leg Ulcers</condition>
  <condition>Diabetic Lower Extremity Ulcers</condition>
  <condition>Traumatic/ Post Operative Wounds</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EscharEx</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Enzymatic debridement</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gel Vehicle</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control arm</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EscharEx</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>EscharEx</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gel Vehicle</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Gel Vehicle</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  Inclusion Criteria

          -  Patients, men or women, are between 18 and 90 years of age.

          -  Patient with venous leg ulcer or diabetic (lower extremity) ulcer or traumatic/post
             operative wound (determined by medical history and physical examination)

          -  Wound is not healing for at least 4 weeks

          -  The necrotic/slough/fibrin non-viable tissue area is at least 50% of wound area
             (assessed by clinical evaluation)

          -  Wound surface area (length X width) is in the range of  5 - 100 cm2 (assessed by
             Acetate tracing)

          -  Patient understands the nature of the procedure, able to adhere to the protocol
             regimen, and provides written informed consent prior to any study procedure

          -  The Wound is classified as  a wound involving full skin thickness but not underlying
             tissue or deeper wound penetrating to cavities, bone, or joint capsule

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Evidence of active osteomyelitis of target organ,

          -  Patients with more than one hard to heal wounds with an area greater than or equal to
             2cm2,

          -  Presence of purulent discharge, deep-tissue abscess, cellulitis extending &gt;2 cm
             around the wound, gangrene or signs of systemic infection,

          -  Wound size decreased by &gt; 20% after 1 week of standard-of-care-only period (screening
             period), (assessed by Acetate tracing)

          -  Patients with pre-enrolment wounds which are covered by eschar heavily saturated with
             iodine or by Silver sulfadiazine (SSD) pseudoeschar (e.g. pseudoeschar as a result of
             SSD treatment),

          -  Ankle-Brachial Index (ABI) ≤ 0.8

          -  Wound has sinus tracts or tunnels extending under healthy tissue,

          -  Patients undergoing renal or peritoneal dialysis,

          -  Recent history (less than 4 weeks) of myocardial infarction (MI) or concurrent acute
             injury or disease that might compromise the patient's welfare,

          -  Any condition that would preclude safe participation in the study: evidence of
             significant hematological (severe pre-existing coagulation disorder), cardiovascular,
             liver or neoplastic disease, or any other immediate life threatening condition,

          -  Patient is currently receiving, or has received at any time within one month prior to
             enrollment, any medications or treatments known to affect the wound healing
             processes; these include: chronic systemic steroid intake with topical skin changes
             (thin, fragile with multiple hematomas and previous laceration history,
             immuno-suppressive drugs, radiation therapy and chemotherapy.

          -  History of allergy or atopic disease or a known sensitivity to pineapples, papaya,
             bromelain or papain,

          -  Pregnant women (positive pregnancy test) or nursing mothers,

          -  Participation in another investigational drug trial within 30 days prior to
             enrollment or anticipated participation while enrolled in the study,

          -  Concurrent use of non-approved drugs or alcohol abuse.

          -  Patients with poor nutritional status (albumin &lt; 2.5g/dl), poor diabetic control
             (HbA1c &gt; 12%), anemia (hemoglobin&lt;9 g/dL), a leukocyte counts &lt; 4,000// μl or
             &gt;15000/μl, abnormal liver function (AST, ALT&gt;2 x upper limit of normal range), renal
             failure (Cr &gt; 3 mg/dl);

          -  Mentally incapacitated adults who are incapable of giving legal consent (e.g.
             dementia, psychiatric patients, etc),

          -  Patients with general skin disorders (Psoriasis, Panniculitis, ect) that might
             deteriorate as a result of local trauma.

          -  Patients with skin disorders unrelated to the wound that are presented adjacent to
             the wound

          -  Clinical suspicion of skin cancer associated with the wound (e.g, BCC, SCC), which
             was not ruled out by biopsy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Limor Dinur-Klein, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>972543301324</phone>
    <email>limord@mediwound.co.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Efrat Hazan</last_name>
    <phone>972523878830</phone>
    <email>efrath@mediwound.co.il</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rambam hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Haifa</city>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yehuda Ullman, MD</last_name>
      <email>yullmann@rambam.health.gov.il</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Leonid Kogan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 1, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 19, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Leg Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Varicose Ulcer</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
