<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="33438">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01874119</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Merck-MISP-50440</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01874119</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fosaprepitant for Nausea and Vomiting During High-dose Interleukin-2 (HD IL-2) for Metastatic Melanoma and Renal Cell Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <acronym>HD IL-2/Emend</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase 2B Double-blind Placebo-controlled Crossover Study Evaluating the Efficacy of Intravenous Fosaprepitant for Chemotherapy-induced Nausea and Vomiting (CINV) Associated With High-dose Interleukin-2 (HD IL-2) for Metastatic Melanoma and Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Louis University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Louis University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate the effectiveness of intravenous fosaprepitant
      therapy to reduce nausea and vomiting during the treatment of high dose interleukin-2 (HD
      IL-2) therapy for metastatic melanoma or metastatic renal cell carcinoma.  Fosaprepitant is
      an intravenous (IV) medication that is FDA- approved for use in adults for the prevention of
      nausea and vomiting during chemotherapy.  Fosaprepitant works by blocking the neurokinin-1
      receptor, which is a receptor in the brain that is known to cause nausea and vomiting.  Past
      studies estimate that up to 70% of patients undergoing treatment with HD IL-2 will have
      nausea and/or vomiting.  While fosaprepitant has been used in clinical practice to treat
      nausea and vomiting during HD IL-2, there have not been any studies done to see how well it
      works.  All patients will receive treatment (IV fosaprepitant) during the study during
      either the first or second hospital admission for HD IL-2.  On the admission that the
      subject is not receiving IV fosaprepitant, the subject will receive placebo (a medicine that
      looks like fosaprepitant, but is not active).  The study is double-blinded, which means
      neither the subject, nor the study doctor will know to which group you have been assigned to
      that admission (IV fosaprepitant or placebo).  This study design was chosen to limit the
      potential for bias, which means the trial was designed to try to ensure that unknown factors
      do not affect trial results.  When patients start the study, patients will be randomly
      assigned to one of two groups: those who receive treatment (IV fosaprepitant) first and
      those who receive placebo first.  During the first admission, subjects will be given the IV
      fosaprepitant or IV placebo during admission.  During the second admission, subjects will
      'crossover' and receive the other treatment that they did not receive during the first
      admission.  Improvement in nausea and vomiting will be assessed by counting the number of
      nausea and vomiting episodes, recording if the subject needs additional medication for
      nausea and vomiting, and by using patient questionnaires.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 2B double-blind placebo-controlled crossover study evaluating the efficacy
      of intravenous fosaprepitant for chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in patients
      undergoing high-dose interleukin-2 (HD IL-2)  therapy (720,000 IU/kg per dose intravenously;
      14 doses, 2 cycles per course) for metastatic melanoma and metastatic renal cell carcinoma.
      A total of 22 subjects will be enrolled in the study.  On study entry, patients will be
      randomized to receive either IV fosaprepitant (150 mg on Day 1, Day 3, or Day 5) or matched
      placebo during first admission of HD IL-2 therapy (cycle 1).  All subjects will crossover
      and receive the opposite treatment during cycle 2.  All patients will receive ondansetron 24
      mg by mouth daily per standard protocol every 24 hours during Days 1-5 of admission starting
      30 minutes prior to first dose of HD IL-2. During the treatment phase, subjects will receive
      Patients will receive IV fosaprepitant 30 minutes before first dose of HD IL-2 therapy and
      every 48 hours until completion of HD IL-2 therapy.  Upon study entry, the subjects will be
      given a dairy to report episodes of vomiting, use of rescue therapy, and nausea assessments
      using the 1-100 scale within the visual analogue scale (VAS).  The subject will be
      instructed to complete entries from baseline assessment (prior to first dose) until 5 days
      after last dose of HD IL-2 for endpoint analysis.  During inpatient admissions, subjects
      will complete diary entries before each dose (q8 hours).  As an outpatient, subjects will
      complete diary entries on a daily basis.  Recording of whether or not pruritus was observed
      will also be collected within the subject diary.  If a patient reports pruritus, the
      severity of pruritus on the 1-100 scale visual analogue scale (VAS) will also be collected.
      The study team will record any episodes of vomiting and the use of rescue therapy and ensure
      completion of patient diary during inpatient portion.  Assessments will be made via
      telephone contact to determine onset of any episodes of CINV during outpatient portion.
      Safety assessments including adverse events (AEs) monitoring will be performed and assessed
      using Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete response during inpatient admission</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>No vomiting during inpatient admissions</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dosage count</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of doses of HD IL-2 administered during inpatient admissions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Chemotherapy-induced Nausea and Vomiting</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fosaprepitant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>During treatment admission, intravenous fosaprepitant 150 mg every 48 hours during 6-day hospital admission</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>During placebo admission, intravenous 0.9% saline every 48 hours during 6-day hospital admission</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fosaprepitant</intervention_name>
    <description>During treatment admission, intravenous fosaprepitant 150 mg every 48 hours during 6-day hospital admission</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fosaprepitant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Emend</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects must meet all of the following inclusion criteria to be eligible for
             enrollment into the study:

               1. Evidence of a personally signed and dated informed consent document indicating
                  that the subject (or legally acceptable representative) has been informed of all
                  pertinent aspects of the trial.

               2. Subjects who are willing to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plan,
                  laboratory tests, and other study procedures.

               3. Be at least 18 years of age at the time of informed consent.

               4. Has a diagnosis of metastatic melanoma or metastatic renal cell carcinoma and
                  who will undergo high-dose interleukin-2 (HD IL-2) therapy

               5. Have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 2 or
                  less at Baseline/Day 1 visit.  (See Appendix 6 on p. 51, ECOG Performance
                  Status)

               6. Female of reproductive potential must agree use non-hormonal methods to avoid
                  pregnancy during study participation and for 1 month after last dose of study
                  drug

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects presenting with any of the following will not be included in the study:

               1. Women who are pregnant or lactating, or planning pregnancy

               2. Women of childbearing potential who refuse to use non-hormonal methods to avoid
                  pregnancy

               3. Known hypersensitivity to any component of fosaprepitant or aprepitant

               4. Have taken pimozide or cisapride &lt;4 weeks, cytochrome P450 3A4 inducers within
                  30 days, strong CYP3A4 inhibitors within 7 days, or antiemetics within 48 hours
                  prior to treatment initiation (See Appendix 7 on p. 52 for list of CYP3A4
                  inducers and strong CYP3A4 inhibitors)

               5. Have evidence of clinically significant and unstable diseases or conditions such
                  as cardiovascular, immunosuppressive, hematologic, hepatic, neurologic, renal,
                  endocrine, collagen-vascular, or gastrointestinal abnormalities that the
                  investigator thinks may interfere with study participation

               6. Participation in other study using an investigational or experimental therapy or
                  procedure within 4 weeks or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer) before study
                  entry

               7. Subjects cannot participate in studies of other investigational or experimental
                  therapies or procedures at any time during their participation in this study.

               8. Other severe acute or chronic medical or psychiatric condition or laboratory
                  abnormality that may increase the risk associated with study participation or
                  may interfere with the interpretation of study results and, in the judgment of
                  the investigator, would make the subject inappropriate for entry into this
                  study.

               9. Subjects who are investigational site staff members or who are Sponsor employees
                  directly involved in the conduct of the trial.

              10. A subject who, in the opinion of the investigator or sponsor, will be
                  uncooperative or unable to comply with study procedures.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John M Richart, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Saint Louis University, Department of Internal Medicine, Division of Hematology and Oncology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Stephanie Kalbouneh</last_name>
    <phone>314-577-8854</phone>
    <email>kalbousl@slu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Melinda B Chu, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>314-409-1045</phone>
    <email>chumb@slu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Saint Louis University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Melinda B Chu, MD</last_name>
      <phone>314-409-1045</phone>
      <email>chumb@slu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Cynthia Cantrell</last_name>
      <phone>314-268-7061</phone>
      <email>cantrell@slu.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John M Richart, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grunberg S, Chua D, Maru A, Dinis J, DeVandry S, Boice JA, Hardwick JS, Beckford E, Taylor A, Carides A, Roila F, Herrstedt J. Single-dose fosaprepitant for the prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting associated with cisplatin therapy: randomized, double-blind study protocol--EASE. J Clin Oncol. 2011 Apr 10;29(11):1495-501. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2010.31.7859. Epub 2011 Mar 7.</citation>
    <PMID>21383291</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Van Laere K, De Hoon J, Bormans G, Koole M, Derdelinckx I, De Lepeleire I, Declercq R, Sanabria Bohorquez SM, Hamill T, Mozley PD, Tatosian D, Xie W, Liu Y, Liu F, Zappacosta P, Mahon C, Butterfield KL, Rosen LB, Murphy MG, Hargreaves RJ, Wagner JA, Shadle CR. Equivalent dynamic human brain NK1-receptor occupancy following single-dose i.v. fosaprepitant vs. oral aprepitant as assessed by PET imaging. Clin Pharmacol Ther. 2012 Aug;92(2):243-50. doi: 10.1038/clpt.2012.62. Epub 2012 Jun 27.</citation>
    <PMID>22739139</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 15, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 6, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>renal cell carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>interleukin-2</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nausea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vomiting</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Interleukin-2</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aprepitant</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
