<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="147830">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01689987</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00008296</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01689987</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cyclophosphamide(Cy)/ Dexamethasone(Dex)/Rapamycin (Rapa)/Hydroxychloroquine (HCQ) for Relapsed or Refractory Myeloma(Rel/Ref MM)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Infusional Cyclophosphamide and Pulse Dexamethasone With Rapamycin and Hydroxychloroquine in Patients With Relapsed or Refactory Myeloma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Multiple myeloma (MM) is a type of cancer with an average survival of 3 to 5 years. The
      disease remains incurable and patients become unresponsive to treatments. Patients also
      develop organ problems and can have severe side effects from therapy. All of these factors
      limit treatment options. This protocol will enroll subjects who have MM that has returned
      after treatment or has stopped responding to treatment. The purpose of this study is to test
      the safety of rapamycin and hydroxychloroquine (study drugs) at different dose levels. The
      investigators want to find out what effects, good and/or bad, it has on MM. The study drugs
      have not been approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) or any other
      regulatory agency for general use in this type of cancer and their benefits and side effects
      are not fully known. These study drugs will be given with standard chemotherapy,
      cyclophosphamide and dexamethasone, which have both been approved by the FDA for use in this
      disease. The investigators believe that the combination of standard chemotherapy, with
      rapamycin and hydroxychloroquine (HCQ), may improve the response outcome compared to
      standard chemotherapy alone. The investigators think that both study drugs will improve the
      sensitivity of the myeloma cells in the body to standard chemotherapy, making it easier for
      the chemotherapy to kill or damage the myeloma cells. However, this combination has never
      been tried in patients before. In future research studies, the investigators hope to
      determine how well this drug combination will work in fighting and killing myeloma cells.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD)of Hydroxychloroquine (HCQ),Rapamycin, Dexamethasone, and Cyclophosphamide.</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of the study; up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of  hydroxychloroquine (HCQ) in combination with rapamycin and infusional cyclophosphamide and pulse dexamethasone (cy/dex) for patients with relapsed/ refractory multiple myeloma.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of biological activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of the study; Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate biological activity of the combination of cyclophosphamide, dexamethasone, rapamycin and hydroxychloroquine in patients with relapsed/ refractory multiple myeloma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of the study; up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate efficacy of the combination of cyclophosphamide, dexamethasone, rapamycin and hydroxychloroquine in patients with relapsed/ refractory multiple myeloma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hydroxychloroquine/Rapamycin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Hydroxychloroquine (HCQ) oral will begin on day 5 of cycle 1 and daily thereafter. It will be given every day of all subsequent cycles (to be given with milk or food at approximately the same time each day, suggested with dinner at 4-6pm).
starting dose of HCQ (dose level 1) will be 400mg escalating as follows: 600mg, 800mg, on to the highest dose of 1200mg daily (dose level 4).
Rapamycin loading dose on day -2 of each cycle, followed by a daily dose on days -1 through 4 (on an empty stomach at approximately the same time every day- suggested at 2pm).
4mg rapamycin daily with 12mg loading dose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hydroxychloroquine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Hydroxychloroquine/Rapamycin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rapamycin</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Hydroxychloroquine/Rapamycin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed multiple myeloma

          -  Documented relapse or persistent disease after at least one prior therapy (which may
             include autologous and allogeneic bone marrow transplantation)

          -  Need for further treatment for myeloma, as determined by the patient's treating
             physician*

          -  Age ≥18 years. Both men and women and members of all races and ethnic groups will be
             included.

          -  ECOG performance status ≤ 2 (Karnofsky ≥ 60%, see Appendix).

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent
             document.

          -  Birth control is required with full barrier contraceptives or complete abstinence for
             the duration of time receiving therapy and for 6 months after completing the last
             drug taken.

               -  The need for further treatment: This is defined as progression of clinical
                  features (worsening anemia, renal function, bone disease, hypercalcemia,
                  recurrent infections, and constitutional symptoms) or biochemical progression
                  (increasing M-spike in serum or urine, involved serum or urine free light chain
                  over 2 consecutive time points greater than 4 weeks apart).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of allergic reactions to compounds of similar chemical or biological
             composition to rapamycin or hydroxychloroquine

          -  Patients may not take any of the following medications while on study, but will be
             considered eligible if medication is discontinued at least 72 hrs prior to first dose
             of Rapamycin.

               -  Carbamazepine (e.g. Tegretol)

               -  Rifabutin (e.g. Mycobutin)

               -  Rifampin (e.g. Rifadin)

               -  Rifapentine (e.g. Priftin)

               -  St. John's Wort

               -  Clarithromycin (e.g. Biaxin)

               -  Cyclosporin e.g. (Neoral or Sandimmune)

               -  Diltiazem (e.g. Cardizem)

               -  Erythromycin (e.g. Akne-Mycin, Ery-Tab)

               -  Itraconazole (e.g. Sporanox)

               -  Fluconazole (e.g. Diflucan)

               -  Ketoconazole (e.g. Nizoral)

               -  Telithromycin (e.g. Ketek)

               -  Verapamil (e.g. Calan SR, Isoptin, Verelan)

               -  Voriconazole (e.g. VFEND)Tacrolimus (e.g. Prograf)

          -  Known macular degeneration or retinopathy (diabetic or otherwise), porphyria, or
             psoriasis (well-controlled psoriasis allowed provided under the care of a specialist
             who agrees to monitor the patient for exacerbations)

          -  Patients with the following cytopenias:

               -  ANC &lt;1.0 x 109/L;

               -  Platelets &lt; 50 x 109/L for any reason

          -  Patients with the following chemistry abnormalities:

               -  Serum Creatinine  &gt; 2.5 mg/dL;

               -  Total or Direct Bilirubin &gt; 2.0 mg/dL;

               -  Transaminases 2 x the upper limit of normal

               -  Fasting Glucose &gt; 200mg/dL

               -  Serum potassium &lt; 3.4 mmol/l

               -  Serum phosphorus &lt; 2.4mg/dl

          -  Other conditions that would require therapy with hydroxychloroquine, including but
             not limited to, any of the following:

               -  Systemic lupus

               -  Rheumatoid arthritis

               -  Porphyria cutanea tarda

               -  Malaria treatment or prophylaxis

          -  Evidence of other active malignancy, except:

               -  Basal cell or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin

               -  Treated carcinoma in situ

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, any of the
             following:

               -  Uncontrolled ongoing infection

               -  HIV

               -  Hepatitis B infection

               -  Known G6PD deficiency

               -  Symptomatic congestive heart failure

               -  Unstable angina pectoris

               -  Uncontrolled cardiac arrhythmia

               -  Psychiatric illness or social situations that would limit compliance with study
                  requirements

               -  Active GvHD

          -  Inability to understand or unwillingness to sign the informed consent document

          -  Concurrent anti-myeloma therapy within:

               -  7 days of prior corticosteroids

               -  14 days of prior antimyeloma agents, including thalidomide or lenalidomide

               -  28 days of a different investigational regimen

               -  14 days of any radiation

          -  Women of child-bearing who are unwilling or unable to use an acceptable method to
             avoid pregnancy for the entire study period and for up to 30 days after the last dose
             of study drug.

          -  Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding.

          -  History of G6PD deficiency

          -  HIV infection
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amy Bedford</last_name>
      <email>bedforda@ohsu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Emma Scott, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 5, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 17, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sirolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydroxychloroquine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone 21-phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
