<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="33529">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01987219</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>S13-00004</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01987219</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects Of Bronchodilator Therapy On Respiratory And Autonomic Function In Patients With Familial Dysautonomia</brief_title>
  <official_title>THE EFFECTS OF BRONCHODILATOR THERAPY ON RESPIRATORY AND AUTONOMIC FUNCTION IN PATIENTS WITH FAMILIAL DYSAUTONOMIA</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Evaluate the effects of bronchodilator therapy on respiratory function. Our overall goal is
      to determine whether, in patients with familial dysautonomia (FD), there is a component of
      airway obstruction that is reversible. To this end, we will evaluate airway resistance
      before and after receiving the anti-cholinergic ipratropium (Atrovent ®) and the
      beta-2-agonist albuterol (ProVentil®/Ventolin®). We predict that the response to either drug
      will depend on the underlying level of sympathetic and parasympathetic activity and airway
      tone. We will then determine the cardiovascular effects of inhaled ipratropium and albuterol
      in patients with FD. Because patients with FD have fewer sympathetic neurons and denervation
      supersenstivity, we predict that following albuterol inhalation, there will be non-selective
      activation of alpha-1-adrenergic receptors. Furthermore, because of a congenital defect in
      the afferent baroreceptor neurons that sense blood pressure, we suspect that the resulting
      vasoconstriction will be unopposed leading to a pressor effect. We hypothesize that
      inhalation of the anti-cholinergic ipratopium will produce little rise in heart rate, due to
      the extent of parasympathetic denervation to the heart.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Familial dysautonomia (FD) is a rare fatal autosomal recessive disease caused by a
      deficiency of the protein IKAP.1 This results in a selective developmental defect that
      affects mostly afferent (sensory) neurons including those in the dorsal root ganglia and
      cranial nerves.2, 3 We have shown recently that the protein deficiency impairs the
      development of afferent baroreceptor pathways, leaving the sympathetic efferent neurons
      reduced in number but functionally active. This results in the complete failure to detect
      and buffer fluctuations in blood pressure leading to volatile hypertension.  In addition to
      the afferent baroreflex pathways, the deficiency of IKAP during embroyogenesis also affects
      the function of the chemoreflex pathways. As a result, patients fail to increase ventilation
      adequately in response to hypoxia and hypercapnia.4 As well as the impairment of the
      neurological mechanisms that regulate breathing, patients with FD also have a combination of
      obstructive, restrictive and probably also neuromuscular lung disease. Failure to coordinate
      swallowing results in recurrent bouts of aspiration pneumonia occurring from birth.5, 6
      Imaging studies show that almost all patients with FD have bronchial wall thickening,
      atelectasis and almost 30% have bronchiectasis7. Pulmonary function tests show air flow
      limitation and associated lung restriction with reduction in diffusion capacity12. Sudden
      attacks of asthma like wheezing are common 8 and frequently associated with emotional
      upset,5 a time when sympathetic outflow to the vasculature is increased heightened.3 There
      is also a component of restrictive lung disease, with a very high incidence of scoliosis,
      which frequently begins at an early age. Complicating matters further, many patients opt to
      undergo spine fusion surgery, 9 which could potentially worsen further chest wall
      compliance.10 Patients with FD also lack muscle spindles, 2 making it likely that they have
      neuromuscular abnormalities arising from the absence of proprioceptive feedback from the
      respiratory muscles involved in the coordination of breathing.

      Severe respiratory disease is a leading cause of death in patients with FD and many are
      treated empirically with inhaled bronchodilators. It is not known, however, whether these
      drugs are effective at reversing increased airway resistance. Hence, there is an urgent need
      to understand if the short acting beta-2-adrenergic agonist albuterol and the
      anticholinergic ipratropium, are effective bronchodilators. Furthermore, because treatment
      with these agents has potential cardiovascular side effects, we will also analyze their
      effects on blood pressure, heart rate and cardiac output.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>respiratory Function (airway resistance, R5HZ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre and 30 minutes post study drug administration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Our overall goal is to evaluate whether there is a component of airway obstruction that is reversible. To address this goal, we will compare the effects of a short acting, inhaled beta-2-adrenergic receptor agonist (albuterol) and an antagonist of acetylcholine (ipratropium) on airway resistance. Using pulse oscillometry, we will compare airway resistance before and after the brochodilators are administered. The variables that measure airway resistance are R5HZ and R20HZ.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>respiratory function (airway resistance, R20HZ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre and 30 minutes post study drug administration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Our overall goal is to evaluate whether there is a component of airway obstruction that is reversible. To address this goal, we will compare the effects of a short acting, inhaled beta-2-adrenergic receptor agonist (albuterol) and an antagonist of acetylcholine (ipratropium) on airway resistance. Using pulse oscillometry, we will compare airway resistance before and after the brochodilators are administered. The variables that measure airway resistance are R5HZ and R20HZ.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiac function (blood pressure)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre and 30 post study drug admistration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Our second aim is to evaluate the effects of both bronchodilators on cardiovascular function. Relative change in BP ,RR intervals and CO from baseline after receiving albuterol or ipratropium will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>RR interval</measure>
    <time_frame>pre and 30 minutes post intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Our second aim is to evaluate the effects of both bronchodilators on cardiovascular function. Relative change in BP ,RR intervals and CO from baseline after receiving albuterol or ipratropium will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiac Output (CO)</measure>
    <time_frame>pre and post 30 minutes intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Our second aim is to evaluate the effects of both bronchodilators on cardiovascular function. Relative change in BP ,RR intervals and CO from baseline after receiving albuterol or ipratropium will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Respiratory Disease in Familial Dysautonomia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Albuterol-sulphate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Albuterol-sulphate (Proventil ®) Beta-2-adrenergic agonist	2.5 mg 3 cc inhalation	Peak effect 15 - 30 mins. Mean duration of effect 3 hours</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ipratropium-bromide (Atrovent ®)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>IpratroAnti-cholinergic(Atrovent ®)	500 mcg 3 cc inhalation	Peak effect 30 - 90 mins. Duration of effect 2 - 4 hours.pium-bromide</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo   Saline solution	3 cc	NA</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Albuterol-sulphate</intervention_name>
    <description>Beta-2-adrenergic agonist	2.5 mg 3 cc inhalation	Peak effect 15 - 30 mins. Mean duration of effect 3 hours</description>
    <arm_group_label>Albuterol-sulphate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>(Proventil ®)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ipratropium-bromide</intervention_name>
    <description>Anti-cholinergic	500 mcg 3 cc inhalation	Peak effect 30 - 90 mins. Duration of effect 2 - 4 hours.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ipratropium-bromide (Atrovent ®)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>(Atrovent ®)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Saline solution	3 cc	NA</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Diagnosis of familial dysautonomia (Riley-Day syndrome, hereditary sensory and
             autonomic neuropathy type III) 2. Ages 12 and older: Bronchodilators are routinely
             used in young children with FD therefore they should be included in this study. The
             spirometry maneuver is highly dependent on patient cooperation and effort, and FD
             patients already have limitations that make the spirometry maneuver more problematic
             to perform such as difficulty with mouth closure and drooling. Therefore, we believe
             age 12 is a suitable age for  FD patients to be included in this study, though in the
             general population reliable results can be obtained from the age of 6 and sometimes
             even younger.

             3. Patients using Albuterol or Ipratroprium will be included in the study but will be
             instructed not to take the 24 hours prior to the testing. It is a common practice in
             clinical medicine to withhold the inhalation drugs prior to performing pulmonary
             function tests in order to evaluate the response to bronchodilators, an integral part
             of the test.  Patients with an acute respiratory exacerbation will not be enrolled,
             as withholding bronchodilators would not be advisable.

             4. Patients who are taking medications that might affect autonomic function such as
             anti-hypertensives, beta-blockers, midodrine and florinef will be included in the
             study and we will record current medication regimen and the time the medication was
             taken.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        - 1. Patients who last used inhaled anti-cholinergics or beta-2-agonists within 4-half
        lives of the drug.

        2. Patients with an acute respiratory illness 3. Patients who have had lobectomies. 4.
        Patients using oxygen therapy throughout the day. 5. Patients who are unable to comply
        with the study requirements.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NYU Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jose Martinez, MA</last_name>
      <phone>212-263-7225</phone>
      <email>jose.martinez@nyumc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Horacio Kaufmann, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 12, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 5, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>New York University School of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Horacio Kaufmann</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Neurology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>familial dysautonomia</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Autonomic Nervous System Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Primary Dysautonomias</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dysautonomia, Familial</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiration Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Tract Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Adrenergic Agonists</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Albuterol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bronchodilator Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ipratropium</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bromides</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
