<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="158194">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02033993</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BL12</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02033993</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial Comparing Nab-Paclitaxel to Paclitaxel in Patients With Advanced Urothelial Cancer Progressing on or After Platinum Containing Regimen.</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multicentre Randomized Phase II Trial Comparing Nab-Paclitaxel to Paclitaxel in Patients With Advanced Urothelial Cancer Progressing on or After a Platinum Containing Regimen.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NCIC Clinical Trials Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Australian and New Zealand Urogenital and Prostate Cancer Group (ANZUP), NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NCIC Clinical Trials Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare the effects on urothelial cancer of nab-paclitaxel
      compared to paclitaxel to treat this disease.

      This research is being done because currently there is no effective treatment for urothelial
      cancer that has progressed after prior chemotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Nab-paclitaxel is a formulation of the chemotherapeutic drug paclitaxel that is combined
      with a human protein called albumin. In Canada, nab-paclitaxel is currently approved for the
      treatment of metastatic breast cancer. This drug has been tested in other cancers and has
      shown promising activity in lung cancer, melanoma and pancreatic cancer. Information from
      research studies suggests that nab-paclitaxel may be a useful treatment for urothelial
      cancer.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>42 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PFS is defined as the time from randomization to the first observation of disease progression or death due to any cause.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>42 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Benefit Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>42 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>ORR+SD &gt; 12 weeks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Response and Response Duration</measure>
    <time_frame>42 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nature, severity and frequency of toxicities</measure>
    <time_frame>42 monts</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Including neuropathy between the two arms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>42 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Quality of life will be assessed using the EORTC-C15-PAL questionnaire plus additional study specific questions.
Changes in quality of life scores while on treatment (compared to baseline scores) will be examined using descriptive analyses and inferential statistics. The primary test to compare treatment arms will be a Wei-lachin test for stochastic ordering, including all time points where QoL was measured. In addition, baseline scores between arms will be compared using a Wilcoxon rank sum test, and a pattern mixture model identifying drop-out patients as a special category will be performed to evaluate the effect of missing data.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost and cost utility ratios between the two arms</measure>
    <time_frame>42 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the incremental costs and effectiveness and cost utility ratios for nab-paclitaxel versus paclitaxel</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Tissue Markers at diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>42 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To correlate the expression of tissue markers (at diagnosis) with outcomes and response in an exploratory fashion.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>genetic polymorphisms that may impact on response or toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>42 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess genetic polymorphisms that may impact on response or toxicity to the taxanes.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Effect modification of clinico-demographic factors</measure>
    <time_frame>42 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess the effect modification of and adjust for clinico-demographic factors captured in a health and demographic questionnaire with respect to the relationships between biomarkers, quality of life, health economics, disease outcomes, and treatment toxicities.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">199</enrollment>
  <condition>Urothelial Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Nab-Paclitaxel - 260mg/m2: q21 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Paclitaxel - 175mg/m2: q21 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nab-Paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of TCC of the urinary tract
             (bladder, urethra, ureter, renal pelvis) and metastatic or locally advanced
             inoperable disease extent (T4, N2, N3 or M1 disease)

        Note: Mixed histologies (except small cell) permitted if predominately TCC by IHC.

          -  Patients must have evidence of metastatic disease, but measurable disease is not
             mandatory. To be considered evaluable for the overall response rate (complete and
             partial response), patients must have at least one measurable lesion as follows:

               -  X-ray, physical exam ≥ 20 mm

               -  Conventional CT scan, MRI ≥ 20 mm

               -  Spiral CT scan ≥ 10 mm

          -  Male or female, 18 years of age or older.

          -  ECOG performance status ≤ 2 at study entry

          -  Adequate hematological, renal and hepatic functions as defined by the following
             required laboratory values obtained within 14 days prior to randomization. If anemic,
             patients should be asymptomatic and should not be decompensated.

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 x10^9/L (1,500 cells/mm3)

               -  Platelet count ≥ 90 x10^9/L (100,000/mm3)

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 90 g/L

               -  Calculated creatinine clearance &gt; 25 mL/min (Cockcroft and Gault formula)

               -  Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 times the upper limit of normal (≤ 2.5X if Gilbert's
                  disease)

               -  ALT (SGPT) ≤ 3 x ULN or ≤ 5 x ULN if hepatic metastases are present

          -  Patients may have had prior neoadjuvant or adjuvant therapy for completely resected
             disease, provided it was completed at least 12 months prior to randomization.
             Patients must have recovered from any acute toxic effects to ≤ Grade 2 from any prior
             treatments. Neoadjuvant or adjuvant chemotherapy will be considered to have been
             first line therapy in the metastatic setting if the patient progressed within 12
             months of the last dose.

          -  Patients must have received one and only one prior chemotherapeutic regimen which
             included a platinum (at least one cycle) for metastatic/recurrent disease. Treatment
             must have been discontinued at least 4 weeks prior to randomization in this study.
             Patients must have recovered from any acute toxic effects to ≤ Grade 2 from any prior
             treatments

          -  Patients may not have had any prior therapy with a taxane in any setting.

          -  Patients may have had prior investigational agents but these must have been
             discontinued at least 4 weeks prior to randomization. Patients must have recovered
             from any acute toxic effects to ≤ Grade 2 from any prior treatments.

          -  Prior treatments with radiation therapy in the adjuvant and/or metastatic setting are
             permitted provided that at least 2 weeks have elapsed since the last fraction of
             radiation therapy and all treatment related adverse events are ≤ Grade 1 at the time
             of randomization.

          -  Patients may have had prior surgery provided that at least 4 weeks elapsed between
             the end of surgery and randomization onto the study. Patients must have recovered
             from any acute toxic effects to ≤ Grade 2 from any prior treatments.

          -  Patients may have peripheral neuropathy from previous treatments assuming it is ≤
             Grade 2.

          -  Patient is able (i.e. sufficiently fluent) and willing to complete the health and
             demographic, quality of life, and health utilities questionnaires in either English
             or French. The baseline assessment must be completed within required timelines, prior
             to registration/randomization. Inability (illiteracy in English or French, loss of
             sight, or other equivalent reason) to complete the questionnaires will not make the
             patient ineligible for the study. However, ability but unwillingness to complete the
             questionnaires will make the patient ineligible.

          -  Patient consent must be appropriately obtained in accordance with applicable local
             and regulatory requirements. Each patient must sign a consent form prior to
             enrollment in the trial to document their willingness to participate.

          -  Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy
             test within 7 days prior to randomization. In addition to routine contraceptive
             methods, &quot;effective contraception&quot; also includes heterosexual celibacy and surgery
             intended to prevent pregnancy (or with a side-effect of pregnancy prevention) defined
             as a hysterectomy, bilateral oophorectomy, bilateral tubal ligation or
             vasectomy/vasectomized partner. However, if at any point a previously celibate
             patient chooses to become heterosexually active during the time period for use of
             contraceptive measures outlined in the protocol, he/she is responsible for beginning
             contraceptive measures.

          -  Patients must be accessible for treatment and follow up. Patients registered on this
             trial must be treated and followed at the participating centre. This implies there
             must be reasonable geographical limits (for example: 1 ½ hour's driving distance)
             placed on patients being considered for this trial.  Investigators must assure
             themselves the patients registered on this trial will be available for complete
             documentation of the treatment, adverse events, response assessment and follow-up.

          -  In accordance with NCIC CTG policy, protocol treatment is to begin within 5 working
             days of patient randomization.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A candidate for potentially curative surgery or radiotherapy.

          -  Patients with brain metastases are ineligible if they meet at least one of the
             following criteria:

               1. diagnosis within 3 months from randomization

               2. untreated brain metastases

               3. unstable brain metastasis as defined by:

                    -  cavitation or hemorrhage in the brain lesion

                    -  symptomatic state

                    -  daily prednisone or equivalent use greater than 10 mg

        Patients do not need CT/MRI scans to rule out brain metastases unless there is a clinical
        suspicion of CNS metastases.

          -  Any evidence of severe or uncontrolled systemic diseases which include known cases of
             hepatitis B or C or human immunodeficiency virus (HIV). Patients with active or
             uncontrolled infections, or with serious illnesses or medical conditions which would
             not permit the patient to be managed according to the protocol. Screening for chronic
             conditions is not required, although patients known to have such conditions at
             screening should not be included.

          -  Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding.

          -  Patients with history of allergic or hypersensitivity reactions to any study drug or
             their excipients or with a history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds with
             similar chemical composition to any of the study drugs.

          -  Planned concomitant participation in another clinical trial of an experimental agent,
             vaccine or device. Concomitant participation in observational studies is acceptable.

          -  Patients with a history of other malignancies, except: adequately treated
             non-melanoma skin cancer, curatively treated in-situ cancer of the cervix, or other
             solid tumours curatively treated with no evidence of disease for ≥ 5 years. Prior
             prostate cancer is allowed provided that it is an incidental finding at
             cystoprostatectomy with a PSA &lt;0.5 ng/mL at randomization or a prior diagnosis of low
             risk prostate cancer at any time as defined by ≤T2, a Gleason Score of 6 or less and
             PSA &lt;10 ng/mL.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Srikala Sridhar</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Univ. Health Network-Princess Margaret Hospital, Toronto, Ontario Canada</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Wendy Parulekar</last_name>
    <phone>613-544-2630</phone>
    <email>wparulekar@ctg.queensu.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cross Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6G 1Z2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Naveen S. Basappa</last_name>
      <phone>780 432-8762</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Juravinski Cancer Centre at Hamilton Health Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L8V 5C2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Som Mukherjee</last_name>
      <phone>905 387-9495</phone>
      <phone_ext>64605</phone_ext>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>London Regional Cancer Program</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N6A 4L6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eric W. Winquist</last_name>
      <phone>519 685-8261</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Univ. Health Network-Princess Margaret Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 2M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Srikala Sridhar</last_name>
      <phone>416 946-4501</phone>
      <phone_ext>2520</phone_ext>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHUM - Hopital Notre-Dame</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H2L 4M1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Normand Blais</last_name>
      <phone>514 890-8444</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 15, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 9, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
