<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="163095">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01862796</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999913096</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-DK-N096</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01862796</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Predicting Adherence to a Heart-Healthy Diet in Lean and Obese Individuals</brief_title>
  <official_title>Is Non-Adherence Unique to Weight-Loss? Predictors of Adherence to a Heart-Healthy Diet in Lean vs. Obese Individuals</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Sticking to a diet plan can be difficult, but is important for many different health
      reasons. Some people seem to have a harder time following and sticking to a diet plan than
      others. It is not clear whether people of different weights (lean or obese) might have
      differences in the way they adhere to diet plans. Researchers want to study three different
      groups of people based on their body mass index (BMI), which measures people based on their
      weight and height. The study will place the participants on a 6-week diet and see how well
      they follow the diet. The information from this study may help develop better weight-loss
      plans and healthy diet ideas.

      Objectives:

        -  To understand what factors affect adherence to a diet plan.

        -  To collect information for future studies that may improve people's ability to stick to
           diets.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals at least 18 years of age who are lean (BMI between 18.5 and 25) or obese (BMI
      greater than 30).

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. Blood and urine
           samples will be collected. They will have a full-body scan to measure fat and muscle.
           They will also answer questions on eating behaviors, mood, and desire to change eating
           patterns.

        -  Participants will be separated into three groups. Each group will have a different
           diet. The lean group will have a heart-healthy diet designed to maintain the same
           weight. One of the obese groups will also have a heart-healthy diet designed to
           maintain the same weight. The other obese group will have a heart-healthy weight loss
           diet. In all groups, all food will be provided by the study doctors. Participants
           should not eat any food other than that provided for the study.

        -  Everyone will start with a 1-week food testing period to find the right number of
           calories for each group. After this first week, participants will attend one diet
           counseling session per week and will be contacted randomly once a week to check on the
           foods they have had in the past 24 hours. Participants will complete daily food diaries
           on paper as well as daily food records using a smart phone.

        -  Participants will come to the clinic twice a week to pick up the diet food. On one of
           those days, they will also have their counseling session.

        -  The study will last for 6 weeks. At the final study visit, participants will repeat the
           tests from the screening study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Adherence, or &quot;sticking to your diet&quot; is important for successful initial weight loss and
      keeping off the weight over the long term (1).  While early behavioral and dietary adherence
      have been associated with greater weight loss, sticking to a diet plan is difficult.  It is
      not clear if adherence to any diet plan (even one which does not produce weight loss) is
      hard or whether people who are overweight have more difficulty with adhering to diet plans
      compared to people who are relatively lean.

      The main aim of this study is to evaluate dietary adherence in 3 groups of individuals
      participating in a 6-week heart-healthy dietary intervention program.  Two groups [1. Lean
      (BMI &lt;  25 kg/m(2)) and 2. Obese (BMI greater than or equal to 30 kg/m(2)) will receive a
      heart-healthy diet designed to maintain their weight, and the third group (3. Obese) will be
      given a heart-healthy diet that is 35% less than their daily calorie needs to lose weight.
      Participants will attend one counseling session per week and will be contacted randomly
      1x/week by study staff for completion of a 24-hour dietary recall. They will complete daily
      food diaries and daily records using smart-phones. Prior to starting the assigned
      heart-healthy dietary intervention, participants will complete questionnaires that include
      questions about how motivated they are to follow a diet, lose weight, and change eating
      patterns.  These findings may help us understand what factors affect adherence, and help us
      design weight loss studies that improve people's ability to stick to diet interventions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Examine differences in dietary adherence between lean and obese individuals</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Overweight</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Food Intake</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Weight Loss</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. BMI

               -  BMI greater than or equal to 30 kg/m(2) for the obese WMEN and UF groups but
                  body weight less than 350 pounds to accommodate the DXA scanner

               -  BMI less than or equal to 25 kg/m(2) (and BMI greater than or equal to 18.5
                  kg/m(2)) for the lean WMEN group

          2. Age greater than or equal to 18 years. Minors under the age of 18 will be excluded
             because growth and pubertal issues are significant parameters that could affect our
             outcomes and also because the time requirements of the study are such that they would
             interfere with school schedules.  Participants must be healthy, as determined by
             medical history, physical examination, and laboratory tests.

          3. Weight stable (plus or minus 2 percent) for last 3 months

        EXCLUSIION CRITERIA:

        Candidates will be screened by phone to exclude those with BMI greater than or equal to 26
        kg/m(2) and BMI less than or equal to  29 kg/m(2), significant health problems, including
        cancer, hypertension, diabetes, current and past 3-month use of certain prescribed
        medications, especially those that could affect body weight, such as antidepressants and
        stimulants as well as smoking, or excess alcohol (greater than 3 drinks/d).  Women must
        not be pregnant or lactating, and be at least 1 year postpartum. Candidates with a history
        of psychotic disorder or hospitalization for psychiatric illness within the past 1 year
        will not be eligible. They will need to be weight stable for the past 3 months (plus or
        minus 2 percent) and cannot be in treatment for obesity or currently receiving
        psychotherapy. Individuals who meet criteria according to the phone screen will be invited
        to come to the unit for a screening visit and their screening sheets are placed in a
        locked filing cabinet. Forms from potential volunteers who are ineligible are shredded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marci Gluck, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marci Gluck, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(602) 200-5312</phone>
    <email>gmarci@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NIDDK, Phoenix</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85014</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fappa E, Yannakoulia M, Pitsavos C, Skoumas I, Valourdou S, Stefanadis C. Lifestyle intervention in the management of metabolic syndrome: could we improve adherence issues? Nutrition. 2008 Mar;24(3):286-91. doi: 10.1016/j.nut.2007.11.008. Epub 2008 Jan 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18201869</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Flegal KM, Graubard BI, Williamson DF, Gail MH. Weight-associated deaths in the United States. J Womens Health (Larchmt). 2007 Nov;16(9):1368-70.</citation>
    <PMID>18001195</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kassirer JP, Angell M. Losing weight--an ill-fated New Year's resolution. N Engl J Med. 1998 Jan 1;338(1):52-4.</citation>
    <PMID>9414332</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 23, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Food Intake</keyword>
  <keyword>Weight Loss</keyword>
  <keyword>Compliance</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
