<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="87459">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02049151</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EMR 63325-021</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-003760-30</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02049151</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tecemotide Following Concurrent Chemo-radiotherapy for Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>START2</acronym>
  <official_title>A Multicenter, Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled Phase III Trial of Tecemotide Versus Placebo in Subjects With Completed Concurrent Chemo-radiotherapy for Unresectable Stage III Non-small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>EMD Serono</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>EMD Serono</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Austria: Federal Office for Safety in Health Care</authority>
    <authority>Australia: Human Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>Belgium: Federal Agency for Medicinal Products and Health Products</authority>
    <authority>Czech Republic: State Institute for Drug Control</authority>
    <authority>Denmark: National Board of Health</authority>
    <authority>France: Agence Nationale de Sécurité du Médicament et des produits de santé</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Paul-Ehrlich-Institut</authority>
    <authority>Ireland: Irish Medicines Board</authority>
    <authority>Italy: The Italian Medicines Agency</authority>
    <authority>Netherlands: The Central Committee on Research Involving Human Subjects (CCMO)</authority>
    <authority>Poland: Office for Registration of Medicinal Products, Medical Devices and Biocidal Products</authority>
    <authority>Portugal: National Pharmacy and Medicines Institute</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Spanish Agency of Medicines</authority>
    <authority>Sweden: Medical Products Agency</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center, double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized, Phase 3 trial in
      subjects with unresectable stage III non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) who have
      demonstrated either stable disease or objective response following primary concurrent
      chemo-radiotherapy (CRT), comparing overall survival (OS) time in subjects treated with
      tecemotide versus subjects treated with tecemotide-matching placebo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS) Time</measure>
    <time_frame>From 1st randomization to about 54 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>OS is defined as the time from randomization to death due to any cause.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Symptom Progression (TTSP)</measure>
    <time_frame>From 1st randomization to about 54 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>TTSP is defined as the time from randomization to first documentation of symptom progression as measured by the Lung Cancer Symptom Scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From 1st randomization to about 54 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PFS is defined as the time from randomization to the first documentation of progressive disease (PD) or to death due to any cause, whichever occurs first. PD is assessed by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1 - Investigator read.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Progression (TTP)</measure>
    <time_frame>From 1st randomization to about 54 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>TTP is defined as the time from randomization to the first documentation of PD. PD is assessed by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1 - Investigator read.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1002</enrollment>
  <condition>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tecemotide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tecemotide</intervention_name>
    <description>Tecemotide injection will be administered once weekly subcutaneously at a dose of 806 microgram up to Week 8 and from Week 14, every 6 weeks until end-of-trial, or until NSCLC progression.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tecemotide</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo injection will be administered once weekly subcutaneously up to Week 8 and from Week 14, every 6 weeks until end-of-trial, or until NSCLC progression.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide (CPA)</intervention_name>
    <description>CPA injection will be administered as a single intravenous infusion at a dose of 300 milligram per square meter (mg/m^2) (to a maximum of 600 mg) 3 days before the first injection of tecemotide.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tecemotide</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline (sodium chloride)</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo (saline) injection will be administered as a single intravenous (0.9 percent [%] sodium chloride) infusion 3 days before the first injection of tecemotide-matching placebo.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Written informed consent, before any trial-related activities are carried out

          -  Histologically or cytologically documented unresectable stage III NSCLC, including
             bronchioalveolar  carcinomas. Cancer stage must be confirmed and documented by
             computed tomography (CT), magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) or positron emission
             tomography (PET) scan

          -  Prior concurrent CRT which is defined as follows:

               -  Minimum of 2 cycles of platinum-based chemotherapy

               -  Radiotherapy with a total tumor dose greater than equal to (&gt;=) 60 Gray and a
                  single fraction dose &gt;= 1.8 Gray

               -  Overlap of radiotherapy with minimum 2 cycles of platinum-based chemotherapy
                  (one cycle is defined as either 3 or 4 weeks depending on the chemotherapy
                  regimen). A deviation of 2 to 3 days from an exact overlap is acceptable. Purely
                  radiosensitizing doses of chemotherapy are not acceptable (for example [e.g.],
                  daily low dose regimens; weekly carbo-platinum + paclitaxel regimens are
                  allowed).

        Subjects must have completed the primary thoracic CRT at least 4 weeks (28 days) and no
        later than 12 weeks (84 days) prior to randomization. Subjects who received prophylactic
        brain irradiation as part of primary CRT are eligible.

          -  Documented stable disease or objective response, according to Response Evaluation
             Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1, after primary concurrent CRT for unresectable
             stage III disease, within 4 weeks (28 days) prior to randomization

          -  An Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0-1

          -  A platelet count, white blood cells (WBC) and hemoglobin value as defined in the
             protocol

          -  Male or female, greater than or equal to 18 years of age

          -  Other protocol defined inclusion criteria could apply

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Undergone lung cancer specific therapy (including surgery) other than initial
             concurrent CRT

          -  Received chemotherapy during radiotherapy in radiosensitizing doses only (e.g., daily
             low dose regimens; weekly carbo-platinum + paclitaxel regimens are allowed).

          -  Metastatic disease

          -  Malignant pleural effusion at initial diagnosis, during initial CRT, and/or at trial
             entry

          -  Past or current history of neoplasm other than lung carcinoma, except for curatively
             treated non-melanoma skin cancer, in situ carcinoma of the cervix or other cancer
             curatively treated and with no evidence of disease for at least 5 years

          -  A recognized immunodeficiency disease including cellular immunodeficiencies,
             hypogammaglobulinemia or dysgammaglobulinemia; subjects who have hereditary,
             congenital or acquired immunodeficiencies

          -  Splenectomy

          -  Any preexisting medical condition requiring chronic systemic steroid or
             immunosuppressive therapy (steroids for the treatment of radiation pneumonitis are
             allowed)

          -  Receipt of immunotherapy (as defined in the protocol) within 4 weeks prior to
             randomization

          -  Receipt of investigational systemic drugs (including off-label use of approved
             products) within 4 weeks prior to randomization

          -  Autoimmune disease

          -  Known active or chronic infectious hepatitis

          -  Infectious process that, in the opinion of the Investigator, could compromise the
             subject's ability to mount an immune response

          -  Clinically significant hepatic dysfunction, renal dysfunction and cardiac disease as
             defined in the protocol

          -  Pregnant or breast-feeding women

          -  Known drug abuse/alcohol abuse

          -  Participation in another interventional clinical trial within the past 28 days
             (excluding purely observational studies)

          -  Requires concurrent treatment with a non-permitted drug

          -  Known hypersensitivity to any of the trial treatment ingredients

          -  Legal incapacity or limited legal capacity

          -  Any other reason that, in the opinion of the Investigator, precludes the subject from
             participating in the trial

          -  Other protocol defined exclusion criteria could apply
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Responsible</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Merck KGaA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>US Medical Information</last_name>
    <phone>888-275-7376</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Merck KGaA Communication Center</last_name>
    <phone>+49 6151 72 5200</phone>
    <email>service@merckgroup.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Please Contact U.S. Medical Information Located in</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rockland</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>for US Recruiting Sites</last_name>
      <phone>888-275-7376</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Please Contact the Merck KGaA Communication Center Located in</name>
      <address>
        <city>Darmstadt</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>for non-US Recruiting Sites</last_name>
      <phone>+49 6151 72 5200</phone>
      <email>service@merckgroup.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 27, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</keyword>
  <keyword>Tecemotide</keyword>
  <keyword>Placebo</keyword>
  <keyword>NSCLC</keyword>
  <keyword>L-BLP25</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
