<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="100958">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02076659</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PH-F8IL10-02/08</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2008-008729-31</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02076659</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Combination Therapy of F8IL10 and Methotrexate in Rheumatoid Arthritis Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Dose-finding, Pharmacokinetic Phase I Study of the Human Monoclonal Antibody-cytokine Fusion Protein F8IL10 (Dekavil) in Combination With Methotrexate in Patients With Active Rheumatoid Arthritis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Philogen S.p.A.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Philogen S.p.A.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Italy: National Institute of Health</authority>
    <authority>Italy: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Phase I, multicenter, open-label, dose escalation study to test the efficacy and safety of
      F8IL10 and methotrexate when given as a combination in rheumatoid arthritis patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Phase I, multicenter, open-label, dose escalation study to test the efficacy and safety of
      F8IL10 and methotrexate when given as a combination in rheumatoid arthritis patients.
      Interleukin-10 (IL10) is a cytokine naturally produced by activated monocytes and T-cells.
      It is deeply involved in the regulation of inflammatory responses and immune reactions.
      Therefore, IL10 has been considered an attractive candidate for therapeutic use based on its
      potent in vitro immunomodulating activities and proven effects in animal models of acute and
      chronic inflammation, autoimmunitiy, cancer and infectious disease.

      In the F8IL10 molecule, IL10 is coupled to the antibody fragment F8 which binds to the
      extra-domain A of fibronectin, which is selectively expressed at newly formed blood vessels
      within inflammatory tissues.Upon injection into a patient F8IL10 is supposed to accumulate
      at the site of arthritis where it exerts its biological activity.

      Antibody-mediated targeted delivery of cytokines to sites of disease is a novel therapeutic
      concept which is largely unexplored for the treatment of chronic inflammatory conditions,
      but has been investigated successfully in the cancer setting over the last few years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) and recommended dose (RD)</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Establish the MTD and the RD of F8IL10 when administered in combination with methotrexate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of the combination treatment with F8IL10 and metotrexate</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluation of the type and the number of adverse events eventually present</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic profile of F8IL10</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Human anti-fusion protein antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>9 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluate the possible induction of human anti-fusion protein antibodies (HAFA) formation through standard laboratory analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Antiarthritic activity</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>ACR and DAS28 criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">34</enrollment>
  <condition>Rheumatoid Arthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>F8IL10 + methotrexate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>F8IL10 in combination with methotrexate. This study foresees one arm of treatment with several coohorts aimed to increase the dosage of F8IL10.
In the study cohorts a fixed dose of MTX (10-15 mg) and  increasing doses of F8IL10 (starting from 6 μg/kg cohort 1) will be administered. Both drugs will be administered on day 1.
In all coohorts a stable dose of folic acid (5 mg) will be administered on day 2</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>F8IL10 in combination with methotrexate</intervention_name>
    <description>Weekly administration of F8IL10 (from 6 to 210 μg/kg) + MTX (10-15 mg, fixed dose) on Day 1 and Folic acid (5 mg, fixed dose) on Day 2.
Patients will receive 4 cycles of 1 week treatment unless there is unacceptable toxicity or withdrawal of consent.
F8IL10 will be administered intravenously. MTX can be administered orally, subcutaneously or intramuscularly. Folic acid will be administered orally.
Study design :
Coohort 1 to 6 --&gt; 10-15 mg MTX (fixed)  + 6/15/30/60/110/160/210 μg/kg F8IL10 (one dosage for each coohort)
ACR and DAS28 responses and safety evaluation will be recorded after 4 cycles of treatment. Patients willing to continue the treatment will receive additional 4 cycles of treatment at the dose they received during the first 4 cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>F8IL10 + methotrexate</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients aged &gt;/=18 and &lt; 75 years

          2. Diagnosis of RA according to ACR criteria (1987) with a disease duration exceeding 12
             months

          3. Active RA (DAS28 &gt;/=3.2) for &gt;/=4 months at time of signing informed consent

          4. Receiving treatment on an outpatient basis

          5. Methotrexate at 10-15 mg/w for a period &gt;/=8 weeks prior to treatment

          6. Inadequate clinical response to at least one anti-TNF therapy applied for at least 4
             months

          7. If patients are receiving an oral corticosteroid, the dose must have been stable for
             at least 25 out of 28 days prior to study treatment and the dose must be less than 10
             mg/day (prednisolone equivalent)

          8. All acute toxic effects of any prior therapy must have returned to classification
             &quot;mild&quot;. according to RCTC V.2.0

          9. Sufficient hematologic, liver and renal function:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 x 10^9/L, platelets ≥ 100 x 10^9/L,
                  hemoglobin (Hb) ≥ 9.5 g/dL

               -  Alkaline phosphatase (AP), alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and or aspartate
                  aminotransferase (AST) ≤ 3 x upper limit of normal range (ULN), and total
                  bilirubin ≤ 2.0 mg/dL (34.2 µmol/L)

               -  Creatinine ≤ 1.5 ULN or 24 h creatinine clearance ≥ 50 mL/min

         10. Documented negative test for human immunodeficiency virus, HBV, and HCV

         11. Male and female patients, who are potentially fertile, must agree to use adequate
             contraceptive methods at the beginning of the screening visit that must be continued
             until 3 months following the last treatment with study drug.

         12. Negative serum pregnancy test (for women of child-bearing potential only) at
             screening

         13. Signed and dated Ethics Committee-approved Informed Consent Form indicating that the
             patient (or legally acceptable representative) has been informed of all pertinent
             aspects of the study

         14. Willingness and ability to comply with the scheduled visits, treatment plan,
             laboratory tests and other study procedures

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Presence of active infections (e.g. requiring antibiotic therapy) or other severe
             concurrent disease, which, in the opinion of the investigator, would place the
             patient at undue risk or would interfere with the study objectives or conduct.

          2. Pregnancy, lactation or unwillingness to use adequate contraceptive methods.

          3. Active or latent tuberculosis (TB)

          4. Chronic active hepatitis or active autoimmune diseases other than RA

          5. History of currently active primary or secondary immunodeficiency

          6. HIV Infection

          7. Acute or chronic-active infection with HBV or HCV

          8. Evidence of active malignant disease at screening or advanced malignancies diagnosed
             within the previous 5 years

          9. Any previous treatment with alkylating agents, such as cyclophosphamide or
             chlorambucil or with total lymphoid irradiation

         10. History within the last year of acute or subacute coronary syndromes including
             myocardial infarction, unstable or severe stable angina pectoris

         11. Treatment with warfarin or other coumarin derivatives

         12. Heart insufficiency (&gt; Grade II, New York Heart Association (NYHA) criteria)

         13. Irreversible cardiac arrhythmias requiring permanent medication

         14. Clinically significant (to clinical investigator's discretion) abnormalities in
             baseline MUGA, ECHO or ECG analyses

         15. Uncontrolled hypertension

         16. Ischemic peripheral vascular disease (Grade IIb-IV)

         17. Severe diabetic retinopathy

         18. Major trauma including surgery within 4 weeks of administration of study treatment

         19. Known history of allergy or other intolerance to IL10, methotrexate, folic acid or
             other drugs based on human proteins/peptides/antibodies

         20. In vivo exposure to monoclonal antibodies for biological therapy (e.g. etanercept,
             adalimumab and infliximab) 8 weeks prior to administration of study medication

         21. Treatment with any investigational agent within the 6 weeks before study treatment

         22. Immunization with a live/attenuated vaccine within 4 weeks prior to baseline

         23. Growth factors or immunomodulatory agents within 7 days of the administration of
             study treatment

         24. Neuropathy &gt; Grade 1 or Neuropathies or other painful conditions (not RA-related)
             that might interfere with pain evaluation

         25. Patients required to be treated with corticosteroids at a dose &gt; 10 mg/day or with
             immunosuppressant drugs other than MTX on a long-term basis. Limited use of
             corticosteroids to treat or prevent acute hypersensitivity reactions is not
             considered an exclusion criterion.

         26. History of alcohol, drug or chemical substance abuse within the 6 months prior to
             screening

         27. Body weight of &gt;100 kg

         28. Any condition that in the opinion of the investigator could hamper compliance with
             the study protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michele Maio, Dr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria Senese</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Leonardo Giovannoni, Dr</last_name>
    <phone>(0039) 0577 588539</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Policlinico San Matteo Pavia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pavia</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Roberto Caporali, Dr.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Roberto Caporali, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Pisa</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pisa</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stefano Bombardieri, Prof.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stefano Bombardieri, Prof</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera San Camillo Forlanini Roma</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Giandomenico Sebastiani, Dr.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Giandomenico Sebastiani, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria Senese</name>
      <address>
        <city>Siena</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mauro Galeazzi, Prof.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mauro Galeazzi, prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 26, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 24, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>F8</keyword>
  <keyword>IL10</keyword>
  <keyword>Interleukin</keyword>
  <keyword>monoclonal</keyword>
  <keyword>antibody</keyword>
  <keyword>Rheumatoid Arthritis</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
