<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="134619">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02077179</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OBGY-249-14</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02077179</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Health Improvement After Pregnancy (HIP) Program Randomized Control Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>HIP</acronym>
  <official_title>Health Improvement After Pregnancy (HIP) Program Randomized Control Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Queen's University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Queen's University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Ethics Review Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Recent Canadian studies, public opinion polls and the Canadian Heart Health Strategy and
      Action Plan state that women's heart health is a key national priority; it should be
      addressed through improving heart health awareness and prevention, and reducing care
      inequities for women in general and younger women in particular. Given the costs of treating
      heart disease and screening for it, new and unique ways to identify women who should undergo
      screening are needed to achieve this goal. Studies have demonstrated that the development of
      pre-eclampsia (PET), gestational hypertension (GHTN), or gestational diabetes (GDM) in
      pregnancy, is associated with a greater risk of developing heart disease and stroke
      suggesting that these conditions and heart disease share a common cause. As previously
      demonstrated, the development of these pregnancy complications provides a window of
      opportunity for identifying women who have underlying heart disease risk factors. The
      investigators have developed an innovative and interactive mobile website based postpartum
      lifestyle modification program (regular physical activity and nutritional guidance), based
      on established national guidelines, to improve heart disease risk factors in women who
      developed PET, GHTN or GDM. The investigators will conduct a trial to determine if the
      mobile website based lifestyle modification program can be maintained and reduces a
      collection of risk factors, which occurring together, greatly increases the risk of
      developing heart disease. The investigators hypothesize that the interactive mobile website
      directing regular physical activity and personalized nutritional guidance, compared to
      standard postpartum care, will be motivational and result in a reduced modified metabolic
      syndrome z score at 8 months postpartum among the intervention group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Metabolic Syndrome Z Score</measure>
    <time_frame>32 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary outcome measure is the metabolic syndrome (MetS) z score, a continuous score of the five metabolic syndrome variables that make up the Adult Treatment Panel (ATP) III diagnostic criteria (waist circumference, blood pressure, high density lipoprotein, triglycerides and glucose). Differences between study arms will be compared.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to the HIP Program; Percent of Workouts Completed</measure>
    <time_frame>32 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Adherence to the HIP Program will be assessed based on the number of times a participant indicates using the mobile website that a prescribed workout has been completed. This outcome will only be measured in the intervention arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences in Biochemical Cardiovascular Risk Markers</measure>
    <time_frame>32 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Differences between study arms for the following biochemical cardiovascular risk markers will be assessed at 32 weeks postpartum; lipid profile, fasting glucose, glycated hemoglobin, high sensitivity C-reactive protein, and urine microalbumin creatinine ratio.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Anthropomorphic Measurements and Blood Pressure from Baseline at Midpoint</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure and weight from baseline measures at 6-8 weeks postpartum will be assessed at the midpoint of the program at 20 weeks postpartum. Differences between study arms will be compared.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Anthropomorphic Measurements and Blood Pressure from Baseline at Study Completion</measure>
    <time_frame>32 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure and weight from baseline measures at 6-8 weeks postpartum will be assessed at the midpoint of the program at 32 weeks postpartum. Differences between study arms will be compared.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Anthropomorphic Measurements and Blood Pressure from Midpoint to Study Completion</measure>
    <time_frame>32 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure, weight, body mass index, hip circumference, and waist circumference from midpoint measures at 20 weeks postpartum will be assessed at the end of the program at 32 weeks postpartum. Differences between study arms will be compared.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to the HIP Program; Percent of Step Counting Completed</measure>
    <time_frame>32 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Adherence to the HIP Program will be assessed based on the number of times a participant uses the mobile website to log their daily step count total. The number of times that the logged step count meets or exceeds the prescribed number of daily steps will also be assessed. This outcome will only be measured in the intervention arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to the HIP Program; Percent of Dietary Logs Completed</measure>
    <time_frame>32 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Adherence to the HIP Program will be assessed based on the number of times a participant uses the mobile website to enter the weekly dietary log. The number of times that the dietary log meets the prescribed intake for each of the Canada's Food Guide food groups will also be assessed.  This outcome will only be measured in the intervention arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">96</enrollment>
  <condition>Metabolic Cardiovascular Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this arm will receive care as per the usual standards from Kingston General Hospital and their primary care provider.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HIP Program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this arm will follow the HIP Program in addition to their usual care from Kingston General Hospital and their primary care provider.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HIP Program</intervention_name>
    <description>The entirety of the HIP Program is delivered through an interactive mobile website.
The physical activity portion of the program consists of daily step counting, prescribed aerobic activity, structured strength and toning workouts, and daily stretching. The program was designed by a local trainer, specializing in postnatal exercise, to increase gradually in intensity, while encouraging a more active lifestyle. The program is designed to be completed at home with minimal equipment.
The nutrition portion of the program consists of 16 video tutorials developed by a local Registered Dietitian and weekly diet logs. The video tutorials cover all aspects of healthy eating, from the basics of Canada's Food Guide, to smart snacking, to eating healthy over the holidays.</description>
    <arm_group_label>HIP Program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of Preeclampsia (PET), Gestational Hypertension (GHTN) or Gestational
             Diabetes (GDM) in their last pregnancy

          -  PET is defined as blood pressure ≥140/90 mmHg and proteinuria (≥300mg/24 hours or ≥30
             mg/mmol albumin:creatine random urine or ≥1+ on repeat dipstick)

          -  GHTN is defined as blood pressure ≥140/90 mmHg and no proteinuria

          -  GDM is defined as a glucose challenge test with a value of &gt;10.2 mmol/L or an oral
             glucose tolerance test with at least 1 abnormal value

          -  must own or have daily access to one or more of the following; smart phone, tablet or
             laptop computer

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous history of chronic hypertension, type 1 or 2 diabetes, renal disease or
             cardiovascular disease

          -  Living greater than 100km from Kingston General Hospital

          -  Having an existing and long term contraindication to exercise at the time of
             recruitment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Graeme N Smith, MD,PhD,FRCSC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Queen's University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Graeme N Smith, MD,PhD,FRCSC</last_name>
    <phone>613-548-2405</phone>
    <email>gns@queensu.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen's Unviersity</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kingston</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K7L 2V7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Graeme N Smith, MD,PhD,FRCSC</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith GN, Pudwell J, Roddy M. The Maternal Health Clinic: a new window of opportunity for early heart disease risk screening and intervention for women with pregnancy complications. J Obstet Gynaecol Can. 2013 Sep;35(9):831-9.</citation>
    <PMID>24099450</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cusimano MC, Pudwell J, Roddy M, Cho CK, Smith GN. The maternal health clinic: an initiative for cardiovascular risk identification in women with pregnancy-related complications. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2013 Dec 4. pii: S0002-9378(13)02159-5. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2013.12.001. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>24316270</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith GN, Pudwell J, Walker M, Wen SW. Risk estimation of metabolic syndrome at one and three years after a pregnancy complicated by preeclampsia. J Obstet Gynaecol Can. 2012 Sep;34(9):836-41.</citation>
    <PMID>22971452</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith GN, Pudwell J, Walker M, Wen SW. Ten-year, thirty-year, and lifetime cardiovascular disease risk estimates following a pregnancy complicated by preeclampsia. J Obstet Gynaecol Can. 2012 Sep;34(9):830-5.</citation>
    <PMID>22971451</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith GN, Walker MC, Liu A, Wen SW, Swansburg M, Ramshaw H, White RR, Roddy M, Hladunewich M; Pre-Eclampsia New Emerging Team (PE-NET). A history of preeclampsia identifies women who have underlying cardiovascular risk factors. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2009 Jan;200(1):58.e1-8. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2008.06.035. Epub 2008 Aug 8.</citation>
    <PMID>18691690</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 26, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Queen's University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Graeme Smith</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor and Head of Obstetrics and Gynecology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Postpartum</keyword>
  <keyword>Preeclampsia</keyword>
  <keyword>Gestational Hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>Gestational Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise Intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Dietary Intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Behavioral Intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Mobile Website</keyword>
  <keyword>Mobile Application</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Syndrome X</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
