<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="82383">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02009748</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VITDZIRR</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02009748</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Vitamin D Supplementation in Cirrhotic Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Vitamin D Supplementation in Cirrhotic Patients: A Randomized, Multi-center, Double-blind, Placebo Controlled Trial to Evaluate Vitamin D Supplementation on Serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D Levels in Cirrhotic Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical University of Graz</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of Graz</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Austria: Federal Office for Safety in Health Care</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Previous studies suggested that vitamin D deficiency is highly prevalent in cirrhotic
      patients and is related to the degree of liver dysfunction as well as mortality. In
      gastrointestinal disorders, vitamin D absorption can be highly reduced.

      We herein aim to investigate the efficacy of oral vitamin D supplementation in cirrhotic
      patients with vitamin D insufficiency.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cirrhosis of the liver is a slowly progressive disease with a high number of complications
      like hepatic encephalopathy, gastrointestinal bleeding, ascites, renal failure and
      hepatocellular cancer leading to death. Cirrhosis as a cause of death has increased
      progressively in the mortality data for the general population.

      This terminal liver disease as a complication of chronic viral hepatitis, alcoholism and
      metabolic disorders, with genetic and non-genetic predisposition, may be linked to
      nutritional aberration as a precursor to or an effect of the illness. Previous studies
      suggested that chronic liver diseases may be related to high prevalence of vitamin D
      deficiency and in gastrointestinal disorders the vitamin D absorption can be highly reduced.

      Patients with cirrhosis are often presented with malnutrition and one of the limiting
      factors of the intestinal malabsorption is the portal hypertension due to the liver disease.
      Beside nutrition the main source of vitamin D is sunlight and ultraviolet-B inducing the
      conversion of 7-dehydrocholesterol to vitamin D in the skin; therefore limited sunlight
      exposure of the skin may lead to an inadequate vitamin D status.

      Vitamin D itself is biologically inactive and has to be hydroxylated in the liver to
      25-hydroxyvitamin D (25(OH)D) as the main circulating metabolite used for classification of
      the vitamin D status. 1,25 hydroxyvitamin D (1,25(OH)D) is produced through conversion by
      the enzyme 1-alpha-hydroxylase in the kidney. This vitamin D metabolite shows a higher
      affinity for the vitamin D receptor (VDR) compared to 25(OH)D. After binding and activation
      of the VDR three percent of the human genome will be regulated.  Among the main role of
      vitamin D metabolites to regulate calcium and bone homeostasis, they also show non-skeletal
      effects with relevance in the development of several chronic diseases. In this context,
      vitamin D deficiency has been associated with an increased risk of cancer , cardiovascular,
      autoimmune, and infectious diseases,  Based on these findings, a significantly reduced risk
      of mortality was shown in patients with oral vitamin D supplementation in randomized
      controlled studies.

      Our previously published study presented a prospective association of vitamin D levels with
      occurrence of hepatic decompensation. Furthermore vitamin D deficiency was associated with
      high mortality in cirrhotic patients dependent on liver dysfunction. Concerning this aspect
      the main point is to investigate in this study whether low vitamin D status is the
      consequence of increasing deterioration of the liver synthesis or may even contribute to
      liver dysfunction. Low synthesis of vitamin D in the skin can be the result of reduced
      sunlight exposure and malnutrition and/or malabsorption in cirrhotic patients. On the other
      hand, organ dysfunction may impair the activity of 25-hydroxylase in the liver.  Despite the
      above mentioned correlation between vitamin D deficiency and liver dysfunction there is
      still insufficient evidence to recommend oral vitamin D supplementation as a concomitant
      therapy in clinical practice because there exists no adequately designed randomized
      controlled trial that evaluates the necessary daily oral dose on vitamin D.

      We aim to address this issue in the present study so that the findings of our study will
      lead to implementation of treatment strategies for maintaining a sufficient vitamin D status
      in cirrhotic patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>serum 25(OH)D</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks after study start</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Liver function tests</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks after study start</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Albumin, prothrombin time, bilirubin</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hyaluronic acid</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks after study start</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Cirrhosis</condition>
  <condition>Vitamin D Deficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin D supplementation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Colecalciferol 2.800 IU/day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Vehicle (coconut oil)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vitamin  D supplementation</intervention_name>
    <description>oral administration of colecalciferol 2.800 IU once daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin D supplementation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>oral administration of placebo (vehicle) once daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  25(OH)D levels below 30 ng/ml (measured at the baseline visit)

          -  Compensated and decompensated cirrhosis diagnosed by the hepatologist for at last
             three months prior to study start

          -  Age between 18 and 75 years

          -  Written informed consent

          -  Negative pregnancy test in women of childbearing potential

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Hypercalcemia defined as total serum calcium &gt;2.65 mmol/L

          -  Pregnancy or lactating women

          -  Drug intake as part of another clinical study

          -  Glomerular filtration rate (GFR) &lt; 15 ml/min/1.73m²

          -  Any disease with an estimated life expectancy below 1 year

          -  Any clinically significant acute disease requiring drug treatment

          -  Anticipated chemotherapy or radiation therapy during the study

          -  Regular intake of more than 800 International Units (IU) of vitamin D during the last
             4 weeks before study entry
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rudolf E Stauber, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dept of Internal Medicine, Medical University of Graz</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rudolf E Stauber, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0043316385</phone>
    <phone_ext>80268</phone_ext>
    <email>rudolf.stauber@medunigraz.at</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Internal Medicine, LKH Hoergas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gratwein</city>
        <state>Styria</state>
        <zip>8112</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Csilla Putz-Bankuti, MD</last_name>
      <phone>00433124501</phone>
      <phone_ext>2549</phone_ext>
      <email>csilla.putz-bankuti@lkh-hoergas.at</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Csilla Putz-Bankuti, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Internal Medicine, Medical University of Graz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Graz</city>
        <state>Styria</state>
        <zip>8036</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rudolf E Stauber, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0043316385</phone>
      <phone_ext>80268</phone_ext>
      <email>rudolf.stauber@medunigraz.at</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rudolf E Stauber, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Walter Spindelboeck, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stefan Pilz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 9, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 9, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical University of Graz</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rudolf Stauber, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Univ. Prof. Dr. med.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Cirrhosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin D Deficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamin D</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ergocalciferols</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
