<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="100643">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01664559</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>WRHR 5K12001259-12 - toradol</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01664559</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pain Control for Intrauterine Device Placement: A Trial of Ketorolac Prior to Intrauterine Device Placement</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pain Control for Intrauterine Device Placement: A Randomized, Double Blind Control Trial of Ketorolac Prior to Intrauterine Device Placement.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lynn Ngo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Diego</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Intrauterine device (IUD) placement can be painful for patients during and after the
      procedure. Fear of pain from IUD insertion can be a barrier to obtaining this highly
      effective long acting reversible contraception. Currently there are no proven effective
      methods for reduction of pain during and after placement of modern IUDs (Mirena IUD and
      Paragard IUD). Ketorolac has not been studied in regards to decreasing pain during and after
      IUD insertion although it is used by some providers for this purpose. It is a strong NSAID
      that is indicated for the treatment of moderate acute pain. In the intramuscular form it has
      an analgesia onset of action at 30min, thus may be a plausible option for pain management in
      the office setting compared to oral NSAIDs, which have a longer time to onset of analgesia
      and have not been proven to be effective in reducing pain associated with IUD placement. The
      primary aim of this study is to determine whether ketorolac (Toradol) decreases pain
      associated with intrauterine device placement compared to placebo. We hypothesize that
      administration of ketorolac 30mg intramuscularly at least 30 minutes prior to IUD insertion
      will decrease pain scores by at least 20mm on a  visual analog scale at various time points
      during IUD insertion when compared to placebo of normal saline injection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Modern intrauterine devices are highly effective long acting reversible forms of
      contraception. The Mirena IUD is 99.8% effective and the Paragard copper IUD is 99.2%
      effective in preventing pregnancy (Zieman 2010). Fear of intrauterine device placement can
      be a barrier to obtaining this highly effective form of birth control. The current standard
      of care for pain management during and after IUD placement is no medication, as randomized
      control trials published to date have limited data regarding use of medications to decrease
      pain. There has been one trial to suggest that the use of naproxen with 1% lidocaine
      paracervical block compared to paracervical block alone may decrease pain after IUD
      placement in primarily nulliparous patients. However, this study was with the much wider and
      no longer available Dalkon Shield IUD. In addition, this study did not show any significant
      decrease in pain scores during IUD placement (Massey 1974). Studies to evaluate
      effectiveness of motrin and misoprostol have shown no significant decrease in pain scores
      during and after IUD insertion, although the majority of participants in these studies were
      multiparous (Jensen 1998, Hubacher 2006, Saav 1997). There is some suggestion that 2%
      lidocaine gel one minute prior to IUD insertion may have some decrease in pain, although
      this study was poorly designed (Oloto 1996).

      There have been no studies published to date regarding the use of ketorolac for decreasing
      pain during and after IUD placement. Ketorolac is an acetic acid NSAID that reversibly
      inhibits COX 1 and 2, leading to decreased formation of prostaglandin precursors, and is
      indicated for the use of moderate acute pain in the short term setting. Its administration
      in the office setting may be good option for providers since intramuscular administration
      leads to analgesia beginning at 30 minutes, maximal effect 1 to 2 hours after
      administration, and duration of analgesia approximately 4 to 6 hours for the 30mg
      intramuscular injection.

      Although there is no standard of care in regards to pain medication administration prior to
      IUD placement, providers at UCSD often suggest certain options. These include ibuprofen at
      least one hour prior to the procedure, or ibuprofen taken within a few hours after the
      procedure, or ketorolac injection at least 15-30 minutes prior to the procedure. It would be
      beneficial for providers to have an evidence based option for patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>VAS (Visual Analogue Scale) measurement of pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated pain, prior to study drug administration, Pain with study drug administration, Speculum placement, Tenaculum placement, Uterine sounding, With intrauterine device placement, 5 min after IUD placement,15 min after IUD placement</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The patient will mark their pain on a 100mm visual analogue scale at 8 different time points as listed above. In addition, at the end of the study they will be offered acetaminophen prior to leaving the office. Their charts will also be assessed to determine if they called in for any additional stronger pain medications within the first 24 hours.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-insertion patient questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>assessed at 15 minutes after IUD insertion</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Questions assessed in multiple choice format:
Side effects
injection site pain
overall satisfaction with IUD insertion experience
would they still recommend IUD placement to a friend?
significant pain for which they desired acetaminophen prior to leaving the office?</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-insertion Provider Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after completion of IUD placement</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The provider will be asked to fill out a multiple choice format questionnaire:
what level training are you?
which IUD was inserted?
what was the purpose of IUD placement?
what was the position of the uterus?
did the IUD placement process require cervical dilation?
were you unable to complete the IUD insertion?
was there bleeding from the cervix that required more than 5 min to control?
were there any major complications with the IUD insertion?
did the patient take tylenol prior to leaving the office?</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">66</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain Control With IUD Insertion</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo with 1cc normal saline IM</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>If the patient is randomized to the placebo arm, they will receive 1cc of normal saline via the intramuscular route.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Toradol, 30mg in 1cc IM</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>If the patient is randomized to the toradol (ketorolac) arm, they will receive 30mg of toradol in a 1cc volume via the intramuscular route.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ketorolac</intervention_name>
    <description>Ketorolac 30mg intramuscular injection, 1cc volume</description>
    <arm_group_label>Toradol, 30mg in 1cc IM</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Brand name: toradol</other_name>
    <other_name>Serial # (01) 1 030409 379649 7</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Normal Saline</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo arm, 1cc of normal saline, 0.9%, intramuscular injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo with 1cc normal saline IM</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>REF# 196604</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Nulliparous and multiparous women ages 18-50, who are English or Spanish speaking,
             who present for intrauterine device placement for contraception or menorrhagia (in
             the case of Mirena IUD insertion).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Any diagnosed chronic pain issues (i.e. fibromyalgia, endometriosis, dysmenorrhea,
             irritable bowel syndrome, interstitial cystitis)

          -  If the patient has taken any pain medications within 6 hours of enrollment, including
             aspirin or other NSAIDs

          -  Misoprostol administration within 24 hours of enrollment

          -  History of prior IUD insertion

          -  Known allergy to NSAIDs including diagnosis of aspirin or NSAID induced asthma or
             urticaria

          -  Known contraindications to NSAIDs, such as the following medications that are risk
             category D (consider therapy modification) or X (avoid combination) including

               -  bile acid sequestrants (D - may decrease absorption of NSAIDs)

               -  cyclosporine (D - NSAIDs may enhance the nephrotoxic effects)

               -  drotrecogin alfa (D - NSAIDs may enhance the adverse/toxic effects, cause
                  bleeding)

               -  floctafenine (X - may enhance adverse/toxic effect of NSAIDs)

               -  lithium (D - NSAIDs may decrease serum concentration)

               -  methotrexate (D - NSAIDs may decrease excretion)

               -  pentoxifylline (X - Ketorolac may enhance adverse/toxic effects)

               -  probenecid (X - may increase serum concentration of Ketorolac)

               -  rivaroxaban (D - Anti-platelet drugs may enhance anti-coagulation effect)

               -  SSRIs (D - may enhance the anti-platelet effect of NSAIDs, NSAIDs may diminish
                  the therapeutic effect of SSRIs)

               -  warfarin (D - NSAIDs may enhance the anti-coagulation effect)

          -  Renal insufficiency (by history and/or chart review)

          -  Peptic ulcer disease or history of significant gastrointestinal bleeding

          -  Known thrombocytopenia, known coagulopathy, or known bleeding disorder

          -  Known contraindications to IUD
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lynn L Ngo, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Diego</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sheila Mody, MD MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Diego</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lynn L Ngo, MD</last_name>
    <phone>6195437878</phone>
    <email>l3ngo@ucsd.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sheila Mody, MD MPH</last_name>
    <phone>619 5437878</phone>
    <email>smody@ucsd.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California San Diego</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lynn Ngo, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sheila Mody, MD MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allen RH, Bartz D, Grimes DA, Hubacher D, O'Brien P. Interventions for pain with intrauterine device insertion. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2009 Jul 8;(3):CD007373. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19588429</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roche NE, Li D, James D, Fechner A, Tilak V. The effect of perioperative ketorolac on pain control in pregnancy termination. Contraception. 2012 Mar;85(3):299-303. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2011.10.001. Epub 2011 Nov 30.</citation>
    <PMID>22133656</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Edelman AB, Schaefer E, Olson A, Van Houten L, Bednarek P, Leclair C, Jensen JT. Effects of prophylactic misoprostol administration prior to intrauterine device insertion in nulliparous women. Contraception. 2011 Sep;84(3):234-9. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2011.01.016. Epub 2011 Mar 3.</citation>
    <PMID>21843686</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 9, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 28, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Diego</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lynn Ngo</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Resident Physician</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>intrauterine device</keyword>
  <keyword>ketorolac</keyword>
  <keyword>toradol</keyword>
  <keyword>mirena</keyword>
  <keyword>paragard</keyword>
  <keyword>pain control</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ketorolac</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ketorolac Tromethamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
