<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="11551">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01846806</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>10-00570</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01846806</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Role of Bacterial Overgrowth and Delayed Intestinal Transit in Hepatic Encephalopathy.</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Role of Bacterial Overgrowth and Delayed Intestinal Transit in Hepatic Encephalopathy. Phase A: Breath Testing and Colonic Transit in Hepatic Encephalopathy. Phase B: The Effect of Rifaximin on Bacterial Overgrowth and Severity of Hepatic Encephalopathy in Patients With Severe Hepatic Encephalopathy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Salix Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective study designed to examine the role of bacterial overgrowth and delayed
      intestinal transit and the effect of Rifaximin with hepatic encephalopathy (HE). This study
      is divided into Phase A and Phase B. The purpose of Phase A is to test patients with
      cirrhosis to determine if they have bacterial overgrowth which may lead to slow intestinal
      transit and hepatic encephalopathy. The purpose of Phase B is to investigate whether the
      improvement found in patients with hepatic encephalopathy taking Rifaximin is also related
      to decreased bacterial overgrowth. The target population is patients with chronic liver
      cirrhosis with or without symptoms of HE. Many patients may present with advanced cirrhosis
      and may be on the liver transplant list.

      During Phase A, 20 patients will be asked to sign the informed consent form and will be
      assigned a subject number. They will be asked to provide demographic information, medical
      history, history of hospitalizations for HE, and HE medication use. They will undergo a
      complete physical examination, urine pregnancy test (women of childbearing potential),
      12-lead EKG, grading of ascites, modified Child Pugh Score, MELD Score. They will also
      complete the following neuropsychological questionnaires: NCT, D-KEFS Trail Making Test,
      California Verbal Learning Test, WAIS-III Digit Symbol-Coding and Block Design, D-KEFS
      Stroop Color-Word Test, Evaluation of Constructional Apraxia, , and asterixis. During the
      evaluatin visit (a minimum of 3 days after the Screening Visit) the following procedures
      will be performed: lab tests (chemistry and hematology panels). They will also complete the
      following questionnaires: Liver Disease Quality of Life Questionnaire, Fisk Fatigue Impact
      Score, Flatulence Survey, Epworth Sleepiness Scale. Finally, they will undergo a Lactulose
      Hydrogen Breath Test: This test is designed to evaluate both intestinal transit and
      bacterial overgrowth.

      Participants in Phase B will be administered of 550 mg of Rifaximin two times a day for 14
      days. Patients will be scheduled to come in on day 14 of the active study period.  The
      follow up visit is day 28, where some of the tests described above will be repeated. During
      Phase B, patients will be asked to undergo a complete physical examination, a Neurological
      Examination [including calculation of modified Child Pugh and MELD Score NCT, and  Trail
      Making Test], evaluation of constructional apraxia and asterixis. In addition, the
      researchers will make sure the patient meets eligibility criteria for participation in open
      label trial of Rifaximin. They will be administered the first dose study drug (Rifaximin) by
      study coordinator or investigator and they will be dispensed the study drug needed for the
      remainder of the trial and a diary for them to record daily flatulence. A urine pregnancy
      test will be performed within 48 hours of first study dose (for women of childbearing
      potential). During Day 14 and Day 28 visits, patients will have 1 tablespoon of blood drawn
      for measurement of the ammonia level and to monitor for potential blood clots. They will
      complete the NCT, Trails Test, Digit Symbol-Coding, Block Design, and Stroop Tests. They
      will also complete the Liver Disease Quality of Life Questionnaire, Fisk Fatigue Impact
      Score, Flatulence Survey (A diary will be provided to the patient with instructions on how
      to record flatulence experiences on a daily basis), and the Epworth Sleepiness Scale
      questionnaires. In addition, on Day 14, they will undergo another Lactulose Hydrogen Breath
      Test.

      Subjects' mental capacity will be assessed at each visit via interview, brief mental status,
      questionnaires and psychometric evaluation. Any subject who appears to have lost capacity to
      continue participation, as evidenced by HE grade 2 or higher, a lack of attentiveness,
      concentration, or understanding of evaluation, will be discontinued from the study. Female
      subjects of childbearing potential will be asked to comply with the use of contraception
      during the Phase B study period as well as throughout the time they remain on study drug.

      Following completion of the study, patients will be categorized by the degree of HE. To
      determine whether impaired intestinal transit and bacterial overgrowth are associated with
      severity of HE, multivariate analysis will be performed to determine whether the independent
      factors of liver disease severity, intestinal transit, and bacterial overgrowth are
      significant predictors of the presence and severity of HE. Also, to determine whether
      treatment with Rifaximin improves bacterial overgrowth, ammonia levels, and HE, changes in
      Breath Test analysis be correlated will be correlated with changes in ammonia levels and HE.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Laboratory results</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Results will be evaluated for the following lab tests: blood chemistry (including ammonia and other potential toxins) and hematology panels</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Lactulose Hydrogen Breath Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 3 and Day 14</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This test is designed to evaluate both intestinal transit and bacterial overgrowth.  Subjects will be asked to breathe into a collection bag, drink 10g of lactulose that has been mixed with 8 oz of water, breathe again into the collection bag after waiting 20 minutes and then again every 10 minutes for a total of 2 hours.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 3, Day 14, and Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants will be asked to rate levels of depression, fatigue, and sleepiness, as well as decreases or increases in their quality of life.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatic Encephalopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rifaximin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in Phase B will be administered 550 mg of Rifaximin two times a day for 14 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rifaximin</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in Phase B will be administered 550 mg of Rifaximin two times a day for 14 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rifaximin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ambulatory patients with HCV cirrhosis will be screened for participation in the
             study

          -  Ability to complete Number Connection Test

          -  Creatinine &lt;1.5mg/dL

          -  Able to provide informed consent

          -  Patients determined to possibly meet the West Haven criteria grade 0 or 1 for HE

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Active interferon therapy

          -  History of alcohol abuse within six months

          -  Active gastrointestinal bleeding

          -  Use of agents that alter intestinal motility, e.g., methadone, cholestyramine,
             Tricyclic antidepressants, etc.

          -  Use of Neomycin or other antibiotics within the past 2 weeks

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Unable to provide informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Samuel Sigal, M</last_name>
    <phone>212-263-3643</phone>
    <email>samuel.sigal@nyumc.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NYU Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Samuel Sigal, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-263-3643</phone>
      <email>samuel.sigal@nyumc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Samuel Sigal, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 12, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 1, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hepatic Encephalopathy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatic Encephalopathy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Damage, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Delirium</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Encephalitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neurotoxicity Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Rifaximin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
