<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="137863">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01894581</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-1420</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U54HD058155-05</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01894581</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Dietary Omega-3 Fatty Acids on Reproductive Hormones in Obese Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Dietary Omega-3 Fatty Acids on Reproductive Hormones in Obese Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The United States has the highest prevalence of obesity among all countries surveyed in 2012
      by the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development. Maternal obesity is linked
      with anovulation, menstrual cycle abnormalities, subfertility, fetal loss, obstetrical
      complications and congenital anomalies. Changes in reproductive hormones and diminished
      oocyte quality have also been demonstrated. A gap of knowledge exists as the mechanisms
      underlying these harmful effects are poorly understood and no specific treatments exist.

      This proposal will test the hypothesis that dietary omega-3 FA will improve the output of
      hypothalamicpituitary- ovarian axis in obese women. The investigators will perform paired
      assessments before and after supplementation in 10 obese and 10 normal weight women. To test
      the pituitary and hypothalamic output, the investigators will examine the luteinizing
      hormone (LH) and follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) responsiveness during frequent blood
      sampling. To test the corpus luteum function, the investigators will examine urinary
      reproductive hormones (E1c, estrone conjugates, and Pdg, pregnanediol glucuronide) over an
      entire menstrual cycle. Our ultimate goal is to collect preliminary data for an adequately
      powered randomized control trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pituitary and hypothalamic output</measure>
    <time_frame>10 minute intervals during 8 hour blood sampling studies. Subjects will undergo two menstrual cycles of study, one prior to dietary supplementation and one after supplementation.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To test the pituitary and hypothalamic output, we will examine the LH and FSH secretion (unstimulated and in response to gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) stimulation) during 8-hour blood sampling studies at 10 min intervals.The primary outcome measure is the change in the average LH pulse amplitude (or mass for deconvolution output) for each patient. The average change in pulse amplitude within each group will be compared using a paired t-test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Corpus luteum function</measure>
    <time_frame>Daily across two menstrual cycles, one prior to dietary supplementation and one after.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To test the corpus luteum function, we will examine daily excretion of urinary sex steroids (E1c, estrone conjugates, and Pdg, pregnanediol glucuronide) across the entire menstrual cycle.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Fertility</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Regimen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be instructed to take 2 grams twice daily of oral omega-3-acid ethyl esters (Lovaza) starting with day 1 to 3 of their menstrual period.  Each capsule contains 60mg of other omega-3 FA.  On day 1 of their subsequent menstrual period, subjects will be instructed to discontinue.
In early follicular phase (cycle day 3-6), an intravenous bolus of exogenous GnRH (75 ng/kg dosing based on total body weight) will be administered at 6 hours.  Pituitary gonadotropin response will be assessed (as described in C.2.3) to determine how dietary intervention alters pituitary sensitivity to GnRH.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LOVAZA</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will be instructed to take 2 grams twice daily of oral omega-3-acid ethyl esters (Lovaza) starting with day 1 to 3 of their menstrual period. Each capsule contains 60mg of other omega-3 FA. On day 1 of their subsequent menstrual period, subjects will be instructed to discontinue.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Regimen</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Omega-3-acid ethyl esters</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GnRH</intervention_name>
    <description>An intravenous bolus of exogenous GnRH (75 ng/kg dosing based on total body weight) will be administered at 6 hours.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Regimen</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Gonadorelin (GnRH)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 18-42 at study entry

          2. Regular menstrual cycles every 25-40 days

          3. BMI at least 30 kg/m2 (obese) or between 18.5 and 25 kg/m2 (normal)

          4. Good general health

          5. Prolactin and thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH) within normal laboratory ranges at
             screening, baseline hemoglobin &gt;11 gm/dl.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Diagnosis of polycystic ovary syndrome (by ultrasound or hyperandrogenic symptoms)

          2. Fish or seafood allergy or hypersensitivity (e.g., anaphylactic reaction) to
             omega-3-acid ethyl esters or any component of the formulation

          3. Coagulopathy or receiving therapeutic anticoagulation (due to potential for
             interaction with omega-3 FA)

          4. History of chronic disease affecting hormone production, metabolism or clearance
             (including diabetes mellitus) or abnormal renal or liver function at screening
             Current use of thiazolidinediones or metformin(known to interact with reproductive
             hormones)

          5. Use of hormones affecting hypothalamic output (HPO) axis (such as hormonal
             contraceptives) within three months of entry

          6. Strenuous exercise (&gt;4 hours of intense physical activity per week)

          7. Pregnancy, breast-feeding or current active attempts to conceive

          8. History of significant recent weight loss or gain
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>42 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alex Polotsky, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Denver</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Celeste Robledo</last_name>
    <phone>303-724-2046</phone>
    <email>celeste.robledo@ucdenver.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mallary Adams</last_name>
    <phone>303-724-2064</phone>
    <email>MALLARY.CROWADAMS@UCDENVER.EDU</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Denver Anschutz Medical Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chanel Ahrendsen, BBA</last_name>
      <phone>303-724-6501</phone>
      <email>chanel.ahrendsen@ucdenver.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alex Polotsky, MD, MS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 9, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 3, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hormones</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
