<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="134446">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01844479</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HUM00059211</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HUM00059211</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01844479</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Multi-layer Insoles for a Patient-specific Approach to Shear and Pressure Reduction in Diabetes-related Foot Ulcer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Multi-material, Layer, and Density Insoles for a Patient-specific Approach to Shear and Pressure Reduction in the Treatment and Prevention of Diabetes-related Foot Ulcer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this pilot study, the first objective is to bench test a novel shear reducing insole and
      compare it to current standard insoles and shoes.  The second objective is to study
      twenty-seven insensate diabetes patients with pre-ulcerative foot callus to examine for
      changes in spatial temporal gait including gait initiation, risk of falling, static and
      dynamic balance, and plantar temperature response to walking and consecutive plantar stress
      in both footwear conditions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Device Description: The Dynamic Foot Orthosis (DFO) is designed with a rolling link
      mechanism at the distal 3rd. It is designed to reduce sliding friction and torque at the
      metatarsal heads in addition to decreasing compressive forces that is accomplished by the
      conventional multi-durometer FOs.  The relative sliding motion of two compliant surfaces
      over each other allows some deformation horizontally and lowers frictional resistance. The
      DFO addresses the friction element by accommodating the normal sliding and rolling motion at
      the distal 3rd of the foot during gait.  Additionally, the DFO has a silicone layer at the
      metatarsal head and the remainder of the anterior section made of 2 separated orthotic
      layers that slide over each other.  This provides an articulating surface to provide a
      relative motion between the orthotic segments while transmitting load.

      Study Objectives:  In this pilot study, the first objective is to bench test a novel shear
      reducing insole and compare it to current standard insoles and shoes.  The second objective
      is to study twenty-seven insensate diabetes patients with pre-ulcerative foot callus to
      examine for changes in spatial temporal gait including gait initiation, risk of falling,
      static and dynamic balance, and plantar temperature response to walking and consecutive
      plantar stress in both footwear conditions.

      Study Design:  This is an interventional study.  For objective one, changes in compression
      stiffness and static coefficients of friction will be measured using a force dynamometer in
      the lab of Professor Albert Shih.  A test platform will be built to evaluate the performance
      of the shear reduction shoe sole design and characteristic of the force, in two directions
      parallel (shear) and perpendicular to the ground, and the associated deformation under the
      steady-state and impulse conditions.

      For objective two, diabetes patients presenting to the Michigan Orthotics and Prosthetics
      Center for fabrication and dispensing of diabetic shoes and innersoles will be invited to
      participate.  Twenty-seven insensate diabetes patients with pre-ulcerative foot callus will
      be enrolled.  Patients will wear body worn sensors (LegSys) to measure changes in
      spatial-temporal gait and static and dynamic balance parameters prior and post usage of the
      insoles.  To reduce the effects of learning from naïve use of novel footwear, the testing
      sequence between the experimental and standard footwear will be randomized.  We will examine
      increase on foot temperature over 200 steps of continuous walking using the DFO and using
      standard insoles.  We will also examine if the thermal changes are mediated by autonomic
      neuropathy as measured by sudomotor function.  The footwear testing sequence will be
      randomized and an acclimatization procedure will be followed in an effort to minimize the
      potential effects of cumulative plantar temperature responses to walking and footwear
      conditions.   We will also examine static balance by measuring center of mass with eyes open
      and eyes closed condition.

      Outcome Measures:  For objective one, the primary endpoints will be the compression
      stiffness and static coefficients of friction.  For objective two, plantar foot temperature
      changes in regions-of-interest in response to walking 200 steps will be measured in each
      footwear condition and compared to baseline.  Other outcome measures include gait analysis,
      including gait initiation, gait speed, double support time, medial and lateral center of
      mass displacement, and inter-cycle variability under single and dual task conditions.  This
      will be measured during each footwear condition.  Static balance will also be measured in
      each footwear condition.  Using the Romberg's test, we will also assess center of mass
      displacement and reciprocal hip and ankle motion under eyes open and closed conditions.
      Sudomotor function will be measured by electrical sweat conductance (ESC), as expressed in
      microSiemens (µS).

      Safety Evaluation: All subjects who sign the informed consent form and are determined to be
      eligible for treatment will be included in the analysis of safety.  Collection,
      classification and summary analysis of adverse events will be performed.

      Duration of Participation: One visit lasting approximately 1 hour.

      Duration of Study: One year

      Inclusion Criteria: Patients will be included if they have diabetes and have been referred
      for diabetic shoes.  They will also be insensate with pre-ulcerative plantar callus or
      previous plantar foot ulcer.

      Exclusion Criteria:  Patients will be excluded if they are unable to independently walk 100
      feet, lower extremity prosthesis user, have active cellulitis, foot ulcer, or Charcot foot.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plantar foot temperature changes in regions-of-interest in response to walking</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and after 200 steps in each condition, this is a single visit study expected to last one hour</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Plantar foot temperature changes in regions-of-interest in response to walking 200 steps will be measured in each footwear condition and compared to baseline.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gait analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>200 steps each condition, this is a single visit study expected to last one hour</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Gait analysis, including gait initiation, gait speed, double support time, medial and lateral center of mass displacement, and inter-cycle variability under single and dual task conditions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Static balance</measure>
    <time_frame>in each condition, this is a single visit study expected to last one hour</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Static balance will also be measured in each footwear condition.  Using the Romberg's test, we will also assess center of mass displacement and reciprocal hip and ankle motion under eyes open and closed conditions.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sudomotor function</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline, this is a single visit study expected to last one hour</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Sudomotor function will be measured by electrical sweat conductance (ESC), as expressed in microSiemens (µS).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">27</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetic Foot Ulcer</condition>
  <condition>Diabetic Foot</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard innersole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The industry standard diabetic innersole will be used as the active comparator</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Diabetic Foot Orthotic</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Dynamic Foot Orthosis (DFO) is designed with a rolling link mechanism at the distal 3rd to reduce sliding friction at the metatarsal heads in addition to decreasing compressive forces. The relative sliding motion of two compliant surfaces over each other allows some deformation horizontally and lowers frictional resistance. The DFO addresses the friction element by accommodating the normal sliding and rolling motion at the distal 3rd of the foot during gait. Additionally, the DFO has a silicone layer at the metatarsal head and the remainder of the anterior section made of 2 separated orthotic layers that slide over each other. This provides an articulating surface to provide a relative motion between the orthotic segments while transmitting load.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>diabetic foot orthotic</intervention_name>
    <description>The Dynamic Foot Orthosis (DFO) is designed with a rolling link mechanism at the distal 3rd to reduce sliding friction at the metatarsal heads in addition to decreasing compressive forces.  The relative sliding motion of two compliant surfaces over each other allows some deformation horizontally and lowers frictional resistance. The DFO addresses the friction element by accommodating the normal sliding and rolling motion at the distal 3rd of the foot during gait.  Additionally, the DFO has a silicone layer at the metatarsal head and the remainder of the anterior section made of 2 separated orthotic layers that slide over each other.  This provides an articulating surface to provide a relative motion between the orthotic segments while transmitting load.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Diabetic Foot Orthotic</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>shear reducing innersole</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard innersole</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Standard innersole</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients will be included if they have diabetes and have been referred for diabetic
             shoes.  They will also be insensate with pre-ulcerative plantar callus or previous
             plantar foot ulcer.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients will be excluded if they are unable to independently walk 100 feet, lower
             extremity prosthesis user, have active cellulitis, foot ulcer, or Charcot foot.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James Wrobel, DPM, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UMHS</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Michigan Orthotics and Prosthetics</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48104-6768</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Belmont B, Wang Y, Ammanath P, Wrobel JS, Shih A. An apparatus to quantify anteroposterior and mediolateral shear reduction in shoe insoles, Journal of Diabetes Science and Technology. March 2013, 7(2); 410-419.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 20, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>James Wrobel, DPM, MS</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>diabetic foot ulcer</keyword>
  <keyword>diabetic foot</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Foot Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Foot</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
