<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="166577">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01989598</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2013-02148</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-02148</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI 9460</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>PHL-091</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>9460</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>N01CM00032</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01989598</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT01951495</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trametinib and Akt Inhibitor GSK2141795 in Treating Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2 Study of Sequential Trametinib and GSK2141795 in Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well trametinib and Akt inhibitor GSK2141795 works in
      treating patients with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma. Trametinib and Akt inhibitor
      GSK2141795 may stop the growth of cancer cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed for
      cell growth.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the antitumor activity of trametinib determined by overall response rate
      (ORR) in patients that are stratified into grouped based on: biomarker positive
      (neuroblastoma RAS viral [v-ras] oncogene homolog [NRAS], v-Ki-ras2 Kirsten rat sarcoma
      viral oncogene homolog [KRAS], v-raf murine sarcoma viral oncogene homolog B1 [BRAF]
      mutated) and biomarker negative (without NRAS, KRAS, BRAF mutation).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate progression free survival (PFS) and duration of response (DOR) in the two
      stratified groups.

      II. To document ORR after the addition of GSK2141795 (Akt inhibitor GSK2141795) to
      trametinib in patients who have developed progressive disease or have achieved less than a
      partial response (PR) after 4 cycles of treatment.

      III. To evaluate PFS and DOR in patients receiving trametinib plus GSK2141795. IV. To
      evaluate the safety profile of trametinib with and without GSK2141795.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To explore the relationship between clinical response and pharmacodynamic (PD) markers.

      II. To explore the relationship between v-maf avian musculoaponeurotic fibrosarcoma oncogene
      homolog (MAF) expression as determined by quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR),
      chromosomal abnormalities detected by florescence in situ hybridization (FISH), and clinical
      response.

      III. To explore the role of integrin beta7 as a biomarker of MAF expression. IV. To explore
      the relationship between objective clinical response as well as progressive disease and the
      tumor mutational profile.

      V. To explore mechanism of phosphatidylinositol 3 kinase (PI3K)/v-akt Murine Thymoma Viral
      Oncogene Homolog 1 (AKT) and retrovirus-associated deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) sequence
      (RAS)-mitogen-activated protein kinase kinase (MEK)-mitogen-activated protein kinase 1 (ERK)
      activation and correlate these with clinical response and PD markers.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive trametinib orally (PO) once daily (QD) on days 1-28. Courses repeat every
      28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients with
      progressive disease or who achieve less than PR after 4 courses may also receive Akt
      inhibitor GSK2141795 PO daily on days 1-28.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for 4 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>ORR evidenced by confirmed response rate, defined as partial response or better by International Myeloma Working Group (IMWG) criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The patient will be classified as having had a response if he/she has a confirmed response (i.e., a stringent complete response, or complete response or near complete response or very good partial response or partial response noted as the objective status of two consecutive assessments). The rate of minimal response (MR) and PD will also be observed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PFS</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from the date of start of treatment to the date of documented progression (based on IMWG criteria) or death due to any cause, assessed up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Summarized for each cohort using the Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>DOR</measure>
    <time_frame>Time measurement criteria are met for CR or PR (whichever is first recorded) until first date that recurrent or progressive disease is objectively documented or to death due to multiple myeloma, assessed up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Summarized for each cohort using the Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ORR after the addition of AKT inhibitor GSK2141795 to trametinib in patients who have developed progressive disease or have achieved less than a PR</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse event reactions reported according to CTCAE v4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Reported by type, frequency, and severity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic markers of trametinib</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, day 1 of course 2, progression</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Analyses will be descriptively summarized.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Quantification of MAF expression by qPCR and FISH</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Analyses will be descriptively summarized.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Chromosomal abnormalities as determined by FISH</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Analyses will be descriptively summarized.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cell surface expression of integrin beta 7 determined by flow cytometry on cluster of differentiation (CD)138 positive myeloma cells derived from screening bone marrow samples</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Analyses will be descriptively summarized.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor mutational profile by sequenom analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Analyses will be descriptively summarized.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in PI3K/AKT activation determined by phospho-flow cytometry and reversal phase protein arrays (RPPA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Analyses will be descriptively summarized.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in RAS-MEK-ERK activation determined by phospho-flow cytometry and RPPA</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Analyses will be descriptively summarized.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">74</enrollment>
  <condition>Refractory Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (trametinib, Akt inhibitor GSK2141795)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive trametinib orally PO QD on days 1-28. Courses repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients with progressive disease or who achieve less than PR after 4 courses may also receive Akt inhibitor GSK2141795 PO daily on days 1-28.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>trametinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (trametinib, Akt inhibitor GSK2141795)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>GSK1120212</other_name>
    <other_name>JTP-74057</other_name>
    <other_name>Mekinist</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Akt inhibitor GSK2141795</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (trametinib, Akt inhibitor GSK2141795)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>GSK2141795</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (trametinib, Akt inhibitor GSK2141795)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (trametinib, Akt inhibitor GSK2141795)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pharmacological studies</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histologically or cytologically confirmed multiple myeloma not
             otherwise specified (NOS) (10028566)

          -  Serum M-protein &gt;= 0.5 g/dl (&gt;= 5 g/l)

          -  Urine M-protein &gt;= 200 mg/24 h

          -  Serum free light chains (FLC) assay: involved FLC level &gt;= 10 mg/dl (&gt;= 100 mg/l) and
             an abnormal serum free light chain ratio (&lt; 0.26 or &gt; 1.65)

          -  Biopsy proven plasmacytoma (should be measured within 28 days of first study drug
             administration); prior biopsy is acceptable

          -  If the serum protein electrophoresis is unreliable for routine M-protein measurement,
             quantitative immunoglobulin levels on nephelometry or turbidimetry will be followed

          -  A diagnosis of multiple myeloma (MM) and documentation of relapsed or
             relapse/refractory status following at least 2 prior lines of therapy

          -  Documented lab results confirming tumor mutational status must be obtained at
             screening; patients in whom mutational status cannot be determined will be deemed
             ineligible

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status =&lt; 2 (Karnofsky &gt;= 60%)

          -  Life expectancy of greater than 6 months

          -  Able to swallow and retain orally-administered medication and does not have any
             clinically significant gastrointestinal abnormalities that may alter absorption such
             as malabsorption syndrome or major resection of the stomach or bowels

          -  All prior treatment-related toxicities must be Common Terminology Criteria for
             Adverse Events (CTCAE) version (v)4 grade =&lt; 1 (except alopecia) at the time of
             randomization

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1.0 x10^9/L

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 8 g/dL

          -  Platelets &gt;= 50 x 10^9/L

          -  Albumin &gt;= 2.5 g/dL

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x institutional upper limit of normal (ULN) (isolated
             bilirubin &gt; 1.5 x ULN is acceptable if bilirubin is fractionated and direct bilirubin
             &lt; 35%)

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) =&lt; 2.5 x
             institutional ULN

          -  Serum creatinine =&lt; 1.5 mg/dL OR calculated creatinine clearance (Cockroft-Gault
             formula) &gt;= 30 mL/min OR 24-hour urine creatinine clearance &gt;= 30 mL/min

          -  Prothrombin time (PT)/international normalized ratio (INR) and partial thromboplastin
             time (PTT) =&lt; 1.5 x institutional ULN

          -  Fasting serum glucose &lt; 126 mg/dl (7 mmol/l)

          -  Subjects that have been previously diagnosed with type 2 diabetes or steroid-induced
             diabetes must also meet the additional following criteria:

               -  Diagnosed with diabetes &gt;= 6 months prior to enrollment

               -  Hemoglobin A1C (HbAIC) =&lt; 8% at screening visit

               -  Left ventricular ejection fraction &gt;= institutional lower limit of normal (LLN)
                  by echocardiogram (ECHO) or multigated acquisition scan (MUGA)

          -  Women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
             (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry and
             for the duration of study participation; women of child-bearing potential must have a
             negative serum pregnancy test within 14 days prior to randomization; should a woman
             become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while she or her partner is participating
             in this study, she should inform her treating physician immediately; men treated or
             enrolled on this protocol must also agree to use adequate contraception prior to the
             study, for the duration of study participation, and 4 months after completion of
             trametinib administration

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of another malignancy; exception: patients who have been disease-free for 3
             years, or patients with a history of completely resected non-melanoma skin cancer
             and/or patients with indolent second malignancies, are eligible; consult the Cancer
             Therapy Evaluation Program (CTEP) medical monitor if unsure whether second
             malignancies meet the requirements specified above

          -  History of interstitial lung disease or pneumonitis

          -  Diabetes mellitus currently requiring insulin; subjects with a history of
             steroid-induced hyperglycemia may be enrolled provided that HbAIC at screening visit
             is =&lt; 8%

          -  Any major surgery, extensive radiotherapy, chemotherapy with delayed toxicity,
             biologic therapy, or immunotherapy within 28 days prior to randomization and/or daily
             or weekly chemotherapy or other approved anti-myeloma therapy without the potential
             for delayed toxicity within 14 days prior to randomization

          -  Use of other investigational drugs within 28 days preceding the first dose of
             trametinib and during the study

          -  Symptomatic or untreated leptomeningeal or brain metastases or spinal cord
             compression

          -  Have a known immediate or delayed hypersensitivity reaction or idiosyncrasy to drugs
             chemically related to trametinib or excipients or to dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) or
             GSK214795

          -  Current use of a prohibited medication; the following medications or non-drug
             therapies are prohibited:

               -  Other anti-cancer therapy while on study treatment; (note: megestrol [Megace] if
                  used as an appetite stimulant is allowed)

               -  Concurrent treatment with bisphosphonates is permitted; however, treatment must
                  be initiated prior to the first dose of study therapy; prophylactic use of
                  bisphosphonates in patients without bone disease is not permitted, except for
                  the treatment of osteoporosis

               -  Because the composition, pharmacokinetics (PK), and metabolism of many herbal
                  supplements are unknown, the concurrent use of all herbal supplements is
                  prohibited during the study (including, but not limited to, St. John's wort,
                  kava, ephedra [ma huang], gingko biloba, dehydroepiandrosterone [DHEA], yohimbe,
                  saw palmetto, or ginseng)

          -  In vitro data indicate that GSK2141795 is a cytochrome P450, family 3, subfamily A,
             polypeptide 4 (CYP3A4) substrate; drugs that potently inhibit CYP3A4 could lead to
             increased GSK2141795 exposure in subjects, and should either be prohibited or used
             with caution; drugs which are strong inducers of cytochrome P450, family 3, subfamily
             A (CYP3A) and may result in lower exposures of GSK2141795 should also be prohibited;
             GSK2141795 also appears to be a moderate in vitro inhibitor of cytochrome P450,
             family 2, subfamily C, polypeptide 8 (CYP2C8) (50% inhibitory concentration [IC50] 3
             mcM) and CYP3A4 (IC50 11 mcM); drugs that are substrates of CYP3A4 or CYP2C8 with a
             narrow therapeutic index may be prohibited; drugs that are sensitive substrates of
             CYP3A4 or CYP2C8 should be used with caution

          -  History or current evidence/risk of retinal vein occlusion (RVO) or central serous
             retinopathy (CSR):

               -  History of RVO or CSR, or predisposing factors to RVO or CSR (e.g., uncontrolled
                  glaucoma or ocular hypertension, uncontrolled systemic disease such as
                  hypertension, diabetes mellitus, or history of hyperviscosity or
                  hypercoagulability syndromes)

               -  Visible retinal pathology as assessed by ophthalmic exam that is considered a
                  risk factor for RVO or CSR such as evidence of new optic disc cupping, evidence
                  of new visual field defects, and intraocular pressure &gt; 21 mmHg

          -  History or evidence of cardiovascular risk including any of the following:

               -  Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &lt; LLN

               -  A QT interval corrected for heart rate using the Bazett's formula QTcB &gt;= 480
                  msec (&gt;= 500 msec for subjects with bundle branch block)

               -  History or evidence of current clinically significant uncontrolled arrhythmias
                  (exception: patients with controlled atrial fibrillation for &gt; 30 days prior to
                  randomization are eligible)

               -  Other clinically significant electrocardiogram (ECG) abnormalities including 2nd
                  degree (type II) or 3rd degree atrioventricular (AV) block

               -  Subject with intra-cardiac defibrillators or pacemakers

               -  History of acute coronary syndromes (including myocardial infarction and
                  unstable angina), coronary angioplasty, or stenting within 6 months prior to
                  randomization

               -  History or evidence of current &gt;= class II congestive heart failure as defined
                  by the New York Heart Association (NYHA) functional classification system

               -  Treatment-refractory hypertension defined as a blood pressure of systolic &gt; 140
                  mmHg and/or diastolic &gt; 90 mmHg which cannot be controlled by anti-hypertensive
                  therapy

               -  Known cardiac metastases

          -  Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis B virus (HBV), or hepatitis C
             virus (HCV) infection (with the exception of chronic or cleared HBV and HCV
             infection, which will be allowed)

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements

          -  The study drug must not be administered to pregnant women or nursing mothers; women
             of childbearing potential should be advised to avoid pregnancy and use effective
             methods of contraception; men with a female partner of childbearing potential must
             have either had a prior vasectomy or agree to use effective contraception; if a
             female patient or a female partner of a patient becomes pregnant while the patient
             receives trametinib, the potential hazard to the fetus should be explained to the
             patient and partner (as applicable); these potential risks may also apply to
             GSK2141795

          -  HIV-positive patients on combination antiretroviral therapy are ineligible;
             appropriate studies will be undertaken in patients receiving combination
             antiretroviral therapy when indicated
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Suzanne Trudel</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Health Network-Princess Margaret Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Foothills Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T2N 2T9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nizar J. Bahlis</last_name>
      <phone>403-944-1564</phone>
      <email>NBahlis@UCalgary.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nizar J. Bahlis</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cross Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6G 1Z2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andrew R. Belch</last_name>
      <phone>780-432-8757</phone>
      <email>Andrew.Belch@albertahealthservices.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrew R. Belch</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vancouver General Hospital-Gordon and Leslie Diamond Health Care Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V5C 1M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kevin W. Song</last_name>
      <phone>604-875-4863</phone>
      <email>KSong@bccancer.bc.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kevin W. Song</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ottawa General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1H 8L6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jason Tay</last_name>
      <phone>613-737-8899ext71281</phone>
      <email>jtay@ottawahospital.on.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jason Tay</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Health Network-Princess Margaret Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 2M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Suzanne Trudel</last_name>
      <phone>416-946-4566</phone>
      <email>strudel@uhnres.utoronto.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Suzanne Trudel</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 9, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
