<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="139683">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02069782</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HHSP23320095644 WC</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02069782</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mother and Infant Home Visiting Program Evaluation</brief_title>
  <acronym>MIHOPE</acronym>
  <official_title>Mother and Infant Home Visiting Program Evaluation (MIHOPE</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>MDRC</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mathematica Policy Research, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Georgia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>James Bell Associates</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>MDRC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Administration for Children and Families within US Dept. of Health and Human Services</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      MIHOPE is a multi-state study of home visiting programs authorized under the Maternal,
      Infant, and Early Childhood Home Visiting (MIECHV) program. The study is required by the
      federal Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act of 2010 (ACA), which created the MIECHV
      program. It is being conducted by MDRC under contract to the Administration for Children and
      Families within the US Department of Health and Human Services. In conducting the research,
      MDRC has subcontracted portions of the research to Mathematica Policy Research, Johns
      Hopkins University, Columbia University, University of Georgia, and James Bell Associates.

      MIHOPE is seeking to randomly assign about 5100 families nationally to home visiting
      services or to a comparison group that will receive referrals to other services in the
      community. The study is seeking to include 85 local home visiting programs (sites) that are
      funded through MIECHV in approximately 12 states. In Washington, the study plans to randomly
      assign approximately 360 families across 6 home visiting program sites. Data will be
      collected from families, local home visiting programs, and state and federal administrative
      data systems to assess the effects of the programs on family outcomes and to learn more
      about how the programs are run. Sites included in the evaluation will be using one of four
      national service models (Nurse Family Partnership, Healthy Families America, Parents as
      Teachers, and Early Head Start—Home Visiting Option) that states have chosen for most of
      their MIECHV funding.  MIHOPE will inform the federal government about the effectiveness of
      the MIECHV program in its first few years of operation, and it will provide information to
      help states develop and strengthen home visiting programs in the future. Research findings
      will be disseminated through a report to Congress in 2015; reports on program impacts,
      implementation, and on the relationship between program features and program impacts;
      journal articles; and practitioner briefs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      MIHOPE includes two groups of participants. First, the study will include 5100 women across
      85 local home visiting programs (sites) in 12 states. Women will be randomized so that half
      can receive home visiting services and half are in a control group that receives referrals
      to other services in the community. Local home visiting programs chosen for the study must
      meet the following criteria: (1) they have been in operation for at least two years, (2)
      they are receiving funds through the MIECHV program, (3) they are operating one of the four
      evidence-based models described earlier, and (4) there is enough need for the program's
      services that they can provide a control group without reducing the number of families that
      receive home visiting.

      Families will be recruited as follows. Mothers will be identified as eligible for a local
      home visiting program by staff from that program, using the program's current procedures. If
      the mother appears to be eligible for MIHOPE (based on the mother's age and pregnancy status
      or child's age), the home visiting staff will mention that a study is going on and that
      someone from the study team would like to be in touch to explain the study and to see if the
      mother is interested in participating. The home visiting program will then enter the
      mother's address and phone number. In addition, the home visiting program will provide
      Mathematica with the mother's name and date of birth and the child's date of birth for
      purposes of making sure the family is not already in the study or has not previously
      declined to participate in the study. The MDRC Institutional Review Board has determined
      that a partial authorization of the HIPAA Authorization requirement is warranted for use of
      the mother's information for sample recruitment.

      Study field staff will attempt to contact the family and schedule a visit to explain the
      study, request their participation, and obtain informed consent for research activities.
      Potential study participants will be asked to sign two consent forms at the beginning of the
      study: one to participate in the study and to allow the team to collect administrative and
      survey data, and a second to be video-recorded during two home visits, if assigned to the
      home visiting group. Mothers are also providing consent to allow us to collect information
      from the home visiting programs about the services they receive and information from the
      government on various information, including Medicaid records, vital records, child welfare
      records, and employment and earnings information from the National Database of New Hires. If
      an applicant is a non-emancipated minor, assent will be obtained and written consent will be
      obtained from her parent or guardian if the parent or guardian is in the home at the time of
      the recruitment visit. If the parent or guardian is not in the home, verbal consent will be
      obtained. If verbal consent is provided, the parent or guardian will be mailed a copy of the
      assent form that the woman signed and that explains what the research entails.

      After consent has been provided, study staff in the family's home will initiate a call to
      the study's survey operations center for purposes of administering a one-hour survey. The
      family baseline survey will include information on several domains specified in the ACA:
      newborn health; parental health and well-being; parenting practices, attitudes, and beliefs;
      domestic violence; history with the criminal justice system; family economic
      self-sufficiency; and referral and coordination of social services. In addition, the
      baseline survey will collect information on demographics and household composition to
      describe the study sample, and will collect information on demographics and household
      composition to describe the study sample, and will collect contact information for family
      members or friends who can help locate the family at follow-up if they move. The survey also
      contains information about the parent's expectations regarding the home visiting program,
      which will inform research on program implementation. While the mother is completing the
      baseline survey by phone, the study field staff will conduct the Home Observation for
      Measuring the Environment (HOME) to assess the quality and amount of stimulation that the
      child receives in the home as well as observations of the home environment. At the end of
      the telephone survey, the interviewer will hang up and determine whether the family is
      assigned to the program (home visiting program) or control group (comparison group that will
      receive referrals to other services in the community); the result of random assignment will
      be sent by automated email to the point of contact at the local program.

      A second round of data will be collected when the child is 15 months old. These include: (1)
      a one-hour telephone interview (the family follow-up survey), (2) a 30-minute
      video-recording of the mother and child playing with some toys (the Three Bags task), (3) a
      direct assessment of the child's receptive language skills (expected to take 40 minutes),
      (4) measurement of the child's weight and height and the mother's weight (expected to take 5
      minutes), and (5) observations of the family's home environment, which will not add time to
      the data collection procedures. Finally, data will be collected from three state systems:
      (1) Medicaid, (2) vital records, and (3) child welfare. Follow-up data collection plans have
      been approved by the federal Office of Management and Budget.

      The family follow-up survey will include information on several domains specified in the
      ACA: infant and child health; child development; parental health and well-being; parenting
      practices, attitudes, and beliefs; domestic violence; history with the criminal justice
      system; family economic self-sufficiency; and use of social services. Survey questions will
      focus on outcomes for which previous studies of home visiting have found effects and on
      outcomes that would not be available from other sources (such as administrative records).

      Follow-up data collection will also include several types of data collected in the family's
      home:

        1. Direct assessments of children's receptive language skills will be done using the
           Preschool Language Scales-5 Auditory Comprehension Scale (PLS-5), which is an
           individually administered test that assesses the child's ability to understand
           language. The child will sit on the mother's lap while the field interviewer
           administers this test. At 15 months, toddlers' spoken language capabilities are only
           just beginning to develop. For this reason, the Auditory Comprehension subtest of the
           PLS-5 will be used. The Auditory Comprehension cluster measures a child's ability to be
           attentive and respond to stimuli in the environment and to comprehend basic vocabulary
           or gestures.

        2. During the follow-up visit, field staff will have a measuring tape and a weighing scale
           when they conduct field visits, which they will use to obtain both the mother's weight
           and the child's height and weight. Direct measurements of the child's weight and length
           will provide information on whether the child's growth is within a normal range or
           exhibits early signs of unhealthy growth trajectories (i.e., risk of obesity or
           under-development). Measurement of the mother's weight along with self-reported height
           will provide information on whether the mother is obese, which is associated with a
           host of other health problems. When measuring weight, if the child is willing, the
           field interviewer will ask him or her to stand on the weighing scale by him or herself.
           If the child is unwilling to do so, then the staff person will obtain the mother's
           weight and then ask her to pick up the child and stand on the scale with the child. The
           mother's weight will then be subtracted from this total weight to obtain the child's
           weight. These measures are being collected out of concern that the mother may not
           accurately report her own weight and may not know her child's current weight and
           height.

        3. The Home Observation for Measuring the Environment (HOME) - described under baseline
           data collection -- will be conducted again at follow-up.

        4. The three bags task, a direct observation of parent-child interactions, will be
           conducted. This assessment is intended to capture the parenting constructs of parental
           sensitivity, cognitive stimulation, positive regard, intrusiveness, negative regard,
           detachment, relationship quality (degree of relatedness and mutual engagement), and
           boundary dissolution (parent's inability to maintain an appropriate role in his or her
           interaction with child). From this task, children's behaviors towards the parent will
           also be gathered in the context of the parent-child interaction, including engagement
           with the parent, sustained attention, and negativity towards the parent.

      In addition, the study is asking approximately 500 home visitors and 100 supervisors in the
      85 sites to enroll in the study. Some supervisors may also see families and carry a
      caseload, acting in the capacity of both supervisor and supervisor. Program staff will be
      identified by a local program manager and sent emails by the study team asking them to
      enroll in the study. Home visitors and supervisors will be asked to complete a 75-minute
      web-based survey around the time that the site enters the study. The home visitor and
      supervisor baseline surveys will collect information on staff characteristics and on staff
      perceptions of organizational factors related to service delivery; employment, supervision
      and program outcomes; staff beliefs about home visitor roles and responsibilities, ratings
      of her or his own training and skills in supervising staff to carry out activities; ratings
      of her or his own ability to secure supervision and professional consultation; and
      demographics and individual background characteristics. Individuals who are both home
      visitors and supervisors will be asked to complete a survey that combines elements of the
      home visitor and supervisor surveys, and lasts about 105 minutes. Because the surveys
      include sensitive information, home visitors and supervisors will be asked to consent to the
      survey and home visitors will be asked to consent to videotaped interactions with families.
      Home visitors and supervisors will be asked to provide consent through a web-based
      application before completing the web-based surveys.

      Home visitors and supervisors will be asked to complete a 75-minute web-based survey again a
      year after enrolling in the study. Staff who are both home visitors and supervisors will be
      asked to complete a 105-minute web-based survey again a year after enrolling in the study.
      Staff follow-up surveys parallel the baseline surveys. They will measure malleable
      respondent characteristics and perceptions of organizational factors related to service
      delivery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Children's physical delays and motor development</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on developing delays in physical or motor development.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Special health care needs</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on children's special health care needs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Injuries</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on childhood injuries.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Receipt of early intervention services</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on children's receipt of early intervention services.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Social-emotional responsivity</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on parent's responsive caregiving.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive stimulation</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on caregiver's provision of cognitive stimulation in the home.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Harsh parenting</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on caregiver's use of harsh parenting techniques.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Nutrition practices</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on caregiver's nutrition practices, such as breast-feeding and sleep habits.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Substantiated reports of child neglect and abuse</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on substantiated reports of child maltreatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of the home environment</measure>
    <time_frame>through the child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on the quality of the child's home environment (such as whether it is clean and uncluttered and whether there is evidence of recent drug use in the home).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal mental health</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on mother's mental health (specifically, anxiety and depressive symptoms).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal substance use</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on mother's substance use, including use of tobacco, illicit drugs and problem alcohol use.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Subsequent pregnancies</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effect of home visiting on the desired and actual timing of mother's subsequent pregnancies.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intimate partner violence</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on maternal experience of physical and psychological violence by and maternal perpetration of physical violence toward her spouse/partner.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Criminal activity</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on maternal arrests.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal and household income</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on maternal and household monthly income.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal employment</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on maternal employment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal highest grade completed</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effect of home visiting on the highest level of education completed by the mother.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Public assistance receipt</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on household receipt of public assistance (SNAP, WIC, TANF, SSI/SSDI).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal monetary assistance from the father</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on material support provided by the child's biological father.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Child's medical insurance status</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on children's medical insurance status (whether or not the child is insured and whether or not the child is insured by Medicaid/CHIP).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Usual source of care</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on whether or not children have a usual source of care.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunizations</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on the adequacy and number of children's immunizations.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospitalizations</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on children's ED visits and hospitalizations.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prescription drugs</measure>
    <time_frame>through the child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on the number of prescription drugs prescribed to the child.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal health insurance</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on mother's health insurance coverage.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Regular source of care</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on whether mothers have a regular source of care.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reproductive services</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on mother's use of reproductive services.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mental and substance use services</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on mother's use of mental health and substance use services.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal hospitalizations</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on maternal ED visits and hospitalizations.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Domestic violence services</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on mother's receipt of domestic violence services.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Education and workforce services</measure>
    <time_frame>through child's 15th month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MIHOPE will assess the effects of home visiting on mother's receipt of education and workforce services.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5100</enrollment>
  <condition>Pregnancy</condition>
  <condition>Infant Development</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Home visiting</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Home visiting programs in the United States grew from three major approaches that first became prominent in the 1960s: visits by public health nurses to promote infant and child health in disadvantaged families, Head Start home visiting to promote school readiness in hard-to-reach families, and home-based family support to promote positive parenting and prevent child abuse in high-risk families. All of these approaches sought to foster early childhood health and development by intervening in the home to support and improve socialization, health, and education practices.Today, home visiting is seen as a particularly important strategy for high-risk families who may be difficult to engage in other services.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Home visiting</intervention_name>
    <description>While all of the models try to improve child health and development, some focus more directly on preventing child maltreatment; others focus on improving maternal and child health; and others prioritize promoting positive parenting or increasing school readiness. Some models also explicitly aim to improve parental self-sufficiency and well-being. Most of these models serve families whom they identify as being at risk of poor child outcomes, based on one or more family characteristics. Although the definition of &quot;at risk&quot; differs by model, most models target low-income families. They may also specifically target young, first-time mothers; parents with past negative school experiences; or families with maternal depression or substance abuse problems. Many of the models begin to work with women when they are pregnant or when they have newborns.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Home visiting</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>HFA</other_name>
    <other_name>PAT</other_name>
    <other_name>EHS</other_name>
    <other_name>NFP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Eligible for home visiting program selected to be in the study

          -  At least 15 years old

          -  Pregnant or have a child under 28 weeks old

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  women already enrolled in home visiting (for example, with an older child)

          -  children in foster care in sites using EHS program model

          -  homeless families in sites using EHS program model

          -  women who speak neither English or Spanish
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Charles Michalopoulos, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>MDRC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Virginia Knox, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>MDRC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anne Duggan, ScD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MDRC</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdrc.org/mihope-research-design</url>
    <description>MIHOPE Research Design (brief description)</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdrc.org/project/mother-and-infant-home-visiting-program-evaluation-mihope#featured_content</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 26, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 19, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>postpartum programs</keyword>
  <keyword>infant health services</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
