<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="162986">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01714596</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>METRC POvIV</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01714596</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Prospective Randomized Trial to Assess PO Versus IV Antibiotics for the Treatment of Early Post-op Wound Infection After Extremity Fractures</brief_title>
  <acronym>POvIV</acronym>
  <official_title>A Prospective Randomized Trial to Assess PO Versus IV Antibiotics for the Treatment of Early Post-op Wound Infection After Extremity Fractures (POvIV)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Major Extremity Trauma Research Consortium</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Major Extremity Trauma Research Consortium</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to evaluate the effect of treatment of post-op wound infection in
      long
                                 bones after fracture fixation or joint fusion and either:  (Group
      1) operative debridement and PO antibiotic treatment for 6 weeks; or (Group 2) operative
      debridement and IV antibiotics for 6 weeks.

      Primary Hypothesis: The rate of treatment failure by one year in Group 1 will be
      non-inferior to the rate in Group 2. Treatment failure is defined as wound problems that
      require surgery &gt;2 weeks after initial debridement, infection recurrence, infection with a
      new pathogen, joint erosion, implant failure, medical problems related to the treatment
      administration which necessitates a switch from one arm to the other.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Not provided here. Details listed above.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary objective: investigate the efficacy of oral (PO) antibiotic therapy versus intravenous (IV) antibiotics in the treatment of acute infection after fixation of fractures or joint fusions.</measure>
    <time_frame>4 Years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Phase III randomized controlled clinical trial to investigate efficacy of PO vs. IV antibiotics in the treatment of early (&lt;6 weeks) post-operative wound infections. Clinical efficacy will be measured by the incidence of treatment failure within the first one-year of follow-up as defined by culture positive recurrence of infection prior to bony union, progressive radiographic plate loosening, joint erosion due to infection that results in amputation or joint fusion, development of adverse reactions to antibiotics that cause change in form of administration.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>4 Years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient adherence with PO antibiotics will be monitored through wireless-enabled microchip monitors embedded in pill bottles. The Home Health agency administering the IV antibiotics will be contacted to assess adherence with IV antibiotic regimen by assessing utilization of supplied antibiotics.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">600</enrollment>
  <condition>Wound Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oral Antibiotic</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oral Antibiotic Arm; Participants assigned to this group will receive oral antibiotics as prescribed by their treating physician.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IV Antibiotic</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants assigned to this group will receive intravenous (IV) antibiotics as prescribed by their treating physician.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PO versus IV antibiotics Route of administration evaluation</intervention_name>
    <description>This is a study of oral (per os, (PO)) antibiotic therapy versus intravenous (IV) antibiotics in the treatment of acute infection after fixation of fractures and joint fusions. This is not a study of an experimental drug but a study of route of administration of standard use antibiotics. Antibiotic regimen options decision will be made by the Study Surgeon at each site in consult with local Infectious Disease experts based on local standard practices and bacterial susceptibilities.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oral Antibiotic</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>IV Antibiotic</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>based on local practices and bacterial susceptibilities</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with fractures (defined as femurs, tibias, and fibulas of the legs, and the
             humeri, radii, and ulnas of the arms) treated with a plate or IMN, or

          2. Patients undergoing fusion of subtalar, ankle, knee, wrist or elbow that develop a
             post op wound infection.

          3. Patients diagnosed with a wound infection of the study injury, defined as deep
             culture positive after operative debridement

          4. Patients who are English or Spanish competent.

          5. Patients aged 18 - 84.

          6. Patients with bacteria susceptible to both PO and IV antibiotics.

          7. Patients able to be treated for their infection at the METRC facility for at least 12
             months following definitive surgical procedure

          8. Patients may have multiple eligible study-eligible injuries.

          9. Patients may have temporary external fixation prior to definitive fixation.

         10. Patients may have received antibiotics prior to operative wound debridement.

         11. Patient is able to obtain study medication(s).

         12. Patient may be pregnant at the time of screening.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who have high risk of amputation of the study limb (based on opinion of the
             initial managing physician).

          2. Patients undergoing treatment with any other investigational therapy within the month
             preceding implantation or planned within the 12 months following implantation.

          3. Patients with prior history of infection at the site of study injury.

          4. Patients with pathological fractures; a known history of Paget's disease.

          5. Patients for whom the definitive treatment of the study injury was an external
             fixator.

          6. Patients who are currently on Selective Serotonin Reuptake Inhibitor (SSRI)
             medication (e.g. Zoloft, Prozac, Celexa), and bacteria is MRSA

          7. Patients with cultures positive in thio only.

          8. Patients who are incarcerated or who have unstable housing situations due to concerns
             regarding ability to receive home care, adherence phone calls, and maintain follow
             up. .

          9. Patients or designated proxy who are unwilling to provide consent.

         10. Patients with a history of IV drug use who in the investigator's opinion are
             unsuitable candidates for IV therapy.

         11. Patients likely to have severe problems maintaining follow-up, including patients
             diagnosed with a severe psychiatric conditions, patients who live too far outside the
             hospital's catchment area.

         12. Patients with traumatic brain injury or who are intellectually challenged and who
             lack adequate family support to ensure adherence to the protocol.

         13. Patients unable to swallow oral medications or without adequately functioning GI
             tract.

         14. Patients who, based upon the clinical judgment of the treating clinician, are NOT
             equally suited for treatment with either oral or intravenous antibiotics (i.e., those
             for whom there is a clinical treatment preference).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>84 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William T Obremskey, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Vanderbilt University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Renan Castillo, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mary Zadnik Newell, ScD, OTR/L</last_name>
    <email>mzadnik@jhsph.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSF Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Theodore Miclau, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Maryland Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrew Pollack, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Carolinas Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlotte</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael J Bossee, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MetroHealth Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Heather A Vallier, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>William T. Obremskey, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 4, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 30, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Oral Antibiotic</keyword>
  <keyword>Intravenous Antibiotic</keyword>
  <keyword>Wound infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Randomized Controlled Trial</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Surgical Wound Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wound Infection</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anti-Bacterial Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibiotics, Antitubercular</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
