<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="43606">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01981525</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>140005</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>14-C-0005</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01981525</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pilot Study of Metformin in Patients With a Diagnosis of Li-Fraumeni Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study of Metformin in Patients With a Diagnosis of Li-Fraumeni Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Li Fraumeni Syndrome (LFS) is a highly penetrant, autosomal dominant cancer
           predisposition disorder. Four main cancer types including sarcoma, adrenocortical
           carcinoma, breast cancer, and malignant brain tumors commonly characterize LFS but the
           syndrome can include other cancers.

        -  Sixty to eighty percent of    classic    LFS families have detectable germline TP53
           mutations.

        -  TP53 encodes p53 protein. Among many other functions p53 is involved in the regulation
           of mitochondrial respiration and energy homeostasis.

        -  Metformin is an oral biguanide drug that is approved by the FDA for the treatment of
           type II diabetes. Metformin has been associated with reduced cancer risk in several
           epidemiologic studies and reduced cancer mortality in patients with type 2 diabetes.

        -  Metformin decreases circulating insulin and IGF1, and promotes glucose uptake in
           skeletal muscle and inhibits gluconeogenesis in the liver. Elevations in circulating
           insulin and IGF1 levels have been associated with increased cancer risk.

        -  Metformin and p53 both have effects on the mitochondria. One effect of metformin is
           inhibition of mitochondrial respiratory complex I, thereby decreasing ATP production
           via oxidative phosphorylation.

        -  It is proposed that in the absence of a normal functioning p53, metformin may modulate
           mitochondrial function by inhibiting oxidative phosphorylation in turn inducing a
           bioenergetic crisis in rapidly proliferating cells and cellular senescence or
           apoptosis.

      Objectives:

        -  Determine the tolerability of oral daily metformin in patients with LFS caused by
           germline TP53 mutations.

        -  Determine if 8 weeks of daily metformin administration has any effect on circulating
           IGF-1, insulin, and IGFBP3

      Eligibility:

        -  Must have a germline TP53 mutation and provide documentation of testing.

        -  Must have adequate organ function.

        -  Age greater than or equal to 18 years.

      Design:

        -  This is a pilot study to assess the tolerability of daily oral metformin administration
           in patients with LFS caused by germline TP53 mutations and to study the effect of
           metformin on biomarker levels in these subjects.

        -  Patients will be assessed for biomarker levels (IGF-1, insulin, IGFBP3) by blood sample
           at baseline, and weeks 2 and 8.

        -  Patients will also undergo optional mitochondrial studies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Li Fraumeni Syndrome (LFS) is a highly penetrant, autosomal dominant cancer
           predisposition disorder. Four main cancer types including sarcoma, adrenocortical
           carcinoma, breast cancer, and malignant brain tumors commonly characterize LFS but the
           syndrome can include other cancers.

        -  Sixty to eighty percent of    classic    LFS families have detectable germline TP53
           mutations.

        -  TP53 encodes p53 protein. Among many other functions p53 is involved in the regulation
           of mitochondrial respiration and energy homeostasis.

        -  Metformin is an oral biguanide drug that is approved by the FDA for the treatment of
           type II diabetes. Metformin has been associated with reduced cancer risk in several
           epidemiologic studies and reduced cancer mortality in patients with type 2 diabetes.

        -  Metformin decreases circulating insulin and IGF1, and promotes glucose uptake in
           skeletal muscle and inhibits gluconeogenesis in the liver. Elevations in circulating
           insulin and IGF1 levels have been associated with increased cancer risk.

        -  Metformin and p53 both have effects on the mitochondria. One effect of metformin is
           inhibition of mitochondrial respiratory complex I, thereby decreasing ATP production
           via oxidative phosphorylation.

        -  It is proposed that in the absence of a normal functioning p53, metformin may modulate
           mitochondrial function by inhibiting oxidative phosphorylation in turn inducing a
           bioenergetic crisis in rapidly proliferating cells and cellular senescence or
           apoptosis.

      Objectives:

        -  Determine the tolerability of oral daily metformin in patients with LFS caused by
           germline TP53 mutations.

        -  Determine if 8 weeks of daily metformin administration has any effect on circulating
           IGF-1, insulin, and IGFBP3

      Eligibility:

        -  Must have a germline TP53 mutation and provide documentation of testing.

        -  Must have adequate organ function.

        -  Age greater than or equal to 18 years.

      Design:

        -  This is a pilot study to assess the tolerability of daily oral metformin administration
           in patients with LFS caused by germline TP53 mutations and to study the effect of
           metformin on biomarker levels in these subjects.

        -  Patients will be assessed for biomarker levels (IGF-1, insulin, IGFBP3) by blood sample
           at baseline, and weeks 2 and 8.

        -  Patients will also undergo optional mitochondrial studies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the tolerability of oral daily metformin in patients with LFS caused by germline TP53 mutations.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine if 8 weeks of daily metformin administration has any effect on circulating IGF-1, insulin, and IGFBP3</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Li-Fraumeni Syndrome</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metformin</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  All TP53 germline mutation positive adult patients will be eligible for this study.
             All patients must have a documented TP53 germline mutation.

          -  Patients with history of cancer must be in remission, with surgery completed at least
             6 months prior to enrollment and chemotherapy completed at least 1 year prior to
             enrollment.

          -  Age greater than or equal to 18 years. The doses of metformin used in this study
             exceed the maximum recommended daily dose for the pediatric population.

          -  ECOG performance status 0 or 1 or Karnofsky greater than or equal to 70%.

          -  Patients must have normal organ and marrow function as defined below:

               -  Leukocytes greater than or equal to 3,000/microL

               -  Absolute neutrophil count greater than or equal to 1,500/microL

               -  Platelets greater than or equal to 100,000/microL

               -  Total bilirubin:  Within normal institutional limits

               -  AST(SGOT) / ALT(SGPT):  less than or equal to 2.5 times institutional upper
                  limit of normal

               -  Creatinine:  Within normal institutional limits OR

               -  Creatinine clearance:  greater than or equal to 60 mL/min/1.73m(2) if serum
                  creatinine &gt;  institutional normal

        Note: If leukopenia is idiopathic and no other significant co-morbidities exist patients
        will not be excluded on the basis of their WBC.

        -Metformin is a category B drug and can be used to treat gestational diabetes. Levels of
        metformin excreted in breast milk appear to be low and not clinically significant.

        However, for protocol safety reasons, we will not be enrolling pregnant and/or nursing
        women in this study as metformin as has not been extensively evaluated in non-diabetic
        pregnant and nursing women. For this reason, women of child-bearing potential must agree
        to use adequate contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence)
        prior to study entry and for the duration of study participation. Women who are nursing
        will be advised to discontinue breastfeeding if the mother is treated with metformin.
        Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while she is participating in
        this study, she should inform Drs. Fojo or Walcott, or protocol physicians/study team at
        NCI and her primary care provider immediately.

        -Ability of subject to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent
        document.

        GENERAL EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Patients who have had stem-cell transplantation.

          -  Current use of metformin or other anti-diabetic agents, or hypersensitivity or
             allergy to

        metformin.

          -  Current use of diuretics.

          -  Patients who are receiving any other investigational agents.

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to metformin or other agents used in study.

          -  Patients with congestive heart failure requiring pharmacological management.

          -  Uncontrolled inter-current illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Antonio T Fojo, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Farzana L Walcott, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(240) 276-7661</phone>
    <email>walcottfl@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact National Cancer Institute Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>888-624-1937</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Robin Eisch</last_name>
      <phone>(301) 402-5958</phone>
      <email>eischar@mail.nih.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2014-C-0005.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Li FP, Fraumeni JF Jr. Soft-tissue sarcomas, breast cancer, and other neoplasms. A familial syndrome? Ann Intern Med. 1969 Oct;71(4):747-52. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>5360287</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Li FP, Fraumeni JF Jr, Mulvihill JJ, Blattner WA, Dreyfus MG, Tucker MA, Miller RW. A cancer family syndrome in twenty-four kindreds. Cancer Res. 1988 Sep 15;48(18):5358-62.</citation>
    <PMID>3409256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Villani A, Tabori U, Schiffman J, Shlien A, Beyene J, Druker H, Novokmet A, Finlay J, Malkin D. Biochemical and imaging surveillance in germline TP53 mutation carriers with Li-Fraumeni syndrome: a prospective observational study. Lancet Oncol. 2011 Jun;12(6):559-67. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(11)70119-X. Epub 2011 May 19.</citation>
    <PMID>21601526</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 7, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>TP53 Mutation</keyword>
  <keyword>Autosomal Dominant Hereditary Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Chemoprevention</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Li-Fraumeni Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
