<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="144678">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01994785</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CC-13-792</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01994785</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Use of Capnography in EGD and Colonoscopy With Moderate Sedation.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Does the Use of Capnography in Routine EGD and Colonoscopy Targeting Moderate Sedation With a Benzodiazepine and Opioid Improve Safety?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Cleveland Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>American College of Gastroenterology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Cleveland Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Cleveland Clinic</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will provide capnography monitoring during routine upper endoscopy and
      colonoscopy with moderate sedation in order to see if it improves safety.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The majority of gastrointestinal endoscopic procedures currently performed in the United
      States are done under moderate sedation, primarily utilizing the combination of an opioid
      and benzodiazepine.  The endoscopy team administers the medications, most commonly the
      endoscopy nursing team at the discretion of the endoscopist, with careful cardiopulmonary
      monitoring during the procedure. The use of sedation can lead to serious unplanned adverse
      events. Cardiopulmonary events related to the use of sedation in GI endoscopy include
      hypotension, hypoxia, and hypopnea/apnea.  The most common of these adverse events is
      hypoxia, which can occur in 10-70% of patients.   Although most of these events are
      transient and respond to supplemental oxygenation, studies have shown electrocardiographic
      signs of cardiac ischemia in patients with no known preexisting heart disease. Pulse
      oximetry can help detect hypoxia related to perfusion deficits (cardiac) or ventilation
      factors (respiratory) however, it is not designed to detect ventilator precursors of
      alveolar hypoventilation, which primarily present as decreased respiratory rate or
      hypopnea/apnea.

      Capnography utilizes the near-infrared spectrophotometric absorption spectrum of carbon
      dioxide (CO2) at 420 nm to provide graphic assessment of the ventilation status via the
      partial pressure of carbon dioxide during the respiratory cycle.  Previous studies have
      shown it to improve safety by detecting early indicators of hypoxia and/or signs of alveolar
      hypoventilation.  Studies have shown that when targeting deep sedation in advanced
      endoscopic procedures utilizing capnography was superior to pulse oximetry alone in
      detecting respiratory depression.  There is also evidence that shows utilizing capnography
      in advanced endoscopic procedures significantly decreased the incidence of hypoxia versus
      standard monitoring with the procedural team blinded to the capnographic data (132 blinded
      vs. 49 open, P&lt;.001) and rates of hypoxia (69% blinded vs. 46% open, P&lt;.001) were
      significantly lower with capnography monitoring.

      Routine esophagogastroduodenoscopy (EGD) and colonoscopy with moderate sedation is safe with
      rates of sedation associated adverse events occurring in 8 per 100,000 cases.  Lightdale and
      colleagues showed in a prospective, double blinded randomized controlled trial in a
      pediatric population undergoing routine EGD or colonoscopy targeting moderate sedation with
      opioid-benzodiazepine combinations that patients in the intervention capnography arm were
      less likely (4% vs. 20%, P&lt;.03) to have an intra-procedural episodes of hypoxia (defined as
      SpO2&lt;95% for &gt;5sec).  No adverse events related to episodes of hypoxia were reported in this
      trial, but it was underpowered to evaluate this outcome.  To our knowledge, there is no data
      on use of capnography in adult patients undergoing EGD and colonoscopy targeting moderate
      sedation with the combination of an opioid and benzodiazepine.

      The American Society of Anesthesiology (ASA) has recently updated their standards for basic
      anesthetic monitoring to now state that during moderate sedation all patients should have
      capnographic monitoring.  This was updated from the previous standards for basic monitoring
      that stated capnography could be used during these levels of sedation. This is a significant
      change in the practice model for monitoring patients undergoing routine endoscopy with
      moderate sedation and, as the standards for basic monitoring are often used as a basis for
      regulatory guidelines applied to hospital or ambulatory care centers, the addition of
      requiring capnographic monitoring changes the landscape of procedural sedation for
      gastrointestinal endoscopy across the United States.  The evidence cited for this update in
      monitoring guidelines included the Lightdale pediatric endoscopy study and our groups study
      that utilized capnography in advanced endoscopic procedures.  There was no data available in
      adult patients undergoing routine EGD or colonoscopy at the time of the updated guidelines.
      The extrapolation of advanced endoscopic procedures to routine endoscopy is of limited use
      as the procedures are targeting different levels of sedation (deep vs. moderate,
      respectively) and the length of the procedures is significantly different.

      The rationale for not using capnography in moderate sedation arises from its ability to lead
      to false alarms, such as pseudo-apnea secondary to swallowing or failure to monitor both the
      oral and nasal airways for respiratory activity, as some patients will transition to nasal
      or mouth breathing during sedation.  These alarms during a procedure may lead to
      interruption, delay, or early termination.  Increased costs for capnography equipment and
      having appropriately trained endoscopy team members to interpret capnography results will be
      difficult to accomplish with no patient data supporting the effectiveness of its use in
      routine EGD and colonoscopy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver)</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>372 study participants will be assessed for rates of hypoxia with the use of capnography monitoring.</measure>
    <time_frame>An average time frame including data from the study of 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants will be followed for the duration of the procedure when data will be collected and the collected data will be presented for up to 2 years following the completion of the study</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">372</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypoxia</condition>
  <condition>Apnea</condition>
  <condition>Hypotension</condition>
  <condition>Hypopnea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EGD capnography open</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EGD capnography blinded</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Colonoscopy capnography open</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Colonoscopy capnography blinded</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Capnostream 20 (Covidien, Mansfield, MA) Capnography monitoring device</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>EGD capnography open</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>EGD capnography blinded</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Colonoscopy capnography open</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Colonoscopy capnography blinded</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  &gt;18yrs with full decision making capacity

          -  Scheduled for elective upper endoscopy or colonoscopy with moderate sedation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  ASAPS class III or higher.

          -  History of a demonstrated allergy or intolerance to a benzodiazepine or opioid

          -  Patients scheduled for both upper endoscopy and colonoscopy during the same endoscopy
             day
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paresh P Mehta, MD</last_name>
    <phone>2164442200</phone>
    <email>mehtap2@ccf.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Independence</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44131</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paresh Mehta, MD</last_name>
      <email>mehtap2@ccf.orf</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paresh P Mehta, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 3, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The Cleveland Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Paresh P. Mehta, M.D</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Fellow, Gastroenterology and Hepatology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sedation</keyword>
  <keyword>Endoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>Capnography</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Apnea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypotension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anoxia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
