<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="152964">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01813890</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR101093</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R331333PAI3035</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01813890</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Effectiveness and Safety of Tapentadol (CG5503) in the Treatment of Acute Pain From Bunionectomy Compared With Placebo</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Parallel-Group, Multicenter Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Tapentadol Immediate-Release Formulation in the Treatment of Acute Pain From Bunionectomy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Janssen-Cilag International NV</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Grünenthal GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Janssen-Cilag International NV</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Taiwan: Department of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the analgesic efficacy and safety of tapentadol
      immediate-release (IR [CG5503]) for use in the relief of moderate to severe acute pain,
      compared with placebo, in adult Taiwanese patients with acute pain following bunionectomy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients undergoing bunionectomy (a surgical procedure to remove a bunion, an enlargement of
      the joint at the base of the big toe comprised of bone and soft tissue) often experience
      moderate to severe acute pain post-surgery. Normally such pain is controlled when patients
      receive repeated doses of opioid analgesics. Tapentadol (CG5503) is a newly synthesized
      opioid drug acting as a centrally acting analgesic like opioid analgesics but has a
      different mode of action. This study, a randomized (patients are assigned different
      treatments based on chance), double-blind (neither investigator nor patient knows which
      treatment the patient receives), placebo-controlled (placebo is an inactive substance that
      is compared with a drug to test whether the drug has a real effect in a clinical trial),
      parallel-group (each group of patients will be treated at the same time), multicenter study
      (the study is performed at more than one clinic) is designed to evaluate the effectiveness
      (level of pain control) and safety (side effects) of tapentadol immediate-release (IR) 50 mg
      or 75 mg versus placebo. The study will consist of a screening phase, during which the
      patients will be evaluated for study entry (Days -28 to -2) followed by the surgical period
      (Day -1) during which the bunionectomy will be performed and which will start with the first
      surgical incision and continues until termination of the popliteal sciatic block (PSB)
      infusion. During the qualification period (Day 1) which starts after termination of the
      post-operative continuous PSB infusion, patients will be evaluated for entry in the double
      blind treatment phase. Patients will be randomly assigned to one of three treatment groups
      to receive either 50 mg tapentadol IR, 75 mg tapentadol IR or a placebo if their PI is equal
      to or greater than 4 on a 0-10 numerical rating scale. The inpatient double-blind treatment
      period will be 72 hours in duration and will include a final end-of-double-blind evaluation
      (on Day 4, i.e., 72 hours after the administration of the first dose) for all patients. Any
      patient requiring analgesia for pain relief in addition to study drug during the
      double-blind treatment period will be discontinued from the study due to lack of efficacy.
      All patients who discontinue for lack of efficacy will complete pain assessments and the
      Patient Global Impression of Change (PGIC) before receiving rescue medication. Pain
      intensity and pain relief will be periodically assessed during the treatment period using
      rating scales. Safety evaluations include monitoring of adverse events, physical
      examinations, and clinical laboratory tests. The study length, including the screening
      period, will be up to a maximum duration of 32 days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>SPID48 (Sum of Pain Intensity Difference)</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The SPID48 score incorporates the cumulative analgesic effects of tapentadol IR on pain intensity over an extended period allowing an evaluation of multiple doses of drug, even when dosing frequency may vary. Scoring is derived from the Numerical Rating Scale where 0 represents &quot;No pain&quot; and 10 represents &quot;Pain as bad as you can imagine&quot;. A positive difference between mean SPID48 for an active study drug and placebo would indicate a numerically larger analgesic effect for patients dosed with active study drug than in the placebo group. A higher value in SPID indicates greater pain reduction.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TOTPAR (Total Pain Relief)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12, 24, 48, and 72 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Total pain relief (PAR) is calculated on a 5-point Numeric Rating Scale. Patients indicate how much relief they had from the starting pain on a scale from 0 to 4, where 0 represents &quot;no relief&quot; and 4 represents &quot;complete relief&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SPRID (Sum of Total Pain Relief and Sum of Pain Intensity Difference)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12, 24, 48 and 72 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The SPRID is calculated using the formula: SPRID equals SPID plus TOTPAR.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PGIC (Patient Global Impression of Change)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 72 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The PGIC scale indicates the patient's overall status. Patients' PGIC is assessed on a 7-point Numerical Rating Scale where 1 represents &quot;very much improved&quot; and 7 represents &quot;very much worse&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time from first dose to the first use of rescue medication</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 72 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The effect of tapentadol (CG5503) IR on the time to the first use of rescue pain medication.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent change from baseline in Pain Intensity (PI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12, 24, 48, and 72 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Pain Intensity will be calculated using an 11-point Numeric Rating Scale. Patients are asked to rate their current pain intensity on a scale from 0 to 10, where 0 represents &quot;no pain&quot; and 10 represents &quot;pain as bad you can imagine&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SPID (Sum of Pain Intensity Difference)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12, 24, and 72 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The SPID score incorporates the cumulative analgesic effects of tapentadol IR on pain intensity over an extended period allowing an evaluation of multiple doses of drug, even when dosing frequency may vary. Scoring is derived from the Numerical Rating Scale where 0 represents &quot;no pain&quot; and 10 represents &quot;pain as bad as you can imagine&quot;. A positive difference between the mean SPID for an active study drug and placebo would indicate a numerically larger analgesic effect for patients dosed with active study drug than in the placebo group. A higher value in SPID indicates greater pain reduction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Hallux Valgus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tapentadol IR 50 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tapentadol IR 75 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tapentadol IR 50 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Tapentadol IR 50 mg will be administered as a single oral dose once every 4 to 6 hours, during the double blind treatment period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tapentadol IR 50 mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tapentadol IR 75 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Tapentadol IR 75 mg will be administered as a single oral dose once every 4 to 6 hours, during the double blind treatment period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tapentadol IR 75 mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo will be administered as a single oral dose once every 4 to 6 hours, during the double blind treatment period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must be undergoing primary unilateral first metatarsal bunionectomy that
             includes a distal Chevron osteotomy only, with or without the Akin procedure

          -  Patients must be healthy or medically stable on the basis of clinical laboratory
             tests performed at screening

          -  Women must be postmenopausal, surgically sterile, abstinent, or practicing or agree
             to practice an effective method of birth control and have a negative serum pregnancy
             test at screening and a negative urine pregnancy test before surgery

          -  If a male, must use an approved method of birth control and does not donate sperm
             from the day of study drug administration until 3 months afterwards

          -  Qualifying baseline Pain Intensity must be rated as greater than or equal to 4 on an
             11-point (0 to 10) PI NRS, recorded within 30 minutes before randomization, no
             earlier than 10 hours after the first surgical incision and within 9 hours after
             termination of the continuous Popliteal Sciatic Block (PSB) infusion Exclusion
             Criteria: - History of seizure disorder or epilepsy, severe traumatic brain injury,
             episode(s) of unconsciousness of more than 24 hours duration, malignancy in the past
             2 years with the exception of successfully treated basal cell carcinoma

          -  Mild or moderate traumatic brain injury, stroke, transient ischemic attack, or brain
             neoplasm within 1 year of screening

          -  Renal insufficiency, impaired hepatic function

          -  Use of anticonvulsants, monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOIs), tricyclic
             antidepressants (TCAs), neuroleptics, serotonin norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors
             (SNRIs), selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) or triptans
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janssen-Cilag International NV Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Janssen-Cilag International NV</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kaohsiung</city>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Taoyuan</city>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 25, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 15, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bunionectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Post-operative pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Tapentadol IR</keyword>
  <keyword>Analgesia</keyword>
  <keyword>Hallux valgus</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hallux Valgus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
