<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="53814">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02125331</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>123.04-2013-GES-0008</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02125331</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Measurement of NonInvasive Blood Pressure in Neonates Through Adults and Special Populations</brief_title>
  <acronym>MISSION</acronym>
  <official_title>Measurement of NonInvasive Blood Pressure With DINAMAP SuperSTAT and Datex-Ohmeda With Intra-arterial Blood Pressure in Neonates Through Adults and Special Populations</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GE Healthcare</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GE Healthcare</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is required to demonstrate that the non-invasive blood pressure (NIBP)
      measurement algorithms on two commercially available devices provide accurate NIBP
      measurements in accordance with the guidelines provided by the most recent International
      Organization for Standardization (ISO) 81060-2:2013 requirements relevant to Unites States
      devices and the BS EN 1060-4:2004 standard widely recognized in Europe. This study will
      assess neonate, infant, children, pediatric, adolescent, and adult patients as well as
      adults with chronic atrial fibrillation in a population that requires non-emergent heart
      catheterization. This is a study conducted to satisfy both standards for two NIBP devices
      and, as such, does not require a statistical hypothesis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is required to demonstrate that the non-invasive blood pressure (NIBP)
      measurement algorithms on two commercially available multifunction hemodynamic acquisition
      modules, the Patient Data Module (PDM) equipped with the DINAMAP® SUPERSTAT algorithm
      (&quot;PDM-SUPERSTAT&quot;) and the Patient Side Module (PSM) equipped with Datex-Ohmeda GE algorithm
      (&quot;PSM-Datex-Ohmeda&quot;), provide accurate NIBP measurements in accordance with the guidelines
      provided by the most recent International Organization for Standardization (ISO)
      81060-2:2013 requirements relevant to Unites States devices and the BS EN 1060-4:2004
      standard widely recognized in Europe.

      Notably, the new ISO 81060-2:2013 supersedes the previous 2009 version of this standard, and
      this study is being conducted in accordance with the most recent applicable standards.

      This study will assess neonate, infant, children, pediatric, adolescent, and adult patients
      as well as adults with chronic atrial fibrillation in a population that requires
      non-emergent heart catheterization.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Accuracy of NIBP Measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Determining the accuracy of non-invasive blood pressure measurement compared to invasive blood pressure. A detailed analysis will be conducted on the invasive blood pressure to verify accuracy as defined in the following standards: BS EN 1060-4:2004 and ISO 81060-2 Second edition 2013-05-01.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Blood Pressure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PDM-SuperSTAT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>PDM-SuperSTAT Arm (minimum of 55 evaluable patients): GE DINAMAP® SuperSTAT algorithm delivered by the PDM acquisition module connected to the CARESCAPE Monitor B650</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PSM-Datex-Ohmeda</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>PSM-Datex-Ohmeda Arm (minimum of 45 evaluable patients): Datex-Ohmeda delivered by the PSM acquisition module connected to the CARESCAPE Monitor B650</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Device: Blood pressure monitoring with GE Healthcare CARESCAPE B650 Patient Monitor-Patient Side Module (PSM) or Patient Data Module (PDM)</intervention_name>
    <description>3-15 Non-Invasive Blood Pressure readings on the CARESCAPE B650 Patient Monitor equipped with PSM-Datex-Ohmeda and PDM-SuperSTAT NIBP measurement devices during non-emergent heart catheterization</description>
    <arm_group_label>PDM-SuperSTAT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>PSM-Datex-Ohmeda</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>GE Healthcare CARESCAPE B650 Patient Monitor</other_name>
    <other_name>Patient Side Module with Datex-Ohmeda software algorithm (PSM)</other_name>
    <other_name>Patient Data Module with SuperSTAT software algorithm (PDM)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Require non-emergent heart catheterization (all subjects except neonates);

          -  Neonates only - umbilical arterial lines that have been placed for route care.

          -  Have an upper limb (right OR left side) that fits a cuff size of the device
             (circumference ranging 3 cm to 40 cm) OR have a thigh (right OR left side) that fits
             a cuff size of the device (circumference ranging 38 to 50 cm);

          -  Is willing and able to provide blood pressure measurements using both IBP and NIBP;

          -  Is able and willing to provide written informed consent or has a legally authorized
             representative that is willing to provide written informed consent

          -  If informed consent is provided by a legally authorized representative on the
             patient's behalf, the subject is willing to provide assent to study participation, if
             capable of providing assent in the opinion of the investigator.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Do not meet the stratification quota set forth in Tables 1 and 2 in the protocol;

          -  Exhibit signs or symptoms or have a current diagnosis of peripheral vascular disease
             in either upper AND/OR lower limbs;

          -  Have current, uncontrolled circulatory shock;

          -  Exhibit injuries, deformities, intravenous lines, or other abnormalities that, in the
             opinion of the investigator, may prevent proper cuff application or functioning;

          -  Are currently pregnant, suspect that they are pregnant, or are currently lactating;

          -  Have contraindications to standard BP measurements;

          -  Have any other condition that makes the subject unable to tolerate 4 fast flushes
             (adult, adolescent, or pediatric) or 1 fast flush (neonates and children &lt;3 years of
             age) for dynamic calibration without posing a risk to the patient's physiological
             stability
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David S Marks, MD, MBA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susan Foerster, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital and Health System  Foundation, Wisconsin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Froedtert Hospital/Medical College of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 15, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 24, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Blood Pressure</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
