<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="62005">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01818336</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AQ-2010-001</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>AllerQuest LLC</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01818336</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Skin Testing Reagents for Penicillin Allergy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Confirmatory Study to Examine Negative Predictive Value (NPV) and Safety of Skin Testing With PRE-PEN, a Minor Determinant MIxture (MDM) of Penicillin Antigens, and Amoxicillin Reagent Against an Oral Challenge With Amoxicillin</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AllerQuest LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AllerQuest LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A self- or parent-reported history of penicillin allergy excludes approximately 10% of the
      US population from receiving penicillin (Kerr 1994, Kagy, Blaiss 1998, Solensky et al. 2000,
      Neugut et al. 2001). Yet approximately 80% of patients labeled as allergic to the
      penicillins can safely take these antibiotics without fear of a life-threatening reaction
      (Gadde et al. 1993, Macy et al. 1997). The outcomes of this erroneous classification of
      patients include unnecessary denial of an effective and well-tolerated class of antibiotics,
      which are often the treatment of choice.

      The primary aim of skin testing with the Penicillin Skin Test Kit is to identify subjects at
      very low risk of developing acute IgE-dependent reactions when given a penicillin or
      cross-reacting drug. The negative predictive value (NPV) of skin testing is assessed by oral
      challenge with a penicillin.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, open-label investigation of skin testing with the Penicillin Skin
      Test Kit in subjects at least 2 years of age with a self-reported history of possible
      IgE-dependent penicillin hypersensitivity.

      At screening on Day 1, subjects and their parents/legal guardians (if applicable) will sign
      the informed consent form/ pediatric assent form. Following consent/assent, demographic
      information and medical history will be obtained, including prior and current medication
      use. Subjects will also be asked if they have had a respiratory infection in the past 2
      weeks or antibiotics within the past 4 weeks. A physical examination will be performed,
      along with measurements of vital signs and, in subjects &gt;5 years of age with active asthma,
      peak expiratory flow rate (PEFR). A urine pregnancy test will be obtained for all female
      subjects of childbearing potential.

      The skin test procedure will first involve puncture testing. Skin test reagents will include
      the Penicillin Skin Test Kit, histamine (positive control), and sodium chloride (negative
      control). Subjects who have negative skin puncture test results to any of the drug antigens
      contained within the Penicillin Skin Test Kit will then undergo intradermal testing in
      duplicate. Subjects who have a positive reaction to one or more puncture or intradermal
      tests contained within the Penicillin Skin Test Kit will be discharged from the study.
      However, subjects with any positive skin test to drug antigens in the Penicillin Skin Test
      Kit will be asked to return for retesting (puncture and intradermal) in 4 weeks.

      Subjects who have negative puncture and intradermal test results will be given the oral
      amoxicillin challenge, which will be comprised of a single, full oral dose of amoxicillin.
      The purpose of the oral amoxicillin challenge is to confirm lack of allergy and confirm the
      NPV (Negative Predictive Value) of skin testing. Subjects will be monitored at the study
      site for 1 hour following oral amoxicillin challenge and then sent home. The study site will
      follow-up by telephone with all subjects (or their parents/legal guardians in the case of
      young children) ≥72 hours after administration of the oral amoxicillin challenge.

      Adverse events (AEs) will be recorded from administration of the Penicillin Skin Test
      throughout the 3-day study period as spontaneously reported by subjects or observed by the
      site staff.

      Two normal subjects (i.e., no history of penicillin allergy) will be skin tested at each
      site to provide data on skin test specificity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Utility of NPV</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Outcome Measure 1: Negative predictive value (NPV) time frame: up to 72 hours description: The primary endpoint is negative predictive value (NPV), which will be estimated as p = percentage of n history-positive subjects with negative skin tests from the Penicillin Allergy Skin Test Kit (as confirmed with an overall negative result for the Skin Puncture/Intradermal Testing) who do not experience an IgE-dependent hypersensitivity reaction within 72 hours of the oral amoxicillin challenge.
Outcome Measure 2: Reproducibility of skin test time frame: 4 weeks description: A test of reproducibility of skin test results will be performed using the Retest Population. It is expected that the results at 4 weeks will be identical or similar to initial results. Analyses will include comparing all individual skin test results that were positive at the initial testing with the results collected at the 4 week retest.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety Endpoints</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The safety endpoints will be the rate and severity of IgE dependent, drug-related AE observed in the 72 hours after a single dose amoxicillin challenge.
The following safety endpoints will be measured:
Number of participants with adverse events
Number of participants with adverse events associated with skin testing
Change from baseline calculation for vital signs
Change from baseline calculation for peak expiratory flow rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">481</enrollment>
  <condition>History of IgE Dependent Reaction to a Penicillin Product</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>all subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention: Penicillin skin test kit
Subjects with negative intradermal tests will be given single oral amoxicillin challenge dose and followed for 72 hours for IgE dependent reactions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Penicillin skin test kit</intervention_name>
    <description>Allergy skin testing is done by puncture and intradermal.  If all tests negative, subjects receive an oral amoxicillin challenge.</description>
    <arm_group_label>all subjects</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PRE-PEN (benzylpenicilloyl polylysine)</other_name>
    <other_name>MDM (minor determinant mixture of penicillins)</other_name>
    <other_name>benzylpenicillin</other_name>
    <other_name>benzylpenicilloate</other_name>
    <other_name>benzylpenilloate</other_name>
    <other_name>amoxicillin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject (and/or parent or legal guardian for subjects &lt;18 years of age) must have
             provided written, informed consent prior to performance of any procedures. Children
             6-11 years of age must provide verbal assent (or written assent, if required by local
             regulations), and children 12-17 years of age must provide written informed consent
             along with their parent or legal guardian.

          2. Subject can be male or female and must be generally healthy and at least two (2)
             years of age.

          3. Subject must have a reported history of possible IgE dependent reaction to a
             penicillin or its semi-synthetic derivatives, including one or more of the following:
             anaphylaxis, decreased blood pressure and/or diminished consciousness, upper or lower
             airway obstruction, angioedema, urticaria, and/or generalized pruritic rash.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Subject who has exhibited a systemic allergic reaction to previous skin-test
             administration of PRE-PEN, MDM, or individual penicillin metabolites
             (benzylpenicillin, benzylpenicilloate, or benzylpenilloate).

             2. Subject who is pregnant or lactating. 3. Subject who has had a respiratory
             infection within the past 2 weeks or has taken antibiotics of any kind during the
             past 2 weeks (except for topical antibiotics for acne).

             4. Subject who has taken an oral H1-antihistamine within 72 hours prior to skin
             testing.

             5. Subject who has taken hydroxyzine or doxepin within 7 days prior to skin testing.

             6. Subject who has had a penicillin reaction, including semisynthetic penicillins,
             within the last 6 weeks prior to skin testing.

             7. Subject who has received an investigational drug within 30 days prior to skin
             testing or who plans to participate in a study in which an investigational drug will
             be administered within the 30 days following skin testing.

             8. Subjects who have planned hospitalizations or medical or surgical procedures
             during the 72 hours following the oral amoxicillin challenge.

             9. Subjects who plan to take any new prescription or over-the-counter medications or
             herbal supplements during the 72 hours following the oral amoxicillin challenge.

             10. Subject who has had a previous adverse reaction to penicillin or semisynthetic
             derivative and subsequently tolerated a penicillin or semisynthetic derivative
             without an adverse experience.

             11. Subject who, in the investigator's opinion, has any other social or medical
             condition (e.g. fever, rash) that may place the subject at increased risk or may
             confound the interpretation of the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>N. Franklin Adkinson, Jr., MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>AllerQuest LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alabama Allergy &amp; Asthma Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Homewood</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35209</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Allergy Associates of Tucson</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tucson</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85716</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Allergy &amp; Asthma Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Walnut Creek</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94590</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fairfield County Allergy, Asthma &amp; Immunology Assoc., Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Norwalk</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06851</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ct. Asthma &amp; Allergy Center LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Hartford</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06119</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Windom Allergy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sarasota</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>34233</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Atlanta Allergy and Asthma Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30060</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University Medical School</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Midwest Allergy &amp; Asthma Clinic PC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Omaha</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68130</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Corvallis Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Corvallis</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97330</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Allergy &amp; Asthma Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>Germantown</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38138</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwest Asthma &amp; Allergy Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Redmond</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98052</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 10, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 11, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>penicillin allergy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Amoxicillin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Penicillin G</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Penicillin G Benzathine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Penicillin G Procaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
