<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="11745">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02091206</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GWEP1332 Part A</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02091206</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Dose-ranging Pharmacokinetics and Safety Study of GWP42003-P in Children With Dravet Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double Blind, Placebo Controlled Two-part Study to Investigate the Dose-ranging Safety and Pharmacokinetics, Followed by the Efficacy and Safety of Cannabidiol (GWP42003-P) in Children and Young Adults With Dravet Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GW Pharmaceuticals Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GW Pharmaceuticals Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objectives are to evaluate the safety of multiple doses of GWP42003-P compared
      with placebo with respect to:

        -  Incidence, type and severity of adverse events.

        -  Effect on vital signs, including weight.

        -  Effect on 12-lead electrocardiogram findings.

        -  Effect on laboratory parameters.

      Secondary objectives are to:

        -  Determine the pharmacokinetics (what the body does to the drug) of GWP42003-P and its
           major human metabolite, following single and multiple doses of GWP42003-P.

        -  Investigate the effect of GWP42003-P on the plasma concentration of clobazam and its
           major metabolite if taken as an adjuvant medication (i.e. at the same time).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This multi-center study will consist of two parts: Part A and Part B. Part A only will be
      described in this record. Part A is a randomized, double blind 21-day treatment study
      period.  Subjects will be randomized to one of three doses of active or placebo at a 4:1
      ratio.

      Subjects who satisfy all inclusion and none of the exclusion criteria will be assigned a
      unique participant number and then begin a 28-day baseline observation period.

      The investigator will assess the subject's daily number of convulsive seizures from the
      subject's diary data. Subjects who have experienced fewer than four convulsive seizures
      (tonic-clonic seizures and/or drop attacks) during the baseline period and who meet all of
      the other inclusion and none of the exclusion criteria will be eligible to continue in the
      study.

      Eligible subjects will then be randomly assigned to receive one of three dose levels of
      GWP42003-P: 5 mg/kg, 10 mg/kg or 20 mg/kg per day, or matching placebo.

      There will be three groups of 10 subjects. In each group, subjects will be randomly assigned
      so that eight subjects receive active treatment and two subjects receive placebo. Subjects
      will receive GWP42003-P or placebo for a 21-day exposure period, which consists of a
      titration period, followed by a stable dose period.

      A pharmacokinetic assessment will take place after the first single dose of GWP42003-P.
      There will be a second pharmacokinetic assessment after 21 days of consecutive dosing with
      GWP42003-P. Subjects who take clobazam as an adjuvant treatment will be asked to take their
      usual dose two hours prior to attending the clinic so that the pre-treatment (with
      GWP42003-P) plasma concentrations of clobazam and its major metabolite N-desmethylclobazam
      can be measured, and the impact of GWP42003-P treatment on these levels evaluated. An
      interim clinical visit to (primarily) evaluate safety and adherence to the titration regimen
      will take place seven days into the treatment period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of adverse events as measure of subject safety</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 - Day 63</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of subjects who experienced an adverse event during the study is presented. The time frame for adverse event reporting was from screening to the Part A follow-up visit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the plasma concentration time curves for cannabidiol and 7-hydroxy-cannabidiol following single and multiple doses of GWP42003-P</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose then 2-3 and 4-6 h post-dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The pre-dose blood sample was taken prior to the administration of the first dose of study medication.
Further samples were taken between 2 and 3 hours post-dose and 4 and 6 hours post-dose, with a minimum of at least 2 hours between each of the three blood sampling time-points
The following pharmacokinetic parameters were investigated:
Cmax
tmax
Area Under the plasma concentration Curve (AUC)(0-∞), AUC(0-t)
t½</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pre-treatment plasma concentrations of clobazam and N-desmethylclobazam if taken concomitantly with GWP42003-P prior to single and multiple doses of GWP42003-P</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Epilepsy</condition>
  <condition>Dravet Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Myoclonic Epilepsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group/dose level 1a</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>5 mg/kg/day GWP42003-P oral solution.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group/dose level 2a</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>10 mg/kg/day GWP42003-P oral solution.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group/dose level 3a</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>20 mg/kg/day GWP42003-P oral solution.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group/dose level 1b</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Matching placebo for Group/dose level 1a.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group/dose level 2b</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Matching placebo for Group/dose level 2a.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group/dose level 3b</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Matching placebo for Group/dose level 3a.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GWP42003-P</intervention_name>
    <description>GWP42003-P is an oral solution presented as an oily solution containing 25 mg/mL cannabidiol (CBD: FT0086) or 100 mg/mL CBD (FT0095) dissolved in the excipients sesame oil and anhydrous ethanol with added sweetener (sucralose) and strawberry flavoring.
Subjects will be randomly assigned to receive either 5, 10 or 20 mg/kg/day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group/dose level 1a</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group/dose level 2a</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group/dose level 3a</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cannabidiol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo control</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo oral solution contains the excipients sesame oil and anhydrous ethanol with added sweetener (sucralose) and strawberry flavoring.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group/dose level 1b</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group/dose level 2b</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group/dose level 3b</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Key Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject must be male or female aged between four and 10 years (inclusive).

          -  Subject must have a documented history of Dravet syndrome which is not completely
             controlled by current antiepileptic drugs.

          -  Subject must be experiencing fewer than four convulsive seizures (tonic-clonic
             seizures and/or drop attacks) during the 28-day baseline observation period.

          -  Subject must be taking one or more antiepileptic drugs at a dose which has been
             stable for at least four weeks.

          -  All medications or interventions for epilepsy (including ketogenic diet and vagus
             nerve stimulation) must have been stable for four weeks prior to screening and
             subject is willing to maintain a stable regimen throughout the study.

        Key Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has clinically significant unstable medical conditions other than epilepsy.

          -  Subject has had clinically relevant symptoms or a clinically significant illness in
             the four weeks prior to screening or randomization, other than epilepsy.

          -  Subject is currently using or has in the past used recreational or medicinal
             cannabis, or synthetic cannabinoid based medications (including Sativex®) within the
             three months prior to study entry and is unwilling to abstain for the duration for
             the study.

          -  Subject has any known or suspected hypersensitivity to cannabinoids or any of the
             excipients of the investigational medicinal products.

          -  Subjects who have been part of a clinical trial involving another investigational
             product in the previous six months.

          -  There are plans for the subject to travel outside their country of residence during
             the study.

          -  Subjects previously randomized into this study.  In particular, subjects
             participating in Part A of the study cannot enter Part B.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>10 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Richard Potts</last_name>
    <phone>+44 (0) 1980 557000</phone>
    <email>rp@gwpharm.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 17, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cannabidiol</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Epilepsy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epilepsies, Myoclonic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
