<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="82484">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02146248</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OHSU IRB 10103</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02146248</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>HSG and Tubal Patency Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Tubal Patency During the Menstrual Cycle and During Treatment With Hormonal Contraceptives: a Pilot Study in Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jeffrey Jensen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oregon Health and Science University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators' research group is working to develop a highly effective, low cost
      non-surgical method of permanent contraception for women. To support this goal, we need to
      know more about the normal fallopian tube (tube that passes the egg from the ovary into the
      womb).   The purpose of this study is to learn about how menstrual cycles and hormonal
      contraceptives affect tubal patency. Normally there is an opening between the tube and
      uterus to permit the flow of fluid and cells.  If this opening is blocked, this can result
      in infertility. Tubal patency is when a woman's fallopian tubes are not blocked. Tubal
      patency is determined by an x-ray test called a hystero-(uterus)salpingo-(fallopian
      tube)graphy (HSG). HSG is a standard radiological imaging study that is used to determine if
      the fallopian tubes are open and free of disease. It is commonly done in women with an
      infertility diagnosis.  The investigators usually do this test in the first 10 days of the
      menstrual cycle.   Sometimes the tubes will appear to be blocked on the HSG when they are
      actually open.  The timing of the HSG study during the menstrual cycle, or the use of
      hormonal contraception may make a difference in whether the tubes appear blocked on the HSG
      when they are actually patent.

      The results of the HSG test provide a good model for how our nonsurgical permanent
      contraception method might work.  The investigators think that if the tubes are not patent,
      that our treatment will not work as well.  Therefore, in this study we want to learn if
      menstrual cycle timing or current hormonal contraception use will affect the patency of the
      tubes as assessed by the HSG.  The investigators want to examine the same women to see if
      tubal patency is changes during the menstrual cycle and during the use of a birth control
      pill and the birth control shot.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>if menstrual cycle stage or hormonal treatment of women affect functional tubal patency as assessed by HSG</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">8</enrollment>
  <condition>Tubal Patency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HSG Studies</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Women will be given combined oral contraceptives and Depo-medroxyprogesterone acetate (DepoProvera®).
2 HSG studies will be done prior to hormonal treatment, 1 after the pill treatment, and depending on whether the tubes appear patent, 1 more after the depoProvera treatment, and a final HSG after another 2 weeks on the pill.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>combined oral contraceptive</intervention_name>
    <description>combined oral contraceptive pill will be dosed continuously for 30 days without cycle interruption</description>
    <arm_group_label>HSG Studies</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pill, birth control pill, COC</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DepoProvera</intervention_name>
    <description>injectable hormonal contraceptive</description>
    <arm_group_label>HSG Studies</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Depo-medroxyprogesterone acetate, DMPA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        i. Women between 18 and 40 years old ii. In good health, with regular menstrual cycles
        that occur 24 - 37 days iii. No current use of hormonal contraception or an intrauterine
        device and having had at least one complete menstrual cycle since having stopped hormonal
        contraception before starting the treatment.

        iv. Have a negative urine pregnancy test at the admission visit. v. Have a negative
        chlamydia test at the admission visit. vi. Not be at risk for pregnancy. They will be
        consistently using a non-hormonal contraception method, have a surgically sterile male
        partner with a vasectomy, be abstinent, or be in a same-sex relationship from the
        screening visit through the first study cycle.  After starting the combined OC (see Visit
        4 below), use of a non-hormonal method is no longer required.

        vii. In the opinion of the investigator, willing and able to follow all study
        requirements, including use of the approved study medications (doxycycline, oral
        contraceptive and DMPA).

        viii.  Understand and sign an IRB approved inform consent form prior to screening
        activities.

        ix. Will have diastolic blood pressure (BP) ≤85 mm Hg and systolic BP ≤145 mm Hg after 5
        minutes in sitting position.

        x. Agree not to participate in any other clinical trials during the course of this study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  i. Women with menstrual cycle length of less than 24 or more than 37 days; or with
             spontaneous irregular menstrual cycle length with intra-individual variations of more
             than 5 days ii. Currently pregnant as confirmed by positive high-sensitivity urine
             pregnancy test iii. Women planning pregnancy within their months of study
             participation iv. Currently breast-feeding or within 30 days of discontinuing breast
             feeding v. Current use of a hormonal IUD, or other hormonal contraception (including
             oral contraceptives, contraceptive vaginal rings, contraceptive patches, or
             contraceptive implants) within 30 days prior to screening. NOTE: Discontinuation of
             hormonal contraception or removal of implanted hormonal contraceptives must have been
             for personal reasons unrelated to the purpose of enrollment in this study.

        vi. Undiagnosed abnormal genital bleeding vii. Known hypersensitivity to radio-opaque
        contrast, doxycycline, levonorgestrel, ethinyl estradiol or depo-medroxyprogesterone
        acetate. The active ingredients in the approved medications used in the study.

        viii. Anomalies in the clinical exam or history done at screening visit recognized as
        clinically significant by the investigator.

        ix. Unable to pass a uterine sound at the screening examination. x. A positive test for
        chlamydia at screening, or a history of a positive test within the last 6 months.

        xi. A clinically significant Pap test abnormality, as managed by current local or national
        guidelines that would require treatment over the next 6 months.

        xii. Invasive cancer (past history of any carcinoma or sarcoma, except non-melanoma skin
        cancer) xiii. Body mass index (BMI) &gt;35. xiv. Current use of a non-hormone containing
        (copper) intrauterine device (IUD). NOTE: Removal of an IUD must have been for personal
        reasons unrelated to the purpose of enrollment in this study.

        xv. Smoking if &gt; age 35. xvi. Personal history of venous or arterial thrombosis or
        embolism, or family history in a first-degree relative &lt;55 years of age suggesting
        familial defect in blood coagulation system, which in the opinion of the principal
        investigator, suggests use of a hormonal contraceptive could pose a significant risk.

        xvii. Cerebrovascular or cardiovascular disease. xviii. History of retinal vascular
        lesions, unexplained partial or complete loss of vision.

        xix. Headaches with focal neurological symptoms. xx. History of cholestatic jaundice of
        pregnancy or jaundice with prior steroid use.

        xxi. Use of liver enzyme inducers on a regular basis. xxii. History of involuntary
        infertility, pelvic inflammatory disease (not followed by a normal pregnancy), or known
        gynecologic conditions or surgery that could affect tubal patency (e.g. tubal adhesions,
        endometriosis, hydrosalpinx, salpingectomy, hysterectomy, oophorectomy).

        xxiii. History of a prior HSG showing tubal occlusion on one or both sides.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeffrey Jensen, MD MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Oregon Health and Science University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cat Dennis, BA</last_name>
    <phone>503-494-3666</phone>
    <email>whru@ohsu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oregon Health &amp; Science University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jeffrey Jensen, MD MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 22, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 21, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Oregon Health &amp; Science University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jeffrey Jensen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr. Jeffrey Jensen</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hysterosalpingography, DMPA, combined oral contraceptive, tubal patency</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Contraceptive Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Medroxyprogesterone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Medroxyprogesterone Acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Contraceptives, Oral</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Contraceptives, Oral, Combined</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
