<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="73808">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01829243</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00026392</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01829243</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Milnacipran and Neurocognition, Pain and Fatigue in Fibromyalgia : A 13-week Randomized, Placebo Controlled Cross Over Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>Milnacipran and Neurocognition, Pain and Fatigue in Fibromyalgia: A 13-week Randomized, Placebo Controlled Cross Over Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Forest Laboratories</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study was designed to  investigate whether milnacipran is safe and effective in
      improving cognitive function in fibromyalgia. In addition, this study was aimed to
      investigate whether improvement in neurocognitive status due to milnacipran correlates with
      improvements in pain, to investigate whether improvement in neurocognitive status due to
      milnacipran correlates with improvements in fatigue, and to determine whether treatment with
      improvement in neurocognitive status, pain and fatigue correlates with functional
      improvement.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cognitive dysfunction is observed in fibromyalgia, especially for episodic memory, learning,
      and working memory.There is evidence for dysregulation of the attention system from
      low-level sensory processes up to emotional processes, and increased sensitivity to
      distraction.Milnacipran's balance of norepinephrine (NE) to serotonin (5-HT) of 3:1, similar
      to amitriptyline, a tricyclic that has demonstrated efficacy in fibromyalgia, as compared to
       venlafaxine which is 1:30, or  duloxetine which is 1:10.7 In addition, because of
      milnacipran's effect on 5-HT, it should also be effective in treating other symptoms such as
      sleep disturbances and mood changes, which are associated to fibromyalgia, as well as other
      functional somatic syndromes. It is worth noting that several medications to treat
      fibromyalgia are sedating (e.g pregabalin, opioids, muscle relaxants) and impair
      neurocognition.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Visual Analogue Scale for Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 1, 2,4, 6, 8 10, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Visual Analogue Scale for Pain operationally is a 100 mm line anchored by word descriptors at each end. The patient marks a point on the line that reflects their current pain state. The distance in mm from the left anchor point is the score.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in The Fatigue Severity Scale (FSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 1, 2,4, 6, 8 10, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Fatigue Severity Scale (FSS) is composed of nine items with a seven-point response format. Sample questions include &quot;I am easily fatigued&quot; and &quot;Exercise brings on my fatigue.&quot; In the initial validation study, internal consistency for the Fatigue Severity Scale was high for specific illness groups (MS and lupus) and healthy controls. The scale clearly distinguished patients from controls and it was moderately correlated with a single-item visual analogue scale of fatigue intensity. In all patients, clinical improvement in fatigue was associated with reductions in scores on the Fatigue Severity Scale. The Fatigue Severity Scale is also a practical measure due to its brevity and ease of administration and scoring.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Brief Assessment of Cognition(BAC) and MATRICS.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 1, 2,4, 6, 8 10, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The BAC was designed to assess longitudinal change in cognition in clinical trials. A description of the BAC and its reliability and validity has been published previously). BAC takes approximately 30 minutes to administer, and measures cognition in four of the major domains of cognition: reasoning and problem solving, processing speed, verbal memory, and working memory.The BAC includes six tests from four of the MATRICS domains. The study team supplemented the BAC to include tests from the three additional MATRICS domains: the Continuous Performance Test (CPT), (vigilance), the Brief Visuospatial Memory Test (BVSMT) (visual learning), and the Managing Emotions tests (MSCEIT) (social cognition).  This BAC/MATRICS Hybrid assessed all seven MATRICS domains in approximately 60 minutes of testing</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">23</enrollment>
  <condition>Fibromyalgia</condition>
  <condition>Neurocognition</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Milnacipran</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Eligible subjects will receive milnacipran (12.5 mg-200 mg/day) in the forces titration schedule in flexible doses to the maximum tolerated dose starting with 12.5 mg qd for 1 day, 12.5 mg bid for 2 days, 25 mg bid for 4 days, 50 mg bid for 7 days and 100 mg bid thereafter. Patients who cannot tolerate higher doses will have a step-wise reduction in doses (e.g. 200 mg/day dose will be reduced to 100 mg/day; 100 mg/day will be reduced to 50 mg/day). Drug will be discontinued at the end of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Eligible subjects will receive placebo (12.5 mg-200 mg/day) in the forces titration schedule in flexible doses to the maximum tolerated dose starting with 12.5 mg qd for 1 day, 12.5 mg bid for 2 days, 25 mg bid for 4 days, 50 mg bid for 7 days and 100 mg bid thereafter. Patients who cannot tolerate higher doses will have a step-wise reduction in doses (e.g. 200 mg/day dose will be reduced to 100 mg/day; 100 mg/day will be reduced to 50 mg/day). Drug will be discontinued at the end of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Milnacipran</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Milnacipran</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Savella</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Milnacipran</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18 to 65 years.

          -  Specific diagnosis of FM by the participant's rheumatologist or           physician,
             including written confirmation, from a physician, of the FM diagnosis.

          -  Confirmation of the FM diagnosis by American College of Rheumatology Criteria and a
             physical tender point examination.

          -  Ability to give informed consent.

          -  If female, nonpregnant/nonlactating.

          -  If a sexually active female of reproductive potential, must be using adequate
             contraception (i.e., oral contraceptives, barrier protection, or prior tubal
             ligation) during the trial.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Bipolar disorders, any psychotic disorder.

          -  the existence of concomitant rheumatological disorders, including rheumatoid
             arthritis, systemic lupus erythematosus, Hashimoto's disease, Sjogren's syndrome or
             scleroderma.

          -  Substance dependence (except nicotine dependence) in the previous 3 months.

          -  Currently suicidal or high suicide risk.

          -  Serious or unstable medical disorders.

          -  Any psychotropic drug treatment in the previous 2 weeks before screening.

          -  A positive urine pregnancy test.

          -  Screening laboratory values three times the limits of normal or judged clinically
             significant by the investigator.

          -  History of hypersensitivity to milnacipran.

          -  Seizure disorder, traumatic brain injury, any CNS disorder that affects cognitive
             status.

          -  Concomitant meds: A minimum of 30 days on stable dose of analgesics and a minimum of
             4 week washout from antidepressants and fibromyalgia specific medication ( e.g.
             pregabalin, neurontin) and supplements ( St John's wort, SAM-E).

          -  Narrow angle glaucoma.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ashwin A Patkar, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Medical Center / Civitan Building</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 9, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 9, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Milnacipran</keyword>
  <keyword>Fibromyalgia</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurocognition</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fibromyalgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myofascial Pain Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Milnacipran</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
