<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="57050">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01947933</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15039</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>I6T-MC-AMAA</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01947933</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of LY3074828 in Participants With Psoriasis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Study of LY3074828, an Anti-IL-23 Humanized Antibody, in Subjects With Psoriasis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eli Lilly and Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eli Lilly and Company</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety of the study drug known as
      LY3074828 in participants with psoriasis.  The study will investigate how the body processes
      the study drug and how the drug affects the body.  The study will last about 3 months for
      each participant.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with One or More Adverse Event(s) (SAEs) Considered by the Investigator to be Related to Study Drug Administration</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline through 12 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics (PK): Area Under the Concentration Curve (AUC) of LY3074828</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline through 12 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics (PK): Maximum Drug Concentration (Cmax) of LY3074828</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline through 12 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Psoriasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo IV</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with psoriasis will receive a single dose of placebo matching LY3074828 intravenously (IV)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LY3074828 IV</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with psoriasis will receive a single escalating dose of LY3074828 starting at 5 mg, IV</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LY3074828 SQ</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with psoriasis will receive a single dose of LY3074828 subcutaneously (SQ).  Dose to be determined based upon pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamic (PK/PD) data.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LY3074828 - IV</intervention_name>
    <description>Administered IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>LY3074828 IV</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LY3074828 - SQ</intervention_name>
    <description>Administered SQ</description>
    <arm_group_label>LY3074828 SQ</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo - IV</intervention_name>
    <description>Administered IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo IV</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Chronic plaque psoriasis based on an investigator confirmed diagnosis of chronic
             psoriasis vulgaris for at least 6 months prior to baseline

          -  Plaque psoriasis involving &gt;2% body surface area (BSA) in affected skin other than
             the face and scalp at screening and baseline

          -  Are willing and able to undergo baseline and posttreatment skin lesion biopsy

          -  Are willing and able to washout topicals for at least 14 days before baseline on the
             2 target lesions

          -  Have adequate organ function including absolute neutrophil count &gt;1.5
             cells/microliter (uL), hemoglobin level &gt;10 grams/deciliter (g/dL), lymphocyte count
             &gt;500 cells/uL, total white blood cell count &gt;3.0 cells/uL, bilirubin level &lt;1.5 times
             the upper limit of normal (ULN) and alkaline phosphatase, alanine transaminase and
             aspartate transaminase &lt;1.5 times ULN

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Have had a clinically significant flare of psoriasis during the 12 weeks before
             randomization

          -  Have a history of drug-induced psoriasis or parapsoriasis

          -  Within 28 days prior to baseline:  have received systemic nonbiologic psoriasis
             therapy (including, but not limited to, oral psoralen plus ultraviolet A light
             therapy (PUVA); cyclosporine; corticosteroids; methotrexate; oral retinoids;
             mycophenolate mofetil; thioguanine; hydroxyurea; sirolimus; azathioprine; fumaric
             acid derivatives; or 1, 25 dihydroxy vitamin D3 and analogues or phototherapy
             (including either oral and topical PUVA light therapy, ultraviolet B or
             self-treatment with tanning beds or therapeutic sunbathing)

          -  Within 14 days prior to baseline: have received topical psoriasis treatment
             (including, but not limited to, corticosteroids, anthralin, calcipotriene, topical
             vitamin D derivatives, retinoids, tazarotene, emollients and other nonprescription
             topical products containing urea, &gt;3% salicylic acid, alpha- or beta-hydroxyl acids,
             or medicated shampoos [for example those that contain &gt;3% salicylic acid,
             corticosteroids, coal tar, or vitamin D3 analogues])

          -  Have recurrent or persistent uncontrolled Stage 1 hypertension (systolic blood
             pressure of 140-159 millimeters of mercury [mmHg] or diastolic blood pressure of
             90-99 mmHg) or greater according to the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common
             Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAS 4.0)

          -  Evidence of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection and/or positive human HIV
             antibodies

          -  Evidence of or test positive for hepatitis C virus (HCV)

          -  Evidence of hepatitis B and/or positive hepatitis B surface antigen or are positive
             for hepatitis B core antibody and negative for hepatitis B surface antibody

          -  Have had clinically significant symptomatic herpes zoster within 3 months of
             screening

          -  Show evidence of active or latent tuberculosis

          -  Have received live vaccine(s) (included attenuated live vaccines) within 1 month of
             screening or intend to during the study

          -  Have received treatment with biologic therapies for psoriasis (such as monoclonal
             antibodies, including marketed or investigational biologic therapy).  Prior or
             current use of biologics for indications other than psoriasis may be allowed with
             sponsor approval

          -  Have had lymphoma, leukemia, or any malignancy within the past 5 years, except for
             basal cell or squamous epithelial carcinomas of the skin that have been resected with
             no evidence of metastatic disease for 3 years and cervical carcinoma in situ, with no
             evidence of recurrence within 5 years prior to baseline

          -  Have any other skin conditions (excluding psoriasis) that would affect interpretation
             of the results (including, but not limited to, scleroderma eczema or cutaneous
             manifestations of other autoimmune disease - such as systemic lupus erythematosus)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Call 1-877-CTLILLY (1-877-285-4559) or 1-317-615-4559 Mon - Fri 9 AM - 5 PM Eastern time (UTC/GMT - 5 hours, EST</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Eli Lilly and Company</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>There may be multiple sites in this clinical trial 1-877-CTLILLY (1-877-285-4559) or</last_name>
    <phone>1-317-615-4559</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>For additional information regarding investigative sites for this trial, contact 1-877-CTLILLY (1-877-285-4559, 1-317-615-4559) Mon - Fri from 9 AM to 5 PM Eastern Time (UTC/GMT - 5 hours, EST), or speak with your personal physician.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Waterloo</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N2J 1C4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eli Lilly</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>For additional information regarding investigative sites for this trial, contact 1-877-CTLILLY (1-877-285-4559, 1-317-615-4559) Mon - Fri from 9 AM to 5 PM Eastern Time (UTC/GMT - 5 hours, EST), or speak with your personal physician.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H2K4L5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eli Lilly</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 30, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Psoriasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
