<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="104253">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01974661</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IM-102</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-001787-31</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01974661</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase I Safety Study of Dendritic Cell Vaccine to Treat Patients With Hepatocellular Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Open-label Study to Evaluate Safety and Immunologic Response of COMBIG-DC Administered Intra-tumorally in Patients With Hepatocellular Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Immunicum AB</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Uppsala University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Immunicum AB</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Sweden: Medical Products Agency</authority>
    <authority>Sweden: Regional Ethical Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to answer the question &quot;Is it possible to inject the
      COMBIG-DC vaccine in a hepatic tumor without getting unacceptable side effects&quot;?
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients diagnosed with hepatocellular carcinoma will get COMBIG-DC vaccinations at three
      occasions with 2-3 weeks and 3-5 weeks between vaccination 2 and 3 respectively. Adverse
      events will be registered until 6 months after last vaccination, as well as changes in vital
      signs (heart rate, blood pressure and body temperature) and lab parameters. Immunologic
      response will be evaluated by measuring immunologic markers in blood. The size of the
      tumor/tumors will be evaluated  after 3 and 6 months and thereafter every three months until
      tumor progression.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Registration of adverse events as a measure of safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months after last patient's last vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in vital signs from baseline (heart rate, blood pressure, body temperature)
Changes in lab parameters from baseline
Short term worsening in ECOG and/or Child Pugh and/or MELD score
Local procedural injuries, assessed by MRI or ultrasound</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate systemic inflammatory response</measure>
    <time_frame>Until 3 months after last vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Potential systemic release of relevant cytokines, chemokines and other inflammatory parameters in blood;IL-1R, IL-2,IL-4, IL-5, IL-6, IL-7, IL-8, IL-10, IL-12p70, IL-13, IL-17A, G-CSF. GM-CSF, IFN-gamma, MCP-1, MIP-1 beta and TNF-alpha.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate tumor control</measure>
    <time_frame>Until 6 months after last patient's last vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>CT/MRI evaluation 3 and 6 months after first vaccination. Patients with stable disease or tumor response will continue tumor evaluation every 3rd month until progress or until last study patient has had his/her 6 month visit.
Measuring number of tumor specific T cells with flow cytometry after in vitro stimulation with different pools of HCC-associated tumor peptides (Alpha-feto protein (AFP), and hTERT)
Measuring AFP (alpha-feto protein) levels in blood
Measuring the level of circulating tumor cell, identified as tested positive for MICA, EpCAM, CD133, CD34, CK18</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Long term changes in ECOG scores</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months after last vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in body weight</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months after last vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate systemic immunological response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 months after last vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Vaccine cell tracking; PBMCs will be stained with antibodies specific for  one HLA class I or one HLA-class II antigen that is selectively expressed on donor vaccine cells.
vaccine-induced alloimmunization; screening of alloantibodies against HLA-A, B, C (MHC-class I) and HLA-DR, DQ, DP (MHC-class II) antigens
autoimmune events; screening of autoantibodies against autoantigens, including  nuclear antigens (ANA, SSA, SSB, Sm, RNP, Scl-70, Centromeres and Jo-1) and liver parenchyma-associated autoantigens (liver-kidney microsomal antigens and mitochondrial antigens)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Long term changes in Quality of Life scores</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months after last vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate systemic immunological response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 months after last vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>complement activation; classical/alternative complement function, C3, C4, C3d, and Factor-B.
immune cell occurrence and activation state; CD3+ , CD3+4+  and CD3+8+  T cells, CD19+ B-cells CD3-16+56+ NK-cells,  CD3-16+56+69+ NK cells, CD3+16+56+ NKT-cells, CD3+16+56+69+ NKT-cells and CD3+HLA-DR+ T cells.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Local tissue changes in injected/non-injected tumor and surrounding tissue, assessed by MRI</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month after each vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>An optional addition to the assessment of local procedural injuries (primary outcome).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatocellular Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>COMBIG-DC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>COMBIG-DC (allogeneic dendritic cells) Cancer Vaccine 3 vaccinations: 5, 10 or 20 million cells per injection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>COMBIG-DC</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>COMBIG-DC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Be informed of the nature of the study and have provided written informed consent

          -  At least 18 years of age.

          -  Diagnosis of hepatocellular carcinoma according to EASL criteria or pathology.

          -  Radiologically measurable liver tumor(s), i.e. at least 20 mm in longest
             uni-dimensional diameter as measured by CT/MRI

          -  Not eligible for curatively aiming treatment or TACE.  Tumor stage B or C according
             to BCLC.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Performance status &gt; ECOG 2

          -  Liver function according to Child-Pugh &gt;7 points.

          -  Known major reaction/adverse event in connection with previously made vaccination
             (e.g. asthma, anaphylaxia or other serious reaction).

          -  Known major reaction/adverse event in connection with previous transfusions of blood
             products

          -  Active autoimmune disease requiring treatment with systemic immunosuppressive agents,
              e.g. inflammatory bowel disease, multiple sclerosis, sarcoidosis,  psoriasis,
             autoimmune  hemolytic anemia, rheumatoid arthritis, SLE, vasculitis, Sjögren's
             syndrome, scleroderma, autoimmune hepatitis, and other rheumatological diseases.

          -  Tested positive for HIV

          -  Active or latent virus disease (HBV and  HCV)

          -  Ongoing infection that requires treatment with antibiotics or antiviral medication

          -  Treatment with immunosuppressive treatments like corticosteroids (Immunosuppression
             (within 28 days) prior to the first injection of COMBIG-DC. Inhaled, intranasal and
             local steroids accepted), or mTor inhibitors within 28 days before first vaccination.

          -  Patients with prior history of malignancy other than HCC, except for 5 years
             follow-up of adequately treated in situ carcinoma without recurrences or non-melanoma
             skin cancer.

          -  Inadequate laboratory parameters, i.e.:

               1. P-Prothrombincomplex (PK) &gt;1.4,

               2. Platelet count &lt;50 75 x109/L

               3. Leukocyte count &lt;3.0 x 109/L

               4. P-APT time outside normal limit

          -  Previous organ transplantation

          -  Women of Childbearing Potential (WOCBP) refusing to use adequate contraception (oral
             or injectable contraceptives, hormone releasing intrauterine device) throughout the
             study period.

          -  Pregnant or lactating women

          -  Life expectancy less than 3 months.

          -  Concomitant anti-tumor treatment (within 28 days) prior to the first injection of
             COMBIG-DC.

          -  Concomitant Investigational treatment (within 28 days) prior to the first injection
             of COMBIG-DC.

          -  Known blood dyscrasia (bleeding complication).

          -  Known malignancy in CNS

          -  Any reason that, in the opinion of the investigator, contraindicates that the patient
             participates in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Magnus Rizell, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Sweden</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dept. of Transplantation and Liver Surgery, Sahlgrenska University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gothenburg</city>
        <zip>SE-413 45</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Magnus Rizell, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+4631 342 15 47</phone>
      <email>magnus.rizell@surgery.gu.se</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Magnus Rizell, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Malin Sternby Eilard, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 25, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 21, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
