<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="135997">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01659580</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>T89-07-CAESA</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>T89-07-GL</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01659580</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase III Trial of Dantonic® (T89) Capsule to Prevent and Treat Stable Angina</brief_title>
  <acronym>CAESA</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase III Confirmatory Trial to Confirm the Anti-anginal Effect of Dantonic® (T89) in Patients With Chronic Stable Angina</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tasly Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tasly Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase III study is designed as a double blind, randomized, multi-nation, multi-center,
      placebo controlled clinical research, which aims to evaluate the safety and efficacy of
      Dantonic® (T89) in patients with chronic stable angina pectoris.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Dantonic® (T89) is a botanical drug consists of extracts of Danshen (Radix Salviae
      Miltiorrhizae) and Sanqi (Radix Notoginseng) with borneol in a capsule form. The drug is
      currently approved in 26 countries outside the USA for the treatment and prevention of
      chronic stable angina pectoris and other cardiovascular disease related conditions. This
      pivotal confirmative Phase III clinical trial is to confirm the efficacy and safety of the
      drug at 150mg and 225mg doses in the prevention and treatment of angina pectoris in patients
      with Chronic Stable Angina. The contribution of the main herb Danshen to, and the difference
      of various production batches in, the overall efficacy and safety profiles will also be
      explored. Patients will take a morning and an evening dose orally (every 12 hours) for 6
      weeks while stop taking any long-acting nitroglycerin, ranolazine, and/or multiple
      beta-blockers or beta blocker(s) with calcium channel blocker during the trial. Single
      beta-blocker and/or on-demand short acting nitroglycerin to relief angina pectoris is
      allowed during the trial.  After physical exams and if eligible to participation, patients
      will stop taking other drugs, and undergo two baseline screen Exercise Treadmill Tests (ETT)
      on Standard Bruce Protocol in the clinic one week before and right before starting the drug
      treatment. Patients will perform three more ETTs before the morning dose at the end of week
      2, 4 and 6 after receiving the drug treatment. The primary efficiency endpoint is the change
      of symptom-limited Total Exercise Duration of the ETT at the end of the 4th week of
      treatment from the average of the two screening baselines compared with that of placebo
      treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The change of symptom-limited TED from baseline compared to placebo at the end of week 4.</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The change of symptom-limited Total Exercise Duration (TED) at trough drug levels at the end of the 4th week of treatment from screen baseline on Standard Bruce Protocol compared with placebo.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The change of symptom-limited TED at trough drug levels at the end of the 2nd and 6th weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>2nd weeks and 6th weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The change of symptom-limited TED at trough drug levels at the end of the 2nd and 6th weeks of treatment from screen baseline on Standard Bruce Protocol compared with placebo;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of weekly angina episodes</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Frequency of weekly angina episodes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Time to onset of angina during Excise Tolerance Test (ETT);</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Time to onset of angina during ETT;</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">960</enrollment>
  <condition>Angina Pectoris</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A: T89 High dose treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Drug to be given as 3x75mg capsule, twice a day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B: T89 Low dose treatment.</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Drug to be given as 2x75mg plus one placebo capsule, twice a day. The daily dose is 300 mg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group C: Exploratory base treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Drug to be given as 3 capsules contains herbal extract of Sanqi and Borneol that matches 75 mg T89 capsule. twice a day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group D: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Drug to be given as 3 placebo capsules, twice a day. The daily dose is 0 mg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>T89</intervention_name>
    <description>A botanical drug</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A: T89 High dose treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B: T89 Low dose treatment.</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group C: Exploratory base treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Dantonic®</other_name>
    <other_name>Dantonic® dripping pill</other_name>
    <other_name>Cardiotonic® pill</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Written informed consent.

          2. Males and females between the ages of 20 and 80 years.

          3. Females of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test, not be breast
             feeding and established on a method of contraception that in the investigator's
             opinion is acceptable. Females must agree to remain on their established method of
             contraception through their participation in the study and for 14 days following the
             last dose of study drug.

          4. Evidence of coronary artery disease that consists of a well-documented medical
             history (over 3 months prior to the enrolment) of myocardial infarction or
             significant coronary artery disease with noninvasive or angiographic confirmation.

          5. Symptoms that support the diagnosis of chronic angina and/or a history of an abnormal
             exercise response limited by angina and/or electrocardiograph (ECG) changes.

          6. Moderate angina pectoris (Class II or III, Grading of Angina Pectoris by the Canadian
             Cardiovascular Society Classification System).

          7. Patient whose symptom-limited Total Exercise Duration (TED) is between 3 to 7 minutes
             in Exercise Tolerance Test (ETT) on Standard Bruce Protocol, and symptom-limited TED
             on two screen examinations (Day -7 and 0) in which the shorter is within 85% of the
             longer .

          8. Patient has been on one beta-blocker or on one calcium-channel blocker for at least
             14 days prior to dosing of study medication and can remain on this treatment
             throughout the study as background anti-anginal treatment. Short-acting nitroglycerin
             for on-demand use is allowed for all eligible patients.

          9. Understand and be willing, able and likely to comply with all study procedures and
             restrictions and comprehends the verbal rating scales and diary cards.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. With contraindication to, unable to, or with other co-morbidities that may prevent or
             interfere with the ability to perform treadmill ETT (including, but not limited to:
             pulmonary hypertension, functionally limiting COPD (chronic obstructive pulmonary
             disease), history of pulmonary tuberculosis, prior hospitalization for acute
             exacerbation of chronic lung disease, home oxygen use, chronic oral steroid therapy
             that can limit exercise capacity, functionally limiting peripheral artery disease,
             etc.).

          2. Presence of electrocardiographic or other abnormalities/factors that could interfere
             with exercise electrocardiograph interpretation or may lead to a false positive
             stress test (e.g., pre-exercise horizontal or down-sloping ST segment depression in
             any standard lead, cardiac glycoside therapy, Lown-Ganong-Levine Syndrome,
             Wolff-Parkinson-White syndrome (WPW), left bundle branch block, left ventricular
             hypertrophy with repolarization abnormality, implanted pacemaker, etc.).

          3. Clinically significant arrhythmias or atrioventricular conduction block greater than
             first degree, decompensated heart failure, atrial fibrillation, hypertrophic
             cardiomyopathy.

          4. Acute coronary syndrome (acute myocardial infarction or unstable angina) in the prior
             2 months or coronary revascularization within the prior 6 months or planned coronary
             revascularization during the study period.

          5. Congenital cardiac defects, ongoing history of decompensated congestive heart
             failure, severe valvular disease, severe uncontrolled hypertension (seated systolic
             blood pressure &gt; 180 mm Hg or diastolic blood pressure &gt; 110 mm Hg), severe anemia,
             suspected or known dissecting aortic aneurysm, acute myocarditis or pericarditis,
             thrombophlebitis or pulmonary embolism.

          6. History of bleeding diathesis, cerebral hemorrhage, or seizure disorders that
             required anticonvulsant medication.

          7. Patients requiring the use of long-acting nitroglycerin, ranolazine, and/or multiple
             anti-anginal drugs.

          8. Aspirin and/or statins started less than 14 days prior to the signing of informed
             consent.

          9. Pregnancy or lactation.

         10. Clinical trials/experimental medication 1) Participation in any other clinical trial
             or receipt of an investigational drug within 30 days prior to the initial visit.

        2) Previous participation in the studies of T89. 11. Substance abuse. Patients with a
        recent history (within the last 2 years) of alcoholism or known drug dependence.

        12. Is a family member or relative of the study site staff. 13. Any other conditions that,
        in the opinion of the investigator, are likely to prevent compliance with the study
        protocol or pose a safety concern if the subject participates in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Henry He Sun, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Tasly Group, Co. Ltd.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Martin Lucas</last_name>
    <phone>+1 215 616 3540</phone>
    <email>Martin.Lucas@iconplc.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jason Zhixin Guo, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+1 301-216-3838</phone>
    <email>Jzxguo@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Contract</name>
      <address>
        <city>Multiple Cities</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Under Contracting</name>
      <address>
        <city>Multiple Citis</city>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.tasly.com</url>
    <description>manufacture and sponsor</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 6, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 19, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Angina Pectoris Treatment Prevention</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Angina Pectoris</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiotonic Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
