<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="61927">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01692236</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>120200</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>12-CC-0200</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01692236</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Brain Imaging for HIV-Associated Thinking and Mood Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>Neurovascular Magnetic Resonance Imaging in the Assessment of HIV-Associated Neurocognitive Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection appears to cause problems with blood vessel
      function. These problems may add to some thinking and mood disorders found in people with
      HIV infection. Researchers want to evaluate HIV infected patients to see if blood vessel
      function contributes to thinking and mood disorders, such as early dementia and depression.
      To do so, they will compare study results between people with and people without HIV
      infection.

      Objectives:

        -  To compare the thickness of blood vessel walls between people with and without HIV
           infection.

        -  To study the relationship between blood vessel thickness and thinking and mood
           disorders.

      Eligibility:

        -  Individuals between 25 and 55 years of age who have HIV infection.

        -  Healthy individuals between 25 and 55 years of age.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. Blood and urine
           samples will be collected.

        -  Participants will have imaging studies of the brain and major blood vessels in the head
           and neck.

        -  Participants will also have neuropsychological testing. These tests will look at
           memory, learning and thinking ability, attention, and mood.

        -  Participants will have the option of coming back for repeat  blood tests every six
           months and repeat imaging studies and neuropsychological tests   every year, over 1- 4
           years period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      HIV/AIDS has been transformed from an inevitably fatal, progressive infection to a
      manageable chronic condition. Yet, HIV associated neurocognitive disorders (HANDs) and major
      depressive disorder (MDD) continue to pose a significant clinical problem, even among
      patients with well-controlled viremia. There is also growing evidence of accelerated
      vascular aging and other types of vascular abnormalities in HIV-infected (HIV+) people, and
      preliminary evidence suggests their association with unfavorable neurocognitive outcomes.
      Thus, one possible contributing factor to the high rates of HANDs and depression could be
      vascular dysfunction, similar to vascular depression and vascular dementia that occur in
      elderly non-HIV+ individuals. One commonly used diagnostic marker of vasculopathy is
      thickening of the vessel wall. Multiple studies have already established the correlation
      between vessel wall thickening and vascular disease manifestations. This prospective
      observational study aims to examine the relationships between neurocognitive and depression
      outcomes and vessel wall thickness as a marker of vascular disease in HIV+ adults. We will
      be using neuropsychological testing, brain imaging, blood biomarkers, and state-of-the-art
      high-resolution MR imaging of the intra- and extracranial vessel walls. Forty HIV+
      participants and 40 HIV-negative controls will be recruited. HIV+ participants who consent
      to longitudinal follow-up will be followed for a total of 4 years starting from the initial
      presentation, with evaluations every 6 months. HIV-negative participants will be followed
      for 1 additional year to provide comparison data. Cross-sectional data analysis will examine
      the vascular and neurocognitive markers in both groups of participants. The longitudinal
      data analysis will assess the temporal progression of vascular disease (blood and imaging
      findings) in relation to changes in neurocognitive and depression scores in both groups.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropsychologic testing scores</measure>
    <time_frame>1-6 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum biomarkers of cardiovascular disease and inflammation</measure>
    <time_frame>1-6 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MRI brain and vascular findings</measure>
    <time_frame>1-6 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Human Immunodeficiency Virus</condition>
  <condition>Neurocognitive Impairment</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Inclusion criteria for all participants:

          1. Age 25-55 years.

          2. Willingness to allow stored samples, human leukocyte antigen (HLA) testing, and
             future genetic testing.

          3. Hemoglobin less than or equal to 9.0 g/dL, HCT less than or equal to 28%, platelets
             less than or equal to 50,000/microL.

          4. English language fluency (required for neuropsychological testing).

        Additional inclusion criteria for HIV+ participants:

          1. Documented HIV infection by standard HIV testing. Prior documentation of HIV-
             antibody status at the NIH will be accepted in lieu of repeat testing.

          2. HIV viral load below the limit of detection on combination antiretroviral therapy for
             less than or equal to 1 year.

          3. Under the care of a primary care physician.

        Additional inclusion criteria for HIV-negative participants:

        1. HIV-antibody negative.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Exclusion criteria for all participants:

          1. Contraindication to MRI scanning, including pacemakers or other implanted electrical
             devices, brain stimulators, some types of dental implants, aneurysm clips (metal
             clips on the wall of a large artery), metallic prostheses (including metal pins and
             rods, heart valves, and cochlear implants), permanent eyeliner, implanted delivery
             pump, or shrapnel fragments.

          2. Subjects requiring sedation for MRI studies.

          3. Subjects with a condition precluding entry into scanner and acquisition of scans
             (e.g., morbid obesity, claustrophobia, back pain, motion disorders).

          4. Chronic renal insufficiency defined as a glomerular filtration rate &lt; 30 mL/min/1.73
             m(2) as estimated using the Modified Diet in Renal Disease equation.

          5. Evidence of current or prior central nervous system opportunistic infection(s) and/or
             space-occupying lesions such as primary CNS lymphoma.

          6. Prior history of intrathecal chemotherapy or radiation therapy to the brain.

          7. History of or current diagnosis of systemic vasculitis.

          8. Active systemic infection or malignancy requiring therapy.

          9. Psychiatric condition interfering with ability to participate in study procedures or
             provide informed consent.

         10. Patient or provider report of alcohol or drug abuse ongoing or within 3 months prior
             to participation.

         11. Sickle cell disease (due to known association with vasculopathy).

         12. Systolic blood pressure less than or equal to 180 mmHg at screening.

         13. Persons infected with hepatitis C virus (HCV) who are being treated or planning to
             seek treatment for HCV.

         14. Women who are lactating, pregnant, or actively seeking to become pregnant.

         15. Other known clinical condition or conditions discovered on MRI that, at the
             discretion of the investigators, precludes serial clinical, neuropsychological, or
             imaging evaluation.

        Additional exclusion criteria for HIV+ participants

        1. HIV acquired perinatally (due to potential effects of HIV and antiretroviral therapy on
        neurocognitive and vascular development).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Caryn G Morse, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cheryl L. Chairez</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-3840</phone>
    <email>chairezc@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Caryn G Morse, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-9320</phone>
    <email>cmorse@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2012-CC-0200.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Connor M. Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) and stroke: targets for intervention. Infect Disord Drug Targets. 2010 Apr;10(2):76-83. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20166974</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Highleyman L. Mortality trends: toward a new definition of AIDS? BETA. 2005 Winter;17(2):18-28.</citation>
    <PMID>15828120</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holtgrave DR. Causes of the decline in AIDS deaths, United States, 1995-2002: prevention, treatment or both? Int J STD AIDS. 2005 Dec;16(12):777-81. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16336756</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 20, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <keyword>MRI</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurocognitive Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Major Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Vasculopathy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunologic Deficiency Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
