<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="149704">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01952288</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>B1195-I</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01952288</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Simvastatin for mTBI</brief_title>
  <official_title>Simvastatin: Proof-of-Concept for Prevention of Neurodegeneration in Mild TBI</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Study of simvastatin in Iraq/Afghanistan Veterans with multiple blast exposure and mTBI. The
      study will measure substances in cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) that are related to dementing
      disorders.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Many Iraq and Afghanistan Veterans have experienced repetitive blast exposure mild traumatic
      brain injury (mTBI) with persistent cognitive, emotional, and neurological postconcussive
      symptoms. There is an urgent need to develop effective treatments to reduce both the
      intensity of these Veterans' current symptoms as well as their potential long-term risks for
      developing neurodegenerative dementing disorders related to repetitive mTBI: chronic
      traumatic encephalopathy (CTE) and Alzheimer's disease (AD). Converging evidence suggests
      that statins may possess neuroprotective effects against pathologic processes related to tau
      protein metabolism that appear to be a common feature of CTE, AD, and other
      neurodegenerative sequelae of repetitive mTBI.

      We propose a 12-month, double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled trial to establish
      proof-of-concept for use of simvastatin (40 mg/d) for decreasing CSF biomarkers of
      neurodegeneration and increasing CSF neurotrophins in 120 Iraq and Afghanistan Veterans with
      repetitive blast trauma mTBI.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) tau concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 months post-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Concentration of cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) Brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 months post-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>TBI-Traumatic Brain Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>simvastatin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>simvastatin 40 mg/day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>simvastatin</intervention_name>
    <description>simvastatin 40 mg/day for 12 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>simvastatin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Zocor</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>placebo once per day for 12 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Males and females ages 21-50 years.

          -  Documented hazardous duty in Iraq and or Afghanistan with the U.S. Armed Forces.

          -  Exposure to one or more blast trauma events resulting in mTBI according to ACRM
             criteria.

          -  More than 6 months since last blast trauma exposure

          -  Ability to complete psychometric and other clinical assessments in English (i.e.,
             adequate English language skills, vision and hearing).

          -  Normal or mildly elevated cholesterol which does not require drug therapy based on
             NCEP/ATP-III guidelines (i.e., fasting LDL &lt;190 for those with 1 cardiovascular risk
             factor and &lt; 160 for those with 2+ risk factors).

          -  No use of statins during the previous year and no recent (past 4 weeks) use of other
             lipid-lowering drugs (e.g., fibrates, niacin &gt; 500mg/d, or high dose omega-3 fatty
             acids) preceding randomization.

          -  No clinically significant laboratory abnormalities (electrolytes, glucose, carbon
             dioxide, BUN, creatinine, vitamin B12, folate, albumin, thyroid stimulating hormone).

          -  Platelet count &gt; 100,000/mm2.

          -  Body Mass Index (BMI) between 18 and 36 inclusive

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of head trauma with LOC&gt;30 minutes, or with a penetrating head wound, or with
             moderate to severe memory or other cognitive impairment.

          -  Neurological disorders: multiple sclerosis, epilepsy, stroke, PD, other degenerative
             CNS disorders, or neuropathy with radicular involvement.

          -  Acute or chronic major psychiatric disorders: schizophrenia, bipolar disorder or
             severe major depressive disorder, or severe anxiety disorder except PTSD and panic
             disorder (PTSD and depressive symptoms are common co-morbid conditions for combat
             mTBI and a subset of these patients have symptoms consistent with panic disorder as
             well).

          -  Use of illegal drugs; alcohol abuse within the past 6 months.

          -  Poorly controlled hypertension, heart failure, coronary heart disease, peripheral
             artery disease, carotid artery disease, diabetes mellitus, pulmonary disease with
             hypoxia or hypercapnia, significant hepatic disease or hepatitis C seropositivity,
             renal failure, treatment for cancer, HIV positive, active infectious disease or
             presence of abdominal aortic aneurysm.

          -  Contraindications to LP (e.g., spinal cord injury; deformity, severe disease or
             infection in the region of the lumbosacral spine; bleeding tendency, use of
             anticoagulant medications, or platelet count &lt;100,000/mm2).

          -  Receiving medication in an investigational drug study.

          -  Exclusionary medications (used in the 4 weeks prior to screening):

          -  Fibrates and niacin due to increased risk for myopathy in combination with statins;

          -  Potential drug-drug interactions with statins via effects on CYP3A4: itraconazole,
             ketoconazole, erythromycin, clarithromycin, HIV protease inhibitors, nefazodone,
             amiodarone, cyclosporine, isoniazid, quinidine, or large quantities of grapefruit
             juice (&gt;1 quart daily);

          -  Selected CNS-acting medications: antipsychotics, anti-Parkinson's disease medications
             and CNS stimulants

          -  Other medications affecting coagulation and/or inflammation: coumadin, potent
             anti-inflammatory medications (hydrocortisone, methotrexate or other potent
             immune-modulating medications), and anti-HIV medications.

          -  All female subjects of childbearing potential will undergo a urine pregnancy test at
             every subject visit; subjects with positive pregnancy test results will be excluded.
             In addition, all female subjects of childbearing potential will be required to use a
             reliable method of contraception throughout the duration of the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elaine R. Peskind, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Puget Sound Health Care System, Seattle</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Elaine R Peskind, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(206) 277-3965</phone>
    <email>elaine.peskind@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Puget Sound Health Care System, Seattle</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elaine R Peskind, MD</last_name>
      <phone>206-277-3965</phone>
      <email>elaine.peskind@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elaine R. Peskind, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 1, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 24, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Simvastatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
