<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="166418">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01806298</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EMR 200104-011</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-004263-47</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01806298</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Open-label Phase 4 Study to Explore Immunogenicity of the Liquid Formulation of Saizen® in Subjects With Growth Hormone Deficiency (GHD) of Adult Onset</brief_title>
  <official_title>Open-label, Single-arm, Phase IV, Multicenter Trial to Explore the Immunogenicity of the Liquid Formulation of Saizen® in Subjects With Growth Hormone Deficiency (GHD) of Adult Onset</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Merck KGaA</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Merck KGaA</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Australia: Department of Health and Ageing Therapeutic Goods Administration</authority>
    <authority>Australia: Human Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>Czech Republic: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>Czech Republic: State Institute for Drug Control</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Ethics Commission</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <authority>Sweden: Medical Products Agency</authority>
    <authority>Sweden: Regional Ethical Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: National Institute for Health Research</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-label, single-arm, multicenter, Phase 4 study to explore the immunogenicity
      of the liquid formulation of Saizen® in subjects with Growth Hormone Deficiency (GHD) of
      adult onset, who are growth hormone (GH) treatment-naïve or who had prior GH treatment for
      adult growth hormone deficiency (AGHD) which was stopped at least 3 months prior to
      Screening.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects developing Binding Antibodies (BAbs) to Saizen®</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Week 39</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with BAbs who become positive for Neutralizing Antibody (NAbs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 2 weeks after last dose of study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Insulin-like growth Factor-I (IGF-I) levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, and Week 2, 8, 16, 29, 39 and 41</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Insulin-like growth factor binding Protein-3 (IGFBP-3) levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, and Week 2, 8, 16, 29, 39 and 41</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Insulin-like Growth Factor-I Standard Deviation Score (IGF-I SDS) levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, and Week 2, 8, 16, 29, 39 and 41</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment adherence rate for each subject as documented using EasypodTM connect</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2, 8, 16, 29 and 39</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with treatment-emergent adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2, 8, 16, 29 and 39</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">77</enrollment>
  <condition>Growth Hormone Deficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Saizen®</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saizen® solution for injection (referred as Saizen®)</intervention_name>
    <description>Saizen® solution for injection will be administered subcutaneously daily for 39 weeks according to the local product label instructions on locally approved product labeling.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Saizen®</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Somatropin</other_name>
    <other_name>Recombinant human growth hormone (r-hGH)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and female subjects, 18-65 years of age, inclusive, at the time of signature of
             informed consent

          -  Documented adult-onset adult growth hormone deficiency (AO-AGHD), either by a
             stimulation test as described in the GH Research Society's 2007 guidelines for the
             diagnosis and treatment of adult GHD, or in the Saizen® label, whichever is more
             stringent, or by confirming the presence of at least 3 pituitary hormone deficiencies
             and an IGF-1 level below the reference range of the laboratory where testing is
             performed. Stimulation test as described in the 2007 GH Research Society guidelines
             and applicable to all subjects who underwent or will undergo a stimulation test:

               -  Insulin Tolerance Test (ITT) or glucagon stimulation test: Peak GH less than 3
                  nanogram per milliliter (ng/mL);

               -  GH-releasing hormone (GHRH) plus arginine test, peak GH depends on body mass
                  index (BMI):

                    -  BMI less than 25 kilogram per square meter (kg/m2) indicates a peak GH less
                       than 11 ng/mL microgram per liter [µg/L]).

                    -  BMI 25-30 kg/m2 indicates a peak GH less than 8 ng/mL (µg/L).

                    -  BMI greater than 30 kg/m2 indicates a peak GH less than 4 ng/mL (µg/L).

        Clonidine, l-dopa, and arginine alone are not acceptable as stimulation tests for
        determining eligibility in this trial. Stimulation tests remain under the Investigator's
        or the subject's physician's responsibility, including the selection of the GH assay.
        Saizen® label: in Europe, only one single test is required; in Australia, 2 stimulation
        tests showing a peak GH less than 2.5 ng/mL are required. The inclusion criteria were
        chosen based on the approved label for Saizen® in the countries where the trial is being
        implemented, as well as in respect of the most current international guidelines for AGHD.
        There is no limit in time prior to the Screening visit for the stimulation test(s), as
        long as documentation is available and the stimulation tests comply with the GH Research
        Society 2007 guidelines, and as such, there is no need to repeat the test for subjects
        having stopped their GH therapy prior to the Screening visit. No stimulation test is
        required for subjects with 3 or more pituitary hormone deficiencies

          -  GH treatment-naïve or prior GH treatment for AGHD stopped at least 3 months prior to
             Screening visit. Whereas any prior use of GH is permitted, providing an adequate
             wash-out period is respected to secure the interpretation of the biomarkers, the
             reason for stopping the GH therapy should neither be safety- nor efficacy-related,
             and documentation should be present in the source information

          -  Negative BAbs from the Screening visit sample

          -  Body mass index (BMI, Weight in kilograms / Height in square meters) measured at
             Screening visit as less than or equal to 35 kilogram per square meter (kg/m2)

          -  Negative serum pregnancy test at the Screening for women of childbearing potential
             and subject is not lactating

          -  Understanding and willingness of the subject to comply with the procedures of the
             study

          -  Informed Consent form signed prior to the performance of any trial-related activities

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Hypersensitivity to the active substance or to any of the Saizen® excipients

          -  Evidence of growing intracranial tumor including pituitary tumor, or affecting the
             optic chiasm, or requiring treatment (surgery or radiation) within the 6 months prior
             to and the 12 months after the Screening visit

          -  History or presence of any malignant tumor

          -  Proliferative or pre-proliferative diabetic retinopathy

          -  Evidence of chronic underlying disease within 6 months prior to the Screening visit
             or concomitant medication that would interfere with subject compliance, the
             evaluation of trial results, or compromise the safety of the subject

          -  Severe hepatic or renal failure that could compromise the interpretation of IGF-1,
             that is: Alanine transaminase [ALT] or aspartate transaminase [AST] greater than 3 *
             upper limit of the normal range; Glomerular filtration rate (GFR) less than 30
             milliliter per minute (mL/min) Note: GFR will be calculated by the laboratory
             according to the Modification of Diet in Renal Disease (MDRD) equation

          -  History of anti-GH antibodies

          -  History or presence of an autoimmune disease, such as Hashimoto's disease or Systemic
             Lupus Erythematosus (SLE), immunosuppression regardless of etiology, or GH1 gene
             defect

          -  Absence of effective contraception in place at the Screening visit in women of
             childbearing potential. Acceptable forms of effective contraception include:
             established use of oral (greater than 2 months), injected, or implanted hormonal
             methods of contraception, intrauterine devices (IUD), or barrier methods of
             contraception, specifically, condom or occlusive cap (diaphragm or cervical/vault
             caps) with spermicidal foam/gel/film/cream/suppository

          -  Diabetes mellitus (per American Diabetes Association 2010 guidelines): either i)
             standard diabetes symptoms and a random glucose greater than or equal to 200
             milligram per deciliter (mg/dL) (11.1 millimolar per liter [mmol/L]); ii) a fasting
             plasma glucose greater than 126 mg/dL (6.99 mmol/L); iii) a 2-hour plasma glucose
             greater than or equal to 200 mg/dL (11.1 mmol/L) during an oral glucose tolerance
             test (OGTT); or iv) an glycosylated hemoglobin (HbA1c) greater than or equal to 6.5
             percent

          -  Concomitant or prior participation in an interventional trial within 30 days prior to
             the Screening visit

          -  Known alcohol or drug addiction/dependency

          -  Has a legal incapacity or limited legal capacity

          -  Has received anabolic steroids (except for gonadal steroid replacement therapy) or
             systemic corticosteroids (except for replacement doses) within 3 months prior to the
             Screening visit

          -  Has received substitutive therapy with glucocorticosteroids, thyroid replacement,
             vasopressin, or sex hormones for less than 3 months or substitutive therapy has not
             been stable (that is, dose was not generally constant or medical condition was not
             controlled) for 3 months prior to Screening
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Merck KGaA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Merck KGaA Communication Center</last_name>
    <phone>+49 6151 72 5200</phone>
    <email>service@merckgroup.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Please contact the Merck KgaA Communications Service located in</name>
      <address>
        <city>Darmstadt</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <phone>+49-6151-72-5200</phone>
      <email>service@merckgroup.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 24, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 5, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Growth hormone deficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>Saizen®</keyword>
  <keyword>Recombinant human growth hormone (r-hGH)</keyword>
  <keyword>Somatropin</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dwarfism, Pituitary</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endocrine System Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hormones</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
