<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="111041">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01970865</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>B7461001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01970865</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study Of PF-06463922 An ALK/ROS1 Inhibitor In Patients With Advanced Non Small Cell Lung Cancer With Specific Molecular Alterations</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 1/2 Study Of PF-06463922 (An ALK/ROS1 Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor) In Patients With Advanced Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer Harboring Specific Molecular Alterations</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pfizer</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Phase 1 and 2 trial to study the safety, pharmacokinetics, pharmacodynamics, patient
      reported outcomes and efficacy of PF-06463922 in ALK + advanced non-small cell lung cancer
      patients and ROS1+ advanced non small cell lung cancer patients .
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with Dose-limiting toxicities (DLT)</measure>
    <time_frame>First Cycle</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Patients With Overall and Intracranial Objective Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 6 weeks from the time of patient enrollment  up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of patients with OR based assessment of intracranial and overall confirmed complete remission (CR) or confirmed partial remission (PR) according to a modified Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST)v 1.1.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose and recommended phase 2 dose</measure>
    <time_frame>At end of cycle 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Recommended phase 2 dose will be determined after the last patient has been treated for at least one cycle in the Phase 1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE) across treatment cycles</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to dosing (Day -7 or Cycle 1 Day 1), Every 3 weeks from the time of enrollment up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>MMSE measured general cognitive functioning: orientation, memory, attention, calculation, language, visuospatial functions. Total score derived from sub-scores; total ranges from 0 to 30, higher score indicates better cognitive state. Change: across treatment cycles</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Curve From Time Zero to Last Quantifiable Concentration (AUClast)</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days prior to first dose of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration time-curve from zero to the last measured concentration (AUClast)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Volume of Distribution at Steady State (Vss)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Volume of distribution is defined as the theoretical volume in which the total amount of drug would need to be uniformly distributed to produce the desired blood concentration of a drug. Steady state volume of distribution (Vss) is the apparent volume of distribution at steady-state.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Reach Maximum Observed Plasma Concentration (Tmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment and pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Observed Plasma Concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment and pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Curve from Time Zero to end of dosing interval (AUCtau)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent Volume of Distribution (Vz/F)</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Volume of distribution is defined as the theoretical volume in which the total amount of drug would need to be uniformly distributed to produce the desired plasma concentration of a drug. Apparent volume of distribution after oral dose (Vz/F) is influenced by the fraction absorbed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Decay Half-Life (t1/2)</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Plasma decay half-life is the time measured for the plasma concentration to decrease by one half.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine clearance of drug  (Clr) for subjects in food effect and Midazolam substudy</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2,3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine Ae% for subjects in food effect and Midazolam substudy</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre Cycle 1 Day 15 dose of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Observed Plasma Concentration (Cmax) for subjects in Midazolam substudy</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment and pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2,3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Reach Maximum Observed Plasma Concentration (Tmax) for subjects in Midazolam substudy</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment and pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2,3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Curve From Time Zero to Last Quantifiable Concentration (AUClast) for subjects in Midazolam substudy</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days prior to first dose and pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2,3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration time-curve from zero to the last measured concentration (AUClast) after administration of MDZ</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Curve From Time Zero to Extrapolated Infinite Time [AUC (0 - 8)]</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment and pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2,3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>AUC (0 - 8)= Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) from time zero (pre-dose) to extrapolated infinite time (0 - 8). It is obtained from AUC (0 - t) plus AUC (t - 8).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Decay Half-Life (t1/2) for subjects in Midazolam substudy</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment and pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2,3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Plasma decay half-life is the time measured for the plasma concentration to decrease by one half after administration of MDZ</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent Oral Clearance (CL/F) for subjects in Midazolam substudy</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment and pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2,3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Clearance of a drug is a measure of the rate at which a drug is metabolized or eliminated by normal biological processes.  Clearance obtained after oral dose (apparent oral clearance) is influenced by the fraction of the dose absorbed. Clearance was estimated from population pharmacokinetic (PK) modeling.  Drug clearance is a quantitative measure of the rate at which a drug substance is removed from the blood after administration of MDZ</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent Oral Clearance (CL/F)</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment and pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2,3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Clearance of a drug is a measure of the rate at which a drug is metabolized or eliminated by normal biological processes.  Clearance obtained after oral dose (apparent oral clearance) is influenced by the fraction of the dose absorbed. Clearance was estimated from population pharmacokinetic (PK) modeling.  Drug clearance is a quantitative measure of the rate at which a drug substance is removed from the blood.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Curve From Time Zero to Last Quantifiable Concentration (AUClast)</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration time-curve from zero to the last measured concentration (AUClast)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Curve From Time Zero to Extrapolated Infinite Time [AUC (0 - 8)]</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days prior to the first dose of treamtent</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>AUC (0 - 8)= Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) from time zero (pre-dose) to extrapolated infinite time (0 - 8). It is obtained from AUC (0 - t) plus AUC (t - 8).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Drug concentration in cerebral spinal fluid (CSF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Optional sample, up to 4 years, if patient undergoes a lumbar puncture</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Should CSF specimen be taken for suspected tumor infiltration this  sample may be used for drug concentration levels.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Selective molecular profiling of circulating nucleic acids (CNA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 28 days of first dose of treatment  and at 28 days after the last dose of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Selective molecular profiling of circulating nucleic acids (CNA) at the end of treatment visit defined as 28 days after the last treatment administration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Selective molecular profiling of tumor tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 28 days prior to first dose of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood specimen optimized for plasma preparation for nucleic acid analysis will be collected at screening and at end of treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating tumor cells (CTC) enumeration and molecular characterization</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to treatment start on Day -7 or Cycle 1 Day 1, at the end of Cycle 2 and at 28 days after the last dose of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>QTc interval</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 28 days prior to first dose of treatment,  7 days prior to the first dose of treatment and Day 1, 8 and  15 of Cycle 1 and Day 1 of Cycles 2-5 and 28 days after the last dose of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>ECGs performed to assess QTc (msec) at baseline and on study treatment and at the end of treatment visit defined as 28 days after the last treatment administration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported Outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to first dosing (Day -7 or Cycle 1 Day 1), Day 1 of every cycle, pre dose, up to 4 years and at 28 days after the last dose of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess impact of disease /treatment related symptoms of lung cancer and quality of life at D1 of every cycle and at the end of treatment visit defined as 28 days after the last treatment administration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 6 weeks from the time of enrollment up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>DR is defined as the time from the first documentation of objective tumor response (CR or PR) to the first documentation of disease progression or to death due to any cause, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 6 weeks from the time of enrollment to the first documented progression or date of death from any cause, assessed  up to  4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The period from study entry until disease progression, death or date of last contact.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the time of enrollment until the date of death from any causes at 18 months and 1 year.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall survival was the duration from enrollment to death. For participants who are alive, overall survival was censored at the last contact.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Control Rate (DCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 12 weeks from the time of enrollment up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>DCR is defined as the percent of patients with a confirmed complete response (CR), partial response (PR) or stable disease (SD) according to RECIST 1.1, at 6  weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective tumor response</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 6 weeks from the time of enrollment up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of patients with OR based assessment of intracranial and overall confirmed complete remission (CR) or confirmed partial remission (PR) according to a modified Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST)v 1.1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction (LVEF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 28 days prior to the first dose of treatment,  pre dose on Day 1 of Cycle 2, pre dose on Day 1 of Cycle 3, pre dose on Day 1 of Cycle 5 and pre dose on Day 1 of every 2 Cycles thereafter; and at 28 days after the last dose of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction percentage change by echocardiogram or by multigated acquisition gated scan (MUGA)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent Volume of Distribution (Vz/F) for subjects in Midazolam substudy</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment and pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2,3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Volume of distribution is defined as the theoretical volume in which the total amount of drug would need to be uniformly distributed to produce the desired plasma concentration of a drug. Apparent volume of distribution after oral dose (Vz/F) is influenced by the fraction absorbed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Tumor Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 6 weeks from the time of enrollment up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>TTR is defined as the time from first dose to first documentation of objective tumor response (CR or PR). For patients whose OR proceeds from PR to CR, the onset of PR is taken as the onset of response. TTR will only be calculated for the subgroup of patients with a confirmed objective tumor response.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Tumor Progression (phase 2 only)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the time of enrollment up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>TTP is defined as the time from first dose to first documentation of objective disease progression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Intracranial progression (phase 2 only)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the time of enrollment up to 4 years.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Time to Intracranial Progression is defined as the time from first dose to first documentation of objective intracranial disease progression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Extracranial Progression (phase 2 only)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the time of enrollment up to 4 years.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Time to Extracranial defined as the time from first dose to first documentation of objective extracranial disease progression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>ALK Positive Non Small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PF-06463922</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PF-06463922</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral, starting dose 10mg once a day, dose escalation in Phase 1 until recommended Phase 2 dose determined, continuous daily dosing, cycles lasting 21 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>PF-06463922</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Evidence of histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of locally advanced
             or metastatic NSCLC (Stage IV, AJCC v7.0) that carries an ALK rearrangement, as
             determined by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approved FISH assay (Abbott
             Molecular Inc) or by Immunohistochemistry (IHC) (Ventana Inc), or a ROS1
             rearrangement as determined by FISH or RT PCR or Next Generation Sequencing (NGS)
             via a local diagnostic test (LDT).

          -  ALK+ NSCLC patients must either be treatment naïve in the advanced setting or have
             had disease progression after 1or 2 previous ALK inhibitor therapy(ies), as the last
             therapy given (Phase 1 allows for intervening chemotherapy).

          -  ROS1+ NSCLC patients must either be treatment naïve in the advanced setting or have
             had disease progression after 1or 2 previous ROS1 inhibitor therapy(ies), as the last
             therapy given (Phase 1 allows for intervening chemotherapy).

          -  archival tissue sample available collected prior to enrollment.

          -  All Patients must have at least one measurable target extracranial lesion according
             to RECIST v1.1. In addition patients with asymptomatic CNS metastases (including
             patients asymptomatic by means of stable or decreasing doses of steroids within the
             last 2 weeks prior to study entry) are eligible.

          -  Adequate bone marrow, pancreatic, renal, liver function.

          -  Pregnancy test (for females of childbearing potential) negative at screening and at
             the baseline visit . Male and female patients of childbearing potential must agree to
             use two highly effective methods of contraception from the time of the first negative
             pregnancy test at screening, throughout the study and for 90 days after the last dose
             of assigned treatment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Radiation therapy (except palliative to relieve bone pain) within 2 weeks of study
             entry.  Stereotactic or small field brain irradiation must have completed at least 2
             weeks prior to study entry.  Whole brain radiation must have completed at least 4
             weeks prior to study entry.

          -  Any one of the following currently or in the previous 3 months: myocardial
             infarction, congenital long QT syndrome, Torsades de Pointes, arrhythmias (including
             sustained ventricular tachyarrhythmia and ventricular fibrillation), right bundle
             branch block and left anterior hemiblock (bifascicular block), unstable angina,
             coronary/peripheral artery bypass graft, symptomatic congestive heart failure (CHF NY
             Heart Association Class III or IV), cerebrovascular accident, transient ischemic
             attack or symptomatic pulmonary embolism not adequately medically managed with
             anticoagulants; as well as bradycardia defined as &lt;50 bpms.  Ongoing cardiac
             dysrhythmias of NCI CTCAE Grade ≥ 2, symptomatic atrial fibrillation of any grade, or
             QTc interval &gt;=481 msec at screening.  Right bundle branch block.

          -  History of extensive, disseminated, bilateral or presence of Grade 3 or 4
             interstitial fibrosis or interstitial lung disease.

          -  Current use or anticipated need for food or drugs that are known strong or moderate
             CYP3A4 inhibitors, inducers and CYP3A4 substrates with narrow therapeutic indices.

          -  Concurrent use of drugs that are CYP2C9 substrates with narrow therapeutic indices or
             those that are sensitive CYP2B6 substrates.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pfizer CT.gov Call Center</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Pfizer</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Pfizer CT.gov Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>1-800-718-1021</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pfizer Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114-2696</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pfizer Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37203-1625</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pfizer Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pfizer Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>East Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3002</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pfizer Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08035</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://trialinfoemail.pfizer.com/pages/landing.aspx?StudyID=B7461001&amp;StudyName=A%20Study%20Of%20PF-06463922%20An%20ALK/ROS1%20Inhibitor%20In%20Patients%20With%20Advanced%20Non%20Small%20Cell%20Lung%20Cancer%20With%20Specific%20Molecular%20Alterations</url>
    <description>To obtain contact information for a study center near you, click here.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 28, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 16, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Phase 1</keyword>
  <keyword>Phase 2</keyword>
  <keyword>safety</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacokinetic</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacodynamic</keyword>
  <keyword>efficacy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
