<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="60430">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01943435</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRO12120422</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01943435</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study Comparing 3 Different Treatments for Arthritis of the Lower Back (Lumbar Spinal Stenosis)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Comparison of Non-Surgical Treatment Methods for Patients With Lumbar Spinal Stenosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pittsburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Patient Centered Outcome Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND: Lumbar spinal stenosis - known by patients as &quot;arthritis of the spine&quot; - is a
      condition that is very common; found in about 30% of older adults. It is the most common
      reason for people over the age of 65 to have back surgery. Some patients with stenosis do
      not need back surgery and can be treated with other methods, such as physical therapy,
      chiropractic, exercise, and medication. But we just don't have enough good research to tell
      us which treatment works best for which patient and under which circumstances. This research
      study hopes to provide more information about the effectiveness of the various non-surgical
      choices for managing stenosis.

      OBJECTIVES: This study will directly compare the effectiveness of three common non-surgical
      treatment approaches for stenosis:

        1. Usual medical care that involves prescription medications and/or spinal injections
           (epidurals)

        2. Group exercise in supervised classes given in a community center setting

        3. Hands-on (manual) therapy and rehabilitative exercises given in a clinic setting by
           physical therapists and chiropractors

      METHODS: This research study will involve 180 adults who are at least 60 years old and have
      been diagnosed with lumbar spinal stenosis. The research volunteers will be divided into
      three groups, each group receiving one of the 3 types of treatments listed above under
      &quot;Objectives&quot;. The determination of which type of treatment each person receives will be
      determined by chance, using a computerized version of flipping a coin. This is a process
      known as randomization, which scientists think reduces the bias in research studies. A
      series of tests and questionnaires will be given to the patients before and after they get
      treatment and comparisons will be made to see how much improvement they made with each of
      the types of treatments. Finally, the researchers will compare the differences between the 3
      treatment groups to see if certain types of treatment produced better results than others,
      and if there were any examination findings that could be used to predict which type of
      patient would do better with which type of treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND: Lumbar spinal stenosis (LSS) is a condition that is highly prevalent in the
      senior citizen population. LSS is the most frequent indication for spinal surgery in
      patients over the age of 65 years. The fastest growth in lumbar surgery in the U.S. this
      past decade has occurred in older adults with LSS and the rate of complex fusion procedures
      has increased 15-fold. These surgical procedures are associated with significant health care
      costs, risks, complications, and re-hospitalization rates. Yet, evidence is lacking for the
      effectiveness of the various non-surgical treatments offered to patients with LSS. This
      knowledge gap has greatly hindered the development of clinical practice guidelines relevant
      to the non-surgical treatment approaches for LSS.

      OBJECTIVES: This study will perform a comparison of three common approaches to the
      non-surgical management and treatment of patients with LSS. The specific research questions
      associated with this study are: (1) How do group exercise and manual therapy with
      rehabilitative exercise compare with usual medical care? (2) How do group exercise and
      manual therapy with rehabilitative exercise compare with each other? (3) Are there any
      baseline predictors associated with clinical improvement in any of these non-surgical
      treatment approaches? The long term objective of this study is to produce research evidence
      relevant to community stakeholders and to inform better decision making about non-surgical
      treatment options available to LSS patients.

      METHODS: This will be a comparative effectiveness study utilizing the research design of a
      randomized controlled clinical trial (RCT). It will be a 3-group RCT that allows for
      pragmatic treatment approaches in each of the three study arms. The study sample will
      consist of 180 older adults (&gt;60 years) who have symptoms consistent with a diagnosis of
      LSS, which will be confirmed by clinical examination and diagnostic imaging. Eligible
      subjects will be randomized into one of three pragmatic treatment approaches:  1) usual
      medical care;  2) group exercise; or  3) manual therapy with rehabilitative exercise.

      All subjects will be treated for a 6-week course of care. Primary outcome measures are two
      validated research measurement tools; the Swiss Spinal Stenosis Questionnaire (self-reported
      pain/function) and the Self Paced Walking Test (performance-based measure). We will also
      employ a novel secondary outcome measure; the Sense Wear Armband which provides a real-time
      measure of physical activity during normal daily living.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Swiss Spinal Stenosis Questionnaire Score</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks ( 2 weeks after 6 week intervention is completed).  We will also re-test participants at 6 months as a long-term follow-up.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Our primary outcome measure is the change in SSS score between baseline and 8 weeks. The Swiss Spinal Stenosis Questionnaire (SSS)is a validated 12-item condition-specific instrument for patients with lumbar spinal stenosis. It provides a patient self-report measure of pain and physical function. The sum total of the 12 items is expressed as a percentage (divided by 55), with each item having a different range of possible individual scores depending on number of possible answers. (1-5 for items with 5 questions; 1-3 for items with 3 questions; and 1-4 for items with 4 questions). Higher scores represent worse symptoms and less physical function.
7-item Symptom Severity subscale
Items 1-4= Pain domain
Items 5-7=Neuro-ischemic domain
5-item Physical Function subscale
Items 8-12= Walking capacity domain</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self Paced Walking Test</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks ( 2 weeks after 6 week intervention is completed). We will also re-test participants at 6 months as a long-term follow-up.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Our secondary outcome measure is the change in SPWT between baseline and 8 weeks.  Self Paced Walking Test (SPWT) is a validated objective measure of a patient's walking capacity. The SPWT is performed on a level walking surface. The patient is instructed to walk at their own pace and to stop when the symptoms are troublesome enough that s/he needs to sit down to rest. The total time and total distance walked are measured by the research assistant.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sense Wear Armband</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks (2 weeks after 6 week intervention has been completed). We will also re-test participants at 6 months as a long-term follow-up.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Our exploratory aim is to measure the change in physical activity between baseline and 8 weeks using the Sense Wear armband (SWA). The SWA is a small device that collects information from multiple sensors: a triaxial accelerometer, heat flux, skin temperature, and galvanic signal. The information is integrated and processed by software using proprietary algorithms utilizing subjects' demographic characteristics (gender, age, height, and weight) to provide minute-by-minute estimates of physical activity. The SWA has shown good reliability and validity. The research participants in our study will wear the SWA for a week before and after they complete the treatment interventions.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Lumbar Spinal Stenosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Medical Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs); adjunctive analgesics; adjunctive anti-depressants. Participants assigned to this group will see a board certified physical medicine and rehabilitation physician for a history and examination, after which a determination will be made about a course of treatment that involve medications that are individualized to the needs of each patient.
NSAIDs: ibuprofen, celecoxib, or diclofenac/misoprostol
Adjunctive analgesics: acetaminophen, tramadol, or gabapentin
Adjunctive antidepressant agents: nortriptyline, duloxetine, sertraline, trazodone, or mirtazapine
Lumbar epidural injection: these will be prescribed by the physician if warranted due to severity of symptoms or lack of adequate response to oral medications.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group Exercise: community setting. This arm will involve attendance at community based group exercise classes that are taught by senior physical fitness instructors. These classes are designed specifically for older adults. Exercise frequency will be 2 times per week, for a total of 12 visits over the 6-week research period. These exercise classes will be attended at local community senior centers which cater to the needs of older adults. The subjects can self-select which particular exercise class they prefer to attend, based upon their level of fitness and physical function.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Manual therapy and exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group of subjects will be treated with a combination of manual therapy and rehabilitative exercise procedures that are commonly used in the physical therapy and chiropractic professions. Subjects will be treated at a frequency of 2 times per week, for a total of 12 visits over the 6-week research period. Treatments will be provided by licensed physical therapists and chiropractors using a combination of joint mobilizations, muscle stretching and strengthening exercises.
Individualized exercises: clinical setting. These exercises will be tailored to the individual needs of each research participant by the treating physical therapist or chiropractor.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NSAIDs; adjunctive analgesics; adjunctive anti-depressants</intervention_name>
    <description>Physician will administer these medications based upon the individual needs of each patient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Medical Care</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ibuprofen</other_name>
    <other_name>celecoxib</other_name>
    <other_name>diclofenac</other_name>
    <other_name>misoprostol</other_name>
    <other_name>acetaminophen</other_name>
    <other_name>tramadol</other_name>
    <other_name>gabapentin</other_name>
    <other_name>nortriptyline</other_name>
    <other_name>duloxetine</other_name>
    <other_name>sertraline</other_name>
    <other_name>trazodone</other_name>
    <other_name>mirtazapine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lumbar epidural injection</intervention_name>
    <description>The attending physician may refer subjects for epidural injections at a pain clinic that is affiliated with the University of Pittsburgh Medical Center. All epidural injections will be provided by licensed physicians who are board certified in physical medicine and rehabilitation or anesthesiology.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Medical Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Joint Mobilizations (spine, sacroiliac, hip)</intervention_name>
    <description>These joint mobilizations will be applied manually to the lumbar facet joints, sacroiliac joints, and/or hip joints by licensed physical therapists and chiropractors.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Manual therapy and exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Individualized exercises: clinical setting</intervention_name>
    <description>The treating physical therapist or chiropractor will work with each subject to develop a set of individualized exercises in the clinic setting. The goal is to have the subjects continue these exercises at home.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Manual therapy and exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Group Exercise: community setting</intervention_name>
    <description>The group exercise will take place at community centers that provide exercise classes for older adult. The exercises are taught by certified fitness instructors in a group setting at these community centers.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group Exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Minimum age of 60 years

          -  Can read/write English and understand directions

          -  Diagnosis of lumbar spinal stenosis confirmed by CT or MRI scan

          -  Has limitation of standing and/or walking tolerance

          -  Willing to attend treatments 2 times per week for 6 weeks

          -  Ability to walk at least 50 feet with the need for a cane or walker

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of metastatic cancer

          -  Advised by a physician not to exercise

          -  History of lumbar surgery for spinal stenosis or previous lumbar fusion

          -  Presence of severe peripheral artery disease in legs

          -  Severe hypertension: Systolic &gt; 200 mm/hg or Diastolic &gt; 110 mm/hg

          -  Ankle brachial index &lt; 0.8

          -  Neurologic or neurodegenerative disease other than stenosis that severly impairs the
             ability to walk

          -  Presence of cauda equina symptoms (saddle paresthesia, progressive loss of
             bladder/bowel function, etc)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael J Schneider, PhD, DC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christine McFarland, BS</last_name>
    <phone>412-623-6872</phone>
    <email>mcfarlandce@upmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Michael J Schneider, DC, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>412-383-6640</phone>
    <email>mjs5@pitt.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UPMC Shadyside Center for Integrative Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christine McFarland, BS</last_name>
      <phone>412-623-6872</phone>
      <email>mcfarlandce@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael J Schneider, PhD, DC</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 8, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael Schneider, DC, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor, Department of Physical Therapy</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Spinal Stenosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Spinal manipulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Epidural injection</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Constriction, Pathologic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Spinal Stenosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Acetaminophen</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diclofenac</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ibuprofen</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Celecoxib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Analgesics</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tramadol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gabapentin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Trazodone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nortriptyline</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mirtazapine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sertraline</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Duloxetine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antidepressive Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anti-Inflammatory Agents, Non-Steroidal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Misoprostol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
