<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="58738">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01952834</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRO00019610</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>FP00004156</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01952834</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Probiotic Supplementation on Endothelial Function</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Probiotic Supplementation on Endothelial Function in Men With Coronary Artery Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical College of Wisconsin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical College of Wisconsin</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study is being performed to determine whether probiotics (GoodBelly) improves blood
      vessel function.Probiotics similar to yogurt are living micro-organisms (beneficial to its
      host) the lives in the intestine. Patients who have coronary artery disease will be enrolled
      in this study.  The research results will be used to determine if the type of bacteria
      present in the intestines play a role in the pathogenesis of cardiovascular disease.
      Patients with coronary artery disease will be enrolled for up to 12 weeks.   Patients will
      take the probiotic for 6 weeks. Following the 6 week period there is a washout period of 4
      weeks, and an optional antibiotic study called vancomycin. Patients will take the vancomycin
      for 10 days.  Blood vessel function will be measured by ultrasound before and after the
      probiotic supplement and vancomycin antibiotic.  Blood will also be taken before and after
      to evaluate for markers of inflammation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We plan to recruit 32 patients, men with coronary artery disease, for this single center,
      interventional trial with the Probiotic-GoodBelly followed by Vancomycin. The study includes
      6 total visits. Subjects who pass a phone screen will be invited to a screening visit for
      study eligibility (Visit 1) Informed consent will be reviewed; a unique  study number will
      be assigned once  written informed consent is obtained (no subject will be assigned more
      than 1 allocation  number); relevant participant medical history will be recorded including
      currently prescribed medications; anthropometric measurements will be taken  (height,
      weight, and waist circumference in metric units) and blood pressure will be recorded
      (measured in triplicate and averaged). Subjects will be allowed to take their blood pressure
      medication on the morning of their screening visit, but not the mornings of any of the other
      study visits to limit the acute influence  of these medications on endothelial function. If
      the potential  participant qualifies for the study,  he will return 1 week after the screen
      for a study visit(Visit 2) where he will turn in his stool sample, undergo initial tests of
      endothelial function and receive 3 week supply of GoodBelly Probiotic. After 3 weeks he will
      have to return (Visit 3) for another 3 week supply of his probiotic.  After a total of 6
      weeks of taking the probiotic he will have to return (Visit 4) with his stool sample. He
      will be asked to fast for 6-8 hours prior to the visit to limit the acute dietary influences
      on vascular endothelial function. During Visit 4, endothelial function will determined by
      brachial artery reactivity testing  His stool samples will be collected and blood samples
      will also be taken at this visit for systemic measurements inflammatory markers. If he
      agrees to the optional Vancomycin study. He will return after 4 weeks for (Visit 5). He will
      be asked to fast for 6-8 hours prior to the visit to limit the acute dietary influences on
      vascular endothelial function. At Visit 5, endothelial function will determined by brachial
      artery reactivity testing  His stool samples will be collected and blood samples will also
      be taken at this visit for systemic measurements inflammatory markers. He will then be given
      a 10 day supply of vancomycin. After 10 days he will return (Visit 6) with his stool sample.
      At Visit 6, endothelial function will determined by brachial artery reactivity testing . His
      stool samples will be collected and blood samples will also be taken at this visit for
      systemic measurements inflammatory markers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Brachial Artery Flow Mediated Dilation</measure>
    <time_frame>Change before  and after 6 weeks of daily Probiotic</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A measurement of endothelial function in humans</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Brachial Artery Flow Mediated Dilation</measure>
    <time_frame>Change before and after 10 days of Vancomycin</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stool Analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Change before  and after 6 weeks of daily Probiotic</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>for microbiotic profile analysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stool Analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Change before and after 10 days of daily Vancomycin</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>for microbiotic profile analysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating inflammatory markers and biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>Change before  and after 6 weeks of daily Probiotic</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating inflammatory markers and biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>Change before and after 10 days of daily Vancomycin</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GoodBelly Probiotic  and Vancomycin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Good Belly Probiotic 2.7 oz Daily x 6 weeks Followed by a 4 week wash out period and then, Vancomycin, a non absorbed antibiotic administered (250 mg four times daily) orally for 10 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GoodBelly Probiotic</intervention_name>
    <description>GoodBelly Probiotic 2.7 oz Daily x 6 weeks. Followed by a 4 week wash out period and then, Vancomycin, a non absorbed antibiotic administered (250 mg four times daily) orally for 10 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>GoodBelly Probiotic  and Vancomycin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>GoodBelly Probiotic</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vancomycin</intervention_name>
    <description>GoodBelly Probiotic 2.7 oz Daily x 6 weeks. Followed by a 4 week wash out period and then, Vancomycin, a non absorbed antibiotic administered (250 mg four times daily) orally for 10 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>GoodBelly Probiotic  and Vancomycin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vancomycin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age between 40-75 years old

          2. Male sex

          3. History of known coronary artery disease (by either history of myocardial infarction,
             angiogram demonstrative &gt;=50% stenosis in at least 1 major epicardial coronary
             artery, or a previous stress test that showed evidence of ischemia that has not been
             revealed to be a false positive test by angiography)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Unstable angina or myocardial infarction by history, ECG, and/or enzymatic criteria
             within 1 month of enrollment.

          2. Left ventricular dysfunction as defined by an left ventricular ejection fraction
             documented as &lt; 45% within 1 year of enrollment by an echocardiogram, MRI, or nuclear
             imaging.

          3. Uncontrolled hypertension with a blood pressure greater than 170/100 mmHg at the
             screening visit.

          4. Known history of chronic renal insufficiency, liver dysfunction, or cancer besides
             non-melanoma skin carcinomas or localized prostate cancer requiring systemic
             treatment within five years of enrollment.

          5. Known history of cognitive impairment or inability to follow study procedures

          6. Patient with an implanted defibrillator or permanent pacemaker on with the potential
             participant is known to rely upon for greater than 50% of ventricular
             depolarizations.

          7. Patients who received probiotics, prebiotics, and antibiotics in the last 12 weeks.

          8. Patients with dosing changes of vasoactive medications and
             3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A reductase inhibitors in the 6 weeks prior to
             enrollment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael E Widlansky, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Baker, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael E Widlansky, MD</last_name>
    <phone>4149556755</phone>
    <email>miwidlans@mcw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>John Baker, Phd</last_name>
    <phone>414-456-8706</phone>
    <email>jbaker@mcw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical College of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwauke</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Allison B Couillard, BS</last_name>
      <phone>414-805-3148</phone>
      <email>acouillard@mcw.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael E Widlansky, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Baker, Phd</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 24, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 24, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CAD, coronary artery disease, men, dietary supplement, antibiotic</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anti-Bacterial Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vancomycin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibiotics, Antitubercular</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
