<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="72234">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01956942</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>041310</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01956942</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Micropulse Laser Trabeculoplasty Versus Selective Laser Trabeculoplasty for Treatment of Open Angle Glaucoma</brief_title>
  <acronym>MLT versus SLT</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase IV Study of Micropulse Laser Trabeculoplasty Versus Selective Laser Trabeculoplasty for Treatment of Open Angle Glaucoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>George Washington University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>George Washington University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the effectiveness of a new laser (called Micropulse
      Laser Trabeculoplasty or MLT) in the treatment of glaucoma compared to the conventional
      laser presently used which is called selective laser trabeculoplasty or SLT. Both lasers
      (SLT and MLT) are used as standard of care in the treatment of open angle glaucoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Glaucoma is the 2nd leading cause of blindness worldwide and affects over 2.5 million
      Americans over the age of 40. It is thought that elevated intraocular pressure causes damage
      to the optic nerve fibers which leads to silent vision loss in glaucoma. Therefore, the
      primary approach to managing this disease process is through intraocular pressure reduction
      with a) topical drops that decrease intraocular fluid production or increase fluid outflow,
      b) laser therapy to the outflow structures in the eye (trabecular meshwork) to increase
      fluid egression, c) or incisional surgery with or without placement of setons to create a
      new pathway for fluid outflow. When medical therapy has been maximized or patients do not
      tolerate topical therapy, laser trabeculoplasty is common applied to achieve further
      intraocular pressure reduction. There are two types of laser therapies: argon laser
      trabeculoplasty (ALT) and selective laser trabeculoplasty (SLT). The former involves
      applying laser to create outflow pathways in the trabecular meshwork (TM) and induces
      thermal damage to the TM. The latter selectively applies energy which induces inflammatory
      restructuring of the TM without creating a burn. Studies have shown comparable results
      between the two treatment modalities with  SLT offering the advantage of repeatable
      treatment. Studies have also shown laser trabeculoplasty to be comparable to the effect of
      topical drops in intraocular pressure reduction. Side effects for both types of laser
      trabeculoplasty include post procedure intraocular pressure elevation and intraocular
      inflammation which is treated with topical drops after the procedure.

      This study aims to evaluate the effectiveness of micropulse laser trabeculoplasty in
      intraocular pressure reduction in patients with open angle glaucoma as compared to
      conventional selective laser trabeculoplasty. Secondary aims would be to determine whether
      its reduction is comparable to that of topical intraocular pressure lowering drops, length
      of therapeutic intraocular pressure reduction, and incidence of side effects commonly
      encountered with traditional laser trabeculoplasty including intraocular inflammation and
      intraocular pressure spikes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraocular pressure reduction</measure>
    <time_frame>within 6 weeks to 3 months after the laser procedure is completed</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>evaluate the effectiveness of micropulse laser trabeculoplasty in intraocular pressure reduction in patients with open angle glaucoma as compared to conventional selective laser trabeculoplasty</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>incidence of intraocular inflammation</measure>
    <time_frame>within 6 weeks following the laser procedure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The incidence of side effects commonly encountered with traditional laser trabeculoplasty including intraocular inflammation  will be measured and compared between both lasers (SLT vs. MLT).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">84</enrollment>
  <condition>Open Angle Glaucoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Micropulse Laser Trabeculoplasty</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient's randomized to MLT would be treated with the following settings: 300 micron spot size, 0.3 second duration, 15% duty cycle, and 1000 milliWatt power.  They would be treated with confluent laser spots across the entire 360 degrees of the trabecular meshwork. Each patient would receive pre-treatment with a drop on iopidine or brimonidine to prevent post-operative intraocular pressure (IOP) spikes as per standard pre-laser trabeculoplasty protocol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Selective Laser Trabeculoplasty (SLT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient's randomized to SLT would be treated with the following settings: 400 micron spot size, 0.3 second duration, and 1.00 milliWatt (mW) power.  They would be treated with confluent laser spots across the entire 360 degrees of the trabecular meshwork. Each patient would receive pre-treatment with a drop on iopidine or brimonidine to prevent post-operative IOP spikes as per standard pre-laser trabeculoplasty protocol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Micropulse Laser Trabeculoplasty</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Micropulse Laser Trabeculoplasty</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MLT</other_name>
    <other_name>Laser</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Selective Laser Trabeculoplasty</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Selective Laser Trabeculoplasty (SLT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SLT</other_name>
    <other_name>Laser</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients of any ange age

          -  Diagnosis of open angle glaucoma who have not had recent changes in their medication
             regimen.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with active neovascularization of the angle, angle closure glaucoma, angle
             recession, or anterior uveitis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Belyea, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>George Washington University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>KHADIJAH ABDALLAH, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>202-741-2826</phone>
    <email>KABDALLAH@MFA.GWU.EDU</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>George Washington University Medical Faculty Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20037</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Belyea, MD</last_name>
      <phone>202-741-2825</phone>
      <email>dbelyea@mfa.gwu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Khadijah Abdallah, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>202-741-2826</phone>
      <email>kabdallah@mfa.gwu.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Belyea, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Detry-Morel M, Muschart F, Pourjavan S. Micropulse diode laser (810 nm) versus argon laser trabeculoplasty in the treatment of open-angle glaucoma: comparative short-term safety and efficacy profile. Bull Soc Belge Ophtalmol. 2008;(308):21-8.</citation>
    <PMID>18700451</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Juzych MS, Chopra V, Banitt MR, Hughes BA, Kim C, Goulas MT, Shin DH. Comparison of long-term outcomes of selective laser trabeculoplasty versus argon laser trabeculoplasty in open-angle glaucoma. Ophthalmology. 2004 Oct;111(10):1853-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15465546</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fea AM, Bosone A, Rolle T, Brogliatti B, Grignolo FM. Micropulse diode laser trabeculoplasty (MDLT): A phase II clinical study with 12 months follow-up. Clin Ophthalmol. 2008 Jun;2(2):247-52.</citation>
    <PMID>19668712</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 6, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 30, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>GLAUCOMA</keyword>
  <keyword>MICROPULSE</keyword>
  <keyword>LASER</keyword>
  <keyword>TRABECULOPLASTY</keyword>
  <keyword>OPEN ANGLE</keyword>
  <keyword>INTRAOCULAR PRESSURE</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma, Open-Angle</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
