<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="18461">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02077010</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>131273</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02077010</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nebulized Inhaled Milrinone in a Hospitalized Advanced Heart Failure Population Awaiting Cardiac Transplantation</brief_title>
  <acronym>iMilrinone</acronym>
  <official_title>Nebulized Inhaled Milrinone in a Hospitalized Advanced Heart Failure Population Awaiting Cardiac Transplantation: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Vanderbilt University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Lipscomb University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Vanderbilt University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients with end stage heart failure have significant symptoms (including fatigue and
      shortness of breath) which prevent them from being able to perform most activities of daily
      living. Milrinone is one of the inotropic medications that has been studied and used in the
      treatment of end stage heart failure. End stage heart failure patients awaiting a heart
      transplantation often have to be maintained on IV milrinone 24 hours a day through a chronic
      IV line. Two problems arise with this therapy. First, the IV line itself creates an
      opportunity for infection and blood clots, in addition to interfering with patient's quality
      of life. Second, patients may be exposed to higher levels of milrinone when given IV than
      are necessary for maintaining their heart's function.

      The investigators goal is to show that inhaled milrinone is equivalent to &quot;standard of care&quot;
      IV milrinone in improving heart and lung pressures in end stage heart failure patients (who
      respond to milrinone therapy) in a prospective, randomized, controlled clinical trial.
      Patients who are sent for a right heart catheterization procedure by their cardiologist to
      determine if they require milrinone while awaiting heart transplantation will be randomly
      chosen to be in the continuous IV milrinone group or the inhaled milrinone group after
      agreeing to participate in this study. Patients in the inhaled milrinone group will receive
      6mg in 6ml of fluid inhaled by a vibrating mesh nebulizer every 4 hours. Patients in the IV
      arm will receive a constant IV infusion rate. Both groups will have a repeat right heart
      catheterization procedure an average of 48 hours after milrinone initiation to evaluate
      their response to milrinone. Afterward, all patients that respond will be placed on the
      standard of care IV milrinone for the duration of their therapy, as directed by their
      cardiologist.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Approximately 5.7 million Americans have heart failure, a leading cause of both morbidity
      and mortality in the United States. Heart failure was listed as a contributing cause in more
      than 280,000 deaths in 2008 in the U.S. (1 in 9) and about half of patients diagnosed with
      heart failure die within 5 years. Patients with end stage heart failure have significant
      symptoms (including fatigue and dyspnea) which prevent them from being able to perform most
      activities of daily living. These patients often require repeated or prolonged
      hospitalizations for disease management which contributes significantly to the cost of heart
      failure for the United States (34.4 billion each year).

      Milrinone, a phosphodiesterase III inhibitor, is one of the inotropic medications that has
      been studied and used in the treatment of acutely decompensated heart failure. Several
      studies have evaluated chronic intravenous (IV) inotrope use in end stage heart failure for
      palliation of symptoms as well as evaluated effect on cost through decreased hospital
      readmissions. Hauptman et al and Harjai et al demonstrated significant decreases in hospital
      costs due to reductions in days hospitalized and readmissions after initiation of inotropes
      including milrinone. However, the concern with IV milrinone use is the possibility of
      increased mortality associated with therapy despite improved hemodynamics (increased cardiac
      output, decreased filling pressures) and symptoms as was observed with chronic use of oral
      inotropes. The OPTIME-CHF study confirmed this concern regarding the use of IV milrinone by
      reporting increased mortality in patients with New York Heart Association (NYHA) class
      III-IV ischemic heart failure without hemodynamic compromise as well as statistically
      significant increases in atrial and ventricular arrhythmias when using intravenous
      milrinone. For this reason, the American Heart Association/American College of Cardiology
      practice guidelines, recommend use of IV milrinone only for patients presenting with
      clinical evidence of hypotension associated with hypo-perfusion and elevated cardiac filling
      pressures in order to maintain systemic perfusion and preserve end-organ performance.
      Administration of chronic IV inotropes in heart failure patients with refractory symptoms is
      categorized as a class IIb indication (&quot;usefulness/efficacy is less well established by
      expert opinion&quot;).

      Patients with end stage HF, at the discretion of their treating cardiologist who ordered the
      initial right heart catheterization (RHC) for evaluation of HF therapy, are sent for right
      heart catheterization (RHC) to determine if inotropic therapy would be beneficial.  If the
      treating cardiologist decides to initiate inotropic therapy based on current
      guideline-recommended therapies after RHC is performed, the patient will undergo
      randomization to either the intervention arm (inhaled milrinone) or the control arm
      (intravenous milrinone) prior to RHC. Randomization will be performed by randomized block
      design using a computer generated random number table with 2 blocks. Because of the
      significant accumulation of milrinone in renal dysfunction, patients with a creatinine
      clearance less than or equal to 40ml/min, as calculated by the Cockcroft-Gault equation
      using the serum creatinine prior to randomization, will be placed into a separate block from
      those with a creatinine clearance greater than 40ml/min. Within the block, even numbers will
      be placed in the intervention arm, and odd numbers will be placed in the control arm.

      The investigators goal is to show that inhaled milrinone is equivalent to &quot;standard of care&quot;
      IV milrinone in improving hemodynamics in end stage heart failure patients (who respond to
      milrinone therapy) in a prospective, randomized, controlled clinical trial. Change in
      patient hemodynamic measurements before and during treatment will be assessed by right heart
      catheterization hemodynamic variables (including right ventricle (RV) stroke work index,
      Cardiac output (CO), mixed venous oxygen saturation, pulmonary venous resistence (PVR), and
      systemic vascular resistence (SVR). This is a prospective, single center,
      drug-interventional, non-blinded, open-label, randomized controlled clinical trial.
      Anticipated number of patients enrolled in this study is n = 40 (20 patients randomized to
      nebulized inhaled milrinone and intravenous milrinone groups).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pulmonary capillary wedge pressure (PCWP) and Cardiac Index (CI) hemodynamics from baseline to second right heart catheterization</measure>
    <time_frame>Right heart catheterization will be performed at baseline to determine need for milrinone initiation.  A second right heart catheterization will be performed an average of 48 hours after initiation of IV or inhaled milrinone.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will compare, in each arm, the baseline hemodynamics of RHC to the hemodynamics from the 2nd RHC, assessing if a greater than or equal to a 20% decrease in PCWP or greater than or equal to a 20% increase in CI has occurred.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemodynamic assessment at repeat right heart catheterization</measure>
    <time_frame>Right heart catheterization will be performed at baseline to determine need for milrinone initiation.  A second right heart catheterization will be performed an average of 48 hours after initiation of IV or inhaled milrinone.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in RHC hemodynamic variables and RV stroke work index and mixed venous oxygen saturation compared to pre-milrinone RHC values</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic analysis of drug exposure between IV and inhaled milrinone</measure>
    <time_frame>Plasma milrinone levels will be determined from 4 blood samples obtained at 30 minutes after 1st dose, prior to second and fourth doses, and 30 min after 5th dose in the inhaled arm and at 6, 12, 24, and 48 hrs in the IV milrinone arm.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Pharmacokinetic profile assessment of inhaled versus IV milrionone including area under the curve (AUC) for total drug exposure.
IV milrinone Arm: plasma samples at 6, 12, 24, and 48 hours after starting therapy Inhlaed milrinone Arm: plasma samples will be drawn at: 0.5 hour after first inhaled treatment, prior to the second inhaled treatment dose, before the 7th inhaled dose, 0.5 hour after the 7th inhaled dose</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse event rates including hypotension and arrhythmias</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until study drug is completed (less than or equal to 72 hr after randomization)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>General adverse event (AE) rates were graded according to National Institutes of Health - Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) and specific AE such as hypotension and arrhythmias defined as:
Hypotension: systolic blood pressure (SBP) &lt; 80mmHg (milimeters mercury) for &gt; 30min or symptomatic hypotension necessitating clinical intervention (See withdrawal criteria for details)
Arrhythmias: &quot;New&quot; atrial or ventricular arrhythmias lasting &gt; 30 seconds or any arrhythmia causing hemodynamic instability requiring intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse event rate by glomerular filtration rate</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until study drug is completed (less than or equal to 72 hr after randomization)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient adverse event (AE) rates stratified by baseline glomerular filtration rate (GFR) &lt; 40ml/min versus GFR &gt; 40ml/min</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma concentrations of milrinone in therapeutic range</measure>
    <time_frame>At steady state, which will be the plasma sample 48 hrs after starting IV milrinone and the plasma concentration 0.5hrs after the 7th inhaled dose in the inhalation arm</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percent achievement of steady state milrinone plasma concentrations in the therapeutic range (100-300ng/ml) for each study group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All cause mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until study drug is completed (less than or equal to 72 hr after randomization)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Death from any cause during the study period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Study Withdrawal Criteria -1</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until study drug is completed (less than or equal to 72 hr after randomization)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The trial will be monitored for the following safety endpoints (see below), using the stopping criteria described below:
1) Sustained ventricular tachycardia (VT) - VT lasting longer than 30 seconds, or frequent non-sustained VT causing hemodynamic instability with MAP &lt; 60 mmHg  requiring intervention or &gt; 1 intra-cardiac defibrillation or external cardiac defibrillation shock.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Withdrawal criteria - 2</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until study drug is completed (less than or equal to 72 hr after randomization)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The trial will be monitored for the following safety endpoints (see below), using the stopping criteria described below:
2) Atrial arrhythmias: A &quot;new&quot; diagnosis of atrial arrhythmia (includes atrial fibrillation, atrial flutter, ectopic atrial tachycardia) lasting &gt; 30 seconds OR any atrial arrhythmia which causes hemodynamic instability (mean arterial pressure (MAP) &lt; 60 and requiring intervention)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Withdrawal criteria - 3</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until study drug is completed (less than or equal to 72 hr after randomization)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The trial will be monitored for the following safety endpoints (see below), using the stopping criteria described below:
3) Hypotension: MAP &lt; 60 for  &gt; 30min or symptomatic hypotension necessitating clinical intervention (defined as vasopressor support, intravenous fluid boluses, or discontinuation of milrinone)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Withdrawal criteria -4</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until study drug is completed (less than or equal to 72 hr after randomization)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The trial will be monitored for the following safety endpoints (see below), using the stopping criteria described below:
4) Hypersensitivity reaction to milrinone:  Systemic hypotension (MAP &lt; 60 for &gt; 30 minutes) plus one of the following: bronchospasm (clinical wheezing) or rash (any type) / urticaria (any type)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Withdrawal criteria -5</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until study drug is completed (less than or equal to 72 hr after randomization)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The trial will be monitored for the following safety endpoints (see below), using the stopping criteria described below:
5) Respiratory distress defined as acute dyspnea with a new higher oxygen requirement through a high-flow or non-rebreather facemask than at baseline OR a new need for inhaled bronchodilators</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Withdrawal criteria -6</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until study drug is completed (less than or equal to 72 hr after randomization)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The trial will be monitored for the following safety endpoints (see below), using the stopping criteria described below:
6) Deterioration of heart failure by the treating cardiologist's clinical assessment that necessitates additional inotrope/vasopressor support (defined as dobutamine, norepinephrine, dopamine at doses &gt; 5mcg/kg/min, epinephrine, phenylephrine, or vasopressin use) or mechanical support cardiovascular support.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <condition>Cardiomyopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Inhaled nebulized milrinone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Inhaled nebulized milrinone 6mg/6ml every 4 hours using a vibrating mesh nebulizer</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intravenous milrinone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Continuously infused IV milrinone at 0.375mcg/kg/min</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Milrinone</intervention_name>
    <description>Milrinone is both the active comparison and experimental arm. The intervention arm will receive milrinone via inhalation of a nebulizer solution. The active comparison arm will receive milrinone via a continuous intravenous infusion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Inhaled nebulized milrinone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intravenous milrinone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Primacor</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients age &gt; 18 years old

          2. Symptomatic Stage D heart failure requiring initiation of inotropic medication at the
             discretion of their cardiologist

          3. Signed informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients incapable of signing informed consent for any reason

          2. Patients who are pregnant or breastfeeding

          3. Systolic blood pressure less than 80 mmHg prior to randomization

          4. Documented allergy or adverse reaction to milrinone

          5. Reactive airway diseases characterized by use of maintenance nebulizers (not inhaler
             devices) as home therapy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicholas Haglund, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Vanderbilt University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zachary L Cox, PharmD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Vanderbilt University Medical Center/ Lipscomb University College of Pharmacy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nicholas Haglund, MD</last_name>
    <phone>615-936-1720</phone>
    <email>nicholas.a.haglund@Vanderbilt.Edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Zachary L Cox, PharmD</last_name>
    <phone>615-966-7107</phone>
    <email>zachary.l.cox@vanderbilt.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37204</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nicholas Haglund, MD</last_name>
      <phone>615-936-1720</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nicholas Haglund, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Zachary L Cox, PharmD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 1, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 25, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Vanderbilt University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nicholas Haglund</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Fellow in Division of Cardiovascular Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>milrinone</keyword>
  <keyword>heart failure</keyword>
  <keyword>cardiomyopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>inhaled</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Milrinone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
