<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="10050">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02064205</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>JZ PDX Satiety</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>WM-01-2014</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02064205</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Appetite Suppression Trial With Polydextrose</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double Blind, Placebo Controlled, Randomized, Cross-over Study to Assess the Effects of Polydextrose on Appetite Suppression and Its Mechanisms of Action in Healthy Women With a Normal Weight and Overweight Female Participants.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>W.J. Pasman</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>TNO</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Netherlands: The Central Committee on Research Involving Human Subjects (CCMO)</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Overweight and obesity are a global epidemic, which causes a rapid increase in the frequency
      of diabetes and cardiovascular diseases. Food ingredients that influence the mechanisms that
      regulate satiety may play a role in weight management. Suppression of appetite may reduce
      energy intake, which in return may lead to body weight reduction. This study aims to verify
      the appetite suppressive effect of polydextrose in comparison to a placebo in normal weight
      and overweight women.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Polydextrose is a well-tolerated, low calorie glucose polymer (4kJ/g) that can be easily
      incorporated into various food applications to replace sugar and fat (Auerbach et al.,
      2007). Polydextrose is poorly digested in the upper gastrointestinal tract and therefore
      shows fiber-like properties. The addition of polydextrose to foods may increase the
      satiating properties of foods.

      Previous studies have shown that:

        -  Consuming polydextrose-containing preloads (6.25 - 25.0 g polydextrose) resulted in a
           significant lower energy intake at lunch compared to the control (Astbury et al., 2013;
           Ranawana et al., 2013; Hull et al., 2012; King et al., 2005).

        -  Polydextrose is able to modify appetite ratings at low (6.25 - 12.5 g polydextrose)
           (Hull et al., 2012) and high doses (56.7 g/d) (Konings et al., 2013).

        -  Polydextrose (15.0 g) induced enhanced GLP-1 response after a high-fat meal in obese
           participants (Tiihonen et al., 2012).

      Therefore, it is hypothesized that with the consumption of 12.5 g polydextrose as compared
      with the placebo, appetite will be suppressed, resulting in:

        -  a lower consumption at lunch (energy intake at lunch)

        -  change in appetite scores (VAS)

        -  change in satiety hormones (CCK, PYY, GLP-1, ghrelin)

        -  change in glucose and insulin

        -  change in stomach emptying rate

        -  change in gastric wellbeing
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Energy intake at an ad libitum lunch on a test-day in normal weight and overweight women.</measure>
    <time_frame>Four hours or 1.5 hour after consumption of a pre-load at up to day 22</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Yogurt with a polydextrose (fiber with satiating effect) is consumed in the morning with breakfast or later in the morning. The satiating effect of the addition of polydextrose is tested on the amount of food consumed with lunch four hours or 1.5h later. A test is performed on day 01, day 08, day 15 and day 22 with at least four days wash-out in-between.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate effect of pre-load on satiety hormones and scores in normal weight and overweight women.</measure>
    <time_frame>Four hour curves (t=0, 30, 60, 90, 150 and 240 min) of day 01, day 08, day 15 and day 22.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The satiety hormones CCK, GLP-1, ghrelin and PYY as well as the satiety feelings (hunger, fullness, desire to eat, prospective food consumption) are measured before, at t=30, 60, 90, 150, 240) after breakfast consumption. This is done on day 01, day 08, day 15 and day 22 with at least four days wash-out in-between.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy, Normal Weight and Overweight Women,</condition>
  <condition>Non-restrained Eaters</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>polydextrose or glucose syrup at breakfast</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Breakfast with pre-load four hours before lunch</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-load with yogurt and polydextrose or glucose later</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Breakfast without pre-load. Pre-load with yogurt provided 1.5h before lunch.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>12.5 g polydextrose</intervention_name>
    <description>Appetite suppressing supplement is added in yogurt and provided with breakfast (four hours before lunch) or 1.5h before lunch. Also yogurt with control (glucose syrup) is tested for its satiating effect.</description>
    <arm_group_label>polydextrose or glucose syrup at breakfast</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-load with yogurt and polydextrose or glucose later</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Litesse®Ultra TM</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>glucose syrup</intervention_name>
    <description>Glucose syrup  is used a control product for the polydextrose</description>
    <arm_group_label>polydextrose or glucose syrup at breakfast</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-load with yogurt and polydextrose or glucose later</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Healthy, female participants aged 20-45 years inclusive

          2. BMI: 20-30 kg/m2 inclusive

          3. Written consent regarding participation after full information regarding all details
             of the study

          4. Normal Dutch eating habits (consuming mostly three main meals per day; used to eat
             bread for lunch)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnancy

          2. On-going or recent treatment for diabetes, hypertension, coronary heart disease,
             psychiatric conditions, inflammatory chronic disease - rheumatoid arthritis, Crohn
             Disease, ulcerous colitis, chronic constipation, eating disorders, or any disease
             condition which interferes with ADME of the investigational product

          3. Reported postmenopausal

          4. Having menstruation problems, e.g. PCOS

          5. Reported to be on a slimming diet or other dietary treatment (currently or during
             last two months, like vegetarian diet, lactose restricted diet etc.)

          6. Aversion towards products (yoghurt) provided in the study

          7. On-going use of any slimming preparations

          8. Any kind of dysfunction of digestive tract, food allergy, chronic constipation,
             recent/actual gastroenteritis

          9. Restrained eaters (score DEBQ &gt;3.4)

         10. Participants consuming more than 23g of dietary fiber per day - P75 according to the
             Dutch National Food Consumption Survey - (as assessed with a general short
             questionnaire which gives estimation on the fiber intake. Exact fiber intake will not
             be calculated)

         11. Smoker in the last 3 months

         12. Heavy coffee drinkers (more than 6 cups a day)

         13. High level of physical activity: Participants who perform more than 3 hours of
             intense training/sport activity per week (this will not include normal cycling
             transport)

         14. Heavy alcohol consumers, no more than 14 units per week (1 unit represents 1 standard
             glass/portion of alcohol, independent of the type of alcoholic drink).

        Remark:

        When enough subjects are eligible (&gt; 32), the women with the highest BMI will be selected
        to participate. At least 50% of the subjects will have a BMI ranging of 25-30. Also at
        least 50% of the women will be in the age range of 25-45 years. When more than 32 subjects
        are eligible the eldest subjects will be included.

        With respect to eligibility of the subjects:

        the BMI criterion always comes for age criterion, meaning that overweight is stressed to
        be of more importance for this study than age. Overweight will always come first, even
        when already &gt; 50% of the women with a BMI 25-30 have been included. In this way the
        overweight group of women will be studied as much as possible.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Naguib Muhsen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>QPS, The Netherlands</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Wilrike Pasman, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+31 888 66 5129</phone>
    <email>wilrike.pasman@tno.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Henk Hendriks, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+31 888 66 1633</phone>
    <email>henk.hendriks@tno.nl</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>QPS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Groningen</city>
        <zip>9713AG</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Daniel Prins, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 11, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>TNO</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>W.J. Pasman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Project Manager Clinical Trials</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pre-load</keyword>
  <keyword>satiety</keyword>
  <keyword>energy intake</keyword>
  <keyword>appetite</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
