<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="114298">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01880567</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013-0090</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-01304</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01880567</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 2 Ibrutinib + Rituximab in Relapsed/Refractory Mantle Cell Lymphoma (R/R MCL)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Ibrutinib Plus Rituximab in Patients With Relapsed/Refractory Mantle Cell Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pharmacyclics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn if a combination of ibrutinib and
      rituximab can help control relapsed or refractory MCL. The safety of this drug combination
      will also be studied.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Drug Administration:

      If you are found to be eligible for this study, you will begin the first cycle of treatment
      with ibrutinib and rituximab. Each cycle is 28 days.

      Ibrutinib Administration:

      Every day you will take 4 ibrutinib capsules with 1 cup (about 8 ounces) of water. You must
      take all 4 capsules at about the same time every day, at least 30 minutes before eating or
      at least 2 hours after a meal.  Do not open the capsules or dissolve them.

      If you miss a dose, you can take it up to 6 hours after the time you would have taken it. If
      it is later than 6 hours, you should skip the dose and start taking the capsules at the same
      time as usual the next day.

      You will need to fill out diary cards with information about when you take ibrutinib. You
      should bring the diary cards with you to appointments. You will receive a 30 day supply of
      the ibrutinib capsules on Day 1 of Cycles 1-9. After that, starting on Cycle 10, you will
      receive a 60-day supply of the drug every other cycle.

      Rituximab Administration:

      On Days 1, 8, 15, and 22 of Cycle 1, you will receive rituximab by vein. The first infusion
      takes 6-8 hours. After that, infusions take about 4 hours.

      You will then receive rituximab by vein over 4 hours on Day 1 of Cycles 3-8 and every other
      cycle after that for up to 2 years.

      For some patients, you may receive the rituximab dose over 2 days. Your doctor will tell you
      if this is the best approach for you.

      Study Visits:

      On Day 1 of all cycles:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 2 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

        -  If your doctor thinks it is needed, you will have a bone marrow biopsy and/or
           aspiration to check the status of the disease.

        -  If the study doctor thinks it is needed, you will have a gastrointestinal endoscopy.

        -  If the study doctor thinks it is needed, you will have a PET/CT scan to check the
           status of the disease.

      On Days 8, 15, and 22 of Cycle 1, blood (about 2 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine
      tests.

      On Day 1 of Cycles 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, and 12, then every 3 cycles after that, if the study
      doctor thinks it is needed, you will have a CT scan to check the status of the disease. You
      may have scans less often.

      On Day 1 of Cycle 1:

        -  Blood (about 2 tablespoons) will be drawn for biomarker testing and to check the status
           of the disease. Biomarkers are found in the blood and may be related to your reaction
           to the study drug.

        -  Blood (about 2 tablespoons) will be drawn  to check your immune system.

      One time between Cycles 2-10, when the study doctor thinks it is needed, blood (about 4
      tablespoons) will be drawn for biomarker testing and to check you immune system.

      Length of Study:

      You may continue taking the study drugs for as long as the doctor thinks it is in your best
      interest.  You will no longer be able to take the drug if the disease gets worse, if
      intolerable side effects occur, or if you are unable to follow study directions.

      Your participation on the study will be over once you have completed follow-up.

      End-of-Treatment Visit:

      After you finish taking the study drugs:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  You will have an EKG to check your heart function.

        -  Blood (about 5-7 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests, for biomarker testing,
           for immune system testing, and to check the status of the disease.

        -  You will have a CT scan and/or x-ray to check the status of the disease.

        -  If your doctor thinks it is needed, you will have a PET/CT scan and/or bone marrow
           biopsy/aspiration to check the status of the disease.

        -  If your doctor thinks it is needed, you will have a gastrointestinal endoscopy.

        -  If you can become pregnant, you will have a blood (about 1½ tablespoons) or urine
           pregnancy test.

        -  Blood (about 2 tablespoons) will be drawn for biomarker testing and to check the status
           of the disease.

        -  Blood (about 2 tablespoons) will be drawn  to check your immune system.

      Long Term Follow-Up:

      After your end-of-treatment visit, you will be called every 3 months for 1 year and every 6
      months after that to see how you are doing. These calls will take about 2-3 minutes.

      If you stop the study drug and the disease has gotten better or is stable at the time you
      stopped taking the study drug, blood will be drawn every month for 3 months, then every 2
      months for 6 months, and then every 3 months after that to check the status of the disease.

      This is an investigational study.  Ibrutinib is FDA approved and commercially available for
      the treatment of patients with MCL. Its use in this study is investigational.  Rituximab is
      FDA approved for the treatment of non-Hodgkin's lymphoma and certain types of leukemia.

      Up to 50 patients will take part in this multicenter study.  All 50 will be enrolled at MD
      Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>8  weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall response rate (ORR) is defined as number of participants with partial response (PR) or better (e.g. Complete response (CR) or Partial Response (PR)) as assessed by International Workshop Standardized Response Criteria for non-Hodgkin Lymphoma (NHL).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ibrutinib + Rituximab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ibrutinib administered orally at 560 mg daily for 28 days (one cycle).  Rituximab given cycle 1 day 1, 8, 15 and 22 +/- 1 day by intravenous infusion (IV) at a fixed dose of 375 mg/m2 (Cycle 1), followed by  rituximab on day one of every cycle starting in cycles 3 - 8.  Following cycle 8 rituximab given on day 1 of every other cycle for up to 2 years.  After 2 years, patients treated with ibrutinib in continuous cycles until progression of disease or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ibrutinib</intervention_name>
    <description>560 mg by mouth daily for each 28 day cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ibrutinib + Rituximab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PCI-32765</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rituximab</intervention_name>
    <description>375 mg/m2 by vein given cycle 1 day 1, 8, 15 and 22 +/- 1 day (Cycle 1), followed by rituximab on day one of every cycle starting in cycles 3 - 8. Following cycle 8 rituximab given on day 1 of every other cycle for up to 2 years.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ibrutinib + Rituximab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Rituxan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Confirmed diagnosis of mantle cell lymphoma with CD20 and cyclin D1 through Cyclin D3
             positivity in tissue biopsy.

          2. Patient has relapsed and or refractory MCL and must have received at least one prior
             treatment regimen for their disease. Patient with leukemia phase (peripheral blood
             involvement), leptomeningeal disease, cerebral spinal fluid (CSF) MCL, central
             nervous system (CNS) MCL, non-measurable disease, gastrointestinal (GI) MCL, or bone
             marrow (BM) MCL are also eligible.

          3. Understand and voluntarily sign an institutional review board (IRB)-approved informed
             consent form.

          4. Patient is age &gt;/= 18 years at the time of signing the informed consent.

          5. Patients with bone marrow or gastrointestinal (GI) only involvement are acceptable.

          6. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 2 or less

          7. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;/= 500/mm^3, platelet count &gt;/= 30,000/mm^3
             (transfusion to reach platelet count allowed). (Patients who have bone marrow
             infiltration by MCL are eligible if their ANC is &gt;/= 500/mm^3 [growth factor allowed]
             or their platelet level is equal to or &gt; than 15,000/mm^3. These patients should be
             discussed with either the PI or Co-PI of the study for final approval).

          8. Aspartate transaminase (AST)[serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT)] and
             alanine transaminase (ALT) [serum glutamic pyruvic transaminase (SGPT)] &lt; 2 x upper
             limit of normal or &lt; 5 x upper limit of normal if hepatic metastases are present.
             Serum bilirubin &lt;1.5 mg/dl and Cr Clearance &gt;/= 30 mL/min.

          9. Patients must be willing to receive transfusions of blood products.

         10. Willing and able to participate in all study related procedures and therapy including
             swallowing capsules without difficulty.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any serious medical condition that places the patient at unacceptable risk and/or
             would prevent the subject from signing the informed consent form. Examples include
             but are not limited to, uncontrolled hypertension, uncontrolled diabetes mellitus,
             active/symptomatic coronary artery disease, active infection, active hemorrhage, or
             psychiatric illness.

          2. Pregnant or breast feeding females.

          3. Known Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection. Patients with active hepatitis B
             infection (not including patients with prior hepatitis B vaccination; or positive
             serum Hepatitis B antibody). Known hepatitis C infection is allowed as long as there
             is no active disease and is cleared by gastrointestinal (GI) consultation.

          4. The patient has a prior or concurrent malignancy that in the opinion of the
             investigator, presents a greater risk to the patient's health and survival, than of
             the MCL, within the subsequent 6 months at the time of consent.

          5. History of stroke or intracranial hemorrhage within 6 months prior to signing the
             consent

          6. Clinically significant cardiovascular disease such as uncontrolled or symptomatic
             arrhythmias, congestive heart failure or myocardial infarction within 6 months at the
             time of consent or any Class 3 (moderate) or 4 (severe) cardiac disease defined by
             the New York Heart Association Classification.

          7. Significant screening electrocardiogram (ECG) abnormalities including left bundle
             branch block, 2nd degree AV block type II, 3rd degree block, bradycardia [&lt; 50 beats
             per minute (bpm)], or QTc &gt;500 msec.

          8. Malabsorption syndrome, disease significantly affecting gastrointestinal function, or
             resection of the stomach or small bowel or ulcerative colitis, symptomatic
             inflammatory bowel disease, or partial or complete bowel obstruction.

          9. Prior chemotherapy within 3 weeks, nitrosoureas within 6 weeks, therapeutic
             anticancer antibodies within 4 weeks, radio- or toxin-immunoconjugates within 10
             weeks, radiation therapy or other investigational agents within 3 weeks, major
             surgery within 4 weeks or vaccination with live attenuated vaccines within 4 weeks of
             the first dose of study drug.

         10. Prior treatment with ibrutinib.

         11. Requires anticoagulation with warfarin or equivalent vitamin K antagonist.

         12. Requires treatment with strong CYP3A4/5 inhibitors.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Wang, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael Wang, MD, MS</last_name>
    <phone>713-792-2860</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 12, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 14, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Relapsed/Refractory Mantle Cell Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>R/R MCL</keyword>
  <keyword>Ibrutinib</keyword>
  <keyword>PCI-32765</keyword>
  <keyword>Rituximab</keyword>
  <keyword>Rituxan</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Mantle-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
