<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="166364">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01715298</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CNVA237A2318</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01715298</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>NVA237 BID Versus Placebo Twelve-week Efficacy Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>A 12-week Multi-center, Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo Controlled Study to Assess the Efficacy and Safety of NVA237 in Stable COPD Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Novartis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study serves to determine whether the treatment of patients with stable, symptomatic
      Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) with the investigational drug NVA237 is
      efficient and safe. The efficacy and safety of the drug will be tested against a placebo
      treatment. The primary criterion to assess efficacy will be the difference between the
      serial lung function measurements of patients who have been treated for 12 weeks with NVA237
      versus those that have received placebo treatment for 12 weeks. A serial lung function
      measurement (FEV1 testing) will be conducted and the &quot;area under the curve&quot; will be the
      measure for the ability to breathe.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Standardized Area Under the Curve for Forced Expiratory Volume in one second post dosing</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The standardized Area Under the Curve (AUC) for Forced Expiratory Volume in one second (FEV1) post dosing (FEV1 AUC) at week 12 of treatment. Serial lung function measurements are taken at various time points following dosing at week 12 to calculate the AUC.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Standardized Area Under the Curve for Forced Expiratory Volume in one second post dosing</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The standardized Area Under the Curve (AUC) for Forced Expiratory Volume in one second (FEV1) post dosing (FEV1 AUC) is assessed at day 1 of treatment. Serial lung function measurements are taken at various time points post dosing at day 1 to calculate the AUC.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Standardized Area Under The Curve for Forced Expiratory Volume in one second for different time spans post dosing</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The standardized Area Under the Curve (AUC) for Forced Expiratory Volume in one second (FEV1) is assessed for different time spans within the overall serial measurement post dosing (FEV1 AUCs Time Spans), at day 1 and at week 12 of treatment. Serial lung function measurements are taken at various time points post dosing on day 1 and at week 12 to calculate the AUC for these different time spans.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Forced Expiratory Volume in one second at all individual timepoints</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Forced Expiratory Volume in one second assessments for all individual time points of the serial measurements on day 1 and at week 12 are analyzed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean trough Forced Expiratory Volume in one second</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Mean trough Forced Expiratory Volume in one second (FEV1) is assessed as the arithmetic mean of two FEV1 measurements, conducted within the last hour of a 24 hour period from a morning dose, either that of day 1 or at week 12 of treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health status assessed by St. George's Respiratory Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The health status, as reported by the patients, is assessed using the St. George's Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ). The assessment is based on total score as well as the percentage of patients with clinically significant improvement at week 12 versus day 1. A clinically significant improvement in SGRQ is defined as less than or equal to -4 change from baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Breathlessness assessed by Transition Dyspnea Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Breathlessness at week 12 is measured using the Transition Dyspnea Index (TDI). On day 1, breathlessness is assessed by the Baseline Dyspnea Index (BDI). Patients are considered to have clinically significant improvement with the TDI score change versus BDI being equal to or greater than 1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean number of puffs of rescue medication per day</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients report the number of puffs of rescue medication (salbutamol / albuterol) using an electronic diary. The use of rescue medication is analyzed as the mean daily number of puffs used per patient over the 12 weeks treatment period. The baseline is calculated from the run-in epoch prior to randomization.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of days without rescue medication use</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients report the number of puffs of rescue medication (salbutamol / albuterol) using an electronic diary. The use of rescue medication is analyzed as the percentage of days without usage of rescue medication over the 12 weeks treatment period. The baseline is calculated from the run-in epoch prior to randomization.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Daily symptom scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients are reporting symptoms by using an electronic diary. Symptom scores are calculated as combined daily symptom scores (combined from morning and evening scores) for each patient over 12 weeks. The baseline is calculated from the run-in epoch prior to randomization.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of nights with &quot;no nighttime awakenings&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients are reporting symptoms by using an electronic diary. A night with &quot;no nighttime awakening&quot; is defined from diary data as any night where the patient did not wake up due to symptoms. The baseline is calculated from the run-in epoch prior to randomization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of days with &quot;no daytime symptoms&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients are reporting symptoms by using an electronic diary. A day with &quot;no daytime symptoms&quot; is defined from diary data as any day where the patient has recorded in the evening no cough, no wheeze, no production of sputum, and no feeling of breathlessness (other than when running) during the past approximately 12 hours. The baseline is calculated from the run-in epoch prior to randomization.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of &quot;days able to perform usual daily activities&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients are reporting symptoms by using an electronic diary. A &quot;day able to perform usual daily activities&quot; is defined from diary data as any day where the patient was not prevented from performing their usual daily activities due to respiratory symptoms. The baseline is calculated from the run-in epoch prior to randomization.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The safety and tolerability of NVA237 will be assessed with regard to vital signs, ECGs, laboratory evaluations and adverse events over the 12 week treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Forced Vital Capacity at all individual timepoints</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Forced Vital Capacity assessments for all individual time points of the serial measurements on day 1 and at week 12 are analyzed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean trough Forced Vital Capacity</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Mean trough Forced Vital Capacity (FVC) is assessed as the arithmetic mean of two FVC measurements, conducted within the last hour of a 24 hours period from a morning dose, either that of day 1 or at week 12 of treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Morning symptom scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients are reporting morning symptoms by using an electronic diary. Morning symptoms scores for each patient over 12 weeks are reported. The baseline is calculated from the run-in epoch prior to randomization.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evening symptom scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients are reporting evening symptoms by using an electronic diary. Evening symptoms scores for each patient over 12 weeks are reported. The baseline is calculated from the run-in epoch prior to randomization.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">432</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NVA237</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>NVA237 will be inhaled from a single-dose dry powder inhaler for a period of 12 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo will be inhaled from a single-dose dry powder inhaler for a period of 12 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NVA237</intervention_name>
    <description>NVA237 (Glycopyrronioum bromide) as a powder for inhalation in single-dose capsules</description>
    <arm_group_label>NVA237</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo powder for inhalation in single-dose capsules (matching those for NVA237).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria: 1. Patients with stable, symptomatic Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary
        Disease (COPD) with airflow obstruction of level 2 and 3 according to the current Global
        initiative for chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) strategy (2011). 2. Patients with
        Forced Expiratory Volume in one second (FEV1) ≥ 30% and &lt;80 % of the predicted normal, and
        FEV1/FVC &lt; 0.70 when measured 45 min after the inhalation of 84 µg ipratropium bromide.

        3. Current or ex-smokers with at least 10 cigarette pack years smoking history.

        Exclusion criteria:

          1. Patients with a history of long QT syndrome, with a prolonged QTc measured during
             screening, or patients who have a clinically significant ECG abnormality at
             screening.

          2. History of malignancy of any organ system (other than localized basal cell carcinoma
             of the skin), treated or untreated, within the past 5 years, regardless of whether
             there is evidence of local recurrence or metastases.

          3. Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women. Women of childbearing potential unless using
             an effective method of contraception.

          4. Patients who in the judgment of the investigator, would be at potential risk if
             enrolled into the study.

          5. Patients who have a clinically significant concomitant disease at screening,
             including but not limited to clinically significant laboratory abnormalities,
             clinically significant renal, cardiovascular, neurological, endocrine, immunological,
             psychiatric, gastrointestinal, hepatic, or hematological abnormalities, or with
             uncontrolled diabetes, which could interfere with the assessment of the efficacy and
             safety of the study treatment.

          6. Patients with a body mass index (BMI) of more than 40 kg/m2.

          7. Patients contraindicated for treatment with, or having a history of reactions/
             hypersensitivity to anticholinergic agents, long and short acting beta-2 agonists, or
             sympathomimetic amines.

          8. Patients with any history of asthma, with onset of symptoms prior to age 40 years, or
             patients with a high blood eosinophil count during screening.

        Other protocol-defnied inclusion/exclusion criteria may apply.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>*See Various Dept.'s*</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chandler</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fresno</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>93726</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fullerton</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92835</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yorba Linda</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92886</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yorba Linda</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92886-7921</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boulder</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80304</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wheat Ridge</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lynn Haven</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32444</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33173</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Port Orange</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32127</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winter Park</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32789</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Conyers</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30094</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>River Forest</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Skokie</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60076</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Evansville</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>47714</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lexington</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40509</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sunset</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70584</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fall River</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02720</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>North Dartmouth</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02747</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55402</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Plymouth</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55441</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63128</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Charles</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63301</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63141</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fremont</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68025</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lincoln</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68510</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Omaha</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cherry Hill</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08003</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <state>New Mexico</state>
        <zip>87108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brooklyn</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brooklyn</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11234</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Great Neck</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Massapequa</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11758</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Windsor</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>12553</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10028</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10003</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlotte</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28207</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45231</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45245</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45242</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Medford</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97504-8741</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Medford</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97504</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Langhorne</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19047</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15243</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pottstown</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19464</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tipton</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>16684</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>East Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02914</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Mill</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29707</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rock Hll</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29732</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denton</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>76210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Midvale</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84047</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>South Burlington</city>
        <state>Vermont</state>
        <zip>05403</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23233</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23219</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tacoma</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98405</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 24, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Anticholinergic</keyword>
  <keyword>Antimuscarinic</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Obstructive Airway Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>COPD</keyword>
  <keyword>LAMA</keyword>
  <keyword>Lung Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Lung Diseases, Obstructive</keyword>
  <keyword>Lung Function</keyword>
  <keyword>Muscarinic receptor antagonist</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</keyword>
  <keyword>Respiratory Tract Diseases</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiration Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases, Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
