<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="16808">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02135809</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>90895329</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02135809</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pancreatic Metal Stents in Chronic Pancreatitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Fully Covered Self Expanding Metal Stents (FCSEMS) for Refractory Pancreatic Duct Strictures in Patients With Chronic Pancreatitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Boston Scientific Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Boston Scientific Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Belgium: Federal Agency for Medicinal Products and Health Products</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to document the performance of a new Fully Covered Self
      Expanding Metal Stents (FCSEMS) for treatment of refractory pancreatic duct strictures in
      patients with painful chronic pancreatitis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease of pain caused by refractory benign pancreatic duct strictures secondary to chronic pancreatitis</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after study stent removal</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Clinical success defined as decrease of pain caused by refractory benign pancreatic duct strictures secondary to chronic pancreatitis 3 months after stent removal compared to baseline prior to stent indwell period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence and severity of serious adverse events related to the stenting procedure, to the indwelling stent and/or to stent removal</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of study participation, an average of 27-30 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Type of additional intervention within pancreatic duct</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of study participation, an average of 27-30 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stent placement success</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Stent Placement Procedure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Ability to deploy the stent in satisfactory position (Stent Placement Success). Satisfactory position is defined as the stent being across the stricture, without visible impaction at an angle and distal end visible into the duodenum.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stent removal success</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Stent Removal</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Successful stent removal (Stent Removal Success) defined as ability to remove stent endoscopically (grasper, snare, stent-in-stent) without serious stent removal-related adverse events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of pain medication intake</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of study participation, an average of 27-30 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change of pain medication intake (type of medication) from baseline to each follow-up visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of device events</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of study participation, an average of 27-30 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Device Events, including findings not associated with adverse events, such as but not limited to asymptomatic stent migration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stricture resolution of pancreatic duct after stent removal</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Stent Removal</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessment of pancreatic duct after stent removal compared to baseline, including ERCP to document extent of stricture resolution, extent of resolution of ductal dilation above the treated dominant stricture, and presence or absence of secondary ductal strictures at the level of where the proximal edge of the stent was located</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>For patients who proceed to surgery, impact of prior SEMS on surgical outcomes.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stent functionality</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to time of study stent removal,average of 3-6 months on study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Stent functionality:  Relief of pain caused by refractory benign pancreatic duct strictures secondary to chronic pancreatitis at 3 days,  2 weeks, 1 month, 2 months, 4 months (Phase 2 patients as applicable) and just prior to stent removal compared to baseline prior to stent placement, using established pancreatic pain score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stricture Resolution at stent removal</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Stent Removal</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Stricture Resolution at stent removal, defined as pancreatographic confirmation of drainage of injected contrast medium after stent removal without visible persistent stricture</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Recurrence of Stricture</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of study participation, an average of 27-30 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Time to Recurrence of Stricture, established in patients who had stricture resolution at stent removal and defined as time elapsed from stent removal till recurrence of pain with associated documentation of narrowing of pancreatic duct. Recurrence of stricture will be documented at the time it is identified and absence of stricture recurrence will be ascertained at 1, 3, 6, 12, 18 and 24 months after stent removal. Pain will be documented using an established pancreatic pain score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reason for additional intervention within pancreatic duct</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of study participation, an average of 27-30 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Timing of additional intervention within pancreatic duct</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of study participation, an average of 27-30 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Refractory Pancreatic Duct Strictures</condition>
  <condition>Painful Chronic Pancreatitis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>WallFlex Pancreatic Stent</intervention_name>
    <description>Temporary placement of the WallFlex Pancreatic Stent for treatment of refractory pancreatic duct strictures in patients with painful chronic pancreatitis. Stent will be removed after 3-6 months indwell.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 18 or older

          2. Willing and able to comply with study procedures and follow-up schedule and provide
             written informed consent to participate in study

          3. Chronic pancreatitis of Cremer Type IV (Segmental pancreatitis of the head of the
             pancreas). See Appendix for Cremer classifications.

          4. Improvement of pancreatic pain during previous placement of a single pancreatic
             plastic stent

          5. At least one of the following:

               -  Abdominal pain most probably related to chronic pancreatitis

               -  Recurrent dominant main pancreatic duct stricture in the head of the pancreas
                  after prior indwell of pancreatic plastic stent(s) if pain score was available
                  prior to preceding stent therapy. Recurrent stricture to be visually assessed at
                  endoscopy and confirmed by recurrent main pancreatic duct dilatation at MRCP.

               -  Relapsing pain due to pancreatic duct stent blockage (with only one stent in
                  place)

          6. Prior endoscopic pancreatic sphincterotomy (EPS), historically or to be provided at
             time of SEMS placement with informed patient consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Strictures caused by malignancies

          2. Biliary strictures caused by chronic pancreatitis

          3. Perforated duct.

          4. Ansa pancreatica or H anatomy

          5. Pancreatic duct stenoses not located in the head of the pancreas

          6. Failed access during an attempted ERCP on a prior date

          7. Prior pancreatic metal stent(s)

          8. Concurrent ESWL (Extracorporeal Shock Wave Lithotripsy) during the same treatment
             session

          9. Patients for whom endoscopic techniques are contraindicated.

         10. Patients who are currently enrolled in another investigational study that would
             directly interfere with the current study, without prior written approval from the
             sponsor

         11. Inability or refusal to comply with the follow-up schedule including subject living
             at such a distance from the investigational center that
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Erin Leckrone</last_name>
    <phone>651-582-4908</phone>
    <email>erin.leckrone@bsci.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Andrea Burbage</last_name>
    <phone>508-683-4387</phone>
    <email>andrea.burbage@bsci.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Erasme Hospital - Belgium</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brussels</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jacques Devière, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>32 25553622</phone>
      <email>jdeviere@ulb.ac.be</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jacques Devière, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 2, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatitis, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Constriction, Pathologic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
