<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="117763">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02033369</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>6853</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01MH099322-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02033369</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Imaging Dopamine Release in Depression</brief_title>
  <official_title>Ventrostriatal Dopamine Release and Reward Motivation in MDD</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York State Psychiatric Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Research Foundation for Mental Hygiene, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mclean Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York State Psychiatric Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to determine whether ventral striatal dopamine release is a mechanism of
      reward motivation in major depression, whether dopamine release is low in depression, and
      whether DA release and reward motivation predict response to dopamine-targeted treatment
      with pramipexole.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Better understanding of the basic neurobiology of mood dysfunction appears necessary to
      enable further progress in the treatment of depression. Reward motivation (and the closely
      related construct of &quot;reward learning&quot;) is a core neurobehavioral domain.(1,2) In major
      depressive disorder (MDD), low reward motivation is a key aspect of anhedonia, a cardinal
      symptom of MDD, and is related to resistance to treatment.(2,3) Although much has been
      learned about reward motivation's neurobiology and relevance to psychopathology, important
      gaps in our knowledge have impeded the application of basic science findings to improving
      treatment of MDD. Reward motivation in healthy subjects involves ventrostriatal (VST)
      dopamine (DA)(4,5), and reduced reward motivation is linked to MDD and anhedonia.(3,6) These
      data suggest that VST DA dysfunction might be present in MDD and manifested clinically by
      anhedonia. While DA neuroreceptor imaging studies have failed to verify this, they have been
      methodologically compromised. Limitations include imaging methods with poor resolution of
      functional striatal subregions, MDD samples heterogeneous for antidepressant use, and use of
      self-report measures of anhedonia, rather than objective behavioral testing of the specific
      domain of reward motivation. This will be the first study of both VST DA release (by PET
      imaging) and reward motivation, and will include patients with MDD and healthy volunteers.
      Reward motivation will be captured and operationalized as reward learning in a probabilistic
      reward task (prior to imaging). This will clarify if VST DA dysfunction is linked to
      impaired motivation in MDD. To test clinical implications in MDD patients, we will assess
      the relationship of VST DA release, reward motivation, and anhedonia to outcome of
      subsequent open label treatment with the DA D2 receptor agonist pramipexole.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Snaith Hamilton Pleasure Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Temporal Experience of Pleasure Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Mood and Anxiety Symptom Questionnaire, Short Form</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Apathy Evaluation Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Items on Side Effect Checklist</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Noting any side effects</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Improvement - Change Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pramipexole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Six weeks of treatment with oral pramipexole, initiated at 0.25 mg/day and titrated to a maximum daily dose of 2.5 mg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pramipexole</intervention_name>
    <description>Dose will be started at 0.125 mg bid, and increased by 0.25 mg/day every 3-4 days to a target range of 1.0 - 2.5 mg/day</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pramipexole</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Mirapex (brand name)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Weight between 44 kg and 115 kg

          -  Meets DSM-IV criteria for principal diagnosis of MDD, current major depressive
             episode, without psychotic features

          -  Score of &gt;16 and &lt;29 on 17-item Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression

          -  Psychotropic-naïve, as defined by lifetime &lt;2 weeks treatment with antidepressants,
             anxiolytics or antipsychotics

          -  Able to tolerate a treatment-free period during study participation

          -  Able to provide informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A principal diagnosis of any current Axis I psychiatric disorder other than the MDD

          -  Lifetime diagnosis of any psychotic disorder, bipolar disorder, mental retardation,
             attention deficit/hyperactivity disorder, or substance use disorders (including
             nicotine use disorders)

          -  Serious suicidal risk or history of violent behavior which would make participation
             in the protocol unsafe

          -  Any tobacco use in the prior three months (if not already excluded for
             abuse/dependence by #1)

          -  Illicit drug use in the prior three months, as evidenced by history or urine
             toxicology screen

          -  Women who are pregnant, nursing, postmenopausal, or using hormonal methods of birth
             control

          -  Women who are not using an effective birth control method or sexual abstinence during
             the ten days before the scan

          -  Any medical or neurological problem that might affect interpretation of findings or
             safety of participation (e.g., blood dyscrasias, lymphomas, hypersplenism,
             endocrinopathies, renal failure or chronic obstructive lung disease, malignancy,
             neurological diseases of the brain, history of seizures or head trauma), low
             hemoglobin (Hb &lt; 12 gm/dL in males, Hb &lt; 10.5 gm/dL in females))

          -  Blood donation within 4 weeks of study

          -  Metal implants or paramagnetic objects in the body that might affect safety of
             undergoing MRI (e.g., heart pacemaker, shrapnel, bullets, surgical prostheses or
             surgical clips), as determined in consultation with a neuroradiologist and according
             to the guidelines set forth in the reference: &quot;Guide to MR procedures and metallic
             objects&quot; Shellock; Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, NY, 2001

          -  More than one major risk factor for coronary artery disease (e.g. hyperlipidemia,
             sedentary lifestyle). Smokers are already excluded by #4 above, and diabetics by #8
             above

          -  Systolic blood pressure &gt; 140 or diastolic blood pressure &gt; 90 based on at least two
             readings at rest

          -  History of untoward reaction to amphetamine or other stimulant medication, or
             pramipexole

          -  Any psychotropic treatment in the past 3 weeks (or depot medication in the past 6
             months), except for lorazepam,which may be administered as needed prior to imaging
             day

          -  Current, past or anticipated exposure to radiation in the workplace, or participation
             in nuclear medicine procedures, including research protocols (In case of previous
             exposure to activity due to research studies, subjects will be eligible if all
             conditions listed below are fulfilled: 1) The injected dose and dosimetry of the
             radiotracer are known; 2) Except for research studies, the subject has not been
             exposed to radiation (workplace and medical); 3) Adding prior exposure to the
             exposure due to the study will result in a yearly cumulative exposure lower than the
             FDA limit for research studies

          -  Family history of schizophrenia in parents, siblings, or children

          -  Ongoing cognitive-behavioral or interpersonal psychotherapy for depression
             (Supportive therapy is not an exclusion)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Franklin Schneier, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NYSPI</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Franklin Schneier, MD</last_name>
    <phone>646-774-8041</phone>
    <email>Fschneier@nyspi.columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York State Psychiatric Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Franklin Schneier, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sanislow CA, Pine DS, Quinn KJ, Kozak MJ, Garvey MA, Heinssen RK, Wang PS, Cuthbert BN. Developing constructs for psychopathology research: research domain criteria. J Abnorm Psychol. 2010 Nov;119(4):631-9. doi: 10.1037/a0020909. PubMed PMID: 20939653.</citation>
    <PMID>20939653</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Treadway MT, Zald DH. Reconsidering anhedonia in depression: lessons from translational neuroscience. Neurosci Biobehav Rev. 2011 Jan;35(3):537-55. doi: 10.1016/j.neubiorev.2010.06.006. Epub 2010 Jul 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20603146</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vrieze E, Pizzagalli DA, Demyttenaere K, Hompes T, Sienaert P, de Boer P, Schmidt M, Claes S. Reduced reward learning predicts outcome in major depressive disorder. Biol Psychiatry. 2013 Apr 1;73(7):639-45. doi: 10.1016/j.biopsych.2012.10.014. Epub 2012 Dec 8.</citation>
    <PMID>23228328</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Forbes EE, Hariri AR, Martin SL, Silk JS, Moyles DL, Fisher PM, Brown SM, Ryan ND, Birmaher B, Axelson DA, Dahl RE. Altered striatal activation predicting real-world positive affect in adolescent major depressive disorder. Am J Psychiatry. 2009 Jan;166(1):64-73. doi: 10.1176/appi.ajp.2008.07081336. Epub 2008 Dec 1.</citation>
    <PMID>19047324</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kumar P, Waiter G, Ahearn T, Milders M, Reid I, Steele JD. Abnormal temporal difference reward-learning signals in major depression. Brain. 2008 Aug;131(Pt 8):2084-93. doi: 10.1093/brain/awn136. Epub 2008 Jun 25.</citation>
    <PMID>18579575</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pizzagalli DA, Iosifescu D, Hallett LA, Ratner KG, Fava M. Reduced hedonic capacity in major depressive disorder: evidence from a probabilistic reward task. J Psychiatr Res. 2008 Nov;43(1):76-87. doi: 10.1016/j.jpsychires.2008.03.001. Epub 2008 Apr 22.</citation>
    <PMID>18433774</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 19, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 9, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Major depressive disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>MDD</keyword>
  <keyword>depression</keyword>
  <keyword>pramipexole</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dopamine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pramipexol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
