<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="121023">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01884571</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013P000981</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NIP-ALS-2013</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01884571</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immunosuppression in Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis (ALS)</brief_title>
  <acronym>NIPALS2013</acronym>
  <official_title>A Novel Immunosuppression Intervention for the Treatment of Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis (ALS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>ALS Association</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Data and Safety Monitoring Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multicenter, 15-month study evaluating the effect of immunosuppression treatment
      on the rate of change on the ALS Functional Rating Scale (Revised) (ALSFRS-R) score in up to
      33 subjects with Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis (ALS).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In an ongoing safety trial of neural stem cell injections into the spinal cord of patients
      with ALS at Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia, one patient has demonstrated clear
      improvement by objective clinical and electrophysiological measures, a finding that is
      unheard of in patients with ALS.

      This patient had an improvement in ALSFRS-R by 1.4 points per month.  In 826 historical
      controls from the Northeast ALS Consortium (NEALS) and the Western ALS Consortium (WALS)
      database where ALSFRS-R was documented at 2 or more visits, there have been no patients that
      have shown improvement in ALSFRS as seen in this case.  Additionally, 5 patients in the stem
      cell trial who were not on mechanical ventilators at the time of surgery seem to have very
      slow disease progression as compared to the expectation from current understanding of
      typical disease course.  This observation raises consideration for a disease-modifying
      effect of the novel immunosuppression regimen used in this trial.  Also, given that ALS is
      clinically an extraordinarily heterogeneous disease, the diagnosis of ALS may represent a
      group of phenotypically similar but pathogenically variable disorders.  It is possible that
      there exists a subset of patients with an immune-responsive ALS subtype that has not been
      previously recognized.

      Recent studies have furthered the understanding of the immune mechanisms that contribute to
      ALS progression.  Microglia and lymphocytes have both neurotoxic and neuroprotective
      functions depending on activation states and physiologic conditions within the nervous
      system.  Therefore, targeted immunotherapies that proportionally suppress neurotoxic immune
      elements, while sparing or promoting protective elements, seemingly have more potential to
      modify disease course in ALS than previously tested regimens.  It is postulated that the
      immunosuppression treatment given to the stem cell patients may have exhibited
      neuroprotective effects by favorably promoting the ratio of regulatory T cells and other
      protective immune mediators in relation to neurotoxic immune modulators.  It is hoped that
      this trial will optimize the chance of replicating these findings and allow the learning
      more about the complex changes that occur within the immune system in patients with ALS
      before and after treatment with an immunosuppression regimen.

      The primary objective of this study is to assess the clinical response rate of a novel
      immunosuppression regimen in a subset of ALS patients.

      The primary outcome measure will be rate of change of ALSFRS-R.  A clinical response will be
      defined as a rate of change of ALSFRS-R of +6 points over a 6 month period (mean of change
      of +1 point per month).

      Secondary outcome measures will include slow vital capacity (SVC), grip strength, and hand
      held dynamometry (HHD).  The change in rate of progression in clinical measures will be
      monitored to look for a potential disease-modifying effect of the immunosuppression regimen.
      Blood and cerebrospinal fluid immune system markers will be also be studied.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis Functional Rating Scale - Revised (ALSFRS-R)</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening, Baseline Visits 1, 2, and 3, Day 1, Months 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8 ,10 , and 12, and at the Final Safety Visit, if a subject discontinues study drug early.  Telephone ALSFRS-R will be collected at Months 7, 9 and 11.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Revised ALS Functional Rating Scale - Revised (ALSFRS-R) is an ordinal rating scale (0 through 4) used to determine the ALS patient's self assessment of their ability and need for assistance in 12 activities or functions. This is a validated scale, both in person and by phone, which provides a total score (best of 48) from four sub-scores which assess speech and swallowing, (bulbar function), use of upper extremities (cervical function), gait and turning in bed (lumbar function), and breathing (respiratory function). A clinical response will be defined as a rate of change of ALSFRS-R of +6 points over 6 months (mean of +1 point per month), where typically patients with ALS have a decline in ALSFRS-R by an average of -1/month.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Slow Vital Capacity (SVC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening, Baseline Visits 1, 2, and 3, Day 1, Months 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8 ,10 , and 12, and at the Final Safety Visit, if a subject discontinues study drug early.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Vital capacity (VC), percent of predicted normal, will be determined using the slow VC method.  SVC measures the amount of air exhaled following a deep breath.  For this test, participants will hold a mouthpiece in their mouth, breathe in deeply, and breathe out as much air as they can.  The test will be done  seated in a chair and then repeated while e lying on an exam table at the Screening Visit.  For all other visits, this test will be done with seated in a chair.  This test will take 15-20 minutes. At the Screening visit, eligibility for Group A will be determined utilizing upright SVC.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Hand-Held Dynamometry (HHD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline Visits 1, 2, and 3, Day 1, Months 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8 ,10 , and 12, and at the Final Safety Visit, if a subject discontinues study drug early.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Hand held dynamometry (HHD) will be used as a quantitative measure of muscle strength for this study.  Six proximal muscle groups will be examined bilaterally in both upper and lower extremities (shoulder flexion, elbow flexion, elbow extension, hip flexion, knee flexion, and knee extension), all of which have been validated against maximum voluntary isometric contraction (MVIC) testing. In addition, wrist extension, first dorsal interosseous contraction and ankle dorsiflexion will be measured bilaterally; these muscles are often affected in Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Cytokine levels in Cerebrospinal Fluid (CSF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline Visit 2 and Months 2, 6 and 12.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Lumbar punctures (LPs) will be done to collect cerebrospinal fluid in order to characterize markers of the participants immune system and further the understanding of the immune factors that contribute to disease progression in ALS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Collection of peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) in Blood</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline Visit 2, Day 1, Months 1, 2, 4, 6, 8 and 12, and at the Final Safety Visit if a subject discontinues study drug early.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood will be drawn in order to characterize markers of the participants immune system and further the understanding of the immune factors that contribute to disease progression in ALS.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Left Grip Strength</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline Visits 1, 2, and 3, Day 1, Months 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8 ,10 , and 12, and at the Final Safety Visit, if a subject discontinues study drug early.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Left hand grip will be measured using a study approved dynamometer to test the maximum isometric strength of the hand and forearm muscles.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Right Grip Strength</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline Visits 1, 2, and 3, Day 1, Months 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8 ,10 , and 12, and at the Final Safety Visit, if a subject discontinues study drug early.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Right Hand grip will be measured using a study approved dynamometer to test the maximum isometric strength of the hand and forearm muscles.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Antibody levels in Cerebrospinal Fluid (CSF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline Visit 2 and Months 2, 6 and 12.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Lumbar punctures (LPs) will be done to collect cerebrospinal fluid in order to characterize markers of the participants immune system and further the understanding of the immune factors that contribute to disease progression in ALS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Collection of Ribonucleic Acid (RNA) in Blood</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline Visit 2, Day 1, and Months 1, 2, 4, 6, 8 and 12, and at the Final Safety Visit if a subject discontinues study drug early</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood will be collected for ribonucleic acid (RNA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis (ALS)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Immunosuppression Regiment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Basiliximab Methylprednisolone Prednisone Tacrolimus Mycophenolate mofetil</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Basiliximab</intervention_name>
    <description>20 mg, IV (in the vein) on day 1 and 4.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immunosuppression Regiment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Simulect</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methylprednisolone</intervention_name>
    <description>125 mg, IV (in the vein) on day 1.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immunosuppression Regiment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Solumedrol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prednisone</intervention_name>
    <description>60 mg PO (by mouth) on days 2-7, 40 mg PO days 8-14, 20 mg PO days 15-21, and 10mg PO days 22-28.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immunosuppression Regiment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tacrolimus</intervention_name>
    <description>1-5 mg PO, BID (twice a day) days 2-180.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immunosuppression Regiment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Prograf</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mycophenolate mofetil</intervention_name>
    <description>500 mg PO, BID days 2-7, 500 mg PO each morning and 1000 mg each night, days 8-14, 1000 mg PO BID days 15-180.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immunosuppression Regiment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cellcept</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Group A Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female patients 18-65 years of age.

          -  ALS diagnosed as possible, laboratory-supported probable, probable, or definite as
             defined by revised El Escorial Criteria.

          -  Symptom onset ≤ 24 months from screening visit.

          -  A score of ≥38 on the Revised ALS Functional Rating Scale.

          -  Slow vital capacity (SVC) measure &gt;80% of predicted for gender, height and age at
             screening.

          -  Subjects must not have taken riluzole for at least 30 days, or be on a stable dose of
             riluzole for at least 30 days, prior to the screening visit (riluzole-naïve subjects
             are permitted in the study).

          -  Negative tuberculosis (TB) test within 3 months of Screening Visit.

          -  Subjects medically able to undergo lumbar puncture (LP) as determined by the
             investigator (i.e., no bleeding disorder, allergy to local anesthetics, or a skin
             infection at or near the LP site).

          -  Capable of providing informed consent and following study procedures.

          -  Women must not be able to become pregnant (e.g. post menopausal, surgically sterile,
             or using adequate birth control methods) for the duration of the study.

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test at   screening
             and be non-lactating.

          -  Geographic accessibility to the study site.

        Group B Inclusion Criteria

          -  Male or female patients age 18 or older.

          -  ALS diagnosed as possible, laboratory-supported probable, probable, or definite as
             defined by revised El Escorial Criteria.

          -  Symptom onset &gt;24 months from screening visit.

          -  Subjects must not have taken riluzole for at least 30 days, or be on a stable dose of
             riluzole for at least 30 days, prior to the screening visit (riluzole-naïve subjects
             are permitted in the study).

          -  Negative tuberculosis (TB) test within 3 months of Screening Visit.

          -  Subjects medically able to undergo lumbar puncture (LP) as determined by the
             investigator (i.e., no bleeding disorder, allergy to local anesthetics, or a skin
             infection at or near the LP site).

          -  Capable of providing informed consent and following study procedures.

          -  Geographic accessibility to the study site.

          -  Women must not be able to become pregnant (e.g. post menopausal, surgically sterile,
             or using adequate birth control methods) for the duration of the study.

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test at   screening
             and be non-lactating.

        Group A &amp; B Exclusion Criteria

          -  Prior use of basiliximab, solumedrol, prednisone, tacrolimus or mycophenolate mofetil
             within 30 days of the Screening Visit.

          -  Known allergy or sensitivity to basiliximab, solumedrol, prednisone, tacrolimus or
             mycophenolate mofetil or a formulation of one of these drugs.

          -  Treatment with an immunosuppressant medication within 30 days of the Screening Visit.

          -  Active peptic ulcer disease.

          -  Any medical disorder that would make immunosuppression contraindicated including, but
             not limited to, human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), tuberculosis, or evidence of
             active cytomegalovirus (CMV) or infection.

          -  Subjects who have a diaphragm pacing system (DPS).

          -  Women who are pregnant, breastfeeding, or planning to become pregnant in the next 12
             months.

          -  Active drug or alcohol use or dependence that, in the opinion of the site
             investigator, would interfere with adherence to study requirements.

          -  Use of invasive or non-invasive mechanical ventilation (including Continuous Positive
             Airway Pressure (CPAP) or Bi-level Positive Airway Pressure (BiPAP)) for any part of
             the day or night prior to the Screening Visit (Group A only).

          -  Exposure to any other agent currently under investigation for the treatment of
             patients with ALS (off-label use or investigational) within 30 days of the Screening
             Visit.

          -  Inability to safely complete study activities based on the discretion of the site
             investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jonathan D Glass, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christina N Fournier, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Katelyn Gilardi</last_name>
    <phone>617-724-5984</phone>
    <email>kgilardi@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alyssa Murphy</last_name>
      <phone>617-724-9196</phone>
      <email>AMURPHY22@PARTNERS.ORG</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James D Berry, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Massachusetts Medical School</name>
      <address>
        <city>Worcester</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>01655</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Diane McKenna-Yasek, RN, BSN</last_name>
      <phone>508-856-4697</phone>
      <email>Diane.McKenna-Yasek@umassmed.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert Brown, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Colin C Quinn, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.alsconsortium.org/</url>
    <description>Northeast ALS Consortium Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 16, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 19, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Emory University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jonathan D. Glass, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Emory ALS Clinic</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Immunosuppression</keyword>
  <keyword>ALS</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Motor Neuron Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone Hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycophenolic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycophenolate mofetil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tacrolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Basiliximab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
