<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="67299">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02109939</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ARX1006</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02109939</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of GeneSight Psychotropic on Response to Psychotropic Treatment in Outpatients Suffering From a Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) and Having Had an Inadequate Response to at Least One Psychotropic Medication Included in GeneSight Psychotropic</brief_title>
  <acronym>RCT</acronym>
  <official_title>A 12-Week, Randomized, Double-Blind, Controlled Evaluation Followed by an Open-Label 12-Week Follow-up Period of the Impact of GeneSight Psychotropic on Response to Psychotropic Treatment in Outpatients Suffering From a Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) and Having Had - Within the Current Episode - an Inadequate Response to at Least One Psychotropic Medication Included in GeneSight Psychotropic</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AssureRx Health, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AssureRx Health, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>USA: INC Research</authority>
    <authority>USA: Copernicus Group IRB</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Evaluate the impact of GeneSight Psychotropic on response to psychotropic treatment as
      judged by the mean change in the 17-item Hamilton Depression (HAM-D17) score from baseline
      to end of Week 8 of the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Major depressive disorder (MDD) is a highly prevalent (Hasin et al., 2005) mental disorder
      and a leading source of disease burden worldwide (Lopez et al., 2006). Epidemiological
      studies estimate 12-month and lifetime prevalence for MDD in the United States to be 5.3%
      and 13.2%, respectively (reviewed in Blanco et al., 2010). MDD is expected to be the second
      greatest cause of disability by 2020 and has been shown to cause significant morbidity,
      affecting people's ability to work, function in relationships, and engage in social
      activities. Moreover, MDD increases the risk of suicidal ideation, attempted suicide, and
      death by completed suicide.

      Prospective longitudinal studies of patient samples show that MDD is a chronic illness,
      characterized by remitting and recurrent depressive episodes (Solomon et al., 1997; Mueller
      et al., 1999). A major depressive episode is characterized by a low mood or an inability to
      experience pleasure (anhedonia), or both, for more than 2 weeks, combined with several
      cognitive and vegetative symptoms and the occurrence of distress or impairment (reviewed in
      Rot et al., 2009). In the US, nearly 1 in 5 people will experience a major depressive
      episode at some point in their lives (reviewed in Rot et al., 2009). Drugs currently
      available to treat depression fall into the categories of those that have their main effect
      by increasing norepinephrine (NE) (the tricyclic or tetracyclic antidepressants [TCAs]),
      those that increase serotonin (5-HT) (the selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors [SSRIs]),
      and those that increase both NE and 5-HT (the monoamine oxidase inhibitors [MAOIs] and the
      serotonin and norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors [SNRIs]). While all antidepressants achieve
      similar levels of efficacy, treatment failures are relatively high ranging from 30 to 60%
      (Simpson and DePaulo). Additionally, many of these compounds are associated with significant
      adverse events (AEs).

      The GeneSight Psychotropic product is a pharmacogenomic decision support tool that helps
      clinicians to make informed, evidence-based decisions about proper drug selection, based on
      the testing for clinically important genetic variants in multiple pharmacokinetic and
      pharmacodynamic genes that affect a patient's ability to tolerate or respond to medications.

      The GeneSight Psychotropic product contains the most commonly prescribed antidepressant and
      antipsychotic medications, including a full representation of the SSRI and SNRI drug
      classes.

      Tricyclic antidepressants, an MAOI, and typical and atypical antipsychotics are also
      represented.

      The clinical utility of GeneSight Psychotropic has been evaluated in three previous
      prospective trials. Hall-Flavin et al reported the results of an open-label pilot study (n =
      44) comparing GeneSight guided treatment to treatment as usual (TAU) without the benefit of
      pharmacogenomic testing (2012). The GeneSight guided arm demonstrated a 30.8% improvement in
      HAM-D17 score by the end of the 8 week treatment period, compared to an 18.2% improvement in
      the TAU arm (p = 0.04). Results of the larger (n = 165) open-label trial (Hall-Flavin, et al
      2013) mirrored these findings, demonstrating a 46.9% improvement in HAMD17 score in the
      GeneSight arm, compared to a 29.9% improvement in the TAU arm (p &lt; 0.0001). The third trial
      used a randomized, double-blind trial design (n = 51). Due to the small sample size, the
      trial was underpowered to detect a significant difference in improvement between the two
      arms (TAU and GeneSight). However, effect sizes of improvement reflected those seen in
      previous trials. The GeneSight group experienced a 30.8% improvement in HAMD17, compared to
      20.7% in TAU. Odds ratios for response were calculated, showing that GeneSight-guided
      subjects had a 2.14 times greater likelihood of response compared to TAU subjects, which was
      similar to the 4.67 (smaller trial) and 2.06 (larger trial) odds ratios calculated for the
      other two studies.

      Previous studies utilizing an open-label design have shown significant improvement in
      patient outcomes following use of the GeneSight test. However, although effect sizes were
      similar to those seen in the open-label studies, a small (n = 51) blinded, randomized
      controlled trial did not detect a statistically significant outcome. Therefore, the primary
      rationale for this trial is to replicate previous findings of improvement in clinical
      outcomes in subjects treated with the benefit of GeneSight testing utilizing a double-blind,
      randomized control trial (RCT) design.

      It is expected that results from this trial will be used to inform guidelines for the use of
      pharmacogenomic testing for the treatment of major depressive disorder. Results may also be
      shared with regulatory bodies in the United States and abroad.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>17-item Hamilton Depression (HAM-D17) score</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of Week 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluate the impact of GeneSight Psychotropic on response to psychotropic treatment as judged by the mean change in the 17-item Hamilton Depression (HAM-D17) score from baseline to end of Week 8 of the study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>16-item Quick Inventory of Depression Symptomology (QIDS-C16) scale</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of Week 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Mean change in the 16-item Quick Inventory of Depression Symptomology (QIDS-C16) scale or the 9-item Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9) from baseline to end of Week 8 of the study;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of responders at Week 8 for HAM-D17</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of responders at Week 8 in each treatment group on the HAM-D17. A responder is defined as a participant with 50% change from baseline in total scale score;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of responders at Week 12 for HAM-D17</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of responders at Week 12 (defined as above) in each treatment group on the HAM-D17</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of remitters at Week 12 defined as HAM-D17 ≤7</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of remitters at Week 12 defined as HAM-D17 ≤7</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of remitters at Week 8 defined as HAM-D17 ≤7 in each treatment group;</measure>
    <time_frame>week 8 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of remitters at Week 8 defined as HAM-D17 ≤7 in each treatment group;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to response/remission of depressive symptoms over 8 weeks;</measure>
    <time_frame>week 8 and 12 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Time to response/remission of depressive symptoms over 8 weeks;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in symptoms from baseline to week 24 across all scales in each treatment group.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 24 visits</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Mean change in symptoms from baseline to week 24 across all scales in each treatment group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of responders at Week 8 for QIDS-C16</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of responders at Week 8 in each treatment group on the QIDS-C16. A responder is defined as a participant with 50% change from baseline in total scale score;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of responders at Week 8 for PHQ-9</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of responders at Week 8 in each treatment group on the PHQ-9. A responder is defined as a participant with 50% change from baseline in total scale score;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of remitters at Week 12 defined as QIDS-C16 ≤5</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of remitters at Week 12 defined as QIDS-C16 ≤5</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of remitters at Week 12 defined as PHQ-9 &lt;5</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of remitters at Week 12 defined as PHQ-9 &lt;5</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of remitters at Week 12 defined as CGI-S ≤1</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of remitters at Week 12 defined as CGI-S ≤1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of responders at Week 12 for QIDS-C16</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of responders at Week 12 (defined as above) in each treatment group on the QIDS-C16</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of responders at Week 12 for PHQ-9</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of responders at Week 12 (defined as above) in each treatment group on the PHQ-9</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of responders at Week 12 for CGI-S</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of responders at Week 12 (defined as above) in each treatment group on the CGI-S (defined as a change in category of severity of at least 1 point),</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of responders at Week 12 for CGI-I</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of responders at Week 12 (defined as above) in each treatment group on the Clinical Global Impression of Improvement (CGI-I; defined as a score from 1 to 3),</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of responders at Week 12 for CGI-EI</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of responders at Week 12 (defined as above) in each treatment group on the Clinical Global Impression of Efficacy (CGI-EI; defined as a scores of 01, 02, 05, or 06);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of remitters at Week 8 defined as QIDS-C16 ≤5 in each treatment group;</measure>
    <time_frame>week 8 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of remitters at Week 8 defined as QIDS-C16 ≤5 in each treatment group;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of remitters at Week 8 defined as PHQ-9 &lt;5 in each treatment group;</measure>
    <time_frame>week 8 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of remitters at Week 8 defined as PHQ-9 &lt;5 in each treatment group;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to response/remission of depressive symptoms over 12 weeks;</measure>
    <time_frame>week 8 and 12 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Time to response/remission of depressive symptoms over 12 weeks;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean percent response from baseline to week 24 across all scales in each treatment group.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 24 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Mean percent response from baseline to week 24 across all scales in each treatment group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean percent remission from baseline to week 24 across all scales in each treatment group.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 24 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Mean percent remission from baseline to week 24 across all scales in each treatment group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in symptoms from week 12 to week 24 across all scales in each treatment group.</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12 to 24 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Mean change in symptoms from week 12 to week 24 across all scales in each treatment group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean percent response from week 12 to week 24 across all scales in each treatment group.</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12 to 24 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Mean percent response from week 12 to week 24 across all scales in each treatment group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in percent remission from week 12 to week 24 across all scales in each treatment group.</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12 to 24 visit info</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Mean change in percent remission from week 12 to week 24 across all scales in each treatment group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder (MDD)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GeneSight Psychotropic Tested</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects being tested with GeneSight Psychotropic</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment As Usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group of subjects will not see their GeneSIght results or know whether or not they are in either arm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GeneSight Psychotropic</intervention_name>
    <description>The GeneSight Psychotropic product is a pharmacogenomic decision support tool that helps clinicians to make informed, evidence-based decisions about proper drug selection, based on the testing for clinically important genetic variants in multiple pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic genes that affect a patient's ability to tolerate or respond to medications.
The GeneSight Psychotropic product contains the most commonly prescribed antidepressant and antipsychotic medications, including a full representation of the SSRI and SNRI drug classes.
tricyclic antidepressants, an MAOI, and typical and atypical antipsychotics are also represented.</description>
    <arm_group_label>GeneSight Psychotropic Tested</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment As Usual</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Assurex Health</other_name>
    <other_name>GeneSight</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Be able to understand the requirements of the study and provide written informed
             consent to participate in this study; a signed and dated ICF will be obtained from
             each patient before participation in the study;

          -  Have provided written authorization for the use and disclosure of their protected
             health information;

          -  Be ≥18 years of age;

          -  Suffer from a Major Depressive Episode meeting DSM-IV-TR criteria;

          -  Have had an inadequate response within the current episode to at least 1 psychotropic
             treatment. Inadequate response is defined as inadequate efficacy after 6 weeks of a
             psychotropic treatment or discontinuation of a psychotropic treatment due to AEs or
             intolerability;

          -  Have a total baseline score on the QIDS-C16 and QIDS-SR16 rating scale ≥11;

          -  Agree to abide by the study protocol and its restrictions and be able to complete all
             aspects of the study, including all visits and tests.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients posing a serious suicidal risk and/or in need of immediate hospitalization
             as judged by the investigator;

          -  Patients with a diagnosis of Bipolar I or II disorder;

          -  Patients with a current Axis I diagnosis of:

               1. Delirium

               2. Dementia

               3. Amnestic and other cognitive disorder

               4. Schizophrenia or other psychotic disorder;

          -  Patients having experienced hallucinations, delusions, or any psychotic
             symptomatology within the current depressive episode or during prior depressive
             episodes;

          -  Patient is currently in an inpatient facility;

          -  Patients with a history of hypothyroidism unless taking a stable dose of thyroid
             medication and asymptomatic or euthyroid for 6 months;

          -  Patients who meet DSM-IV-TR criteria for any significant current substance use
             disorder;

          -  Patients with significant unstable medical condition; life threatening disease;
             hepatic insufficiency (3X ULN for AST and/or ALT); liver transplant recipient;
             cirrhosis of the liver; need for therapies that may obscure the results of treatment
             and/or of the study; malignancy (except basal cell carcinoma) and/or chemotherapy
             within 1 year prior to screening; malignancy more than 1 year prior to screening must
             have been local and without metastasis and/or recurrence, and if treated with
             chemotherapy, without nervous system complications;

          -  Participation in another clinical trial within 30 days of the screening visit;

          -  Anticipated inability to attend scheduled study visits;

          -  Patients who in the judgment of the Investigator may be unreliable or uncooperative
             with the evaluation procedure outlined in this protocol;

          -  Patients with a history of prior pharmacogenomic testing;

          -  Any change in psychotropic medication (including change in dosage) between screening
             and randomization;

          -  Patients receiving ECT, DBS or TMS treatment (should a Subject receive any of these
             treatments they must be discontinued from the study);

          -  Patients who are known to be pregnant or lactating;

          -  Patients with a history of gastric bypass surgery.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Greden, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amanda Martin</last_name>
    <phone>215-923-3853</phone>
    <email>amanda.martin@incresearch.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alabama at Birmingham</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35233</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard Shelton, MD</last_name>
      <phone>205-975-3442</phone>
      <email>rshelton@uab.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Richard Shelton, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Leah Pickett, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rachel Fargason, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Li Li, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Synergy Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Escondido</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92025</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Charmaine Semeniuk, MD</last_name>
      <phone>760-871-0286</phone>
      <email>semeniukc@synergyescondido.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Charmaine Semeniuk, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gregory Paniccia, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pharmacology Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Alamitos</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90720</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nader Oskooilar, MD</last_name>
      <phone>714-827-3667</phone>
      <email>noskooilar@priresearch.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nader Oskooilar, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jeffrey Litzinger, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Atlanta Institute of Medicine and Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30328</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Angelo Sambunaris, MD</last_name>
      <phone>770-817-9200</phone>
      <email>a.sambunaris@atlanta-institute.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Angelo Sambunaris, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Melvin McInnis</last_name>
      <email>mmcinnis@med.umich.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Eastside Comprehensive Medical Center, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ram Shrivastava, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-288-0138</phone>
      <email>drramshrivastava@aol.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ram Shrivastava, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Midwest Clinical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dayton</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45417</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bernadette D'Souza, MD</last_name>
      <phone>937-424-1050</phone>
      <email>bdsouza@midwestclinical.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bernadette D'Souza, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Otto Dueno, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jeffrey Bishop, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oklahoma Clinical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marvin L Peyton, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>405-753-4994</phone>
      <email>drpeyton@okcrc.net</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marvin L Peyton, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Frontier Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Spokane</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>99204</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John Tran, MD</last_name>
      <phone>509-710-8750</phone>
      <email>jtranfi@smhca.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Tran, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Melody Stupey, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 4, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>MDD</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacogenomic</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacogenomic Testing</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacogenomics</keyword>
  <keyword>Genetic Testing</keyword>
  <keyword>Genetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Major Depressive Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>GeneSight</keyword>
  <keyword>Assurex</keyword>
  <keyword>AssureRx</keyword>
  <keyword>Psychotropic</keyword>
  <keyword>Randomized</keyword>
  <keyword>Double Blind</keyword>
  <keyword>Placebo Controlled</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress, Psychological</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Psychotropic Drugs</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
