<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="149708">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01958788</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MOP-69066-620</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01958788</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Testing Beliefs About Uncertainty in the Treatment of Generalized Anxiety Disorder</brief_title>
  <official_title>Beliefs About Uncertainty: Development and Evaluation of a Novel Cognitive-behavioural Treatment for Generalized Anxiety Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Concordia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hopital du Sacre-Coeur de Montreal</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Concordia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Canadian Institutes of Health Research</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Generalized Anxiety Disorder (GAD) is an anxiety disorder characterized by excessive and
      uncontrollable worry. Our research group has developed a cognitive-behavioural treatment
      (CBT) for GAD centered upon intolerance of uncertainty, a dispositional characteristic that
      arises from a set of negative beliefs about uncertainty and its consequences (Dugas &amp;
      Robichaud, 2007). This CBT protocol has demonstrated good efficacy over four previous
      clinical trials: approximately 70% of participants fully remit from GAD following treatment
      and maintain these gains over extended follow-up periods. These results, while positive, do
      suggest that a substantial minority of individuals do not fully benefit from the existing
      treatment protocol. Across our randomized clinical trials, individuals who do not achieve
      diagnostic remission of GAD continue to endorse elevated levels of intolerance of
      uncertainty. This suggests that the current CBT protocol does not effectively reduce
      intolerance of uncertainty in some treated individuals. To address this, we have developed a
      modified version of the original CBT protocol that targets intolerance of uncertainty more
      directly. The goal of the current proposal is to determine whether this newly developed CBT
      protocol with fewer components can deliver comparable or superior GAD symptom reduction. A
      total of 10 participants with a primary diagnosis of GAD will receive the newly developed
      CBT protocol over 10 weekly sessions. Measures of GAD symptoms, psychopathology, and
      intolerance of uncertainty will be administered at pre-, mid-, and post-treatment, as well
      as at 3- and 6-month follow-ups. The proposed study will provide information about the
      efficacy, clinical utility, and potential mechanisms of change in GAD symptoms in this new
      CBT protocol.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Generalized anxiety disorder (GAD) is characterized by excessive and uncontrollable worry
      and anxiety. This common and debilitating anxiety disorder is associated with significant
      distress as well as substantial impairment in occupational, social, and daily functioning.
      As a result, effective treatment for GAD is essential. Several cognitive-behavioural
      treatment (CBT) protocols have been developed for GAD, including an efficacious treatment
      developed by our research group. This CBT protocol for GAD centres upon intolerance of
      uncertainty, a dispositional characteristic that arises from a set of negative beliefs about
      uncertainty and its consequences (Dugas &amp; Robichaud, 2007). Previous research has shown that
      individuals with GAD demonstrate high intolerance of uncertainty, and that there are a
      number of potential pathways by which intolerance of uncertainty may lead to symptoms of GAD
      (see Dugas &amp; Robichaud, 2007 for a review). Our CBT protocol targeting intolerance of
      uncertainty has demonstrated good efficacy across four published randomized clinical trials:
      approximately 70% of participants have fully remitted from GAD following treatment and have
      maintained these gains over extended follow-up periods. These results, while positive, do
      suggest that a substantial minority of individuals do not fully benefit from the existing
      treatment protocol. Across our randomized clinical trials, individuals who do not achieve
      diagnostic remission of GAD continue to endorse elevated levels of intolerance of
      uncertainty. This suggests that the current CBT protocol does not effectively reduce
      intolerance of uncertainty in some treated individuals. Additionally, the existing treatment
      protocol has 6 major components, utilizes a number of cognitive and behavioural techniques
      (including symptom monitoring, motivational interviewing, situational exposure,
      problem-solving training, and imaginal exposure), and requires at least 14 sessions to
      implement. Recent literature (e.g., Cougle et al., 2011) has suggested that there is
      increased need for parsimony and efficiency in CBT protocols. As a result, our research
      group is investigating new methods of targeting intolerance of uncertainty that demonstrate
      greater parsimony and efficiency.

      Our previous CBT protocol for GAD targeted intolerance of uncertainty directly through
      situational exposure, and indirectly through motivational interviewing, problem-solving
      training, and imaginal exposure. In an effort to streamline and strengthen GAD treatment,
      the newly developed CBT protocol will only target intolerance of uncertainty directly. In
      this new CBT protocol, intolerance of uncertainty will be targeted using behavioural
      experiments in which participants identify and test out their beliefs about uncertainty
      (e.g., uncertainty spoils everything). The extant literature suggests that behavioural
      experiments are an efficacious way to target the emotional, cognitive, and behavioural
      components of anxiety disorders and may be superior to habituation-based exposure paradigms
      (McMillan &amp; Lee, 2010; Salkovskis et al., 2007).

      The current study will determine if a newly developed CBT protocol with fewer components can
      deliver comparable or superior GAD symptom reduction. Ten (10) individuals with a primary
      diagnosis of GAD will complete 10 sessions of CBT using a newly developed treatment protocol
      focusing exclusively on intolerance of uncertainty. The treatment will consist of 50-minute,
      weekly sessions targeting intolerance of uncertainty primarily via behavioural experiments.
      The three treatment components include: (1) psychoeducation and uncertainty awareness
      training; (2) testing beliefs about uncertainty (via behavioural experiments); and (3)
      relapse prevention. Measures of GAD symptoms, general psychopathology, and intolerance of
      uncertainty will be administered at pre-, mid-, and post-treatment, as well as at 3- and
      6-month follow-ups. The proposed investigation will provide information about the efficacy,
      clinical utility, and potential mechanisms of change in GAD symptoms in this new CBT
      protocol. The proposed study has the potential to provide similar or greater reductions in
      GAD symptoms while offering superior efficiency and parsimony as compared to our previous
      CBT protocol.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinician's Severity Rating (CSR) scale of Anxiety Disorders Interview Schedule for DSM-IV (ADIS-IV)</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-Treatment (10 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change from baseline in severity of GAD symptoms assessed by structured interview</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Worry and Anxiety Questionnaire (WAQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-treatment (10 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change from baseline in severity of GAD symptoms</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Penn State Worry Questionnaire (PSWQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-treatment (10 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change from baseline in severity of worry</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Generalized Anxiety Disorder - Safety Behaviours Questionnaire (GAD-SBQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-treatment (10 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change from baseline in severity of safety behaviours</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intolerance of Uncertainty Scale (IUS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-treatment (10 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change from baseline in intolerance of uncertainty</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-treatment (10 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change from baseline in somatic anxiety</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beck Depression Inventory, 2nd edition (BDI-II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-treatment (10 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change from baseline in depressive symptoms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Why Worry, 2nd edition (WW-II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-treatment (10 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change from baseline in beliefs about worry</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Negative Problem Orientation Questionnaire (NPOQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-treatment (10 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change from baseline in problem orientation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive Avoidance Questionnaire (CAQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-treatment (10 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change from baseline in cognitive avoidance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Generalized Anxiety Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive-Behavioural Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>10 sessions of cognitive-behavioral treatment targeting negative beliefs about uncertainty</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive-Behavioural Treatment</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive-Behavioural Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Principal diagnosis of GAD

          -  Willingness to keep medication status stable while participating in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Change in medication type or dose in 12 weeks before study entry

          -  Use of herbal products known to have CNS effects in the 2 weeks before study entry

          -  Evidence of suicidal intent

          -  Evidence of current substance abuse

          -  Evidence of current or past schizophrenia, bipolar disorder or organic mental
             disorder

          -  Current participation in other trials

          -  Concurrent psychotherapy during treatment phase of trial

          -  Evidence of anxiety symptoms due to a general medical condition
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elizabeth A Hebert, M.A.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Concordia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michel J Dugas, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>1-819-595-3900</phone>
    <phone_ext>2509</phone_ext>
    <email>michel.dugas@uqo.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Concordia University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H4B 1R6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 7, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 7, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Concordia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Elizabeth A. Hebert</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>M.A., Ph.D. Candidate</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cognitive-behavioral treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Generalized anxiety disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Worry</keyword>
  <keyword>Behavioral experiments</keyword>
  <keyword>Safety behaviors</keyword>
  <keyword>Anxiety</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
