<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="14776">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01665508</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BYS-IT-75</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01665508</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Evaluate Effect of Nebivolol on Angina in Women With Microvascular Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>NIRVANA</acronym>
  <official_title>Nebivolol for the Relief of Microvascular Angina in Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Forest Laboratories</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Women have less significant blockages of coronary arteries, however have greater symptoms
      and worse outcomes compared to their age-matched male counterparts.  This paradox has led to
      the recognition and importance of the microvasculature ( small vessels) as a contributor to
      symptoms and outcomes.  Nebivolol has unique antioxidant properties and dilates blood
      vessels and it is therefore proposed that treatment with nebivolol will reduce angina (chest
      symptoms) in women with microvascular disease as well as improve exercise capacity, reduce
      resource utilization and improve other measures of artery function.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Though women have less obstructive coronary artery disease (CAD) they continue to have a
      greater burden of symptoms, more myocardial ischemia, and a higher rate of adverse outcomes
      than their age-matched male counterparts.  This ostensible paradox has led to the
      recognition of a distinct pathophysiology of ischemic heart disease, in part related to
      microvascular dysfunction, and abnormal coronary reactivity. The term primary microvascular
      angina, (MVA) is used to describe a syndrome among  patients who have symptoms suggestive of
      cardiac ischemia, evidence of electrocardiographic abnormalities, abnormalities on stress
      imaging or a history of ACS, but no evidence of obstructive epicardial coronary disease. In
      this population, microvascular angina causes significant morbidity and in some may
      contribute to increased mortality.

      The treatment of microvascular disease remains empirical due to lack of data regarding
      symptom alleviation, as well as ultimate mortality reduction. Women with ischemic heart
      disease and microvascular angina continue to report more frequent angina and worse quality
      of life. They frequently seek medical attention for the evaluation of cardiovascular
      symptoms including chest pain and shortness of breath.  Consequently, these women incur
      greater healthcare costs, with more office visits, hospitalizations, and myocardial
      infarctions. In fact, more than one half of women without obstructive coronary disease
      continue to have ischemic symptoms that lead to further consumption of CAD resources, most
      often because of diagnostic uncertainty.

      In the absence of robust outcomes data to drive the care of these women with microvascular
      ischemia, various approaches are taken, in addition to the fundamental management of
      baseline risk factors. Some physicians treat these women as they would treat patients with
      known obstructive CAD, while some, in the setting of &quot;open&quot; coronary arteries and persistent
      chest pain, opt for reassurance.  Nevertheless, given that these women with microvascular
      ischemia continue to have higher morbidity and mortality, as well as increased resource
      consumption, there is a widely recognized need for effective therapeutic agents to reduce
      symptoms, improve quality of life, decrease resource consumption, and ultimately reduce
      mortality.

      Nebivolol, due to its unique antioxidant and vasodilator properties, via its effect on NO
      bioactivity, and subsequent effects on the endothelium may be a potentially ideal
      therapeutic agent for the treatment of microvascular angina among women. For example, one
      previous study showed that nebivolol improved exercise parameters, as well as endothelial
      function, more effectively than other beta blockade with metoprolol, among patients with
      persistent angina and non-obstructive coronary disease.

      Cardiopulmonary exercise testing is an ideal diagnostic test in this study as it will
      provide unique information on how microvascular ischemia influences functional capacity as
      measured through sensitive gas exchange parameters.   Because it is known that a distinct
      pathophysiology contributes to microvascular angina among this subset of women, these
      parameters provided by CPET may provide essential information regarding the mechanism of
      symptom mitigation should nebivolol confer therapeutic value.

      Furthermore, because exercise tolerance is often significantly impaired, objective measures
      of gas exchange that reflect submaximum and maximum fitness among these women will be useful
      both at baseline and on nebivolol.

      Peripheral arterial tone and pulse wave analysis will also be performed.  PAT signal
      technology provides a widely validated measurement of endothelium-mediated changes in
      vascular tone, using non-invasive bio-sensors on the fingertips that are elicited by
      creating a down-stream hyperemic response.  This parameter correlates well with endothelial
      dysfunction in coronary arteries.  We will perform endothelial function testing at baseline
      and after 3 months.

      Metabolomics is an emerging field that offers the possibility of using the body's
      metabolites to both phenotype a disease as well as track its response to isolated
      perturbations, such as administration of a drug.   In this study we will utilize
      metabolomics to define signatures of microvascular ischemia as well as nebivolol-mediated
      changes in metabolic profiles.  Baseline metabolic profiling, as well as metabolic profiling
      after 3 months of nebivolol treatment will be performed in this study.

      This type of assessment is an ideal complement to the clinical parameters delineated above
      as it combines targeted mass spectrometry to measures small molecules related to nitric
      oxide metabolism (ie:  arginine, arginosuccinate, citrulline, ornithine, cGMP, ADMA) as well
      as more unbiased screening of metabolites that are not known to be associated with either
      nebivolol exposure or microvascular angina.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Seattle Angina Questionnaire Score</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Seattle Angina Questionnaire (SAQ):
The SAQ is a 5 part survey that is widely used and well validated tool to assess angina stability and angina frequency among patients with coronary artery disease.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>peak VO2      measured by cardiopulmonary exercise testing</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessment of exercise capacity (peak VO2) as determined by CPET, additional fitness parameters will include: VO2 at the anaerobic threshold, peak work-load, time-to-angina, aerobic efficiency and O2 pulse)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>resource utilization questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Resource utilization as determined by patient phone calls, office visits, emergency room visits, and number of hospitalizations, as well an index cost for any hospitalizations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SF36</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 12 week follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>widely used questionnaire used as a measure of health status will be obtained at baseline ( standardized care )  and follow-up  ( 3 months on nebivolol)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Microvascular Angina</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nebivolol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Testing will be performed at baseline (SAQ questionnaire, cardiopulmonary testing, resource utilization, metabolomics and vascular testing).  This will be repeated on the same group of patients after 3 months of nebivolol treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nebivolol</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient to start nebivolol and have repeat testing in 3 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nebivolol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Bystolic</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  women between the ages of 40-80

          -  with evidence of coronary microvascular dysfunction as determined by the presence of
             rest and or exertional chest tightness and a history of either an elevated troponin
             level or positive stress test ( EKG criteria or imaging) , as well as non-obstructive
             coronary artery disease (&lt;50% epicardial obstruction) by either diagnostic
             catheterization with coronary angiography or CT angiography.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women who cannot tolerate a beta blocker.

          -  Women receiving Hormone Replacement Therapy

          -  Women of child-bearing age who are not on a birth-control method.

          -  Women with inability to exercise.

          -  Women with left ventricular systolic dysfunction (LVEF less than 40%)

          -  Women who have a medical condition that, in the Investigator's opinion, would expose
             them to an increased risk of a significant adverse event or interfere with
             assessments of safety and efficacy during the course of the trial.

          -  Women with any current malignancy, or any clinically significant hematological,
             endocrine, cardiovascular, renal, hepatic, gastrointestinal or neurological disease.
             If there is a history of such disease but the condition has been stable for at least
             the past year and is judged by the investigator not to interfere with the patient's
             participation in the study, the patient may be included.

          -  Women who are unable to speak, read, and understand English and are judged by the
             investigator to be unable or unlikely to follow the study protocol and complete all
             scheduled visits.

          -  Women with any contraindications to beta blocker therapy

          -  Women with myocardial bridging

          -  Women with Prinzmetal's angina
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nandita S Scott, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Malissa J Wood, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nandita S Scott, MD</last_name>
    <phone>617 724 1739</phone>
    <email>nsscott@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Malissa J Wood, MD</last_name>
    <phone>617 724 1986</phone>
    <email>mjwood@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nandita S Scott, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-724-1739</phone>
      <email>nsscott@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Aaron Baggish, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Malissa J Wood, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nandita S Scott, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gregory Lewis, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 9, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nandita Scott</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Co-Director Corrigan Women's Heart Health Program</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>angina</keyword>
  <keyword>cardiopulmonary testing</keyword>
  <keyword>metabolomics</keyword>
  <keyword>nebivolol</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Angina Pectoris</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Microvascular Angina</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Nebivolol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
