<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="25259">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02143414</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2014-01047</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2014-01047</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>SWOG-S1318</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>S1318</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>S1318</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U10CA180888</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02143414</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Blinatumomab and Combination Chemotherapy or Dasatinib, Prednisone, and Blinatumomab in Treating Older Patients With Newly Diagnosed Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Blinatumomab (NSC-765986) and POMP (Prednisone, Vincristine, Methotrexate, 6-Mercaptopurine) for Patients ≥ 65 Years of Age With Newly Diagnosed Philadelphia-Chromosome Negative (Ph-) Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL) and of Dasatinib (NSC-732517), Prednisone and Blinatumomab for Patients ≥ 65 Years of Age With Newly Diagnosed Philadelphia-Chromosome Positive (Ph+) ALL</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies the side effects and how well blinatumomab and combination
      chemotherapy or dasatinib, prednisone, and blinatumomab works in treating older patients
      with newly diagnosed acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Monoclonal antibodies, such as
      blinatumomab, find cancer cells and help kill them. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as
      prednisone, vincristine sulfate, methotrexate, and mercaptopurine, work in different ways to
      stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells, by stopping them from
      dividing, or by stopping them from spreading. Dasatinib may stop the growth of cancer cells
      by blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell growth. Giving blinatumomab with combination
      chemotherapy or dasatinib and prednisone may kill more cancer cells.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the 3-year survival rate in elderly patients with newly diagnosed
      Philadelphia (Ph)-negative acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) treated with blinatumomab
      followed by POMP (prednisone, vincristine sulfate, methotrexate, and mercaptopurine)
      maintenance.

      II. To evaluate in a preliminary manner (feasibility study) the safety of dasatinib-steroid
      based induction followed by blinatumomab treatment in combination with dasatinib followed by
      dasatinib-based maintenance in elderly patients with newly diagnosed Ph-positive ALL.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate toxicities in these patient populations treated with these regimens.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To estimate the rates of complete response (CR), complete remission with incomplete count
      recovery (CRi) and disease-free survival in Ph-negative patients.

      II. To estimate disease-free and overall survival in Ph-positive patients. III. To estimate
      in each cohort the rate of minimal residual disease (MRD) negativity, and the time to
      achieve MRD negativity.

      OUTLINE: Patients are assigned to 1 of 2 treatment cohorts according to Philadelphia
      chromosome status.

      COHORT I (PHILADELPHIA CHROMOSOME NEGATIVE PATIENTS):

      INDUCTION: Patients receive blinatumomab intravenously (IV) continuously over 24 hours on
      days 1-28. Treatment repeats every 42 days for 2 courses in the absence of disease
      progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      RE-INDUCTION: Patients not achieving CR or CRi after Induction, receive blinatumomab IV
      continuously over 24 hours on days 1-28 in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity.

      POST-REMISSION: Patients receive blinatumomab IV continuously over 24 hours on days 1-28.
      Treatment repeats every 42 days for 3 courses in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity.

      MAINTENANCE: Patients receive prednisone orally (PO) on days 1-5, vincristine sulfate IV on
      day 1, mercaptopurine PO on days 1-28, and methotrexate PO on days 1, 8, 15, and 22.
      Treatment repeats every 28 days for 18 courses in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity.

      COHORT II (PHILADELPHIA CHROMOSOME POSITIVE PATIENTS):

      INDUCTION: Patients receive dasatinib PO twice daily (BID) on days 1-84 and prednisone PO on
      days 1-24 with tapering on days 25-32 in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable
      toxicity.

      RE-INDUCTION: Patients receive blinatumomab IV continuously over 24 hours on days 1-28.
      Treatment repeats every 42 days for 2 courses in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity.

      POST-REMISSION: Patients receive blinatumomab IV continuously over 24 hours on days 1-28 and
      dasatinib PO once daily (QD) on days 1-42. Treatment repeats every 42 days for 3 courses in
      the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      MAINTENANCE: Patients receive dasatinib PO BID on days 1-28 and prednisone PO on days 1-5.
      Courses repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up periodically for 10 years
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS) (Cohort I)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the day of registration on study until death from any cause, assessed at 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The final analysis will test whether the observed 3-year OS is improved over an historical rate of 10% with a one-sided binomial test at the 0.04 level. In the event of censoring, the 3-year OS rate will be estimated using the method of Kaplan-Meier and a one-sided 90% confidence interval will be constructed with the standard error calculated using the log-log transformation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of dose-limiting toxicity, defined as any grade 3-4 non-hematologic toxicity in the first cycle of post-remission therapy (blinatumomab/dasatinib) (Cohort II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 42 of post-remission therapy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete response (CR + CRi) rate (Cohort I)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated with a 95% confidence interval.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date the patient first achieves CR or CRi until relapse from CR/CRi or death from any cause, assessed up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Distributions of disease-free survival will be estimated using the method of Kaplan-Meier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rates (Cohort II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated with a 95% confidence interval.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>OS (Cohort II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated using the method of Kaplan-Meier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of toxicity graded according to National Cancer Institute CTCAE version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated with a 95% confidence interval.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MRD negativity</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to achieve MRD negativity</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Philadelphia Chromosome Negative Adult Precursor Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Philadelphia Chromosome Positive Adult Precursor Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Untreated Adult Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I (blinatumomab, POMP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>INDUCTION: Patients receive blinatumomab IV continuously over 24 hours on days 1-28. Treatment repeats every 42 days for 2 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
RE-INDUCTION: Patients not achieving CR or CRi after Induction, receive blinatumomab IV continuously over 24 hours on days 1-28 in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
POST-REMISSION: Patients receive blinatumomab IV continuously over 24 hours on days 1-28. Treatment repeats every 42 days for 3 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
MAINTENANCE: Patients receive prednisone PO on days 1-5, vincristine sulfate IV on day 1, mercaptopurine PO on days 1-28, and methotrexate PO on days 1, 8, 15, and 22. Treatment repeats every 28 days for 18 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort II (dasatinib, prednisone, blinatumomab)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>INDUCTION: Patients receive dasatinib PO BID on days 1-84 and prednisone PO on days 1-24 with tapering on days 25-32 in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
RE-INDUCTION: Patients receive blinatumomab IV continuously over 24 hours on days 1-28. Treatment repeats every 42 days for 2 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
POST-REMISSION: Patients receive blinatumomab IV continuously over 24 hours on days 1-28 and dasatinib PO QD on days 1-42. Treatment repeats every 42 days for 3 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
MAINTENANCE: Patients receive dasatinib PO BID on days 1-28 and prednisone PO on days 1-5. Courses repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>blinatumomab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I (blinatumomab, POMP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort II (dasatinib, prednisone, blinatumomab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>anti-CD19/anti-CD3 recombinant bispecific monoclonal antibody MT103</other_name>
    <other_name>bispecific T-cell engager MT103</other_name>
    <other_name>MEDI-538</other_name>
    <other_name>MT-103</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>prednisone</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I (blinatumomab, POMP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort II (dasatinib, prednisone, blinatumomab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>DeCortin</other_name>
    <other_name>Deltra</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>vincristine sulfate</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I (blinatumomab, POMP)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>leurocristine sulfate</other_name>
    <other_name>VCR</other_name>
    <other_name>Vincasar PFS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>methotrexate</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I (blinatumomab, POMP)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>amethopterin</other_name>
    <other_name>Folex</other_name>
    <other_name>methylaminopterin</other_name>
    <other_name>Mexate</other_name>
    <other_name>MTX</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>mercaptopurine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I (blinatumomab, POMP)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>6-mercaptopurine</other_name>
    <other_name>6-MP</other_name>
    <other_name>Leukerin</other_name>
    <other_name>MP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>dasatinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort II (dasatinib, prednisone, blinatumomab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BMS-354825</other_name>
    <other_name>Sprycel</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I (blinatumomab, POMP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort II (dasatinib, prednisone, blinatumomab)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have a new morphologic diagnosis of precursor B cell acute
             lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) (non T cell) based on World Health Organization (WHO)
             criteria; patients with Burkitt's (L3) are excluded

          -  Patients must have a diagnosis of Philadelphia chromosome negative ALL or Ph
             chromosome positive ALL by cytogenetics, fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) or
             polymerase chain reaction (PCR); diagnostic specimens must be submitted to the site's
             local Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments (CLIA)-approved cytogenetics
             laboratory and results of tests (cytogenetics, FISH or PCR) must confirm Ph status
             prior to registration; if not already known, BCR-ABL status (p190 or p210) must be
             evaluated in Ph-positive patients by PCR

          -  Patients must have evidence of ALL in their marrow or peripheral blood with at least
             20% lymphoblasts present in blood or bone marrow collected within 14 days prior to
             registration; for ALL in marrow or peripheral blood, immunophenotyping of the blood
             or marrow lymphoblasts must be performed to determine lineage (B cell, T cell or
             mixed B/T cell); appropriate marker studies including cluster of differentiation
             (CD)19 (B cell), must be performed; co-expression of myeloid antigens (CD13 and CD33)
             will not exclude patients; if possible, the lineage specific markers (myeloid cells)
             should be determined; the blood/bone marrow sample for these assays must be obtained
             within 14 days prior to registration; patients with only extramedullary disease in
             the absence of bone marrow or blood involvement are not eligible

          -  Patient must not have a history or presence of clinically relevant central nervous
             system (CNS) pathology such as epilepsy, seizure, paresis, aphasia, stroke, severe
             brain injuries, dementia, Parkinson's disease, cerebellar disease, organic brain
             syndrome, psychosis, or other significant CNS abnormalities, unless adequately
             controlled by intrathecal (IT) chemotherapy (at the discretion of the treating
             physician)

          -  Patients must have a lumbar puncture to determine CNS involvement of ALL within 14
             days prior to registration; patients with cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) has &gt;= 5 white
             blood cell (WBC)/mcL with cytospin positive for blasts; or &gt;= 10 red blood cell
             (RBC)/mcL, &gt;= 5 WBC/mcl and positive by Steinharz/Bleyeer algorithm; or clinical
             signs of CNS leukemia (such as facial nerve palsy, brain/eye involvement or
             hypothalamic syndrome) (CNS3) are excluded from the trial; patients with CSF has &lt; 5
             WBC/mcL with cytospin negative for blasts; or &gt; 10 RBC/mcL with cytospin negative for
             blasts (CNS1) or CSF has &lt; 5 WBC/mcL with cytospin positive for blasts; or &gt; 10
             RBC/mcL with cytospin positive for blasts; or &gt;= 10 RBC/mcL, WBC/mcL &gt;= 5, but less
             than Steinharz/Bleyer algorithm with cytospin positive for blasts (CNS2) will be
             eligible, but will be monitored for CNS involvement; note that intrathecal
             methotrexate administered during the pre-study lumbar puncture may count as the first
             dose of intrathecal therapy required as part of the study

          -  Patients must not have received any prior chemotherapy, radiation therapy, or other
             therapy for the treatment of ALL (other than those noted below) and must not be
             receiving any immunosuppressive therapy; patients may not have received any prior
             investigational therapy within 28 days prior to registration; patients may have
             received the following within any time prior to registration: low dose chemotherapy,
             tyrosine kinase inhibitor (TKI) therapy, steroids, hydroxyurea, leukapheresis,
             intrathecal chemotherapy or vincristine (vincristine sulfate); patients must not have
             received any monoclonal antibody therapy within 42 days of registration

          -  For patients 65-69 years of age, patient must be deemed not suitable for standard
             intensive induction chemotherapy at the discretion of the local investigator, or must
             have refused standard intensive chemotherapy

          -  Patients must not be candidates for allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant

          -  Patients must have a Zubrod performance status of 0-2

          -  Patients must have serum creatinine =&lt; 1.5 mg/dl

          -  Patients must have aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase
             (ALT) =&lt; 3.0 x institutional upper limit of normal (IULN)

          -  Patients must have total bilirubin =&lt; 2.0 x IULN

          -  Patients must have alkaline phosphatase =&lt; 2.5 x IULN

          -  Patients must not have systemic fungal, bacterial, viral or other infection that is
             not controlled (defined as exhibiting ongoing signs/symptoms related to the infection
             and without improvement, despite appropriate antibiotics or other treatment)

          -  Patients must not have Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) &gt;=
             grade 2 neuropathy (cranial, motor or sensory) within 14 days prior to registration

          -  Patients known to be positive for HIV (the human immunodeficiency virus) may be
             eligible, providing they meet the following additional criteria within 28 days prior
             to registration:

               -  No history of acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS)-defining conditions

               -  CD4 cells &gt; 350 cells/mm^3

               -  If on antiretroviral agents, must not include zidovudine or stavudine

               -  Viral load =&lt; 50 copies HIV messenger ribonucleic acid (mRNA)/mm^3 if on
                  combination antiretroviral therapy (cART) or =&lt; 25,000 copies HIV mRNA/mm^3 if
                  not on cART

               -  Highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART) regimens are acceptable providing
                  they have only weak P450A4 interactions

          -  Patients must not have any known autoimmune disease

          -  Patients must not have testicular involvement; if clinical or ultrasound findings are
             equivocal, biopsy must be performed; all tests for establishing testicular
             involvement must be completed within 14 days prior to registration

          -  Patients with evidence of extramedullary disease at diagnosis will have computed
             tomography (CT) scan or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the chest, abdomen and
             pelvis to obtain baseline values within 28 days prior to registration

          -  No other prior malignancy is allowed except for the following: adequately treated
             basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer, in situ cervical cancer, adequately treated
             stage I or II cancer from which the patient is currently in complete remission, or
             any other cancer from which the patient has been disease free for five years

          -  PH NEGATIVE PATIENTS ONLY: Patients must have the following tests within 28 days
             prior to registration to obtain baseline measurements:

               -  Prothrombin time (PT)/partial thromboplastin time (PTT)/international normalized
                  ratio (INR)/fibrinogen

               -  Neurologic assessment

          -  PH POSITIVE PATIENTS ONLY: Patients must not have active pericardial effusion,
             ascites or pleural effusion of any grade based on chest x-ray and echocardiogram
             within 28 days prior to registration; exception: if the effusion is suspected to be
             related to the leukemia, the patient may have pericardial effusion =&lt; grade 2 or
             pleural effusion =&lt; grade 1

          -  PH POSITIVE PATIENTS ONLY: Patients must have ejection fraction &gt;= 45% based on
             echocardiogram performed within 28 days prior to registration

          -  Patients must have QTcF (by Fridericia calculation) &lt; 500/msec based on
             electrocardiogram (EKG) performed within 28 days prior to registration

          -  Patients must not be receiving any proton pump inhibitors at the time of registration

          -  Pretreatment cytogenetics must be performed on all patients; collection of
             pretreatment specimens must be completed within 14 days prior to registration to
             S1318; specimens must be submitted to the site's preferred CLIA-approved cytogenetics
             laboratory; BCR-ABL status must be verified in Ph-positive patients by FISH,
             cytogenetics, and/or PCR prior to enrollment; if a patient is Ph-positive, PCR for
             both p190 and p210 must be sent

          -  Patients must be offered participation in specimen submission for future research;
             with patient's consent, specimens must be submitted as outlined

          -  Patients or their legally authorized representative must be informed of the
             investigational nature of this study and must sign and give written informed consent
             in accordance with institutional and federal guidelines

          -  As a part of the OPEN registration process the treating institution's identity is
             provided in order to ensure that the current (within 365 days) date of institutional
             review board approval for this study has been entered in the system

          -  Patients planning to enroll in Cohort 2 (Ph-positive) must first have a slot reserved
             in advance of the registration; all site staff will use OPEN to create a slot
             reservation

          -  COHORT 1 (PH-NEGATIVE): Patients must have achieved CR or CRi within 2 cycles of
             induction/re-induction with blinatumomab

          -  COHORT 2 (PH-POSITIVE): Patients must have achieved CR or CRi within 1 cycle of
             induction with dasatinib/prednisone, or within 2 cycles of re-induction with
             blinatumomab

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 750/mcl

          -  Platelets &gt;= 50,000/mcl

          -  Patients must be registered to Step 2 within 28 days after count recovery; (note:
             there is no maximum allotted time period for count recovery, providing patient
             remains in CR or CRi)

          -  All non-hematologic treatment related toxicities that are deemed clinically
             significant by the treating investigator must have resolved to =&lt; grade 2

          -  MAINTENANCE: Patients must have documented CR or CRi within 28 days prior to
             registration; note that bone marrow examination is only required if there are
             clinical signs/symptoms of progression; if progression is a concern due to the length
             of the time for count recovery, a bone marrow examination is recommended

          -  MAINTENANCE: Patients must have total bilirubin &lt; 2.0

          -  MAINTENANCE: Platelets &gt;= 75,000/mcl
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anjali Advani</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Southwest Oncology Group</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SWOG</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anjali S. Advani</last_name>
      <phone>216-445-9354</phone>
      <email>advania@ccf.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anjali S. Advani</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 19, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 19, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Philadelphia Chromosome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>6-Mercaptopurine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vincristine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dasatinib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Bispecific</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
