<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="33471">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01900119</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130161</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-CC-0161</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01900119</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Description of Bacteria in the Mouths of Patients With Severe Aplastic Anemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Description of the Oral Microbiome of Patients With Severe Aplastic Anemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - This research is being done to describe the types of bacteria found in the mouths of
      patients who have severe aplastic anemia (SAA) and are treated with drugs that suppress the
      immune system or with stem cell transplant. People with SAA who receive these treatments are
      more likely to get infections. Studies show that there might be a link between the bacteria
      in your mouth and those bacteria that can cause infections. The bacteria found in the mouths
      of patients with SAA will be described.

      Objectives:

      - To understand the changes in mouth bacteria that are related to treatment and to describe
      the oral bacterial environment.

      Eligibility:

        -  Adults at least 18 years of age who are going to be treated for SAA.

        -  Healthy volunteers at least 18 years of age.

      Design:

        -  Participants will answer questions about their medical history and dental care. Their
           mouths will be examined.

        -  Participants with SAA will be tested during treatment for their disease, over the
           course of 1 year. All participants with SAA will be tested at 3 scheduled appointments.
           Any participants who require a breathing tube will receive additional  tests.

        -  Healthy volunteers will be tested during  1 visit.

        -  Participants will give two samples each time. A saliva sample will be taken with a
           disposable padded tool. Skin cells will be collected from the tongue with a small
           plastic brush.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The mouth is a complex biological ecosystem normally containing over 700 different species
      of bacteria. Some of these bacteria live in an exopolysacchride matrix biofilm and occupy
      specific niches in this complex oral environment. Understanding the oral environment and the
      microbiota that inhabit it will assist in determining their impact on health and disease.
      There are several studies in critically ill patients demonstrating changes in oral bacteria
      related to acute illness. Identification of respiratory pathogens in the mouth has led
      researchers to hypothesize that a relationship exists between the oral cavity and pulmonary
      infections. Identification of potential pathogens in the oral cavity of patients with severe
      aplastic anemia could indicate a similar association between oral pathogens and infection in
      patient who develop respiratory infections that are severe enough to require intubation.
      This descriptive case-control study will characterize the oral microbiota of patients who
      have severe aplastic anemia (SAA). Patients will be followed for 1 year after treatment for
      development of respiratory symptoms that require intubation (cases). The cases will be
      compared to two groups of controls, namely those SAA patients who did not require intubation
      that received treatment for SAA and normal healthy volunteers who are age and gender
      matched. A difference in the oral microbiome will be identified in specimens collected
      before and after treatment and in those patients who require intubation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the oral microbiome of SAA patients prior to treatment and after treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>one year following enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Severe Aplastic Anemia (SAA)</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  All adult patients who are scheduled to receive treatment for SAA will be screened
             for this protocol. These patients will be recruited from the numerous protocols that
             are actively accepting new research participants at the Clinical Center, NIH. The
             healthy controls will be recruited from volunteers who present to the Clinical Center
             and are on the approved healthy volunteer list.

        INCLUSION CRITERIA

        Any adult patient (greater than or equal to18 years of age), diagnosed with SAA.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA

        Any SAA patient or matched healthy volunteer found to have significant tooth loss from
        decay or is edentulous are excluded. This exclusion criteria will be assessed by the PI or
        her representative prior to signing the informed consent.

        Additional exclusion criteria for matched healthy volunteers are:

          -  Periodontal disease as defined by the Periodontal Screening and Recording (a score of
             greater than Code 4 in one sextant)

          -  Use of antibiotics or steroids within the last 6 weeks.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nancy Ames, R.N.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nancy Ames, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-0565</phone>
    <email>names@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-CC-0161.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Socransky SS, Haffajee AD. Periodontal microbial ecology. Periodontol 2000. 2005;38:135-87. Review. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>15853940</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mager DL, Ximenez-Fyvie LA, Haffajee AD, Socransky SS. Distribution of selected bacterial species on intraoral surfaces. J Clin Periodontol. 2003 Jul;30(7):644-54.</citation>
    <PMID>12834503</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kolenbrander PE, Andersen RN, Blehert DS, Egland PG, Foster JS, Palmer RJ Jr. Communication among oral bacteria. Microbiol Mol Biol Rev. 2002 Sep;66(3):486-505, table of contents. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12209001</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 9, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 11, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Oral Microbiome</keyword>
  <keyword>Next Generation Sequencing</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Aplastic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
