<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="94107">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01924455</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DK094818</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01924455</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>HBV-HIV Coinfection Research Network</brief_title>
  <official_title>HBV-HIV Coinfection Research Network</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Virginia Commonwealth University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Virginia Commonwealth University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Despite effective ART that can suppress both HIV and HBV, HBV-related liver disease remains
      a significant co-morbidity in this population.  Little is known about the histologic
      spectrum of liver disease, the significance of complete vs. incomplete HBV suppression, the
      utility of novel virologic and serum markers of disease severity, and the long-term renal
      and bone effects of TDF-based therapy.  This proposal will address these important questions
      and impact the science and health of those coinfected with HBV-HIV.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Since the introduction of highly active antiretroviral therapy (ART) in 1996, there has been
      a dramatic reduction in morbidity and mortality among those living with HIV.  However,
      chronic liver disease due to coinfection with hepatitis B (HBV) or C (HCV) virus has emerged
      as the second leading cause of mortality among HIV-infected persons.  The natural history of
      HBV infection is altered in those with HIV.  Current guidelines recommend that most
      coinfected patients be treated for both HIV and HBV infection using combinations of ART that
      include tenofovir (TDF).  Despite widespread adoption in the US, the effect of this regimen
      on long-term outcomes of HBV disease such as histologic severity, progression, and risk of
      emergence of resistant HBV variants, and  the long term risks of TDF therapy remains
      unanswered. Further investigation is required to address the following important questions:
      (1) what is the proportion of HIV-coinfected patients who have incomplete viral suppression
      on TDF?; (2) is incomplete suppression of HBV acceptable in HIV coinfected persons and if
      so, what threshold HBV DNA level constitutes an adequate clinical goal?; (3) in view of the
      lack of acceptance of liver biopsy among HIV practitioners, can noninvasive markers
      accurately assess HBV disease activity and the impact of ART on disease progression?; (4)
      What are the long term risks of TDF-based therapy for HBV in HIV coinfection?  In short,
      what are the risks and benefits of TDF-based therapy for CHB in patients with HIV
      coinfection?  The NIH Hepatitis B Research Network (HBRN) is the first major effort to
      elucidate the natural history and treatment outcomes of persons with chronic HBV the US.
      The HBRN will not address the critical issue of HBV liver disease progression in
      HIV-infected persons because patients with HIV coinfection will be excluded.  The current
      proposal, an approved ancillary study of the HBRN, offers a unique opportunity to fill major
      gaps in HBV-HIV knowledge and to compare HBV-HIV infected persons to those with HBV
      monoinfection participating in the HBRN.  No other funded research network in North America
      has the expertise, patient population, and structure to carry out the proposed studies. The
      Specific Aims are: 1. Define the problem. We will clinically, histologically, serologically,
      and virologically characterize a well-defined cohort of HBV-HIV patients in North America in
      a cross-sectional manner; 2. Define the benefit of long term therapy. We will longitudinally
      determine the impact of complete vs. incomplete viral suppression on clinical and serologic
      outcomes, and histologic progression by paired biopsy and 2a. Define a threshold HBV DNA
      level associated with disease progression; 2b. Establish the utility of noninvasive
      assessment of hepatic fibrosis compared with biopsy; and 2c. Define the frequency of
      genotypic and phenotypic TDF resistance with long term therapy; and finally 3. Define the
      risk of long term therapy. We will assess the long term renal and bone effects of TDF-based
      therapy in the HBV-HIV cohort.  Collectively, this study will fulfill many of the key
      priorities outlined in the NIH Action Plan for Liver Disease for HBV-HIV coinfection.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Liver disease severity</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will clinically, histologically, serologically, and virologically characterize a well-defined cohort of HBV-HIV patients in North America in a cross-sectional manner</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Outcome of viral suppression</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>We will longitudinally determine the impact of complete vs. incomplete viral suppression on clinical and serologic outcomes, and histologic progression by paired biopsy.
Define a threshold HBV DNA level associated with disease progression.
Establish the utility of noninvasive assessment of hepatic fibrosis compared with biopsy.
Define the frequency of genotypic and phenotypic TDF resistance with long term therapy
We will assess the long term renal and bone effects of TDF-based therapy in the HBV-HIV cohort.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">250</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatitis B</condition>
  <condition>Human Immunodeficiency Virus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HBV-HIV coinfected subjects</arm_group_label>
    <description>HBV-HIV coinfected subjects seen at one of 7 participating centers.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        HBV-HIV coinfection
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria: (1) Male and female subjects ≥ 18 years of age; (2) Serologic evidence
        of HIV infection by HIV antibody positivity or positive HIV-RNA &gt; 6 months prior to
        screening (3) Serologic evidence of chronic hepatitis B infection by HBsAg positivity(4)
        Willingness to provide informed consent.

        -

        Exclusion Criteria: (1) Estimated life expectancy of less than one year based on clinical
        judgment of the investigator; (2) Hepatic decompensation as defined by presence of ascites
        or hepatic hydrothorax, variceal or portal hypertensive bleeding, hepatic encephalopathy,
        or  Child-Turcotte-Pugh (CTP) score of 7 or above; (3) Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC); (4)
        Anti-HCV positive; (5) History of solid organ or bone marrow transplantation; (6) Pregnant
        women; (7) Medical or social condition which in the opinion of the study physician would
        make the patient unsuitable for the study or will interfere with or prevent follow-up per
        protocol; (8) Unable or unwilling to return for follow-up visits; (9) Contraindications to
        liver biopsy.

        -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Richard Sterling, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <email>rksterli@vcu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mandana Khalili, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Balitmore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark Sulkowski, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mass General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Raymond Chung, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mauricio Lisker-Melman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT Southwestern</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mamta Jain, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virginia Commonwealth University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Richard Sterling, MD, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Toronto Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.hepbnet.org/</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>HBV</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis B</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunologic Deficiency Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
