<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="95952">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02145156</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14-0402</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>PCORI 1455</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02145156</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Educational Intervention to Minimize Disparities in Humanpapillomavirus Vaccination</brief_title>
  <acronym>HPV</acronym>
  <official_title>Educational Intervention to Minimize Disparities in HPV Vaccination</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate an innovative approach to improving HPV vaccination
      among the Hispanic population. The objectives/aims of this HPV educational intervention
      project are:

        1. To determine patterns of intervention utilization among parents/patients in different
           arms of the intervention,

        2. To measure the quality of the HPV vaccine decision among parents/patients in different
           arms of the intervention, and

        3. To determine if different arms of the intervention affect the likelihood of HPV
           vaccination among patients.

      The implementation of this educational intervention in clinic waiting rooms is intended to
      assist primary care providers in communicating HPV vaccine awareness and education to
      parents and patients in a culturally tailored format.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      While HPV infection is nearly ubiquitous among the sexually active population, the morbidity
      and mortality from HPV-related diseases disproportionately affects minorities and the poor.
      Hispanic women are at particularly high risk as they have the highest rates of invasive
      cervical cancer when compared to all other racial or ethnic groups in the U.S. Initiating
      the 3-dose HPV vaccination series is more common among Hispanic adolescents than whites, but
      series completion has been lowest among Hispanic populations.

      To understand barriers to HPV vaccination and to provide insight into ways in which an
      existing educational intervention should be modified for a Hispanic population, the
      investigators conducted focus groups among Hispanic parents and Latina young adults. All
      groups reported vaccine cost, access to insurance, and a general lack of awareness and/or
      understanding of either HPV or the vaccine as barriers. All groups also wanted substantially
      more &quot;general&quot; information about both HPV and the vaccine in order to make informed
      vaccination decisions. The educational intervention was generally well received but there
      were universal suggestions from all the groups to provide additional basic information about
      HPV infection, to add information about the vaccine for boys/young men, and to modify the
      color scheme and logo to make it more eye-catching and pleasing.

      This next phase of the project will be comprised of real world testing of an iPad-based
      educational intervention about HPV, &quot;Combatting HPV Infection and Cancer&quot; (CHICOS) that has
      been revised and developed per focus group feedback to target the Hispanic population.

      By providing information that patients and parents have clearly indicated they want in a way
      that is culturally sensitive and meaningful and also individually personalized, the
      investigators hope to improve both the HPV vaccination decision-making process and HPV
      vaccination rates.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of the HPV vaccine decision among parents/patients</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>One of the primary outcomes measured in this project will be the &quot;quality&quot; of the HPV vaccine decision arising from the different arms of the study. This will be assessed among users of both the tailored and untailored computer-based decision tool, and among the subset of individuals in the &quot;usual care with survey&quot; arm of the study, using the Post-Intervention and Follow Up surveys. A variety of validated measures related to patient-centered outcomes such as satisfaction, regret and acceptability will be used. These measures will be assessed in the post-intervention survey and also in the follow up survey to determine if they are stable over time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Likelihood of HPV vaccination among patients</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Vaccination uptake will be assessed using the clinic's Electronic Medical Record (EMR)with the Colorado Immunization Information System (CIIS) as a &quot;back up&quot; data source. Essentially all vaccines delivered within any of the participating clinics have vaccination status recorded in their centralized EMR system. Vaccination status will be calculated for each of the study arms by dividing the number of individuals who received a dose of the vaccine by the number of individuals who were eligible for a dose during the study time period, stratified by study arm. Several measures of vaccine uptake will be assessed including: series initiation among those eligible, series completion among those who initiated, time between the intervention and when an HPV vaccine dose was provided, and time between each HPV vaccine dose received.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention utilization among parents/patients</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The iPad will automatically collect &quot;paradata&quot; on each user's navigation through the iPad's educational pages. This includes the number of pages viewed, order viewed and time spent per page. These data will be available for each user. The demographic characteristics of participants will be assessed using information collected in the baseline survey. Paradata characteristics will be compared between participants with different demographic characteristics and who are in different arms of the study (tailored or untailored).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1100</enrollment>
  <condition>HPV Vaccination Status</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tailored intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention: tailored educational materials.  In this arm, participants will complete a baseline survey on an iPad, view a series of educational webpages on the iPad, and complete a brief post intervention survey. The iPad will use an automated &quot;tailoring engine&quot; programmed into the intervention to immediately retrieve participants' survey responses to generate tailored educational messages about the HPV vaccine. These educational messages will be individually tailored to reflect the top concerns indicated by the participant about the HPV vaccine for themselves or their adolescent child. Additional tailoring will occur in the form of images matched to self-reported race and age, and using participants' first name in the information presented.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Untailored Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention: untailored educational materials.  In this arm, patients will view educational information on the iPad that is not responsive to their baseline questionnaire answers and instead is derived directly from the HPV &quot;Vaccine Information Sheet&quot; that has been created by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention and is required to be given to patients prior to HPV vaccine administration.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention: survey-only.  Participants in the standard of care arm will not view any educational materials or complete the baseline survey. A random ½ of the sample in this arm will be provided with a paper version of the Post Intervention Survey to be completed after the clinic visit in person or by mail.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tailored educational materials</intervention_name>
    <description>The tailored intervention will use an automated &quot;tailoring engine&quot; to retrieve participants' baseline survey responses to generate tailored educational messages about the HPV vaccine. To do this, the survey engine retrieves from a &quot;message library&quot; the specific educational messages that are linked to each individual participant's survey. These educational messages will be individually tailored to reflect the top concerns indicated by the participant about the HPV vaccine for themselves or their adolescent child. Additional tailoring will occur in the form of images matched to self-reported race and age, and using participants' first name in the information presented.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tailored intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Untailored educational materials</intervention_name>
    <description>The untailored intervention will present educational information on the iPad that is not responsive to participants' baseline questionnaire answers and instead is derived directly from the HPV &quot;Vaccine Information Sheet&quot; that has been created by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention and is required to be given to patients prior to HPV vaccine administration</description>
    <arm_group_label>Untailored Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Survey-only</intervention_name>
    <description>For those in the &quot;Standard of Care&quot; arm, a random ½ of the sample will be provided with a paper version of the Post Intervention Survey. This will be provided to participants after their clinic visit is completed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Parents of an adolescent between the ages of 9-17; OR a young adult patient between
             the ages of 18-26;

          2. Adolescent/young adult has not yet received all three doses of the HPV vaccine.

          3. Parent/young adult can read and converse in either English or Spanish

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Age &lt;18,

          2. Prisoners

          3. Decisionally challenged subjects

          4. Those who cannot read and converse in either English or Spanish

          5. Those who have received all 3 doses of the HPV vaccine
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amanda F Dempsey, MD, PhD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Denver</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Julie A Maertens, PhD</last_name>
    <email>julie.maertens@ucdenver.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Andrea Jimenez-Zambrano, MPH</last_name>
    <email>andrea.jimenez-zambrano@ucdenver.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Denver</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 20, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HPV vaccination</keyword>
  <keyword>Vaccination decision-making</keyword>
  <keyword>Tailored health messaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Barriers to vaccination</keyword>
  <keyword>Attitudes</keyword>
  <keyword>Intentions</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
