<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="53714">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01999231</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LTao-EC</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>LTao</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01999231</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase I Clinical Human Tolerability Study of Recombinant Mycobacterium Tuberculosis ESAT6-CFP10 Allergen</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Clinical Human Tolerability Study of Recombinant Mycobacterium Tuberculosis ESAT6-CFP10 Allergen</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Anhui Zhifei Longcom Biologic Pharmacy Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shanghai Public Health Clinical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Anhui Zhifei Longcom Biologic Pharmacy Co., Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>China: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In the tests, small sample of clinical study about Recombinant Mycobacterium Tuberculosis
      ESAT6-CFP10 Allergen  ( Recombination EC Allergen） healthy adults was carried out.

      24 healthy adults were  included  as study objects, they were randomly divided into four
      groups of different Recombinant EC Allergen dose (1, 5, 10μg/mL, maximum tolerated dose
      20μg/mL, 6 person/dose) for single arm intradermal injection.

      The main test items include vital signs at 15min, 30min, 1h, 2h, 4h, 8h, 24h, 48h, 72h, 96h
      after injection, skin reactivity (blushes and calluses ) diameter of injection sites, local
      reaction ( rash, pain, itching, and skin and mucous membranes ) and a variety of adverse
      events, and blood, urine, liver and kidney function, ECG （electrocardiogram）and chest X-ray
      films before and 7 days after injection.

      Preliminary evaluation of safety and tolerability of Recombinant EC Allergen  applied in
      humans, which can provide a safe dosage range for phase II clinical study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This clinical study adopts an open, randomized study methods to carry out Recombinant EC
      Allergen  on small sample of healthy adults.

      24 healthy adults were included as study objects, they were randomly divided into four
      groups of different Recombinant EC Allergen dose (1, 5, 10μg/mL, maximum tolerated dose
      20μg/mL, 6 person/dose) for single arm intradermal injection, and set up two people as
      replacement for each group (one male and one female).

      Intradermal injection into one third site of healthy subjects' left or right forearm
      palmaris with 0.1ml Recombinant EC Allergen for only one time.

      Vital signs (breathing, heart rate, blood pressure, body temperature ) of each volunteer at
      15min, 30min, 1h, 2h, 4h, 8h, 24h, 48h, 72h, 96h after injection, skin reactivity (blushes
      and calluses ) diameter of injection sites,local reaction ( rash, pain, itching, and skin
      and mucous membranes ) should be measured, and record a variety of adverse events, and
      blood, urine, liver and kidney function, ECG and chest X-ray films before and 7 days after
      intradermal injection.

      In phaseⅠclinical study, each person can accept only one dose, After injection of the same
      dose of a volunteer group, be sure the next injection of a volunteer at 40 minutes interval.
      Different dose groups: the next dose test should be carried on in the case of no serious
      adverse events appear in 7days after the last one volunteer's injection in a former lower
      dose group.

      Statistical analysis is performed using SAS9.3 software, and all analytic process is
      routinization.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vital Signs</measure>
    <time_frame>7days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Vital signs at 15min, 30min, 1h, 2h, 4h, 8h, 24h, 48h, 72h, 96h after injection.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Skin reactivity ( blushes and calluses ) diameter of injection sites, local reaction ( rash, pain, itching, and skin and mucous membranes ) and a variety of adverse events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mycobacterium Riyadhense</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intradermal injection with 0.1ml  allergen by a syringe (1ml), the injection site is one third site of left or right forearm palmaris (Piercing intradermal with needle bevel up 5°-10°, the injection depth is moderate, so that the skin rash can hunch at local area )</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mycobacterium Riyadhense</intervention_name>
    <description>Intradermal injection with 0.1ml  allergen by a syringe(1ml), the injection site is one third site of left or right forearm palmaris (Piercing intradermal with needle bevel up 5°-10°, the injection depth is moderate, so that the skin rash can hunch at local area ).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mycobacterium Riyadhense</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Recombinant EC Allergen</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged from 18 to 40 years old, age difference is not more than 10 years old within the
             same batch of healthy volunteers, the male to female ratio of cases is 1:1. Body mass
             index should be in the range of 20 to 27 Body Mass Index BMI: weight (Kg)/ height
             (M2);

          -  Agreed to participate in the test and sign the informed consent;

          -  Subjects should comply with the requirements of the clinical trial protocol and be
             followed;

          -  Subjects have no history of TB or family history of tuberculosis;

          -  People have no pulmonary tuberculosis or extrapulmonary tuberculosis,respiratory
             symptom or systemic symptoms;

          -  People have no tuberculosis focus after examination by X-ray chest radiograph and
             sputum bacilli;

          -  Subjects have no acute or chronic disease, acute infectious diseases, dermatoses or
             skin allergy caused by various reasons;

          -  Physical condition: have no history of heart, liver, kidney, gastrointestinal tract,
             nervous system, or metabolic disturbance, etc. ECG, blood pressure, heart rate,
             respiratory status and lab test indexes including blood, urine, liver and kidney
             function, etc are all normal within 4 weeks before screening;

          -  No close contacts of tuberculosis;

          -  Subjects have not participated in other clinical drug trials or inoculated against
             other prophylactic and immune globulin in the nearly 3 months;

          -  Temperature is normal;

          -  Stop smoking, drinking and drinking contains caffeinated.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Health people have close contacts of TB patients, especially excreter in 3 weeks
             before selection;

          -  Suffering from any other serious disease, e.g. during cancer treatment, autoimmune
             disease, progressive atherosclerosis, diabetes accompanied with complications,
             chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) needing oxygen therapy, acute or
             progressive liver or kidney disease, congestive heart failure, etc.;

          -  People have history of allergy, convulsions, epilepsy, cerebropathy, neurological
             symptoms and signs;

          -  Patients who have impaired or abnormal immune function, e.g. patients treated with
             immunosuppressor or immunopotentiator, received immunoglobulin preparation or blood
             products or plasma extraction outside the gastrointestinal tract in 3 months, human
             immunodeficiency virus or related diseases;

          -  Acute febrile illness and infection;

          -  Taking part in other clinic trials;

          -  Subjects have participated in any other clinical drug trials in 3 months before our
             clinical tests;

          -  Allergic constitution, e.g. patients have allergic history to two or more kinds of
             drugs or food, or drug components;

          -  Substance abuse and alcoholics ;

          -  Pregnant or breast feeding women;

          -  Mental or physical disability;

          -  Informed leavers;

          -  Any other cases that may influence the test evaluation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shuihua Lu</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Shanghai Public Health Clinical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <link>
    <url>https://wbca.cde.org.cn/wbca/clinmain.do?method=edit&amp;ckmIdCode=8BE5738082A97A9E5471F80B4F814FCF</url>
    <description>Center for drug evaluation, CFDA ,China</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.chictr.org/usercenter/project/edit.aspx?proj=5856</url>
    <description>Chinese Clinical Trial Registry</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Pinxteren LA, Ravn P, Agger EM, Pollock J, Andersen P. Diagnosis of tuberculosis based on the two specific antigens ESAT-6 and CFP10. Clin Diagn Lab Immunol. 2000 Mar;7(2):155-60.</citation>
    <PMID>10702486</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ravn P, Munk ME, Andersen AB, Lundgren B, Lundgren JD, Nielsen LN, Kok-Jensen A, Andersen P, Weldingh K. Prospective evaluation of a whole-blood test using Mycobacterium tuberculosis-specific antigens ESAT-6 and CFP-10 for diagnosis of active tuberculosis. Clin Diagn Lab Immunol. 2005 Apr;12(4):491-6.</citation>
    <PMID>15817755</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brusasca PN, Colangeli R, Lyashchenko KP, Zhao X, Vogelstein M, Spencer JS, McMurray DN, Gennaro ML. Immunological characterization of antigens encoded by the RD1 region of the Mycobacterium tuberculosis genome. Scand J Immunol. 2001 Nov;54(5):448-52.</citation>
    <PMID>11696195</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weldingh K, Andersen P. ESAT-6/CFP10 skin test predicts disease in M. tuberculosis-infected guinea pigs. PLoS One. 2008 Apr 23;3(4):e1978. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0001978.</citation>
    <PMID>18431468</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aagaard C, Govaerts M, Meikle V, Vallecillo AJ, Gutierrez-Pabello JA, Suarez-Güemes F, McNair J, Cataldi A, Espitia C, Andersen P, Pollock JM. Optimizing antigen cocktails for detection of Mycobacterium bovis in herds with different prevalences of bovine tuberculosis: ESAT6-CFP10 mixture shows optimal sensitivity and specificity. J Clin Microbiol. 2006 Dec;44(12):4326-35. Epub 2006 Sep 27.</citation>
    <PMID>17005738</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 26, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 4, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Safety</keyword>
  <keyword>Tolerability</keyword>
  <keyword>Recombinant EC Allergens</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Mycobacterium Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
