<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="107750">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02111863</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>140062</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>14-C-0062</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02111863</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Cell Transfer Therapy for Metastatic Melanoma Using 4-1BB Tumor Infiltrating Lymphocytes Plus IL-2 Following a Non-Myeloablative Lymphocyte Depleting Chemotherapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Cell Transfer Therapy for Metastatic Melanoma Using 41BB Selected Tumor Infiltrating Lymphocytes Plus IL-2 Following a Non-Myeloablative Lymphocyte Depleting Chemotherapy Regimen</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      The NCI Surgery Branch has developed an experimental therapy that involves taking white
      blood cells from patients' tumors, growing them in the laboratory in large numbers, and then
      giving the cells back to the patient. These cells are called Tumor Infiltrating Lymphocytes,
      or TIL and we have given this type of treatment to over 100 patients. In this study, we are
      selecting a specific subset of white blood cells from the tumor that we think are the most
      effective in fighting tumors and will use only these cells in making the tumor fighting
      cells.

      Objective:

      The purpose of this study is to see if these specifically selected tumor fighting cells can
      cause melanoma tumors to shrink and to see if this treatment is safe.

      Eligibility:

      - Adults age 18 and over with metastatic melanoma who have a tumor that can be safely
      removed.

      Design:

        -  Work up stage: Patients will be seen as an outpatient at the NIH clinical Center and
           undergo a history and physical examination, scans, x-rays, lab tests, and other tests
           as needed

        -  Surgery: If the patients meet all of the requirements for the study they will undergo
           surgery to remove a tumor that can be used to grow the TIL product.

        -  Treatment: Once their cells have grown, the patients will be admitted to the hospital
           for the conditioning chemotherapy, the TIL cells and aldesleukin.  They will stay in
           the hospital for about 1-2 weeks to recover from the treatment.

        -  Patients will return to the clinic for a physical exam, review of side effects, lab
           tests, and scans about every 1-3 months for the first year, and then every 6 months to
           1 year as long as their tumors are shrinking.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Autologous tumor infiltrating lymphocytes (TIL) followed by high dose aldesleukin can
           mediate the regression of bulky metastatic melanoma when administered to a patient
           following a non-myeloablative but lymphodepleting chemotherapy preparative regimen.

        -  In animal models, mixing irrelevant (non-reactive) cells with tumor-reactive cells
           negatively impacts on tumor treatment possibly by competing for cytokines, suggesting
           that enrichment for tumor-reactive cells could enhance clinical efficacy. Additionally,
           preclinical animal models and clinical investigation have demonstrated that prolonged
           in vitro culture negatively impacts on tumor treatment.

        -  The current method for enrichment of tumor-reactive TIL requires screening of multiple
           independent TIL cultures for anti-tumor specificity using gamma-interferon production
           by TIL. However, in vitro screening depends on autologous tumor reagents that are often
           unavailable, and IFN gamma release in vitro may not be the best effector function to
           evaluate tumor recognition. The screen increases the length of in vitro culture times (
             30 days), which results in shorter telomere lengths and more differentiated cells.
           Additionally, selection of a few highly reactive cultures for further expansion may
           reduce the diversity of CD8+ repertoire recognizing the tumor.

        -  4-1BB is a co-stimulatory molecule up-regulated on the cell surface of T cells upon TCR
           engagement. Pre-clinical studies in the Surgery Branch have evaluated a fast and
           simplified method to select and expand a diverse tumor-reactive repertoire, regardless
           of knowledge of the specific antigen recognized, based on selection of 4-1BB expressing
           TIL from the fresh tumor digest.

      Objectives:

        -  To determine the safety and objective response rate of patients with metastatic
           melanoma receiving ACT using 4-1BB selected TIL plus aldesleukin treatment following a
           chemotherapy preparative regimen.

        -  To determine the survival of patients receiving this treatment regimen.

      Eligibility:

      Patients who are 18 years or older must have:

        -  Evaluable metastatic melanoma;

        -  Metastatic melanoma lesion suitable for surgical resection for the preparation of TIL;

        -  No contraindications to high-dose aldesleukin administration;

        -  No concurrent major medical illnesses or any form of immunodeficiency

      Design:

        -  Patients with metastatic melanoma will have a lesion resected and 4-1BB expressing
           tumor infiltrating lymphocytes will be isolated using a FACS sorter approved for
           clinical use. The 4-1BB selected cells will be rapidly expanded in vitro and
           administered plus aldesleukin following a non-myeloablative chemotherapy preparative
           regimen.

        -  The study will be conducted using a stage 2 optimal design to determine if this
           treatment is able to be associated with a clinical response rate that can rule out 10%
           (p0=0.10) in favor of a modest 30% PR + CR rate (p1=0.30).

        -  Up to 35 patients may be enrolled over 2 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary objective of this pilot trial is to determine whether theregimen will result in objective clinical responses</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Skin Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Interleukin-2</intervention_name>
    <description>Aldeskeukin 720,000 IU/kg every eight up to 5 days (maximum of 15 doses).</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Fludarabine 25 mg/m2/day IVPB daily X 5 days</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cylcophosphamide</intervention_name>
    <description>Cyclophosphamide 60 mg/kg/day X 2 days</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>41BB Selected Tumor Infiltrating Lymphocytes</intervention_name>
    <description>between 1e8 and 5e10 cells IV infused over 20-30 minutes</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Measurable metastatic melanoma with at least one lesion that is resectable for TIL
             generation. The lesion must be at least 1 cm in diameter that can be surgically
             removed with minimal morbidity (defined as any operation for which expected
             hospitalization &lt; less than or equal to days).

          2. Confirmation of diagnosis of metastatic melanoma by the Laboratory of Pathology of
             the NCI.

          3. 3 or fewer brain metastases. Note: If lesions are symptomatic or greater than or
             equal to

             1 cm each, these lesions must have been treated and stable for 3 months for the
             patient to be eligible.

          4. Greater than or equal to 18 years of age and less than or equal to age 66.

          5. Able to understand and sign the Informed Consent Document

          6. Willing to sign a durable power of attorney

          7. Clinical performance status of ECOG 0 or 1

          8. Oxygen saturation of greater than or equal to 90% on room air

          9. Life expectancy of greater than three months

         10. Patients of both genders must be willing to practice birth control from the time of
             enrollment on this study and for up to four months after treatment.

         11. Serology:

               -  Seronegative for HIV antibody. (The experimental treatment being evaluated in
                  this protocol depends on an intact immune system. Patients who are HIV
                  seropositive can have decreased immune-competence and thus be less responsive to
                  the experimental treatment and more susceptible to its toxicities.)

               -  Seronegative for hepatitis B antigen, and seronegative for hepatitis C antibody.
                  If hepatitis C antibody test is positive, then patient must be tested for the
                  presence of antigen by RT-PCR and be HCV RNA negative.

         12. Women of child-bearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test because of the
             potentially dangerous effects of the treatment on the fetus.

         13. Hematology

               -  Absolute neutrophil count greater than 1000/mm3 without the support of
                  filgrastim

               -  WBC greater than or equal to 3000/mm (3)

               -  Platelet count greater than or equal to 100,000/mm (3)

               -  Hemoglobin &gt;  8.0 g/dl

         14. Chemistry:

               -  Serum ALT/AST less than or equal to 2.5 times the upper limit of normal

               -  Serum creatinine less than or equal to 1.6 mg/dl

               -  Total bilirubin less than or equal to 2.0 mg/dl, except in patients with Gilbert
                    s Syndrome who must have a total bilirubin less than 3.0 mg/dl.

         15. More than four weeks must have elapsed since any prior systemic therapy at the time
             the patient receives the preparative regimen, and patients    toxicities must have
             recovered to a grade 1 or less (except for toxicities such as alopecia or vitiligo).
             Patients must have progressing disease after prior treatment.

             Note: Patients may have undergone minor surgical procedures within the past 3 weeks,
             as long as all toxicities have recovered to grade 1 or less or as specified in the
             eligibility criteria in Section 2.1.1.

         16. Six weeks must have elapsed from the time of any antibody therapy that could affect
             an anti cancer immune response, including anti-CTLA4 antibody therapy at the time the
             patient receives the preparative regimen to allow antibody levels to decline.

        Note: Patients who have previously received ipilimumab and have documented GI toxicity
        must have a normal colonoscopy with normal colonic biopsies.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Prior treatment with an anti-4-1BB antibody.

          2. Women of child-bearing potential who are pregnant or breastfeeding because of the
             potentially dangerous effects of the treatment on the fetus or infant.

          3. Active systemic infections, coagulation disorders or other active major medical
             illnesses of the cardiovascular, respiratory or immune system, as evidenced by a
             positive stress thallium or comparable test, myocardial infarction, cardiac
             arrhythmias, obstructive or restrictive pulmonary disease.

          4. Any form of primary immunodeficiency (such as Severe Combined Immunodeficiency
             Disease).

          5. Concurrent opportunistic infections (The experimental treatment being evaluated in
             this protocol depends on an intact immune system. Patients who have decreased immune
             competence may be less responsive to the experimental treatment and more susceptible
             to its toxicities).

          6. Concurrent systemic steroid therapy.

          7. History of severe immediate hypersensitivity reaction to any of the agents used in
             this study.

          8. History of coronary revascularization or ischemic symptoms.

          9. Documented LVEF of less than or equal to 45%, testing is required in patients with:

               -  Clinically significant atrial and/or ventricular arrhythmias including but not
                  limited to: atrial fibrillation, ventricular tachycardia, second or third degree
                  heart block

               -  Age greater than or equal to 60 years old

         10. Documented FEV1 less than or equal to 60% predicted tested in patients with:

               -  A prolonged history of cigarette smoking (20 pk/year if smoking within the

        past 2 years)

        -Symptoms of respiratory dysfunction
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>66 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven A Rosenberg, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>June Kryk, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-1929</phone>
    <email>ncisbirc@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Steven A Rosenberg, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-4164</phone>
    <email>sar@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact NCI/Surgery Branch Recruitment Center</last_name>
      <phone>866-820-4505</phone>
      <email>ncisbirc@mail.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2014-C-0062.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jemal A, Siegel R, Ward E, Murray T, Xu J, Thun MJ. Cancer statistics, 2007. CA Cancer J Clin. 2007 Jan-Feb;57(1):43-66.</citation>
    <PMID>17237035</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Atkins MB, Kunkel L, Sznol M, Rosenberg SA. High-dose recombinant interleukin-2 therapy in patients with metastatic melanoma: long-term survival update. Cancer J Sci Am. 2000 Feb;6 Suppl 1:S11-4.</citation>
    <PMID>10685652</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gogas HJ, Kirkwood JM, Sondak VK. Chemotherapy for metastatic melanoma: time for a change? Cancer. 2007 Feb 1;109(3):455-64. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17200963</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 9, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 9, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Skin Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic Melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Adoptive Cell Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Clinical Response</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Skin Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine monophosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Interleukin-2</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
