<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="63641">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01738737</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CAPPESQ 455/11</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01738737</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Static Stretching and Low Intensity Laser Therapy in Patients With Knee Osteoarthritis: Randomized Clinical Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Static Stretching and Low Level Laser Therapy in Patients With Knee Osteoarthritis: Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Sao Paulo General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Sao Paulo General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Brazil: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Introduction: Osteoarthritis (OA) is a prevalent disease associated with significant
      morbidity, one of the most common causes of functional limitations and dependence. This
      study aims to investigate the effects of low intensity laser therapy (904nm) and stretching
      exercises in pain, range of motion, flexibility, functionality and quality of life of
      patients with knee OA according to the criteria of the American College of rheumatology.
      Methods: The sample consists of 125 patients aged between 50 and 75 years, from the
      Rehabilitation Center in the city of Taboão da Serra - São Paulo/Brasil, who have knee pain,
      functional reduction in the last three months and grade between 2 and 4 classification of OA
      by Kellgren and Lawrence (1957). Patients will be divided into five groups: Group A - Low
      Intensity Laser Therapy (LILT) with an active dose of 3 Joules more stretching exercises,
      Group B - LILT placebo plus stretching exercises, Group C - only stretching exercises, Group
      D - only LILT and Group E - control. For groups A and B, in the first three weeks, the
      treatment will be done with the LILT (active or placebo) totaling nine sessions and in the
      next eight weeks will be performed stretching exercises totaling 24 sessions. C and D groups
      will realize eight weeks of stretching exercises and LILT, respectively. The patients will
      be assessed before and after each intervention. The clinical evaluation includes pain
      intensity by visual analogue scale (VAS) functionality by the Lequesne's Functional
      Questionnaire and Get Up and Go Test, the range of movement of flexion and knee extension
      and shortening of the hamstrings with the goniometer; flexibility through the
      finger-to-floor distance test and the quality of life by the Western Ontario and McMaster
      Universities Arthritis Index (WOMAC). The data will be considered statistically significant
      at ± &lt;0.05.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Physical performance as a determinant of disability in osteoarthritis (OA) has been
      investigated extensively, but research has focused primarily on the effect that the decrease
      in muscle strength has on the functionality in patients with OA. However, the reduced range
      of motion in affected joints is also an important risk factor for the occurrence of
      locomotor disability and other developing disability in patients with OA.

      Studies using stretching exercises are scarce in the Reid &amp; Mc Nair (2010) specifically
      examined the range of motion can be improved in subjects with knee osteoarthritis, although
      this study did only stretching the hamstrings. The results indicate that there is immediate
      benefits of stretching in subjects with osteoarthritis of the knee joint, providing evidence
      for the long term development of stretching programs for this population.

      In the literature are observed inconsistent results regarding the benefits of laser
      treatment in improving pain and function in individuals with knee OA. Also there are few
      studies that specify which dosage and frequency of laser must be used.

      In view of the increasing need to support the role of physiotherapy in evidence-based
      practice, this study is justified by the need to test the effectiveness of stretching
      exercises and elucidate the effectiveness of low intensity laser therapy in patients with
      knee OA.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Factorial Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Visual Analogue Scale for pain</measure>
    <time_frame>before and after each intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The assessment will be done in the patient's first evaluation and after each intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and after each intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The assessment will be done in the patient's first evaluation and after each intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in range of motion of flexion and extension of the knee</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and after each intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The assessment will be done in the patient's first evaluation and after each intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Lequesne Functional Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and after each intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The assessment will be done in the patient's first evaluation and after each intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Get Up and Go Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and after each intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The assessment will be done in the patient's first evaluation and after each intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">125</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis, Knee</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stretching</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Seven stretching exercises for lower limbs during 24 sessions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo laser + Stretching</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>application of placebo laser therapy during nine sessions plus stretching exercises during 24 sessions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active laser + Stretching</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>application of active laser therapy during nine sessions plus stretching exercises during 24 sessions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active Laser</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Application of active laser only during 24 sessions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control group that will receive a small book with informations about knee osteoarthritis and postural orientation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>low intensity laser therapy (904nm)</intervention_name>
    <description>18 points of application of laser in the knee (frontal faces, lateral and medial)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active laser + Stretching</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Active Laser</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LaserPulse class II IBRAMED</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stretching exercises</intervention_name>
    <description>7 stretching exercises for lower limbs lasting 30 seconds with 4 repetitions</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stretching</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo laser + Stretching</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Active laser + Stretching</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo laser therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>18 points of application of placebo laser in the knee (frontal faces, lateral and medial)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo laser + Stretching</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LaserPulse class II IBRAMED</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical diagnosis of knee osteoarthritis

          -  functional reduction in the last three months

          -  osteoarthritis´s grade 2-4  (Kellgren and Lawrence, 1957)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  cancer

          -  insulin dependent diabetes

          -  symptomatic hip osteoarthritis

          -  impossibility of performing the evaluation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sarah Rubia F Meneses</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Sao Paulo</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Specialized rehabilitation service</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taboao da Serra</city>
        <state>Sao Paulo</state>
        <zip>55</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sarah Meneses</last_name>
      <phone>41388550</phone>
      <email>sarahmeneses@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 1, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 28, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
