<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="30251">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02089217</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Mayo IRB: 13-004051</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U01 NS080168</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>IDE: G130221</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02089217</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Carotid Revascularization for Primary Prevention of Stroke</brief_title>
  <acronym>CREST-2</acronym>
  <official_title>Carotid Revascularization for Primary Prevention of Stroke</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Thomas G. Brott, M.D.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Carotid revascularization for primary prevention of stroke (CREST-2) is two independent
      multicenter, randomized controlled trials of carotid revascularization and intensive medical
      management versus medical management alone in patients with asymptomatic high-grade carotid
      stenosis.  One trial will randomize patients in a 1:1 ratio to endarterectomy versus no
      endarterectomy and another will randomize patients in a 1:1 ratio to carotid stenting with
      embolic protection versus no stenting.  Medical management will be uniform for all
      randomized treatment groups and will be centrally directed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Prevention of stroke involves managing and treating risk factors. Most strokes are caused
      when blood flow to a portion of the brain is blocked. One place this often happens is in the
      carotid artery. This blockage is called atherosclerosis or hardening of the arteries.

      The purpose of this trial is to determine the best way to prevent strokes in people who have
      a high amount of blockage of their carotid artery but no stroke symptoms related to that
      blockage. Each eligible participant will be evaluated to determine which procedure(s) is
      best for him/her. All participants will receive intensive medical treatment.  In addition,
      participants will be randomized to receive the selected procedure or not.

      The trial will be conducted in the United States and Canada by physicians carefully selected
      on their ability to perform the procedures at low risk. Another key component of the trial
      is that important stroke risk factors, including hypertension, diabetes, high cholesterol,
      cigarette smoking, physical activity, and diet will be managed intensively.  Participants
      will remain in the study for 4 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke and death</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary outcome is the composite of stroke plus death within 30 days after randomization and ipsilateral stroke thereafter up to 4 years.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive Function</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The assess if MEDICAL management differs from CAS, and differs from CEA, to maintain the level of cognitive function at the 4-year assessment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Major Stroke</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>if there are treatment differences in the incidence of major stroke at 4-years among all arms of the study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect modification</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Potential effect modification of the CAS or CEA versus MEDICAL differences, based on patient age, sex, severity of carotid stenosis, restenosis, risk factor level, and duration of asymptomatic period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2480</enrollment>
  <condition>Carotid Stenosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Carotid Endarterectomy (CEA)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Carotid endarterectomy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Carotid Stenting (CAS)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Carotid stenting</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Medical</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intensive medical management</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carotid endarterectomy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Carotid Endarterectomy (CEA)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carotid stenting</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Carotid Stenting (CAS)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        General Inclusion Criteria

          1. Patients ≥ 35 years old.

          2. Carotid stenosis defined as: stenosis ≥ 70% by angiography (NASCET Criteria); or by
             DUS with ≥ 70% stenosis defined by a peak systolic velocity of at least 230 cm/s and
             an end diastolic velocity ≥ 100 cm/s, or internal carotid/ common carotid artery peak
             systolic velocity ratio ≥ 4.0, or by a peak systolic velocity on DUS ≥ 230 cm/s plus
             CTA or MRA confirmation.

          3. No medical history of stroke or TIA ipsilateral to the stenosis within 180 days of
             randomization.  Life-long asymptomatic patients will be defined as having no medical
             history of stroke or transient ischemic attack and negative responses to all of the
             symptom items on the Questionnaire for Verifying Stroke-free Status (QVSS).

          4. Patients must have a modified Rankin score of 0 or 1 at the time of informed consent.

          5. Women must not be of childbearing potential or, if of childbearing potential, have a
             negative pregnancy test prior to randomization.

          6. Patients must agree to comply with all protocol-specified follow-up appointments.

          7. Patients must sign a consent form that has been approved by the local governing
             Institutional Review Board (IRB)/Medical Ethics Committee (MEC) of the respective
             clinical site.

          8. Randomization to treatment group will apply to only one carotid artery for patients
             with bilateral carotid stenosis.  Management of the non-randomized stenosis may be
             done in accordance with local PI recommendation.  Treatment of the non-study internal
             carotid artery must take place at least 30 days prior to randomization, or at least
             30 days after the study procedure is completed.

          9. Carotid stenosis must be treatable with CEA, CAS, or either procedures.

        General Exclusion Criteria

          1. Intolerance or allergic reaction to a study medication without a suitable
             alternative.

          2. GI hemorrhage within 1 month prior to enrollment that would preclude antiplatelet
             therapy.

          3. Major ipsilateral stroke in the past with substantial residual disability (mRS ≥ 2)
             that is likely to confound study outcomes.

          4. Severe dementia.

          5. Intracranial hemorrhage within the past 12 months.

          6. Neurologic illness characterized by fleeting or fixed neurologic deficits that cannot
             be distinguished from TIA or stroke.

          7. Patient objects to future blood transfusions.

          8. Platelet count &lt; 100,000/microliter, uncorrected INR &gt; 1.5, bleeding time &gt; 1 minute
             beyond upper limit normal (at screening), or history of heparin-induced
             thrombocytopenia.

          9. Anticoagulation with Phenprocoumon, warfarin, or a direct thrombin inhibitor.

         10. Chronic atrial fibrillation.

         11. Any episode of atrial fibrillation within the past 6 months or history of paroxysmal
             atrial fibrillation that is deemed to require chronic anticoagulation.

         12. Other high-risk cardiac sources of emboli, including left ventricular aneurysm,
             severe cardiomyopathy, aortic or mitral mechanical heart valve, severe calcific
             aortic stenosis (valve area &lt; 1.0 cm2), endocarditis, moderate to severe mitral
             stenosis, left atrial thrombus, or any intracardiac mass.

         13. Unstable angina defined as rest angina with ECG changes that is not amenable to
             revascularization (patients should undergo planned coronary revascularization at
             least 30 days before randomization).

         14. Ejection fraction &lt; 30% or admission for heart failure in prior 6 months.

         15. Respiratory insufficiency with life expectancy &lt; 4 years or FEV1&lt; 30% of predicted
             value (example, diagnosed malignancy).

         16. Any major surgery, major trauma, revascularization procedure, or acute coronary
             syndrome within the past 3 months.

         17. Serum creatinine ≥ 2.5 mg/dl or estimated GFR ≤ 50cc/min (at screening).

         18. Major (non-carotid) surgery/procedures planned within 3 months after enrollment.

         19. Currently listed or being evaluated for major organ transplantation (i.e. heart,
             lung, liver, kidney).

         20. Actively participating in another drug or device trial that has not completed
             follow-up.

         21. Inability to understand and cooperate with study procedures or provide informed
             consent.

         22. Non-atherosclerotic carotid stenosis (dissection, fibromuscular dysplasia, or
             stenosis following radiation therapy).

         23. Previous ipsilateral CEA or CAS.

         24. Ipsilateral internal or common carotid artery occlusion.

         25. Intra-carotid floating thrombus.

         26. Ipsilateral intracranial aneurysm &gt; 5mm.

         27. WHO Class III obesity (BMI &gt; 40 kg/m2).

         28. Contra-lateral common or internal carotid artery occlusion.

        Specific carotid endarterectomy exclusion criteria

        Patients who are being considered for revascularization by CEA must not have any of the
        following criteria:

          1. Serious adverse reaction to anesthesia not able to be overcome by pre-medication.

          2. Coronary artery disease with two or more proximal or major diseased coronary arteries
             with greater than or equal to 70% stenosis that have not, or cannot, be
             revascularized prior to CEA.

          3. Any of the following anatomical exclusions for CEA: radical neck dissection;
             surgically inaccessible lesions (e.g. above cervical spine level 2 (C2)); adverse
             neck anatomy that limits surgical exposure (e.g. spinal immobility - inability to
             flex neck beyond neutral or kyphotic deformity, or short obese neck); presence of
             tracheostomy stoma; laryngeal nerve palsy contralateral to target vessel; or previous
             extracranial-intracranial or subclavian bypass procedure ipsilateral to the target
             vessel.

          4. Known allergy to heparin or bivalirudin.

          5. For age &lt; 50 years, CAS is the favored procedure. However, the CREST results for
             asymptomatic patients showed wide confidence intervals about the point estimates
             comparing CAS and CEA.  Accordingly, choice of CEA or CAS cannot be mandated;
             individual patient characteristics and preferences may supersede guidelines based
             upon patient age. (See Section 8.1.3 for more details)

        Specific Carotid Artery Stenting Exclusion Criteria

        Patients who are being considered for revascularization by CAS must not have any of the
        following criteria:

          1. Allergy to intravascular contrast dye not amenable to pre-medication.

          2. Occlusive or critical ilio-femoral disease including severe tortuosity or stenosis
             that necessitates additional endovascular procedures to facilitate access to the
             aortic arch or that prevents safe and expeditious femoral access to the aortic arch.

          3. Angiographic, CT, MR or ultrasound evidence of severe atherosclerosis of the aortic
             arch or origin of the innominate or common carotid arteries.

          4. Type III, calcified aortic arch anatomy.

          5. Qualitative characteristics of stenosis and stenosis-length of the carotid
             bifurcation (common carotid) and/or ipsilateral external carotid artery, in
             combination with elements of the exclusions # 3 and 4 that preclude safe sheath
             placement.

          6. Angulation or tortuosity (≥ 90 degree) of the innominate and common carotid artery
             that precludes safe, expeditious sheath placement or that will transmit a severe loop
             to the internal carotid after sheath placement.

          7. Severe angulation or tortuosity of the internal carotid artery (including calyceal
             origin from the carotid bifurcation) that precludes safe deployment of embolic
             protection device or stent.  Severe tortuosity is defined as 2 or more ≥ 90 degree
             angles within 4 cm of the target stenosis.

          8. Excessive circumferential calcification of the stenotic lesion defined as &gt; 3mm
             thickness of calcification seen in orthogonal views on fluoroscopy.

          9. Anatomic considerations such as tortuosity, arch anatomy, and calcification must be
             evaluated even more carefully in elderly subjects (≥ 70 years).

         10. &quot;String sign&quot; of the ipsilateral common or internal carotid artery.

         11. Lesions &gt; 20 mm in length.

         12. Target ICA vessel reference diameter &lt; 4.0 mm or &gt; 9.0 mm. Target ICA measurements
             may be made from angiography of the contralateral artery. The reference diameter must
             be appropriate for the devices to be used.

         13. Inability to deploy or utilize an FDA-approved Embolic Protection Device (EPD).

         14. For age &gt; 74 years, CEA is the favored procedure. However, the CREST results for
             asymptomatic patients showed wide confidence intervals about the point estimates
             comparing CAS and CEA.  Accordingly, choice of CEA or CAS cannot be mandated;
             individual patient characteristics and preferences may supersede guidelines based
             upon patient age)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas G. Brott, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James F. Meschia, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brajesh K. Lal, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Maryland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>George Howard, DrPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>CREST-2 Administrative Center</last_name>
    <phone>844-956-1826</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 13, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Thomas G. Brott, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>asymptomatic</keyword>
  <keyword>carotid</keyword>
  <keyword>stent</keyword>
  <keyword>endarterectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>embolic protection</keyword>
  <keyword>medical management</keyword>
  <keyword>hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>hyperlipidemia</keyword>
  <keyword>cognition</keyword>
  <keyword>risk factor control</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carotid Stenosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
