<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="158036">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01859793</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Merck-50600</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01859793</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Randomized, Crossover Design Study of Acute and Chronic Effects of Sitagliptin on Endothelial Function in Humans With Type 2 Diabetes on Background Metformin Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Crossover Design Study of Acute and Chronic Effects of Sitagliptin on Endothelial Function in Humans With Type 2 Diabetes on Background Metformin</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical College of Wisconsin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical College of Wisconsin</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Research Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study is being performed to determine whether sitagliptin, a dipeptidyl peptidase-4
      inhibitor, both acutely and chronically improves blood vessel function.  Patients with type
      2 diabetes who are on metformin will be enrolled in this study for up to 22 weeks in this
      double blinded cross over study where they will receive a sitagliptin pill once a day for 8
      weeks and during a separate 8 weeks receive a matching placebo pill.  The treatment periods
      are divided by a 4 week period.  Blood vessel function will be measured by ultrasound before
      and after a single dose of sitagliptin and placebo, as well as after 8 weeks of treatment
      with each.  Blood will also be taken to measure blood markers of inflammation at each time
      the ultrasounds are performed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We plan to recruit 38 patients with T2DM for this single center, double blind randomized,
      interventional crossover trial comparing sitagliptin (100 mg/day) to matching placebo.  We
      have chosen placebo over a comparator for this study as our goal is to determine whether
      sitagliptin both improves glycemic control and endothelial function, properties not shared
      by other popular classes of agents like sulfonylureas.   Subjects will be randomized with a
      1:1 allocation ratio to either sitagliptin 1st or placebo 1st.

      The study have 5 total visits.  Subjects who pass a phone screen will be invited to a
      screening visit for study eligibility (Visit 1)   Informed consent will be reviewed; a
      unique study number will be assigned once written informed consent is obtained (no subject
      will be assigned more than 1 allocation number); relevant participant medical history will
      be recorded including currently prescribed medications; anthropometric measurements will be
      taken (height, weight, and waist circumference in metric units) and blood pressure will be
      recorded (measured in triplicate and averaged).  Subjects will be allowed to take their
      blood pressure medication on the morning of their screening visit, but not the mornings of
      any of the other study visits to limit the acute influence of these medications on
      endothelial function.  If the potential participant qualifies for the study, he/she will be
      randomized either to receive sitagliptin 1st (100 mg/day) or matching placebo.  Prior to
      receiving either of set of pills, subjects will return to the study center within
      approximately 1-2 weeks of the screening visit to undergo initial tests of endothelial
      function and receive their pills.  Prior to all study visits except screening, subjects will
      also be asked to refrain from any vigorous physical activity (no weight lifting, jogging or
      any activity vigorous than walking) 24 hours to reduce the risk of fasting hypoglycemia
      during the study visits. Subjects will also be asked to fast for 6-8 hours prior to the
      visit to limit the acute dietary influences on vascular endothelial function.  At Visit 2,
      endothelial function will determined by brachial artery reactivity testing  prior to and
      following a single dose of 100 mg of sitagliptin or matching placebo depending on the arm
      to which the subject was randomized.  Blood samples will also be taken at this visit for
      systemic measurements of endothelial cell activation/inflammation (VCAM-1 and ICAM-1) prior
      to and 2 hours following acute drug administration.   These will be measured at the
      indicated time points using commercially available kits.

      Endothelial function, like the blood samples, will be measured just prior to medication
      administration and then 2 hours following medication administration by brachial artery
      reactivity testing as described in Section D.3.  The 2 hour time from was chose in given the
      plasma levels of sitagliptin appear to peak 2 hours following dose administration.32  At the
      end of this visit, subjects will be given a 9 week supply of the study pills (sitagliptin or
      matching placebo) as dispensed by the Froedtert Hospital Investigational Pharmacy, and
      scheduled to return for Visit 3 approximately 8 weeks following Visit 2.  Subjects will be
      asked to not take any study medication for the 24 hours prior to Visit 3.  At Visit 3,
      subjects will undergo repeat testing of endothelial function.  Following this study visit,
      subjects will remain off study pills until they return for Visit 4 approximately 4 weeks
      following Visit 3.  Visit 4 repeats Visit 2 except subjects will receive the set of pills to
      which they had been randomized to receive second.  Subjects will return to the study center
      for Visit 5 approximately 8 weeks after Visit 4.  Visit 5 is identical to Visit 3.   Subject
      adherence will be determined by pill counts performed by MCW Translational Research Unit
      nursing staff who will perform all pill accounting.   All medication dispensation will be
      handled by the Froedtert Hospital Investigational Drug Pharmacy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacodynamics Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Brachial Artery Flow Mediated Dilation</measure>
    <time_frame>Change before and after 8 weeks after daily dosing</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A measurement of endothelial function in humans</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Brachial Artery Flow Mediated Dilation</measure>
    <time_frame>Change before and after 2 hours of single dose of medication</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measurement of endothelial function</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating inflammatory markers ICAM-1 and VCAM-1</measure>
    <time_frame>Change before and after 8 weeks after daily dosing of medication</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating inflammatory markers ICAM-1 and VCAM-1</measure>
    <time_frame>Change before and after 2 hours a single dose of medication</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">38</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Atherosclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Endothelial Function</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Matching Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Matching Placebo for Sitagliptin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sitagliptin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>100mg pill, PO administered once daily.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>sitagliptin</intervention_name>
    <description>100 mg pill, administered once/day orally</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sitagliptin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Januvia</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Matching Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult age 21-70 years of age.

          2. Diagnosis of type 2 diabetes by a physician as defined by the American Diabetes
             Association standard criteria: 1) Fasting Plasma glucose at or above 126 mg/dL 2) a
             two-hour value in an oral glucose tolerance test at or above 200 mg/dL, or 3) a
             random plasma glucose concentration 200 mg/dL in the presence of symptoms, or 4)
             glycosylated hemoglobin greater than or equal to 6.5%.

          3. On stable metformin therapy for at least 6 weeks prior to enrollment.

          4. Glycosylated Hemoglobin  ≥6.5% and ≤ 9.5%.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of stroke, peripheral arterial disease, or coronary artery disease (as
             defined by the presence of at least one coronary stenosis ≥ 50% on angiography or by
             confirmed history of  myocardial infarction by standard criteria.)

          2. Evidence of other evident major illness including chronic renal insufficiency
             (creatinine clearance less than 60 mL/min),chronic liver disease  (AST or ALT greater
             than 2.5 x normal), or cancer currently undergoing systemic therapy or had systemic
             therapy for cancer within 1 year of enrollment.

          3. Pregnancy as determined by urinary beta-HCG test

          4. Illicit drug use (heroin, cocaine etc) in the past 1 year.

          5. Alcohol abuse, defined as the equivalent of 14 beers/week for a man or 7 beers/week
             for a woman

          6. History of allergy to DPP-4 inhibitors at the time of screening/enrollment

          7. Prior history of pancreatitis

          8. Patients currently on insulin or sulfonylurea therapy.

          9. Patients currently on digoxin.

             -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael E Widlansky, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Allison Coulliard, BS</last_name>
    <phone>414-805-3148</phone>
    <email>acouillard@mcw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical College of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Gutterman, MD</last_name>
      <email>grants@mcw.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael E Widlansky, MD MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical College of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Allison Couillard, BS</last_name>
      <phone>414-805-3148</phone>
      <email>acouillard@mcw.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 28, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 17, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael E. Widlansky</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>dipeptidyl peptidase-4 inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>endothelium, vascular</keyword>
  <keyword>diabetes type 2</keyword>
  <keyword>nitric oxide</keyword>
  <keyword>inflammation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Sitagliptin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dipeptidyl-Peptidase IV Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
