<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="117531">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01734369</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130015</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-E-0015</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01734369</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Environmental Risk Factors for Myositis in Military Personnel</brief_title>
  <official_title>Environmental Risk Factors for the Development of Myositis in Military Personnel</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences (NIEHS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Myositis is a rare disease in which the body   s immune cells attack the muscle tissue.
           It can cause muscle weakness, swelling, and pain. It can develop in people with no
           history of muscle problems. Environmental exposures may determine who develops
           myositis. Genes may also affect development of the disease.

        -  Some people who serve in the military develop myositis. However, other military
           personnel do not. Researchers want to compare military personnel with and without
           myositis. They will look for common factors that might have led to the disease.

      Objectives:

      - To study environmental risk factors for myositis in military personnel.

      Eligibility:

        -  Military personnel who developed myositis during their period of service.

        -  Healthy military personnel who do not have myositis or another autoimmune disease.

      Design:

        -  Participants will have a physical exam and medical history.

        -  Participants will fill out forms about environmental exposures, particularly while in
           the military. The questions will ask about past infections, vaccines and medications,
           and personal habits. They will also ask about participants    occupations during
           military service and their deployments.

        -  Participants will also provide blood samples for study.

        -  No treatment will be provided as part of this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Myositis, an autoimmune muscle disease, likely develops as a result of environmental
      exposures in genetically susceptible persons. Preliminary data suggest a trend for an
      increasing incidence in myositis in military personnel over the last decade for unknown
      reasons. Although a few environmental exposures have been preliminarily associated with
      myositis in the civilian population, these have not been confirmed.  In addition, no study
      has assessed exposures that might result in the development of myositis in military
      personnel. Military personnel experience a number of intense, unique exposures, often over a
      relatively short interval, which include different stresses, novel vaccines, distinct
      occupational exposures, battlefield injuries and unique chemicals during field deployment,
      that differ from those exposures in non-military populations. Therefore, we propose a
      protocol that consists of three complementary approaches to attempt to determine the
      environmental factors associated with the development of myositis in active duty military
      personnel and an initial understanding of the possible mechanisms involved. In the first
      approach, we will assess risk factors in a case-control study of 300 patients who developed
      myositis while on active duty by comparing them to 1500 active duty military personnel
      (randomly selected, but matched 5:1 by gender, race, and age and military service within 10
      years) who have not been diagnosed with an autoimmune disease or chronic muscle disease. For
      this first approach, we will analyze existing military databases for information on
      medications, vaccines, infections, co-existing medical conditions, military occupations,
      deployments, and worldwide active duty locations. In the second case-control approach, we
      will attempt to define environmental factors associated with the development of myositis
      that developed in military personnel (n=150) by comparing them to 150 similarly matched
      military personnel who have not been diagnosed with an autoimmune disease or chronic muscle
      disease. This second approach will differ from the first approach, in that subjects will be
      prospectively enrolled and assessed during a single clinic visit to confirm diagnoses and
      examine patient questionnaires on focused environmental exposures, including those not
      captured in the military databases. A third laboratory approach will identify, in an
      exploratory study, the global DNA methylation epigenetic changes, microRNA and mRNA profiles
      in peripheral blood and muscle tissues from 18 subjects (six PM and six DM compared to six
      non-myositis controls enrolled in the second approach) and assess the effects of selected
      environmental exposures on these parameters. These complementary approaches should enhance
      the understanding of environmental factors and possible mechanisms associated with the
      development of myositis in the military, and provide insights into environmental risk
      factors that may also be relevant to the development of myositis in non-military
      populations.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>N/A</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Military Myositis Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Time of enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Dermatomyositis</condition>
  <condition>Adult Polymyositis</condition>
  <condition>Inclusion Body Myositis</condition>
  <condition>Myositis</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  ELIGIBILITY  CRITERIA:

        For Aim 1 of the study:

        The inclusion criteria for myositis subjects are:

        -Diagnosis of PM, DM or IBM during military service.  Subjects may be active duty or no
        longer active duty personnel.  A matrix diagnosis of myositis will be based on ICD-9
        codes, laboratory tests and medical records in an attempt to match criteria for probable
        or definite PM, DM or IBM

        The inclusion criteria for matched control subjects are:

        -The same gender, race, age within 10 years, and service in the military within 10 years
        as the myositis subject.

        The exclusion criteria for control subjects are:

        -A matrix diagnosis of autoimmune or chronic muscle disease based on ICD-9 codes and
        medical records (Appendix 2).

        For Aims 2 and 3 of the study:

        The inclusion criteria for enrollment of myositis subjects are:

          -  Diagnosis of myositis during military service based on criteria for probable or
             definite PM or DM, or clinically or pathologically defined or possible IBM.  Subjects
             may be active duty or no longer active duty personnel.

          -  Able and willing to give informed consent, to complete the questionnaires and to
             donate blood samples.

        The inclusion criteria for matched controls are:

          -  Persons with military experience attending the same clinic or hospital as the
             myositis subject to which they are matched, or if not available, volunteers from the
             general community (such as other participating military or VA hospitals, private
             HCPs, or the NIH Normal volunteer program), gender- race- and age- (within 10 years)
             and military service period (within 10 years) matched to the myositis subject.

          -  Controls should be without a recognized autoimmune or chronic muscle disease, able
             and willing to give informed consent, to complete the questionnaires and to donate
             blood samples.

        The exclusion criteria for all protocol subjects are:

          -  Medical illness that in the judgment of the investigators does not allow safe blood
             draws or other clinical evaluations needed for study participation.

          -  Chronic muscle diseases other than idiopathic inflammatory myopathy (i.e. infectious,
             dystrophic, metabolic, toxic or drug-induced myopathies).

          -  Cognitive impairment.

          -  Not able or willing to give informed consent.

          -  Age &lt; 18 years.

        There are no gender or ethnic restrictions to enrollment in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Frederick W Miller, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences (NIEHS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>James Ridley</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-2348</phone>
    <email>ridleyjt@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-E-0015.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bacarese-Hamilton T, Mezzasoma L, Ardizzoni A, Bistoni F, Crisanti A. Serodiagnosis of infectious diseases with antigen microarrays. J Appl Microbiol. 2004;96(1):10-7.</citation>
    <PMID>14678154</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aggarwal R, Lucas M, Fertig N, Oddis CV, Medsger TA Jr. Anti-U3 RNP autoantibodies in systemic sclerosis. Arthritis Rheum. 2009 Apr;60(4):1112-8.</citation>
    <PMID>19333934</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bach JF. The effect of infections on susceptibility to autoimmune and allergic diseases. N Engl J Med. 2002 Sep 19;347(12):911-20. Review. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>12239261</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 23, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 22, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dermatomyositis</keyword>
  <keyword>Inclusion Body Myositis</keyword>
  <keyword>Myositis</keyword>
  <keyword>Polymyositis</keyword>
  <keyword>Military</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dermatomyositis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myositis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Polymyositis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myositis, Inclusion Body</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
