<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="3268">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02027701</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IgPro20_3004</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-004157-24</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02027701</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Extension Study of Maintenance Treatment With Subcutaneous Immunoglobulin (IgPro20) for Chronic Inflammatory Demyelinating Polyneuropathy (CIDP)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Multicenter, Open-label Extension Study to Investigate the Long-term Safety and Efficacy of IgPro20 in Maintenance Treatment of Chronic Inflammatory Demyelinating Polyneuropathy (CIDP) in Subjects Completing Study IgPro20_3003</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>CSL Behring</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>CSL Behring</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is an extension study to the pivotal study IgPro20_3003 (NCT01545076). The
      purpose of this extension study is to investigate the long-term treatment of CIDP with
      IgPro20, with regard to safety and efficacy.

      Subjects who have participated in the subcutaneous (SC) Treatment Period of Study
      IgPro20_3003 (NCT01545076) will have the option to receive open-label high-dose IgPro20 (0.4
      g/kg bodyweight [bw]) weekly for 24 weeks. After this period, the IgPro20 dose will be
      reduced to low-dose IgPro20 (0.2 g/kg bw) weekly for 24 weeks. Subjects relapsing on
      high-dose IgPro20 will either remain on high dose or be discontinued, depending on
      investigator's judgment. Subjects relapsing on low-dose IgPro20 will either return to
      high-dose IgPro20 immediately or be discontinued, depending on investigator's judgment.
      Subjects returning to high-dose IgPro20 will continue on high-dose until they have completed
      a total of 48 weeks of IgPro20 treatment. If subjects do not successfully recover from CIDP
      relapse within 4 weeks, they will be withdrawn.

      The treatment duration will be up to 48 weeks, followed by a completion visit (week 49) and
      a follow-up phone call (week 53).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall rate of adverse events (AEs) per infusion - high-dose IgPro20</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall rate of AEs per infusion during high-dose IgPro20 treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of adverse events (AEs) per infusion by severity, causality, and seriousness - high-dose IgPro20</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with adverse events (AEs) - high-dose IgPro20</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of subjects with AEs, overall and by severity, causality and seriousness, during high-dose IgPro20 treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of adverse events (AEs) per infusion - low-dose IgPro20</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 28 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Rate of AEs per infusion, overall and by severity, causality and seriousness, during low-dose IgPro20 treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with adverse events (AEs) - low-dose IgPro20</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 28 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of subjects with AEs, overall and by severity, causality and seriousness, during low-dose IgPro20 treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total Inflammatory Neuropathy Cause and Treatment (INCAT) score at all study visits</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 49 weeks (baseline [Week 1], Weeks 2, 9, 17, 25, 33, 41, and at completion visit)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first CIDP relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 49 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Time to first CIDP relapse based on adjusted INCAT score, using the Kaplan-Meier estimator. Relapse is defined as an increase of at least 1 INCAT score point (except for the increase from 0 to 1 in the upper limb score only).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Inflammatory Demyelinating Polyneuropathy (CIDP)</condition>
  <condition>Polyradiculoneuropathy, Chronic Inflammatory Demyelinating</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IgPro20</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>20% liquid formulation (200 mg/mL) of human normal immunoglobulin for SC use administered SC weekly: for 24 weeks at 0.4 g/kg bw (high-dose IgPro20), then for 24 weeks at 0.2 g/kg bw (low-dose IgPro20). Subjects who experience CIDP relapse on high-dose IgPro20  will either continue on high-dose IgPro20 until week 48 or are withdrawn, according to investigator's judgment. Subjects who experience CIDP relapse on low-dose IgPro20  will return to high-dose IgPro20 immediately and will continue on high-dose until they have completed a total of 48 weeks of IgPro20 treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IgPro20</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>IgPro20</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects having participated in the SC Treatment Period of pivotal study IgPro20_3003
             (NCT01545076).

          -  Written informed consent for study participation obtained before undergoing any
             study-specific procedures.

          -  If treatment for CIDP is required, it has to include Immunoglobulin G (IgGs).

          -  Subjects who completed study IgPro20_3003 before study IgPro20_3004 study was open
             for enrollment at the site must be enrolled no later than 8 weeks after study
             IgPro20_3004 is open for enrollment at the site.

          -  Subjects who completed study IgPro20_3003 after study IgPro20_3004 study was open for
             enrollment at the site must be enrolled no later than 8 weeks after the completion
             visit of study IgPro20_3003.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any polyneuropathy of other causes

          -  Any other disease (mainly neurological or chronic orthopedic) that has caused
             neurological symptoms or may interfere with treatment or outcome assessments

          -  Severe diseases and conditions that are likely to interfere with evaluation of the
             study product or satisfactory conduct of the study

          -  History of thrombotic episodes within the 2 years prior to enrolment

          -  Known allergic or other severe reactions to blood products including intolerability
             to previous IVIG (normal human immunoglobulin for intravenous administration) and/or
             SCIG (subcutaneous immunoglobulin)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Prof. Dr. Ivo N. van Schaik</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Academic Medical Center, University of Amsterdam</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Clinical Trial Registration Coordinator</last_name>
    <email>clinicaltrials@cslbehring.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 11, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 3, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Polyradiculoneuropathy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Polyneuropathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Polyradiculoneuropathy, Chronic Inflammatory Demyelinating</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
