<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="36751">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01813721</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20110146</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01813721</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study Investigating How Physicians Assess the Risk of Patients Developing Febrile Neutropenia During Chemotherapy.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Study to Investigate Which Clinical Risk Factors Are Considered by Physicians When Conducting Overall Febrile Neutropenia Risk Assessments for Patients Receiving Chemotherapy With an Intermediate (10% - 20%) Febrile Neutropenia Risk.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Amgen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Amgen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Australia: Human Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>Austria: Federal Office for Safety in Health Care</authority>
    <authority>Canada: Ethics Review Committee</authority>
    <authority>France: Comité consultatif sur le traitement de l'information en matière de recherche dans le domaine de la santé</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Ethics Commission</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <authority>Greece: Local Hospital Scientific Boards</authority>
    <authority>Ireland: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>Italy: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>Poland: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>Romania: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>Romania: National Medicines Agency</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Agencia Española de Medicamentos y Productos Sanitarios</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective observational study investigating how physicians assess the risk of
      febrile neutropenia (FN) developing in patients who will receive chemotherapy.

      Approximately 150-200 investigators will take part in about 100 sites in Europe, Canada and
      Australia. Approximately 1000 subjects will be studied, all of whom will have non-small cell
      lung cancer (NSCLC), small cell lung cancer (SCLC), non-Hodgkin's lymphoma (NHL) or breast
      cancer and will be due to receive one of the specific chemotherapy regimens of interest.

      Investigators' approach to FN risk assessment will be studied using lists of possible risk
      factors they may consider during their assessment. Investigators will be asked to select and
      rank the factors they consider the most important when assessing the overall FN risk of a
      subject and when making the decision whether to treat with granulocyte-colony stimulating
      factor (G-CSF) primary prophylaxis (PP). They will be asked to make these selections based
      initially on their own routine clinical practise and subsequently relating specifically to
      each subject recruited.

      This is a non-interventional study that involves no procedures outside normal care for the
      subjects; all data collection will be completed prior to chemotherapy administration.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Although a formal hypothesis will not be tested in this observational study, it is
      hypothesized that the clinical risk factors ranked as the most important when conducting FN
      risk assessments by investigators are aligned with international guidelines and published
      data. Also, that the investigator's decision to treat with G-CSF PP is influenced by
      clinical and non-clinical risk factors (such as distance from site, estimated subject
      compliance, and access to fully reimbursed G-CSF).

      Study Design: Prior to identifying eligible subjects, Investigators will be registered and
      will record baseline information. During this Baseline Investigator Assessment investigators
      will be provided with two lists of risk factors. Investigators must rank selected risk
      factors that they consider to be the most important when assessing 1) overall FN risk (only
      scientific factors will be included), and 2) when deciding on whether G-CSF PP treatment
      will be used or not (this list will also contain non clinical factors). They will also
      record their own FN risk intervention threshold, which is  the FN risk threshold score at
      which they would use G-CSF PP in their usual clinical practice.

      Investigators will then prospectively and sequentially identify eligible subjects with NHL,
      breast or lung cancer who are due to initiate one of the permitted standard dose
      chemotherapy regimens listed in the protocol. The permitted chemotherapy regimens have an
      estimated intermediate FN risk (10%-20%) documented in published data and/or international
      guidelines.

      For each enrolled subject, Investigators will complete a Subject Assessment prior to the
      start of their chemotherapy. They will be provided with the same two lists of risk factors
      as in the Baseline Assessment and asked to complete them based on each specific subject.
      Investigators must rank selected risk factors that they consider to be the most important
      when assessing 1) overall FN risk (only scientific factors will be included), and 2) when
      deciding on whether G-CSF PP treatment will be used or not. They will also document their
      final estimated FN risk score as a percentage based on the subject's medical history and
      standard of care (SOC) assessments (their routine practice for assessing this risk), and a
      decision as to whether G-CSF PP will be administered. Investigators will record which type
      of G-CSF they plan to use if one will be used.

      End of Study for a subject will occur once these activities have been completed, and a
      prescription for the first cycle of chemotherapy has been written. The subject data
      collected will only be historical subject information and laboratory data from SOC
      assessments performed prior to beginning chemotherapy treatment. No data will be collected
      after the initiation of chemotherapy.

      The approach to the statistical analysis will be generally descriptive in nature. The
      primary analysis will be conducted at two levels; investigator level and the subject level.
      It is expected that the opinions of investigators at a single site (that is, a department
      within a cancer treatment centre) will be correlated. Also, that the opinions about subjects
      from a single investigator will be more alike than subjects of other investigators;
      adjustments will be made in the analyses to account for this. Confidence intervals for the
      investigator level analysis and the subject level data will obtained from Multi-level
      Modelling (MLM) to allow for the expected intra-site and intra-investigator correlation of
      investigators within sites and subjects within investigator. In general, categorical data
      will be summarised by the number and percentage of subjects in each category. Continuous
      data will be summarised by mean, standard deviation, median, lower and upper quartiles,
      minimum and maximum values. Two-sided exact 95% confidence intervals (obtained using MLM)
      will be presented, where appropriate.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case-Only, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of times that each FN risk factor is ranked as important during the Baseline Investigator Assessment; occurence of age and chemotherapy regimen among the ranked risk factors are of particular interest</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline, prior to subject enrolment.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of times that each FN risk factor is ranked as important during the Subject Assessment; occurence of age and chemotherapy regimen among the ranked risk factors are of particular interest</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days post-enrolment, prior to chemotherapy initiation.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of times each factor in the G-CSF PP decision is ranked as important during the Baseline Physician Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline, prior to subject enrolment.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of times each factor in the G-CSF PP decision is ranked as important during the Baseline Investigator Assessment by investigator characteristics and country</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline, prior to subject enrolment.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of times each factor in the G-CSF PP decision is ranked as important during the Subject Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days post-enrolment, prior to chemotherapy initiation.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of times each factor in the G-CSF PP decision is ranked as important during the Subject Assessment by investigator characteristics, tumour type, and country</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days post-enrolment, prior to chemotherapy initiation.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of times each FN risk factor is ranked as important during the Baseline Investigator Assessment, by investigator characteristics and country</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline, prior to subject enrolment.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of times each FN risk factor is ranked as important during the Subject Assessment by investigator characteristics, tumour type, and country</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days post-enrolment, prior to chemotherapy initiation.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with an investigator-assessed FN risk at or above the investigator self-reported FN-risk intervention threshold that are receiving G-CSF PP</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days post-enrolment, prior to chemotherapy initiation.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1007</enrollment>
  <condition>Chemotherapy-induced Febrile Neutropenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <description>All patients enrolled</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Eligible subjects will have NHL, breast or lung cancer and be due to initiate one of the
        permitted standard dose chemotherapy regimens listed in the protocol (those with a
        documented intermediate FN risk of 10-20%). Subjects will be prospectively and
        sequentially identified by approximately 150-200 investigators during their clinics
        distribututed in 11 countries.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 18 years old

          -  Any stage NHL, small cell lung cancer (SCLC), non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC), or
             breast cancer initiating a new chemotherapy course

          -  Scheduled to receive one of the permitted standard dose chemotherapy regimens with an
             estimated intermediate (10%-20%) FN risk according to published data or guidelines
             (planned dose modifications +/-10% are allowable).

          -  Before any study-specific procedure, the appropriate written informed consent must be
             obtained where this is required by local regulations

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Ongoing or planned concurrent participation in any clinical study involving
             Investigational Product that has not been approved by the European Medicines Agency
             (EMA) or competent authority for any indication,

          -  Ongoing or planned concurrent participation in any clinical study where the
             administration of Colony Stimulating Factor (CSF) is determined by the protocol
             (clinical trials on an approved drug and observational trials are permitted as long
             as these do not mandate how neutropenia should be treated)

          -  Prior stem-cell transplantation (includes bone marrow transplantation)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Amgen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tweed Heads</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2485</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bendigo</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3550</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shepparton</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3630</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wodonga</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3690</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Eggenburg</city>
        <zip>3730</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Graz</city>
        <zip>8036</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leoben</city>
        <zip>8700</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vöcklabruck</city>
        <zip>4840</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wien</city>
        <zip>1090</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wien</city>
        <zip>1030</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moncton</city>
        <state>New Brunswick</state>
        <zip>E1C 6Z8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sault Ste. Marie</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>P6B 0A8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H2W 1T8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Alès Cédex</city>
        <zip>30103</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Arras</city>
        <zip>62000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Besançon Cedex</city>
        <zip>25030</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brest Cedex 2</city>
        <zip>29609</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Créteil</city>
        <zip>94010</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grenoble Cedex 9</city>
        <zip>38043</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille</city>
        <zip>13009</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montluçon</city>
        <zip>03100</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Neuilly sur Seine</city>
        <zip>92202</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nimes Cedex 2</city>
        <zip>30900</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pierre Bénite Cedex</city>
        <zip>69495</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Quentin</city>
        <zip>02321</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulon Cedex</city>
        <zip>83056</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Villefranche Sur Saone Cedex</city>
        <zip>69400</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>10317</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bonn</city>
        <zip>53111</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fulda</city>
        <zip>36043</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mainz</city>
        <zip>55131</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Neustadt/Sachsen</city>
        <zip>01844</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rostock</city>
        <zip>18107</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stralsund</city>
        <zip>18435</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Twistringen</city>
        <zip>27239</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <zip>11527</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <zip>18547</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <zip>11522</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <zip>11525</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chania</city>
        <zip>73300</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Larissa</city>
        <zip>41110</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nea Kifissia, Athens</city>
        <zip>14564</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Thessaloniki</city>
        <zip>57010</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Thessaloniki</city>
        <zip>54645</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Thessaloniki</city>
        <zip>54636</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cork</city>
        <country>Ireland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Galway</city>
        <country>Ireland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Catania</city>
        <zip>95122</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Firenze</city>
        <zip>50134</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Foggia</city>
        <zip>71100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Monza (MB)</city>
        <zip>20900</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pordenone</city>
        <zip>33170</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Reggio Calabria</city>
        <zip>89100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <zip>00128</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Torino</city>
        <zip>10125</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Varese</city>
        <zip>21100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bialystok</city>
        <zip>15-027</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bydgoszcz</city>
        <zip>85-796</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Elblag</city>
        <zip>82-300</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gdynia</city>
        <zip>81-519</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lodz</city>
        <zip>90-722</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lodz</city>
        <zip>93-509</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Szczecin</city>
        <zip>71-730</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Warszawa</city>
        <zip>02-781</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wroclaw</city>
        <zip>50-981</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Braila</city>
        <zip>810325</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brasov</city>
        <zip>500052</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brasov</city>
        <zip>500152</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bucharest</city>
        <zip>030171</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cluj Napoca</city>
        <zip>400352</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cluj-Napoca</city>
        <zip>400006</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Focsani</city>
        <zip>620165</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Iasi</city>
        <zip>700483</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Onesti</city>
        <zip>601048</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oradea</city>
        <zip>410469</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pitesti</city>
        <zip>110084</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Suceava</city>
        <zip>720237</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Timisoara</city>
        <zip>300167</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Timisoara</city>
        <zip>300239</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Huelva</city>
        <state>Andalucía</state>
        <zip>21005</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Malaga</city>
        <state>Andalucía</state>
        <zip>29010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zaragoza</city>
        <state>Aragón</state>
        <zip>50009</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palma de Mallorca</city>
        <state>Baleares</state>
        <zip>07198</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>La laguna</city>
        <state>Canarias</state>
        <zip>38320</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Avila</city>
        <state>Castilla León</state>
        <zip>05004</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valladolid</city>
        <state>Castilla León</state>
        <zip>47005</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <state>Cataluña</state>
        <zip>08003</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <state>Cataluña</state>
        <zip>08035</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <state>Comunidad Valenciana</state>
        <zip>46015</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pamplona</city>
        <state>Navarra</state>
        <zip>31008</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Austria</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Greece</country>
    <country>Ireland</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>Romania</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.amgentrials.com</url>
    <description>AmgenTrials clinical trials website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 8, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>NHL</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Lung Cancer</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fever</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neutropenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
