<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="164757">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01833897</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>6535</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01833897</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>NMDA Antagonists in Bipolar Depression</brief_title>
  <official_title>NMDA Antagonists in Bipolar Depression</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York State Psychiatric Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York State Psychiatric Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to test whether ketamine and D-cycloserine can be safely and
      effectively used for the treatment of depression. The investigators hypothesize that
      ketamine will serve as a rapid acting and safe antidepressant in patients with bipolar
      depression, and furthermore, that D-cycloserine will serve as an effective therapy following
      ketamine treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Bipolar disorder affects 2% of the population in the United States and the depressive phase
      contributes disproportionally to morbidity and mortality. At present, few approved
      treatments for bipolar depression are available, and have primarily depended on
      manipulations of brain monoaminergic systems. In contrast, recent studies suggest that the
      N-methyl-D-aspartate glutamate-receptor (NMDAR) antagonist, ketamine, may provide
      near-immediate relief for treatment resistant depression. Its utility during long-term
      treatment, however, is limited by its psychotomimetic potency and the need for repeated IV
      infusions. D-cycloserine (DCS) is an approved oral antibiotic for tuberculosis drug and a
      well-studied mixed agonist/antagonist at the NMDAR/glycine binding site. DCS showed
      preliminary evidence of efficacy in a pilot study. DCS would thus be practical from both a
      safety and route of administration perspective. The present study will explore the
      feasibility and safety of DCS for maintenance treatment following ketamine.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety, tolerability and efficacy of ketamine and d-cycloserine</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Vital signs will be closely monitored throughout ketamine infusion (60 min) and evaluation 2 consecutive days during phase.  If responding, will begin 8 week treatment with d-cycloserine with weekly visits.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Bipolar Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine and DCS treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard of Care: Subjects will receive treatment with either quetiapine or olanzapine-fluoxetine.  If after about 2 week, subjects are symptomatic, subjects will receive infusion of ketamine hydrochloride (0.5 mg/kg).  After the ketamine phase, subject who show improvement will begin an 8-week treatment of oral D-cycloserine.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard of Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Quetiapine and olanzapine-fluoxetine are the only two approved treatments for bipolar depression. Quetiapine dosing will follow the product label(Anon), and will be titrated over the first 4 days to the target dose of 300 mg. Olanzapine-fluoxetine dosing will also follow standard guidelines. Study physicians will use clinical judgment to choose between standard-of care treatments, and have the option to titrate standard-of-care within approved ranges, and to prescribe adjunctive benztropine and benzodiazepines if clinically indicated.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine and DCS treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Quetiapine</other_name>
    <other_name>Olanzapine</other_name>
    <other_name>fluoxetine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ketamine</intervention_name>
    <description>Ketamine administration will be carried out according to the methods as described by previous studies. Subjects will receive ketamine hydrochloride (0.5 mg/kg) intravenously during 60 minutes. This dosage was selected based on previous trials of ketamine for the treatment of refractory depression and bipolar depression. Vital signs (blood pressure, heart rate) will be closely monitored throughout the time of infusion. Subjects will be evaluated for 2 consecutive days during this phase; i.e. treatment days (day 1) and rating days (day 2). Non-responders to ketamine will not proceed into the DCS phase. Response will be a 25% improvement on the Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (HDRS).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine and DCS treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ketamine Hydrochloride</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>D-cycloserine</intervention_name>
    <description>Immediately after the ketamine infusion, subjects will begin an eight-week treatment of adjunctive DCS. DCS dosing will begin at 250 mg for three days→500mg (2 capsules)/day for 1 week → 750 mg (3 capsules)/day for 1 week → and 1000 mg (4 capsules)/day for the remainder of the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine and DCS treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>DCS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and female patients with Diagnostic and Statistical Manual, Version 4 (DSM-IV)
             diagnosis of bipolar disorder I or II, current major depressive episode without
             psychotic features, 18-60

          -  Insufficient therapeutic response during the current episode

          -  Medically stable for study participation

          -  Judged clinically not to be at significant suicide or violence risk

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of chronic psychosis or drug induced psychosis of any kind

          -  Current DSM-IV diagnosis of drug abuse/dependence in the last six months. Subjects
             must have a negative drug screen at baseline.

          -  Women will be excluded if they are pregnant lactating, or not either
             surgically-sterile or using appropriate methods of birth control.  Women must agree
             to continue using applicable birth control throughout the trial.  All women of
             child-bearing potential must have a negative urine pregnancy test

          -  Taking any medication contraindicated with ketamine or DCS (ethionamide, isoniazid)

          -  History of seizures, renal insufficiency or congestive heart failure

          -  History of clinically significant violence

          -  History of ketamine abuse/dependence or prior clinically significant adverse reaction
             to ketamine

          -  Current alcohol abuse or dependence

          -  Untreated hypertension

          -  Clinically abnormal liver function tests (LFTs), thyroid, renal function or anemia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joshua T Kantrowitz, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>New York State Psychiatric Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joshua T Kantrowitz, MD</last_name>
    <phone>646-774-6738</phone>
    <email>kantrow@nyspi.columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York State Psychiatric Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joshua T Kantrowitz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 19, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bipolar Disorder</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Bipolar Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ketamine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluoxetine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Quetiapine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Olanzapine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cycloserine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
