<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="46957">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01970527</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>9031</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-01757</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>9031</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA015704</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01970527</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Stereotactic Body Radiation Therapy and Ipilimumab in Treating Patients With Stage IV Melanoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>RADVAX: A Stratified Phase I/II Dose Escalation Trial of Stereotactic Body Radiotherapy Followed by Ipilimumab in Metastatic Melanoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Washington</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I/II trial studies the side effects and best dose of stereotactic body
      irradiation (SBRT) and to see how well it works when given together with ipilimumab in
      treating patients with stage IV melanoma. Stereotactic radiation therapy may be able to send
      x-rays directly to the tumor and cause less damage to normal tissue. Monoclonal antibodies,
      such as ipilimumab, can block tumor growth in different ways. Some block the ability of the
      tumor to grow and spread. Others find tumor cells and help kill them or carry tumor-killing
      substances to them. Giving SBRT with ipilimumab may be effective in treating melanoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine, for each stratum, feasibility, dose-limiting toxicities and maximum
      tolerated SBRT fraction when given in conjunction with ipilimumab. (Phase I)

      II. To determine, for each stratum, immune-related clinical response rate, immune-related
      progression-free survival rate at 6 months (irPFS6), overall survival rate at 12 months
      (OS12) and immune pharmacodynamic changes. (Phase II)

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine, for each stratum and dose level, late toxicity, immune-related clinical
      responses and immune pharmacodynamic changes after SBRT followed by ipilimumab. (Phase I)

      II. To gather additional data on acute and late toxicity. (Phase II)

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study of SBRT.

      Patients undergo a total of 2-3 fractions of SBRT between days 1-13. Patients then receive
      ipilimumab intravenously (IV) every 3 weeks. Treatment repeats every 3 weeks for 4 courses
      in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up within 30 days, within 60
      days, and then every 3 months thereafter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose-limiting toxicity (DLT), defined as any treatment related grade 4 or higher immune-related toxicity or grade 3 or higher non-immune related toxicity, graded by Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 30 days after last injection of ipilimumab</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>All dose-limiting toxicities and late toxicities will be graded and tabled by lesion site stratum and SBRT fraction dose level. Toxicity attribution to either SBRT or ipilimumab will be described if possible.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated SBRT fraction (MTD), defined as the SBRT fraction dose level at which 0-1/6 patients experience DLT and at least 2 patients treated at the next higher dose level experience DLT (or the apparent MTD is dose level 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>13 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>All dose-limiting toxicities and late toxicities will be graded and tabled by lesion site stratum and SBRT fraction dose level. Toxicity attribution to either SBRT or ipilimumab will be described if possible.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Late toxicities, graded according to the Radiation Therapy Oncology Group (RTOG)/European Organization for Research and the Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) late morbidity scoring system</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Defined generally as an adverse event associated with the treatment which occurs beyond 30 days after last injection (i.e., adverse events which are observed months after treatment are most likely associated with SBRT). All dose-limiting toxicities and late toxicities will be graded and tabled by lesion site stratum and SBRT fraction dose level. Toxicity attribution to either SBRT or ipilimumab will be described if possible.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune-related clinical response, defined as proportion of patients treated at the MTD who achieve either a complete or partial immune-related response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of immune-related responses will be tabled by stratum and SBRT fraction dose level. At the MTD, the immune-related response rate and 95% exact confidence interval (CI) will be estimated separately for previously untreated and previously treated metastatic patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune-related progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from first day of radiotherapy to first documented immune-related progressive disease, death due to any cause or last patient contact alive and progression-free, assessed at 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be estimated by the Kaplan-Meier method separately for previously untreated and previously treated metastatic patients who were treated at the MTD.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from first day of radiotherapy to death due to any cause or last patient contact alive, assessed at 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be estimated by the Kaplan-Meier method separately for previously untreated and previously treated metastatic patients who were treated at the MTD.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Lymphocyte analysis and activation</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after last ipilimumab injection</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Outcomes will first be described using plots and descriptive statistics. Natural log transformation may be applied, as necessary, prior to statistical comparison. Within-patient differences (e.g., baseline vs. post-treatment) will be examined by Student's t test for paired data or nonparametric Wilcoxon signed ranks test.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>T cell response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after last ipilimumab injection</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of immune responses (&gt; 2 fold pre/post increase) will be tabled by fraction dose level. The overall immune response rate and 95% exact CI will be estimated separately for previously untreated and previously treated metastatic patients treated at the MTD.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Recurrent Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (SBRT, ipilimumab)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo a total of 2-3 fractions of SBRT between days 1-13. Patients then receive ipilimumab IV every 3 weeks. Treatment repeats every 3 weeks for 4 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>stereotactic body radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo SBRT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (SBRT, ipilimumab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SBRT</other_name>
    <other_name>stereotactic radiation therapy</other_name>
    <other_name>stereotactic radiotherapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ipilimumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (SBRT, ipilimumab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>anti-cytotoxic T-lymphocyte-associated antigen-4 monoclonal antibody</other_name>
    <other_name>MDX-010</other_name>
    <other_name>MDX-CTLA-4</other_name>
    <other_name>monoclonal antibody CTLA-4</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (SBRT, ipilimumab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pharmacological studies</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (SBRT, ipilimumab)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed diagnosis of melanoma

          -  Previously treated or previously untreated stage IV melanoma by American Joint
             Committee on Cancer (AJCC) staging criteria

          -  Presence of an index lesion between 1 and 5 cm

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0 or 1

          -  Signed informed consent document

          -  Adequate renal, hepatic, and hematologic indices for ipilimumab therapy

          -  Ability to tolerate stereotactic body radiation therapy (e.g. lie flat and hold
             position for treatment)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior systemic therapy within 14 days of study enrollment; patients must be
             adequately recovered from prior systemic therapy side effects as deemed by the
             treating investigator

          -  Clinical contraindication to stereotactic body radiotherapy (e.g. active systemic
             sclerosis, active inflammatory bowel disease if bowel is within target field, etc)

          -  Presence or history of central nervous system metastasis (including brain)

          -  Long-term use of systemic corticosteroids

          -  Prior radiation therapy (RT) that precludes the delivery of SBRT
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ramesh Rengan</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ramesh Rengan</last_name>
      <phone>206-598-4110</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ramesh Rengan</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 22, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cytotoxic T-lymphocyte antigen 4</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
