<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="161451">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01915095</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>B0815-R</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01915095</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Enhancement of Hand Motor Function After Cervical Spinal Cord Injury</brief_title>
  <official_title>Enhancement of Hand Motor Function After Cervical Spinal Cord Injury</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Pittsburgh Medical Center Presbyterian Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Pittsburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Very often, people have difficulty doing things with their hands after experiencing a spinal
      cord injury (SCI). This can cause problems performing even the simplest of everyday tasks
      such as eating, grasping, writing, and many others.  The purpose of this research study is
      to examine how the central nervous system contributes to the control of hand movements after
      cervical SCI and promote the recovery of hand movements by using non-invasive brain
      stimulation and motor training. Results from this study could provide information that can
      be used to develop the best possible rehabilitation for individuals with SCI to help improve
      hand and arm function.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hand motor function is largely disrupted in veterans with cervical spinal cord injury (SCI).
      This has tremendous impact in daily-life activities. This study will examine physiological
      changes in pathways controlling hand motor function after cervical SCI and novel methods to
      enhance the recovery of hand motor function by combining non-invasive repetitive brain
      stimulation with motor training. The repetitive brain stimulation will occur using a wire
      coil placed over the participants head. When activated, this coil will generate a magnetic
      pulse over a specified area of the head. During training, we will monitor muscle activity
      through the use of surface electrodes. Subjects will perform precision grip and wrist
      movements. Impairment in hand function is a major problem after stroke, amyotrophic lateral
      sclerosis, multiple sclerosis, and other motor disorders, therefore, our work may also be
      relevant for individuals with other lesions of the nervous system.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary outcome measures of this study are muscle responses evoked by using transcranial magnetic stimulation of the primary motor cortex and electrical stimulation of a peripheral nerve in the arm</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurements will be taken immediately at one, two, and three months after the study intervention.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Spinal Cord Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>rTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>rTMS stimulation with magnetic pulses using transcranial magnetic stimulation and electrical stimulation targeting finger and wrist muscles during precision grip and wrist voluntary contractions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham rTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>rTMS stimulation with magnetic pulses using transcranial magnetic stimulation and electrical stimulation targeting finger and wrist muscles during precision grip and wrist voluntary contractions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham rTMS over control brain area</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>rTMS will be applied over the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC) or at the leg representation of the primary motor cortex</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High frequency non-invasive repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Stimulation with magnetic pulses using transcranial magnetic stimulation and electrical stimulation of a peripheral nerve in the arm</description>
    <arm_group_label>rTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sham rTMS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham rTMS over control brain area</intervention_name>
    <description>rTMS stimulation with magnetic pulses using transcranial magnetic stimulation and electrical stimulation applied over the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex or at the leg representation of the primary motor cortex</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham rTMS over control brain area</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Participants who are unimpaired healthy controls:

          -  Male and females between ages 18-85 years

          -  Right handed

          -  Able to complete precision grips with both hands

          -  Able to complete full wrist flexion-extension bilaterally

        Participants who have had a spinal cord injury:

          -  Male and females between ages 18-85 years

          -  Chronic SCI ( 1 year of injury)

          -  Cervical injury at C8 or above (tetraplegia)

          -  Intact or impaired but not absent lower motor neuron innervations in dermatomes C6,
             C7 and C8 during light touch and pin prick stimulus using the American Spinal Injury
             Association (ASIA) sensory scores,

          -  The ability to produce a visible precision grip force with one hand

          -  Individuals who have the ability to pick up a small object (large paperclip) from a
             table independently

          -  Able to perform 30  or more of wrist flexion and extension (measured by a goniometer)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Uncontrolled medical problems including pulmonary, cardiovascular or orthopedic
             disease

          -  Any debilitating disease prior to the SCI that caused exercise intolerance

          -  Premorbid, ongoing major depression or psychosis, altered cognitive status

          -  History of head injury or stroke

          -  Pacemaker

          -  Metal plate in skull

          -  History of seizures

          -  Receiving drugs acting primarily on the central nervous system, which lower the
             seizure threshold

          -  Pregnant females

          -  Ongoing cord compression or a syrinx in the spinal cord or who suffer from a spinal
             cord disease such as spinal stenosis, spina bifida or herniated cervical disk

          -  Individuals with scalp shrapnel, cochlear implants, or aneurysm clips
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Monica Alicia Perez, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Pittsburgh Healthcare System University Drive Division, Pittsburgh, PA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Monica A Perez, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(412) 383-6563</phone>
    <email>Monica.Perez@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Christine N Sanserino, BSN BA</last_name>
    <phone>(412) 624-7733</phone>
    <email>cns47@pitt.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Pittsburgh Healthcare System University Drive Division, Pittsburgh, PA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15240</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nicholas L Squeglia</last_name>
      <phone>(412) 360-2387</phone>
      <email>nicholas.squeglia@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mary B Walsh, RN</last_name>
      <phone>(412) 954-5256</phone>
      <email>mary.walsh3@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Monica Alicia Perez, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 5, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 19, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>spinal cord injury</keyword>
  <keyword>motor learning</keyword>
  <keyword>electrophysiology</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
