<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="11555">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01842906</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SLEEP-AID</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01842906</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study Looking at End Expiratory Pressure for Altitude Illness Decrease (SLEEP-AID)</brief_title>
  <acronym>SLEEP-AID</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomized Controlled Trial for Assessment of a Novel Non-Pharmacologic Intervention for Decrease in Altitude Illness</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Utah</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study is examining if an over-the-counter device (Theravent) worn while sleeping can
      reduce acute mountain sickness upon awakening in a high altitude trekking population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The specific aim of this study is to evaluate if an inexpensive and disposable
      end-expiratory pressure device can prevent acute mountain sickness (AMS). AMS is a common
      disorder found in 25-75% of hikers and trekkers in N. America and Europe who expediently
      ascend high altitude (&gt;8,000 ft). This environmental malady is insidious in onset and
      prevention is necessary not just to limit progression to severe or fatal disease, but also
      to limit physiologic deterioration in those who seek enjoyment or employment at high
      altitudes. One of the hallmarks of both healthy and sick individuals sleeping at high
      altitude is an oscillating pattern of respiration marked by periods of hyperventilation
      alternating with apnea or hypopnea. This distressing &quot;periodic breathing&quot; pattern leads to a
      feeling of suffocation, prevents restful sleep, and the hypoxic events may well worsen
      ensuing AMS. Prior studies have found positive end-expiratory pressure (PEEP) an effective
      non-pharmacologic method to prevent nocturnal desaturations and decreasing both AMS
      incidence and severity.

      Traditionally, PEEP devices are cumbersome and expensive, and while showing promising
      efficacy, are limited by both cost and portability as a useful non-pharmacologic option for
      AMS prophylaxis. The SLEEP-AID methodology is designed to prospectively enroll participants,
      randomized in a double blind placebo-controlled fashion to either the intervention
      [Theravent (Ventus Medical) which is single use, inexpensive, and very small] or a visually
      identical &quot;sham&quot; placebo group, and gather physiologic data to accurately reflect sleep
      patterns of high altitude travelers and objective as well as subjective outcomes of the
      intervention. The benefit of this approach will be to provide definitive data in a large and
      diverse cross section of a real hiking population that is generalizable to the majority of
      tens of millions of hikers, climbers, and high altitude tourists in the United States,
      Europe, Asia, and South America.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of acute mountain sickness</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 10 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Acute mountain sickness will be measured by Lake Louise Criteria and diagnosed as LLC &gt; or = to 3 with presence of a headache. Study participants will be followed approximately for 10 hours, from when they go to sleep until awakening the next morning.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>number of nocturnal desaturations</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 10 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of nocturnal desaturations will be measured by Watch-PAT200, a wristwatch type continuous sleep cycle and pulse oximetry analyzer. Study participants will be followed approximately for 10 hours, from when they go to sleep until awakening the next morning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>acute mountain sickness severity</measure>
    <time_frame>approximately 10 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Severity of acute mountain sickness will be evaluated by the Lake Louise Criteria. Study participants will be followed approximately for 10 hours, from when they go to sleep until awakening the next morning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>nocturnal awakenings</measure>
    <time_frame>approximately 10 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of nocturnal desaturations will be measured by Watch-PAT200, a wristwatch type continuous sleep cycle and pulse oximetry analyzer. Study participants will be followed approximately for 10 hours, from when they go to sleep until awakening the next morning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>subjective quality of sleep</measure>
    <time_frame>approximately 10 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Quality of sleep will be analyzed by sub-group analysis of the Lake Louise Criteria( 0 to 3 scale) for acute mountain sickness. Study participants will be followed approximately for 10 hours, from when they go to sleep until awakening the next morning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">175</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Mountain Sickness</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Theravent</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A singe use, disposable, positive end expiratory pressure device worn over the nostrils while sleeping.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A visibly identical sham device that does not provide positive end expiratory pressure.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Theravent</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Theravent</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ages 18-65

          -  Lake Louise Score (LLS) of &lt; 3

          -  Have not taken NSAIDs, acetazolamide, or corticosteroids in the prior week

          -  Have not traveled above 4200 m in the prior week.

          -  First night in Pheriche or Dingboche

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to read the consent form

          -  Taken NSAIDs, acetazolamide, or corticosteroids in the week prior to study
             enrollment.

          -  Hazardous medical conditions which precludes the ability to tolerate the experimental
             device.

          -  Pregnancy or suspected pregnancy.

          -  Participants who are younger than 18 years of age and more than 65.

          -  Travel to or above 4200m in the preceding week.

          -  Diagnosis of AMS upon enrollment (LLS ≥3 with symptoms of headache)

          -  Previously diagnosed obstructive sleep apnea

          -  Current symptoms of nasal congestion, rhinorrhea, sinusitis, upper respiratory
             infection, asthma, COPD exacerbation, pneumonia, bronchitis, or other disease of the
             respiratory tract.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Grant S Lipman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Grant S Lipman, MD</last_name>
    <phone>415-290-9286</phone>
    <email>grantlip@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nicholas C Kanaan, MD</last_name>
    <phone>650-387-5792</phone>
    <email>nkanaan@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Pheriche &amp; Dingboche</city>
        <state>Khumbu</state>
        <country>Nepal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Nepal</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 11, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 22, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>positive end expiratory pressure</keyword>
  <keyword>acute mountain sickness</keyword>
  <keyword>prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>high altitude</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Altitude Sickness</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
