<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="95903">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02085356</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20130238</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01HD078187</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02085356</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Implementing a Comprehensive Prevention of Mother-to-Child Transmission of HIV Program for South African Couples</brief_title>
  <official_title>Implementing Comprehensive PMTCT and HIV Prevention for South African Couples</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Miami</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Human Sciences Research Council</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Miami</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>South Africa: Human Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will test the effectiveness of a behavioral intervention to increase Prevention
      of Mother-to-Child Transmission of HIV (PMTCT) protocol uptake among South African HIV
      positive pregnant women. This study will also determine whether the participation of male
      partners will have additional positive impact on PMTCT uptake. The intervention will utilize
      a combination of both gender-concordant groups and individual or couples counseling
      strategies, before and after birth. During antenatal care, the intervention will use a
      gender-concordant group format to address PMTCT information, HIV disclosure, coping with
      stigma, intimate partner violence, and adherence to the overall PMTCT protocol. Just prior
      to birth and following birth, the intervention will shift to individual or couples-based
      counseling, targeting medication adherence, safer infant feeding, and family planning. It is
      hypothesized that women attending the intervention will be more likely to properly take HIV
      medication before birth and provide it to their infants. Additionally, it is hypothesized
      that male partner involvement will further increase the likelihood that mothers will take
      their HIV medication as prescribed and provide it to their infants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Factorial Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dried blood spot analysis of medication adherence- Mother and Infant</measure>
    <time_frame>32 weeks gestation/6 weeks postnatal</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Presence/absence of prescribed PMTCT protocol medications among mothers will be assessed by dried blood spot at 32 weeks gestation. Provision of ART to infants will be assessed at 6 weeks of age.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Infant HIV seroconversions</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks postnatal and 12 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Infants will be tested for HIV at 6 weeks per the South African standard of care and at 12 months per study protocol</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mother reported rates of infant exclusive breastfeeding</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 6 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Feeding practices will be assessed at 6 weeks and 6 months postpartum, and rates of exclusive breastfeeding will be assessed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Attendance at scheduled ante and postnatal clinic appointments</measure>
    <time_frame>32 weeks gestation, 6 weeks and 6 and 12 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Attendance at clinic appointments will be collected from patient records and self-report pre- and post-natal</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported use of condoms and &quot;dual protection&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>32 weeks gestation, 6 weeks and 6 and 12 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Sexual behavior (i.e., condom use, rates of dual protection postpartum) will be collected by participant self-report</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2160</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <condition>Pregnancy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention women with partners</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Women will enroll with male partners and both members of the couple will attend the Protect your Family intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention women without partners</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Women will enroll alone and will attend the Protect your Family Intervention without a partner</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control women with partners</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Women will enroll with male partners and both members of the couple will attend time-matched video sessions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control women alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Women will enroll alone and will attend time-matched video sessions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Protect your family</intervention_name>
    <description>&quot;Protect Your Family&quot;  intervention is a manualized, closed, structured behavioral risk reduction program targeting HIV, stigma, disclosure, communication, intimate partner violence (IPV), PMTCT knowledge, safer conception, family planning and dual method sexual barrier use.
Intervention participants will attend 3 prenatal weekly 2 hour gender-specific (male or female, 5-7 participants) group sessions followed by 1 individual counseling session and 2 monthly couples or individual (women-only) counseling sessions (1 prenatal, 2 postpartum) led by study-trained clinic staff (e.g., nurses, HIV counseling and testing (HCT) counselors) plus standard of care (PMTCT)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention women with partners</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention women without partners</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV seropositive pregnant women with partners, 20-24 weeks pregnant (typical time of
             entry into antenatal clinic care), aged &gt;18.

          -  In Phase 2 (couples phase), both women and their partners will be enrolled. For the
             purposes of this study, primary male partners are defined as 1) husband, 2) current
             baby's father, or 3) current sexual partner.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Persons actively psychotic (auditory or visual hallucination) or intoxicated (e.g.,
             under the influence of alcohol of illegal drugs) will not be eligible and will be
             referred for treatment. Following resolution of symptoms, these persons will be
             eligible for the study. N.B.: Any person presenting for sessions actively psychotic
             or intoxicated will be referred for treatment and will not be eligible to participate
             in sessions until symptoms are resolved due to reduced likelihood of benefit from
             sessions.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Deborah L Jones, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Miami</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karl Peltzer, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Human Sciences Research Council</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Deborah L Jones, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>3052432041</phone>
    <email>djones@med.miami.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ryan R Cook</last_name>
    <phone>3052432188</phone>
    <email>rcook@med.miami.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Human Sciences Research Council</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pretoria</city>
        <state>Gauteng</state>
        <zip>0002</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sibusiso Sifunda, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karl Peltzer, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>South Africa</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 6, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 10, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Miami</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Deborah Jones</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Research Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>PMTCT</keyword>
  <keyword>South Africa</keyword>
  <keyword>Couples</keyword>
  <keyword>Male involvement</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
