<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="33514">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01975519</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>105SAR101</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01975519</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase 1B Dose-escalation Study of TRC105 in Combination With Pazopanib in Patients With Advanced Soft Tissue Sarcoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1B Dose-escalation Study of TRC105 in Combination With Pazopanib in Patients With Advanced Soft Tissue Sarcoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tracon Pharmaceuticals Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tracon Pharmaceuticals Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate safety and tolerability and determine a recommended
      phase 2 dose for TRC105 when added to standard dose pazopanib in patients with advanced soft
      tissue sarcoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pazopanib is an oral inhibitor of multiple receptor tyrosine kinases, including vascular
      endothelial growth factor receptor VEGFR-1, VEGFR-2, and VEGFR-3 at therapeutic plasma
      concentrations. These receptors are implicated in pathologic angiogenesis, tumor growth, and
      cancer progression. Pazopanib is approved for the treatment of advanced soft tissue sarcoma,
      following progression on one prior systemic therapy, based on improved progression free
      survival. TRC105 is an antibody to CD105, an important angiogenic target on vascular
      endothelial cells that is distinct from VEGFR. TRC105 inhibits angiogenesis, tumor growth
      and metastases in preclinical models and complements the activity of bevacizumab and
      multi-kinase inhibitors that target the VEGFR. In a phase 1 study of advanced solid tumors,
      TRC105 therapy caused a global reduction in angiogenic biomarkers and reduced tumor burden
      at doses that were well-tolerated. In a phase 1b study, the combination of TRC105 and
      bevacizumab produced radiographic reductions in tumor volume in bevacizumab-refractory
      patients, and was well tolerated. TRC105 potentiates bevacizumab and VEGFR tyrosine kinases
      (VEGFR TKI) in preclinical models. By targeting a non-VEGF pathway that is upregulated
      following VEGF inhibition, TRC105 has the potential to complement VEGFR TKIs and could
      represent a major advance in cancer therapy. Together, the use of TRC105 with pazopanib may
      result in more effective angiogenesis inhibition and improved clinical efficacy over that
      seen with pazopanib alone.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine Maximum Tolerated Dose of TRC105 in Combination with Pazopanib</measure>
    <time_frame>5 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety and dose limiting toxicity will be assessed by dose cohort.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Characterize TRC105 pharmacokinetic Concentrations when given with pazopanib</measure>
    <time_frame>14 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Plasma TRC105 concentrations will be measured at specified timepoints.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Soft Tissue Sarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TRC105 and Pazopanib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Weekly TRC105 in combination with standard dose Pazopanib.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TRC105 and Pazopanib</intervention_name>
    <description>Weekly TRC105 in combination with standard dose Pazopanib.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TRC105 and Pazopanib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Chimeric Antibody (TRC105) to CD105</other_name>
    <other_name>Votrient</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologically confirmed unresectable soft tissue sarcoma (i.e., non-GIST,
             non-adipocytic)that has progressed following treatment with chemotherapy. Prior
             pazopanib is allowed if the drug was not discontinued for toxicity.

          2. Measurable disease by RECIST

          3. Age of 18 years or older

          4. ECOG performance status ≤ 1

          5. Resolution of all acute adverse events resulting from prior cancer therapies to NCI
             CTCAE grade ≤ 1 or baseline (except alopecia)

          6. Adequate organ function

          7. Willingness and ability to consent for self and to comply with scheduled visits,
             treatment plan, laboratory tests, and other study procedures

          8. Available archival tumor specimen of the soft tissue sarcoma that meets inclusion
             criterion #1.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Prior treatment with TRC105

          2. Current treatment on another therapeutic clinical trial

          3. Receipt of a small molecule anticancer agent, including an investigational anticancer
             small molecule, within 14 days of starting study treatment-

          4. Receipt of a large molecule anticancer agent (e.g., antibody), including an
             investigational anticancer antibody, within 28 days of starting study treatment

          5. Prior surgery (including open biopsy) within 28 days of starting the study treatment
             or the anticipated need for a major surgical procedure within the next six months

          6. Prior radiation therapy within 28 days of starting the study treatment, except
             radiation therapy for bone metastases is permitted up to 14 days of starting
             treatment

          7. Minor surgical procedures such as fine needle aspiration, Mediport placement or core
             biopsy within 7 days of study treatment

          8. Uncontrolled chronic hypertension defined as systolic &gt; 150 or diastolic &gt; 90 despite
             optimal therapy (initiation or adjustment of BP medication prior to study entry is
             allowed provided that the average of 3 BP readings at a visit prior to enrollment is
             &lt; 140/90 mm Hg)

          9. Symptomatic ascites or pericardial or pleural effusion

         10. History of brain involvement with cancer, spinal cord compression, or carcinomatous
             meningitis, or new evidence of brain or leptomeningeal disease. Patients with
             radiated or resected lesions are permitted, provided the lesions are fully treated
             and inactive, patients are asymptomatic, and no steroids have been administered for
             at least 30 days.

         11. Angina, MI, symptomatic congestive heart failure, cerebrovascular accident, transient
             ischemic attack, arterial embolism, pulmonary embolism, Venous thrombosis, including
             pulmonary embolism and deep venous thrombosis (unless adequately anticoagulated
             without warfarin for more than two weeks), PTCA or CABG within the past 6 months

         12. Active bleeding or pathologic condition that carries a high risk of bleeding (e.g.
             hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia). Patients who have been uneventfully
             anti-coagulated with low molecular weight heparin are eligible.

         13. Thrombolytic use (except to maintain i.v. catheters) within 10 days prior to first
             day of study therapy

         14. Cardiac dysrhythmias of NCI CTCAE grade ≥ 2 within the last 28 days

         15. Known active viral or nonviral hepatitis or cirrhosis

         16. History of hemorrhage or hemoptysis (&gt; ½ teaspoon bright red blood) within 6 months
             of starting study treatment

         17. History of peptic ulcer disease or erosive gastritis within the past 6 months, unless
             treated for the condition and complete resolution has been documented by
             esophagogastroduodenoscopy (EGD)within 28 days of starting study treatment

         18. History of gastrointestinal perforation or fistula in the past 6 months, or while
             previously on antiangiogenic therapy, unless underlying risk has been resolved (e.g.,
             through surgical resection or repair)

         19. Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or acquired immunodeficiency syndrome
             (AIDS)related illness

         20. Pregnancy or breastfeeding.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Charles Theuer, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>TRACON Pharmaceutitcals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bonne Adams, MBA</last_name>
    <phone>858-550-0780</phone>
    <phone_ext>228</phone_ext>
    <email>badams@traconpharma.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Delia Alvarez</last_name>
    <phone>858-550-0780</phone>
    <phone_ext>232</phone_ext>
    <email>dalvarez@traconpharma.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alabama at Birmingham</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35243</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic Jacksonville</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic Rochester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Sinai School of Medicine-Tisch Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 5, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 23, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>TRC105</keyword>
  <keyword>CD105</keyword>
  <keyword>Endoglin</keyword>
  <keyword>Angiogenesis Inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>STS</keyword>
  <keyword>Soft Tissue Sarcoma</keyword>
  <keyword>TKI</keyword>
  <keyword>Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Pazopanib</keyword>
  <keyword>Votrient</keyword>
  <keyword>Advanced Soft Tissue Sarcoma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Angiogenesis Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
