<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="92222">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01659554</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAI1246</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01659554</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase II Combined Modality Protocol of Debulking Surgery With HIPEC Followed by Intraperitoneal Chemotherapy for the Treatment of Recurrent Ovarian, Primary Peritoneal &amp; Fallopian Tube Cancers</brief_title>
  <acronym>HIPEC</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase II Combined Modality Protocol of Debulking Surgery With Heated Intraoperative Chemotherapy (HIPEC) Followed by Intraperitoneal Chemotherapy for the Treatment of Recurrent Ovarian, Primary Peritoneal and Fallopian Tube Cancers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to investigate the feasibility, tolerability and
      safety of surgical debulking and resection with heated intraoperative chemotherapy (HIPEC)
      followed by repeated intraperitoneal chemotherapy for treatment of recurrent ovarian,
      primary peritoneal, and fallopian tube carcinomas.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase II , open label, single center study of surgery followed by heated
      intraoperative cisplatin in patients with recurrent ovarian, primary peritoneal or fallopian
      tube cancers. Approximately twenty patients will receive surgery and intraoperative
      (hyperthermic) cisplatin followed by four consecutive courses of outpatient intraperitoneal
      cisplatin and doxorubicin given on days 1 and 8 during a 3 week cycle.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Event Rate and/or laboratory changes</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The adverse event rate and laboratory changes will be used to investigate the safety of surgical debulking with heated intraperitoneal chemotherapy (HIPEC) combined with repeated intraperitoneal  chemotherapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity Rating based on NCI Common Toxicity Criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients will be rated for toxicity prior to each cycle using the NCI Common Toxicity Criteria (NCICTC; see the CTCAE, Version 4.0).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Serum Ca-125 Nadir and/or CT Response (RECIST criteria)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years (survival)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Efficacy of surgical resection with HIPEC combined with repeated intraperitoneal chemotherapy: The end point will be the objective response rate and progression-free survival as well as the overall survival, if feasible. We will analyze the time to serum Ca 125 nadir and/or CT response based on Recist criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Kaplan-Meier curves for patient overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years, survival</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Kaplan-Meier analysis will be done using PROC LIFETEST in Statistical Application Software (SAS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Recurrent Ovarian Cancer,</condition>
  <condition>Fallopian Tube Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intraoperative Cisplatin followed by IP Chemotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intraoperative (hyperthermic) cisplatin followed by 4 courses of intraperitoneal cisplatin and doxorubicin given on days 1 &amp; 8 during a 3 week cycle</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intraoperative (hyperthermic) cisplatin  followed by IP Cisplatin; Doxorubicin</intervention_name>
    <description>Cisplatin 75 mg/m2 at 40.5-42.5 Celsius intraoperatively administered; IP Cisplatin 75 mg/m2 (Day 1) week 1 followed by IP Doxorubicin 25 mg week 2 (day 8) for four sequential 3 week cycles;</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intraoperative Cisplatin followed by IP Chemotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients must have histologically confirmed ovarian, primary peritoneal or fallopian
             tube carcinoma.

          2. Patients must have measurable evidence of recurrent intraabdominal disease based on
             Computed tomography (CT scan) findings.

          3. Patients must fulfill the following with regard to prior chemotherapy:

               1. 4 weeks or greater since conclusion of prior chemotherapy;

               2. Prior intraperitoneal chemotherapy with cisplatin is acceptable; and,

               3. Prior systemic chemotherapy is acceptable.

          4. Patients must have a Karnofsky Performance Status of &gt; 70%

          5. Patients must have an estimated life expectancy of at least 16 weeks.

          6. Patient assurance of study compliance and geographic proximity that allows for
             adequate follow-up.

          7. Patients must have adequate organ function at the screening visit as defined by the
             following laboratory values:

        Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥1.5 x 109/L Platelet count ≥100 x 109/L Hemoglobin ≥8
        g/dL Albumin ≥ 2 g/dL Total Bilirubin ≤ 2.5 x ULN* Alkaline phosphatase ≤ 3.0 x ULN*
        Aspartate transaminase (AST) and alanine transaminase (ALT) ≤ 3.0 x ULN Creatinine ≤ 1.5 x
        ULN

        [8] Patient must have signed informed consent

        [9] Patient must be at least 18 years of age

        [10] Following cytoreductive surgery, patient's residual disease should be no larger than
        1cm to Receive HIPEC and continue with normothermic IP chemotherapy

        -Exclusion criteria

          1. Have active peripheral neuropathy of Grade 2 or greater intensity, as defined by the
             National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE;
             Version 4).

          2. Have experienced myocardial infarction within 6 months prior to enrollment or have
             New York Hospital Association (NYHA) Class III or IV heart failure (see section
             16.4), uncontrolled angina, severe uncontrolled ventricular arrhythmias, or
             electrocardiographic evidence of acute ischemia or active conduction system
             abnormalities.

          3. Prior radiation therapy within 4 weeks of enrollment.

          4. Have uncontrolled active systemic infection requiring therapy.

          5. Have a history of allergic reaction attributable to compounds containing boron or
             mannitol or hypersensitivity reactions to drugs formulated with polysorbate 80.

          6. Have had a serious concomitant systemic disorders (including oncologic emergencies)
             incompatible with the study (at the discretion of the investigator).

          7. Have had a &quot;currently active&quot; second malignancy other than non-melanoma skin cancer
             or carcinoma in situ of the cervix are not to be registered.   Patients who are not
             considered to have a &quot;currently active&quot; malignancy if they have completed therapy and
             are considered by their physician to be at less than 30% risk of relapse.

          8. Have had any investigational agent within 4 weeks before enrollment into the study.

          9. Have a history of a serious medical or psychiatric illness preventing informed
             consent or, in the opinion of the investigator, would make the patient a poor study
             candidate.

         10. Evidence of extraabdominal metastasis on preinclusion thoracic computed tomography
             (CT) scans (i.e. brain or chest disease).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sharyn Lewin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Reena Vattakalam</last_name>
    <phone>212-342-6895</phone>
    <email>rmv2110@columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Reena Vattakalam</last_name>
      <phone>212-342-6895</phone>
      <email>rmv2110@columbia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sharyn N Lewin, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-305-3410</phone>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sharyn Lewin, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 22, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 10, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Columbia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sharyn Lewin, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Clinical professor Division of Gynecologic Onoclogy</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Primary peritoneal</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fallopian Tube Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Doxorubicin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
