<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="158239">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02111993</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>110647</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02111993</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluating Myocardial Injury During ICD Implantation Using the Upper Limit of Vulnerability (ULV) Method vs. Standard Defibrillation Threshold Testing</brief_title>
  <acronym>ULV</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluating Myocardial Injury During ICD Implantation Using the Upper Limit of Vulnerability (ULV) Method vs. Standard Defibrillation Threshold Testing</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Diego</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Diego</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to evaluate myocardial injury, if any, as quantified by
      cardiac markers (Troponin-T) in defibrillation threshold (DFT) testing during implantation
      of implantable cardioverter defibrillators (ICDs) using the upper limit of vulnerability
      (ULV) method vs. standard defibrillation threshold method.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, randomized (1:1 DFT vs ULV testing), controlled clinical research
      trial. Patients undergoing ICD implant or device change out will be candidates for this
      study. Medical records for these patients will be screened prior to enrollment to ensure
      eligibility for the study. Each patient who is a candidate and who agrees to participate in
      the study will undergo the standard of care pre-procedure evaluation including a complete
      medical history evaluation, a complete physical examination and routine laboratory testing
      including chemistry panel, hematology panel, coagulation panel, a 12-lead electrocardiogram,
      and a urine pregnancy test (all females of child-bearing age).  A candidate patient will be
      randomly assigned to either the standard DFT testing method group or the ULV testing method
      group.

      For the standard DFT testing group, per routine standard of care, the patient will be
      admitted to the hospital. The study requires a pre-procedure blood test of 3 ml for
      Troponin-T (TnT) which will be drawn prior to any DFT testing. The blood sample will be sent
      to the University of California, San Diego (UCSD) central laboratory for processing.  The
      patient will then undergo the scheduled ICD implant procedure in a standard fashion.  The
      standard defibrillation threshold testing will be performed using a low energy shock
      delivered on T-wave to induce ventricular fibrillation (VF).  If VF is induced, the first
      shock is 25J. If success, we will wait 5 minutes and repeat the process.  If the 2nd shock
      yields success, the DFT testing is complete and a 10J safety margin achieved (device shock
      energy is set at 35J).  A back-up external defibrillator will always be immediately
      available in case transvenous shocks fail.  A safety margin of 10J (i.e. DFT + 10J) will be
      considered adequate for safe implantation of modern ICD systems.  This is standard DFT
      testing as clinically done at each implant today.  Blood pressure will be monitored before
      and immediately after each shock.  After 4 hours, 8 hours and 20 hours post DFT testing,
      blood samples (3 ml for Troponin-T) will be drawn and sent to the UCSD central laboratory
      for processing.

      For the ULV testing group, per routine standard of care, the patient will be admitted to the
      hospital. The study requires a pre-procedure blood test (3 ml for Troponin-T.) which will be
      drawn prior to any ULV testing. The blood sample will be sent to the UCSD central laboratory
      for processing.  The patient will then undergo the scheduled ICD implant procedure in a
      standard fashion.  The ULV testing is performed as followed: for single coil device, a 18J
      shock will be delivered at 0msec, +20 msec, -20msec and -40msec measured from the peak of
      the T-wave; for dual coil device, a 18J shock will be delivered at 0msec, -20msec, +20msec,
      and  +40msec measured from the peak of the T-wave.  If VF is not induced with any of the
      above mentioned shocks, the ULV will be considered as 18J and the ICD will be implanted with
      the first shock strength set at 30 joules. If VF is induced, a 25J rescue shock will be
      delivered as is standard and if successful, the device will be programmed to the maximum
      output of 35 joules. If the rescue shock is unsuccessful, external rescue shock will be
      performed and the ICD lead system will be repositioned and testing repeated until the ULV is
      acceptable. The ULV is the weakest shock strength that does not induce VF and this value
      correlates closely with the defibrillation threshold obtained using alternating current for
      VF induction.  Blood pressure will be monitored before and immediately after each shock.
      After 4 hours, 8 hours and 20 hours post ULV testing, blood samples (3 ml for Troponin-T)
      will be drawn and sent to the UCSD central laboratory for processing.

      Other than the blood tests for Troponin-T, there is no change in routine post-operative
      management. Patients will be followed every three months, as is standard management for
      patients with ICDs.

      The results of Troponin-T measurement for the study patients will be assessed by the
      electrophysiology (EP) staff covering the case.  If myocardial injury is noted (any TnT
      value &gt;0.1 as per current assay at the UCSD laboratory), the patient will be monitored with
      appropriate laboratories including repeat TnT measurements.  The patient will need to stay
      in the hospital until all lab results obtained.  The TnT blood draws at 4-hour, 8-hour and
      20-hour post implantation will not require longer hospital stay since they are still in the
      24-hour window observation which is routine admission status for device implantation.  If
      the repeat TnT measurement is &lt;0.1, then myocardial injury is most unlikely and the positive
      TnT value is likely due to DFT shocks.  Only if the repeat TnT value is 0.1 or above, then
      the patient will require longer hospital stay to work up for myocardial infarction.  During
      this stay, additional TnT values will be drawn; a cardiac stress test will likely be
      performed to rule out coronary blockage.  The patient will also be treated with appropriate
      therapy for myocardial injury including aspirin and beta-blocker (if the patient is not
      already taking these) while further tests are being carried out.  If the stress test is
      negative, positive TnT values are likely due to DFT shocks and not ischemia per se.  If
      stress test is positive, consultation with interventional cardiology will be obtained for
      cardiac angiogram. Only if the patient has a positive stress test and a positive cardiac
      angiogram will the patient be diagnosed with myocardial infarction.  We will follow standard
      of care for management of myocardial injury as recommended by the American Heart Association
      and the American College of Cardiology. All patients are required to stay overnight after
      ICD implantation and this is standard of care. All lab results should be obtained during
      patient's hospitalization.

      Analysis will be performed using a two-tailed t-test at alpha = 0.05.  A sample size of 25
      patients in each group will have 90% power to detect a difference in means of 0.019 ng/mL,
      assuming a common standard deviation of 0.020.  This standard deviation was computed based
      on a range of 0.030 to 0.100 ng/mL using nQuery Advisor version 4.0.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Myocardial Damage</measure>
    <time_frame>20 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Myocardial damage will be evaluated at 4 hours, 8 hours, and 20 hours after ULV or DFT testing by measuring serum Troponin T levels.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Study Focus: Is ULV a Safer Method to Set ICD Defibrillator Output Settings When Compared to Standard DFT?</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Defibrillation Threshold (DFT) Testing</arm_group_label>
    <description>Prior to the procedure, baseline serum Troponin T will be measured. Once the ICD is implanted, a low energy shock will be delivered to the heart during the T wave to induce ventricular fibrillation (VF). Once VF is induced, a rescue shock of 25J will be delivered to restore sinus rhythm. This process will be repeated once more and the device shock output is set to 35J. Troponin T labs will be taken again at 4, 8, and 20 hours after DFT testing to assess myocardial damage, if present.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Upper Limit of Vulnerability (ULV) Testing</arm_group_label>
    <description>Prior to the procedure, baseline labs will be taken to measure serum Troponin T levels. Once the ICD is implanted, ULV testing will commence. ULV testing differs based on whether a single coil or a double coil device is used.
For single coil devices, a 18J shock will be delivered at 0 ms, -20 ms, +20ms, and -40 ms from the peak of the T wave. For double coil devices, a 18J shock will be delivered at 0 ms, -20 ms, +20 ms, and +40 ms from the T wave peak.
If VF is not induced with any of these shocks, then the ULV will be considered to be 18J and the device output shock will be set at 30J. If VF is induced, then a 25 J rescue shock will be delivered and the device output shock is set to 35J (as in DFT testing).
Serum Troponin T levels will be measured at 4, 8, and 20 hours after ULV testing to assess myocardial damage, if present.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study population for this trial will include patients who have a standard indication
        for ICD implantation, generator change, or upgrade. These patients must have a right
        ventricle lead located in the right ventricle apex.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients eligible to receive an ICD implant or change out.

          -  Patients with a single or dual coil right ventricle (RV) defibrillation lead located
             in the RV apex.

          -  Patients greater than 18 years of age.

          -  Patients willing and able to give informed consent.

          -  Patients who have insurance which may cover additional hospital stay if myocardial
             injury resulted from testing

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with medical conditions that would limit study participation.

          -  Patients that are pregnant (all females of child-bearing potential must have a
             negative pregnancy test within 1 week of enrollment or positive pregnancy test
             performed prior to the procedure).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ulrika Birgersdotter-Green, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Diego</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Manely L Yafeh, M.S.</last_name>
    <phone>858-657-5397</phone>
    <email>mlyafeh@ucsd.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jessica Hunter, BHS</last_name>
    <phone>858-657-5323</phone>
    <email>j2hunter@ucsd.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, San Diego</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Jolla</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92093</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Manely L Yafeh, MS</last_name>
      <phone>858-657-5397</phone>
      <email>mlyafeh@ucsd.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jessica Hunter, BHS</last_name>
      <phone>858-657-5323</phone>
      <email>j2hunter@ucsd.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ulrika Birgersdotter-Green, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Swerdlow CD, Shehata M, Chen PS. Using the upper limit of vulnerability to assess defibrillation efficacy at implantation of ICDs. Pacing Clin Electrophysiol. 2007 Feb;30(2):258-70. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17338725</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Day JD, Doshi RN, Belott P, Birgersdotter-Green U, Behboodikhah M, Ott P, Glatter KA, Tobias S, Frumin H, Lee BK, Merillat J, Wiener I, Wang S, Grogin H, Chun S, Patrawalla R, Crandall B, Osborn JS, Weiss JP, Lappe DL, Neuman S. Inductionless or limited shock testing is possible in most patients with implantable cardioverter- defibrillators/cardiac resynchronization therapy defibrillators: results of the multicenter ASSURE Study (Arrhythmia Single Shock Defibrillation Threshold Testing Versus Upper Limit of Vulnerability: Risk Reduction Evaluation With Implantable Cardioverter-Defibrillator Implantations). Circulation. 2007 May 8;115(18):2382-9. Epub 2007 Apr 30.</citation>
    <PMID>17470697</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen PS, Shibata N, Dixon EG, Martin RO, Ideker RE. Comparison of the defibrillation threshold and the upper limit of ventricular vulnerability. Circulation. 1986 May;73(5):1022-8.</citation>
    <PMID>3698224</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen PS, Feld GK, Kriett JM, Mower MM, Tarazi RY, Fleck RP, Swerdlow CD, Gang ES, Kass RM. Relation between upper limit of vulnerability and defibrillation threshold in humans. Circulation. 1993 Jul;88(1):186-92.</citation>
    <PMID>8319332</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hwang C, Swerdlow CD, Kass RM, Gang ES, Mandel WJ, Peter CT, Chen PS. Upper limit of vulnerability reliably predicts the defibrillation threshold in humans. Circulation. 1994 Nov;90(5):2308-14.</citation>
    <PMID>7955188</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martin DJ, Chen PS, Hwang C, Gang ES, Mandel WJ, Peter CT, Swerdlow CD. Upper limit of vulnerability predicts chronic defibrillation threshold for transvenous implantable defibrillators. J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol. 1997 Mar;8(3):241-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9083873</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Birgersdotter-Green U, Undesser K, Fujimura O, Feld GK, Kass RM, Mandel WJ, Peter CT, Chen PS. Correlation of acute and chronic defibrillation threshold with upper limit of vulnerability determined in normal sinus rhythm. J Interv Card Electrophysiol. 1999 Jul;3(2):155-61.</citation>
    <PMID>10387143</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Swerdlow CD, Davie S, Ahern T, Chen PS. Comparative reproducibility of defibrillation threshold and upper limit of vulnerability. Pacing Clin Electrophysiol. 1996 Dec;19(12 Pt 1):2103-11.</citation>
    <PMID>8994950</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Swerdlow CD, Ahern T, Kass RM, Davie S, Mandel WJ, Chen PS. Upper limit of vulnerability is a good estimator of shock strength associated with 90% probability of successful defibrillation in humans with transvenous implantable cardioverter-defibrillators. J Am Coll Cardiol. 1996 Apr;27(5):1112-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8609329</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Swerdlow CD. Implantation of cardioverter defibrillators without induction of ventricular fibrillation. Circulation. 2001 May 1;103(17):2159-64.</citation>
    <PMID>11331256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Green UB, Garg A, Al-Kandari F, Ungab G, Tone L, Feld GK. Successful implantation of cardiac defibrillators without induction of ventricular fibrillation using upper limit of vulnerability testing. J Interv Card Electrophysiol. 2003 Feb;8(1):71-5.</citation>
    <PMID>12652181</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Swerdlow C, Shivkumar K, Zhang J. Determination of the upper limit of vulnerability using implantable cardioverter-defibrillator electrograms. Circulation. 2003 Jun 24;107(24):3028-33. Epub 2003 Jun 16.</citation>
    <PMID>12810611</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shehata M, Belk P, Kremers M, Saba S, Cao J, Swerdlow CD. Automatic determination of timing intervals for upper limit of vulnerability using ICD electrograms. Pacing Clin Electrophysiol. 2008 Jun;31(6):691-700. doi: 10.1111/j.1540-8159.2008.01072.x.</citation>
    <PMID>18507541</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 9, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 9, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Diego</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ulrika Birgersdotter-Green</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Defibrillation Testing, Upper Limit of Vulnerability, ULV, DFT, ICD,</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
