<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="8236">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01916304</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LE-9999-401-BE</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-005732-28</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1145-3526</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01916304</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Dose Adjustment From Levothyroxine to a New Levothyroxine Sodium Test Formulation.</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multicentre, Open-label Switch Study to Investigate the Necessity of Dose Adjustment After Switching From L-Thyroxine Christiaens® to the New Levothyroxine Sodium Test Formulation in (Near) Total Thyroidectomised Patients.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Takeda</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Belgium: Federal Agency for Medicinal Products and Health Products</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate the effect of switching participants taking
      levothyroxine to a new sodium formulation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The drug being tested in this study is a new sodium formulation of levothyroxine.
      Levothyroxine (L-Thyroxine Christiaens®) is used in the treatment of hypothyroidism. This
      study will investigate the effect of switching subjects taking levothyroxine to a new
      levothyroxine sodium formulation.

      The results of this study will be used to provide instructions to general practicioners and
      endocrinlogists assisting patients on levothyroxine hormone substitution in performing the
      switch to the new formulation.

      The study will enroll approximately 90 patients. Patients receiving the same daily dose of
      L-Thyroxine Christiaens® during the past 6 weeks and with serum thyroid stimulating hormone
      (TSH) levels between 0.4-2.5 mU/L will be switched to the equivalent daily dose of the new
      formulation of levothyroxine. After the switch, patients will be followed up after 2 (± 2
      weeks) and 4 months (± 4 weeks).

      All participants will be asked to take a daily dose at the same time each day throughout the
      study.

      This study will be conducted in Belgium. The overall time to participate in this study is
      about 3 to 7,5 months. Participants will make 3 to 4 visits to the clinic.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of patients that do not need a change of dose.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months (± 2 weeks) after switch to sodium formulation.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Dose change determined by physician according to their clinical judgement.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The magnitude of the change in daily dose needed.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 to 5 months after switch to sodium formulation.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Magnitude will be determined via a change table (which provides the fraction of patients that needed a change of -75 μg, -50 μg, -25 μg, 0 μg, +25 μg, +50 μg and +75 μg in daily dose).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients that obtained a thyroid stimulating hormone between 0.4-2.5 mU/L</measure>
    <time_frame>3 to 5 months after inclusion into study.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline serum thyroid stimulating hormone (in mIU/L and percentage).</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 2 (± 2 weeks) and Month 4 (± 4 weeks) after inclusion into study.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypothyroidism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Levothyroxine sodium new formulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Levothyroxine (25-225 μg), tablets, orally, once daily for up to 12 to 20 weeks. Dose administered depends on the thyroid stimulating hormone level.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Levothyroxine sodium new formulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Levothyroxine tablets</description>
    <arm_group_label>Levothyroxine sodium new formulation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        -1. (Near) total thyroidectomised patients. 2. Aged between 18 and 70 years. 3. Stabilised
        on the same daily dose of L-Thyroxine Christiaens® during the last 6 weeks before
        inclusion in the study.

        4. Written informed consent given. 5. Able and willing to comply with protocol
        requirements and to complete the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1. History of Graves' disease or positive TSH-receptor antibodies. 2. History of
             thyroid cancer requiring TSH suppression. 3. Medical procedures or treatments planned
             that could influence the thyroid hormone state of the patients during this trial.

             4. Use of levothyroxine containing medicines provided by other brands to treat
             hypothyroidism.

             5. Pregnant or planning pregnancy. Female patients of childbearing potential need to
             apply highly effective methods of birth control.

             6. Participation in another trial in the past 6 weeks. 7. Exclusion criteria during
             the study are the occurrence of any serious adverse reaction, any laboratory or
             clinically relevant change in patient status, any change in smoking status, use of
             drugs non-authorized by the physician (to avoid relevant drug interactions) and lack
             of patient compliance with the study drug. (OR events not considered as exclusion
             criteria but to be documented in the case report form, as a possible explanation for
             change in lab parameters and/or dose switch)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Responsible</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Takeda</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Takeda Study Registration Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>+1-800-778-2860 (USA &amp; EU)</phone>
    <email>medicalinformation@tpna.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 1, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 1, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Drug Therapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hypothyroidism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
