<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="117847">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02120469</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14036</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2014-00844</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>14036</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02120469</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Eribulin Mesylate and Everolimus in Treating Patients With Triple-Negative Metastatic Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I/IB Trial of Eribulin and Everolimus in Patients With Triple Negative Metastatic Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>City of Hope Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>City of Hope Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial studies the side effects and best dose of eribulin mesylate and
      everolimus in treating patients with triple-negative metastatic breast cancer. Eribulin
      mesylate and everolimus may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking some of the enzymes
      needed for cell growth. Giving eribulin mesylate together with everolimus may be a safe and
      successful treatment for patients with triple-negative metastatic breast cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the safety and tolerability of everolimus and eribulin (eribulin mesylate),
      and determine the recommended Phase IB dose (RP2D) of the drug combination in patients with
      resistant metastatic triple negative breast cancer (TNBC). (Phase I) II. To evaluate the
      event-free survival (EFS) rate for patients with resistant metastatic TNBC at the RP2D of
      everolimus and eribulin to determine if the drug combination is worthy of further study.
      (Phase IB)

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine response rate in patients with resistant metastatic TNBC. (Phase IB) II. To
      determine overall survival (OS) in patients with resistant metastatic TNBC. (Phase IB) III.
      To determine toxicity in patients with resistant metastatic TNBC. (Phase IB) IV. To
      determine pharmacokinetics (PK) for everolimus and eribulin in patients with resistant
      metastatic TNBC. (Phase IB) V. To collect blood, skin punch biopsies, and tumor biopsies
      before and after treatment from all patients and perform proteomic analysis to determine the
      level of inhibition of the phosphatidylinositol 3 kinase (PI3K) pathway in tumor cells
      versus non-therapeutic targets. (Phase IB)

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study of everolimus.

      Patients receive everolimus orally (PO) once daily (QD) on days 1-21 and eribulin mesylate
      intravenously (IV) on days 1 and 8. Courses repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease
      progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up periodically.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>R2PD of the eribulin mesylate and everolimus, determined according to the NCI CTCAE v4.0 (Phase I)</measure>
    <time_frame>21 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Tables will be created to summarize all toxicities and side effects by dose, course, organ and severity. Rates and associated 95% confidence limits will be estimated for dose-limiting toxicities at the R2PD.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Event-free survival using the Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) (Phase IB)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 4 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Rates and associated 95% confidence limits will be estimated. Kaplan Meier methods will be used to estimate the median and 95% confidence limits. Descriptive statistics will be provided for the patient demographics.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events, graded according to the NCI CTCAE v4.0 (Phase IB)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Tables will be created to summarize all toxicities and side effects by dose, course, organ and severity. Rates and associated 95% confidence limits will be estimated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate using the RECIST (Phase IB)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Rates and associated 95% confidence limits will be estimated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (Phase IB)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Kaplan Meier methods will be used to estimate the median and 95% confidence limits. Descriptive statistics will be provided for the patient demographics.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters of everolimus in blood samples</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 24 hours on day 1 of course 1 and 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Non-compartmental PK analyses of everolimus will be performed using statistical moment theory and according to the rule of linear trapezoids and statistical moment theory.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters of eribulin mesylate in plasma samples</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 5, 10, 15, and 30 minutes, 1, 2, 4, 6, 24, 48, 72, and 167 hours on day 1 of course 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Compartmental analyses will be performed for eribulin data. Secondary pharmacokinetic parameters (e.g. CLsys, Volume of distribution [Vd], half-life [t1/2's], and area under the curve [AUC 0-&gt;infinity) will be determined for each individual and a two-stage approach will be used to describe the study population pharmacokinetics. Population means and standard deviations will be compared to values obtained from patients treated on trials of single agent eribulin mesylate.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Estrogen Receptor-negative Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>HER2-negative Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Progesterone Receptor-negative Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Triple-negative Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (everolimus, eribulin mesylate)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive everolimus PO QD on days 1-21 and eribulin mesylate IV on days 1 and 8. Courses repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>everolimus</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (everolimus, eribulin mesylate)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>42-O-(2-hydroxy)ethyl rapamycin</other_name>
    <other_name>Afinitor</other_name>
    <other_name>RAD001</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>eribulin mesylate</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (everolimus, eribulin mesylate)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>B1939</other_name>
    <other_name>E7389</other_name>
    <other_name>ER-086526</other_name>
    <other_name>halichrondrin B analog</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (everolimus, eribulin mesylate)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pharmacological studies</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (everolimus, eribulin mesylate)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with histologically-confirmed stage IV adenocarcinoma TNBC

          -  Patients who progressed on anthracyclines and/or taxanes (resistant)

          -  Patients with measurable disease, defined as at least one lesion that can be
             accurately measured in at least one dimension (longest diameter to be recorded) as &gt;
             20 mm with conventional techniques or as &gt; 10 mm with spiral computed tomography (CT)
             scan

          -  Previous chemotherapy for metastatic disease (up to =&lt; 3 prior lines of chemotherapy
             for MBC); this includes prior everolimus therapy

          -  Prior radiation therapy

          -  Life expectancy of &gt; 6 months

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status (PS) 0-2

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 9.0 g/dl

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1,500/mm^3

          -  Platelet count &gt;= 100,000/mm^3

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.0 times upper limit of normal limit (ULN)

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) =&lt; 1.5 times the
             ULN

          -  Creatinine =&lt; 1.5 times the ULN

          -  Women of child-bearing potential must agree to use adequate contraception (hormonal
             or barrier method of birth control or abstinence) prior to study entry and for six
             months following duration of study participation; should a woman become pregnant or
             suspect that she is pregnant while participating on the trial, she should inform her
             treating physician immediately

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have had chemotherapy or radiotherapy within 4 weeks prior to entering
             the study or those who have not recovered from adverse events (AEs) due to agents
             administered &gt; 4 weeks prior to entering the study

          -  Patients may not be receiving any other investigational agents

          -  Patients with known brain metastases are excluded from this trial; patients with
             neurological symptoms must undergo a CT scan/magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the
             brain to exclude brain metastasis

          -  Uncontrolled current illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection (&gt; grade 2 based on the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology
             Criteria for Adverse Events [NCI CTCAE] version [v]4.0, symptomatic congestive heart
             failure, unstable angina pectoris, myocardial infarction within the past 6 months,
             cardiac ventricular arrhythmias requiring anti-arrhythmic therapy, or psychiatric
             illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study requirements

          -  Pregnant women

          -  Prior eribulin use

          -  Patients with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), chronic hepatitis B, or chronic
             hepatitis C (known from the existing medical record)

          -  Concomitant use with cytochrome P450, family 3, subfamily A, polypeptide 4
             (CYP3A4)/P-glycoprotein (PgP) inducers

          -  Women of child-bearing potential (WOCBP), defined as all women physiologically
             capable of becoming pregnant, must use highly effective methods of contraception
             during the study and 8 weeks after; highly effective contraception methods include
             combination of any two of the following:

               -  Use of oral, injected or implanted hormonal methods of contraception or

               -  Placement of an intrauterine device (IUD) or intrauterine system (IUS)

               -  Barrier methods of contraception: condom or occlusive cap (diaphragm or
                  cervical/vault caps) with spermicidal foam/gel/film/cream/vaginal suppository

               -  Total abstinence

               -  Male/female sterilization

                    -  Women are considered post-menopausal and not of child-bearing potential if
                       they have had 12 months of natural (spontaneous) amenorrhea with an
                       appropriate clinical profile (e.g., age appropriate, history of vasomotor
                       symptoms) or have had surgical bilateral oophorectomy (with or without
                       hysterectomy) or tubal ligation at least six weeks prior to randomization;
                       in the case of oophorectomy alone, only when the reproductive status of the
                       woman has been confirmed by follow up hormone level assessment is she
                       considered not of child-bearing potential

          -  Male patients whose sexual partner(s) are WOCBP who are not willing to use adequate
             contraception, during the study and for 8 weeks after the end of treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thehang Luu</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>City of Hope Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City of Hope Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Duarte</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thehang H. Luu</last_name>
      <phone>800-826-4673</phone>
      <email>TLuu@coh.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Thehang H. Luu</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 18, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 18, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sirolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
