<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="80567">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01851447</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130112</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-CH-0112</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01851447</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Skeletal Muscle Biomarkers in People With Fragile Sarcolemmal Muscular Dystrophy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot Study to Assess Biomarkers of Changes in Barrier Function of Skeletal Muscle in Patients With a Fragile Sarcolemmal Muscular Dystrophy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Some kinds of muscular dystrophy affect the skeletal muscle membrane. In these conditions,
      the muscle membrane is more fragile. This affects how the muscles contract and relax, which
      causes movement problems. Researchers are looking at several muscle enzymes, or chemicals
      that affect how muscle cells function. By studying changes in these enzymes, they may be
      able to better understand how muscular dystrophy affects the cells. Researchers want to
      collect biomarkers (chemicals from blood samples) from people with fragile sarcolemmal
      muscular dystrophy. This information may provide better treatments for this condition.

      Objectives:

      - To study biomarkers that may affect the muscles of people with fragile sarcolemmal
      muscular dystrophy.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals at least 18 years of age with fragile sarcolemmal muscular dystrophy.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a medical history and physical exam.

        -  Participants will have four visits to the National Institutes of Health Clinical
           Center. The visits will be about 3 months apart. Each visit will require participants
           to stay for 5 days at the clinical center.

        -  During each visit, participants will provide frequent small blood samples. These
           samples will be collected while at rest and after physical exercise.

        -  Participants will also have a physical therapy assessment. They will perform standard
           motor function tests. These tests may take up to 1 hour each time.

        -  Treatment will not be provided as part of this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives: the aim of this protocol is to identify biomarker and clinical correlates of
      changes in the barrier function of skeletal muscle membrane (i.e. cell membrane
      permeability) before and after routine motor function testing in patients with one of the
      Fragile Sarcolemmal Muscular Dystrophies (FSMD). Study population: patients with early
      adulthood or later onset of a FSMD (LGMD2B-F, I, L, MM, BMD, and MMD3). Design: pilot study.
      Outcome measures: increased change in baseline levels of proteins that are released into the
      blood from damaged skeletal muscle, such as creatine kinase (CK), lactate dehydrogenase
      (LDH), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT), troponins, and
      myoglobin in serum, changes in inflammation markers and circulating microRNAs to identify
      effective biomarkers for use in future clinical trials.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>changes in serum enzyme, protein, cytokine and microRNA levels with both activity and time</measure>
    <time_frame>multiple assessments within each visit for 4 visits total over 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>changes in motor function abilities</measure>
    <time_frame>once each visit</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Genetic Disorder</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Aged 18 or older

          -  Have a confirmed genetic diagnosis of one of the FSMDs

          -  Have a clinical phenotype consistent with one of the FSMDs

          -  Be able to travel to the NIH Clinical Center at the NIH for studies

          -  Able to commit to multiple 5 day stays at the NIH Clinical Center

          -  Established primary care physician

          -  Ambulant: able to walk 10 meters or 33 feet without walking aids or orthotics.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Fail to meet the above inclusion criteria

          -  Are unable or unwilling to be examined

          -  Adults unable to provide their own consent

          -  Have active, on-going medical problems such as (e.g. diabetes, hypothyroidism,
             pancreatitis, anemia, cancer, renal, hepatic, pulmonary or cardiac disease) or who
             have undergone recent surgery (i.e. less than 8 days post-surgery)

          -  Pregnant females

          -  Currently taking any or a combination of anti-inflammatory drugs, statins or other
             drugs with known myotoxicity, narcotics
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joshua J Zimmerberg, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ivonne Morales</last_name>
    <phone>Not Listed</phone>
    <email>moralesbenaviij@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Joshua J Zimmerberg, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-6571</phone>
    <email>zimmerbj@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-CH-0112.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bansal D, Campbell KP. Dysferlin and the plasma membrane repair in muscular dystrophy. Trends Cell Biol. 2004 Apr;14(4):206-13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15066638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohn RD, Campbell KP. Molecular basis of muscular dystrophies. Muscle Nerve. 2000 Oct;23(10):1456-71. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11003781</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wallace GQ, McNally EM. Mechanisms of muscle degeneration, regeneration, and repair in the muscular dystrophies. Annu Rev Physiol. 2009;71:37-57. doi: 10.1146/annurev.physiol.010908.163216. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18808326</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 9, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Muscle</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammatory Cytokines</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Biomarkers</keyword>
  <keyword>Predictors of Outcome</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Genetic Diseases, Inborn</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Muscular Dystrophies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
