<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="72095">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01777542</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB-P00005610</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01777542</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Rett Syndrome With Recombinant Human IGF-1</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pharmacological Treatment of Rett Syndrome by Stimulation of Synaptic Maturation With Recombinant Human IGF-1(Mecasermin [rDNA] Injection)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital Boston</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>International Rett Syndrome Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Autism Speaks</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital Boston</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Investigators are recruiting children for a clinical trial using the medication recombinant
      human IGF-1 (a.k.a. mecasermin or INCRELEX) to see if it improves the health of children
      with Rett syndrome (RTT). While IGF-1 is approved by the Food &amp; Drug Administration (FDA)
      for certain use in children, it is considered an investigational drug in this trial because
      it has not previously been used to treat RTT. Information from this study will help
      determine if IGF-1 effectively treats RTT but will not necessarily lead to FDA approval of
      IGF-1 as a treatment for RTT.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Enrolled subjects will complete five study periods: screening, two 20-week long treatment
      periods, a 10-week break between treatment periods (&quot;washout&quot;), and a follow-up phone call 4
      weeks after all treatment ends. Subjects will be chosen at random to receive either IGF-1 or
      placebo during the first treatment period and then switch to the alternate medication for
      the second treatment period. Therefore, by completion of the trial, all subjects will have
      received treatment with IGF-1 for 20 weeks. The study will be double-blinded; meaning,
      neither subjects' families nor study investigators will know who is receiving IGF-1 or
      placebo at any time. Treatment must be administered by the caregiver twice daily through
      subcutaneous (just underneath the skin) injections. Caregivers will be trained by research
      nurses in how to administer the medication. Participation in this study will last
      approximately one year.

      Throughout the course of the trial, investigators will collect information to assess the
      effects of IGF-1 and monitor for safety.  Families must attend study visits at Boston
      Children's Hospital every 10 weeks; requiring families to travel to and stay in Boston for
      about a week each time. These visits cannot be completed at any other hospital. Parents will
      fill out questionnaires and undergo a structured interview reporting on their child's
      health, behavior, and mood. Subjects will undergo clinical and physical examinations by a
      study doctor. Non-invasive devices and cameras will also be used to monitor things like
      breathing, hand movements, heart rate, and body temperature. Blood and urine will be
      collected for routine laboratory tests to monitor for safety. Investigators will also
      monitor safety by asking parents to complete a medication diary and side effect reporting
      form on a regular basis. Between trips to Boston Children's Hospital, parents will complete
      a set of online questionnaires and undergo a structured interview over the phone.

      The cost of travel and lodging during research-related visits to and from the hospital will
      not be covered by the study. If a condition or illness is identified during the trial (and
      is determined to be unrelated to study treatments), referrals to outside medical care will
      be made. Study medications and all research-related materials and services will be provided
      at no cost to participants. Parking vouchers will be provided for all study-related hospital
      visits.

      The study is investigating 5 potential effects:

        1. IGF-1 may improve subjects' behavior, communication and/or mood. In order to measure
           this, investigators will evaluate subjects every 5 weeks throughout each treatment
           period with behavioral and psychological assessments. All of the tests used during
           these evaluations are non-invasive. Investigators will ask parents what their
           impressions are about their child's behavior and day-to-day activities through a
           structured parental interview and various questionnaires.

        2. Investigators will examine subjects' brain function through use of a brain- monitoring
           device known as electroencephalography (EEG). The EEG measurements will be taken while
           investigators present subjects with exercises to stimulate their vision and hearing.
           EEG is a non-invasive way of recording the electrical activity of a subject's brain by
           applying a net of monitors (electrodes) to their scalp. Through this method
           investigators gain insight into how brain function links to behaviors in individuals
           with RTT. By understanding this relationship, investigators will be better able to
           identify whether or not treatment with IGF-1 affects the way the brain communicates
           with the body.

        3. As one of the features of RTT is unstable vital signs, investigators are trying to
           determine if IGF-1 has any effect on normalizing subjects' heart rate and breathing
           patterns. To measure this, investigators will ask subjects to wear a BioCapture® during
           hospital study visits every 10 weeks throughout each treatment period. The BioCapture®
           is a device that includes three electrocardiogram connectors and two stretchy bands
           that measure heart rate and respiratory patterns in a non-invasive way. This
           information will be recorded and stored on an accompanying laptop.

        4. The safety of IGF-1 in children with RTT is very important. Investigators will ask
           parents to complete a medication diary and side effect reporting form on a regular
           basis. In addition, laboratory tests will be performed every 10 weeks throughout each
           treatment period to evaluate the safety of IGF-1. These will be blood tests similar to
           those provided in typical clinical care. Subjects will undergo regular non-invasive
           comprehensive physical and neurological examinations, tonsil evaluation,
           electrocardiogram (ECG), echocardiogram, scoliosis x-ray, bone age x-ray, and
           measurement of height, weight and head circumference.

        5. Children with RTT often experience unintended, stereotyped hand movements. The Qsensor®
           is a non-invasive device worn on a fabric bracelet that continually measures subjects'
           movement. Investigators will use the Qsensor® to determine whether or not IGF-1 affects
           the presentation of stereotyped hand movements. As such, investigators will ask
           subjects to wear the Qsensor® during study visits every 10 weeks throughout each
           treatment period and occasionally at home.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rett Syndrome Behavior Questionnaire (RSBQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 5 weeks during each of the two 20-week treatment periods, and once 4 weeks after final treatment ends</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impression Scales</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 10 weeks during each of the two 20-week treatment periods</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantitative Measures of Respiration</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 10 weeks during each of the two 20-week treatment periods</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of cortical function using Visual Evoked Potentials</measure>
    <time_frame>At the beginning and end of each of the two 20-week treatment periods</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of hand stereotypies with the QSensor© accelerometer</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 10 weeks during each of the two 20-week treatment periods</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Rett Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Period 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>One half of subjects will be randomly assigned to receive Recombinant Human Insulin Growth Factor 1 (rhIGF-1) , and the other half of subjects will be randomly assigned to receive placebo.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Period 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects that initially received Recombinant Human Insulin Growth Factor 1 (rhIGF-1)  will now receive placebo, and subjects that initially received placebo will now receive Recombinant Human Insulin Growth Factor 1 (rhIGF-1).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Recombinant Human Insulin Growth Factor 1 (rhIGF-1)</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will receive twice daily subcutaneous injections of IGF-1.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Period 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Period 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>mecasermin [rDNA] injection</other_name>
    <other_name>Increlex</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will receive twice daily subcutaneous injections of a saline solution (placebo).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Period 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Period 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>saline</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of &quot;classic&quot; or &quot;typical&quot; Rett Syndrome

          -  Genetic documentation of MECP2 mutation

          -  Subject must be post-regression (Hagberg Stage 2)

          -  Subject and caregiver's primary language must be English

          -  Subject must reside in North America (US and Canada)

          -  Caregiver must have internet access and be able to complete questionnaires  online
             and communicate via email

          -  Subject is stable on current medications for at least 4 weeks

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Severe scoliosis (curvature &gt;40 degrees)

          -  Bone-age greater than 11

          -  Cardiomegaly (enlarged heart)

          -  Tanner stage 2 or higher breast development

          -  Allergy to IGF-1

          -  Prior use of IGF-1, growth hormone, or sex steroids
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>10 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Walter E. Kaufmann, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital Boston</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Katherine Barnes</last_name>
    <phone>617-355-5230</phone>
    <email>rettresearch@childrens.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Natalie Bruck</last_name>
    <phone>617-355-5230</phone>
    <email>rettresearch@childrens.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boston Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 14, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 23, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Harvard Medical School</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Walter Kaufmann</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Neurology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Rett syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>RTT</keyword>
  <keyword>IGF-1</keyword>
  <keyword>autism spectrum disorder</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Rett Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Mitogens</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insulin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
