<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="153038">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01908790</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HUM00075160</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01908790</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Correlation of Venous Oxygen Saturation Measurements by Non-invasive Mespere Venous Oximeter and Central Venous Catheter</brief_title>
  <official_title>Correlation of Venous Oxygen Saturation Measurements by Non-invasive Mespere Venous Oximeter vs Venous Oxygen Saturation From Blood Samples From the External Jugular Vein vs Central Venous Oxygen Saturation (ScvO2) vs Mixed Venous Oxygen Saturation (SvO2), Measured by a CO-Oximeter.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mespere Lifesciences Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mespere Lifesciences Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to establish the accuracy of the non-invasive Mespere VA
      Oximeter that uses near infrared spectroscopy (NIRS) to estimate venous oxygen saturation.
      The VA Oximeter will be validated by comparing it to the analysis of blood samples from the
      external jugular vein, internal jugular vein, and pulmonary artery measurements via right
      heart catheter (RHC). Furthermore, cardiac output (CO) measured from the Mespere VA Oximeter
      using the jugular vein and finger pulse oximeter will be compared to CO typically measured
      in practice using the central line, finger pulse oximeter, and Fick's equation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The conventional pulse oximeter has been a standard in clinical care for non-invasive
      hemodynamic monitoring, which only measures arterial blood oxygenation.  The clinical
      application of venous oximetry is numerous, including severe sepsis and septic shock, severe
      trauma and hemorrhagic shock, and heart failure and cardiac arrest.

      The existing method for venous blood oxygenation monitored is either through an invasive
      fiber optic catheter, or intermittently by blood sampling and CO-Oximetry.  However,
      catheterization can be costly and can include inherent risks.  Therefore, due to the
      inherent risks of catheterization, venous oximetry is limited only to critically ill
      patients.

      By non-invasively monitoring both venous and arterial blood oxygenation, Mespere VA Oximeter
      provides more complete information on patient hemodynamics and has clear advantages over
      conventional pulse oximeters.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>VA Oximeter ScvO2 Accuracy compared to CO-Oximeter</measure>
    <time_frame>0-10 minutes</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Accuracy of venous oxygen saturation measurements by VA Oximeter vs direct measurement of blood samples using CO-Oximeter (Avoximeter 4000)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Validation of VA Oximeter System</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Heart Failure Patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Acute and chronic heart failure patients already receiving right heart catheterization (RHC) as part of their usual care</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mespere VA Oximeter</intervention_name>
    <description>The Mespere VA Oximeter System is a novel non-invasive medical device for simultaneous measurement of venous blood oxygenation through the external jugular vein and arterial blood oxygenation through the finger tip (SpO2).  The Mespere VA Oximeter is based upon near infrared spectroscopy. The System consists of a portable display unit and two sensor probes. The user interface simultaneously displays the measured arterial and venous oxygen saturation percentage, at a refresh rate of approximately one (1) second, and their respective plethysmographic waveforms.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Heart Failure Patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Avoximeter 4000</intervention_name>
    <description>The portable Avoximeter 4000 provides rapid, accurate assessment of the patient's true oxygenation status at the bedside. Features: Results in less than 10 seconds; No sample preparation required; Uses whole blood sample; Easy to use.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Heart Failure Patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Whole blood
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Acute and chronic heart failure patients already receiving right heart catheterization
        (RHC) as part of their usual care
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18 and older

          -  Heart failure patients already receiving RHC as part of their usual care

          -  Subject has visible left or right external jugular vein (EJV)

          -  Signed written and informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Lack of patient consent

          -  Subject is pregnant

          -  Evidence of abnormal neck anatomy

          -  Subject does not have visible left and right external jugular vein (EJV)

          -  Subject has occluded internal jugular veins under ultrasound imaging

          -  Allergic to adhesive tape

          -  Ongoing photodynamic therapy

          -  Presence of known anatomical shunt or AV dialysis fistula

          -  Known central vein stenosis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Todd M Koelling, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan Cardiovascular Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 23, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>venous oximeter</keyword>
  <keyword>CO-Oximeter</keyword>
  <keyword>right heart catheter (RHC)</keyword>
  <keyword>non-invasive monitor</keyword>
  <keyword>heart failure (HF)</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
