<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="13115">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01699607</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0910005822</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01699607</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Test-retest Reproducibility of [11C]PHNO PET Using the Constant Infusion Paradigm</brief_title>
  <acronym>phno_amth</acronym>
  <official_title>Test-retest Reproducibility of [11C]PHNO PET Using the Constant Infusion</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yale University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Yale University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A research study designed to examine amphetamine-induced dopamine release using the PET
      imaging agent [11C]PHNO in tobacco smokers while currently smoking and during acute
      withdrawal and in nonsmokers. Twenty healthy men and women tobacco smokers and twenty
      healthy nonsmokers will be recruited. Each subject will participate in 1 MRI and up to 2
      [11C]PHNO PET scans. On the study day subjects will participate in two [11C]PHNO scans
      (ideally, the two PET scans will be carried out in the same day). Three hours before the
      second PET scan, amphetamine (0.5 mg/kg, PO) will be administered. In smokers, the scanwill
      occur at 10-21 days of smoking abstinence.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To determine amphetamine-induced DA release in tobacco smokers while currently smoking and
      during acute withdrawal and in nonsmokers. Twenty healthy men and women tobacco smokers and
      twenty healthy nonsmokers will be recruited. Each subject will participate in 1 MRI and up
      to 2 [11C]PHNO PET scans. On the PET study day  subjects will participate in two [11C]PHNO
      scans (ideally, the two PET scans will be carried out in the same day). Three hours before
      the second PET scan, amphetamine (0.5 mg/kg, PO) will be administered. In smokers, the set
      of scans will occur at 10-21 days of smoking abstinence.  Smoking abstinence will be
      determined by carbon monoxide and urine cotinine (a breakdown product of nicotine in
      cigarette smoke) levels. Subjects will be asked to breathe into a breathalyzer to measure
      carbon monoxide and to provide a urine sample to measure cotinine.  Smoking abstinence will
      be confirmed by carbon monoxide and cotinine levels that are reduced as compared to actively
      smoking.  We hypothesize that smokers at 10-21 days of withdrawal will have
      amphetamine-induced DA release that is blunted compared to healthy nonsmokers.

      Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans (3 T) will be collected in each subject to
      co-register PET and MRI for image analysis. Within two weeks of the PET study, an MRI will
      be acquired at the Yale University MRI Center. Subjects will be taken through a
      ferromagnetic metal detector before entering the scan room. The acquisition sequence is a 3D
      fast spoiled grass (FSPGR) MR pulse sequence with an IR prep of 300 ms. (TE= 3.3 ms, flip
      angle=17 degrees; slice thickness= 1.2 mm) optimized for delineating gray matter/white
      matter/CSF boundaries. The small voxel size (0.93 X 1.2 X 0.93 mm) provides high-resolution
      volumetric images. MR images provide a matching anatomical atlas for creating individualized
      region-of-interest templates for each subject.

      Subject preparation consists of two intravenous (IV) catheterizations and immobilization of
      the head. PET scans are acquired as subjects rest using an HRRT PET scanner (207 slices,
      resolution better than 3 mm FWHM). This resolution permits visualization of the PHNO and
      raclopride uptake in the ventral/dorsal striatum, in globus pallidus (GP) and substantia
      nigra (SN). A transmission scan using an orbiting 137Cs point-source is obtained for each
      emission scan. Motion correction will be performed dynamically with measurements from the
      Vicra (NDI Systems, Waterloo, Ontario) used by a dedicated list-mode reconstruction
      algorithm.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case Control, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Nicotine Dependence,</condition>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Smokers</arm_group_label>
    <description>20 Subjects with nicotine dependence to participate in two [11C]PHNO scans with amphetamine administration</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non Smokers</arm_group_label>
    <description>20 Healthy control subjects to participate in two [11C]PHNO scans with amphetamine administration</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Healthy Female and Male Non Smokers
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  men and women, aged 18-55 years

          -  who are able to read and write

          -  who are able to give voluntary written informed consent

          -  have no current uncontrolled medical condition such as neurological, cardiovascular,
             endocrine, renal, liver, or thyroid pathology

          -  have no history of a neurological or psychiatric disorder, e.g., no DSMIV Axis 1
             diagnosis in 2 preceding years, except nicotine dependence in smokers)

          -  drink less than 21 drinks/week for women and less than 35 drinks per week for men

          -  have not used marijuana in the past 30 days and have not met criteria for dependence
             in the past 2 years

          -  do not suffer from claustrophobia or any MRI contradictions

          -  nonsmokers (smoked &lt; 40 cigarettes in lifetime with urinary cotinine levels 0-30
             ng/mL both at intake evaluation and on scan day)

          -  smokers (smoked at least 10 cigarettes/day for at least one year with an FTND&gt;3,
             urine cotinine &gt;150 ng/mL and CO &gt;12 ppm at intake)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  psychosis

          -  presence of acute or unstable medical or neurological illness. Subjects will be
             excluded from the study if they present with any history of serious medical or
             neurological illness or if they show signs of a major medical or neurological illness
             on examination or lab testing including history of seizures, head injury, brain
             tumor, heart, liver or kidney disease, eating disorder, diabetes.

          -  regular use of any psychotropic drugs including anxiolytics and antidepressants and
             other over-the-counter medications and herbal products within the last six months

          -  pregnancy/breast feeding (as documented by pregnancy testing at screening or on days
             of the imaging studies),

          -  suicidal ideation or behavior

          -  pacemaker or other ferromagnetic material in body.

          -  use of medications which affect dopamine transmission within 2 weeks of the PET study

          -  participation in other research studies involving ionizing radiation within one year
             of the PET scans that would cause the subject to exceed the yearly dose limits for
             normal volunteers
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kelly Cosgrove, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assistant Professor</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kelly Cosgrove, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>203-932-5711</phone>
    <phone_ext>3329</phone_ext>
    <email>kelly.cosgrove@yale.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Evgenia Perkins</last_name>
    <phone>203-932-5711</phone>
    <phone_ext>4108</phone_ext>
    <email>evgenia.perkins@yale.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Connecticut Health Care System</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06516</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kelly Cosgrove, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>203-932-5711</phone>
      <phone_ext>3329</phone_ext>
      <email>kelly.cosgrove@yale.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kelly Cosgrove, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 29, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 1, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Yale University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kelly  Cosgrove</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cigarette Smokers</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Non Smokers</keyword>
  <keyword>Amphetamine</keyword>
  <keyword>PET</keyword>
  <keyword>Controls</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Tobacco Use Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
