<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="68929">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02055040</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11-443</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02055040</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Detection of Cardiac Fibrosis in Patients With Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Non-invasive Detection of Cardiac Fibrosis After Administration of Doxorubicin-Based Chemotherapy in Patients With Lymphoma Using Cardiac Magnetic Resonance: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research study is a clinical trial. Clinical trials test the effectiveness of an
      investigational imaging technique to learn whether the investigational imaging technique
      works in detecting cardiac injury after the administration of certain chemotherapies, such
      as doxorubicin. &quot;Investigational&quot; means that the imaging technique is still being studied
      and that research doctors are trying to find out more about it-such as whether the technique
      can detect lower levels of cardiac injury after treatment with doxorubicin. It also means
      that the FDA has not yet approved the use of gadolinium or approved the use of CMR studies
      for detection of cardiac toxicity after doxorubicin.

      The chemotherapy drug that you have been scheduled to be treated with, doxorubicin, has been
      associated with the development of heart failure in some patients.

      Cardiac Magnetic Resonance (CMR) is a type of MRI scan that uses a magnetic field to produce
      pictures of the heart. The CMR scan has been used in other studies and information from
      those other research studies suggest that this imaging technique may help to better detect
      differences in the structure of the heart muscle after treatment with doxorubicin.

      In this research study, the investigators hope that they can better detect changes in the
      heart muscle before and after treatment with doxorubicin with the CMR scan in hopes that
      cardiac injury can be detected and treated earlier to prevent heart failure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      If you decide to participate in this research study, you will be asked to undergo some
      screening procedures to determine if you are eligible. These procedures include: medical
      history, determination of kidney function and a pregnancy test (if applicable). The
      investigators will also ask you to sign a CMR safety screening form that makes sure it is
      safe for you to have the CMR scan. If you have metallic implants (pacemakers,
      defibrillators, or aneurysm clips) or metallic fragments in your eye, you should not have a
      CMR. If these tests show that you are eligible to participate in the research study, you
      will begin the study. If you do not meet the eligibility criteria, you will not be able to
      participate in this research study.

      Visit 1 will take place prior to starting doxorubicin chemotherapy. The visit will take
      about 1.5 hours. The investigators will ask you to come to the Shapiro Cardiovascular Center
      at the Brigham and Women's Hospital for your study visit. For subjects that qualify, the
      investigators will bring you to the basement level of the hospital for the heart CMR scan,
      an echocardiogram and some blood work. Before your CMR scan the investigators will take some
      blood via the IV cannula. The investigators will take about 4 tubes of blood. This is
      equivalent to 2.5 tablespoons of blood. From this blood the investigators will test for
      blood markers of cardiac injury and compare these results to your other tests.

      For the CMR scan, you will be asked to lie still on the scanner table that slides into a
      tunnel-shaped machine. Four electrocardiogram (EKG) patches with wires attached will be
      placed on your chest or your back to check your heart rate. The investigators will place an
      intravenous (IV) catheter in one of your arms. An IV catheter is a thin plastic tube that is
      put into a vein with a needle. The IV catheter will be used to give you a CMR contrast dye
      (gadolinium). The dye will help us to identify subtle changes within the heart muscle. This
      dye, gadolinium, is used routinely in CMR studies. The investigators will also draw a sample
      of blood from the IV catheter to measure your red blood cell count. Then, the scanner table
      will move slowly into the tunnel-shaped CMR machine so the pictures can be taken. The
      machine is slightly wider than your body and there may be little room to move. If you feel
      any discomfort or need to stop the test, you will be able to tell this to the research
      staff. You will be able to speak to them while you are having the CMR and they will be able
      to speak to you. If you think that you might be too anxious about being inside the narrow
      CMR scanner for a long period of time, the investigators may prescribe a drug to help you
      relax you if you think it might be helpful. The CMR scan will take one hour.

      An echocardiogram is a test used by doctors to monitor heart function. An echocardiogram is
      a safe test that uses ultrasound to image the heart. After completion of the CMR test, you
      will have an echocardiogram. This test will take place in the same area as the CMR test. The
      echocardiogram test will take 40 minutes.

      Visit 2 will take place about 2-4 weeks after your last cycle of doxorubicin chemotherapy.
      When you come back for Visit 2, you will have the same type of CMR scan, echocardiogram and
      blood testing that you had during Visit 1.

      At Visit 3 the investigators will perform an exercise test on a bicycle. The test is
      designed to test the oxygen consumption of your body when exercising. It provides a way of
      quantifying the ability of the body to exercise. This test will take 30 minutes. During this
      test subjects sit on the bicycle for at least 3 minutes pedaling at a rate of 60 cycles per
      minute and slowly the work-load is increased until peak exercise is obtained. The
      investigators define peak exercise as being tired or breathless. Heart rate and blood
      pressure are recorded during the test. During the test you will breathe through a mouthpiece
      from which the investigators will measure oxygen levels.

      It will take you 12-16 months to complete this research study, depending on the date and
      timing of your chemotherapy. During this time, the investigators will ask you to make 3
      study visits. The investigators will call you after approximately six months to see how you
      are doing.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 0</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Early detection of DOX-induced cardiac injury</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A novel cardiac magnetic resonance-based index of interstitial myocardial fibrosis. Dimensionless measure of extra-cellular volume fraction in myocardial tissue.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alteration of serum biomarkers after doxorubicin based chemotherapy</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Serum biomarkers of cardiac stress, collagen turn-over, and myocardial injury. Values represent absolute serum concentrations.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alteration of echocardiographic indices after doxorubicin-based chemotherapy</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Conventional and novel echocardiographic indices of cardiac function. Indices are dimensionless and represent ratios measured by echocardiography.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of cardiopulmonary functional capacity</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measures of cardiopulmonary functional capacity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine association between measurements pre- and post-doxorubicin-based chemotherapy</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Statistical measures of association between CMR, echocardiographic, serum and functional measures pre- and post-doxorubicin-based chemotherapy. Measures are unitless.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">77</enrollment>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cardiac Magnetic Resonance</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cardiac Magnetic Resonance scan at visits 1 and 2</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cardiac Magnetic Resonance Scan</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cardiac Magnetic Resonance</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  New diagnosis of lymphoma

          -  Scheduled to undergo doxorubicin-based chemotherapy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Concurrent radiotherapy prior to the performance of both CMR studies

          -  Prior malignancy treated with chemotherapy or mediastinal radiotherapy

          -  Contraindications to performance of a magnetic resonance study: presence of implanted
             metallic object, implanted neural stimulator, ferromagnetic implants not deemed MRI
             safe, intra-ocular metallic foreign bodies, severe claustrophobia, pregnancy,
             inability to perform exercise test
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Jerosch-Herold, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael Jerosch-Herold, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>6175258959</phone>
    <email>mjerosch-herold@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham and Women's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Jerosch-Herold, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>617-525-8959</phone>
      <email>mjerosch-herold@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Jerosch-Herold, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Javid Moslehi, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-307-1964</phone>
      <email>jmoslehi@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Javid Moslehi, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 3, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael Jerosch-Herold</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
