<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="40209">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01937923</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>455690</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>DR2A-05415</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01937923</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pre-Cellular Therapy Observational Study in Early Huntington's Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>PRE-CELL</acronym>
  <official_title>A Pre-Cellular Therapy Observational Study in Early Huntington's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Davis</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Davis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This observational study will establish a clinical baseline and measure changes over time in
      movement, thinking, behavior, brain imaging, blood and spinal fluid markers in subjects with
      early stage Huntington's disease. Participants enrolled in this study may be eligible to
      participate in a future planned study of stem cell therapy for Huntington's Disease (HD).

      In-person study visits occur at screening, baseline, and every 6 months thereafter for a
      minimum of 12 months, with interim phone call assessments.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In PRE-CELL the investigators propose to enroll a cohort of early-stage HD patients in a
      prospective observational study designed to characterize clinical, neuro-imaging, laboratory
      and biomarker correlates of disease progression over 12-18 months. Subjects who complete a
      minimum of 12 months' participation in this trial will be candidates for enrollment in the
      future planned Phase 1 trial of intrastriatal delivery of mesenchymal stem cell
      (MSC)/Brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of change from baseline in white matter volume on magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) brain scan.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 or 18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of change from baseline on the UHDRS total motor score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 or 18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of change from baseline on the Total Functional Capacity score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 or 18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Huntington Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No treatment</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Safety labs: Complete blood count, comprehensive metabolic panel, international normalized
      ration, partial thromboplastic time, thyroid stimulating hormone, urinalysis, HIV screen.

      Biomarkers: Brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF) in cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) and
      Plasma, BDNF related and Huntington's Disease (HD) specific gene transcription markers in
      CSF and blood, Small molecule markers of HD in CSF and plasma
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects will be primarily recruited from the Huntington's disease clinic in the
        University of California, Davis (UC Davis) department of neurology. We also plan to
        recruit participants from among northern California regional support groups, from letters
        to neurologists and psychiatrists who are treating patients with HD, from listing our
        study on clinical trials.gov, and at regional and national HD meeting presentations, and
        via print and video recordings on our website.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men or women age 18 and older, English speaking, able to give informed consent and
             comply with study procedures.

          -  HD diagnosis confirmed with genetic testing demonstrating CAG trinucleotide repeat
             length (CAGn) greater than 37

          -  Early stage HD with Total Functional Capacity (TFC) score of 9-13

          -  Demonstrable motor signs with a Unified Huntington's Disease Rating Scale (UHDRS)
             diagnostic confidence level of 4

          -  Must have a caregiver or informant able to give feedback about the participant and
             willing to report observations about subject on standardized forms.

          -  Subjects of child bearing potential must agree to adequate birth control measures
             including intrauterine device, hormone therapy, hormone rings or barrier methods
             including foams/gels AND condoms.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Very early disease without demonstrable motor signs (diagnostic confidence level &lt; 4)

          -  Significant cognitive impairment or dementia as defined by Montreal Cognitive
             Assessment (MoCA) score &lt; 12.

          -  Moderate or advanced disease with TFC &lt; 9

          -  Concurrent active unstable psychiatric disease including history of suicide attempts
             within the last year, major personality or psychiatric disorders.

          -  History of concurrent serious medical illness such as HIV or current anti-retroviral
             treatment, cancer, major cardiac, pulmonary, immunological or other organ disease.

          -  History of coagulopathy, bleeding disorder, or concurrent use of blood thinners.

          -  History of brain tumor, serious traumatic brain injury with coma, or history of brain
             surgery.

          -  Any comorbid condition that presents an unacceptable health risk to the patient in
             the investigator's view

          -  Clinically significant laboratory test abnormalities, including full blood count,
             chemistry panel, liver function tests, Prothrombin time/international normalized
             ratio (PT/INR), lipid panel, electrocardiogram (EKG), or chest x-ray as judged by the
             investigator.

          -  Active drug or alcohol use or dependence that, in the opinion of the site
             investigator, would interfere with safety or adherence to study requirements.

          -  History or documentation of contraindication for MRI brain scan, including the
             presence of pacemaker, neurostimulator, aneurysm clips, artificial heart valves,
             cochlear implants, metal fragments in the eyes, orbits or skin or any other known
             contraindication to MRI.

          -  Any significant MRI brain scan findings other than those characteristic of HD.

          -  Any contraindications to surgery or to the use of general anesthesia, including
             allergy.

          -  History of use of any investigational agent within 60 days prior to enrollment

          -  History of current or previous gene therapy or stem cell therapy.

          -  History of previous or current treatment with cytokines

          -  History of sensitivity to ganciclovir.

          -  Pregnant and/or lactating women
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vicki Wheelock, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Davis</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Teresa Tempkin, RNC MSN ANP</last_name>
    <phone>916-734-6278</phone>
    <email>teresa.tempkin@ucdmc.ucdavis.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Amanda Martin, BA</last_name>
    <phone>916-734-3541</phone>
    <email>amanda.martin@ucdmc.ucdavis.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UC Davis Medical Center, Clinical and Translational Science Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mather</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95655</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 4, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 26, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Huntington Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
