<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="72032">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01672242</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HP-00052656</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01672242</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of End Expiratory Lung Volumes in Healthy Subjects Using High Flow Oxygen (Vapotherm®)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessment of End Expiratory Lung Volumes in Healthy Subjects Using High Flow Oxygen (Vapotherm®)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Maryland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Vapotherm, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Maryland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Respiratory distress is a common problem in an intensive care unit. There are multiple
      mechanisms that are used to help patients who are in respiratory distress including
      mechanical ventilation, continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP), bilevel positive airway
      pressure (BiPAP), high flow oxygen, and oxygen supplementation through nasal cannula or a
      facemask.

      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the mechanism by which Vapotherm, a high flow
      oxygen system, provides breathing support. Vapotherm provides high flow oxygen at different
      flow rates, meaning one can increase the amount of oxygen flow to help with breathing
      support. The investigators believe that this high flow oxygen system may provide similar
      breathing support that a continuous positive airway pressure machine (CPAP) machine does.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      High flow nasal cannula oxygen therapy (HFNC) is a method of oxygen delivery now commonly
      used in persistently hypoxic patients refractory to conventional modes of oxygen
      supplementation (i.e. nasal cannula, facemask, non-rebreather facemask). Initially used in
      neonates, it is now increasingly popular in the adult population. While the investigators
      know how HFNC provides oxygen supplementation, the physiologic mechanism of correcting
      hypoxemia is still unclear. There are five mechanisms of hypoxemia, four which correct with
      oxygen supplementation - decreased FiO2, hyperventilation, V/Q mismatch, and diffusion
      defect; and one that does not - shunt. The hypoxemia refractory to supplemental oxygen
      suggests the presence of physiologic shunt. The conventional non-invasive therapy to reduce
      shunt fraction requires raising end-expiratory lung volumes by raising end-expiratory airway
      pressures using the application of continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) or bilevel
      positive airway pressure (BiPAP). The Vapotherm® (Vapotherm®, Stevensville, Maryland)
      product of high flow oxygen therapy (Precision Flow®) is one the investigators frequently
      use in intensive care units at the University of Maryland Medical Center. It does not create
      a leak proof seal in the nose as seen in CPAP and BiPAP. Positive pressure generation has
      been studied in another high flow oxygen system called Optiflow™ (Fisher &amp; Paykel
      Healthcare, Ltd., Auckland, New Zealand). However this device differs from Vapotherm® in
      that its nasal bores are large and create a seal in each nares thereby affected both
      ventilation and the level of PEEP generation. Additionally, these studies measured positive
      expiratory lung pressures, not volume. Positive end expiratory alveolar pressure and
      increase expiratory lung volumes in adults have not yet been demonstrated using Precision
      Flow®.

      HFNC is intriguing because studies and clinical data have shown it is a relatively
      non-invasive method of oxygen delivery that appears to correct hypoxemia better than other
      non-invasive methods. It is more comfortable than a CPAP machine and thus is better
      tolerated among patients, especially those who are critically ill and possibly altered.
      While it has been used in neonates for some time, its use with adults is new and needs more
      research.

      The investigators hypothesis is that HFNC corrects persistent hypoxemia by producing
      increased end-expiratory lung volumes thus keeping alveoli open throughout the respiratory
      cycle which other oxygen supplements are unable to do. Using healthy volunteers the
      investigators will measure end expiratory lung volumes on HFNC and compare them to those
      obtained with CPAP at graded pressures.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Bio-equivalence Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>End-expiratory lung volume</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Adult Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-invasive ventilation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Graded high flow nasal cannula oxygen and facial CPAP will be randomly applied to each subject and end-expiratory lung volume measured by respiratory inductive plethysmography.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High-flow nasal cannula oxygen</intervention_name>
    <description>Graded levels of HFNC will be applied and end-expiratory lung volumes measured by respiratory inductive plethysmography</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non-invasive ventilation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Precision Flow®, Vapotherm®, Stevensville, MD</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Facial CPAP</intervention_name>
    <description>Graded levels of CPAP will be applied by face mask and end-expiratory lung volumes measured by respiratory inductive plethysmography</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non-invasive ventilation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Respironics</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age between 18 and 75

          -  Able to follow and understand simple instructions to collect spirometry

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Younger than 18y/o

          -  Older than 75 years old

          -  History of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)

          -  History of asthma

          -  History of congestive heart failure

          -  Measured FEV1/FVC &lt;70 when undergoing spirometry
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carl B. Shanholtz, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Maryland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Maryland School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 25, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 9, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Maryland</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carl Shanholtz</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
