<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="84089">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02057549</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13040380</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02057549</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Haloperidol vs Conventional Therapy for Gastroparesis</brief_title>
  <acronym>HATGAS</acronym>
  <official_title>Haloperidol vs Conventional Therapy for Gastroparesis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Randomized controlled trial comparing haloperidol combined with conventional therapy and
      conventional therapy alone in patients with symptomatic gastroparesis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Design This study is a prospective, double-blind randomized placebo controlled trial
      involving adult ED patients who present with an acute exacerbation of gastroparesis.  This
      study design will have two arms in the clinical trials. An experimental arm will receive an
      intravenous dose of haloperidol 5 mg in addition to conventional therapy, and the control
      arm will receive conventional therapy. Patients will be randomized as described below.
      Neither the physician nor the patient will be aware of the group to which the patient was
      randomized.

      Methods Upon arrive at to the ED at the Memorial Hermann Hospital located in the Texas
      Medical Center; patients with GP exacerbation will be assessed for eligibility for
      enrollment in this trial by the clinicians on duty.  Informed consent will be obtained from
      eligible patients that meet inclusion and exclusion criteria by trained ED residents.   A 12
      lead electrocardiogram will be performed to evaluate the presence of QT segment
      prolongation. Enrolled patients will be given 5 mg of intravenous haloperidol or equivalent
      volume of placebo pre-packaged and coded with a study ID number provided by the
      investigational pharmacy.

      No unique identifiers or other PHI will be collected on enrolled patients. Information will
      also be recorded on the time elapsed from the time it took to provide the study medication
      and the time of the decision on disposition (admit or discharge).  A record will be
      maintained if any additional medications including analgesics and antiemetics given to the
      patient before and after the study vial are given. Data will be collected on any adverse
      effects or complications the patients may experience (i.e. dystonic reactions, allergies
      etc.). After the data is collected at one hour for the primary outcome the trial will end
      and the physician will be unblended so they can choose subsequent medication.

      All completed data collection forms will be dropped off in a secure locked mailbox and
      collected on a weekly basis by research staff.  Collected forms will be housed in the ED
      office located in the Jesse Jones Library (JJL) 4th floor in a locked cabinet.  Data will be
      entered electronically and analyzed using SPSS statistical software (version 19.0).  This
      database will be housed on a rights-protected research drive with limited access for
      viewing.

      Informed Consent Patients will be notified of this study and they will be asked if they are
      interested in participating. If they are interested in participating, they will have the
      informed consent (IC) explained to them in either English or Spanish (Beaudoin, Nagdev,
      Merchant &amp; Becker, 2010).  The patient will sign, date, and put the time on the IC.  The
      consenter will also do the same.  A copy of the IC will be made in the ED and given to the
      patient for their records.  The original copy will be housed in the regulatory binder
      located in JJL.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptoms relief - defined as improvement on mean change in Liker pain scale 1-5</measure>
    <time_frame>we estimate that the time frame will be 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>&quot;Symptom relief&quot; - is defined as improvement on mean change in Liker pain scale 1-5</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time frame for discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>we estimate the time frame to be 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The &quot;time frame&quot; starts from the moment of receiving the study drug to the time when the decision for final disposition is made. Usually after symptoms are controlled, patients are given a PO challenge (food or drink) in order to establish if they are OK to go home. If  symptoms return, additional medications are given, the treatment is consider failed and they are admitted to the Hospital.
Patients will not be followed up if admitted to any service. The study ends when final disposition is made.
Patients follow up after final disposition is not part of the study and will not be done.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastroparesis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Haloperidol + conventional care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>an intravenous dose of 5mg haloperidol in addition to conventional therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Therapy alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>the control arm will receive conventional therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Haloperidol</intervention_name>
    <description>adding haloperidol to conventional therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Haloperidol + conventional care</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Haldol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous diagnosis of GP including those without formal gastric emptying studies.

          -  Patients presenting with unresolving nausea, vomiting, and abdominal pain that is
             attributable to their GP.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of QT prolongation or presence on a 12 leads electrocardiogram.

          -  Presence of concomitant acute abdominal pathology including but not limited to
             hepatobiliary disease, ischemia, and abdominal aneurysm.

          -  Prisoners

          -  Hypotension (systolic blood pressure below 90 mm Hg)

          -  Pregnant women

          -  Patients who are cognitively impaired and/or unable to consent for the study

          -  Age &lt;18

          -  Allergy to haloperidol
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carlos J Roldan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Texas</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Carlos J Roldan, MD</last_name>
    <email>Carlos.J.Roldan@uth.tmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Yashwant Chathampally, MD</last_name>
    <email>Yashwant.Chathampally@uth.tmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lyndon Baines Johnson General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77026</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carlos J Roldan, MD</last_name>
      <email>Carlos.J.Roldan@uth.tmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carlos J Roldan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yashwant Chathampally, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Linda Paniagua, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter J Carlson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sonali Patel, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 5, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 29, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carlos Roldan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, Associate professor in Emergency Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Gastroparesis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Haloperidol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Haloperidol decanoate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
