<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="68967">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02105740</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UNB19739513900000030</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02105740</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hypnosis in Pain Management of Mucositis Lesions, Anxiety and Depression in Oncological Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>HPADM</acronym>
  <official_title>Hypnosis as a Complementary Practice in Pain Management of Mucositis Lesions, Anxiety and Depression in Oncological Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Gil Montenegro</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Brasilia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Brasilia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Brazil: National Committee of Ethics in Research</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study's aim is to use hypnosis in cancer patients with mucositis (grades 1,2 or 3),
      caused by radiotherapy, in order to reduce the level of pain in the mucositis lesions, as
      well as anxiety and depression, as compared to the control group. For this evaluation
      development scales of mucositis proposed by World Health Organization (WHO), the Visual
      Analogue Scale (VAS) and Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale ( HADS) will be used.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Voluntary Oncology Patients of both sexes, aged between 18 and 80 years old, without
      neurological or psychiatric disorders that present degree of mucositis (1,2 or 3) will be
      randomly distributed into 2 groups of 40 participants each. Both groups will receive
      treatment protocol for the application of low-power laser. All participants will be assessed
      using the mucositis Development Scale proposed by the WHO, by 3 different examiners and will
      answer the variables control record as well as the Visual Analogue Scale  (VAS) and Hospital
      Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) in 3 different moments, at the beginning of the study,
      after 3 days and after 2 weeks from the second evaluation. The experimental group will
      evaluate the effects of hypnosis on the intensity of the pain in mucositis lesions, as well
      as depression and anxiety. The control group will only follow the treatment protocol
      mentioned above, being monitored by the scales as to the progression of symptoms.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease of score of pain of mucositis in the Visual Analogic Scale,  using hypnosis.</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Compare through the scores on the Visual Analogic Scale (VAS) the effect of hypnosis in reducing the pain caused by mucositis among the 40 patients  of the experimental group and the 40 patients of the control group. To measure the development of mucositis the scale from World Health Organization will be used.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease of anxiety and depression with the use of hypnosis.</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Comparison between the experimental group and the control group as to the effect of hypnosis in reducing anxiety and depression, using  for this the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS): which has 14 items, seven of which are directed to the evaluation of anxiety (HADS-A) and seven to depression (HADS - D).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Mucositis</condition>
  <condition>Depression Anxiety Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hypnosis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Use of hypnosis in the reduction of the levels of pain from mucositis lesions, depression and anxiety.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control x Experimental Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Comparison of the effects of hypnosis between the control group and the experimental group regarding pain, anxiety and depression  with the application of the scales.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hypnosis</intervention_name>
    <description>The hypnosis intervention consists of two 40-minute sessions, with an interval of 3 days between them, emphasizing the pain blocking, the well-being of the patient and the reduction of the symptoms of anxiety and depression of the same.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hypnosis</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control x Experimental Group</intervention_name>
    <description>The control and experimental groups respond in 3 different distinct moments, with the Visual Analog Scale (VAS) for the evaluation of pain, and the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) to evaluate the depression and the anxiety. The first evaluation will be made before the research. The second within an interval of 3 days, so being that in the experimental group the same will happen after the hypnosis session and in the control group after the follow-up visit. The third evaluation will be two weeks later, in order to provide a follow-up to assess the efficacy of the technique. The experimental group and the control group will be compared in relation to the intensity of the pain of mucositis lesions, and depression and anxiety</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control x Experimental Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with mucositis resulting from cancer treatment , regardless of the location
             of the primary tumor , chemotherapy or radiation may or may not have concomitant
             surgical indication.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        -  Patients outside this age range , users of psychotropic drugs , patients terminally ill
        with cancer , psychiatric patients , hearing impaired , patients with mental disabilities
        such as Down syndrome , autism and others.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GIL MONTENEGRO, DOUTORANDO</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>GIL MONTENEGRO, doutorado</last_name>
    <phone>055 61 81487323</phone>
    <email>prof.gilmontenegro@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UNB- Universidade de Brasilia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brasilia</city>
        <state>Distrito Federal</state>
        <zip>70910900</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>GIL MONTENEGRO, Doutorando</last_name>
      <phone>055 61 81487323</phone>
      <email>prof.gilmontenegro@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>GIL MONTENEGRO, DOUTORANDO</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lalla RV, Sonis ST, Peterson DE. Management of oral mucositis in patients who have cancer. Dent Clin North Am. 2008 Jan;52(1):61-77, viii. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18154865</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bardia A, Barton DL, Prokop LJ, Bauer BA, Moynihan TJ. Efficacy of complementary and alternative medicine therapies in relieving cancer pain: a systematic review. J Clin Oncol. 2006 Dec 1;24(34):5457-64. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17135649</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Montgomery GH, Bovbjerg DH, Schnur JB, David D, Goldfarb A, Weltz CR, Schechter C, Graff-Zivin J, Tatrow K, Price DD, Silverstein JH. A randomized clinical trial of a brief hypnosis intervention to control side effects in breast surgery patients. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2007 Sep 5;99(17):1304-12. Epub 2007 Aug 28.</citation>
    <PMID>17728216</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Porter LS, Keefe FJ. Psychosocial issues in cancer pain. Curr Pain Headache Rep. 2011 Aug;15(4):263-70. doi: 10.1007/s11916-011-0190-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21400251</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Spiegel D, Bloom JR. Group therapy and hypnosis reduce metastatic breast carcinoma pain. Psychosom Med. 1983 Aug;45(4):333-9.</citation>
    <PMID>6622622</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Trijsburg RW, van Knippenberg FC, Rijpma SE. Effects of psychological treatment on cancer patients: a critical review. Psychosom Med. 1992 Jul-Aug;54(4):489-517. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>1502290</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Landier W, Tse AM. Use of complementary and alternative medical interventions for the management of procedure-related pain, anxiety, and distress in pediatric oncology: an integrative review. J Pediatr Nurs. 2010 Dec;25(6):566-79. doi: 10.1016/j.pedn.2010.01.009. Epub 2010 Mar 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21035021</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 27, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Brasilia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gil Montenegro</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Doutorando em Ciências Médicas</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>BEHAVIORAL</keyword>
  <keyword>HYPNOSIS</keyword>
  <keyword>MUCOSITIS</keyword>
  <keyword>ANXIETY</keyword>
  <keyword>DEPRESSION</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mucositis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dysthymic Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
