<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="144502">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01760785</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>08-0582</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>PT075168</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01760785</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Valproate for Mood Swings and Alcohol Use Following Head Injury</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double Blind Trial of Divalproex Sodium for Affective Lability and Alcohol Use Following Traumatic Brain Injury</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Department of Defense</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Despite the body's natural healing during the first year after a head injury, many veterans
      who have suffered even mild brain injuries find themselves easily upset or fearful as they
      go about their daily lives. While these reactions to the world around them were easily
      managed before the head injury, they now occur with little or no interruption and are
      exceedingly difficult to manage. Such reactions include a sense of always being upset or
      fearful that often makes it difficult to get along with family members, friends, coworkers,
      and employers. This may lead to broken marriages, unemployment, and even homelessness.

      Some people with head injuries try to manage their unmanageable moods by drinking alcohol
      because it can create a sense of calm. However, alcohol's actions are short in duration.
      Most find that they have to drink more and more for a similar calming effect, and they soon
      become dependent on alcohol. This makes working and being part of their families even more
      difficult.

      To treat the unmanageable mood, we tried a medicine called valproate, one that eases mood
      problems in people without head injury. We gave valproate to head injured persons with mood
      problems in a &quot;non-blinded&quot; study where both the doctor and the patient knew that the
      medicine was valproate and both were optimistic that it would work. In a small sample of
      eighteen people, 85% found mood relief and most of those either stopped drinking alcohol or
      drank much less than before. However, this might have been because both the doctor and
      patient were hopeful that the medication would make the patient feel better or because the
      medicine actually worked.

      The only way to know for sure if the medicine works is to perform a study in which people
      receive either valproate or a sugar pill while neither they nor their doctor know which one
      they are taking. This is called a double blind study, as proposed here, and will involve
      nearly three times as many head injured persons as the first study.

      If it is successful, the new study will show that valproate treatment helps head injured
      people manage their moods and allows them to return to families, friends, and work. It will
      also show that they drink alcohol less or not at all, improving their health even further.
      Then doctors will know that they can use this medicine for large numbers of people who
      suffer from head injury and help them to lead normal lives. If the outcome of the study
      shows that the medicine works well, doctors can then use this medicine to treat people with
      head injury immediately after the study results are published.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Affective Lability</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1-10</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Symptom frequencies of affective lability will be measured weekly using the Agitated Behavior Scale and Neurobehavioral Rating Scale (Revised).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol Use</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1-10</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Frequencies of alcohol use/misuse will be measured weekly utilizing the Timeline Followback assessment.  Participants will also be given an alcohol breath test at every clinic visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Traumatic Brain Injury (TBI)</condition>
  <condition>Alcoholism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>divalproex sodium</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>sugar pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>divalproex sodium</intervention_name>
    <description>Doses will be given in 250mg increments and titrated over the first four days of study until a starting dose of 750 mg is reached. The Study Oversight Team, who is not involved in any clinical visits, will be un-blinded to study drug assignment and will have plasma concentration results and adverse event reports available to them. If a subject has no adverse events and is not at therapeutic level as indicated by the blood levels, the Study Oversight Team may inform the research pharmacy to increase the dose by 1 tablet of 250 mg to 1000 mg per day. The Study Oversight Team may also inform the research pharmacy to reduce the daily dosage back down to 750 mg per day if plasma concentrations or adverse events become intolerable. The maximum dose for the purpose of this study will be 1250 mg daily and the minimum dose will be 750 mg daily. Subjects who cannot tolerate the minimum dose will be excluded from any further study participation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>divalproex sodium</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Doses will be titrated over the first four days of study in the same manner as the active study drug. After titration, the research pharmacy may increase the dose by 1 tablet per day, in the same fashion that the active drug may be adjusted, so that the participant and clinical team remain blinded to the drug assignment. The research pharmacy may also reduce the daily dosage back down by one tablet per day for the same reason.</description>
    <arm_group_label>sugar pill</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>sugar pill</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Veteran

          -  history of closed-head traumatic brain injury (TBI) at least one year prior to
             enrollment

          -  symptoms of affective lability such as mood swings, irritability, frustration and
             anxiety

          -  currently using alcohol

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  history of Axis I bipolar disorder or anxiety disorder prior to the TBI

          -  skull opened either surgically or traumatically

          -  history of stroke

          -  current diagnosis or past history of major psychosis as defined by Diagnostic and
             Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-IV)

          -  active liver disease

          -  evidence of the alcohol amnesic syndrome

          -  history of seizure disorder other than those caused by ethanol withdrawal

          -  any type of dementia

          -  current suicidal/homicidal ideations

          -  symptomatic thiamine, folate or Vitamin B-12 deficiency

          -  HIV positive

          -  any medical conditions that would constitute contraindications to treatment with
             divalproex sodium
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas P Beresford, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Denver Veteran's Affairs Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Brandon Schmidt, MA</last_name>
    <phone>720-854-4200</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Denver Veteran's Affairs Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80220</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Brandon Schmidt, MA</last_name>
      <phone>720-854-4200</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 2, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 8, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Veterans</keyword>
  <keyword>Traumatic Brain Injury(TBI)</keyword>
  <keyword>Alcoholism</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Alcohol Drinking</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alcoholism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Valproic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
