<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="26774">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01955915</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB#00009475</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01955915</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Blood Vessel Patterns in Small Choroidal Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>Characterization of Small Choroidal Tumors Using Functional Optical Coherence Tomography</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oregon Health and Science University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oregon Health and Science University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Unites States: National Institutes of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to see if mapping blood vessel patterns with optical coherence
      tomography (OCT) will help identify life-threatening choroidal tumors in their early stages
      and improve overall patient survival through early detection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Uveal melanomas are melanocytic tumors that arise in the pigmented tissues of the eye: the
      iris, ciliary body, and choroid. Iris melanomas rarely metastasize (spread to other tissues
      or organs). In contrast, uveal melanomas arising in the ciliary body and choroid are highly
      malignant (cancerous and invasive to other tissues or organs). Despite having excellent
      local tumor control rates, uveal melanoma remains a life-threatening cancer, and even
      eye-sparing therapy with radiation treatment often leads to significant loss of vision.
      Therefore patients diagnosed with uveal melanoma must cope with not only a life-threatening
      illness, but also the frightening prospect of significant vision loss. Choroidal melanomas
      located in the posterior pole, an anatomical area of the eye which includes the optic nerve
      and macula (central retina), are of particular concern with regards to visual outcome, as
      radiation treatment to these areas for even the smallest of tumors is often associated with
      severe vision loss. The accurate diagnosis and treatment of small choroidal melanomas is
      critical to patient survival. When tumors with metastatic potential are recognized and
      treated at an early stage, survival prognosis improves dramatically.

      The purpose of this study is to learn if malignant (life-threatening) choroidal tumors
      versus benign (non-life-threatening) tumors will show distinct blood vessel patterns using
      functional optical coherence tomography (OCT) angiography. Angiography is the mapping of
      blood vessels. The investigators believe that OCT angiography can provide data which may
      help in identifying life-threatening tumors at the earliest stages and improve overall
      survival for patients with this type of melanoma.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood vessel patterns in small choroidal tumors</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine if identifying early changes in blood vessel patterns will aid in early diagnosis and treatment of potentially aggressive choroidal tumors. This will be assessed using functional OCT angiography technology.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Small Posterior Choroidal Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Choroidal Tumor Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>15 patients diagnosed with small posterior choroidal tumors will be considered and evaluated for enrollment into this study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        This study will measure blood vessel pattern/flow changes in 15 patients with small
        posterior choroidal tumors.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults older than age 18 with small (&lt; 3mm) choroidal tumors located within the
             posterior pole region which can be imaged using OCT technology. Subjects with
             benign-appearing and malignant-appearing lesions meeting these criteria will be
             enrolled.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to give informed consent.

          -  Inability to maintain stable fixation for OCT imaging.

          -  Significant renal disease, defined as a history of chronic renal failure requiring
             dialysis or kidney transplant.

          -  A condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, would preclude participation in
             the study (e.g., unstable medical status including blood pressure, cardiovascular
             disease, and glycemic control).

          -  Blood pressure &gt; 180/110 (systolic above 180 OR diastolic above 110). If blood
             pressure is brought below 180/110 by anti-hypertensive treatment, subject can become
             eligible.

          -  Women who are pregnant or lactating at the time of enrollment due to unknown safety
             of fluorescein angiography.  Women that become pregnant during the course of the
             study may remain enrolled; however, flurorescein and ICG angiography will not be
             performed until they are no longer pregnant or nursing an infant.

          -  Patients receiving treatment for uveal melanomas will be excluded from the
             longitudinal natural history portion of this study, but may enroll for a single study
             visit prior to treatment of their melanoma. They will then be eligible to enroll in
             IRB 9501, which will follow radiation-treated patients longitudinally.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alilson Skalet, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Oregon Health and Science University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Denny Romfh</last_name>
    <phone>503-494-4351</phone>
    <email>romfhd@ohsu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Janice Ladwig</last_name>
    <phone>503-494-8024</phone>
    <email>ladwig@ohsu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>OHSU</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Denny Romfh</last_name>
      <phone>503-494-4351</phone>
      <email>romfhd@ohsu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Janice Ladwig</last_name>
      <phone>503-494-8024</phone>
      <email>ladwig@ohsu.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Wilson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Huang, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Chiang, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 30, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Oregon Health and Science University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Huang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Alison Skalet, MD, PhD, Assistant Professor of Ophthalmology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>choroid</keyword>
  <keyword>tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>OCT</keyword>
  <keyword>malignant melanoma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Choroid Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
