<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="120876">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01722071</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UL1RR024986</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01722071</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Deciphering the Role of Oxytocin in Motivation: an fMRI Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Deciphering the Role of Oxytocin in Motivation: an fMRI Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tiffany Love</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study will investigate the effects of intranasal oxytocin administration on
      neural activity associated with social and non-social motivation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Oxytocin is a well-known social and reproductive hormone demonstrated to have a variety of
      prosocial effects in humans including enhancing trust and generosity, improving positive
      communication, increasing eye gaze, and reducing anxiety. Oxytocin is hypothesized to
      facilitate social behaviors via its modulation of motivational networks. With this study, we
      will characterize oxytocin's effects on the neural processing of salient stimuli. We will
      utilize a noninvasive brain imaging technique, functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI),
      to assess brain activity while participants perform tests designed to engage neural circuits
      associated with the processing of social and non-social stimuli.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI) Data: Change in BOLD activity between placebo and oxytocin treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Week 1, Day 1 (Scan 1) and Scan 2 (within the first 30 days after scan 1).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Drug effect will be assessed by ascertaining changes in brain activity between placebo and oxytocin sessions.
Imaging data will be analyzed from all subjects in a final analysis. Individual subject analyses will be done on a bimonthly basis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Salivary Oxytocin Levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Collected at Week 1, Day 1  (Scan 1) and Scan 2 (within the first 30 days after scan 1).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Saliva will be collected during each of the scanning sessions and analyzed for oxytocin levels.  Associations between oxytocin levels and BOLD activity will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavioral Data</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Week 1, Day 1 (Scan 1) and Scan 2 (within the first 30 days after scan 1).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Behavioral data (e.g. measures of mood, anxiety, social perception) will be collected during each of the study visits.  Drug effect will be determined by comparing data obtained during placebo and oxytocin visits.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemodynamic Response Function</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Week 1, Day 1 (Scan 1) and Scan 2 (within the first 30 days after scan 1).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Drug effect will be assessed by ascertaining changes in hemodynamic response functions (i.e. vascular responses to neural events) between placebo and oxytocin sessions.
Imaging data will be analyzed from all subjects in a final analysis. Individual subject analyses will be done on a bimonthly basis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trait Measures</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Trait (i.e. personality) measures will be analyzed to determine whether these traits play a mediating role in brain activity associated with the processing of motivational stimuli during placebo or oxytocin administration.
Final analyses will be performed following the final participant's last scanning session.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Focus of Study: Neural Correlates of Oxytocin Administration</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each participant will be studied using fMRI following self-administration of placebo.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oxytocin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each participant will be studied using fMRI following self-administration of oxytocin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo intranasal administration, 3 puffs per nostril delivered approximately 30 minutes prior to scanning session.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oxytocin</intervention_name>
    <description>Oxytocin intranasal administration, 24 IU, 3 puffs per nostril at 4 IU per puff delivered approximately 30 minutes prior to scanning session.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oxytocin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Syntocinon®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male

          -  20-35 years of age at the time of screening

          -  Right-handedness

          -  Non-smoking

          -  No current or past history of neurological or psychiatric illness, including
             substance abuse or dependence

          -  No acute medical illness

          -  Written informed consent obtained from subject

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Female

          -  Left-handedness or ambidextrous

          -  Presence of a condition or abnormality that in the opinion of the Investigator would
             compromise the safety of the patient or the quality of the data

          -  Known allergies to oxytocin or to preservatives in the nasal spray

          -  Participants who exhibit nasal obstruction or upper-respiratory tract infection at
             the time of scanning or report the use of intranasally administered medications for
             up to two weeks prior to screening

          -  Participants unable to tolerate the scanning procedures or would be unfit for
             scanning purposes (e.g. metal implants, claustrophobic, unable to lie still for the
             duration of the scan)

          -  Any current or past history of medical, neurological, or psychiatric illness or
             family history of psychiatric or neurologic disease in first-degree relatives

          -  Neurological illness, abnormal MRI (except if due to technical factors)

          -  Acute or uncorrected medical illnesses, including history of hepatic or renal
             dysfunction.

          -  Participants currently taking medications including any treatment, current or past
             with antipsychotics, mood stabilizers, isoniazid, glucocorticoids, psychostimulants
             and psychostimulant appetite suppressants, or centrally active antihypertensive drugs
             (e.g., clonidine, reserpine).

          -  Treatment within six months with any of the following: hormone use (testosterone,
             DHEA), antidepressants, opioid drugs.

          -  Treatment within one month with sedative hypnotic medications (benzodiazepines,
             barbiturates), or over the counter sleeping aids

          -  Current or past history of substance abuse or dependence

          -  Any reported lifetime use of any category of illicit drugs

          -  Positive urine drug screen
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tiffany M Love, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 4, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 29, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tiffany Love</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Research Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Oxytocin</keyword>
  <keyword>Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Social</keyword>
  <keyword>Motivation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Oxytocin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
