<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="168102">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01825499</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VON001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01825499</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Vermont Oxford Network Very Low Birth Weight Database</brief_title>
  <acronym>VON VLBW</acronym>
  <official_title>Vermont Oxford Network Very Low Birth Weight Database of Infants 401 to 1500 Grams or 22 to 29 Weeks Gestational Age at Birth</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Vermont Oxford Network</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Vermont Oxford Network</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Vermont Oxford Network maintains a database for live born infants 401 to 1500 grams or 22 to
      29 weeks gestational age who are born at participating hospitals or admitted to them within
      28 days of birth, regardless of where the infant receives care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Database collects observational baseline data on both mothers and infants, and the
      therapies used and outcomes of the infants. The information collected is not specific to a
      disease or treatment. The data collected includes information on:

        -  Demographics of mother and infant

        -  Mother's health, labor and delivery

        -  Infant's health upon admission, procedures and interventions, and medical outcomes

      These data are used to: provide member centers with reporting for use in quality
      improvement; examine associations between baseline characteristics, treatments, and
      outcomes; and track trends in incidences of disease and effectiveness of therapies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 1990</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2040</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2040</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <target_duration>1 Year</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Registry of baseline and outcome data for VLBW infants with data collected in a uniform manner</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Data items include infant and maternal characteristics, delivery room interventions, respiratory care and outcomes, surgeries, infections, comorbid conditions, and length of stay. Time frames for data collection include: characteristics of birth; at day 28; and at discharge. Tracking ends at discharge home (including for infants transferred out) or at one year.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <condition>Neonatology</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Very low birth weight infants</arm_group_label>
    <description>Infants 401 to 1500 g or 22 to 29 weeks gestational age admitted to Vermont Oxford Network member centers within 28 days of birth</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Registry</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Very low birth weight infants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Infants who are 401 to 1500 grams birth weight or 22 to 29 weeks gestational age and who
        are admitted to Vermont Oxford Network member centers within 28 days of birth without
        first going home
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Any infant who is born alive and whose birth weight is 401 to 1500 grams or 22 weeks
             0 days and 29 weeks 6 days gestational age (inclusive) who is born at or admitted to
             a Vermont Oxford Network member center within 28 days of life without having first
             gone home, regardless of the where the infant receives care

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Stillborn infants

          -  Infants discharged home prior to admission to a member center

          -  Infants admitted after 28 days
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>28 Days</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeffrey D Horbar, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Vermont Oxford Network</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lynn Stillman</last_name>
    <phone>802-865-4814</phone>
    <email>mail@vtoxford.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Beth Anderson</last_name>
    <phone>802-865-4814</phone>
    <email>mail@vtoxford.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vermont Oxford Network</name>
      <address>
        <city>Burlington</city>
        <state>Vermont</state>
        <zip>05401</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jeffrey D Horbar, MD</last_name>
      <phone>802-865-4814</phone>
      <email>mail@vtoxford.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.vtoxford.org</url>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.vtoxford.org/about/references.aspx</url>
    <description>Additional publications and posters</description>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Horbar JD, Carpenter JH, Badger GJ, Kenny MJ, Soll RF, Morrow KA, Buzas JS. Mortality and neonatal morbidity among infants 501 to 1500 grams from 2000 to 2009. Pediatrics. 2012 Jun;129(6):1019-26. doi: 10.1542/peds.2011-3028. Epub 2012 May 21.</citation>
    <PMID>22614775</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lake ET, Staiger D, Horbar J, Cheung R, Kenny MJ, Patrick T, Rogowski JA. Association between hospital recognition for nursing excellence and outcomes of very low-birth-weight infants. JAMA. 2012 Apr 25;307(16):1709-16. doi: 10.1001/jama.2012.504.</citation>
    <PMID>22535856</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Archer JM, Yeager SB, Kenny MJ, Soll RF, Horbar JD. Distribution of and mortality from serious congenital heart disease in very low birth weight infants. Pediatrics. 2011 Feb;127(2):293-9. doi: 10.1542/peds.2010-0418. Epub 2011 Jan 10.</citation>
    <PMID>21220403</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Horbar JD, Soll RF, Edwards WH. The Vermont Oxford Network: a community of practice. Clin Perinatol. 2010 Mar;37(1):29-47. doi: 10.1016/j.clp.2010.01.003.</citation>
    <PMID>20363446</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fitzgibbons SC, Ching Y, Yu D, Carpenter J, Kenny M, Weldon C, Lillehei C, Valim C, Horbar JD, Jaksic T. Mortality of necrotizing enterocolitis expressed by birth weight categories. J Pediatr Surg. 2009 Jun;44(6):1072-5; discussion 1075-6. doi: 10.1016/j.jpedsurg.2009.02.013.</citation>
    <PMID>19524719</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zupancic JA, Richardson DK, Horbar JD, Carpenter JH, Lee SK, Escobar GJ; Vermont Oxford Network SNAP Pilot Project Participants. Revalidation of the Score for Neonatal Acute Physiology in the Vermont Oxford Network. Pediatrics. 2007 Jan;119(1):e156-63. Epub 2006 Dec 11.</citation>
    <PMID>17158947</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Walsh MC, Yao Q, Horbar JD, Carpenter JH, Lee SK, Ohlsson A. Changes in the use of postnatal steroids for bronchopulmonary dysplasia in 3 large neonatal networks. Pediatrics. 2006 Nov;118(5):e1328-35.</citation>
    <PMID>17079534</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Morales LS, Staiger D, Horbar JD, Carpenter J, Kenny M, Geppert J, Rogowski J. Mortality among very low-birthweight infants in hospitals serving minority populations. Am J Public Health. 2005 Dec;95(12):2206-12.</citation>
    <PMID>16304133</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rogowski JA, Staiger DO, Horbar JD. Variations in the quality of care for very-low-birthweight infants: implications for policy. Health Aff (Millwood). 2004 Sep-Oct;23(5):88-97.</citation>
    <PMID>15371373</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Payne NR, Carpenter JH, Badger GJ, Horbar JD, Rogowski J. Marginal increase in cost and excess length of stay associated with nosocomial bloodstream infections in surviving very low birth weight infants. Pediatrics. 2004 Aug;114(2):348-55.</citation>
    <PMID>15286215</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Suresh G, Horbar JD, Plsek P, Gray J, Edwards WH, Shiono PH, Ursprung R, Nickerson J, Lucey JF, Goldmann D. Voluntary anonymous reporting of medical errors for neonatal intensive care. Pediatrics. 2004 Jun;113(6):1609-18.</citation>
    <PMID>15173481</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Horbar JD, Carpenter JH, Buzas J, Soll RF, Suresh G, Bracken MB, Leviton LC, Plsek PE, Sinclair JC; Vermont Oxford Network. Timing of initial surfactant treatment for infants 23 to 29 weeks' gestation: is routine practice evidence based? Pediatrics. 2004 Jun;113(6):1593-602.</citation>
    <PMID>15173479</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lucey JF, Rowan CA, Shiono P, Wilkinson AR, Kilpatrick S, Payne NR, Horbar J, Carpenter J, Rogowski J, Soll RF. Fetal infants: the fate of 4172 infants with birth weights of 401 to 500 grams--the Vermont Oxford Network experience (1996-2000). Pediatrics. 2004 Jun;113(6):1559-66.</citation>
    <PMID>15173474</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rogowski JA, Horbar JD, Staiger DO, Kenny M, Carpenter J, Geppert J. Indirect vs direct hospital quality indicators for very low-birth-weight infants. JAMA. 2004 Jan 14;291(2):202-9.</citation>
    <PMID>14722146</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Horbar JD, Badger GJ, Carpenter JH, Fanaroff AA, Kilpatrick S, LaCorte M, Phibbs R, Soll RF; Members of the Vermont Oxford Network. Trends in mortality and morbidity for very low birth weight infants, 1991-1999. Pediatrics. 2002 Jul;110(1 Pt 1):143-51.</citation>
    <PMID>12093960</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Suresh GK, Horbar JD, Kenny M, Carpenter JH; Vermont Oxford Network. Major birth defects in very low birth weight infants in the Vermont Oxford Network. J Pediatr. 2001 Sep;139(3):366-73.</citation>
    <PMID>11562615</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bernstein IM, Horbar JD, Badger GJ, Ohlsson A, Golan A. Morbidity and mortality among very-low-birth-weight neonates with intrauterine growth restriction. The Vermont Oxford Network. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2000 Jan;182(1 Pt 1):198-206.</citation>
    <PMID>10649179</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Finer NN, Horbar JD, Carpenter JH. Cardiopulmonary resuscitation in the very low birth weight infant: the Vermont Oxford Network experience. Pediatrics. 1999 Sep;104(3 Pt 1):428-34.</citation>
    <PMID>10469765</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Horbar JD. The Vermont Oxford Network: evidence-based quality improvement for neonatology. Pediatrics. 1999 Jan;103(1 Suppl E):350-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9917477</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Horbar JD, Badger GJ, Lewit EM, Rogowski J, Shiono PH. Hospital and patient characteristics associated with variation in 28-day mortality rates for very low birth weight infants. Vermont Oxford Network. Pediatrics. 1997 Feb;99(2):149-56.</citation>
    <PMID>9024438</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Horbar JD. Increasing use of antenatal corticosteroid therapy between 1990 and 1993 in Vermont Oxford Network. J Perinatol. 1997 Jul-Aug;17(4):309-13.</citation>
    <PMID>9280098</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>De Nisi G, Berti M, Malossi R, Pederzini F, Pedrotti A, Valente A. Comparison of neonatal intensive care: Trento area versus Vermont Oxford Network. Ital J Pediatr. 2009 Mar 14;35(1):5. doi: 10.1186/1824-7288-35-5.</citation>
    <PMID>19490662</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Boghossian NS, Horbar JD, Murray JC, Carpenter JH; Vermont Oxford Network. Anthropometric charts for infants with trisomies 21, 18, or 13 born between 22 weeks gestation and term: the VON charts. Am J Med Genet A. 2012 Feb;158A(2):322-32. doi: 10.1002/ajmg.a.34423. Epub 2012 Jan 13.</citation>
    <PMID>22246859</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Boghossian NS, Horbar JD, Carpenter JH, Murray JC, Bell EF; Vermont Oxford Network. Major chromosomal anomalies among very low birth weight infants in the Vermont Oxford Network. J Pediatr. 2012 May;160(5):774-780.e11. doi: 10.1016/j.jpeds.2011.11.005. Epub 2011 Dec 16.</citation>
    <PMID>22177989</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 4, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 27, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Birth weight</keyword>
  <keyword>Gestational age</keyword>
  <keyword>Very low birth weight</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Birth Weight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
