<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="151416">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01971489</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>I 240413</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-01941</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>I 240413</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016056</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01971489</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PI3K Inhibitor BKM120, Gemcitabine Hydrochloride, and Cisplatin in Treating Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of the PI3-Kinase Inhibitor BKM120 in Combination With Gemcitabine and Cisplatin in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I clinical trial studies the side effects and the best dose of phosphoinositide
      3-kinase (PI3K) inhibitor BKM120, gemcitabine hydrochloride, and cisplatin when given
      together in treating patients with advanced solid tumors. PI3K inhibitor BKM120 may stop the
      growth of tumor cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell growth. Drugs used in
      chemotherapy, such as gemcitabine hydrochloride and cisplatin, work in different ways to
      stop the growth of tumor cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from
      dividing. Giving PI3K inhibitor BKM120 with gemcitabine hydrochloride and cisplatin may be
      an effective treatment for advanced solid tumors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To describe the dose-limiting toxicities and identify the recommended Phase II dose
      (RP2D) of the combination of BKM120 (PI3K inhibitor BKM120, gemcitabine (gemcitabine
      hydrochloride), and cisplatin in patients with advanced solid tumors.

      II. To describe safety and tolerability of the combination of BKM120, gemcitabine, and
      cisplatin in patients with advanced solid tumors.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To describe preliminary evidence of efficacy with this combination. II. To describe any
      pharmacokinetic (PK) effect of gemcitabine and cisplatin on the plasma concentrations of
      BKM120.

      III. To evaluate phosphatidylinositol-4, 5-bisphosphate 3-kinase, catalytic subunit alpha
      (PIK3CA) mutations as predictive biomarkers of efficacy for the combination.

      IV. To evaluate PIK3CA polymorphisms and polymorphisms in BKM120 transport and metabolism as
      predictors of toxicity and/or efficacy.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study.

      Patients receive PI3K inhibitor BKM120 orally (PO) once daily (QD) on days 1-21, gemcitabine
      hydrochloride intravenously (IV) over 30 minutes on days 1 and 8 and cisplatin IV over 2
      hours on day 1. Courses repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for 30 days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events using the National Cancer Institute (NCI) CTCAE version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after completion of study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Severity of adverse events will be summarized by system organ class and preferred term.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum-tolerated dose (MTD) of PI3K inhibitor BKM120 based on dose-limiting toxicity (DLT) using NCI CTCAE version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 21 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>This study will utilize a Bayesian interpretation of the probability of DLT at the MTD</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (ORR) (complete response [CR], partial response [PR]) using Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after completion of study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Tumor response will be summarized for the evaluable patient population, and the 95% confidence interval for ORR (CR+PR) will be presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>RECIST response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after completion of study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The number and percent of patients qualifying for each RECIST response category (CR, PR, stable disease [SD], and progressive disease [PD]).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease control rate using RECIST (CR, PR, and SD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after completion of study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic (PK) parameters of PI3K inhibitor BKM120</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose and at 0.5, 1, 2, and 4 hours post-dose on day 21 of course 1 and pre-dose and 0.5, 1, 2, and 4 hours post-dose on day 1 of course 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PK parameters include time to reach maximum concentration (Tmax), maximum concentration (Cmax), clearance (CL), half-life (T1/2), area under the curve (AUC)0-infinity, and AUC0-t for the dosing interval following multiple dose administration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">38</enrollment>
  <condition>Unspecified Adult Solid Tumor, Protocol Specific</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (BKM120, gemcitabine hydrochloride, cisplatin)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive PI3K inhibitor BKM120 PO QD on days 1-21, gemcitabine hydrochloride IV over 30 minutes on days 1 and 8 and cisplatin IV over 2 hours on day 1. Courses repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PI3K inhibitor BKM120</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (BKM120, gemcitabine hydrochloride, cisplatin)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BKM120</other_name>
    <other_name>PI3K_Inhibitor_BKM120</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>gemcitabine hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (BKM120, gemcitabine hydrochloride, cisplatin)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>dFdC</other_name>
    <other_name>difluorodeoxycytidine hydrochloride</other_name>
    <other_name>gemcitabine</other_name>
    <other_name>Gemzar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cisplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (BKM120, gemcitabine hydrochloride, cisplatin)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CACP</other_name>
    <other_name>CDDP</other_name>
    <other_name>CPDD</other_name>
    <other_name>DDP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (BKM120, gemcitabine hydrochloride, cisplatin)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pharmacological studies</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (BKM120, gemcitabine hydrochloride, cisplatin)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of solid malignancy

          -  Have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of =&lt; 1

          -  Life expectancy of &gt;= 12 weeks

          -  Platelet count &gt;= 150 x 10^9/L

          -  Absolute neutrophile count (ANC) &gt;= 1.5 x 10^9/L

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 9 g/dL

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) =&lt;1.5 upper limit
             normal (ULN), or &lt; 3 x ULN if liver metastases are present

          -  Serum total bilirubin =&lt; ULN or 1.5 x ULN if liver metastases are present or total 3
             x ULN with direct bilirubin =&lt; ULN in patients with well documented Gilbert syndrome

          -  Serum creatinine =&lt; 1.5 x ULN or calculated or measured creatinine clearance &gt;= 50
             mL/min

          -  Fasting plasma glucose &lt; 120 mg/dL

          -  Magnesium &gt;= the lower limit of normal

          -  Lipase =&lt; 1.5 ULN

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test performed within
             7 days prior to the start of study drug

          -  Male and female subjects of child-bearing potential must agree to use double-barrier
             contraceptive measures, oral contraception, or avoidance of intercourse during the
             study and for 90 days after last investigational drug dose received

          -  Subject or legal representative must understand the investigational nature of this
             study and sign an Independent Ethics Committee/Institutional Review Board approved
             written informed consent form prior to receiving any study related procedure

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous anti-cancer chemotherapy, immunotherapy or investigational agents &lt; 4 weeks,
             or palliative radiation &lt; 2 weeks prior to the first day of study treatment; patients
             who receive gamma knife radiosurgery for brain metastases are eligible if procedure
             was performed &gt; 2 weeks before treatment is started, is clinically stable and has
             been on stable low dose corticosteroid treatment (e.g., dexamethasone 2 mg/day,
             prednisolone 12 mg/day for at least 14 days before start of study treatment are
             eligible); ongoing hormonal therapies (luteinizing hormone-releasing hormone [LHRH]
             antagonists, megestrol) are allowed

          -  Major surgery &lt; 4 weeks or minor surgery &lt; 2 weeks prior to the first day of study
             treatment

          -  Previous treatment with a phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase (P1-3K) inhibitor

          -  Patients who have any of the following mood disorders as judged by the investigator
             or a psychiatrist or psychologist, or who meets the cut-off score of &gt;= 12 the
             Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9) or a cut-off of &gt;= 15 in the General Anxiety
             Disorder-7 (GAD-7) mood scale, respectively, or selects a positive response of '1, 2,
             or 3' to questions number 9 regarding potential for suicidal thoughts in the PHQ-9
             (independent of the total score of the PHQ-9)

               -  Medically documented history of or active major depressive episode, bipolar
                  disorder (I or II), obsessive compulsive disorder, schizophrenia, a history of
                  suicidal attempt or ideation, or homicidal ideation (immediate risk of doing
                  harm to others)

               -  &gt;= Common Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) grade 3 anxiety

          -  Active cardiac disease described as:

               -  Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &lt; 50% by multiple gated acquisition
                  (MUGA) scan or echocardiogram (ECHO)

               -  Corrected QT interval (QTc) &gt; 480 msec on screening electrocardiogram (EKG)
                  (using the Fridericia corrected QT interval [QTcF] formula)

               -  Congenital long QT syndrome

               -  Myocardial infarction or active uncontrolled angina pectoris within the last 6
                  months prior to the first day of study treatment

               -  Uncontrolled significant cardiac arrhythmias except for benign premature
                  ventricular contractions (PVC) and premature atrial contractions (PAC)

               -  Symptomatic pericarditis

               -  History of cardiomyopathy

          -  Active clinically serious infections or other serious uncontrolled medical conditions

          -  Substance abuses, medical, psychological or social conditions that may, in the
             opinion of the investigator, interfere with the patient's participation in the study
             or evaluation of the study results

          -  Patients with poorly controlled diabetes mellitus, steroid-induced diabetes mellitus;
             diabetic patients with glycated hemoglobin (HbA1C) &gt; 7% will be excluded

          -  Patients receiving chronic systemic treatment with steroids or another systemic
             immunosuppressive agent, except for patients previously treated brain metastases as
             described previously are eligible

          -  Impairment of gastrointestinal (GI) function or GI disease that may significantly
             alter the absorption of BKM120 or inability to swallow oral medications

          -  Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection

          -  Patients who are currently treated with drugs known to be moderate and strong
             inhibitors or inducers of isoenzyme cytochrome P450 family 3, subfamily A,
             polypeptide 4 (CYP3A), and the treatment cannot be discontinued or switched to a
             different medication prior to starting study drug; (please note that co-treatment
             with weak inhibitors of CYP3A is allowed)

          -  Patients who have taken herbal medications and certain fruits within 7 days prior to
             starting study drug; herbal medications include, but are not limited to St. John's
             wort, Kava, ephedra (ma huang), gingko biloba, dehydroepiandrosterone (DHEA),
             yohimbe, saw palmetto, and ginseng; fruits include the CYP3A inhibitors Seville
             oranges, grapefruit, pummelos, or exotic citrus fruits

          -  Patients who are currently taking therapeutic doses of warfarin sodium or any other
             Coumadin-derivative anticoagulant (use of low molecular weight heparin is allowed)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alex Adjei</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14263</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Roswell Park</last_name>
      <phone>877-275-7724</phone>
      <email>ASKRPCI@roswellpark.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alex A. Adjei</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 23, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Gemcitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
