<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="67327">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02154139</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>265-201</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02154139</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Leuprorelin Acetate SR 11.25 mg for Injection Specified Drug-use Survey &quot;Long-term Use Survey on Premenopausal Breast Cancer Patients (96 Weeks)&quot;</brief_title>
  <official_title>Leuplin SR 11.25 mg for Injection Specified Drug-use Survey &quot;Long-term Use Survey on Premenopausal Breast Cancer Patients (96 Weeks)&quot;</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Takeda</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Japan: Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this survey is to examine the safety and efficacy of long-term use (96 weeks)
      of leuprorelin acetate SR (slow release) 11.25 mg for injection (Leuplin SR 11.25 mg for
      Injection) in premenopausal breast cancer patients in daily medical practice, as well as to
      examine factors that can influence the safety and efficacy of treatment with leuprorelin
      acetate SR 11.25 mg for injection (Leuplin SR 11.25 mg for Injection).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This survey was designed to examine the safety and efficacy of long-term use (96 weeks) of
      leuprorelin acetate 3 months depot for injection (Leuplin SR 11.25 mg for Injection) in
      premenopausal breast cancer patients in daily medical practice, as well as to examine
      factors that can influence the safety and efficacy of treatment with leuprorelin acetate SR
      11.25 mg for injection (Leuplin SR 11.25 mg for Injection).

      For adults, 11.25 mg of leuprorelin acetate is usually administered subcutaneously once
      every 12 weeks. Prior to injection, the plunger rod of the syringe is pushed upward with the
      needle pointed upward, allowing the entire suspension fluid contained to be transferred to
      the powder. The powder is then fully suspended in the fluid while ensuring that bubbles are
      not generated.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of adverse drug reactions</measure>
    <time_frame>For 96 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The frequencies of all adverse events observed during the observation period will be tabulated by type and seriousness. Adverse events are defined as any unfavorable and unintended signs, symptoms or diseases temporally associated with administration of leuprorelin acetate whether or not it was considered related to treatment. Among these, events that are considered as having a causal relationship with leuprorelin acetate are defined as adverse drug reactions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Antitumor efficacy over the 96-week period of treatment with leuprorelin acetate SR 11.25 mg for injection (Leuplin SR 11.25 mg for Injection) in patients with advanced or recurrent breast cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 96 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>For patients with advanced or recurrent breast cancer, the antitumor efficacy (best response) of leuprorelin acetate SR 11.25 mg for injection (Leuplin SR 11.25 mg for Injection) will be evaluated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recurrence-free survival over the 96-week period of treatment with leuprorelin acetate SR 11.25 mg for injection (Leuplin SR 11.25 mg for Injection) in patients who were treated asadjuvant therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 96 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>For patients who were treated as adjuvant therapy, recurrence-free survival will be determined and tabulated, based on the date recurrence is confirmed, the presence or absence of recurrence, continued survival or death, and the date of death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">651</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>leuprorelin acetate</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subcutaneous administration of leuprorelin acetate once every 12 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Leuprorelin acetate</intervention_name>
    <description>Leuprorelin acetate SR 11.25 mg for injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>leuprorelin acetate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Leuplin SR 11.25 mg for Injection</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Breast cancer
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Premenopausal breast cancer patients (patients with advanced or recurrent breast
             cancer and patients who received adjuvant therapy).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a history of treatment with Leuplin SR 11.25 mg for Injection
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Postmarketing Group Manager</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Takeda</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 23, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pharmacological therapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Leuprolide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
