<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="10118">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02153905</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>140110</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>14-C-0110</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02153905</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Metastatic Cancer That Expresses MAGE-A3 Using Lymphodepleting Conditioning Followed by Infusion of Anti-MAGE-A3 HLA-A*01-restricted TCR-Gene Engineered Lymphocytes and Aldesleukin</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I-II Study of the Treatment of Metastatic Cancer That Expresses MAGE-A3 Using Lymphodepleting Conditioning Followed by Infusion of Anti-MAGE-A3 HLA-A*01 Restricted TCR-Gene Engineered Lymphocytes and Aldesleukin</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      The NCI Surgery Branch has developed an experimental therapy for treating patients with
      cancer that involves taking white blood cells from the patient, growing them in the
      laboratory in large numbers, genetically modifying these specific cells with a type of virus
      (retrovirus) to attack only the tumor cells, and then giving the cells back to the patient.
      This type of therapy is called gene transfer.   In this protocol, we are modifying the
      patient   s white blood cells with a retrovirus that has the gene for anti-MAGE-A3
      incorporated in the retrovirus.

      Objective:

      The purpose of this study is to see if these particular tumor-fighting cells (anti-MAGE A3
      cells) cause tumors to shrink and to be certain the treatment is safe

      Eligibility:

      - Adults age 18   66 with cancer containing the MAGE-A3 molecule.

      Design:

      Work up stage: Patients will be seen as an outpatient at the NIH clinical Center and undergo
      a history and physical examination, scans, x-rays, lab tests, and other tests as needed

      Leukapheresis: If the patients meet all of the requirements for the study they will undergo
      leukapheresis to obtain white blood cells to make the anti ESO-1 cells.  {Leukapheresis is a
      common procedure, which removes only the white blood cells from the patient.}

      Treatment: Once their cells have grown, the patients will be admitted to the hospital for
      the conditioning chemotherapy, the anti-ESO 1 cells and aldesleukin.  They will stay in the
      hospital for about 1-2 weeks to recover from the treatment.

      Patients will return to the clinic for a physical exam, review of side effects, lab tests,
      and scans about every 1-3 months for the first year, and then every 6 months to 1 year as
      long as their tumors are shrinking.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  We have constructed a single retroviral vector that contains both alpha and beta chains
           of a T cell receptor (TCR) that recognizes the HLA-A 01 restricted MAGE-A3 tumor
           antigen, which can be used to mediate genetic transfer of this TCR with high
           efficiency.

        -  In co-cultures with HLA-A 01 and MAGE-A3 double positive tumors, the anti-MAGE-A3- A 01
           restricted (anti-MAGE-A3-01) TCR transduced T cells secreted significant amounts of
           IFN- &gt;= with high specificity.

      Objectives:

      Primary objectives:

        -  Determine a safe dose of administration of autologous T cells transduced with an anti-
           MAGE-A3 HLA-A 01-restricted TCR (MAGE-A3-01) TCR and aldesleukin to patients following
           a nonmyeloablative but lymphoid depleting preparative regimen.

        -  Determine if this approach will result in objective tumor regression in patients with
           metastatic cancer expressing MAGE-A3.

        -  Determine the toxicity profile of this treatment regimen.

      Secondary Objective:

      - Determine the in vivo survival of TCR gene-engineered cells.

      Eligibility:

      Patients who are HLA-A 01 positive and 18 years of age or older must have:

        -  Metastatic cancer whose tumors express the MAGE-A3 antigen;

        -  Previously received and have been a non-responder to or recurred following at least one
           first line treatment for metastatic disease;

      Patients may not have:

      - Contraindications for high dose aldesleukin administration.

      Design:

        -  PBMC obtained by leukapheresis will be transduced with the retroviral vector
           supernatant encoding the anti-MAGE-A3 HLA-A 01-restricted TCR.

        -  The study will begin with a phase I dose escalation. After the MTD cell dose has been
           determined, patients will be enrolled into the phase 2 portion of the trial at the MTD
           established during the phase I portion of the study. In the phase 2 portion, patients
           will be entered into two cohorts: cohort 1 will include patients with metastatic
           melanoma; cohort 2 will include patients with renal cancer and other types of
           metastatic cancer.

        -  Patients will receive a nonmyeloablative but lymphocyte depleting preparative regimen
           consisting of cyclophosphamide and fludarabine followed by intravenous infusion of ex
           vivo tumor reactive, TCR gene-transduced PBMC plus IV aldesleukin.

        -  Patients will undergo complete evaluation of tumor response every 1-6 months until off
           study criteria are met.

        -  For each of the 2 strata evaluated in the phase 2 portion, the study will be conducted
           using a phase II optimal design where initially 21 evaluable patients will be enrolled.
           For each of these two arms of the trial, if 0 or 1 of the 21 patients experiences a
           clinical response, then no further patients will be enrolled but if 2 or more of the
           first 21 evaluable patients enrolled have a clinical response, then accrual will
           continue until a total of 41 evaluable patients have been enrolled in that stratum.

        -  For both strata, the objective will be to determine if the treatment regimen is able to
           be associated with a clinical response rate that can rule out 5% (p0=0.05) in favor of
           a modes 20% PR + CR rate (p1=0.20).

        -  In order to complete the dose escalation phase and both phase 2 cohorts, a total of up
           to 20+82=102 patients may be required (20 + 2 strata with a maximum of 41 apiece). Up
           to 6 patients enrolled at the MTD will count towards the accrual in the appropriate
           phase 2 strata if they are evaluable for response and if they would be fully eligible
           for enrollment in the phase 2 portion of the trial. Provided that about 4-5 patients
           per month will be able to be enrolled onto this trial, approximately 2 to 3 years may
           be needed to accrue the maximum number of required patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine safety and objective response rate of administration of autologous T cells transduced with an anti- MAGE-A3 HLA-A*01-restricted TCR (MAGE-A3-01) TCR and aldesleukin</measure>
    <time_frame>approximately three years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">102</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Melanoma</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aldesleukin</intervention_name>
    <description>Administered at a dose of 720,000 IU/kg (based on total body weight) as an intravenous bolus over a 15 minute period approximately every eight hours (+/- 1hr) beginning within 24 hours of cell infusion and continuing for up to 5 days (maximum 15 doses).</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Fludarabine 25 mg/m2/day IVPB daily over 30 minutes for 5 days.</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide</intervention_name>
    <description>Cyclophosphamide 60 mg/kg/day X 2 days IV in 250 ml D5W with Mesna 15 mg/kg/day X 2 days over 1 hr.</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anti-MAGE-A3 HLAA* 01-restricted TCR</intervention_name>
    <description>Cells will be infused intravenously (i.v.) on the Patient Care Unit over 20 to 30 minutes via non-filtered tubing, gently agitating the bag during infusion to prevent cell clumping.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. Metastatic cancer that expresses MAGE-A3 as assessed by one of the following
                  methods: RT-PCR on tumor tissue defined as 30,000 copies of MAGE-A3 per 106
                  GAPDH copies, or by immunohistochemistry of resected tissue defined as 10% or
                  greater of tumor cells being 2-3+ for MAGE-A3, or serum antibody reactive with
                  MAGE-A3. Metastatic cancer diagnosis will be confirmed by the Laboratory of
                  Pathology at the NCI.

               2. Patients must have previously received at least one systemic standard care (or
                  effective salvage chemotherapy regimens) for metastatic disease, if known to be
                  effective for that disease, and have been either non-responders (progressive
                  disease) or have recurred.

               3. Patients must be HLA-A*01 positive.

               4. Greater than or equal to 18 years of age and less than or equal to age 66.

               5. Able to understand and sign the Informed Consent Document

               6. Willing to sign a durable power of attorney

               7. Clinical performance status of ECOG 0 or 1

               8. Life expectancy of greater than three months

               9. Patients of both genders must be willing to practice birth control from the time
                  of enrollment on this study and for up to four months after the cells are no
                  longer detected in the blood.

              10. Serology:

                    -  Seronegative for HIV antibody. (The experimental treatment being evaluated
                       in this protocol depends on an intact immune system. Patients who are HIV
                       seropositive can have decreased immune-competence and thus be less
                       responsive to the experimental treatment and more susceptible to its
                       toxicities.)

                    -  Seronegative for hepatitis B antigen, and seronegative for hepatitis C
                       antibody. If hepatitis C antibody test is positive, then patient must be
                       tested for the presence of antigen by RT-PCR and be HCV RNA negative.

              11. Women of child-bearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test because of
                  the potentially dangerous effects of the treatment on the fetus.

              12. Hematology

                    -  Absolute neutrophil count greater than 1000/mm3 without the support of
                       filgrastim

                    -  WBC greater than or equal to 3000/mm3

                    -  Platelet count greater than or equal to 100,000/mm3

                    -  Hemoglobin &gt;  8.0 g/dl

              13. Chemistry:

                    -  Serum ALT/AST less than or equal to to 2.5 times the upper limit of normal

                    -  Serum creatinine less than or equal to to 1.6 mg/dl

                    -  Total bilirubin less than or equal to to 1.5 mg/dl, except in patients with
                       Gilbert   s Syndrome who must have a total bilirubin less than 3.0 mg/dl.

              14. More than four weeks must have elapsed since any prior systemic therapy at the
                  time the patient receives the preparative regimen, and patients    toxicities
                  must have recovered to a grade 1 or less (except for toxicities such as alopecia
                  or vitiligo). Patients must have progressing disease after prior treatment.

              15. Six weeks must have elapsed from the time of any antibody therapy that could
                  affect an anti cancer immune response, including anti-CTLA4 antibody therapy, at
                  the time the patient receives the preparative regimen to allow antibody levels
                  to decline.

        Note: Patients who have previously received ipilimumab and have documented GI toxicity
        must have a normal colonoscopy with normal colonic biopsies.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Women of child-bearing potential who are pregnant or breastfeeding because of the
             potentially dangerous effects of the treatment on the fetus or infant.

          2. Active systemic infections, coagulation disorders or other active major medical
             illnesses of the cardiovascular, respiratory or immune system, as evidenced by a
             positive stress thallium or comparable test, myocardial infarction, cardiac
             arrhythmias, obstructive or restrictive pulmonary disease.

          3. Any form of primary immunodeficiency (such as Severe Combined Immunodeficiency
             Disease).

          4. Concurrent opportunistic infections (The experimental treatment being evaluated in
             this protocol depends on an intact immune system. Patients who have decreased immune
             competence may be less responsive to the experimental treatment and more susceptible
             to its toxicities).

          5. Concurrent systemic steroid therapy.

          6. History of severe immediate hypersensitivity reaction to any of the agents used in
             this study.

          7. History of any cardiac events including coronary revascularization or ischemic
             symptoms.

          8. Documented LVEF of less than or equal to 45%; testing is required in patients who
             are:

             -- Age greater than or equal to 60 years old

          9. Documented FEV1 less than or equal to 60% predicted tested in patients with:

               -  A prolonged history of cigarette smoking (20 pk/year if smoking within the past
                  2 years)

               -  Symptoms of respiratory dysfunction

         10. Patients with CNS metastases or symptomatic CNS involvement (including cranial
             neuropathies or mass lesions).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>66 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven A Rosenberg, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>June Kryk, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-1929</phone>
    <email>ncisbirc@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Steven A Rosenberg, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-4164</phone>
    <email>sar@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact NCI/Surgery Branch Recruitment Center</last_name>
      <phone>866-820-4505</phone>
      <email>ncisbirc@mail.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2014-C-0110.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morgan RA, Dudley ME, Yu YY, Zheng Z, Robbins PF, Theoret MR, Wunderlich JR, Hughes MS, Restifo NP, Rosenberg SA. High efficiency TCR gene transfer into primary human lymphocytes affords avid recognition of melanoma tumor antigen glycoprotein 100 and does not alter the recognition of autologous melanoma antigens. J Immunol. 2003 Sep 15;171(6):3287-95.</citation>
    <PMID>12960359</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johnson LA, Morgan RA, Dudley ME, Cassard L, Yang JC, Hughes MS, Kammula US, Royal RE, Sherry RM, Wunderlich JR, Lee CC, Restifo NP, Schwarz SL, Cogdill AP, Bishop RJ, Kim H, Brewer CC, Rudy SF, VanWaes C, Davis JL, Mathur A, Ripley RT, Nathan DA, Laurencot CM, Rosenberg SA. Gene therapy with human and mouse T-cell receptors mediates cancer regression and targets normal tissues expressing cognate antigen. Blood. 2009 Jul 16;114(3):535-46. doi: 10.1182/blood-2009-03-211714. Epub 2009 May 18.</citation>
    <PMID>19451549</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Robbins PF, Morgan RA, Feldman SA, Yang JC, Sherry RM, Dudley ME, Wunderlich JR, Nahvi AV, Helman LJ, Mackall CL, Kammula US, Hughes MS, Restifo NP, Raffeld M, Lee CC, Levy CL, Li YF, El-Gamil M, Schwarz SL, Laurencot C, Rosenberg SA. Tumor regression in patients with metastatic synovial cell sarcoma and melanoma using genetically engineered lymphocytes reactive with NY-ESO-1. J Clin Oncol. 2011 Mar 1;29(7):917-24. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2010.32.2537. Epub 2011 Jan 31. PubMed PMID: 21282551; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3068063.</citation>
    <PMID>21282551</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 31, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 31, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Metastatic Melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Renal Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Adoptive Cell Therapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Second Primary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine monophosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aldesleukin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
