<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="52155">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02146430</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DS5565-A-E309</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02146430</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Pain Associated With Fibromyalgia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo- and Active-Controlled Study of DS-5565 for Treatment of Pain Associated With Fibromyalgia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Daiichi Sankyo Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>INC Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Daiichi Sankyo Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      DS 5565 will be better than placebo (sugar pill without active drug) in managing
      fibromyalgia pain and will be well tolerated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change in weekly average daily pain score (ADPS), DS-5565 versus placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (week 0) to week 13</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary objective is to compare change in weekly average daily pain score (ADPS) from baseline to Week 13 in subjects receiving either dose of DS-5565 versus placebo.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in ADPS from baseline to Week 13, DS-5565 versus pregabalin</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (week 0) to Week 13</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To compare change in ADPS from baseline to Week 13 in subjects receiving either dose of DS-5565 versus pregabalin</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>proportion of responders at week 13, DS-5565 versus placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (week 0) to Week 13.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To compare the proportion of subjects receiving either dose of DS-5565 versus placebo who meet fixed definitions of response (i.e. ≥ 30% or ≥ 50% reduction from baseline to Week 13 in ADPS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in patient global impression measure, DS-5565 versus placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (week 0) to Week 13.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess the effects of either dose of DS-5565 versus placebo on patient global impression of change (PGIC).
This standard instrument is a well-validated outcome measure for pain treatment and shows close correlation with the 11-point pain intensity NRS in the setting of chronic pain. The 7-point PGIC measures change in the subject's overall status using the following categorical scale: 1) very much improved, 2) much improved, 3) minimally improved, 4) no change, 5) minimally worse, 6) much worse, and 7) very much worse.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in FIQ measure, DS-5565 versus placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (week 0) to Week 13</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the effects of either dose of DS-5565 versus placebo on the fibromyalgia (FM) Impact Questionnaire (FIQ).
The FIQ is composed of 10 items. The first item contains 11 questions related to physical functioning - each question is rated on a 4-point Likert-type scale. Items 2 and ask the patient to mark the number of days that they feel well and the number of days they were unable to work (including housework) because of FM symptoms. Items 4 through 10 are horizontal linear scales marked in 10 increments on which the patient rates work difficulty, pain, fatigue, morning tiredness, stiffness, anxiety, and depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in MFI-20 measure, DS-5565 versus placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (week 0) to Week 13</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the effects of either dose of DS-5565 versus placebo on fatigue as assessed by the Multidimensional Fatigue Inventory (MFI-20).
The Multidimensional Fatigue Inventory (MFI) is a validated 20-item, self-report instrument designed to measure fatigue. It covers the following dimensions: general fatigue, physical fatigue, mental fatigue, reduced motivation, and reduced activity. The respondent is asked to mark an X in 1 of 5 boxes arranged linearly and anchored by &quot;yes, that is true&quot; at one pole to &quot;no, that is not true&quot; at the opposite pole. The MFI-20 is a brief measure of fatigue that appears to capture relevant dimensions of fatigue severity and offers great clarification of the type of fatigue being experienced and good assessment and precision. It has been used successfully in clinical trials of FM and appears to be a good marker of illness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in HADS measure, DS-5565 versus placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (week 0) to Week 13</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the effects of either dose of DS-5565 versus placebo on depression and anxiety as assessed by the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS).
The HADS questionnaire is a reliable, widely-used self -assessment scale to assess symptoms of anxiety and depression. The instrument consists of 7 questions related to anxiety and 7 related to depression, each rated on a 4-point scale (score of 0 to 3).  Scores for anxiety and depression are independently summed to compute HADS-Anxiety and HADS-Depression subscale scores, with ranges from 0 to 21, where higher scores indicate greater severity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in SF-36 measure, DS-5565 versus placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (week 0) to Week 13</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess the effects of either dose of DS-5565 versus placebo on subject general health status as assessed by the Short Form 36 (SF-36) questionnaire.
The SF-36 is a generic health survey that asks 36 questions to measure functional health and well-being from the patient's point of view. It is a practical, reliable, and valid measure of physical and mental health widely used across various disease areas, including FM. The SF-36 provides scores for 8 health domains (physical functioning, role-physical, bodily pain, general health, vitality, social functioning, role-emotional, and mental health) as well as psychometrically-based physical component summary (PCS) and mental component summary (MCS) scores.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in EQ-5D measure, DS-5565 versus placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (week 0) to Week 13</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess the effects of either dose of DS-5565 versus placebo on subject quality of life as assessed by the EuroQoL Instrument 5 Domains (EQ-5D).
The EQ-5D is a well-standardized instrument that shows high construct validity and responsiveness in patients with chronic pain and has been used specifically in FM. The EQ-5D includes a descriptive section with 5 dimensions (mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, and anxiety/depression) that are combined into an overall health utilities index, and an NRS (100 mm VAS) that measures perception of overall health, with zero indicating worst health and 100 representing best imaginable health.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in pain-associated sleep interference, DS-5565 versus placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (week 0) to week 13</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess the effects of either dose of DS-5565 versus placebo on pain-associated sleep interference as assessed by average daily sleep interference score (ADSIS) and the Medical Outcomes Study (MOS) Sleep Scale.
Pain-associated sleep interference will be assessed using electronic daily diaries using an 11-point NRS ranging from 0 (pain does not interfere with sleep) to 10 (pain completely interferes with sleep, unable to sleep). The diary is to be filled out every day, along with the pain diary question, from the start of the Baseline Period through the last day on blinded study drug (including the morning following the last dose of blinded study medication).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in BPI-SF measure, DS-5565 versus placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (week 0) to week 13</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess the effects of either dose of DS-5565 versus placebo on pain as assessed by the Brief Pain Inventory Short Form (BPI-SF).
The BPI-SF has been used in many clinical studies across a wide variety of chronic pain conditions, including FM. This instrument measures pain severity and interference within the past 24 hours. Each item is rated on an 11-point NRS from 0 to 10.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>number and severity of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>enrollment through week 18</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>All clinical AEs occurring after the subject has signed the ICF and up to 4 weeks after the last dose of study medication (i.e. the follow-up period), whether observed by the investigator or reported by the subject, will be recorded on the AE eCRF page. Medical conditions (including laboratory values/vital signs that are out of range) that exist prior to Informed Consent will be recorded as part of medical history.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>proportion of days a rescue medication was used</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (week 0) to Week 13</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>number of days rescue medication used divided by total number of study days</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1200</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain Associated With Fibromyalgia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DS-5565, once daily at bedtime</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>one 15mg DS-5565 tablet taken orally at bedtime</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DS-5565, twice daily</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>one 15mg DS-5565 tablet taken twice daily. (titrated from 15 mg once daily after 1 week); during the first week subject will take DS-5565 placebo in the morning.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pregabalin 150 mg capsule twice daily</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>One pregabalin 150 mg capsule taken orally in the morning and one pregabalin 150 mg capsule taken orally at bedtime for 13 weeks (during the first week of blinded-treatment, subjects will take one pregabalin 75 mg capsule in the morning and one pregabalin 75 mg capsule at bedtime</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>One placebo tablet and one placebo capsule taken orally in the morning and one placebo tablet and one placebo capsule taken orally at bedtime daily for 13 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DS-5565 15mg tablet</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>DS-5565, once daily at bedtime</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>DS-5565, twice daily</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>150mg pregabalin capsule</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Pregabalin 150 mg capsule twice daily</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>matching DS-5565 tablet</description>
    <arm_group_label>DS-5565, once daily at bedtime</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Pregabalin 150 mg capsule twice daily</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo capsule</intervention_name>
    <description>matching pregabalin capsule</description>
    <arm_group_label>DS-5565, once daily at bedtime</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>DS-5565, twice daily</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>75mg pregabalin capsule</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Pregabalin 150 mg capsule twice daily</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 18 years

          -  Able to give written informed consent

          -  Able to complete subject-reported questionnaires per the investigator's judgment

          -  At screening, subjects must meet the 1990 American College of Rheumatology (ACR)
             criteria for FM, i.e. widespread pain present for at least 3 months and pain in at
             least 11 of 18 specific tender point sites. In addition, the 2010 ACR criteria must
             be met:

          -  Widespread pain index (WPI) ≥ 7 and symptom severity (SS) scale score ≥ 5, or WPI 3
             to 6 and SS scale score ≥ 9

          -  Symptoms have been present at a similar level for at least 3 months

          -  The subject does not have a disorder that would otherwise explain the pain

          -  ADPS of ≥ 4 on the 11-point numeric rating scale (NRS) over the past 7 days prior to
             randomization (based on completion of at least 4 daily pain diaries during the 7-day
             baseline period prior to randomization)

          -  Subject must have documented evidence of a fundoscopic examination (with pupil
             dilation) within 12 months prior to screening or at screening.

          -  Women of child-bearing potential (WOCBP) must be using an adequate method of
             contraception to avoid pregnancy during the study and for 4 weeks after study
             completion.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinically significant unstable neurologic, psychiatric, ophthalmologic,
             hepatobiliary, respiratory, or hematologic illness or unstable cardiovascular disease
             (e.g. severe hypotension, uncontrolled cardiac arrhythmia, or myocardial infarction)
             or any other concurrent disease within 12 months prior to screening that in the
             opinion of the investigator would interfere with study participation or assessment of
             safety and tolerability

          -  Anticipation of initiation or significant change to normal daily exercise routines or
             need for ongoing use of concomitant medications or non-pharmacological pain
             management techniques that may confound assessments of efficacy and/or safety

          -  Unable to undergo pre-study washout of prohibited concomitant medications

          -  Subjects who are at risk of suicide as defined by their responses to the
             Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS) or in the opinion of the
             investigator. Note: Patients answering &quot;yes&quot; to any of the questions about active
             suicidal ideation/intent/behaviors occurring within the past 12 months must be
             excluded (C-SSRS Suicide Ideation section - Questions 3, 4, or 5; C-SSRS Suicidal
             Behavior section, any of the suicide behaviors questions). Such patients should be
             referred immediately to a mental health professional for appropriate evaluation.

          -  Current severe or uncontrolled major depressive disorder or anxiety disorders as
             assessed by the Mini-international Neuropsychiatric Interview (MINI) mild to moderate
             major depression or anxiety disorders are permitted provided that the investigator
             assesses the patient as clinically stable and appropriate for entry into the study.

          -  Any diagnosis of lifetime bipolar disorder or psychotic disorder

          -  Subjects with pain due to other conditions (e.g. diabetic peripheral neuropathic pain
             or post-herpetic neuralgia) that in the opinion of the investigator, would  confound
             assessment or self-evaluation of the pain associated with FM.

          -  Subjects with pain due to any widespread inflammatory musculoskeletal disorder (e.g.
             rheumatoid arthritis, lupus) or widespread rheumatic disease other than FM.

          -  Abuse or dependence of prescription medications, street drugs, or alcohol within the
             last 1 year

          -  Any history of a malignancy other than basal cell carcinoma within the past 5 years

          -  A diagnosis of untreated sleep apnea or initiation of treatment for sleep apnea
             within the past 3 months

          -  Pregnancy or breast-feeding, or intent to become pregnant during the study period

          -  Subject is currently enrolled in or has not yet completed at least 30 days since
             ending another investigational device or drug study or is receiving other
             investigational agents.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to alpha2-delta (α2δ) ligands or other components of the study
             medications. Note: Prior exposure to DS-5565 is allowed, as long as hypersensitivity
             to DS-5565 was not observed.

          -  Subjects who are unlikely to comply with the protocol (e.g. uncooperative attitude,
             inability to return for subsequent visits) and/or otherwise considered by the
             investigator to be unlikely to complete the study.

          -  Abnormal investigative tests (i.e. electrocardiograms [ECGs]) and laboratory values
             judged by the investigator to be clinically significant at screening, with particular
             focus on: a. Abnormal renal function defined as calculated creatinine clearance
             (CrCl) &lt; 60 mL/min determined by the central laboratory using the modified
             Cockcroft-Gault equation; blood urea nitrogen&gt; 1.5 × upper limit of normal (ULN);
             creatine kinase &gt; 3.0 × ULN; serum creatinine &gt; 1.6 mg/dL (&gt; 141.4 μmol/L); b.
             Abnormal liver function defined as aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &gt; 2.0 × ULN,
             alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &gt; 2.0 × ULN; alkaline phosphatase &gt; 1.5 × ULN; total
             bilirubin&gt; 1.2 × ULN. If a subject has total bilirubin &gt; 1.2 ULN, unconjugated and
             conjugated bilirubin fractions should be analyzed and only subjects documented to
             have Gilbert's syndrome may be enrolled.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nico Merante, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Daiichi Sankyo Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>INC Research</last_name>
    <email>SM_DS5565_FM_Info@incresearch.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 21, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pain</keyword>
  <keyword>fibromyalgia</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fibromyalgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myofascial Pain Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Pregabalin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gamma-Aminobutyric Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
