<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="102690">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02142660</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UF8744</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02142660</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sprayshield as Adhesion Barrier System for Obese Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>Sprayshield</acronym>
  <official_title>Prospective Study Evaluating the Usefulness of Sprayshield as Adhesion Barrier System in Two Steps Laparoscopic Bariatric Surgery for Obese Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Montpellier</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Montpellier</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>France: The Commission nationale de l’informatique et des libertés</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The application of SprayShield during a laparoscopic band removal (first surgical step) will
      be evaluated to see if the postoperative adhesions between the stomach, the left liver and
      the diaphragm are not severe, facilitating the surgical surgical step of a gastric bypass or
      a sleeve gastrectomy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Monocenter and observational study on 20 obese patients, requiring removal of the gastric
      band for poor results (weight regain or insufficient weight-loss) or mechanical
      complications of the band ( slippage, esophageal dilation) and schedule for a second step
      surgery of gastric bypass or sleeve gastrectomy  2 months later.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>During the second surgical step the intensity of the adhesions in the operative field will be determined by the adhesion surface area and the adhesion intensity using</measure>
    <time_frame>intra operative</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>During  Conversion in Bypass or Sleeve Gastrectomy the intensity of the adhesions in the operative field will be determined by the adhesion surface area and the adhesion intensity using a 4-point  : scale 0 (no adhesion), 1 (fine and esily detachable adhesions), 2 (thick vascularize adhesion), 3 (intense adhesion preventing the identification of cleavable plane between organs)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>30 day surgical mortility</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Duration of surgery 30 day surgical mortility</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Severe Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sprayshield</arm_group_label>
    <description>Applied to the operating zone during an ablation of gastric died ring at obese patients programmed for the second bariatric surgery to type of bypass gastric or of gastrectomie</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ablation of gastric</intervention_name>
    <description>Applied to the operating zone during an ablation of gastric died ring at obese patients programmed for the second bariatric surgery to type of bypass gastric or of gastrectomie in wing</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sprayshield</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ablation of gastric</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Obese male or female  who would benefit from a gastric band removal and for whom a second
        surgical step with conversion to sleeve gastrectomy or bypass is scheduled
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Obese male or female who would benefit from a gastric band removal and for whom a
             second surgical step with conversion to sleeve gastrectomy or bypass is scheduled

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The patients having an ablation of ring motivated for an infectious complication
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jean Michel FABRE</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Montpellier</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jean Michel FABRE</last_name>
    <phone>330467337542</phone>
    <email>jm-fabre@chu-montpellier.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Digestive Surgery A, Saint Eloi Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montpellier</city>
        <zip>342950</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jean Michel FABRE</last_name>
      <phone>330467337542</phone>
      <email>jm-fabre@chu-montpellier.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nocca D, Guillaume F, Noel P, Picot MC, Aggarwal R, El Kamel M, Schaub R, de Seguin de Hons C, Renard E, Fabre JM. Impact of laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy and laparoscopic gastric bypass on HbA1c blood level and pharmacological treatment of type 2 diabetes mellitus in severe or morbidly obese patients. Results of a multicenter prospective study at 1 year. Obes Surg. 2011 Jun;21(6):738-43. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>21468625</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fezzi M, Kolotkin RL, Nedelcu M, Jaussent A, Schaub R, Chauvet MA, Cassafieres C, Lefebvre P, Renard E, Bringer J, Fabre JM, Nocca D. Improvement in quality of life after laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy. Obes Surg. 2011 Aug;21(8):1161-7. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>21298508</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Blanc PM, Lagoutte JM, Picot MC, Denève E, de Seguin C, Fabre JM, Nocca D. Preliminary results of the laparoscopic adjustable gastric banding procedure by a new generation of silicone band: MIDBAND. Obes Surg. 2008 May;18(5):569-72. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>18340499</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nocca D, Krawczykowsky D, Bomans B, Noël P, Picot MC, Blanc PM, de Seguin de Hons C, Millat B, Gagner M, Monnier L, Fabre JM. A prospective multicenter study of 163 sleeve gastrectomies: results at 1 and 2 years. Obes Surg. 2008 May;18(5):560-5. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>18317859</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nocca D, Aggarwal R, Blanc P, Gallix B, Di Mauro GL, Millat B, Seguin des De Hons C, Deneve E, Rodier JG, Tincani G, Pierredon MA, Fabre JM. Laparoscopic vertical banded gastroplasty. A multicenter prospective study of 200 procedures. Surg Endosc. 2007 Jun;21(6):870-4. Epub 2006 Nov 14. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>17103270</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 19, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 5, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Adhesion barrier system</keyword>
  <keyword>Bariatric surgery</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Tissue Adhesions</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obesity, Morbid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
