<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="149812">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02090088</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20080046</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02090088</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nplate® Pregnancy Exposure Registry</brief_title>
  <acronym>NPER</acronym>
  <official_title>Nplate® Pregnancy Exposure Registry (NPER)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Amgen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Amgen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      US study to estimate the prevalence at birth of major birth defects (ie, those that cause
      significant functional or cosmetic impairment, require surgery, or are life-limiting) in
      children born to mothers who have received Nplate® therapy at any time during the pregnancy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the NPER is to monitor pregnancies exposed to Nplate® and to detect and
      record serious adverse events in infants up to one year after birth. The lack of adequate
      human fetal safety data for Nplate® makes the NPER an important component of the
      pharmacovigilance program on the safety of this drug. With respect to fetal outcome, it is
      important to evaluate the spectrum of outcomes that may be relevant to a medication exposure
      during pregnancy, and these include both easily recognizable defects that are visible at
      birth, as well as more subtle or delayed defects that may not be readily identifiable
      without special expertise and observation beyond the newborn period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case Control, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <target_duration>21 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Major birth defects</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of children born with major birth defects (ie, those that cause significant functional or cosmetic impairment, require surgery, or are life-limiting) among children born to mothers who have received Nplate® therapy at any time during the pregnancy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Minor birth defects</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of children born with any three or more minor birth defects among children born to mothers who have received Nplate® therapy at any time during the pregnancy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Minor birth defects</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of children born with a specific pattern of minor birth defects among children born to mothers who have received Nplate® therapy at any time during the pregnancy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Spontaneous and elective abortions, stillbirths</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of each of spontaneous abortions, elective abortions, and stillbirths among mothers who have received Nplate® therapy at any time during the pregnancy,</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Low birth weight</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of children with preterm birth (&lt;37 weeks gestation) or low birth weight (&lt;2,500 grams) among children born to mothers who have received Nplate® therapy at any time during the pregnancy,</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>IUGR</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of children born with intrauterine growth restriction (weight, length or head circumference less than tenth percentile for sex and gestational age) among mothers who have received Nplate® therapy at any time during the pregnancy,</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>21 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>In the first year of life, the incidence of all serious adverse events, as well as of nevi and angiomata, among infants whose mothers received Nplate® therapy at any time during the pregnancy.
• Incidence of all adverse events among mothers who have received Nplate® therapy at any time during the pregnancy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">4</enrollment>
  <condition>Birth Defect</condition>
  <condition>Spontaneous Abortions</condition>
  <condition>Low Birth Weight</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>All Subjects</arm_group_label>
    <description>All Subjects</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Not applicable- observational study</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>All Subjects</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study population consists of two cohorts of women and their offspring who reside in
        the U.S. The exposed cohort is defined as pregnant women who have received at least one
        dose of Nplate® during pregnancy and their offspring up to one year of age. The unexposed
        cohort is defined as women unexposed to Nplate® during pregnancy matched on disease status
        (cITP) and age (childbearing) to the exposed. In order to provide context for any possible
        Nplate® exposed women without cITP, comparators from published literature will be used.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Eligible subjects will be currently pregnant women residing in the US who: Have had
             any exposure to Nplate® at any time during the pregnancy, which is defined as the
             period between first day of the last menstrual period (LMP) (ie, within two weeks of
             conception) up to any date before the date of delivery or end of the pregnancy. The
             date of conception will be defined as fourteen days prior to the next expected
             menstrual period for women who report a regular menstrual cycle. If the date of the
             first day of the LMP is unclear, or if the estimated date of conception as determined
             by a first-trimester ultrasound differs by more than one week from the date as
             determined by the first day of LMP, the first-trimester ultrasound-derived date will
             be used to estimate the timing of exposure to Nplate®, as well as timing of
             enrollment. If neither a clear date of the first day of the LMP nor a first-trimester
             ultrasound is available, the estimated date of conception for purposes of enrollment
             will be determined by best estimate of the woman's prenatal care provider.

          -  Agree to enroll at any time from the estimated date of conception up to any date
             before the date of delivery or end of the pregnancy and who have not already had
             prenatal diagnosis of any major structural birth defect in the current pregnancy
             prior to enrollment.

          -  Agree to provide consent for participation in the registry including follow-up
             interviews.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects will be ineligible for study participation if any of the following apply:

          -  Exposure to Nplate® did not occur during pregnancy.

          -  Prior knowledge of prenatal diagnosis of a birth defect. Patients who fall under this
             category will be encouraged to call the Amgen PSP toll free number for enrollment and
             follow-up.

          -  Cases reported to the NPER after completion of the exposed pregnancy. Patients who
             fall under this category will be encouraged to call the Amgen PSP toll free number
             for enrollment and follow-up.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Amgen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.amgentrials.com</url>
    <description>AmgenTrials clinical trials website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 14, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Congenital Abnormalities</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Abortion, Spontaneous</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Birth Weight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
