<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="141207">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01870583</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CCI#12-07-248</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01870583</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Surgical Skin Preps During Cesarean Deliveries</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of Surgical Skin Preps During Cesarean Deliveries</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Montefiore Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Montefiore Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In women that undergo non-emergency cesarean delivery, we are comparing the skin preparation
      solutions for best outcome of surgical site infection. The three different solutions are:
      Group 1: Iodine povidone based skin preparation solution. Group 2: Chlorhexidine based skin
      preparation solution or Group 3: Combination usage of iodine povidone and chlorhexidine
      based skin preparation solutions. Women are prospectively randomized to one of the three
      groups and followed until thier postpartum visit at 6-8 weeks following delivery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Currently the skin preparation solutions currently in use for cesarean delivery are
      chlorhexidine-alcohol based solutions or iodine povidone solutions There had been no
      recommendations of which surgical skin prep wound be best utilized for cesarean delivery,
      especially if the patient has risk factors for surgical site infection. Chlorhexidine
      solution has been reported to take minimal of 2 minutes after application to decrease the
      bacterial load, and continue to decrease the bacteria load up to 1 hour. Iodine povidone
      solution has been reported to be completely effective within 4 minutes of application.
      Patient's risk factor for surgical site infection, including obesity, history of incision
      complications, maternal diabetes, chorioamnionitis, potentially influence which surgical
      skin prep to be applied. Finally, the majority of postpartum infections manifest after
      hospital discharge and  most of these post-discharge infections are diagnosed and treated
      entirely in the ambulatory setting, without the patients' returning to the hospital.

      The purpose of the study is:

        1. To compare chlorhexidine based solution, iodine povidone solution, and combination of
           both agents in cesarean delivery skin preparation solution for prevention of surgical
           site infection (SSI)

        2. To determine if surgical site infection (SSI) risk factors should guide selection of
           one specific surgical skin preparation solution.

      This will be a prospective randomized observational study of the women presenting for care
      to the Montefiore Medical Center. All patients will undergo routine obstetrical care and
      preparation for cesarean delivery as if they were not participating in this research study.
      All patients in the study will receive the pre-operative intravenous antibiotics
      pre-operatively as part of departmental protocol for cesarean delivery.

      The patients will be randomized after informed consent obtained into one of three groups:
      Group 1: Iodine povidone based skin preparation solution. Group 2: Chlorhexidine based skin
      preparation solution or Group 3: Combination usage of iodine povidone and chlorhexidine
      based skin preparation solutions. Sequentially numbered envelopes will contain the group of
      randomization for the patient created by a computer generated program which will occur prior
      to commencement of the study.

      Surgical preparation will follow the departmental protocol as if the patient were not in the
      study with exception of the skin preparation. Once the patient is randomized to the skin
      preparation group, the corresponding skin preparation solution will be used in accordance to
      manufacturer's guidelines for the product and Departmental protocol. If randomized to group
      3 (combination), the iodine based preparation will occur first followed by the chlorhexidine
      based skin preparation. All groups will wait a minimal of 4 minutes prior to skin incision
      after application of skin prep, and all patients will be surgically draped with the standard
      drapes as if not participating in a study. Cesarean delivery will occur following the
      technique of the surgeon, including skin closure method, suture or staples.

      All patients will be followed until the routine postpartum visit occurs at 6-8 weeks
      following delivery. Postpartum visit information will be extracted from the medical record.
      If no postpartum visit occurs, the patient will be contacted by telephone at 8 weeks post
      delivery and asked about any incisional complications which may have occurred and required
      treatment by as physician or healthcare provider in the office or hospital.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cesarean surgical site infection</measure>
    <time_frame>42 days after delivery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Surgical site infection will follow CDC guidelines: A) Superficial incisional surgical site infection B) Deep incisional surgical site infection or C) Organ/space surgical site infection.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2188</enrollment>
  <condition>Surgical Site Infection Following Cesarean Delivery</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Combination iodine and chlorhexidine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The combincation skin preparation will utilize the iodine based preparation  first followed by the chlorhexidine based skin preparation prior to cesarean delivery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Chlorhexidine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Chlorhexidine based skin preparation solution applied to skin prior to cesarean delivery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Iodine povidone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Iodine povidone based skin preparation solution applied to skin prior to cesarean delivery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Iodine povidone</intervention_name>
    <description>Iodine skin preparation solution prior to cesarean delivery</description>
    <arm_group_label>Iodine povidone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chlorhexidine</intervention_name>
    <description>Chlorhexidine skin preparation solution prior to cesarean delivery</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chlorhexidine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Combination iodine and chlorhexidine</intervention_name>
    <description>Combination iodine povidone and chlorhexidine skin preparation solution prior to cesarean delivery</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combination iodine and chlorhexidine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Gestational age &gt; 37 weeks 0/7 days

          -  Non-emergency indication for cesarean

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Urogenital tract infection within 2 weeks prior to surgery

          -  Chronic oral or injectable steroid use (&gt; 2 weeks)

          -  Emergency cesarean delivery

          -  Participation in another research study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David A Wallach, CIP</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Einstein IRB</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David J Garry, DO</last_name>
    <phone>718-920-9647</phone>
    <email>dgarry@montefiore.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ivan Ngai, MD</last_name>
    <phone>718-920-9647</phone>
    <email>ingai@montefiore.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Montefiore Medical Center Wakefield Division</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10466</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David J Garry, DO</last_name>
      <phone>718-920-9647</phone>
      <email>dgarry@montefiore.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ivan Ngai, MD</last_name>
      <phone>718-920-9647</phone>
      <email>ingai@montefiore.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David J Garry, DO</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ivan Ngai, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nancy Judge, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Montefiore Medical Center Weiler Division</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10461</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David J Garry, DO</last_name>
      <phone>718-920-9647</phone>
      <email>dgarry@montefiore.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ivan Ngai, MD</last_name>
      <phone>718-920-9647</phone>
      <email>ingai@montefiore.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David J Garry, DO</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ivan Ngai, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jeffery Bernstein, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nancy Judge, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zinn J, Jenkins JB, Harrelson B, Wrenn C, Haynes E, Small N. Differences in intraoperative prep solutions: a retrospective chart review. AORN J. 2013 May;97(5):552-8. doi: 10.1016/j.aorn.2013.03.006.</citation>
    <PMID>23622828</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berkelman RL, Holland BW, Anderson RL. Increased bactericidal activity of dilute preparations of povidone-iodine solutions. J Clin Microbiol. 1982 Apr;15(4):635-9.</citation>
    <PMID>7040461</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stinner DJ, Krueger CA, Masini BD, Wenke JC. Time-dependent effect of chlorhexidine surgical prep. J Hosp Infect. 2011 Dec;79(4):313-6. doi: 10.1016/j.jhin.2011.08.016. Epub 2011 Oct 15.</citation>
    <PMID>22000737</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Olsen MA, Butler AM, Willers DM, Gross GA, Hamilton BH, Fraser VJ. Attributable costs of surgical site infection and endometritis after low transverse cesarean delivery. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2010 Mar;31(3):276-82. doi: 10.1086/650755.</citation>
    <PMID>20102279</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gong SP, Guo HX, Zhou HZ, Chen L, Yu YH. Morbidity and risk factors for surgical site infection following cesarean section in Guangdong Province, China. J Obstet Gynaecol Res. 2012 Mar;38(3):509-15. doi: 10.1111/j.1447-0756.2011.01746.x. Epub 2012 Feb 22.</citation>
    <PMID>22353388</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miner AL, Sands KE, Yokoe DS, Freedman J, Thompson K, Livingston JM, Platt R. Enhanced identification of postoperative infections among outpatients. Emerg Infect Dis. 2004 Nov;10(11):1931-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15550202</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Opøien HK, Valbø A, Grinde-Andersen A, Walberg M. Post-cesarean surgical site infections according to CDC standards: rates and risk factors. A prospective cohort study. Acta Obstet Gynecol Scand. 2007;86(9):1097-102.</citation>
    <PMID>17712651</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lobdell KW, Stamou S, Sanchez JA. Hospital-acquired infections. Surg Clin North Am. 2012 Feb;92(1):65-77. doi: 10.1016/j.suc.2011.11.003. Epub 2011 Dec 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22269261</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Segal CG, Anderson JJ. Preoperative skin preparation of cardiac patients. AORN J. 2002 Nov;76(5):821-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12463081</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 6, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 3, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Montefiore Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Garry</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Co-Director Obstetrics &amp; MFM service Wakefield Division</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cesarean delivery</keyword>
  <keyword>Surgical site infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>Postpartum</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Povidone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chlorhexidine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chlorhexidine gluconate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Iodine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cadexomer iodine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Povidone-Iodine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
