<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="14944">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01894308</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PARC-Testosterone-D1/09/13</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01894308</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Dose Ranging Study to Examine Testagen™ TDS®-Testosterone 5%</brief_title>
  <acronym>PARC-T-D</acronym>
  <official_title>A Multiple-Dose, Single Period, Phase II Dose Ranging Study to Examine Testagen™ TDS®-Testosterone 5% in Adult Male Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Transdermal Delivery Solutions Corp</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Barts &amp; The London NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Transdermal Delivery Solutions Corp</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a continuation of previous studies done in healthy volunteers to prove the
      efficacy of delivering Testosterone, the male hormone, rapidly across intact skin in s
      series of doses from low to high in men with low-to-no natural testosterone production to
      measure their response to the varying doses.  The results of this study will inform further
      studies which will be longer in length, as to the starting doses.  The study will be
      conducted in London, U.K. at Barts and the London NHS Hospital and the London Clinic.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Bio-availability Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Range</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>A pharmacokinetic measure of serum levels of testosterone in response to varying doses of from 10 to 70 mgs of Testosterone.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Skin response and general response to daily dosing over 7 days.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypogonadotropism</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Testosterone</intervention_name>
    <description>10,30,50 and 70 mg doses of micronized Testosterone delivered by means of a new liquid transdermal delivery solution, HypoSpray(TM)once daily for 7 days or until halted due to systemic or dermal reactions.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Hypogonadal Male subjects - morning testosterone level ≤300 ng/dL (10.4 ng/L).

          2. 18 and 75 years of age, inclusive.

          3. The subject is willing and able to read, understand the Subject Information Sheet and
             provide written informed consent.

          4. The subject has a body mass index (BMI) within 18-30 kg/m2.

          5. The subject is in otherwise good health as determined by medical history and physical
             examination.

          6. The subject is a non-smoker.

          7. The subject must agree to comply with the placement of an indwelling catheter on two
             separate occasions and the drawing of blood samples for the pharmacokinetic
             assessments.

          8. The subject is willing and able to comply with all testing and requirements defined
             in the protocol.

          9. The subject is willing and able to return to the study site for all visits.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. The subject has any relevant deviations from normal in physical examination,
             electrocardiogram (ECG), or clinical laboratory tests, as evaluated by the
             investigator, particularly an elevated PSA reading &gt;4.0 ng/ml or ALT and AST greater
             than 2 times the upper limit of normal, clinically significant anemia (hematocrit
             &lt;35%) or renal dysfunction (creatinine &gt;2mg/dL), active deep vein thrombosis,
             thromboembolic disorders or history of these conditions.

          2. The subject has had a clinically significant illness within 30 days preceding entry
             into this study.

          3. The subject has a history of significant neurological, hepatic, renal, endocrine,
             cardiovascular, gastrointestinal, pulmonary, or metabolic disease.

          4. The subject has a known allergy or history of hypersensitivity to Testosterone or
             similar compounds.

          5. The subject has used any prescription medication within 14 days or over-the-counter
             (OTC) medication or alcohol within 48 hours of dosing or intends to use any
             prescription or OTC medication during the study that may interfere with the
             evaluation of study medication.

          6. The subject has donated or lost a significant volume of blood (&gt;450 mL) within four
             (4) weeks of the study, and their haemoglobin concentration and haematocrit have not
             returned to within 5% of normal.

          7. The subject has a Hematocrit level  &gt; 51%

          8. The subject has a history of substance abuse or a current positive urine drug screen
             or urine alcohol test.

          9. Alcohol consumption greater than community norms (i.e. more than 21 standard drinks
             per week for males).

         10. Subjects who have received an investigational drug or have used an investigational
             device in the 30 days prior to study entry.

         11. Subjects with an American Urological Association System Index for Prostatism score
             greater than 7

         12. Subjects with a history of prostate or breast carcinoma.

         13. Subjects with prostatic mass on screening physical examination.

         14. Subjects with a history of significant skin disease.

         15. Subjects with a history of sleep apnea.

         16. Subject with a partner with a history of breast cancer.

         17. Subject with a partner of child bearing potential who is not willing to use adequate
             contraception for the duration of the trial.

         18. Subject whose partner is pregnant.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The London Clinic, St. Bartholomews Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>EC1A 7BE</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Endocrine Studies Unit, Barts and the London NHS Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>London,</city>
        <zip>EC1A 7BE</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chik Z, Johnston A, Tucker AT, Chew SL, Michaels L, Alam CA. Pharmacokinetics of a new testosterone transdermal delivery system, TDS-testosterone in healthy males. Br J Clin Pharmacol. 2006 Mar;61(3):275-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16487220</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 1, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 3, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Male Hormone Replacement</keyword>
  <keyword>Multiple Dose</keyword>
  <keyword>Single Period</keyword>
  <keyword>Phase II</keyword>
  <keyword>Dose Ranging</keyword>
  <keyword>Adult Male Subjects</keyword>
  <keyword>Testosterone Replacement</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hypogonadism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Testosterone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone enanthate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone undecanoate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone 17 beta-cypionate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methyltestosterone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
