<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="3232">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01987401</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>595</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01987401</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Service and Health During the Iraq and Afghanistan Era</brief_title>
  <acronym>CSP #595 Pilot</acronym>
  <official_title>CSP #595 - Respiratory Health and Deployment to Iraq and Afghanistan Pilot</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of CSP #595, &quot;Service and Health During the Iraq and Afghanistan Era,&quot;
      is to characterize the impact of deployment to Iraq and Afghanistan on the respiratory
      health of Veterans. The purpose of the pilot study is to determine the willingness of
      Veterans who served during the Iraq and Afghanistan Era to provide health and military
      service information. This information will help us design a larger national study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of CSP #595, &quot;Respiratory Health and Deployment to Iraq and
      Afghanistan,&quot; is to assess the association of airborne exposures encountered during
      deployment with current measures of respiratory health among U.S. military Veterans who
      served in Iraq and Afghanistan.

      The purpose of the pilot study is to assess the feasibility and approach to conducting a
      large, multi-site Cooperative Studies Program (CSP) initiative to characterize the impact of
      deployment to Iraq and Afghanistan on the respiratory health of Veterans. We will (a)
      determine the most efficient and feasible method for recruitment; (b) understand
      demographic, health-related, and military service-related factors influencing participation
      so that potential biases can be identified; and (c) demonstrate that the proposed individual
      exposure reconstruction techniques based on deployment history are feasible.

      Three aims are proposed: Aim 1: Using the Department of Defense (DoD) Defense Manpower Data
      Center (DMDC) master personnel roster, identify a representative sample of deployed Veterans
      who have served in Iraq and Afghanistan as well as a sample of non-deployed Veterans;
      identify the optimal methods for recruitment of participants to Phase 1 of data collection
      (mailed survey or telephone interview on self-reported health and military service history)
      and assess the willingness of Veterans to visit a nearby Veterans Health Administration
      (VHA) medical center to participate in Phase 2 in-person data collection, which includes
      more extensive self-reported health information, lifetime exposure ascertainment, and
      assessment of pulmonary function. Aim 2: Assess the Phase 2 participation rate of Veterans
      using VA Boston Healthcare System as a pilot study site. Aim 3: Using publically available
      exposure data and data from the DoD personnel file, demonstrate that the proposed individual
      exposure reconstruction techniques are feasible.

      The study is organized by the CSP Epidemiology Center program with the Seattle Epidemiologic
      Research and Information Center serving as the CSP coordinating center. The 2 participating
      sites are at the VA Boston Healthcare System and Durham VA Medical Center. The pilot study
      will provide information that will allow the planning of a national, large-scale health
      study to assess the residual effects of exposure to high levels of particulate matter while
      deployed. This will help inform VA health policy for Iraq and Afghanistan Veterans.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Cross-Sectional</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Participation Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>From the national sample, we will compare Phase 1 participation rates obtained in each of the 4 recruitment approaches and characterize the sample of participants compared with non-participants in terms of exposure profiles and DMDC-obtained demographic characteristics to evaluate potential recruitment biases. Among a sample of Veterans living in the greater Boston area, we will calculate Phase 2 participation rates and compare the military, exposure, and health characteristics of participants with non-participants.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2760</enrollment>
  <condition>Iraq and Afghanistan Era Veterans</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Iraq and Afghanistan Era Veterans</arm_group_label>
    <description>Those who served during the Iraq and Afghanistan Era without regard to actual deployment to Southwest Asia.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Veterans who served during the Iraq and Afghanistan Era, without regard to actual
        deployment, identified from the Department of Defense (DoD) Defense Manpower Data Center
        (DMDC) master personnel roster of all persons serving during the time period of interest.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All competent, living men and women who served during the Iraq and Afghanistan Era
             and been discharged from the Army, Air Force, Marine Corps, or Navy are eligible to
             participate.

          -  Individuals in respective Guard and Reserve units are also eligible to participate.

          -  A Veteran is eligible without regard to deployment or combat status and without
             regard to current or past user status in the Veterans Health Administration.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Veterans of the Coast Guard, including individuals in respective Guard and Reserve
             units, are not eligible to participate.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eric Garshick, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>VA Boston Healthcare System, Brockton Campus</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susan P Proctor, DSc</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>VA Boston Healthcare System Jamaica Plain Campus, Jamaica Plain, MA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karen S Nakayama, BA</last_name>
    <phone>(206) 277-3587</phone>
    <email>Karen.Nakayama@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jennifer Sporleder</last_name>
    <phone>(206) 764-2557</phone>
    <email>jennifer.sporleder@med.va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Boston Healthcare System Jamaica Plain Campus, Jamaica Plain, MA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02130</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eric Garshick, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-203-5536</phone>
      <email>Eric.Garshick@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Susan P Proctor, DSc</last_name>
      <phone>(508) 233-4465</phone>
      <email>susan.proctor@us.army.mil</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Susan P Proctor, DSc</last_name>
      <role>Study Chair</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Puget Sound Health Care System Seattle Division, Seattle, WA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karen S Nakayama, BS</last_name>
      <phone>206-277-3587</phone>
      <email>Karen.Nakayama@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.seattle.eric.research.va.gov/</url>
    <description>Click here for more information about this study: CSP #595 - Respiratory Health and Deployment to Iraq and Afghanistan Pilot</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.research.va.gov/programs/csp/</url>
    <description>Click here for more information about this study: CSP #595 - Respiratory Health and Deployment to Iraq and Afghanistan Pilot</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 5, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pulmonary</keyword>
  <keyword>lung</keyword>
  <keyword>military and environmental exposures</keyword>
  <keyword>epidemiologic</keyword>
  <keyword>observational</keyword>
  <keyword>interview or questionnaire</keyword>
  <keyword>deployment related</keyword>
  <keyword>Enduring Freedom</keyword>
  <keyword>Iraqi Freedom</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
