<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="30144">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01929317</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>116991</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01929317</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Efficacy of 18 to 24mg/Day Ropinirole Controlled Release (CR) Tablets in Early and Advanced Parkinson's Disease (PD) Patients.</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study ROP116991, Clinical Evaluation of 18 to 24mg/Day Ropinirole CR for Parkinson's Disease.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Japan: Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a Phase III, multicentre, randomized, initial double-blind study with
      subsequent open label phases. The study will havea screening phase (4 weeks), a dose
      increase effect verification phase (12 weeks), a down titration 1 phase (1 week), a
      long-term phase (39 weeks), down titration 2 phase (1 to 2 weeks) and a follow up phase.
      Subjects will be assigned to Ropinirole CR high-dose group or Ropinirole CR maintenance
      group at a ratio of 3:1. This study is being conducted to evaluate the efficacy (effect of
      increasing Ropinirole dose from 16 mg/day to 18-24 mg/day) of the Ropinirole CR tablets in
      early and advanced PD patients who have not achieved an optimal therapeutic response with
      marketed Ropinirole Immediate release (IR) (15 mg/day) or marketed Ropinirole CR (16 mg/day)
      formulations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline (Week 0 visit) in UPDRS part III total score at 12 week in CR high-dose group</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale (UPDRS) is a tool developed to assess the status of PD patients objectively and was introduced as a rating scale that would allow the physician to assess symptoms of PD. Japanese UPDRS (Parts I, II, III, and IV) evaluations will be conducted at each visit after the administration of investigational drug.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects achieving a 30% and 20% reduction from Baseline in UPDRS total part3 score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Up to Weeks 52/Withdrawal</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The UPDRS is a tool developed to assess the status of PD patients objectively and was introduced as a rating scale that would allow the physician to assess symptoms of PD. Japanese UPDRS (Parts I, II, III, and IV) evaluations will be conducted at each visit after the administration of investigational drug.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Japanese UPDRS Part 1, 2, and 4 total score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Up to Weeks 52/Withdrawal</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Japanese UPDRS Part 1, 2, 3 and 4 total score</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Weeks 52/Withdrawal</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Japanese UPDRS Part 1, 2, 3 and 4 total score percent change from Baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Up to Weeks 52/Withdrawal</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical global impression of Improvement</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12 and Weeks 52/Withdrawal</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Clinical global impression of Improvement of the subject's condition as compared with that at Week 0 will be assessed into 7 grades (1= Very much improved and 7=Very much worse) at Week 12 and Week 52 (or at withdrawal).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in awake time &quot;Off&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Up to Weeks 52/Withdrawal</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Diary cards will be used to check &quot;off&quot;, &quot;on&quot;, troublesome dyskinesia during the study. Before issuing diary cards, the investigator, subinvestigator or person assisting with the study will fully explain to each subject how to complete diary cards. Actual hours and proportion of &quot;off&quot; time in awake time was recorded for L dopa adjunct subjects only</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in awake time &quot;On&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Up to Weeks 52/Withdrawal</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Actual hours of &quot;on&quot; time in awake time was recorded for L dopa adjunct subjects only</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in awake time &quot;On&quot; without troublesome dyskinesias</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Up to Weeks 52/Withdrawal</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>For L dopa adjunct subjects only</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects remaining in the study</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Weeks 52/Withdrawal</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ropinirole CR high-dose group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The subjects will receive Ropinirole CR 16mg/day for 4 weeks in screening phase. After randomization the subject will enter dose increase effect verification phase, where Ropinirole CR dose will titrated (2 mg /day/week) from 18 mg/day up to a maximum 24mg/day at intervals of 1 week or longer for 8 weeks, till subject reaches a dose level above which further symptomatic improvement cannot be expected; the subject will be maintained on that dose for 4 weeks. This will be followed by a down titration phase of one week and long term phase of 39 weeks in which the subjects will receive incremental doses (2 mg /day/week) of Ropinirole CR from 18 mg/day till to a maximum of 24 mg/day till subject reaches a dose level above which further symptomatic improvement cannot be expected; the subject will be maintained on that dose. Subjects completing the long term phase will undergo a down titration phase of 1 to 2 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ropinirole CR maintenance group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The subjects will receive Ropinirole CR 16mg/day for 4 weeks in screening phase. After randomization the subject will enter dose increase effect verification phase and Ropinirole CR dose will maintained at 16mg/day and placebo will be increased at intervals of 1 week for 8 weeks till subject reaches a dose level above which further symptomatic improvement cannot be expected; the subject will be maintained on that dose for 4 weeks. This will be followed by a down titration phase of one week and long term phase of 39 weeks in which the subjects will receive incremental doses (2 mg/day/week) of Ropinirole CR from 18 mg/day till to a maximum of 24 mg/day till subject reaches a dose level above which further symptomatic improvement cannot be expected; the subject will be maintained on that dose. Subjects completing the long term phase will undergo a down titration phase of 1 to 2 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ropinirole CR 2mg tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>Ropinirole CR 2mg tablets will be supplied as white oval film-coated tablets.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ropinirole CR maintenance group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ropinirole CR high-dose group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ropinirole CR 8mg tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>Ropinirole CR 8mg tablets will be supplied as white oval film-coated tablets.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ropinirole CR maintenance group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ropinirole CR high-dose group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ropinirole CR matching Placebo tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>Ropinirole CR matching Placebo tablet tablets (containing no active ingredients) indistinguishable in appearance from Ropinirole CR 2 mg tablets.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ropinirole CR maintenance group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Inclusion criteria at the start of the screening

          -  Patients who are diagnosed as Parkinson's Disease with severity of the modified Hoehn
             &amp; Yahr criteria Stages I-IV.

          -  1) Monotherapy subject: Subjects who have never received L-dopa, or subjects who have
             had prior exposure to L-dopa (up to 450 milligram (mg)/day) for up to 3 months in
             total and L-dopa treatment has been discontinued, for a minimum of 4 weeks prior to
             the screening phase. 2) L-dopa adjunct subject: Subjects receiving L-dopa (up to 450
             mg/day) for at least 4 weeks prior to the screening phase.

          -  Patients receiving 15mg/day Ropinirole IR or 16mg/day Ropinirole CR for 4 weeks prior
             to the screening phase, UPDRS Part III total (on) scores is 10 points or more at
             screening visit and can expect clinical efficacy by increasing Ropinirole CR.

          -  Age: 20years or older (at the time of informed written consent)

          -  Informed consent: Patients who are able to give informed written consent in person.
             (i.e. patients who are capable of giving informed written consent on their own)

          -  Sex: Either sex. Women of child-bearing potential will be eligible for inclusion in
             this study. However they have to have a negative pregnancy test at the screening
             visit and will have to agree to further pregnancy testing at the time points
             determined in study assessments and procedures and practice one of the methods of
             contraception mentioned in the protocol from the screening visit until the end of the
             follow-up examination  -  Outpatient status

          -  corrected QT (QTc) &lt;450 millisecond (msec) or &lt;480msec for subjects with Bundle
             Branch Block. The QTc should be based on single or averaged QTc values of triplicate
             electrocardiograms (ECGs) obtained over a brief recording period.

          -  Liver function tests: Patients with aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine
             aminotransferase (ALT) &lt; 2x upper limit of normal (ULN); and Alkaline Phosphatase and
             bilirubin =&lt; 1.5xULN (isolated bilirubin &gt; 1.5ULN is acceptable if bilirubin is
             fractionated and direct bilirubin &lt; 35%) at the screening visit.

        Randomization Criteria

          -  Patients whose UPDRS Part III total (on) scores is 10 points or more at week 0

          -  Patients who did not achieve an optimal therapeutic response by treatment with
             16mg/day Ropinirole CR and required higher dose of Ropinirole CR

          -  Patients who are 80% or more compliant taking study drug

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Late stage advanced patients demonstrating incapacitating peak dose or biphasic
             dyskinsia on their stable dose of L-dopa.

          -  Patients who have used any other dopamine agonist (except for Ropinirole IR and CR)
             within 4 weeks prior to the screening phase.

          -  Patients who have been treated with the following drugs at 4 weeks or earlier before
             the start of the screening phase, and whose treatment regimen of the drug has been
             changed. Anticholinergic agents: trihexyphenidyl hydrochloride, piroheptine
             hydrochloride, mazaticol hydrochloride, metixene hydrochloride, biperiden
             hydrochloride, profenamine, amantadine hydrochloride,droxidopa, citicoline,
             selegiline hydrochloride, entacapone, zonisamide, Estrogens, CYP1A2 inhibitors.

          -  Patients who have been changing in smoking habit (started or stopped smoking) within
             the screening phase.

          -  Patients who have been treated with any other investigational drug within 12 weeks
             prior to the screening phase.

          -  Patients who present serious physical signs and symptoms other than those of the PD
             (e.g. cardiac/hepatic/renal disorder and haematopoietic disorder).

          -  Patients with symptomatic postural hypotension. (e.g. dizziness and syncope).

          -  Patients with a current or history of drug abuse or alcoholism.

          -  Patients with severe dementia such as score 3 or 4 of the UPDRS item 1 (Mentation,
             behaviour, and mood).

          -  Patients with current or history of major psychosis (e.g. schizophrenia or psychotic
             depression) such as score 3 or 4 of the UPDRS item 2 (thought disorder) or item
             3(depression).

          -  Patients who have received surgical treatment for PD in the past (e.g. pallidectomy,
             deep brain stimulation).

          -  Female patients who are pregnant or lactating, who may be pregnant, or who plan for
             pregnancy during the study or within 30 days after the last dose of the study drug.

          -  Unstable liver disease (as defined by the presence of ascites, encephalopathy,
             coagulapathy, hypoalbuminaemia, oesophageal or gastric varices or persistent
             jaundice), cirrhosis, known biliary abnormalities (with the exception of Gilbert's
             syndrome or asymptomatic gallstones). Chronic hepatitis B administered
             immunosuppressive agents due to risk of hapatitis B reactivation.

          -  Patients with a history of drug allergy to Ropinirole hydrochloride.

          -  Except for patients with a history of basal cell carcinoma, patients with a current
             or history of cancer or malignant tumor within 5 years prior to the screening phase.

          -  Others whom the investigator (subinvestigator) considers ineligible for the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
    <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aichi</city>
        <zip>466-8560</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Akita</city>
        <zip>010-0874</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aomori</city>
        <zip>030-8553</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hokkaido</city>
        <zip>070-8644</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hokkaido</city>
        <zip>070-8530</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hyogo</city>
        <zip>674-0081</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hyogo</city>
        <zip>672-8043</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Iwate</city>
        <zip>020-0878</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Iwate</city>
        <zip>025-0075</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kagawa</city>
        <zip>760-0027</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kanagawa</city>
        <zip>252-0392</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kyoto</city>
        <zip>600-8811</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Okayama</city>
        <zip>703-8265</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Osaka</city>
        <zip>578-8588</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Osaka</city>
        <zip>530-8480</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shizuoka</city>
        <zip>416-0955</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shizuoka</city>
        <zip>433-8125</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 17, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 22, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ropinirole</keyword>
  <keyword>Parkinson's disease</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ropinirole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
