<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="78989">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01983046</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NL44507.068</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01983046</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rectal Short Chain Fatty Acids Combinations and Substrate and Energy Metabolism</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effects of Rectal Administration of SCFA on Human Substrate and Energy Metabolism</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Maastricht University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Top Institute Food and Nutrition</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Maastricht University Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Netherlands: The Central Committee on Research Involving Human Subjects (CCMO)</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Gut microbiota is being increasingly recognized as an important factor in fat distribution,
      insulin sensitivity and glucose and lipid metabolism. Accordingly, the intestinal microbiota
      could play an important role in the development of obesity and type 2 diabetes mellitus. The
      role of gut-derived short-chain fatty acids (SCFA), the formation of which is enhanced by
      microbial fermentation of fiber, is still controversial. One study found that an increase in
      the formation of SCFA stimulated energy extraction from diet, with subsequent weight gain.
      In contrast, supplementation of non-fermentable carbohydrates, which lead to an increase in
      SCFA formation, had beneficial effects on body weight control and insulin sensitivity. Of
      note, a study showed that butyrate supplementation in mice prevented diet-induced obesity
      and insulin resistance. At the present time, our understanding of the effects of SCFA on
      human metabolism (in gut or systemically) is still limited. Yet, in light of the health
      claims of certain dietary fibers (prebiotics), a detailed picture of the physiology of human
      SCFA metabolism and its interaction with the microbiome is of pivotal importance. We
      hypothesize that the differential availability of SCFA impacts human metabolism differently.
      To determine whether rectal administration of SCFA is a good model for studying the
      metabolic effects of SCFA we first have performed a pilot study (METC 11-3-079). In this
      pilot study we have determined if rectal administration of sodium acetate has the same
      effects on substrate and energy metabolism compared to proximal administration. Our results
      indicate that the primary outcome parameter fat oxidation was significantly changed during
      post-absorptive conditions, when sodium acetate in a concentration of 180mM was administered
      in the distal part of the colon. In contrast, no effect on energy expenditure or substrate
      oxidation was seen when sodium acetate was administered in the proximal colon. Consequently,
      the distal part of the colon seems to be a good model to determine effects of gut-derived
      SCFA on the human substrate and energy metabolism. Therefore, we will administer in this
      study the SCFA rectally by using enemas. We will administer different combinations of SCFA
      to healthy, overweight male volunteers and examine effects on metabolism. This study is an
      important part of a Gastrointestinal Health TIFN project (GH003 WP 1.2), which will provide
      more insight in how increased availability of a beneficial SCFA mixture might serve as a
      basis for rational nutritional strategies in the prevention and treatment of obesity and
      type 2 diabetes mellitus. To obtain rational nutritional strategies, a next step in this
      TIFN project will be focusing on dietary ingredients modulating intestinal microbiota and
      subsequent SCFA production.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>fat oxidation</measure>
    <time_frame>4 hours total (2 hours fasting, 2 hours postprandial)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>we will measure fat oxidation and energy expenditure by using the ventilated hood system</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hormones that influence energy metabolism</measure>
    <time_frame>4 hours total (2 hours fasting and 2 hours postprandial)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating metabolites</measure>
    <time_frame>4 hours total (2 hours fasting and 2 hours postprandial)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hormones that influence energy metabolism - Circulating metabolites  - Inflammatory markers  - plasma SCFA content; - Indirect markers of insulin sensitivity  - Appetite (VAS-scoring).</measure>
    <time_frame>4 hours total (2 hours fasting and 2 hours postprandial)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>high acetate ratio</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>high acetate ratio</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>high butyrate ratio</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>high butyrate ratio</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>high propionate ratio</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>high propionate ratio</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Three different mixture of acetate, butyrate and propionate and palcebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>high acetate ratio</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>high butyrate ratio</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>high propionate ratio</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Overweight

          -  Obese men

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Athletes

          -  Diabetes mellitus
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ellen E Blaak</last_name>
    <phone>+31 43 3881503</phone>
    <email>e.blaak@maastrichtuniversity.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Maastricht</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maastricht</city>
        <state>Limburg</state>
        <zip>6229 ER</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ellen E Blaak</last_name>
      <phone>81503</phone>
      <email>e.blaak@maastrichtuniversity.nl</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 12, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 17, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
