<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="99197">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01958658</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2013-01765</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-01765</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>9407</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>PHL-087</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>9407</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>N01CM00032</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01958658</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT01925326</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MK-1775, Cisplatin, and Radiation Therapy in Treating Patients With Cervical Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of the Wee 1 Kinase (Wee 1) Inhibitor MK-1775 in Combination With Cisplatin and Radiation in Cervical Cancer (10041848, 10008224, 10008328)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial studies the side effects and the best dose of WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775
      (MK-1775) when given together with cisplatin and radiation therapy in treating patients with
      cervical cancer. WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775 may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking some
      of the enzymes needed for cell growth. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as cisplatin, work
      in different ways to stop the growth of tumor cells, either by killing the cells or by
      stopping them from dividing. Radiation therapy uses high energy x rays to kill tumor cells.
      Giving WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775 with cisplatin and radiation therapy may be an effective
      treatment for cervical cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the recommended phase II dose (RP2D) and safety profile of MK-1775 (WEE1
      inhibitor MK-1775) in combination with cisplatin and radiation in patients with cervical
      cancer (phase I).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the pharmacodynamic effects of MK-1775 drugs when administered in combination
      with cisplatin and radiation (in particular, for the 15 patients treated in an expansion
      cohort at the RP2D). Pharmacodynamic biomarkers will include: phosphorylated cell division
      cycle protein 2 homolog (pCDC2), antigen Ki-67 (Ki67), gamma H2A histone family, member X
      (γH2AX), phospho-histone (pH3), and cleaved caspase-3 (CC3).

      II. To obtain preliminary information about the progression-free survival of MK-1775 in
      combination with standard radiation and chemotherapy in women with locally advanced
      high-risk cervix cancer.

      III. To determine the acute and late toxicity of MK-1775 when administered to patients with
      cervix cancer in combination with standard radiation and concurrent chemotherapy.

      IV. To correlate the serum pharmacokinetic parameters—maximum concentration (Cmax), time to
      peak concentration (Tmax), 8-hours concentration (C8), and area under the curve (AUC)
      (0-8)—with the drug concentration in the tumor tissue (for patients in the expansion
      cohort).

      OUTLINE: This is a phase I, dose-escalation study of WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775. Patients are
      assigned to 1 of 3 treatment groups.

      COHORT I: Patients receive WEE1 inhibitor MK-177 orally (PO) twice daily (BID) on days 1-2,
      8-9, 15-16, 22-23, and 29-30.

      COHORT II: Patients receive WEE1 inhibitor MK-177 PO BID on days 4-5, 11-12, 18-19, 25-26,
      and 32-33 or on days 3-5, 10-12, 17-19, 24-26, and 31-33.

      COHORT III: Patients receive WEE1 inhibitor MK-177 PO BID on days 1-5, 8-12, 15-19, 22-26,
      and 29-33.

      In all Cohorts, patients also receive cisplatin intravenously (IV) over 1 hour on days 1, 8,
      15, 22, and 29 and undergo external beam radiation therapy 5 days a week for 5 weeks
      followed by pulsed-dose rate or high-dose rate brachytherapy 5 days a week on weeks 6-8.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 4 weeks, at 3, 6, and 12
      months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>RP2D defined as the dose level with &lt; 1/6 patients with dose-limiting toxicity (DLT) as assessed by the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Clinical Trials Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Frequency and severity of adverse events will be tabulated using counts and proportions detailing frequently occurring, serious and severe events of interest. Adverse events will be summarized using all adverse events experienced, although a subanalysis may be conducted including only those adverse events in which the treating physician deems possibly, probably or definitely attributable to one or both study treatments.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety profile of MK-1775 in combination with cisplatin and radiation therapy as assessed by the NCI CTCAE version 4.0 (Phase I)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Frequency and severity of adverse events will be tabulated using counts and proportions detailing frequently occurring, serious and severe events of interest. Adverse events will be summarized using all adverse events experienced, although a subanalysis may be conducted including only those adverse events in which the treating physician deems possibly, probably or definitely attributable to one or both study treatments</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response to treatment using Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) version 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival using RECIST version 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>From the start of treatment to time to progression or death, whichever occurs first, assessed up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic (PK) parameters of MK-1775</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at 1, 2, and 6 hours between day 1 and 5</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PK parameters will be calculated by non-compartmental methods.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic effects of MK-1775</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and at day 2-5 of week 1 or 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Standard descriptive statistics, such as the mean, median, range and proportion, will be used to summarize the patient sample and to estimate parameters of interest. Ninety-five percent confidence intervals will be provided for estimates of interest where possible.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">57</enrollment>
  <condition>Stage IB Cervical Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIA Cervical Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIB Cervical Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIA Cervical Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Cervical Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I (MK-1775, cisplatin, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive WEE1 inhibitor MK-177 PO BID on days 1-2, 8-9, 15-16, 22-23, and 29-30. Patients also receive cisplatin IV over 1 hour on days 1, 8, 15, 22, and 29 and undergo external beam radiation therapy 5 days a week for 5 weeks followed by pulsed-dose rate or high-dose rate brachytherapy 5 days a week on weeks 6-8.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort II (MK-1775, cisplatin, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive WEE1 inhibitor MK-177 PO BID on days 4-5, 11-12, 18-19, 25-26, and 32-33 or on days 3-5, 10-12, 17-19, 24-26, and 31-33. Patients also receive cisplatin IV over 1 hour on days 1, 8, 15, 22, and 29 and undergo external beam radiation therapy 5 days a week for 5 weeks followed by pulsed-dose rate or high-dose rate brachytherapy 5 days a week on weeks 6-8.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort III (MK-1775, cisplatin, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive WEE1 inhibitor MK-177 PO BID on days 1-5, 8-12, 15-19, 22-26, and 29-33. Patients also receive cisplatin IV over 1 hour on days 1, 8, 15, 22, and 29 and undergo external beam radiation therapy 5 days a week for 5 weeks followed by pulsed-dose rate or high-dose rate brachytherapy 5 days a week on weeks 6-8.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I (MK-1775, cisplatin, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort II (MK-1775, cisplatin, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort III (MK-1775, cisplatin, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AZD1775</other_name>
    <other_name>MK-1775</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cisplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I (MK-1775, cisplatin, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort II (MK-1775, cisplatin, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort III (MK-1775, cisplatin, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CACP</other_name>
    <other_name>CDDP</other_name>
    <other_name>CPDD</other_name>
    <other_name>DDP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>external beam radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo external beam radiation therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I (MK-1775, cisplatin, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort II (MK-1775, cisplatin, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort III (MK-1775, cisplatin, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>EBRT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pulsed-dose rate brachytherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo pulsed-dose rate or high-dose rate brachytherapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I (MK-1775, cisplatin, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort II (MK-1775, cisplatin, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort III (MK-1775, cisplatin, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PDR brachytherapy</other_name>
    <other_name>PDR curietherapy</other_name>
    <other_name>pulsed-dose rate curietherapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I (MK-1775, cisplatin, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort III (MK-1775, cisplatin, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pharmacological studies</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I (MK-1775, cisplatin, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort II (MK-1775, cisplatin, radiation therapy)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have biopsy-proven epithelial carcinoma of the cervix, T1B-3B*, N0/1,
             M0/1** with visible or palpable disease and a decision to treat radically with
             radiotherapy and concurrent cisplatin chemotherapy (RT-CT)

               -  During the dose escalation phase of the study, high risk patients (tumor &gt; 5 cm
                  or node positive or metastatic) ONLY will be enrolled

               -  During the dose escalation phase, patients with asymptomatic metastatic disease
                  of little extent will be eligible provided they were candidates for treatment of
                  the primary tumor with radiotherapy and concurrent cisplatin chemotherapy

               -  Patients requiring radiation to the para-aortic lymph nodes are ineligible

          -  Patients must be planned to received radiotherapy to 40 Gray (Gy) or greater

          -  Patients must be able to receive weekly cisplatin

          -  No prior anticancer treatment to treat the current cervical cancer is allowed

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0 or 1 (Karnofsky &gt;=
             60%)

          -  Life expectancy of greater than 3 months

          -  Leukocytes &gt;= 3,000/mcL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1,500/mcL

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100,000/mcL

          -  Hemoglobin =&lt; 9 g/dL

               -  Blood transfusions are allowed at any time during the screening, treatment or
                  follow-up period, according to the center recommendations

          -  Prothrombin time (PT)/partial thromboplastin time (PTT)/international normalized
             ratio (INR) =&lt; 1.5 upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Total bilirubin within normal institutional limits

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST)(serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase [SGOT])/
             alanine aminotransferase (ALT)(serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT]) =&lt; 1.5 x
             institutional upper limit of normal

          -  Creatinine within normal institutional limits OR creatinine clearance &gt;= 60
             mL/min/1.73 m^2 for patients with creatinine levels above institutional normal

               -  Patients with elevated creatinine secondary to hydronephrosis may be eligible if
                  renal function returns to normality after placing an internal stent or
                  nephrostomy

          -  Patients must be able to swallow whole capsules

          -  Willingness to undergo biopsy for p53 immunohistochemistry and correlative analyses

          -  Women of child-bearing potential must agree to use two birth control methods (two
             barrier methods or a barrier method plus a hormonal method) or abstinence prior to
             study entry, for the duration of study participation prior to study entry, for the
             duration of study participation, and for 4 months after coming off study; should a
             woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while she or her partner is
             participating in this study, she should inform her treating physician immediately

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have received any anticancer treatment for their cervical cancer

          -  Patients who are receiving any other investigational agents concurrently or within 4
             weeks

          -  Patients that required radiation treatment to the para-aortic lymph nodes are
             excluded

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to MK-1775 or cisplatin

          -  Patients taking the following prescription or non-prescription drugs or other
             products (i.e. grapefruit juice) are ineligible: sensitive cytochrome P450 3A4
             (CYP3A4) substrates, CYP3A4 substrates with a narrow therapeutic index, moderate to
             potent inhibitors/inducers of CYP3A4; patients would be eligible if the medications
             can be discontinued two weeks prior to day 1 of dosing and withheld throughout the
             study until 2 weeks after the last dose of study medication

               -  As part of the enrollment/informed consent procedures, the patient will be
                  counseled on the risk of interactions with other agents, and what to do if new
                  medications need to be prescribed or if the patient is considering a new
                  over-the-counter medicine or herbal product

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, myocardial
             infarction within 6 months, congestive heart failure, symptomatic congestive heart
             failure, unstable angina pectoris, active cardiomyopathy, unstable ventricular
             arrhythmia, uncontrolled hypertension, uncontrolled psychotic disorders, serious
             infections, active peptic ulcer disease, active liver disease or cerebrovascular
             disease with previous stroke, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would
             limit compliance with study requirements

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study; breastfeeding should be discontinued if
             the mother is treated with MK-1775 and cisplatin

          -  Patients with another uncontrolled malignancy; patients with a previous malignancy,
             treated curatively and without evidence of disease relapse are eligible

          -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-positive patients on combination antiretroviral
             therapy are ineligible; appropriate studies will be undertaken in patients receiving
             combination antiretroviral therapy when indicated

          -  History of active clinically significant bleeding

          -  History of bowel obstruction or malabsorption syndromes which might limit the
             absorption of the study drug
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Helen Mackay</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Health Network-Princess Margaret Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Juravinski Cancer Centre at Hamilton Health Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L8V 5C2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Holger W. Hirte</last_name>
      <phone>905-387-9495</phone>
      <email>hal.hirte@hrcc.on.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Holger W. Hirte</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>London Regional Cancer Program</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N6A 4L6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stephen A. Welch</last_name>
      <phone>519-685-8640</phone>
      <email>stephen.welch@lhsc.on.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephen A. Welch</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Victoria Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N6K 1C2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David P. D'Souza</last_name>
      <phone>519-685-8650</phone>
      <email>david.dsouza@lhsc.on.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David P. D'Souza</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Health Network-Princess Margaret Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 2M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Helen J. Mackay</last_name>
      <phone>416-946-2253</phone>
      <email>helen.mackay@uhn.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Helen J. Mackay</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 7, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Uterine Cervical Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
