<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="168110">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01829399</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-2373</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01829399</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Control of Tourniquet Pain With an Axillary Ring of Subcutaneous Local Anesthetic</brief_title>
  <official_title>Control of Tourniquet Pain With an Axillary Ring of Subcutaneous Local Anesthetic</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Purpose:  Even with excellent regional anesthesia of the upper extremity, tourniquet (Tq)
      pain from an upper arm Tq can limit the ability to use regional anesthesia as the primary
      anesthetic for surgical procedures on the upper extremity.  The aim of this study is to
      determine whether a subcutaneous ring of local anesthetic on the inner aspect of the upper
      arm just distal to axillary crease will significantly diminish Tq pain.  If it does,
      peripheral nerve blocks distal to the Tq (i.e., nerve blocks at the elbow) could be used as
      the primary anesthetic for surgery of the hand and forearm.  These distal peripheral nerve
      blocks have fewer complications than brachial plexus blocks performed at higher levels, and,
      postoperatively, the patient has better control of his or her arm when distal nerve blocks
      are used.

      Procedures (methods):  This is a prospective, cross-over study to examine the effectiveness
      of an upper arm Subcutaneous ring of local anesthetic alone in relieving Tq pain.  This
      Subcutaneous ring of local anesthetic is often referred to as &quot;Intercostobrachial nerve
      block&quot; or &quot;Subcutaneous ring anesthesia (SRA).&quot; Twenty volunteers will be randomized into
      four groups of 5 participants each. During the initial experiment, the first group will be
      given SRA with 10-15 mL of 0.25% Bupivacaine with Epinephrine 1:200,000 on their dominant
      arm, the second group will be given SRA with 10-15 mL of 0.25% Bupivacaine with Epinephrine
      1:200,000 on their non-dominant arm, the third group will be given &quot;sham&quot; SRA with saline on
      their dominant arm, and the fourth group will be given &quot;sham&quot; SRA with saline on their
      non-dominant arm. 15 minutes after SRA, a Tq will be applied to the arm with the
      subcutaneous injection and it will be inflated to 100 mm Hg above the subject's baseline
      systolic blood pressure.  We will monitor heart rate, blood pressure (opposite arm) and pain
      (0 to 10 VAS) every 5 minutes.  Each Tq will be released when the subject requests deflation
      or when 1 hour of Tq time has elapsed, whichever occurs first.  The subject's discomfort
      level (VAS) just prior to deflation will be recorded.  Since Tq pressure alone can inhibit
      nerve function, we will monitor motor and sensory function distal to the Tq every 10 minutes
      during Tq inflation and for 30 minutes after Tq deflation.  One to two weeks after this
      initial study, the same 20 subjects will receive SRA on the same arm and the same parameters
      will be measured.  The 10 subjects who received 0.25% Bupivacaine the first time will
      receive Normal Saline, and the 10 subjects who received Normal Saline the first time will
      receive 0.25% Bupivacaine.  In this way, each subject will act as his or her own control.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time in minutes that Tq remains inflated</measure>
    <time_frame>Tq will be inflated 15 minutes after injection of local anesthetic or placebo and will remain inflated until subject can no longer tolerate. Maximum allowable Tq inflation time per session is 60 minutes.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Tq will be inflated to 100 mm Hg over subjects systolic blood pressure.  When subject finds Tq too uncomfortable, Tq will be deflated and time will be documented.  Two weeks later when the subject has the opposite injection of either placebo or local anesthetic, duration of Tq inflation will again be measured.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain score at time of Tq deflation</measure>
    <time_frame>Tq will be deflated upon subject's request. VAS assessed at time of Tq deflation for degree of discomfort prompting deflation request.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A visual analog pain score from 0 to 10 will be assessed at the time of Tq deflation.  For those subjects who request Tq deflation before 60 minutes, deflation should be requested at the same pain score.  For those subjects who tolerate Tq inflation for the full 60 minutes, there may be a difference in pain score depending on whether they received placebo injection or local anesthetic injection.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Tourniquet Pain</condition>
  <condition>Tourniquet Discomfort</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dominant arm injected with local</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A subcutaneous axillary ring of 10 to 15 mL of 0.25% Bupivacaine with epinephrine 1:200,000 will be injected in the dominant arm 15 minutes prior to tourniquet inflation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dominant arm injected with saline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A subcutaneous axillary ring of 10 to 15 mL of normal saline will be injected in the dominant arm 15 minutes prior to tourniquet inflation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-dominant arm injected with local</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A subcutaneous axillary ring of 10 to 15 mL of 0.25% Bupivacaine with epinephrine 1:200,000 will be injected in the non-dominant arm 15 minutes prior to tourniquet inflation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-dominant arm injected with saline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A subcutaneous axillary ring of 10 to 15 mL of normal saline will be injected in the non-dominant arm 15 minutes prior to tourniquet inflation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>0.25% Bupivacaine with Epinephrine 1:200,000</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Dominant arm injected with local</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Non-dominant arm injected with local</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Normal Saline</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Dominant arm injected with saline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Non-dominant arm injected with saline</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria: Volunteers will be eligible for the study if they meet     all of the
        below criteria;

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) classification I or II

          -  18 years of age to a maximum of 70 years of age

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Pre-existing parasthesia or neuropathy of any kind

          -  History of excessive alcohol consumption (&gt; three drinks per night)

          -  Take analgesics on a regular basis

          -  History of any drug abuse

          -  Baseline systolic blood pressure ≥ 150

          -  Baseline diastolic blood pressure ≥ 85

          -  BMI ≥ 30 Pregnancy Allergic reaction to local anesthetic
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Randall F Coombs, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of NC at Chapel Hill Dept. of Anesthesiology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 25, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tourniquet pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Subcutaneous axillary local anesthetic</keyword>
  <keyword>ability to tolerate tourniquet discomfort.</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Epinephrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epinephryl borate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bupivacaine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics, Local</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
