<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="132793">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01886378</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UX007-CL201</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01886378</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Open-label Phase 2 Study of UX007 (Triheptanoin) in Subjects With Long-Chain Fatty Acid Oxidation Disorders (LC-FAOD)</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label Phase 2 Study to Assess Safety and Clinical Effects of UX007 in Subjects With Long-Chain Fatty Acid Oxidation Disorders (LC-FAOD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ultragenyx Pharmaceutical Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ultragenyx Pharmaceutical Inc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      UX007-CL201 is an open-label Phase 2 study to assess the safety and clinical effects of
      UX007 in subjects with LC-FAOD. Following a 4 week run in period on current therapy,
      subjects will cross over to daily UX007 treatment for an initial 24 week treatment period,
      followed by an additional 54 week extension period. Approximately 30 subjects between 6
      months and 35 years of age inclusive with severe LC-FAOD, specifically VLCAD, LCHAD, CPT 2,
      or TFP disorders, will be enrolled and treated with UX007.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the impact of UX007 on acute clinical pathophysiology associated with LC-FAOD (following 24 weeks of treatment)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The impact of UX007 on acute clinical pathophysiology associated with LC-FAOD will be assessed by evaluating the change from baseline over 24 weeks of treatment across the following 3 relevant disease areas: (1) skeletal myopathy: exercise intolerance measured by cycle ergometry, muscle weakness and fatigue, muscle function measured by the 12 Minute Walk Test (12MWT), motor development measured by the PDMS-2, functional disability, the number and duration of major rhabdomyolysis events, and non-CK levels; (2) hepatic disease: number of symptomatic or clinically important hypoglycemia events treated at home, number and duration of major hypoglycemia events, fasting serum glucose levels, liver size by hepatic ultrasound; and (3) cardiac disease: cardiac medication required for maintenance treatment, number and duration of major cardiomyopathy events, cardiomyopathy and cardiac function as measured by ECHO and ECG, and non-acute levels of BNP and troponin.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the safety of UX007 treatment in subjects with LC-FAOD</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks and 78 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The safety of UX007 treatment will be assessed based on the incidence rate of AEs, SAEs, and clinically significant changes in physical examination findings, vital signs, clinical laboratory parameters, ECHOs, ECGs, hepatic ultrasounds.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the effect of UX007 on energy metabolism in LC-FAOD</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks and 78 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The effect of UX007 on energy metabolism will be assessed by evaluating the change from baseline over 24 weeks and 78 weeks of treatment across biomarkers of UX007 effects, PK of UX007 and UX007 metabolites, LC-FAOD related laboratory parameters, and LC-FAOD laboratory parameters.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the impact of UX007 on major clinical events associated with LC-FAOD (following 78 weeks of treatment)</measure>
    <time_frame>78 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The impact of UX007 on major clinical events will be assessed by evaluating the change from baseline over 78 weeks of treatment of the number and duration of musculoskeletal, hepatic, and cardiac disease events caused by LC-FAOD, or intercurrent illness complicated by LC-FAOD, resulting in any hospitalization, ER visit, or emergency intervention (any unscheduled administration of therapeutics at home or in the clinic).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Long-chain Fatty Acid Oxidation Disorders (LC-FAOD)</condition>
  <condition>Carnitine Palmitoyltransferase (CPT II) Deficiency</condition>
  <condition>Very Long Chain Acyl-CoA Dehydrogenase (VLCAD) Deficiency</condition>
  <condition>Longchain 3-hydroxy-acyl-CoA Dehydrogenase (LCHAD) Deficiency</condition>
  <condition>Trifunctional Protein (TFP) Deficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>UX007</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>UX007</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>UX007</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Triheptanoin</other_name>
    <other_name>C7 oil</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Confirmed diagnosis of CPT II, VLCAD, LCHAD, or TFP deficiency, based on results of
             acylcarnitine profiles, fatty acid oxidation probe studies in cultured fibroblasts,
             and/or mutation analysis obtained from medical records.

          -  Male or female, 6 months - 35 years of age

          -  Willing and able to complete all aspects of the study through the end of the study.
             If a minor, have a caregiver(s) willing and able to assist in all applicable study
             requirements.

          -  Provide written informed consent (subjects aged ≥ 18 years), or provide written
             assent (where appropriate) and have a legally authorized representative willing and
             able to provide written informed consent

          -  Willing and able to provide access to medical records charting the last 18-24 months
             of care prior to the study initiation, or from birth for those subjects less than 18
             months of age

          -  No history of serious adverse reactions or known hypersensitivity to triheptanoin

          -  Currently managed on a stable treatment regimen (including diet), which may include
             low-fat/high-carbohydrate diet, avoidance of fasting, carnitine and/or MCT oil.  The
             treatment regimen (including diet) should be stable for the last 60 days to assure
             that changes in the subject's condition are not confounded by recent changes in the
             treatment regimen that could affect the 4 week run-in evaluation period.  Once study
             drug treatment has started, must be willing to maintain all aspects of the subject's
             treatment regimen and diet unchanged, other than discontinuation of MCT oil, in order
             to avoid potential variability of response due to variations in dietary intake.

          -  Have severe LC-FAOD, as evidenced by ANY ONE of the following significant clinical
             manifestations despite therapy:

               -  Chronic Elevated CK with Major Clinical Events:  Elevated mean CK levels over
                  the last 6 months -1 year (defined as ≥ 2X upper limit of age/gender-matched
                  normal, or  ≥ 500  units/L if age-matched reference not established) not
                  associated with an acute rhabdomyolysis event, AND at least two major clinical
                  events (as defined in the protocol) in the last year, or at least four major
                  clinical events over the last two years,

               -  Episodic Elevated CK with Reported Muscle Dysfunction:  Episodes of elevated CK
                  levels over the last 6 months -1 year (defined as ≥ 2X upper limit of
                  age/gender-matched normal, or  ≥ 500  units/L if age-matched reference is not
                  established) not associated with an acute rhabdomyolysis event, AND patient
                  report of frequent muscle fatigue, exercise intolerance, or limitation of
                  exercise,

               -  Highly Elevated CK but Asymptomatic:  More seriously elevated mean CK levels
                  (defined as ≥ 4X upper limit of age/gender-matched normal, or  ≥ 1000  units/L
                  if age-matched reference is not established) consistent with substantial chronic
                  muscle rupture over the last 6 months-1 year, regardless of frequency of
                  hospitalizations or ER events,

               -  Frequent Severe Major Medical Episodes (at least 3 within the past year, or 5
                  within 2 years) of hypoglycemia, rhabdomyolysis, or exacerbation of CM,
                  requiring ER/acute care visits or hospitalizations,

               -  Severe Susceptibility to Hypoglycemia (serum glucose &lt;60 mg/dL) after short
                  periods of fasting (less than 4-12 hours, depending on age), with at least 2
                  events in the last year that require ongoing prophylactic management, OR
                  recurrent symptomatic hypoglycemia (blood glucose levels or clinical symptoms of
                  hypoglycemia) at home requiring intervention ≥ 2 times per week,

               -  Evidence of Functional Cardiomyopathy (with echocardiogram (ECHO) within past 90
                  days documenting poor EF) requiring ongoing medical management

          -  Females who have reached menarche must have a negative pregnancy test at Screening.
             If sexually active, subject must be willing to use acceptable method of contraception
             and have additional pregnancy tests during the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of CACT or CPT I

          -  Diagnosis of medium-chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase (MCAD) deficiency, short- or
             medium-chain FAOD, ketone body metabolism defect, propionic acidemia or methylmalonic
             acidemia

          -  Enrolled in a clinical study involving concurrent use of an investigational drug
             product within the last 30 days, or unwilling to discontinue use of a prohibited
             medication or other substance that may confound study objectives

          -  Unwilling to sign informed consent or release of medical records

          -  Have any co-morbid conditions, including unstable major organ-system disease(s) that
             in the opinion of the Investigator, places the subject at increased risk of
             complications, interferes with study participation or compliance, or confounds study
             objectives
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kim Mooney</last_name>
    <phone>+1-415-483-8872</phone>
    <email>kmooney@ultragenyx.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's National Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lindsay Kehoe</last_name>
      <phone>202-476-4549</phone>
      <email>lkehoe@childrensnational.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pranoot Tanpaiboon, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Southern Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33606</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Denise Casey</last_name>
      <phone>813-259-8674</phone>
      <email>dcasey1@health.usf.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amarilis Sanchez-Valle, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ann &amp; Robert H. Lurie Children's Hospital of Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clare Edano, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>312-227-6129</phone>
      <email>CEdano@LurieChildrens.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Barbara K Burton, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boston Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Vera Anastasoaie</last_name>
      <phone>617-355-7346</phone>
      <email>vera.anastasoaie@childrens.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gerard Berry, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elizabeth McCracken, MS CGC</last_name>
      <phone>412-692-5662</phone>
      <email>Elizabeth.Mccracken@chp.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gerard Vockley, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Natalie Owen</last_name>
      <phone>615-322-7602</phone>
      <email>natalie.n.owen@Vanderbilt.Edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Phillips, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Utah</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84132</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carrie Bailey</last_name>
      <phone>801-587-3605</phone>
      <email>Carrie.Bailey@hsc.utah.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nicola Longo, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>FAOD</keyword>
  <keyword>VLCAD</keyword>
  <keyword>CPT II</keyword>
  <keyword>CPT2</keyword>
  <keyword>CPT 2</keyword>
  <keyword>LCHAD</keyword>
  <keyword>UX007</keyword>
  <keyword>Triheptanoin</keyword>
  <keyword>TFP</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
