<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="146282">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01883986</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NRI 12-141</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NRI12-241</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01883986</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Supportive Care for Patients Newly Diagnosed With Lung Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Palliative Care Interventions for Outpatients With Newly Diagnosed Lung Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aims of this project are to assess the feasibility of recruiting patients and delivering
      a nurse-led telephone based palliative care intervention for patients with newly diagnosed
      lung cancer and to assess if among patients with newly diagnosed lung cancer, the
      investigators can estimate the effect of a nurse-led telephone based palliative care
      intervention on quality-of-life, symptom burden and patient satisfaction.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients meeting entry criteria will be randomized to the intervention arm, palliative care
      plus usual care or the usual care arm. Patients randomized to the intervention arm will
      receive usual oncologic care and phone calls from a nurse. Outcomes measures will be
      collected at baseline, and 3 months.

      The study will be performed at the VA Puget Sound Health Care System. The investigators will
      recruit individuals (n=40) with lung cancer over 1 year. The primary objective is to test
      the feasibility and acceptability of the intervention, and recruitment of subjects. We will
      estimate the effect of a nurse-led telephone based palliative care intervention to improve
      quality-of-life, symptom burden and patient satisfaction. In addition, using validated
      instruments, we will assess the potential effect size of the intervention on quality of
      provider communication and on clinician knowledge of patient preferences for life sustaining
      therapies. The results of this pilot study will inform a future randomized clinical trial to
      test the efficacy of the intervention on a larger scale.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Quality of Life including symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient Quality of Life including symptoms as measured by the FACT-L</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Satisfaction of Care</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient satisfaction with care will be assessed by using the FAMCARE- Patient Survey.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Clinician Communication</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The quality of clinician end-of-life communication will be measured from the patient's perspective by the Quality of Communication Questionnaire (QOC).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinician knowledge of patient preferences</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Clinician knowledge of patient preferences for life sustaining treatments will be assessed at baseline and at the study end point by asking 2 validated questions to both the clinician and the patient and determining the level of agreement between the responses.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is a 3 month nurse-led telephone based program integrating palliative care into usual oncologic care for patients diagnosed within 2 months of any type and stage of lung cancer.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects randomized to usual care will receive medical oncology, radiation oncology, pulmonary, CT surgery  as indicated by the type of cancer.  At the completion of 3 months of usual care, subjects are invited to join the intervention arm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Palliative Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Care delivered by a nurse including symptom assessment and management, patient education on lung cancer and treatment options , discussion and communication about preferences for care, psychosocial assessment including referrals to ancillary services such as social services and spiritual care as requested by the patient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients diagnosed at the Puget Sound Health Care System with a primary diagnosis of
             lung cancer, any cell type or stage, diagnosed within 8 weeks of study enrollment.

          -  Must have telephone access, ability of understand English and provide informed
             consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        -Patients not eligible to participate in the study include those who are inpatients prior
        to randomization, those who are under the care of palliative care or hospice at the time
        of randomization, those who have severe mental health disorders, those who are unable to
        speak directly with the nurse over the telephone, or those that have the inability to
        provide informed consent.

        Investigators will recruit individuals (n=40) with lung cancer over a 12 month period.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lynn F. Reinke, PhD ARNP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Puget Sound Health Care System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Puget Sound Health Care System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>palliative care</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
