<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="75718">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02124044</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>140065</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>14-CC-0065</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02124044</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety, Tolerability, and Efficacy of Asunaprevir and Daclatasvir in Subjects Coinfected With HIV-HCV</brief_title>
  <official_title>Safety, Tolerability, and Efficacy of Asunaprevir and Daclatasvir in Subjects Coinfected With HIV-HCV</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chronic hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection is a major public health problem with an estimated
      180 million people infected worldwide. In the United States an estimated 4.1 million people
      are infected and HCV is the principal cause of death from liver disease and leading
      indication for liver transplantation. Within HIV/HCV co-infected patients, liver disease due
      to Hepatitis C progresses even more rapidly. While combination of ribavirin (RBV) and
      pegylated interferon (PEG) in combination with boceprevir/telaprevir is the currently
      recommended therapy for chronic HCV infection and has superior cure rates compared to
      PEG+RBV alone in HCV monoinfected patients, treatment is still associated with a high
      incidence of adverse events (AEs), discontinuations and poor cure rates in several
      populations. Within the HIV/HCV co-infected population treatment for HCV remains complicated
      given drug interactions between anti-retrovirals and HCV protease inhibitors, in addition to
      the extensive side-effects due to PEG +RBV alone. Recent studies have demonstrated that the
      use of a combination of anti-virals which target HCV without interferon (IFN) can cure HCV,
      without additional toxicities. These novel therapies that do not rely on an IFN backbone may
      additionally enhance cure rates in HIV/HCV co-infected, a population which has historically
      been difficult to cure.

      This is an open label study to assess the safety, tolerability and efficacy of asunaprevir
      (ASV) 100 mg BID and daclatasvir (DCV) 60 mg daily (selective HCV NS3 and NS5A inhibitors
      respectively) in 20 HIV/HCV co-infected treatment-na(SqrRoot) ve and treatment experienced
      HCV genotype 1b individuals.

      The findings from this study will aid in the understanding of antiviral and host responses
      and determinants of response to an IFN free regimen in HIV/HCV co-infected patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection is a major public health problem with an estimated
      180 million people infected worldwide. In the United States an estimated 4.1 million people
      are infected and HCV is the principal cause of death from liver disease and leading
      indication for liver transplantation. Within HIV/HCV co-infected patients, liver disease due
      to Hepatitis C progresses even more rapidly. While combination of ribavirin (RBV) and
      pegylated interferon (PEG) in combination with boceprevir/telaprevir is the currently
      recommended therapy for chronic HCV infection and has superior cure rates compared to
      PEG+RBV alone in HCV monoinfected patients, treatment is still associated with a high
      incidence of adverse events (AEs), discontinuations and poor cure rates in several
      populations. Within the HIV/HCV co-infected population treatment for HCV remains complicated
      given drug interactions between anti-retrovirals and HCV protease inhibitors, in addition to
      the extensive side-effects due to PEG +RBV alone. Recent studies have demonstrated that the
      use of a combination of anti-virals which target HCV without interferon (IFN) can cure HCV,
      without additional toxicities. These novel therapies that do not rely on an IFN backbone may
      additionally enhance cure rates in HIV/HCV co-infected, a population which has historically
      been difficult to cure.

      This is an open label study to assess the safety, tolerability and efficacy of asunaprevir
      (ASV) 100 mg BID and daclatasvir (DCV) 60 mg daily (selective HCV NS3 and NS5A inhibitors
      respectively) in 20 HIV/HCV co-infected treatment-na(SqrRoot) ve and treatment experienced
      HCV genotype 1b individuals.

      The findings from this study will aid in the understanding of antiviral and host responses
      and determinants of response to an IFN free regimen in HIV/HCV co-infected patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of grade 3 and 4 adverse events (AEs) following 24 weeks of treatment with ASV and DCV in HIV-HCV coinfected subjects and the proportion of subjects who achieve SVR12 (serum HCV RNA &amp; lt; LOD 12 weeks after completion of treatm...</measure>
    <time_frame>36 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV-HCV</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Asunaprevir and Dalatasvir</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA

        Subjects who meet the following criteria are eligible to enter the study:

          1. Eighteen years of age or older at screening

          2. Na(SqrRoot) ve to treatment for hepatitis C or treatment experienced on previous
             IFN-containing treatment for chronic HCV infection. Patients who have been
             re-infected with HCV are excluded.

          3. Women are allowed to participate if they agree to always use at least two forms of
             birth control. One form must be barrier protection (i.e., condom or female condom)
             and the other is to meet one of the criteria below:

               1. Non-childbearing potential status (i.e., physiologically incapable of becoming
                  pregnant)

                  - Has had a hysterectomy or

                  - Has had a bilateral oophorectomy or

                  - Is post-menopausal (age greater than or equal to 50 and a demonstration of a
                  total cessation of menses for greater than or equal to 1 year) or

                  - Has had a bilateral tubal ligation or fallopian tube inserts

               2. Childbearing potential status   women must have a negative serum pregnancy test
                  at screening and agree to use an acceptable form of birth control, such as any
                  of the following:

                  - Complete abstinence from sexual intercourse 2 weeks prior to administration of
                  the study drug until completion of the follow-up procedures and at least 5 weeks
                  (women) after the last dose of the study drugs.

                  - Vasectomized partner in reliably monogamous relationship.

                    -  An intrauterine device (IUD) 2 weeks prior to administration of the study
                       drugs continuously until completion of the follow-up procedures and at
                       least 5 weeks after the last dose of the study drugs.

                    -  Double contraceptive method (condom or occlusive cap [diaphragm or
                       cervical/vault caps]; spermicidal foam/gel/film/cream/suppository).

                    -  Oral, implantable, transdermal, or injectable or any other form of hormonal
                       contraceptives are NOT an acceptable form of contraception for females on
                       this study.

          4. Men are allowed to participate if they agree to use at least 2 forms of birth
             control. One form must be barrier protection (i.e., condom or female condom) and the
             other is to meet one of the criteria below:

               1. Are sterile or

               2. Agree to use at least one of the following approved methods of contraception 2
                  weeks prior to administration of the study drug until the completion of the
                  followup procedures and at least 14 weeks after the last dose of the study
                  drugs:

                    -  A male condom with spermicide.

                    -  A sterile sexual partner.

                    -  A female sexual partner who has an IUD.

                    -  A female sexual partner using a female condom with spermicide, intravaginal
                       system (e.g., NuvaRing[registered]), diaphragm with spermicide, cervical
                       cap with spermicide, or oral, implantable, transdermal, or injectable
                       contraceptives.

          5. Chronic GT1b infection as documented by one or more measurements of serum HCV RNA
             greater than or equal to 2,000 IU/mL during screening and at least one of the
             following:

               1. A positive anti-HCV antibody, HCV RNA, or HCV genotype test result greater than
                  or equal to 12 months prior to the baseline (Day 0) visit together with current
                  positive HCV RNA or anti-HCV antibody test results.

        Or

        b. Positive HCV RNA test and anti-HCV antibody test results together with a liver biopsy
        consistent with chronic HCV infection or a liver biopsy performed before Day 0 with
        evidence of chronic hepatitis C infection disease, such as the presence of fibrosis.

        6. HIV treatment status:

          1. Documented HIV infection (defined by positive Western blot result or detectable HIV
             viral load), ARV untreated for &gt; 8 weeks preceding dosing and having either:

               1. A CD4 T-cell count greater than or equal to 500 cells/mm3 within 8 weeks of Day
                  0 or

               2. An HIV viral load less than 500 copies/mL with a stable CD4 count for at least 3
                  months

          2. Documented HIV (defined by positive western blot result or detectable HIV viral load)
             infection on a stable protocol-approved, ARV regimen for greater than or equal to 4
             weeks prior to dosing and is expected to continue the current ARV regimen through the
             end of study with all of the following

               1. a CD4 T-cell count &gt;  100 cells/mm3

               2. a documented plasma HIV-1 RNA level less than the level of detection measured at
                  least twice in the 4 weeks preceding dosing. If the lower limit of detection of
                  the local HIV-1 RNA result is &gt; 50 copies/mL (e.g., &lt; 70 copies/mL, the
                  screening plasma HIV-1 RNA level cannot exceed 50 copies/mL).

               3. HIV ARV agents including only:

        a. Raltegrativir plus one of the following

        b. Tenofovir and emtricitabine or abacavir and lamivudine

        7. Documentation of hepatitis C genotype 1b alone infection within 6 months prior to Day
        0.

        8. Liver biopsy obtained within 36 calendar months prior to the baseline (Day 0) visit to
        verify the presence or absence of cirrhosis, except as indicated below. If no recent (&lt; 24
        months) liver biopsy is available, a liver biopsy may be performed prior to the baseline
        visit.

          1. Cirrhosis is defined as any one of the following:

               1. Any biopsy showing cirrhosis.

               2. A FibroSUR[trademark] score, of &gt; 0.75 and an aspartate aminotransferase (AST)
                  platelet ratio index (APRI) of &gt; 2 within the last year.

          2. Absence of cirrhosis is defined as any one of the following:

               1. A liver biopsy performed within 36 calendar months of screening showing absence
                  of cirrhosis.

               2. A FibroSUR[trademark] score, within the last year, of &lt; 0.48 and an APRI of &lt; 1.

                  In the absence of a definitive diagnosis of presence or absence of cirrhosis by
                  the criteria detailed above, a liver biopsy is required. The
                  FibroSURE[trademark]test can be performed and the results can be used to
                  determine the inclusion and exclusion criteria. Patients with Child Pugh B or C
                  cirrhotics are excluded

             9. Ability to communicate effectively with the study investigator and other key
             personnel.

             10. Willingness to comply with the study restrictions and requirements.

             11. Opioid-dependent individuals must be participating in a supervised treatment
             program.

             12. Subjects must have an external primary care doctor (outside of the Clinical
             Center and the NIH) for their medical management.

             13. Willingness to have blood or tissue samples stored for future use to study liver
             disease and immune function.

             14. Willingness to undergo HLA typing.

             15. Otherwise healthy status as determined by medical history, physical examination,
             electrocardiogram (ECG), and clinical laboratory measurements performed at screening.

        Contraception

        The effects of ASV and DCV on the developing human fetus are unknown. For this reason, men
        and women of childbearing potential must agree to use adequate contraception as outlined
        in the inclusion and exclusion criteria prior to study entry and until 5 weeks (women )
        and 14 weeks (men) after last dose of study medication. Hormonal contraception is NOT
        considered an effective form of birth control for female subjects on this study. Oral
        contraceptives are not as effective in women taking ASV and DCV so women cannot rely on
        this form of birth control to prevent pregnancy. Females of childbearing-age must have a
        negative pregnancy test result prior to receiving ASV and DCV. If a woman becomes pregnant
        or suspects of being pregnant during the course of the study, she should inform the study
        staff and her primary care physician immediately.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA

          1. Current or prior history of any of the following:

               1. Clinically significant illness (other than HCV) or any other major medical
                  disorder that may interfere with the subject treatment, assessment of compliance
                  with the protocol; subjects currently under evaluation for a
                  clinically-significant illness (other than HCV) are also excluded

               2. Gastrointestinal disorder with post-operative condition that could interfere
                  with the absorption of the study drug

               3. Poor venous access interfering with required study blood collection

               4. Clinical hepatic decompensation (i.e.,-ascites, encephalopathy or variceal
                  hemorrhage)

               5. Solid organ transplantation

               6. Significant pulmonary disease, significant cardiac disease or porphyria.

               7. Unstable psychiatric disease (subjects with psychiatric illness that is well
                  controlled on a stable treatment regimen or currently not requiring medication
                  may be included)

               8. Any malignancy or its treatment that in the opinion of the PI may cause ongoing
                  interference with host immunity; subjects under evaluation for malignancy are
                  not eligible

               9. Significant drug allergy (such as anaphylaxis or hepatotoxicity)

              10. Chronic liver disease of a non-HCV etiology (e.g., hemochromatosis, Wilson   s
                  disease, alfa-1 antitrypsin deficiency, cholangitis)

          2. Positive test results at screening for hepatitis B virus (HBV) surface antigen
             (HBsAg) or HBV RNA (completed only if necessary to rule out chronic HBV)

          3. Current use of non-protocol approved ARVs

          4. A new AIDS-defining condition diagnosed within 30 days prior to date screening
             consent is signed or active serious infection (other than HIV and HCV), requiring
             parenteral antibiotics, antivirals or antifungals within 30 days prior to Day 0

          5. Abnormal hematological and biochemical parameters at screening, including:

               1. Neutrophil count &lt; 750 cells/mm3

               2. Hemoglobin level &lt; 9 g/dL

               3. Platelet count less than or equal to 50,000 cells/mm3

               4. Estimated glomerular filtration rate, calculated by the chronic kidney disease
                  epidemiology collaboration formula: &lt; 50 mL/min/1.73 m2

               5. ALT or AST level greater than or equal to10 times upper limit of normal (ULN)

               6. Serum lipase level greater than or equal to 1.5 times ULN at screening or during
                  the screening period

               7. Total bilirubin level greater than or equal to 2.0 times ULN, except in subjects
                  with Gilbert   s syndrome

               8. Albumin level less than or equal to 3.0 g/dL

          6. Donation or loss of blood of &gt; 400 mL within 8 weeks prior to the first dose of the
             study drugs

          7. Poorly controlled diabetes as indicated by a screening glycosylated hemoglobin
             (HbA1c) &gt; 10

          8. Known hypersensitivity to ASV, DCV or formulation excipients

          9. Pregnant or breastfeeding

         10. Screening or baseline with clinically significant ECG findings, or personal/first
             degree relative history of Torsade de pointes

         11. Need for the use of the following medications from 21 days prior to the start of
             study drugs through the end of treatment:

               1. Hematologic stimulating agents, erythropoiesis stimulating agents (ESAs),
                  granulocyte colony stimulating factor (GCSF), thrombopoeitin (TPO) mimetics

               2. Chronic systemic antineoplastic or immunomodulatory treatment including
                  supraphysiologic doses of immunosuppressants such as corticosteroids (e.g.,
                  prednisone equivalent &gt; 10 mg/day for &gt; 2 weeks), azathioprine or monoclonal
                  antibodies (e.g., infliximab)

               3. Investigational agents or devices for any indication

         12. Previous treatment with an HCV protease inhibitor or any drugs not approved by the
             Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for the treatment of hepatitis C

         13. Medications for disease conditions excluded from the protocol (e.g., active cancer,
             transplantation) are not listed under the Concomitant medication section, and are
             disallowed from the study

         14. Concomitant use of certain medications and herbal/natural supplements per PI
             discretion, expected to result in increases or decreases in exposure to study or
             non-study medications

         15. Co-enrollment Guidelines: Co-enrollment in other clinical trials is restricted, other
             than enrollment in observational studies or those evaluating the use of a licensed
             medication. Study staff should be notified of co-enrollment status, as it may require
             prior approval of the investigator
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Henry Masur, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Julia B Purdy, C.R.N.P.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-9109</phone>
    <email>purdyj@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Henry Masur, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-9320</phone>
    <email>hmasur@cc.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Family Medical and Conseling Services</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington, DC</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20020</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Unity Health Care, Inc./DC General</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington, DC</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20002</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2014-CC-0065.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Armstrong GL, Wasley A, Simard EP, McQuillan GM, Kuhnert WL, Alter MJ. The prevalence of hepatitis C virus infection in the United States, 1999 through 2002. Ann Intern Med. 2006 May 16;144(10):705-14. Summary for patients in: Ann Intern Med. 2006 May 16;144(10):I20.</citation>
    <PMID>16702586</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 25, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Coinfection</keyword>
  <keyword>HCV Genotype 1b</keyword>
  <keyword>Interferon Free therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Liver Biopsy</keyword>
  <keyword>Virological Response</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
