<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="147853">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01722487</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PCYC-1115-CA</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-003967-23</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01722487</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Multicenter, Open-label, Phase 3 Study of the Bruton's Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor PCI-32765 Versus Chlorambucil in Patients 65 Years or Older With Treatment-naive Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia or Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma (RESONATE™-2)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Multicenter, Open-label, Phase 3 Study of the Bruton's Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor PCI-32765 Versus Chlorambucil in Patients 65 Years or Older With Treatment-naive Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia or Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma (RESONATE™-2)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pharmacyclics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pharmacyclics</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Australia: Department of Health and Ageing Therapeutic Goods Administration</authority>
    <authority>Belgium: Federal Agency for Medicinal Products and Health Products</authority>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <authority>China: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Czech Republic: State Institute for Drug Control</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <authority>Ireland: Irish Medicines Board</authority>
    <authority>Israel: Israeli Health Ministry Pharmaceutical Administration</authority>
    <authority>Italy: The Italian Medicines Agency</authority>
    <authority>New Zealand: Food Safety Authority</authority>
    <authority>Poland: Office for Registration of Medicinal Products, Medical Devices and Biocidal Products</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Agencia Española de Medicamentos y Productos Sanitarios</authority>
    <authority>Turkey: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <authority>Ukraine: State Pharmacological Center - Ministry of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A Randomized, Multicenter, Open-label, Phase 3 Study of the Bruton's Tyrosine Kinase
      Inhibitor PCI-32765 versus Chlorambucil in Patients 65 Years or Older with Treatment-naive
      Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia or Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study design: This is a randomized, multicenter, open-label, Phase 3 study designed to
      compare the safety and efficacy of PCI-32765 versus chlorambucil in treatment-naive patients
      65 years or older who have CLL or SLL.

      Eligible patients will be randomized in a 1:1 ratio to Treatment Arm A or B:

        -  Treatment Arm A:  Oral chlorambucil 0.5 mg/kg on Days 1 and 15 of each 28-day cycle;
           the dose can be increased, if well tolerated, in increments of 0.1 mg/kg on Day 1 of
           each cycle to a maximum of 0.8 mg/kg; patients receive a minimum of 3 and a maximum of
           12 cycles, in the absence of progressive disease or unacceptable toxicity

        -  Treatment Arm B:  Oral PCI-32765 420 mg/day Randomization will be stratified on Eastern
           Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status (0,1 versus 2); presence of
           advanced Rai stage (yes/no), advanced being defined as Stages 3-4; and geographic
           region:  US versus non-US.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary endpoint of this study is PFS as assessed by IRC review according to IWCLL 2008 criteria with modification for treatment-related lymphocytosis</measure>
    <time_frame>All enrolled patients have  completed at least 12 months of treatment and/or follow-up and either (a) 81 progression or death events have been observed or (b) 15 months have elapsed after the last patient is randomized, whichever occurs first.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessment of response should include physical examination, radiographic imaging, and evaluation of blood and marrow (if applicable).  Patients who withdraw from the study or are considered lost to follow-up without prior documentation of disease progression will be censored on the date of the last adequate disease assessment.  Patients who start new anticancer therapy before documentation of disease progression will be censored on the date of the last adequate disease assessment that is on or before the start date of the new anticancer therapy.  For patients without an adequate post-baseline disease assessment, PFS will be censored on the date of randomization.  Patients who have 2 or more consecutive missing disease assessments immediately before PD or death will be censored for analysis of PFS at the time of last adequate disease assessment.  The adequate disease assessment is defined as physical examination and CBC, or CBC and CT scan.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To measure Efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Secondary endpoints will be collected for 12 months of treatment and/or follow-up and either (a) 81 progression or death events have been observed or (b) 15 months have elapsed after the last patient is randomized whichever occurs first.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Efficacy ORR defined as the proportion of patients who achieve CR, CR with incomplete bone marrow recovery (CRi), nodular partial response (nPR), or partial response (PR) per IWCLL 2008 criteria over the course of the study as assessed by the IRC. OS Rate of MRD-negative CRs, Change from baseline FACiT-Fatigue score, Rate of hematological improvement in patients with baseline anemia and thrombocytopenia defined by hemoglobin &gt; 11 g/dL or increase ≥ 50% over baseline or platelet count &gt; 100,000/mm3, respectively.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>Secondary endpoints will be collected for 12 months of treatment and/or follow-up and either (a) 81 progression or death events have been observed or (b) 15 months have elapsed after the last patient is randomized whichever occurs first.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety Incidence of adverse events (AEs) and changes in laboratory variables, vital signs, and ECG. In addition, Event-Free Survival (EFS), will be included as a secondary endpoint in response to European Medicines Agency (EMA) recommendation, where progressive disease (PD), death, and non response at 3 months are defined as events.  Non-response is defined as patients who do not have CR, CRi, nPR, PR, or PR with lymphocytosis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate and compare the treatment groups in terms rate of hematological improvement, changes in disease related symptoms, patient reported outcomes, PK characteristics, medical resource utilization and potential predictive biomarkers.</measure>
    <time_frame>Exploratory endpoints will be collected for 12 months of treatment and/or follow-up and either (a) 81 progression or death events have been observed or (b) 15 months have elapsed after the last patient is randomized whichever occurs first.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Rate of hematological improvement in patients with baseline neutropenia, Changes in disease-related symptoms.Changes and differences in PRO measures EORTC QLQ-30 &amp; EQ-5D-5L. The efficacy criteria for the EQ-5D-5L will be the change in weighted utility score from baseline to each assessment, Time to treatment failure, Change in immunoglobulin levels from baseline, Medical resource utilization (MRU) associated with therapy including the number of hospitalizations, emergency department visits, blood product transfusions, and use of hematopoietic growth factors.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate and compare the treatment groups in terms rate of hematological improvement, changes in disease related symptoms, patient reported outcomes, PK characteristics, medical resource utilization and potential predictive biomarkers.</measure>
    <time_frame>Exploratory endpoints will be collected for 12 months of treatment and/or follow-up and either (a) 81 progression or death events have been observed or (b) 15 months have elapsed after the last patient is randomized whichever occurs first.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PK characteristics of PCI-32765 in patients with CLL/SLL and determination of which, if any, covariates (ie, age, gender, body size, race) influence exposure to ibrutinib, Response based on predictive biomarkers.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate and compare the treatment groups in terms rate of hematological improvement, changes in disease related symptoms, patient reported outcomes, PK characteristics, medical resource utilization and potential predictive biomarkers.</measure>
    <time_frame>Exploratory endpoints will be collected for 12 months of treatment and/or follow-up and either (a) 81 progression or death events have been observed or (b) 15 months have elapsed after the last patient is randomized whichever occurs first.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of patients with elevated TSH compared to a normal baseline value Percentage of patients with low free T4 compared to a normal baseline value</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">272</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PCI-32765</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PCI-32765 will be supplied as hard gelatin 140-mg capsules for oral (PO) administration.PCI-32765 420 mg (3 x 140-mg capsules) is administered orally once daily.  The first dose will be delivered in the clinic on Day 1, after which subsequent dosing is typically on an outpatient basis.  PCI-32765 will be dispensed to patients in bottles at each visit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Chlorambucil</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Chlorambucil will be supplied as 2-mg tablets for PO administration.Chlorambucil is administered orally on Days 1 and 15 of each 28-day cycle.The starting dosage (Cycle 1) is 0.5 mg/kg.  If well tolerated, the chlorambucil dose can be increased starting at Cycle 2, with increments of 0.1 mg/kg on Day 1 of each cycle to a maximum of 0.8 mg/kg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PCI-32765</intervention_name>
    <description>PCI-32765 will be supplied as hard gelatin 140-mg capsules for oral (PO) administration.PCI-32765 420 mg (3 x 140-mg capsules) is administered orally once daily.  The first dose will be delivered in the clinic on Day 1, after which subsequent dosing is typically on an outpatient basis.  PCI-32765 will be dispensed to patients in bottles at each visit.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PCI-32765</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chlorambucil</intervention_name>
    <description>Chlorambucil will be supplied as 2-mg tablets for PO administration.Chlorambucil is administered orally on Days 1 and 15 of each 28-day cycle.  The starting dosage (Cycle 1) is 0.5 mg/kg.  If well tolerated, the chlorambucil dose can be increased starting at Cycle 2, with increments of 0.1 mg/kg on Day 1 of each cycle to a maximum of 0.8 mg/kg.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chlorambucil</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Males or females of 65 years of age or greater.  Patients between the ages of 65 and
             70 years of age must have 1 or more of the following comorbidities that may preclude
             the use of frontline chemo-immunotherapy with fludarabine, cyclophosphamide, or
             rituximab:

               -  creatinine clearance &lt; 70 mL/min using the Cockcroft-Gault equation

               -  platelet count &lt; 100,000/μL or hemoglobin &lt; 10 g/dL

               -  clinically apparent autoimmune cytopenia (autoimmune hemolytic anemia or immune
                  thrombocytopenia)

               -  ECOG performance score = 1 or 2

          2. Diagnosis of CLL/SLL that meets IWCLL diagnostic criteria (Hallek 2008)

          3. Active disease meeting at least 1 of the following IWCLL criteria (Hallek 2008) for
             requiring treatment:

               -  Evidence of progressive marrow failure as manifested by the development of, or
                  worsening of, anemia and/or thrombocytopenia Massive, progressive, or
                  symptomatic splenomegaly

               -  Massive nodes or progressive or symptomatic lymphadenopathy

               -  Progressive lymphocytosis

               -  Autoimmune hemolytic anemia and/or immune thrombocytopenia that is poorly
                  responsive to corticosteroids or standard therapy

               -  Constitutional symptoms

          4. Measurable nodal disease by computed tomography (CT)

          5. ECOG performance status of 0-2

          6. Life expectancy &gt; 4 months from randomization

          7. Adequate hematologic function, defined as absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1,000/μL
             (independent of growth factor support for at least 7 days prior to screening) and
             platelet count ≥ 50,000/μL (independent of transfusion and growth factor support for
             at least 7 days prior to screening)

          8. Adequate hepatic function, defined as serum aspartate transaminase (AST) and alanine
             transaminase (ALT) &lt; 2.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN), and total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x
             ULN

          9. Adequate renal function, defined as estimated creatinine clearance ≥ 30 mL/min using
             the Cockcroft-Gault equation

         10. Willingness to receive all outpatient treatment, all laboratory monitoring, and all
             radiological evaluations at the institution that administers study drug for the
             entire study

         11. Willingness of male patients, if sexually active with a female of childbearing
             potential, to use an effective barrier method of contraception during the study and
             for 3 months following the last dose of study drug

         12. Ability to provide written informed consent and to understand and comply with the
             requirements of the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Known involvement of the central nervous system by lymphoma or leukemia

          2. History or current evidence of Richter's transformation or prolymphocytic leukemia

          3. Documentation of deletion of the short arm of chromosome 17: del(17p13.1) in more
             than 20% of cells examined on any pretreatment fluorescence in situ hybridization
             (FISH) or cytogenetic evaluation

          4. Uncontrolled autoimmune hemolytic anemia or idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura

          5. Any previous treatment (chemotherapy, radiotherapy, and/or monoclonal antibodies)
             intended specifically to treat CLL/SLL

          6. Received any immunotherapy, vaccine, or investigational drug within 4 weeks prior to
             randomization

          7. Corticosteroid use within 1 week prior to first dose of study drug, with the
             exception of inhaled, topical, or other local administrations.  Patients requiring
             systemic steroids at daily doses &gt; 20 mg prednisone (or corticosteroid equivalent,
             see Appendix N), or those who are administered steroids for leukemia control or white
             blood cell (WBC)-count-lowering are excluded.

          8. Major surgery within 4 weeks prior to randomization

          9. History of prior malignancy, with the exception of the following:

               -  malignancy treated with curative intent and with no evidence of active disease
                  present for more than 3 years prior to screening and felt to be at low risk for
                  recurrence by treating physician

               -  adequately treated nonmelanomatous skin cancer or lentigo maligna melanoma
                  without current evidence of disease

               -  adequately treated cervical carcinoma in situ without current evidence of
                  disease

         10. Currently active, clinically significant cardiovascular disease or a history of
             myocardial infarction within 6 months prior to randomization

         11. Inability to swallow capsules or tablets, or disease significantly affecting
             gastrointestinal function

         12. Uncontrolled active systemic fungal, bacterial, viral, or other infection or
             requirement for intravenous (IV) antibiotics

         13. Known history of infection with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)

         14. Serologic status reflecting active hepatitis B or C infection

         15. History of stroke or intracranial hemorrhage within 6 months prior to enrollment

         16. Current life-threatening illness, medical condition, or organ-system dysfunction that
             could compromise patient safety or put the study at risk

         17. Requirement for anticoagulation with warfarin

         18. Requirement for treatment with a strong CYP3A4/5 and/or CYP2D6 inhibitor
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lori Styles, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Pharmacyclics</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>China</country>
    <country>Czech Republic</country>
    <country>Ireland</country>
    <country>Israel</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>New Zealand</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>Turkey</country>
    <country>Ukraine</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.pharmacyclics.com</url>
    <description>www.pharmacyclics.com</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 29, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CLL, SLL</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Chlorambucil</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
