<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="99231">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02026258</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IE-12-047-2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02026258</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficiency of Piezotome-Corticision Assisted Orthodontics</brief_title>
  <official_title>Efficiency of Piezotome-Corticision Assisted Orthodontics in Alleviating Mandibular Anterior Crowding - A Randomized Controlled Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Connecticut Health Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Connecticut Health Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to evaluate the hypothesis that a piezotome-corticision procedure
      will have a transient acceleratory effect on the rate of tooth alignment and the overall
      treatment time. In addition, the subjects in the piezotome-corticision orthodontics group
      will experience a different level of pain, comfort, and satisfaction as opposed to the
      conventional orthodontics group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will specifically try:

        1. To compare the time required to achieve complete alignment of crowded mandibular
           anterior teeth (canine to canine) between piezotome-corticision assisted and
           conventional orthodontics.

        2. To investigate the rate of alignment of mandibular anterior teeth at different time
           points until complete alignment is achieved using dental casts taken at every visit.

        3. To compare subject's perception of pain, comfort and satisfaction between the
           piezotome-corticision assisted and conventional orthodontics using two questionnaires.

      Eligibility criteria includes:

        -  Adult patients 18 or older

        -  Single arch or double arch treatment

        -  Non-extraction treatment in the mandibular arch

        -  Presence of full complement dentition from first molar to first molar

        -  No spaces in the mandibular arch

        -  Mandibular anterior irregularity index greater than 5

        -  Patient with healthy periodontium and attachment loss of up to 2mm

        -  The amount of crowding should allow for bracket placement

        -  No therapeutic intervention planned involving intermaxillary or other intraoral or
           extraoral appliances including elastics, lip bumpers, maxillary expansion appliances,
           or headgear prior to the complete alignment of mandibular anterior teeth.

      Exclusion criteria includes:

        -  Failure to provide oral and written consent to participation

        -  Medical problems that affect tooth movement (Refer to Appendix I)

        -  Presence of primary teeth in the mandibular anterior area

        -  Missing permanent mandibular anterior teeth

        -  Inability to place brackets in the anterior mandibular teeth

        -  Breakage of any of the mandibular anterior brackets that have not been replaced within
           a week

      Outcome measures

        1. Two outcome assessors will be  calibrated in the assessment of the Little's
           irregularity index. The irregularity index will be measured twice by two blinded
           outcome assessors using a fine-tip digital caliper.

        2. The subjects will be instructed to record their level of pain: immediately, 1 hour, 12
           hours, and 7 days after the first wire placement [76, 82]. They will be also asked to
           report if they had taken any pain medications, their level of ease and satisfaction
           with the procedure, if they would undergo this procedure again, and if they would
           recommend it to a friend. A 100 mm Visual Analog Scale (VAS) will be used to evaluate
           the level of pain, ease, and satisfaction of all the subjects, with anchors at each end
           of the line that read &quot;no pain (easy, satisfied)&quot; (0 mm) and &quot;most pain (complicated,
           not satisfied)&quot; (100 mm).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Little's irregularity index of mandibular anterior teeth</measure>
    <time_frame>From the placement of the first wire to complete alignment of mandibular anteiror teeth, assessed up to 9 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Questionnaires involving pain level</measure>
    <time_frame>One week after wire placement and one month after wire placement</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Specific questions in the questionnaire include:
How much pain/discomfort did you have at the following time points?
Did you take any type of pain medication after your treatment? If yes, when? Indicate which one of the following pain killers?
Salicylate NSAIDs (Example: Aspirin, Diflunisal, etc.)
Propionic NSAIDs (Example: Ibuprofen/Motrin/Advil, Naproxen, etc.)
Aniline analgesic (Example: Acetaminophen/Tylenol)
Opioids (Example: Codeine, Hydrocodone, Morphine, etc.)
Combination drugs (Example: Vicodin/Acetaminophen and Hydrocodone)
Other
If other, please write the name of the medication below:
2.  Are you satisfied with your treatment? 3.  How easy was the procedure to you? 4.  Would you undergo this procedure again? 5. Would you recommend this procedure to a friend?</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Mandibular Anterior Crowding</condition>
  <condition>Piezocision</condition>
  <condition>Pain Perception</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Orthodontics no piezocision</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will have orthodontic treatment without corticision with piezotome. Subjects will be followed every 4-5 weeks after the first wire placement until full alignment of the lower arch (irregularity index 0-1mm). The archwire sequence will be 0.014-in Cu-NiTi wire for the first two visits followed by a 0.014 X 0.025-in Cu-NiTi wire until completion of alignment. The time taken to reach complete alignment for each patient and the rate of tooth alignment will be calculated.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Orthodontics with piezotome corticision</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects receiving orthodontic treatment in conjunction with piezotome-corticision. Subjects will be followed every 4-5 weeks after the first wire placement until full alignment of the lower arch (irregularity index 0-1mm). The archwire sequence will be 0.014-in Cu-NiTi wire for the first two visits followed by a 0.014 X 0.025-in Cu-NiTi wire until completion of alignment. The time taken to reach complete alignment for each patient and the rate of tooth alignment will be calculated.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Piezotome-Corticision</intervention_name>
    <description>Local anesthetic will be administered to the labial sulcus of the mandibular incisors. A scalpel will be used to make three vertical incisions through the gingiva, 4mm below the interdental papilla, interproximally between mandibular canines and lateral incisors, and central incisors on the labial aspect of the mandible. The incisions will be 4mm in length. A piezosurgery knife will be used to create the cortical alveolar incisions to a depth of 1mm within the cortical bone. The depth of the cortical incision will be limited to 1mm for a safety margin. Postoperatively, subjects will be advised to rinse with chlorhexidine mouthwash twice a day for one week and take acetaminophen as needed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Orthodontics with piezotome corticision</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Orthodontics</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will be followed every 4-5 weeks after the first wire placement until full alignment of the lower arch (irregularity index 0-1mm). The archwire sequence will be 0.014-in Cu-NiTi wire for the first two visits followed by a 0.014 X 0.025-in Cu-NiTi wire until completion of alignment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Orthodontics no piezocision</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Orthodontics with piezotome corticision</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Adult patients 18 or older

          -  Single arch or double arch treatment

          -  Non-extraction treatment in the mandibular arch

          -  Presence of full complement dentition from first molar to first molar

          -  No spaces in the mandibular arch

          -  Mandibular anterior irregularity index greater than 5

          -  Patient with healthy periodontium and attachment loss of up to 2mm

          -  The amount of crowding should allow for bracket placement

          -  No therapeutic intervention planned involving intermaxillary or other intraoral or
             extraoral appliances including elastics, lip bumpers, maxillary expansion appliances,
             or headgear prior to the complete alignment of mandibular anterior teeth.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Failure to provide oral and written consent to participation

          -  Medical problems that affect tooth movement (Refer to Appendix I)

          -  Presence of primary teeth in the mandibular anterior area

          -  Missing permanent mandibular anterior teeth

          -  Inability to place brackets in the anterior mandibular teeth

          -  Breakage of any of the mandibular anterior brackets that have not been replaced
             within a week
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Leyla Davoody, DMD</last_name>
    <phone>860 69 2550</phone>
    <email>ldavoody@gde.uchc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Orthodontic Clinic University of Connecticut</name>
      <address>
        <city>Farmington</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Flavio A Uribe, DDS, MDent Sc</last_name>
      <phone>860 679 3656</phone>
      <email>furibe@uchc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Leyla Davoody, DMD</last_name>
      <phone>860 679 2550</phone>
      <email>ldavoody@gde.uchc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Flavio A Uribe, DDS MDentSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Khalid Almas, BDS, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gameiro GH, Pereira-Neto JS, Magnani MB, Nouer DF. The influence of drugs and systemic factors on orthodontic tooth movement. J Clin Orthod. 2007 Feb;41(2):73-8; quiz 71.</citation>
    <PMID>17473406</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee WC. Experimental study of the effect of prostaglandin administration on tooth movement--with particular emphasis on the relationship to the method of PGE1 administration. Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop. 1990 Sep;98(3):231-41.</citation>
    <PMID>2403075</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Verna C, Dalstra M, Melsen B. The rate and the type of orthodontic tooth movement is influenced by bone turnover in a rat model. Eur J Orthod. 2000 Aug;22(4):343-52.</citation>
    <PMID>11029824</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yamasaki K, Shibata Y, Fukuhara T. The effect of prostaglandins on experimental tooth movement in monkeys (Macaca fuscata). J Dent Res. 1982 Dec;61(12):1444-6.</citation>
    <PMID>6960050</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liou EJ, Huang CS. Rapid canine retraction through distraction of the periodontal ligament. Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop. 1998 Oct;114(4):372-82.</citation>
    <PMID>9790320</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ren A, Lv T, Kang N, Zhao B, Chen Y, Bai D. Rapid orthodontic tooth movement aided by alveolar surgery in beagles. Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop. 2007 Feb;131(2):160.e1-10.</citation>
    <PMID>17276852</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim SJ, Park YG, Kang SG. Effects of Corticision on paradental remodeling in orthodontic tooth movement. Angle Orthod. 2009 Mar;79(2):284-91. doi: 10.2319/020308-60.1.</citation>
    <PMID>19216591</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Generson RM, Porter JM, Zell A, Stratigos GT. Combined surgical and orthodontic management of anterior open bite using corticotomy. J Oral Surg. 1978 Mar;36(3):216-9.</citation>
    <PMID>272455</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gantes B, Rathbun E, Anholm M. Effects on the periodontium following corticotomy-facilitated orthodontics. Case reports. J Periodontol. 1990 Apr;61(4):234-8.</citation>
    <PMID>2324923</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>KOLE H. Surgical operations on the alveolar ridge to correct occlusal abnormalities. Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol. 1959 May;12(5):515-29 concl.</citation>
    <PMID>13644913</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wilcko WM, Wilcko T, Bouquot JE, Ferguson DJ. Rapid orthodontics with alveolar reshaping: two case reports of decrowding. Int J Periodontics Restorative Dent. 2001 Feb;21(1):9-19.</citation>
    <PMID>11829041</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chung KR, Kim SH, Lee BS. Speedy surgical-orthodontic treatment with temporary anchorage devices as an alternative to orthognathic surgery. Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop. 2009 Jun;135(6):787-98. doi: 10.1016/j.ajodo.2007.03.036.</citation>
    <PMID>19524840</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frost HM. The regional acceleratory phenomenon: a review. Henry Ford Hosp Med J. 1983;31(1):3-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>6345475</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang L, Lee W, Lei DL, Liu YP, Yamashita DD, Yen SL. Tisssue responses in corticotomy- and osteotomy-assisted tooth movements in rats: histology and immunostaining. Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop. 2009 Dec;136(6):770.e1-11; discussion 770-1. doi: 10.1016/j.ajodo.2009.05.015.</citation>
    <PMID>19962598</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bogoch E, Gschwend N, Rahn B, Moran E, Perren S. Healing of cancellous bone osteotomy in rabbits--Part I: Regulation of bone volume and the regional acceleratory phenomenon in normal bone. J Orthop Res. 1993 Mar;11(2):285-91.</citation>
    <PMID>8483041</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wilcko MT, Wilcko WM, Pulver JJ, Bissada NF, Bouquot JE. Accelerated osteogenic orthodontics technique: a 1-stage surgically facilitated rapid orthodontic technique with alveolar augmentation. J Oral Maxillofac Surg. 2009 Oct;67(10):2149-59. doi: 10.1016/j.joms.2009.04.095.</citation>
    <PMID>19761908</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iino S, Sakoda S, Ito G, Nishimori T, Ikeda T, Miyawaki S. Acceleration of orthodontic tooth movement by alveolar corticotomy in the dog. Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop. 2007 Apr;131(4):448.e1-8.</citation>
    <PMID>17418709</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mostafa YA, Mohamed Salah Fayed M, Mehanni S, ElBokle NN, Heider AM. Comparison of corticotomy-facilitated vs standard tooth-movement techniques in dogs with miniscrews as anchor units. Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop. 2009 Oct;136(4):570-7. doi: 10.1016/j.ajodo.2007.10.052.</citation>
    <PMID>19815161</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sanjideh PA, Rossouw PE, Campbell PM, Opperman LA, Buschang PH. Tooth movements in foxhounds after one or two alveolar corticotomies. Eur J Orthod. 2010 Feb;32(1):106-13. doi: 10.1093/ejo/cjp070. Epub 2009 Sep 7.</citation>
    <PMID>19736219</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fischer TJ. Orthodontic treatment acceleration with corticotomy-assisted exposure of palatally impacted canines. Angle Orthod. 2007 May;77(3):417-20.</citation>
    <PMID>17465647</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vercellotti T, Podesta A. Orthodontic microsurgery: a new surgically guided technique for dental movement. Int J Periodontics Restorative Dent. 2007 Aug;27(4):325-31.</citation>
    <PMID>17726988</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fleming PS, DiBiase AT, Sarri G, Lee RT. Efficiency of mandibular arch alignment with 2 preadjusted edgewise appliances. Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop. 2009 May;135(5):597-602. doi: 10.1016/j.ajodo.2007.06.014.</citation>
    <PMID>19409342</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ngan P, Kess B, Wilson S. Perception of discomfort by patients undergoing orthodontic treatment. Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop. 1989 Jul;96(1):47-53.</citation>
    <PMID>2750720</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scheurer PA, Firestone AR, Bürgin WB. Perception of pain as a result of orthodontic treatment with fixed appliances. Eur J Orthod. 1996 Aug;18(4):349-57.</citation>
    <PMID>8921656</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 31, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 23, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Connecticut Health Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Flavio Uribe</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
