<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="112723">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02023866</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RP103-MITO-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02023866</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Open-Label, Dose-Escalating Study to Assess Safety, Tolerability, Efficacy, PK and PD of RP103 in Children With Inherited Mitochondrial Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>RP103-MITO-001</acronym>
  <official_title>Open-Label, Dose-Escalating Study to Assess Safety, Tolerability, Efficacy, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of Cysteamine Bitartrate Delayed-release Capsules (RP103) in Children With Inherited Mitochondrial Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Raptor Pharmaceuticals Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Raptor Pharmaceuticals Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients (male or female) with either documented genetically confirmed diagnosis of
      inherited mitochondrial diseases, who are ≥ 2 years old and &lt; 18 years, and meet other
      specified inclusion and exclusion criteria, will be included in this study.

      Patients with inherited mitochondrial diseases associated with nuclear or mitochondrial DNA
      mutations that impair the respiratory chain. These include, but are not limited to the
      following clinical syndromes: Leber's hereditary optic neuropathy; myoclonic epilepsy and
      ragged-red fibers (MERFF); mitochondrial encephalomyopathy, lactic acidosis, and stroke-like
      syndrome (MELAS); Kearn-Sayre syndrome; subacute necrotizing encephalopathy (Leigh
      Syndrome); POLG-related disorders (Alpers-Huttenlocher Syndrome, Autosomal Dominant
      Progressive External Ophthalmoplegia, Autosomal Recessive Progressive External
      Ophthalmoplegia, Childhood Myocerebrohepatopathy Spectrum Disorders, Myoclonic Epilepsy
      Myopathy Sensory Ataxia, POLG-Related Ataxia Neuropathy Spectrum Disorders); Mitochondrial
      neurogastrointestinal encephalopathy syndrome (MNGIE), also called myoneurogastrointestinal
      encephalopathy syndrome or POLIP syndrome; others, e.g., mitochondrial cardiomyopathies and
      other syndromes due to multiple mitochondrial DNA deletions.

      Screening eligibility criteria for each subject will be reviewed by participating
      Investigators and Raptor's medical officer, in an attempt An effort to ensure at least 2/3
      of the enrolled subjects have Leigh Syndrome (i.e., patients with Leigh Syndrome clinical
      presentation, genetically confirmed by known Leigh Syndrome mutations and no variants of
      uncertain significance).

      Initially, up to 32 patients will be enrolled if there is no toxicity up to the level of 1.3
      g/m2/day of RP103.  After the two interim analyses planned to occur after 12 and then 24
      subjects complete Week 24, sample size may be decreased to 24 or increased to a maximum of
      64 subjects.

      The rationale for choosing patients with inherited mitochondrial disease who are age 2 and
      older is based on available clinical data collected in previous and current RP103 studies in
      other indications, in subjects aged 2 years and older.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Newcastle Paediatric Mitochondrial Disease Scale (NPMDS) Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline vs. Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Quality of life</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change over time in Pharmacodynamic Biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>glutathione, acetoacetate, beta-hydroxybutyrate, lactate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Inherited Mitochondrial Disease, Including Leigh Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RP103</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cysteamine Bitartrate Delayed-release Capsules (RP103)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>RP103</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≥ 2 years and &lt; 18 years

          2. Body weight ≥ 5 kgs

          3. Documented (genetically confirmed known mutation, i.e. no variants of uncertain
             significance) diagnosis of inherited mitochondrial disease other than Friedreich's
             ataxia (FRDA)

          4. Moderate disease severity based on Newcastle Pediatric Mitochondrial Disease Scale
             (NPMD) score, with a score between 15 to 45 inclusive

          5. For patients regularly taking dietary supplements such as creatinine, alpha-lipoic
             acid, CoQ10, vitamin B, carnitine, etc. they have to have been taking them for at
             least 3 months pre-study and will agree to keep these the same throughout the study
             (from the Screening Visit to Study Exit)

          6. Willing to abstain from initiating dietary supplements and non-prescribed
             medications, except as allowed by the Investigator, throughout the study

          7. Willing and able to comply with study drug dosing requirements, i.e. ingest the RP103
             capsules intact, or sprinkled in liquid or soft food, or using a g-tube

          8. Sexually active female subjects of childbearing potential (i.e., not surgically
             sterile [tubal ligation, hysterectomy, or bilateral oophorectomy]) must agree to
             utilize two of the following acceptable forms of contraception throughout the study
             (from the Screening Visit to Study Exit):

               1. Hormonal contraception: birth control pills, injection, patch, vaginal ring or
                  implant;

               2. Condom or diaphragm, with spermicide;

               3. Intrauterine device (IUD)

               4. Sterile male partner (vasectomy performed at least 6 months prior to the study).

          9. Patient's legally authorized representative must provide written informed consent;
             Patient must provide assent, if required by local/institutional requirements

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Documented diagnosis of concurrent inborn errors of metabolism

          2. Non-elective hospitalization relative to mitochondrial disease or direct complication
             of disease within 60 days prior to the Screening Visit.

          3. Platelet count, lymphocyte count or hemoglobin below the lower limit of normal (LLN)
             at the Screening Visit

          4. Hepatic insufficiency with liver enzyme tests (alkaline phosphatase, AST or ALT)
             greater than 2.5 times the upper limit of normal (ULN) at the Screening Visit

          5. Bilirubin &gt; 1.2 g/dl at the Screening Visit

          6. Inability to complete the elements of the study, e.g., coma, hemodynamic instability
             or ventilator.

          7. Malabsorption requiring TPN, chronic diarrhea, bouts of pseudo obstruction

          8. Severe end-organ hypo-perfusion syndrome secondary to cardiac failure resulting in
             lactic acidosis

          9. Patients with suspected elevated intracranial pressure, pseudotumor cerebri (PTC)
             and/or papilledema

         10. Severe gastrointestinal disease including gastroparesis

         11. History of angina, myocardial infarction, or cardiac surgery within 2 years prior to
             the Screening Visit

         12. Any clinically significant ECG, including dysrhythmia, or clinically significant
             abnormal laboratory finding not already listed above at the Screening Visit

         13. History of drug or alcohol abuse

         14. History of pancreatitis

         15. Participated in an investigational drug trial within 30 days or, within 90 days for a
             biologic, device, or surgical treatment, for inherited mitochondrial diseases prior
             to the Screening Visit

         16. Known or suspected hypersensitivity to cysteamine and penicillamine

         17. Female subjects who are nursing, planning a pregnancy, known or suspected to be
             pregnant, or with a positive serum pregnancy test at the Screening Visit

         18. Patients who, in the opinion of the Investigator, are not able or willing to comply
             with the protocol
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bruce H. Cohen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Akron Children's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kenny Jones PhD, Raptor Clinical Operations</last_name>
    <phone>415-408-6283</phone>
    <email>kjones@raptorpharma.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California at San Diego (UCSD)</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard Haas, MD</last_name>
      <phone>858-822-6700</phone>
      <email>rhaas@ucsd.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Gail Reiner, FNP, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(619) 471-9134</phone>
      <email>gereiner@ucsd.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Richard Haas, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gregory Enns, MB, ChB</last_name>
      <phone>650-498-5798</phone>
      <email>greg.enns@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gregory Enns, MB, ChB</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Akron Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Akron</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bruce Cohen, MD</last_name>
      <phone>330-543-8050</phone>
      <email>bcohen@chmca.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Hilary Tonni</last_name>
      <phone>(330) 543-4734</phone>
      <email>htonni@chmca.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bruce Cohen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Fernando Scaglia, MD</last_name>
      <phone>832-822-4280</phone>
      <email>fscaglia@bcm.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Dianne X Dang, Clinical Research Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>832-822-4283</phone>
      <email>diannen@bcm.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Fernando Scaglia, MD, FACMG</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bousquet M, Gibrat C, Ouellet M, Rouillard C, Calon F, Cicchetti F. Cystamine metabolism and brain transport properties: clinical implications for neurodegenerative diseases. J Neurochem. 2010 Sep;114(6):1651-8. doi: 10.1111/j.1471-4159.2010.06874.x. Epub 2010 Aug 19.</citation>
    <PMID>20569301</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Salmi H, Leonard JV, Rahman S, Lapatto R. Plasma thiol status is altered in children with mitochondrial diseases. Scand J Clin Lab Invest. 2012 Apr;72(2):152-7. doi: 10.3109/00365513.2011.646299. Epub 2012 Jan 2.</citation>
    <PMID>22208644</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maher P, Lewerenz J, Lozano C, Torres JL. A novel approach to enhancing cellular glutathione levels. J Neurochem. 2008 Nov;107(3):690-700. doi: 10.1111/j.1471-4159.2008.05620.x. Epub 2008 Aug 12.</citation>
    <PMID>18702664</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mancuso M, Orsucci D, Logerfo A, Rocchi A, Petrozzi L, Nesti C, Galetta F, Santoro G, Murri L, Siciliano G. Oxidative stress biomarkers in mitochondrial myopathies, basally and after cysteine donor supplementation. J Neurol. 2010 May;257(5):774-81. doi: 10.1007/s00415-009-5409-7. Epub 2009 Dec 4.</citation>
    <PMID>19960200</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 16, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 17, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>subacute necrotizing encephalopathy (Leigh Syndrome);</keyword>
  <keyword>Leber's hereditary optic neuropathy;</keyword>
  <keyword>myoclonic epilepsy and ragged-red fibers (MERFF);</keyword>
  <keyword>mitochondrial encephalomyopathy, lactic acidosis, and stroke-like syndrome (MELAS);</keyword>
  <keyword>Kearn-Sayre syndrome;</keyword>
  <keyword>POLG-related disorders;</keyword>
  <keyword>Mitochondrial neurogastrointestinal encephalopathy syndrome (MNGIE)</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Leigh Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mitochondrial Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cysteamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
