<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1347">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01722500</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PBRC10042CC</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01722500</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>International Study of Childhood Obesity, Lifestyle and the Environment</brief_title>
  <acronym>ISCOLE</acronym>
  <official_title>International Study of Childhood Obesity, Lifestyle and the Environment (ISCOLE)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Coca-Cola Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary aim of the International Study of Childhood Obesity, Lifestyle and the
      Environment (ISCOLE) is to determine the relationship between lifestyle characteristics and
      obesity in a large multi-national study of 10 year-old children, and to investigate the
      influence of behavioral settings and physical, social and policy environments on the
      observed relationships within each country.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Data will be collected in 12 countries (500 children per site) from five major regions of
      the world (Eurasia &amp; Africa, Europe, Latin America, North America, and the Pacific).
      Cross-sectional evaluations will be undertaken in each country. The physical characteristics
      of the children will be directly measured in order to classify their body weight and
      adiposity status, and physical activity and dietary patterns will be measured with the most
      objective techniques currently available. A concise set of environmental measures that are
      feasible, valid and meaningful across the international settings included in this research
      will also be employed. The results of this study will provide a robust examination of the
      correlates of obesity and weight gain in children, focusing on both sides of the energy
      balance equation. The results will also provide important new information that will inform
      the development of lifestyle interventions to address childhood obesity that can be
      culturally adapted for implementation around the world.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Cross-Sectional</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Testing of Children</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>BMI, waist circumference and obesity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Testing of Children</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Physical activity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Testing of Children</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Dietary intake</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">6000</enrollment>
  <condition>Childhood Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>10 year old children</arm_group_label>
    <description>500 children with mean age 10.5 years from each of 12 countries</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        boys and girls who are approximately 10 years
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  students 10 years of age

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  has pacemaker or other internal medical devices
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>9 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>11 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter T. Katzmarzyk, PhD, FACSM</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Timothy S. Church, MD, MPH, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baton Rouge</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70808</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>School of Health Sciences at University of South Australia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Adelaide</city>
        <zip>5001</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro de Estudos do Laboratório de Aptidão Física de São Caetano do Sul (CELAFISCS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sao Paulo</city>
        <zip>09501-000</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Pediatrics, University of Ottawa</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1N 6N5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tianjin Women's &amp; Children's Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tianjin</city>
        <zip>300070</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Public Health School of Medicine at Universidad de los Andes</name>
      <address>
        <city>Carrera</city>
        <state>Bogata</state>
        <country>Colombia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Food &amp; Environmental Sciences, University of Helsinki</name>
      <address>
        <city>Helsinki</city>
        <zip>00014</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St John's National Academy of Health Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangalore</city>
        <state>Karnataka</state>
        <zip>560034</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Exercise, Recreation and Sports Science at Kenyatta University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nairobi</city>
        <country>Kenya</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Faculty of Sport Sciences and Physical Education - University of Porto</name>
      <address>
        <city>Porto</city>
        <zip>4200-450</zip>
        <country>Portugal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Cape Town</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rondebosch</city>
        <state>Cape Town</state>
        <zip>7701</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Health at University of Bath</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bath</city>
        <zip>BA2 7AY</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Brazil</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>China</country>
    <country>Colombia</country>
    <country>Finland</country>
    <country>India</country>
    <country>Kenya</country>
    <country>Portugal</country>
    <country>South Africa</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adachi-Mejia AM, Longacre MR, Gibson JJ, Beach ML, Titus-Ernstoff LT, Dalton MA. Children with a TV in their bedroom at higher risk for being overweight. Int J Obes (Lond). 2007 Apr;31(4):644-51. Epub 2006 Sep 12.</citation>
    <PMID>16969360</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adair LS, Popkin BM. Are child eating patterns being transformed globally? Obes Res. 2005 Jul;13(7):1281-99.</citation>
    <PMID>16077000</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cameron R, Manske S, Brown KS, Jolin MA, Murnaghan D, Lovato C. Integrating public health policy, practice, evaluation, surveillance, and research: the school health action planning and evaluation system. Am J Public Health. 2007 Apr;97(4):648-54. Epub 2007 Feb 28.</citation>
    <PMID>17329662</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cerin E, Saelens BE, Sallis JF, Frank LD. Neighborhood Environment Walkability Scale: validity and development of a short form. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2006 Sep;38(9):1682-91.</citation>
    <PMID>16960531</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chaput JP, Després JP, Bouchard C, Tremblay A. The association between sleep duration and weight gain in adults: a 6-year prospective study from the Quebec Family Study. Sleep. 2008 Apr;31(4):517-23.</citation>
    <PMID>18457239</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen X, Beydoun MA, Wang Y. Is sleep duration associated with childhood obesity? A systematic review and meta-analysis. Obesity (Silver Spring). 2008 Feb;16(2):265-74. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18239632</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Delmas C, Platat C, Schweitzer B, Wagner A, Oujaa M, Simon C. Association between television in bedroom and adiposity throughout adolescence. Obesity (Silver Spring). 2007 Oct;15(10):2495-503.</citation>
    <PMID>17925476</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dennison BA, Erb TA, Jenkins PL. Television viewing and television in bedroom associated with overweight risk among low-income preschool children. Pediatrics. 2002 Jun;109(6):1028-35.</citation>
    <PMID>12042539</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ekelund U, Sardinha LB, Anderssen SA, Harro M, Franks PW, Brage S, Cooper AR, Andersen LB, Riddoch C, Froberg K. Associations between objectively assessed physical activity and indicators of body fatness in 9- to 10-y-old European children: a population-based study from 4 distinct regions in Europe (the European Youth Heart Study). Am J Clin Nutr. 2004 Sep;80(3):584-90.</citation>
    <PMID>15321796</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Franzini L, Elliott MN, Cuccaro P, Schuster M, Gilliland MJ, Grunbaum JA, Franklin F, Tortolero SR. Influences of physical and social neighborhood environments on children's physical activity and obesity. Am J Public Health. 2009 Feb;99(2):271-8. Epub 2008 Dec 4.</citation>
    <PMID>19059864</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hearst MO, Lytle LA, Pasch KE, Heitzler CD. Inventory versus checklist approach to assess middle school à la carte food availability. J Sch Health. 2009 Dec;79(12):593-8; quiz 603-5.</citation>
    <PMID>19909423</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Janssen I, Katzmarzyk PT, Boyce WF, Vereecken C, Mulvihill C, Roberts C, Currie C, Pickett W; Health Behaviour in School-Aged Children Obesity Working Group. Comparison of overweight and obesity prevalence in school-aged youth from 34 countries and their relationships with physical activity and dietary patterns. Obes Rev. 2005 May;6(2):123-32. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15836463</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jones NR, Jones A, van Sluijs EM, Panter J, Harrison F, Griffin SJ. School environments and physical activity: The development and testing of an audit tool. Health Place. 2010 Sep;16(5):776-83. doi: 10.1016/j.healthplace.2010.04.002. Epub 2010 Apr 14.</citation>
    <PMID>20435506</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leyden KM. Social capital and the built environment: the importance of walkable neighborhoods. Am J Public Health. 2003 Sep;93(9):1546-51.</citation>
    <PMID>12948978</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lytle LA. Examining the etiology of childhood obesity: The IDEA study. Am J Community Psychol. 2009 Dec;44(3-4):338-49.</citation>
    <PMID>19838791</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khamis HJ, Roche AF. Predicting adult stature without using skeletal age: the Khamis-Roche method. Pediatrics. 1994 Oct;94(4 Pt 1):504-7. Erratum in: Pediatrics 1995 Mar;95(3):457.</citation>
    <PMID>7936860</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kumanyika SK, Obarzanek E. Pathways to obesity prevention: report of a National Institutes of Health workshop. Obes Res. 2003 Oct;11(10):1263-74. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14569052</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lobstein T, Baur L, Uauy R; IASO International Obesity TaskForce. Obesity in children and young people: a crisis in public health. Obes Rev. 2004 May;5 Suppl 1:4-104. Review. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>15096099</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martinez-Gomez D, Ruiz JR, Ortega FB, Veiga OL, Moliner-Urdiales D, Mauro B, Galfo M, Manios Y, Widhalm K, Béghin L, Moreno LA, Molnar D, Marcos A, Sjöström M; HELENA Study Group. Recommended levels of physical activity to avoid an excess of body fat in European adolescents: the HELENA Study. Am J Prev Med. 2010 Sep;39(3):203-11.</citation>
    <PMID>20709251</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mirwald RL, Baxter-Jones AD, Bailey DA, Beunen GP. An assessment of maturity from anthropometric measurements. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2002 Apr;34(4):689-94.</citation>
    <PMID>11932580</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moreno LA, De Henauw S, González-Gross M, Kersting M, Molnár D, Gottrand F, Barrios L, Sjöström M, Manios Y, Gilbert CC, Leclercq C, Widhalm K, Kafatos A, Marcos A; HELENA Study Group. Design and implementation of the Healthy Lifestyle in Europe by Nutrition in Adolescence Cross-Sectional Study. Int J Obes (Lond). 2008 Nov;32 Suppl 5:S4-11.</citation>
    <PMID>19011652</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Motl RW, Dishman RK, Trost SG, Saunders RP, Dowda M, Felton G, Ward DS, Pate RR. Factorial validity and invariance of questionnaires measuring social-cognitive determinants of physical activity among adolescent girls. Prev Med. 2000 Nov;31(5):584-94.</citation>
    <PMID>11071840</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Patel SR, Hu FB. Short sleep duration and weight gain: a systematic review. Obesity (Silver Spring). 2008 Mar;16(3):643-53. Epub 2008 Jan 17. Review. PubMed PMID: 18239586; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC2723045.</citation>
    <PMID>18239586</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ravens-Sieberer U, Erhart M, Rajmil L, Herdman M, Auquier P, Bruil J, Power M, Duer W, Abel T, Czemy L, Mazur J, Czimbalmos A, Tountas Y, Hagquist C, Kilroe J; European KIDSCREEN Group. Reliability, construct and criterion validity of the KIDSCREEN-10 score: a short measure for children and adolescents' well-being and health-related quality of life. Qual Life Res. 2010 Dec;19(10):1487-500. Epub 2010 Jul 30.</citation>
    <PMID>20668950</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosenberg D, Ding D, Sallis JF, Kerr J, Norman GJ, Durant N, Harris SK, Saelens BE. Neighborhood Environment Walkability Scale for Youth (NEWS-Y): reliability and relationship with physical activity. Prev Med. 2009 Aug-Sep;49(2-3):213-8. Epub 2009 Jul 24.</citation>
    <PMID>19632263</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saelens BE, Sallis JF, Black JB, Chen D. Neighborhood-based differences in physical activity: an environment scale evaluation. Am J Public Health. 2003 Sep;93(9):1552-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12948979</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sallis JF, Cervero RB, Ascher W, Henderson KA, Kraft MK, Kerr J. An ecological approach to creating active living communities. Annu Rev Public Health. 2006;27:297-322. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16533119</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sallis JF, Kerr J, Carlson JA, Norman GJ, Saelens BE, Durant N, Ainsworth BE. Evaluating a brief self-report measure of neighborhood environments for physical activity research and surveillance: Physical Activity Neighborhood Environment Scale (PANES). J Phys Act Health. 2010 Jul;7(4):533-40.</citation>
    <PMID>20683096</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sallis JF, Prochaska JJ, Taylor WC. A review of correlates of physical activity of children and adolescents. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2000 May;32(5):963-75. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10795788</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sampson RJ, Raudenbush SW, Earls F. Neighborhoods and violent crime: a multilevel study of collective efficacy. Science. 1997 Aug 15;277(5328):918-24.</citation>
    <PMID>9252316</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Story M, Kaphingst KM, Robinson-O'Brien R, Glanz K. Creating healthy food and eating environments: policy and environmental approaches. Annu Rev Public Health. 2008;29:253-72. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18031223</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Striegel-Moore RH, Morrison JA, Schreiber G, Schumann BC, Crawford PB, Obarzanek E. Emotion-induced eating and sucrose intake in children: the NHLBI Growth and Health Study. Int J Eat Disord. 1999 May;25(4):389-98.</citation>
    <PMID>10202649</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Van den Bulck J, Van Mierlo J. Energy intake associated with television viewing in adolescents, a cross sectional study. Appetite. 2004 Oct;43(2):181-4.</citation>
    <PMID>15458804</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Sluijs EM, Skidmore PM, Mwanza K, Jones AP, Callaghan AM, Ekelund U, Harrison F, Harvey I, Panter J, Wareham NJ, Cassidy A, Griffin SJ. Physical activity and dietary behaviour in a population-based sample of British 10-year old children: the SPEEDY study (Sport, Physical activity and Eating behaviour: environmental Determinants in Young people). BMC Public Health. 2008 Nov 14;8:388.</citation>
    <PMID>19014571</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Currie C, Gabhainn SN, Godeau E, et al., eds. Inequalities in Children's Health: HBSC International Report from the 2005/2006 Survey Geneva: World Health Organization; 2008.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 19, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 29, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Peter T. Katzmarzyk</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Executive Director of Population Science</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>International</keyword>
  <keyword>Childhood</keyword>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>ISCOLE</keyword>
  <keyword>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</keyword>
  <keyword>PBRC</keyword>
  <keyword>longitudinal</keyword>
  <keyword>multinational</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
