<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="65625">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02125838</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>859-GOA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02125838</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Laryngeal Mask Supreme During Laparoscopic Gynecologic Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Application of Endotracheal Intubation and Laryngeal Mask Supreme Without Neuromuscular Blocker in Laparoscopic Gynecologic Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dokuz Eylul University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dokuz Eylul University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Turkey: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Laryngeal mask (LM) use in gynecological laparoscopy, contrary to widespread opinion, does
      not increase the incidence of gastric aspiration, the failure of ventilation or the risk of
      pulmonary aspiration . LM is presented as an alternative to endo tracheal tube (ETT) in
      spontaneous or positive pressure ventilation (PPV) . LM has gained widespread popularity in
      England for gynecological laparoscopic procedures. In addition in many previous studies LM
      has been successfully shown to provide appropriate lung ventilation in laparoscopic surgical
      interventions .Miller et al. compared the use of ETT, LM-P laparoscopic gynecological
      interventions and identified advantages to LM use. The most important of these advantages
      was that, contrary to tracheal tube techniques for laparoscopic surgeries, use of
      supraglottic laryngeal devices or neuromuscular blocker agents (NBA) were not required
      during placement. Thus for  laparoscopic surgeries, compared with the ETT technique, without
      the need for supraglottic laryngeal devices or muscular relaxants, it is easily placed and
      reduces the time spent in the operating room.

      Our aim; to compare the use of LM-S and ETT without neuromuscular agents for laparoscopic
      gynecological intervention with positive pressure ventilation from a surgical viewpoint and
      in terms of effect on ventilation parameters.

      Secondary aim, comparison of airway morbidity with endotracheal intubation and supraglottic.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This prospective, randomized and double-blind study received permission from &quot;Dokuz Eylül
      University Medical Faculty Non-Interventional Research Ethics Committee&quot; and after obtaining
      patients' informed consent, 100 patients with American society of anesthesiologists (ASA)
      classification group I-II, between 18-65 years, undergoing elective laparoscopic
      gynecological surgery were included.

      Patients were divided into:

      Group 1=&gt;ETT (50 patients) Group 21=&gt;LM-S (50 patients) Patients and surgeons performing the
      operation were not aware of which airway device was used. The patients in the groups were
      determined by block randomized methods.

      Patients taken to the surgical room were given standard monitoring (non-invasive blood
      pressure measurements, electrocardiogram, and peripheral oxygen saturation measurements)
      before anesthesia induction. For preoperative sedation 0.02 mg/kg midazolam IV was
      administered.

      Patients were preoxygenated with 6 L/min oxygen for 3 minutes through a face mask.

      For anesthesia induction after 2 minutes of 0.2 µg/kg/min remifentanil and 6 mg/kg/hr
      propofol infusion, IV 1-2 mg/kg propofol was administered. After induction patients were
      ventilated with 6 L/min 100% fraction of inspired oxygen inspired oxygen fraction  oxygen
      through a face mask. Anesthesia depth was standardized in all patients using bispectral
      index monitoring (BIS, ASPECT A-2000 BIS XP monitor). BIS values were held between 40-60.
      BIS values were maintained in this interval by increasing or decreasing propofol infusion by
      1 mg/kg.

      Airway devices were inserted by two researchers with more than 5 years experience.

      During airway device placement according to patient reactions an extra dose of 0.5 mg/kg
      propofol was given if necessary.

      Anesthetic maintenance was provided by 50% O2/air mixture with 0.1-0.4 µg/kg/min
      remifentanil and 50-150 µg/kg/hr (3-9 mg/kg/hr) propofol IV infusion (24).

      Before LM-S was inserted, to lubricate the surface in contact with the palate a water-based
      K-YTM gel (Johnson &amp; Johnson Ltd. Maidenhead, UK) without local anesthetic was applied to
      completely cover the LM-S cuff. Depending on the patient's body weight For &lt;50 kg, no. 3
      Between 50-70 kg, no. 4 Between 70-100 kg, no. 5 LM-S (The Laryngeal Mask Company Limited,
      Singapore) was inserted.

      After LM-S placement the cuff was inflated with air so as to have a pressure below 60
      centimeters of water (cuff pressure manometer, Rusch, Germany). Two minutes after LM-S
      placement, before insufflation, 10 minutes after insufflation and trendelenburg position,
      before desufflation and before LM-S removal, cuff pressure was measured repeatedly and
      recorded. At the same time intervals in the ETT group, ETT cuff pressure was measured.

      In the ETT group for women no. 7-7.5 tube was used. The ETT cuff was inflated until the leak
      sound ceased. It was measured with a manometer to remain between 20-30 centimeters of water.

      Successful placement of LM or ETT was confirmed by square-shaped waves observed on the
      capnogram, easy ventilation of the respiration balloon and visible chest movements. After
      successful placement of the airway device, it was covered to prevent observation of which
      device was used.

      The length of time for successful placement (duration from mouth opening to first successful
      ventilation), number of tries, and ease of placement were recorded. Ease of placement was
      evaluated by the anesthetist in charge of the airway as easy, hard or unsuccessful
      (alternative airway management) (6,25).

      In a situation where airway provision was unsuccessful after 3 tries, patients without
      placement of LM-S or who could not be intubated were switched to the other group and airway
      management was provided.

      For oropharyngeal leak test after the expiratory valve was closed air was shut off, O2 was
      reduced to 3 L/min and the first pressure value when a leak sound was heard was recorded as
      the oropharyngeal leak pressure. To prevent exposure of the lungs to barotrauma, when the
      peak inspiratory pressure reached 40centimeters of water the expiratory valve was opened and
      the test was concluded (29-31). This test was repeated before peritoneal insufflation, 10
      minutes later and immediately before desufflation and was completed by a researcher blind to
      the type of airway device inserted.

      Positive pressure respiration was begun by using a ring system, 2-4 L/min fresh gas flow and
      0.5 volume controlled 6-8 ml/kg tidal volume and 10 respirations/min frequency. PEEP was not
      administered and I:E ratio was adjusted to 1:2. ETCO2 was held between 35-45 mmHg, if
      necessary first respiration frequency was increased then tidal volume was increased.
      Permission was given for CO2 insufflation for the laparoscopic intervention with peritoneal
      interior pressure of 15 mmHg.

      Two minutes after LM-S or ETT placement, before insufflation, 10 minutes after insufflation
      and trendelenburg position, immediately before peritoneal desufflation and before airway
      device removal, ventilation parameters were evaluated.

      Respiratory measurements to be recorded: Tidal volume (TV), respiration number (RN),
      peripheral oxygen saturation (SPO2), end-tidal carbon dioxide pressure (PETCO2), peak airway
      pressure (P peak), mean airway pressure (P mean) and expiration volume per minute (VE).

      Hemodynamic measurements to be recorded: (simultaneous to the measurements above and
      additionally before induction) Systolic arterial pressure (SAP), diastolic arterial pressure
      (DAP), mean arterial pressure (MAP) and heart rate (HR).

      Evaluation related to gastric tube:

      Immediately after airway device placement using either the LM-S drainage tube or in
      intubated patients using a 14 Ch orogastric probe within the airway (Bıcakcılar Tibbi
      Cihazlar Sanayi ve Ticaret A.Ş. Istanbul, Turkey), the stomach was reached and the gastric
      contents were aspirated. Ease of placement and amount of fluids aspirated were recorded.
      Ease of placement was classified by the person who inserted the orogastric probe as very
      easy, easy, difficult and very difficult (28).

      The number of interventions with Verres needle, initial intra-abdominal pressure, duration
      to reach intra-abdominal pressure of 15 mmHg, and insufflated volume of CO2 were recorded.
      Sufficiency of pneumoperitoneum (sufficient/insufficient), and quality of airway provision
      were evaluated by the surgeon who was blind to the airway device used by giving points
      between 1-4 (23).

      Immediately after the intra-abdominal laparoscopic intervention and immediately before
      peritoneal insufflation was ended, gastric distension was evaluated by a surgeon blind to
      the airway device used between 0-10 (0=empty stomach, 10=distension obstructing the surgical
      field) and the difference between the scores at the start and end of the operation was
      recorded (29).

      When the patient cooperated LM-S or ETT was removed and total anesthesia duration and
      peritoneal insufflation duration was recorded. Possible complications that could develop
      during airway device removal (coughing, vomiting, laryngeal stridor, laryngeal spasm or
      requirement for airway intervention) were recorded.

      After laryngeal supra glottic airway device removal the presence of blood was evaluated as

        1. no blood

        2. trace amounts of blood

        3. clear amount of blood Revived patients were taken to the recovery unit and a blind
           researcher evaluated the patients' throat pain, hoarseness and presence of difficulty
           swallowing in the 1st and 24th hours. To evaluate throat pain the VAS-10 (visual
           analogue scale) was used.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To asses the effective ventilation parameters without neuromuscular agents</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To asses to achieve ventilation parameters without neuromuscular agents; tidal volume, respiration number,  peripheral oxygen saturation, end-tidal carbon dioxide pressure, peak airway pressure, mean airway pressure and expiration volume per minute.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Surgeon wiev</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To reveal the best surgical viewpoint of either the LM-Supreme or the tracheal tube, as assigned</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of gastric distention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To provide the adequate gastric distention of either the LM-Supreme or the tracheal tube, as assigned. Gastric distension was evaluated by a surgeon blind to the airway device used between 0-10 (0=empty stomach, 10=distension obstructing the surgical field)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of attempts taken for successful placement of gastric tube</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of attempts needed for successful placement of gastric tube. Correct gastric tube placement was determined by positive suctioning of gastric contents or detection of injected air with epigastric auscultation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Haemodynamic response to insertion of airway device</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Systolic blood pressure and heart rate at two minutes after LM-S placement, before insufflation, 10 minutes after insufflation and trendelenburg position, before desufflation and before LM-S removal  .</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of post-operative sore throat</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients were asked about the presence of sore throat - defined as the presence of constant pain in the throat, independent of swallowing, 1 hr and 24 hr after the end of surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Anaesthesia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group ETT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group ETT (Endotracheal tube Group). In the ETT group for women no. 7-7.5 tube will use. ETT:Rüschelit, Teleflex Medical Snd. Bhd. Malaysia. Ref:112482</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group LMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group LM-S (Laryngeal mask supreme Group) For &lt;50 kg, no. 3 Between 50-70 kg, no. 4 Between 70-100 kg, no. 5 LM-S (The Laryngeal Mask Company Limited, Singapore) will insert.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laryngeal Mask Airway-Supreme</intervention_name>
    <description>Group LM-S (laryngeal mask group)Before LM-S was inserted, to lubricate the surface in contact with the palate a water-based K-YTM gel (Johnson &amp; Johnson Ltd. Maidenhead, UK) without local anesthetic was applied to completely cover the LM-S cuff. Depending on the patient's body weight For &lt;50 kg, no. 3 Between 50-70 kg, no. 4 Between 70-100 kg, no. 5 LM-S (The Laryngeal Mask Company Limited, Singapore) was inserted.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group LMS</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LM-S (The Laryngeal Mask Company Limited, Singapore)</other_name>
    <other_name>serial number: 175030</other_name>
    <other_name>lot: hmabw7</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Endotracheal Tube</intervention_name>
    <description>ETT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group ETT</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Group ETT (Endotracheal tube Group).</other_name>
    <other_name>ETT:Rüschelit, Teleflex Medical Snd. Bhd. Malaysia. Ref:112482</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ASA classification group I-II

          -  Between 18-65 years

          -  Undergoing elective laparoscopic gynecological surgery

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals with any neck and upper respiratory pathology

          -  Individuals at risk of gastric content regurgitation/aspiration (previous upper
             gastrointestinal surgery, known hiatus hernia, gastroesophageal reflux, history of
             peptic ulcer, full stomach, pregnancy)

          -  Individuals with low pulmonary compliance or high airway resistance (chronic lung
             diseases)

          -  Obese patients (BMI &gt;35)

          -  Individuals with sore throat, dysphagia and dysphonia

          -  Individuals with possibility or history of difficult airway

          -  Operation time planned for more than 4 hours
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>SULE OZBİLİGİN, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>STUDY DESİGN</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>SULE OZBILGIN</last_name>
    <phone>009005055252901</phone>
    <email>ozbilginsule@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>BAHAR KUVAKİ</last_name>
    <phone>009002324122836</phone>
    <email>bkuvaki@deu.edu.tr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sule Ozbilgin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Izmi̇r</city>
        <state>Narlıdere</state>
        <zip>35320</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>SULE OZBILGIN, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>009005055252901</phone>
      <email>ozbilginsule@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>BAHAR KUVAKİ, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>009002324122836</phone>
      <email>bkuvaki@deu.edu.tr</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>BAHAR KUVAKİ, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 28, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 31, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Dokuz Eylul University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sule Ozbilgin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Anaesthesiology and Reanimation</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>laryngeal mask Supreme</keyword>
  <keyword>laparoscopic gynecologic surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Laryngeal mask during surgery</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neuromuscular Blocking Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
