<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="94151">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01982955</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>200095-006</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01982955</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MSC2156119J With Gefitinib in Subjects With Advanced Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase Ib/II Multicenter, Randomized, Open Label Trial to Compare MSC2156119J Combined With Gefitinib Versus Chemotherapy as Second-line Treatment in Subjects With MET Positive, Locally Advanced or Metastatic Non-small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) Harboring EGFR Mutation and Having Acquired Resistance to First-line Gefitinib</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Merck KGaA</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Merck KGaA</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>China: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>South Korea: Ministry of Food and Drug Safety</authority>
    <authority>Taiwan : Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Singapore: Health Sciences Authority</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center, open-label, randomized, Phase 1b/2 trial to determine the
      recommended phase 2 dose (RP2D) and to evaluate the efficacy in terms of progression free
      survival (PFS) of MSC2156119J when used in combination with gefitinib in subjects with MET
      positive locally advanced or metastatic non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) harboring
      epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) mutation and having acquired resistance to
      first-line gefitinib.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects experiencing at least one dose limiting toxicity (DLT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 21 of Cycle 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number   of subjects with adverse events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Day 30 after the last dose of study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression   free survival (PFS) time: Investigator assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PFS time is defined as the time (in months) from randomization either the first observation of progressive disease (PD) (as assessed by the investigator)  or occurrence of death due to any cause within 84 days of either randomization or the last tumor assessment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival (PFS) time: Independent review assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PFS time is defined as the time (in months) from randomization either the first observation of PD (as assessed by the independent review committee) or occurrence of death due to any cause within 84 days of either randomization or the last tumor assessment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival Time</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from randomization to the date of death or up to 8 months whichever occur first</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall survival time will be measured from randomization to the date of death or up to 8 months whichever occur first.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage  of subjects with objective response according to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors version 1.1 (RECIST v 1.1) criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 6 weeks until Week 72 and every 12 weeks after Week 72 until radiologically documented progressive disease, death, end of trial, or starting a new treatment, whichever occurs first</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage  of subjects with disease control according to RECIST version 1.1 criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 6 weeks until Week 72 and every 12 weeks after Week 72 until radiologically documented progressive disease, death, end of trial, or starting a new treatment, whichever occurs first</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Disease control defined as proportion of subjects with complete response (CR), partial response (PR), or stable disease (SD) as the best overall response according to RECIST version 1.1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics parameters: AUC (0-t), AUC (0-tau), Cmax, Cavg, Cmin, Tmax, AUC (0-infinity), CL/F, Vz/F, Vss/F, lambda_z, and t1/2</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 and 15 of Cycle 1 and Day 1 of Cycle 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">218</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MSC2156119J plus Gefitinib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pemetrexed plus Cisplatin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MSC2156119J</intervention_name>
    <description>MSC2156119J will be administered at a total dose range of 300-500 milligram (mg) orally once daily over a 21-day cycle until progressive disease, intolerable toxicity, subject's withdrawal from treatment or a maximum of 6 cycles. Dose adjustment will be done as per safety monitoring committee (SMC) discretion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MSC2156119J plus Gefitinib</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gefitinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Gefitinib will be administered at a dose of 250 mg orally as once daily over a 21-day cycle until progressive disease, intolerable toxicity, subject's withdrawal from treatment or a maximum of 6 cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MSC2156119J plus Gefitinib</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pemetrexed</intervention_name>
    <description>Pemetrexed will be administered at a dose of 500 milligram per square meter (mg/m^2) as intravenous infusion over 10 minutes on Day 1 of each 21-day cycle  until progressive disease, intolerable toxicity, subject's withdrawal from treatment or a maximum of 6 cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pemetrexed plus Cisplatin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cisplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Cisplatin will be administered at a dose of 75 mg/m^2 as intravenous infusion over 2 hours on Day 1 of each 21-day cycle  until progressive disease, intolerable toxicity, subject's withdrawal from treatment or a maximum of 6 cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pemetrexed plus Cisplatin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Phase I

        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologically or cytologically confirmed advanced NSCLC, regardless of histology
             subtype

          2. Documented (pre-existing) activating mutation of the EGFR: only required for subjects
             who are eligible for first-line gefitinib treatment

          3. Availability of a fresh or archived pretreatment tumor biopsy (excluding fine needle
             aspiration and cytology samples). For subjects who have had at least 1 prior
             anticancer treatment, a biopsy obtained between failure of the most recent anticancer
             treatment and enrolment is mandatory;

          4. MET+, as determined by the central laboratory

          5. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status (PS) of 0 or 1

        Phase II

        Inclusion criteria

          1. Histologically or cytologically confirmed advanced NSCLC other than predominantly
             squamous histology

          2. Activating mutation of the EGFR receptor (documented, or as determined by the central
              laboratory)

          3. Results of EGFR T790M mutation testing (positive/negative/indeterminate) after
             acquired resistance to gefitinib treatment, as determined by the central laboratory

          4. &quot;Acquired resistance&quot; on first-line gefitinib

          5. Availability of a fresh or archived tumor tissue (excluding fine needle aspiration
             and cytology samples) obtained between documentation of acquired resistance to
             gefitinib  and enrolment is mandatory

          6. MET+ status, as determined by the central laboratory

          7. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1

        Exclusion Criteria (Phase I and II):

          1. Estimated life expectancy less than (&lt;) 3 months

          2. Inadequate bone marrow, liver or renal functions

          3. Prior systemic anticancer treatment with chemotherapy or other agents targeting EGFR
             pathway excluding gefitinib for advanced NSCLC (1 additional chemo regimen for (neo)
             adjuvant purpose is allowed)

          4. Other protocol defined exclusion criteria could apply
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Responsible</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Merck KGaA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Merck KGaA Communication Center</last_name>
    <phone>+49 6151 72 5200</phone>
    <email>service@merckgroup.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Please contact the Merck KGaA Communication Center located in</name>
      <address>
        <city>Darmstadt</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <phone>+49 6151 72 5200</phone>
      <email>service@merckgroup.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 29, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>MSC2156119J</keyword>
  <keyword>Gefitinib</keyword>
  <keyword>Pemetrexed</keyword>
  <keyword>Cisplatin</keyword>
  <keyword>MET positive</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Pemetrexed</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gefitinib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
