<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="77191">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01848145</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SCRI CLL 18</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01848145</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rapid Infusion of Ofatumumab in Patients With Previously Treated Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Rapid Infusion of Ofatumumab in Patients With Previously Treated Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia, a Phase II Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>SCRI Development Innovations, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>SCRI Development Innovations, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase II, single-arm study of ofatumumab investigating the safety of an
      accelerated infusion schedule of ofatumumab in patients who have received at least one prior
      therapy for CLL.  The primary endpoint is to evaluate the number of subjects able to
      complete infusion number 3 (2000 mg) within 15 minutes of the planned time.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to develop an accelerated infusion regimen that allows
      ofatumumab to be delivered in a safe manner while minimizing the time required administering
      the treatment.    We hypothesize there will be fewer infusion-related reactions using the
      proposed dose-dense approach the first week before accelerating the rate of infusion.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>18 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary objective of this study is to evaluate the safety of an accelerated infusion schedule of ofatumumab in patients with CLL. All adverse events (AEs) will be tabulated both together and individually (per type of AE) to assess safety.  The number of patients who require dose reductions or must discontinue study therapy because of AEs will also be reported.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of infusion reactions with pre-treatment clinical characteristics and FcGamma polymorphisms.</measure>
    <time_frame>18 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Correlation of infusion reactions with pre-treatment clinical characteristics and FcGamma polymorphisms.A number of CLL-associated markers and prognostic factors, will be measured and correlated with response to treatment and response duration with ofatumumab. The primary correlation will be with Fc Receptor polymorphisms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">43</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ofatumumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Rapid Infusion of Ofatumumab</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ofatumumab</intervention_name>
    <description>The first dose of ofatumumab administered on Day 1 will be 300 mg to minimize infusion reactions.  If the initial 300 mg dose of ofatumumab is well-tolerated, without occurrence of any infusion-associated AEs of &gt;= grade 3, on Day 3 ofatumumab will increase to 1000 mg IV.   If the Day 3 dose was well-tolerated (i.e., no infusion-associated AE &gt;= grade 3), on Day 8 the ofatumumab dose will escalate to 2000 mg IV.  To achieve the primary endpoint for this study, 20% of the  2000 mg ofatumumab dose only will be administered over the first 30 minutes and if tolerated the remaining 80% of the dose will be infused over the remaining 1.5/hours of each treatment.  Ofatumumab doses, weeks 3-8, will remain at 2000 mg IV with no further dose escalations.  If the Day 8 (Week 2) dose is tolerated all subsequent doses may be infused in the same manner.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ofatumumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Arzerra</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. CD20+ B-cell chronic lymphocytic leukemia (B-CLL) according to International Workshop
             on CLL Working Group (IWCLL WG) Diagnostic Criteria.

          2. Have received at least one prior therapy for CLL.

               -  If previously treated with ofatumumab must have achieved at least a partial
                  response (PR) and maintained PR for &gt;= 6 months.

          3. Requires treatment according to IWCLL-Working Group guidelines.

          4. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group Performance Status (ECOG PS) &lt;=1.

          5. Laboratory parameters &lt;=7 days prior to treatment initiation:

               1. Creatinine  &lt;= 1.5 mg/dL upper limit normal (ULN)

               2. Aspartate amino transferase (AST) or alanine amino transferase (ALT) &lt;= 3.0 x
                  ULN

               3. Alkaline phosphatase (ALP) &lt;= 3.0 x ULN

               4. Total Bilirubin level of &lt; 1.5 mg/dL x the institutional ULN unless secondary to
                  Gilbert's disease (or pattern consistent with Gilbert's)

          6. Hepatitis B sAg negative and HepB cAb negative.  Note:  Patients who are HepB sAg
             negative but are HepB cAb positive (regardless of HepB sAb status) will NOT be
             allowed.

          7. Women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test performed
             &lt;=72 hours prior to start of treatment.  Women of childbearing potential or men with
             partners of childbearing potential must use effective birth control measures during
             treatment.  If a woman becomes pregnant or suspects she is pregnant while
             participating in this study, she must agree to inform her treating physician
             immediately.

          8. Accessible for treatment and follow-up.

          9. Able to understand the nature of this study, give written informed consent prior to
             study entry, and comply with study requirements.

         10. No prior antibody therapy for CLL within the previous 3 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Previous treatment with ofatumumab that resulted in a Grade 3 or 4 infusion reaction.

          2. Treatment for CLL within last 4 weeks.  (Patients who have received steroids or IVIG
             for autoimmune complications of CLL are eligible).

          3. Current active hepatic or biliary disease (with the exception of patients with
             Gilbert's syndrome, asymptomatic gallstones, liver metastases, or stable chronic
             liver disease, per assessment by the treating physician).

          4. Active bacterial or viral infection or infection requiring intravenous antibiotic
             treatment at the time of accrual.

          5. Central nervous system lymphoma/CLL.

          6. Transformation of CLL to aggressive non-Hodgkin lymphoma (NHL) (i.e., Richter's
             transformation).

          7. History of other malignancy &lt;/= 2 years of study entry which could affect compliance
             with the protocol or interpretation of results.  History of curatively treated basal
             or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin or in situ carcinoma of the cervix, low grade,
             early-stage, localized prostate cancer treated surgically with curative intent,
             ductal carcinoma in situ (DCIS) of the breast treated with curative intent, are
             generally eligible.

          8. Active hepatitis B or C or known HIV positive.

          9. Treatment with any known non-marketed drug substance or experimental therapy within 5
             terminal half lives or 4 weeks prior to visit 1, whichever is longer.

         10. History of significant cerebrovascular disease in the past 6 months or ongoing event
             with active symptoms or sequelae.

         11. Clinically significant cardiac disease including unstable angina, acute myocardial
             infarction (within 6 months of enrollment), congestive heart failure (NYHA III-IV),
             and arrhythmia unless controlled by therapy, with the exception of extra systoles or
             minor conduction abnormalities.

         12. Significant concurrent, uncontrolled medical condition including, but not limited to,
             renal, hepatic, gastrointestinal, endocrine, pulmonary, neurological, cerebral or
             psychiatric disease which in the opinion of the investigator may represent a risk for
             the patient.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ian Flinn, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>SCRI Development Innovations, LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ian Flinn, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>877-691-7274</phone>
    <email>asksarah@scresearch.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Trial Info</last_name>
    <phone>877-691-7274</phone>
    <email>asksarah@scresearch.net</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Colorado Blood Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80218</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Florida Cancer Specialists-South</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Myers</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33916</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Florida Cancer Specialists-North</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Petersburg</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oncology Hematology Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45242</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chattanooga Oncology Hematology Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chattanooga</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37404</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tennessee Oncology PLLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 2, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Ofatumumab</keyword>
  <keyword>Rapid Infusion</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
