<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="73828">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01840943</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR100654</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>DOXILOVC3001</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01840943</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Compare CAELYX With Topotecan HCL in Patients With Recurrent Epithelial Ovarian Carcinoma Following Failure of First-Line, Platinum-Based Chemotherapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 3, Randomized, Open-Label, Comparative Bridging Study of CAELYX® Versus Topotecan HCl in Subjects With Epithelial Ovarian Carcinoma Following Failure of First-Line, Platinum-Based Chemotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Xian-Janssen Pharmaceutical Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Xian-Janssen Pharmaceutical Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>China: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare the effectiveness between CAELYX and topotecan
      hydrochloride (HCl) in Chinese participants with recurrent epithelial ovarian carcinoma
      following failure of first-line, platinum-based chemotherapy, who have received no more than
      one prior platinum-based regimen therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-label (all people know the identity of the intervention), randomized (the
      study medication is assigned by chance), comparative bridging study (a supplemental study
      which performs to provide data of effectiveness, safety, and dosage to compare two study
      medications in a new region). The study consists of 3 phases: screening phase (30 days
      before administration of study medication), treatment phase, and follow up phase (every 8
      weeks for tumor assessment until disease progression or death, or until the study
      completion, whichever is earlier and every 3 months after disease progression for overall
      survival and for anti-tumor therapy for a minimum of 1 year). In the treatment phase,
      approximately 120 eligible participants will be categorized prospectively for
      platinum-sensitivity (sensitive versus refractory) and bulky disease (presence versus
      absence). Later on participants will be randomly assigned either to experimental arm
      (CAELYX: administer on Day 1 of each cycle) or control arm (topotecan HCl: administer on Day
      1 to Day 5 of each cycle). Treatment will continue until disease progression occurs and may
      continue for at least 2 cycles after confirmed complete response (disappearance of all
      target lesions). On average, it is expected that participants will continue treatment for
      approximately 3 to 6 cycles in experimental arm (CAELYX) or 4 to 8 cycles in Control arm
      (topotecan HCl). Safety evaluations will include assessment of adverse events, clinical
      laboratory tests, electrocardiogram, echocardiogram (or multiple gated acquisition scans),
      vital signs, and physical examination which will be monitored throughout the study. The
      total duration of the study will be approximately 23 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival rate at Week 24</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Progression-free survival rate will be measured as number of participants who are progression-free and alive.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 24 (until  disease progression or death due to any cause, whichever occurs first)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>It is calculated as the time, in weeks, from the day of randomization until documented disease progression or death due to any cause, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Response rate will be measured as number of participants with at least a durable response: Complete response or partial response. Complete response is defined as the disappearance of all target lesions. Partial response is defined as at least a 30 percentage decrease in the sum of diameters of target lesions, taking as reference of the baseline sum diameters.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>It is calculated as the day of randomization to the first observation of a durable response (the first of the 2 confirmatory measurements).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>It is calculated as the first observation of a durable response (the first of the 2 confirmatory measurements) to the first observation of disease progression or death due to any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-related quality of life assessment (HQL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 of each cycle of study medication and Week 4 after last dose of study medication</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Calculation of each HQL domain scale will be performed according to the scoring guidelines for each of the HQL measures. The HQL analyses will include scales measuring physical functioning, pain, nausea, fatigue, and global quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 4 after the last dose of the study medication and approximately up to 1 year after the disease progression or completion of the study treatment or death, whichever is earlier</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall survival is defined as the time interval from randomization to death from any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum plasma concentration of CAELYX</measure>
    <time_frame>0 hour, 30 minutes, 90 minutes, 2 hours, 4 hours, 8 hours, 12 hours, Day 2, Day 3, Day 5, Day 8, and Day 11 for Cycle 1 and Cycle 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This sample will be used for pharmacokinetics analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to reach the maximum plasma concentration of CAELYX</measure>
    <time_frame>0 hour, 30 minutes, 90 minutes, 2 hours, 4 hours, 8 hours, 12 hours, Day 2, Day 3, Day 5, Day 8, and Day 11 for Cycle 1 and Cycle 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This sample will be used for pharmacokinetics analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration of CAELYX</measure>
    <time_frame>0 hour, 30 minutes, 90 minutes, 2 hours, 4 hours, 8 hours, 12 hours, Day 2, Day 3, Day 5, Day 8, and Day 11 for Cycle 1 and Cycle 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This sample will be used for pharmacokinetics analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent terminal elimination half-life of plasma concentration of CAELYX</measure>
    <time_frame>0 hour, 30 minutes, 90 minutes, 2 hours, 4 hours, 8 hours, 12 hours, Day 2, Day 3, Day 5, Day 8, and Day 11 for Cycle 1 and Cycle 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This sample will be used for pharmacokinetics analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent terminal elimination rate constant of plasma concentration of CAELYX</measure>
    <time_frame>0 hour, 30 minutes, 90 minutes, 2 hours, 4 hours, 8 hours, 12 hours, Day 2, Day 3, Day 5, Day 8, and Day 11 for Cycle 1 and Cycle 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This sample will be used for pharmacokinetics analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Systemic clearance of plasma concentration of CAELYX</measure>
    <time_frame>0 hour, 30 minutes, 90 minutes, 2 hours, 4 hours, 8 hours, 12 hours, Day 2, Day 3, Day 5, Day 8, and Day 11 for Cycle 1 and Cycle 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This sample will be used for pharmacokinetics analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent volume of distribution of plasma concentration of CAELYX</measure>
    <time_frame>0 hour, 30 minutes, 90 minutes, 2 hours, 4 hours, 8 hours, 12 hours, Day 2, Day 3, Day 5, Day 8, and Day 11 for Cycle 1 and Cycle 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This sample will be used for pharmacokinetics analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after the last dose of study medication</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Epithelial Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CAELYX</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive CAELYX 50 mg per square meter intravenously on Day 1 of each cycle as: 60 to 90-minute infusion to the participants not undergoing pharmacokinetic (PK) evaluation and 90-minute infusion to the participants undergoing PK evaluation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Topotecan hydrochloride (HCl)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive topotecan HCl 1.25 mg per square meter per day, intravenously for 30-minutes duration, on Day 1 to Day 5 of each cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CAELYX</intervention_name>
    <description>CAELYX 50 mg per square meter will be administered intravenously on Day 1 of each cycle as: 60 to 90-minute infusion to the participants not undergoing pharmacokinetic (PK) evaluation and 90-minute infusion to the participants undergoing for PK evaluation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CAELYX</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Topotecan HCl</intervention_name>
    <description>Topotecan 1.25 mg per square meter per day will be administered, intravenously for 30-minutes duration, on Day 1 to Day 5 of each cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Topotecan hydrochloride (HCl)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histological diagnosed with epithelial ovarian carcinoma with measurable disease

          -  Recurrent epithelial ovarian carcinoma or disease progression following failure of
             first-line, platinum-based chemotherapy with no more than one prior platinum based
             regimen therapy

          -  Adequate laboratory values of bone marrow function, renal function, liver function,
             and echocardiogram tests

          -  Agrees to use protocol-defined effective contraception. A woman must agree not to
             donate eggs (ova, oocytes) for the purpose of assisted reproduction

          -  Disease-free from prior malignancies for more than 5 years with the exception of
             curatively treated basal cell or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin or carcinoma in
             situ of the cervix

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Females who are pregnant or breast feeding or planning to become pregnant while
             enrolled in this study or within 1 year after the last dose of study medication

          -  Myocardial infarct within 6 months before enrollment, class II or greater heart
             failure, uncontrolled angina, severe uncontrolled ventricular arrhythmias, clinically
             significant pericardial disease, or electrocardiographic evidence of acute ischemic
             or active conduction system abnormalities

          -  Uncontrolled systemic infection that requires systemic anti-infective treatment

          -  Prior therapy with CAELYX or topotecan HCl

          -  Prior chemotherapy within 28 days of first dose of study medication (or 42 days if
             participant has received a nitrosourea or mitomycin)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Xian-Janssen Pharmaceutical Ltd., China Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Xian-Janssen Pharmaceutical Ltd.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Use link at the bottom of the page to see if you qualify for an enrolling site (see list). If you still have questions:</last_name>
    <email>JNJ.CT@sylogent.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Chang Sha</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Guangzhou</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Jinan</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Nanjing</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Nanning</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Tianjin</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Wuhan</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Xian</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://pam.sylogent.com/cr/CR100654</url>
    <description>To learn how to participate in this trial please click here.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Epithelial ovarian cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Recurrent epithelial ovarian carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Malignancy</keyword>
  <keyword>Ovarian carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>CAELYX</keyword>
  <keyword>Topotecan hydrochloride</keyword>
  <keyword>Topotecan</keyword>
  <keyword>Platinum-based regimen chemotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Chinese patients</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Glandular and Epithelial</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Doxorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Topotecan</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
