<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="8176">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01838304</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>817166</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01838304</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Probability Ramp Control of Propofol for EGD</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Randomized Comparison of Depth of Sedation With Propofol Titrated by Probability Ramp Control to Control by Anesthesia Providers During Esophagogastroduodenoscopy (EGD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Endoscopic sedation requires titration of propofol to deep sedation without minimum
      overshoot into general anesthesia. This skill is demanding and acquired slowly. Probability
      Ramp Control (PRC) simplifies this by providing the clinician with a simple infusion
      sequence that permits gradual titration of propofol. The purpose of this study is to compare
      the performance of this technology to that of experienced anesthesia providers in endoscopic
      sedation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Administration of propofol to achieve a target of moderate sedation is a challenging task
      for which anesthesia providers receive minimal training. Undersedation results in a
      noncompliant patient, while oversedation results in airway obstruction, respiratory
      depression, and hypotension. Considerable variability in patient pharmacokinetics (the
      distribution of drug within the body) and pharmacodynamics (the translation of drug
      concentration to clinical effect) has been demonstrated. The skill of titrating propofol to
      the desired target and maintaining this state is slowly acquired in the clinical environment
      of the endoscopy center with frequent reliance on rescue skills. An automated system that
      facilitates this process would be useful.

      Pharmacokinetic models allow us to make predictions of the results of drug administration.
      If we know the age and size of the patient, we can determine a quantity of propofol that
      will attain a desired concentration at some point in the future (within the predictive
      accuracy of the model). If they are old, this is less than if they are young. If they are
      obese, this is more than if they are thin. By adjusting the dosing, we can achieve similar
      concentrations at a specified time in a wide range of patients.

      Pharmacodynamic models allow us to relate drug concentration to a probability of response.
      Sensitivity is a randomly distributed variable, and the cumulative probability of response
      to propofol is well represented by a sigmoid curve. While we do not know the concentration
      that will suffice for a given individual, we can determine the probability that this
      individual will lose responsiveness within an interval of concentrations. For example, the
      probability of loss of responsiveness between 1 µg/ml and 6 µg/ml is around 99%. For any
      given age and size, an infusion sequence can be determined so that we traverse this interval
      smoothly. The infusion sequence is determined by minimization of the difference between the
      simulated probability and the target (1). We predict that 90% of 50 year old 70 kg patients
      will lose responsiveness between one minute and three minutes after initiating the infusion,
      and 99% by five minutes.  The infusion sequence for this patient is comprised of a bolus of
      287 µg/kg followed by an initial infusion of 216 µg/kg/min, with an increase to 550
      µg/kg/min after 147 seconds. By selecting the infusion sequence based on the age and size of
      the patient, all patients will track the same target line. These infusion rates are
      determined prior to initiation of sedation, and the clinician can verify that they are
      appropriate for the patient before beginning sedation.

      Once the endpoint of adequate sedation is observed, the effect site concentration associated
      with this endpoint is inferred, and the infusion that will maintain this concentration can
      be determined. This allows the clinical observation to be translated into an infusion rate,
      much as a driver accelerates to a desired speed and then engages the cruise control to
      maintain that speed.

      The intent of this study is to demonstrate equivalent safety and efficacy of PRC to control
      by a skilled clinician.

      References

      1.  Mandel JE, Sarraf E. The Variability of Response to Propofol Is Reduced When a Clinical
      Observation Is Incorporated in the Control: A Simulation Study. Anesthesia &amp; Analgesia.
      2012;114:1221-9.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Depth of sedation, as assessed by SEDLine processed EEG.</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraprocedure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>SEDLine® is a device that analyzes the electroencephalogram (EEG) with a proprietary algorithm and produces a number between zero and 100 that is related to the depth of anesthesia.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Predicted effect site concentrations for propofol</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraprocedure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Minute ventilation, as assessed by calibrated RIP</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraprocedure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Respiratory Inductance Plethysmography (RIP) utilizes fabric bands with a coil that is energized with an alternating current. The magnetic inductance is related to the area enclosed by the coil, which is proportional to lung volume. By calibration against a spirometer, continuous estimates of minute ventilation can be made.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemoglobin saturation, as assessed by pulse oximetry</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraprocedure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Endoscopist satisfaction, as assessed by 10 point Likert scale</measure>
    <time_frame>At completion of the procedure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Satisfaction by 10 point Likert scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to discharge from endoscopy suite, typically 30 minutes</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient satisfaction with sedation experience</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastrointestinal Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard of care sedation by CRNA using proposal with manual recording of drug dosing</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Probability ramp control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Propofol titrated to deep sedation using PRC software.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Probability ramp control</intervention_name>
    <description>Decision support software that calculates propofol doses appropriate for age and weight of the patient</description>
    <arm_group_label>Probability ramp control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Monitoring</intervention_name>
    <description>Manual recording of drug doses determined by CRNA</description>
    <arm_group_label>Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Manual recording of drug doses determined by CRNA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  scheduled for elective EGD

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to provide informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeff E Mandel, MD MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Endoscopy Center, Perelman Center for Advanced Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mandel JE, Sarraf E. The variability of response to propofol is reduced when a clinical observation is incorporated in the control: a simulation study. Anesth Analg. 2012 Jun;114(6):1221-9. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0b013e31824cb853. Epub 2012 Mar 30.</citation>
    <PMID>22467886</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 21, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>propofol sedation endoscopy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Gastrointestinal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Digestive System Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Propofol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
