<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="154865">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02081391</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR100949</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R331333PAI3037</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-004359-35</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>KF5503/65</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02081391</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Efficacy and Safety Study of Tapentadol in the Treatment of Post-operative Acute Pain Requiring Opiod Treatment in Pediatric Participants</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Evaluation of the Efficacy and Safety of Tapentadol Oral Solution in the Treatment of Post-operative Acute Pain Requiring Opioid Treatment in Pediatric Subjects Aged From Birth to Less Than 18 Years Old</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Grünenthal GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to evaluate the efficacy of tapentadol oral solution, based on
      the total amount of supplemental opiod analgesic used over 12 hours or 24 hours after
      initiation of investigational medicinal product in children and adolescents who have
      undergone surgery that would produce moderate to severe pain during opiod treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized (the study medication is assigned by chance), multi-site, double-blind
      (neither physician nor participant knows the treatment that the participant receives),
      placebo-controlled (placebo is compared with the study medication to test whether the study
      medication has a real effect in clinical study), parallel group (each group of participants
      will be treated at the same time), and multiple oral dose study. This study will consist of
      an enrollment phase (up to 28 days), a treatment phase (2 days), and a follow-up phase (up
      to 12 days). A dose regimen of 1.25 mg/kg will be used for the first 24 hours of treatment
      in this study in children aged 6 years to less than 18 years old. After 24 hours after the
      start of study medication, and based on clinical judgment, the dose may either be continued
      at 1.25 mg/kg or it may be decreased to 1.0 mg/kg. A decision to maintain or alter the dose
      will depend on the effectiveness of the analgesia (pain killer) and the adverse event
      profile observed in each child over the first 24 hour dosing period. The doses for
      participants aged less than 6 years old will be defined based on the forthcoming
      pharmacokinetic (what the body does to a medication) data. The rescue medication will be
      available as patient or nurse controlled intravenous morphine or hydromorphone. This rescue
      medication will be given to control pain, as needed, in both the treatment and placebo
      groups. Safety evaluations will include assessment of adverse events, vital signs,
      laboratory parameters, electrocardiogram, and specific scale to assess suicidal ideation.
      The maximum study duration for each participant will be 42 days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>For US: The total amount of supplemental opioid analgesic medication used within the first 12 hours after first intake of investigational medicinal product (IMP) [tapentadol oral solution or placebo] in participants aged from birth to less than 17 years</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>For Europe: The total amount of supplemental opioid analgesic (pain killer) medication used within the first 24 hours after first intake of IMP in participants aged from 2 years to less than 18 years</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The total amount of supplemental opioid analgesic medication used within the first 12 hours after the first intake of IMP in participants from 2 years to less than 18 years</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The total amount of supplemental opioid analgesic medication used within the first 24 hours after the first intake of IMP in participants aged from birth to less than 17 years</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The total amount of supplemental opioid analgesic medication received during treatment with IMP over a maximum period of 48 hours after the first dose of IMP</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The total amount of non-opioid analgesics used (irrespective of the indication) during the treatment period (2 days) within the first 24 hours or within the first 12 hours after the first dose of IMP</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 hours or 24 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Palatability of IMP in participants aged 3 years to less than 18 years assessed using facial 5-point hedonic scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Palatability of IMP will be assessed using 5-point hedonic scales in combination with verbal rating. A question &quot;How does the medication taste&quot; will be asked and the verbal rating will be from really good, good, a bit good/a bit bad, bad, and really bad. The pictorial scale of facial expressions will be co-related with verbal rating range where 5 = really good, 4 = good, 3 = a bit good/a bit bad, 2 = bad, and 1 = really bad. Higher scores represent good palatability.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability of IMP in participants aged 3 years to less than 18 years assessed using facial 5-point hedonic scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Acceptability of IMP will be assessed using 5-point hedonic scales in combination with verbal rating. A question &quot;Swallowing the medication is&quot; will be asked and the verbal rating will be from really good, good, a bit good/a bit bad, bad, and really bad. The pictorial scale of facial expressions will be co-related with verbal rating range, where 5 = really easy, 4 = easy, 3 = a bit easy/a bit difficult, 2 = difficult, and 1 = really difficult. Higher scores represent good acceptability.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in the Face, Leg, Activity, Cry, and Consolability (FLACC) total score in participants aged less than 3 years</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The FLACC scale is used to measure the pain intensity based on 5 criteria relating to face, legs, activity, crying, and consolability. Each criteria is assigned a score of 0, 1 or 2. The total score is the sum of the 5 individual criteria. Higher scores represent worse condition.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in the Faces Pain Scale-Revised (FPS-R) pain intensity score in participants aged 6 to less than 12 years</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The FPS-R is a validated self-reported 6-point scale with 0 representing no pain and 10 representing very much pain. Facial representations are used to indicate how much the pain hurts. Higher scores represent worse condition.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in the Visual Analog Scale (VAS) pain intensity score in participants aged 12 to less than 18 years</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The participant will be asked to draw a single line to indicate the current level of pain intensity on 100 mm long VAS. The scoring is the distance in millimeters across the scale with 0 mm is no pain and 100 mm is worst possible pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impression of Change (CGIC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The investigator rated the participant's global improvement and satisfaction with the treatment on a 7-point scale with 1=very much improved, 2=much improved, 3=minimally improved, 4=no change, 5=minimally worse, 6=much worse, and 7=very much worse. Higher scores indicate worsening.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Global Impression of Change (PGIC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants verbally rated their impression of overall status on a 7-point scale with 1=very much improved, 2=much improved, 3=minimally improved, 4=no change, 5=minimally worse, 6=much worse, and 7=very much worse. Higher scores indicate worsening.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to receive first and second patient or nurse controlled analgesia after the first dose of IMP</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time from first dose of IMP until treatment discontinuation due to lack of efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tapentadol IR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tapentadol immediate release oral solution 1.25 mg/kg will be given every 4 hours to participants aged 6 years to less than 18 years.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tapentadol 4 mg/mL</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants aged from 6 years to less than 18 years with body weight less than 20 kg will receive 1.25 mg/kg of tapentadol 4 mg/mL solution orally (by mouth) every 4 hours during the first 24 hours and 1.25 mg/kg or 1.0 mg/kg during the second 24 hours for 2 days. Dose of tapentadol 4 mg/mL solution for participants aged birth to less than 6 years with body weight less than 20 kg will be decided based on the forthcoming pharmacokinetic (PK) [what the body does to a medication] data.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tapentadol IR</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tapentadol 20 mg/mL</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants aged from 6 years to less than 18 years with body weight greater than or equal to 20 kg will receive 1.25 mg/kg of tapentadol 20 mg/mL solution orally every 4 hours during the first 24 hours and 1.25 mg/kg or 1.0 mg/kg during the second 24 hours for 2 days. Dose of tapentadol 20 mg/mL solution for participants aged birth to less than 6 years with body weight greater than or equal to 20 kg will be decided based on the forthcoming PK data.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tapentadol IR</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo solution will be administered orally every 4 hours during the first 24 hours and second 24 hours for 2 days..</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  A female participant must be pre-menarchal, or surgically incapable of childbearing,
             or sexually abstinent, or if a female participant is sexually active, then she must
             be practicing an effective method of birth control (eg, prescription hormonal
             contraceptives, intra-uterine devices used according to the product's instruction,
             double-barrier methods) before study entry and throughout the study

          -  A female participant must have a negative urine pregnancy test if aged 12 years or
             older, or is post-menarchal, or is sexually active

          -  Participant has undergone surgery (other than brain surgery or gastrointestinal
             surgery expected to affect the absorption of tapentadol [in the investigator's
             judgment]) that, in the investigator's opinion, would reliably produce moderate to
             severe pain requiring opioid treatment for at least 24 hours after
             allocation/randomization to investigational medicinal product (IMP) [a term used to
             describe the preparations under investigation in this study, ie, tapentadol oral
             solution and placebo]

          -  Participant has received post-operative morphine or hydromorphone by nurse controlled
             analgesia (NCA)/patient controlled analgesia (PCA), with or without a background
             infusion of the same opioid, according to standard of care prior to
             allocation/randomization to IMP and participant is expected to require this morphine
             or hydromorphone by NCA/PCA after starting IMP

          -  Participant is able to tolerate liquids at the time of allocation/randomization to
             IMP

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant has been previously exposed to tapentadol

          -  Participant has received an experimental drug or used an experimental medical device
             within 28 days before allocation/randomization to IMP, or within a period less than
             10 times the drug's half-life, whichever is longer

          -  Participant has a concomitant disease or disorder (e.g., endocrine, metabolic,
             neurological, psychiatric, infection, febrile seizure, paralytic ileus) that in the
             opinion of the investigator may affect or compromise participant safety during the
             study participation

          -  Participant has history of suicidal ideation or behavior

          -  Participant has a history of alcohol and/or substance abuse in the investigator's
             judgment based on participant's history and physical examination
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>This study is not yet recruiting patients. Please check back for future recruiting sites, or email</last_name>
    <email>JNJ.CT@sylogent.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 5, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Acute Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Post-operative</keyword>
  <keyword>Tapentadol</keyword>
  <keyword>Opiod Treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Pediatric Participants</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
