<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="50286">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01911429</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>D1050301</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-001695-38</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01911429</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pediatric Schizophrenia Efficacy and Safety Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>A 6-Week Randomized, Parallel, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Fixed-Dose, Multicenter Study To Evaluate The Efficacy and Safety of Lurasidone in Adolescent Subjects With Schizophrenia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sunovion</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sunovion</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Ukraine: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>Italy: The Italian Medicines Agency</authority>
    <authority>Serbia: Medicines and Medical Devices Agency</authority>
    <authority>Bulgaria: Bulgarian Drug Agency</authority>
    <authority>Colombia: National Institutes of Health</authority>
    <authority>China: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>Romania: National Medicines Agency</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Spanish Agency of Medicines</authority>
    <authority>Korea: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Malaysia: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>Philippines : Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Mexico: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Efficacy and Safety study of Lurasidone in pediatric patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the efficacy of lurasidone (40 mg/day and 80 mg/day) compared with placebo in
      adolescent subjects with schizophrenia (diagnosed by Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of
      Mental Disorders, 4th Ed., Text Revision [DSM-IV-TR] criteria) as measured by the change
      from Baseline in the Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) total score at Week 6.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary efficacy variable is change from Baseline in the Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) total score at Week 6.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Clinical Global Impression severity (CGI-S) scale at Day 4, Weeks 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in PANSS total score at Day 4, Weeks 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5</measure>
    <time_frame>5 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in PANSS positive, negative, general psychopathology, and excitability subscale scores at Day 4, Weeks 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of responders, where response is based on ≥ 20% improvement from Baseline in PANSS total score at Week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Pediatric Quality of Life Enjoyment and Satisfaction Questionnaire (PQ-LES-Q) at Week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Clinician-rated Children's Global Assessment Scale (CGAS) at Week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vital signs - will consist of supine systolic and diastolic blood pressures, respiration rate, heart rate, and oral body temperature</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight and Waist circumference</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CogState Computerized Cognitive Test Battery</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Barnes Akathisia Rating Scale (BARS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Abnormal Involuntary Movement Scale (AIMS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Simpson-Angus Scale (SAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tanner Staging</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Menstrual Cyclicity - At Baseline, female subjects will be given a calendar to mark the beginning and end of each menses. History of menstrual cyclicity and irregularities will be collected at Visit 1.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of remitters, defined as subjects who have score not exceeding 3(mild severity) for items P1, P3, N1, N4, N6, G5 and G9 of the PANSS at Week 6.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">249</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lurasidone 40 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Lurasidone 40 mg once daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lurasidone 80 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Lurasidone 80 mg once daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo 40 or 80 mg once daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lurasidone 40 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Lurasidone 40 mg once daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lurasidone 40 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Latuda</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lurasidone 80 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Lurasidone 80 mg once daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lurasidone 80 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Latuda</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo 40 or 80 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo 40 or 80 mg once daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Written informed consent from parent(s) or legal guardian(s) with sufficient
             intellectual capacity to understand the study and support subjects' adherence to the
             study procedures must be obtained for subjects who are not emancipated. In accordance
             with Institutional Review Board (IRB) requirements, the subject will complete an
             informed assent prior to study participation.

          -  Male or female subjects 13 to 17 years of age, inclusive, at the time of consent.

          -  DSM-IV-TR axis I primary diagnosis of schizophrenia (including disorganized (295.10),
             paranoid (295.30), undifferentiated (295.90) subtypes) and confirmation of the
             schizophrenia diagnosis by an adequately trained clinician at the time of screening,
             by means of the Schedule for Affective Disorders and Schizophrenia for School-age
             Children (K-SADS-PL).

          -  PANSS total score ≥ 70 at screening and Baseline.

          -  CGI-S ≥ 4 at screening and Baseline.

          -  Within 5th to 95th percentile for gender specific weight-for-age and height-for-age
             Growth Charts from National Center for Health Statistics.

          -  In good physical health on the basis of medical history, physical examination, and
             laboratory screening.

          -  Females who participate in this study:

        are unable to become pregnant (eg, premenarchal, surgically sterile, etc.); -OR-

        practices true abstinence (consistent with lifestyle) and must agree to remain abstinent
        from signing informed consent to at least 30 days after the last dose of study drug has
        been taken;

        -OR-

        are sexually active and willing to use a medically effective method of birth control
        (e.g., male using condom and female using condom, diaphragm, contraceptive sponge,
        spermicide, contraceptive pill, or intrauterine device) from signing informed consent to
        at least 7 days after the last dose of study drug has been taken.

          -  Males must be willing to remain sexually abstinent (consistent with lifestyle) or use
             an effective method of birth control (eg, male using condom and female using condom,
             diaphragm, contraceptive sponge, spermicide, contraceptive pill, or intrauterine
             device) from signing informed consent to at least 30 days after the last dose of
             study drug has been taken.

          -  In the judgement of the clinician, the subject has an acute exacerbation of psychotic
             symptoms (no longer than 2 months in duration) and marked deterioration of function
             from baseline (by history) or, the subject has been hospitalized for the purpose of
             treating an acute psychotic exacerbation for 2 consecutive weeks or less immediately
             before screening.

          -  In the judgment of the investigator, the subject is able to swallow the size and
             number of study drug tablets specified per protocol.

          -  Willing and able to adhere to protocol-specified meal requirements during dosing.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has an Axis I or Axis II diagnosis other than schizophrenia that has been the primary
             focus of treatment within 3 months of screening.

          -  Has a history or current diagnosis of mental retardation, neuroleptic malignant
             syndrome, or any neurologic disorder, or severe head trauma.

          -  Lifetime history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positive or acquired immune
             deficiency syndrome (AIDS), or history of Hepatitis B or C.

          -  Any of the following:

        Documented history of chromosomal disorder with developmental impairment (ie, trisomy
        chromosome 21; 22q11 deletion syndrome).

        Evidence of any chronic organic disease of the CNS such as tumors, inflammation, active
        seizure disorder, vascular disorder, potential CNS related disorders that might occur in
        childhood- eg, Duchenne Muscular dystrophy, myasthenia gravis, or other neurologic or
        serious neuromuscular disorders. In addition, subjects must not have a history of
        persistent neurological symptoms attributable to serious head injury. Past history of
        febrile seizure, drug-induced seizure, or alcohol withdrawal seizure is not exclusionary.

          -  PANSS total scores ≥ 120 at screening or Baseline.

          -  Exhibits evidence of moderate or severe extrapyramidal symptoms, dystonia, tardive
             dyskinesia, or any other moderate or severe movement disorder. Severity to be
             determined by the investigator.

          -  Lifetime history of electroconvulsive therapy (ECT).

          -  Resistant to antipsychotic treatment based on at least two different prior adequate
             trials (ie, adequate dose and duration) of an antipsychotic agent within the current
             episode of schizophrenia.

          -  Clinically significant neurological, metabolic (including type 1 diabetes), hepatic,
             renal, hematological, pulmonary, cardiovascular, gastrointestinal, carcinoma, and/or
             urological disorder that would pose a risk to the subjects if they were to
             participate in the study or that might confound the results of the study.

        Note: Active medical conditions that are minor or well-controlled are not exclusionary if
        they do not affect risk to the subject or the study results. In cases in which the impact
        of the condition upon risk to the subject or study results is unclear, the Medical Monitor
        should be consulted. Any subject with a known cardiovascular disease or condition (even if
        controlled) must be discussed with the Medical Monitor during screening.

          -  Has a history of malignancy &lt; 5 years prior to signing the informed consent.

          -  Clinically significant finding(s) on physical examination determined by the
             investigator to pose a health concern to the subject while on study.

          -  Clinically relevant abnormal laboratory values or abnormal vital sign
             values/findings.

        Note: If any laboratory results are outside the normal range, the site may have the
        subject retested. If upon retesting the value remains outside the normal range, the
        significance of this value must be discussed with the Medical Monitor for enrollment
        consideration.

          -  A history or presence of abnormal ECG, which in the investigator's opinion is
             clinically significant. Abnormal screening ECGs will be centrally over-read, and
             eligibility will be determined based on the over-read.

          -  Presence or history (within the last year) of a medical or surgical condition (eg,
             gastrointestinal disease) that might interfere with the absorption, metabolism, or
             excretion of orally administered lurasidone.

          -  Clinically significant alcohol abuse/dependence or drug abuse/dependence based on
             DSM-IV-TR criteria within the last 6 months prior to screening.

          -  Positive test results at screening or Baseline for:

               1. Urine drugs of abuse (amphetamines, barbiturates, benzodiazepines, cocaine,
                  opiates, phencyclidine, cannabinoids, and methadone). A positive test for
                  amphetamines, barbiturates, opiates, benzodiazepines or methadone may not result
                  in exclusion of subjects if the investigator determines that the positive test
                  is as a result of taking prescription medicine(s) as prescribed. In the event a
                  subject tests positive for cannabinoids (tetrahydrocannabinol) or alcohol, the
                  investigator will evaluate the subject's ability to abstain from prohibited
                  substances during the study. If in the investigator's clinical judgment the
                  subject will abstain, the subject may be enrolled after consultation with the
                  Medical Monitor.

               2. Pregnancy test.

          -  Females who are pregnant, lactating, or likely to become pregnant during the study.

          -  Participated in another interventional clinical trial or receiving an investigational
             product within 30 days prior to randomization.

          -  Donation of whole blood within 60 days prior to randomization.

          -  Known history or presence of clinically significant intolerance to any antipsychotic
             medications including but not limited to angioedema, serotonin or neuroleptic
             malignant syndromes.

          -  Clinically relevant history of drug hypersensitivity to lurasidone or any components
             in the formulation.

          -  Use of concomitant medications that consistently prolong the QT/QTc interval within
             28 days prior to randomization.

          -  Received depot neuroleptics unless the last injection was at least 1 month or 1
             treatment cycle prior to screening, whichever is longer.

          -  Received treatment with antidepressants, stimulants, or atomoxetine within 3 days
             prior to randomization, fluoxetine hydrochloride within 21 days of randomization,
             monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitor within 28 days of randomization, or clozapine
             within 120 days of randomization.

          -  Use of any antipsychotic medication (other than study drug), carbamazepine,
             oxcarbazepine, eslicarbazepine acetate, or fluvoxamine, within 3 days prior to
             randomization (7 days prior to randomization for aripiprazole) and until follow-up.

          -  Has a prolactin concentration ≥ 100 ng/mL at screening, or has a history of pituitary
             adenoma.

          -  At screening or Baseline the subject answers &quot;yes&quot; to &quot;Suicidal Ideation&quot; Items 4 or
             5 on the C-SSRS.

          -  Subject is considered by the investigator to be at imminent risk of suicide or injury
             to self, others, or property during the study. Subject has a history of one or more
             serious suicide attempts (based on the investigator's judgment) in the 3 months prior
             to screening. Subjects determined to be at risk of suicide or injury, as assessed by
             the investigator at screening, will be referred for further psychiatric evaluation.

          -  Adhering to a special diet for the 28 days prior to drug administration (eg, liquid,
             protein, raw food diet).

          -  Subject is planning to move during the study, is chronically homeless, or is unable
             to attend all planned study visits. The Medical Monitor will be consulted for
             individual cases, as needed.

          -  Demonstrates a decrease (improvement) of &gt; 25% in the PANSS score between screening
             and Baseline visits.

          -  Subject with newly diagnosed Type 2 diabetes during screening. A subject with Type 2
             diabetes is eligible for study inclusion if considered clinically stable, which is
             defined as:

        Random (non-fasting) screening glucose is &lt; 200 mg/dl (11.1 mmol/L); and If ≥ 200 mg/dL
        (11.1 mmol/L) must be retested in a fasted state. Retested fasted value cannot be ≥ 126
        mg/dL.

        HbA1c ≤ 6.5%; and If a subject is currently being treated with oral anti-diabetic
        medication(s), the dose must have been stable for at least 4 weeks prior to screening.
        Such medication may be adjusted or discontinued during the study, as clinically indicated.

          -  Subject has required hospitalization for diabetes or related complications in the
             past 12 months.

          -  Subject requires use of concomitant medications that are potent inducers or
             inhibitors of the cytochrome P450 (CYP) 3A4 enzyme system (Appendix C) from signing
             informed consent until follow-up.

          -  Clinically significant orthostatic hypotension (ie., a drop in systolic blood
             pressure of 20 mmHg or more and/or drop in diastolic blood pressure of 10 mmHg or
             more within 4 minutes of standing up).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lurasidone Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Sunovion</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <phone>1-866-503-6351</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Harmonex Neuroscience Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dothan</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>36303</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nelson Handel, MD</last_name>
      <phone>334-836-2000</phone>
      <email>nhandal@harmonex.us</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nelson Handel, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ProScience Research Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Culver City</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90230</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marina Bussel, MD</last_name>
      <phone>424-227-8127</phone>
      <email>marina.bussel@prosciencerg.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marina Bussel, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Diligent Clinical Trials, Inc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Downey</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90241</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elizabeth Zarat-Rowell, MD</last_name>
      <phone>562-622-0700</phone>
      <email>elizabethrowellmd@diligentclinicaltrials.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elizabeth Zarat-Rowell, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Collaborative Neuroscience Network, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Garden Grove</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92845</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Walling, MD</last_name>
      <phone>714-799-7799</phone>
      <email>davidwalling@cnstrial.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Walling, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Neuropsychiatric Research Center of Orange County</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orange</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92868</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Daniel Chueh, MD</last_name>
      <phone>714-289-1100</phone>
      <email>dchueh@ocresearchtrials.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Daniel Chueh, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hartford Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hartford</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Salma Malik, MD</last_name>
      <phone>860-545-7239</phone>
      <email>salma.malik@hhchealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Salma Malik, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Florida Clinical Research Center, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bradenton</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>34201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jose Zaglul, MD</last_name>
      <phone>941-747-7900</phone>
      <email>jzaglul@flcrc.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jose Zaglul, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sarkis Clinical Trials - Parent</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32607</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elias Sarkis, MD</last_name>
      <phone>352-333-0094</phone>
      <email>ok@ehsfamily.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elias Sarkis, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>APG Research, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32803</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Morteza Nadjafi, MD</last_name>
      <phone>407-423-7149</phone>
      <email>morinadjafi@aol.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Morteza Nadjafi, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical Research Group of Central Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sanford</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32771</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Adly Thebaud, MD</last_name>
      <phone>407-330-2262</phone>
      <email>athebaud@mrgcf.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Adly Thebaud, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Atlanta Center for Medical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30308</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andro Giorgadze, MD</last_name>
      <phone>404-881-5800</phone>
      <email>agiorgadze@acmr.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andro Giorgadze, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute for Behavioral Medicine, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Smyrna</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30080</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ashraf Attalla, MD</last_name>
      <phone>770-319-8025</phone>
      <email>pi@drashrafattalla.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ashraf Attalla, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lake Charles Clinical Trials, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lake Charles</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70629</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kashinath Yadalam, MD</last_name>
      <phone>337-564-6405</phone>
      <email>yadalamk@msn.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kashinath Yadalam, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Neurobehavioral Medicine Group, PLLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bloomfield Hills</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48302</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sanjeev Venketraman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>248-290-5400</phone>
      <email>raman.sanjeev@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sanjeev Venketraman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Finger Lakes Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14618</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sarah Atkinson, MD</last_name>
      <phone>585-241-9670</phone>
      <email>sda@flclinical.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sarah Atkinson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Richmond Behavioral Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Staten Island</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10312</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mark DiBuono, MD</last_name>
      <phone>718-317-5522</phone>
      <email>dibuono@rbany.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark DiBuono, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Cincinnati Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Melissa DelBello, MD</last_name>
      <phone>513-245-3415</phone>
      <email>delbelmp@email.uc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Melissa DelBello, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospitals Case Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nora McNamara, MD</last_name>
      <phone>216-844-5295</phone>
      <email>nora.mcnamara@uhhospitals.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nora McNamara, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cutting Edge Research Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73116</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Willis Holloway, MD</last_name>
      <phone>405-603-8068</phone>
      <email>wholloway@cuttingedgeresearch.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Willis Holloway, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Strategies of Memphis, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38119</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anita Varma, MD</last_name>
      <phone>901-685-8890</phone>
      <email>varmamd@researchmemphis.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anita Varma, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>BioBehavioral Research of Austin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Austin</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78759</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Divyansu Patel, MD</last_name>
      <phone>512-382-6661</phone>
      <email>patel@bbraustin.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Divyansu Patel, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pillar Clinical Research, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75243</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Scott Bartley, MD</last_name>
      <phone>214-396-4844</phone>
      <email>sbartley@pillarhc.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Scott Bartley, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Family Psychiatry of The Woodlands, P.A.</name>
      <address>
        <city>The Woodlands</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77381</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marshall Lucas, MD</last_name>
      <phone>281-367-1015</phone>
      <email>mlucasmd2011@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marshall Lucas, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aspen Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orem</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84058</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Harris, MD</last_name>
      <phone>801-356-5555</phone>
      <email>drmharris@aspclinic.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Harris, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pacific Institute Of Medical Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bothell</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98011</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Syed Mustafa, MD</last_name>
      <phone>425-949-5779</phone>
      <email>souad@pspc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Syed Mufstafa, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro de Investigacion Clinica Psiquiatrica</name>
      <address>
        <city>Caguas</city>
        <zip>00725</zip>
        <country>Puerto Rico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jorge Matta-Gonzalez, MD</last_name>
      <phone>787-744-0857</phone>
      <email>drjmatta@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jorge Matta-Gonzalez, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro de Investigacion Clinica Psiquiatrica</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ponce</city>
        <zip>00731</zip>
        <country>Puerto Rico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Osvaldo Caro,, MD</last_name>
      <phone>787-842-2841</phone>
      <email>clinicainvestigativa@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Osvaldo Caro, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>INSPIRA Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Juan</city>
        <zip>00918</zip>
        <country>Puerto Rico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yvette Cruz, MD</last_name>
      <phone>787-753-9515</phone>
      <email>yvette_marie_cru@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yvette Cruz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 22, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>schizophrenia</keyword>
  <keyword>Lurasidone</keyword>
  <keyword>Latuda</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
