<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="131296">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02134977</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>265-211</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02134977</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Leuprorelin Acetate SR 11.25 mg Injection Kit Specified Drug-use Survey: &quot;QOL Survey in Premenopausal Breast Cancer Patients&quot;</brief_title>
  <official_title>Leuplin SR 11.25 mg Injection Kit Specified Drug-use Survey: &quot;QOL Survey in Premenopausal Breast Cancer Patients&quot;</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Takeda</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Japan: Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this survey is to examine the effect on QOL improvement and convenience of
      switching to Leuprorelin acetate 3 moths depot 11.25 mg Injection Kit (Leuplin SR 11.25 mg
      Injection Kit) from a 4-week adjuvant therapy with a LH-RHa 1 month depot over 48 weeks in
      premenopausal breast cancer patients in daily medical practice. Influence of condition of
      estrogen receptor expression on the efficacy and safety of Leuprorelin acetate SR 11.25 mg
      Injection Kit was also evaluated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This survey was designed to examine the effect on QOL improvement and convenience of
      switching to Leuprorelin acetate 3 month depot 11.25 mg Injection Kit (Leuplin SR 11.25 mg
      Injection Kit) from a 4-week adjuvant therapy with a LH-RHa 1 month depot over 48 weeks in
      premenopausal breast cancer patients in daily medical practice, as well as to evaluate the
      influence of condition of estrogen receptor expression  on the efficacy and safety of
      Leuprorelin acetate SR 11.25 mg Injection Kit .

      For adults, Leuprorelin acetate SR 11.25 mg Injection Kit (Leuplin SR 11.25 mg Injection
      Kit) is usually administered subcutaneously once every 12 weeks. Prior to injection, the
      plunger rod of the syringe is pushed upward with the needle pointed upward, allowing the
      entire suspension fluid contained to be transferred to the powder. The powder is then fully
      suspended in the fluid while ensuring that bubbles are not generated.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in QOL</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 48 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>For the efficacy analysis set, the following parameters will be tabulated: changes in QOL (QOL-ACD score, QOL-ACD-B score, patient impression to switching medication) from baseline to 48 weeks of treatment will be tabulated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of adverse drug reactions</measure>
    <time_frame>For 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The frequencies of all adverse events observed during the observation period will be tabulated by type and seriousness. Adverse events are defined as any unfavorable and unintended signs, symptoms or diseases temporally associated with administration of leuprorelin acetate whether or not it was considered related to treatment. Among these, events that are considered as having a causal relationship with leuprorelin acetate are defined as adverse drug reactions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2816</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>leuprorelin acetate</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subcutaneous administration of leuprorelin acetate once every 12 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Leuprorelin acetate</intervention_name>
    <description>Leuprorelin acetate SR 11.25 mg Injection Kit</description>
    <arm_group_label>leuprorelin acetate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Leuplin SR 11.25 mg Injection Kit</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Breast cancer
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Premenopausal breast cancer patients who meet all the following criteria are to be
             enrolled in the surveillance:

               1. Patients who received 4 weeks of treatment with a repository LH-RHa preparation
                  within 1 week prior to administration of Leuplin SR 11.25 mg Injection Kit

               2. Patients receiving Leuplin SR 11.25 mg Injection Kit as adjuvant therapy

               3. Patients with performance status grade of 0 or 1

               4. Patients who answered all of the questions on the &quot;QOL check sheet (I)&quot; at the
                  start (Week 0) of treatment with Leuplin SR 11.25 mg Injection Kit

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who meet any of the following criteria are to be excluded from the
             surveillance:

               1. Patients with a history of hypersensitivity to ingredient(s) in Leuplin SR 11.25
                  mg Injection Kit or synthetic derivatives of LH-RH or LH-RH

               2. Pregnant women, possibly pregnant women, and nursing mothers

               3. Patients with advanced (T4 or M1 according to the TNM classification [General
                  Rules for Clinical and Pathological Recording of Breast Cancer: 16th edition])
                  or recurrent breast cancer
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Postmarketing Group Manager</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Takeda</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 23, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pharmacological therapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Leuprolide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
