<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="58620">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01802034</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1207012648</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01802034</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Repository of Novel Analytes Leading to Autoimmune, Inflammatory and Diabetic Nephropathies (RENAL AID)</brief_title>
  <acronym>RENAL AID</acronym>
  <official_title>Repository of Novel Analytes Leading to Autoimmune, Inflammatory and Diabetic Nephropathies (RENAL AID)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Rogosin Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>New York Presbyterian Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Rogosin Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The central goal of this data repository is to collect data from a large population of
      patients with diabetic nephropathy and inflammatory renal conditions.  This initiative will
      provide an opportunity to compare data from various disease states with the objective of
      determining clinical and biological factors that predict disease progression, response to
      therapy and identify discriminating noninvasive clinical and biological features that
      predict renal biopsy findings.  Other objectives include the discovery of new molecules and
      molecular pathways that lead to the tissue fibrosis that invariably leads to diminished
      renal function.  Finally, a central aim of this study is to explore the biologic mechanisms
      that shift the balance of fibrotic mediators to a state of anti-fibrosis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to collect subject data demographic, clinical, biochemical,
      histological, and RNA (genetic) data that will further explore the natural history of
      diabetic nephropathy (DN), autoimmune nephropathies (AN), and inflammatory nephropathies
      (IN) in order to assess for factors that may be associated with the progression of disease,
      the incidence of complications (including renal failure), and the response to therapy.

      This research is being done because relatively few subjects have been studied for a
      sufficient period to fully understand how subjects are affected over the course of their
      lifetime. The reason for creating this repository is to collect information about
      inflammatory, autoimmune, or diabetic nephropathy in order to assess for factors that may be
      associated with the progression of disease, the incidence of complications (including renal
      failure) and the response to therapy.  Also, certain patterns of inflammatory and/or immune
      mediators present in the serum, whole blood, and urine of subjects with renal disease may be
      predictive of the underlying histopathology present in renal biopsy specimens.  The
      potential correlation of non-invasive markers with underlying histopathology in subjects
      undergoing renal biopsy may afford the ability to make renal diagnoses non-invasively in the
      future.

      The study will have two Cohorts:

        1. DN Cohort:  Subjects with clinical diagnosis of diabetic nephropathy.  Criteria for DN
           cohorts includes: a) Clinical diagnosis of Type 1 or 2 diabetes, b) Any of the
           following: microalbuminuria (&gt;40mg/day), proteinuria (&gt;300mg/day), impaired glomerular
           filtration rate (GFR), diabetic retinopathy, c) Diagnosis of diabetic nephropathy based
           upon renal biopsy findings.

           These subjects will be subdivided into sub-cohorts: DN-Descriptive and DN-Detailed:

             1. Subjects in the DN-Descriptive sub-cohort will be asked to return to study clinic
                every six months in the first year and then once a year thereafter.

             2. Subjects in the DN-Detailed sub-cohort will be evaluated more frequently than the
                DN-Descriptive sub-cohort and will be asked to return to the study clinic every 3
                months for the first two years of the protocol, then every six months thereafter.
                In most cases, the follow-up study visits will be conducted simultaneously with
                regularly scheduled clinic visits.

        2. IN Cohort:  Subjects undergoing renal biopsies for presumed inflammatory or autoimmune
           renal conditions.  Criteria for IN cohorts include: a) Present necessity for renal
           biopsy based upon standard clinical criteria, b) Previous renal biopsy leading to
           historic diagnosis of inflammatory or autoimmune nephritides.

      These subjects will be subdivided into two sub-cohorts: IN-Descriptive and IN-Detailed:

        1. Subjects in the IN-Descriptive sub-cohort will be seen at the study clinic on the day
           of their renal biopsy and asked to return to the study clinic one month, six months and
           12 months after the biopsy and then one a year thereafter. Patients with prior renal
           biopsy are also eligible without having to undergo repeat biopsy.  In most cases, the
           follow up study visits will be conducted simultaneously with regularly scheduled clinic
           visits.

        2. Subjects in the IN-Detailed sub-cohort will be evaluated more frequently than the
           IN-Descriptive sub-cohort and will be seen at the study clinic on the day of their
           biopsy and asked to return to the study clinic one month after the biopsy, then every
           three months for the first two years of the protocol and then every six months
           thereafter. In most cases, the follow up study visits will be conducted simultaneously
           with regularly scheduled clinic visits.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <target_duration>10 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in disease progression</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Kidney Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Kidney Failure, Chronic</condition>
  <condition>Diabetic Nephropathy</condition>
  <condition>Lupus Nephritis</condition>
  <condition>Glomerulonephritis, IGA</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Diabetic Nephropathy (DN)</arm_group_label>
    <description>This Cohort will be sub-divided into to two Sub-cohorts:
A. DN-Descriptive
B. DN-Detailed</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Inflammatory/autoimmune Renal Condition (IN)</arm_group_label>
    <description>This Cohort will be sub-divided into two Sub-cohorts:
A. IN-Descriptive
B. IN-Detailed</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood, urine, tissue
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects in the Descriptive Sub-cohorts will be recruited from The Rogosin Institute,
        NewYork Presbyterian Hospital and affiliated institutions.

        Subjects in the Detailed Sub-cohorts will be recruited from The Rogosin Institute and
        NewYork Presbyterian Hospital.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  DN Cohort: Males or females, age 18 and older, with presumptive diagnosis of diabetic
             nephropathy are eligible to participate.

          -  IN Cohort: Males or females, age 18 and older. Indication for native renal biopsy
             based upon the clinical suspicion for an autoimmune or inflammatory nephropathy
             (IN-Detailed sub-cohort and IN-Descriptive sub-cohorts). Previous renal biopsy with
             resultant historic clinical diagnosis (IN-Descriptive sub-cohort). Willing and able
             to provide informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  DN Cohort: Exclusion criteria: Inability to provide informed consent.

          -  IN Cohort: Exclusion criteria: Inability to provide informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alan S Perlman, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Rogosin Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shaquanda Lippman, B.A.</last_name>
    <phone>646-898-2753</phone>
    <email>shl9081@nyp.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alan Perlman, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>212-746-1580</phone>
    <email>alp9021@nyp.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Rogosin Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alan S Perlman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nathaniel Berman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Miriam H Chung, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James M Chevalier, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Choli Hartono, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Surya Seshan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert R Riggio, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Manikkam Suthanthiran, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John CL Wang, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 22, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 15, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Nephropathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glomerulonephritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glomerulonephritis, IGA</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lupus Nephritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nephritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
