<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="94139">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01971255</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130215</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-I-0215</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01971255</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Anti-Hemagglutinin (Anti-HA) Antibodies as Protection From the Flu in Healthy People</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Anti-Hemagglutinin Antibodies as a Correlate of Protection in an H1N1 Influenza Healthy Human Challenge Model</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Researchers want to know if a certain type of antibody in the blood affects whether people
      get influenza (the flu). They will study 2 different groups with different levels of anti-HA
      antibodies and expose them to the flu virus. They will study how the flu develops in a
      healthy person. This may lead to future studies to develop new vaccines and treatments for
      the flu.

      Objective:

      - To study how people can be protected from flu infection.

      Eligibility:

      - Healthy volunteers 18 to 50 years of age.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened through the use of a medical history, physical exam, and
           laboratory tests.

        -  Groups of 7 participants will stay in an isolation unit in a hospital for at least 9
           days with no visitors.

        -  Participants will be screened again upon admission. They will also have:

        -  ECG: soft electrodes will be stuck to the skin. A machine will record the heart   s
           electrical signals.

        -  Echocardiogram: a small probe will be held to the chest to take pictures of the heart.

        -  Lung tests: participants will blow into a machine.

        -  They will also have nasal fluid collected. This will be done either with a swab or with
           a tube of water washing out the nose. This will be done once every day.

        -  The flu virus will be sprayed into the participant   s nose. This will be done only
           once.

        -  Participants will complete a questionnaire on day 1 and twice a day after that for 14
           days.

        -  A medical team will watch participants 24 hours a day. They will go home after 2 days
           of negative flu tests.

        -  Participants will have 4 follow-up visits over 8 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The high morbidity and mortality associated with both pandemic and seasonal influenza, and
      the threat of new pandemic strains emerging, continues to keep influenza at the forefront of
      infectious disease and public health research.  Mean annual estimates of influenza deaths
      due to seasonal influenza alone, attributes 36,000 deaths in the US and 250,000 to 500,000
      deaths in industrialized countries to influenza.  Pandemics can have an even more
      devastating effect, and we must continue to be prepared by making attempts to reduce the
      public health impact of this important virus.

      Currently, influenza vaccination is the cornerstone of prophylaxis and most effective method
      available to reduce the impact of influenza on the world   s population each year.  Data
      from the 2013 influenza season suggest that current seasonal vaccines held to these
      standards are greatly underperforming especially in those that really need protection such
      as the elderly, young, and infirmed.

      Multiple factors could play a role in defining the true correlates of protection to
      influenza infection and disease and many of these factors are yet to be clearly defined.  In
      our own influenza challenge study, protocol 12-I-0077, we have clearly seen evidence that
      not everyone with a low HAI titer is susceptible to influenza, and that there must be other
      factors protecting certain individuals.  There are many examples like this that demonstrate
      that there may be much more to immune protection to influenza than just anti-HA antibodies.

      Live virus challenge studies have played an important role in defining the correlates of
      protection of influenza in the past, and we believe they can continue to do so in the
      future.  Since the last time a wild-type influenza challenge has been performed to
      investigate correlates of protection over 20 years ago, many new scientific tools and a
      significant increase in knowledge of the immune system have developed.  In this study we
      will enroll participants at different hemagglutinin inhibition titer levels and evaluate
      this as a correlate of protection to the 2009 H1N1 while exploring the other possible
      correlates of protection that may be identified.  This study represents the first
      opportunity to examine the correlates of protection of influenza in a fully validated and
      described wild-type virus challenge model. We believe that studies like this are an ideal
      use of a wild-type influenza challenge study and can lead to intelligent universal vaccine
      design as well as a basis to begin evaluating novel vaccine strategies in wild-type
      challenge studies in the future.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Viral shedding detected by positive diagnostic test from a nasal wash or swab as well as clinical symptoms.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza, Human</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Virus administration</intervention_name>
    <description>Virus administration influenza A/H1N1 challenge virus, IND#14969</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Greater than or equal to 18 and less than or equal to 50 years of age.

          2. Agrees to not use tobacco products during participation in this study.

          3. Willingness to remain in isolation for the duration of viral shedding (at a minimum 9
             days) and to comply with all study requirements.

          4. A female participant is eligible for this study if she is not pregnant or breast
             feeding and 1 of the following:

               -  Of nonchildbearing potential (i.e., women who have had a hysterectomy or tubal
                  ligation or are postmenopausal, as defined by no menses in greater than or equal
                  to 1 year).

               -  Of childbearing potential but agrees to practice effective contraception or
                  abstinence for 4 weeks prior to and 8 weeks after administration of the
                  influenza challenge virus. Acceptable methods of contraception include 1 or more
                  of the following: 1) male partner who is sterile prior to the female participant
                    s entry into the study and is the sole sexual partner for the female
                  participant; 2) implants of levonorgestrel; 3) injectable progestogen; 4) an
                  intrauterine device with a documented failure rate of &lt; 1%; 5) oral
                  contraceptives; and 6) double barrier methods including diaphragm or condom with
                  a spermicide.

          5. Willing to have samples stored for future research.

          6. Prechallenge serum hemagglutination inhibition (HAI) titer against the challenge
             virus of greater than or equal to 1:40 or less than or equal to 1:10 during a
             screening visit in protocol #11-I-0183

          7. HIV uninfected.

        EXCLUSION CRITEIRA:

          1. Presence of self-reported or medically documented significant medical condition
             including but not limited to:

               1. Chronic pulmonary disease (e.g., asthma, emphysema).

               2. Chronic cardiovascular disease (e.g., cardiomyopathy, congestive heart failure,
                  cardiac surgery, ischemic heart disease, known anatomic defects).

               3. Chronic medical conditions requiring close medical follow-up or hospitalization
                  during the past 5 years (e.g., diabetes mellitus, renal dysfunction,
                  hemoglobinopathies).

               4. Immunosuppression or ongoing malignancy.

               5. Neurological and neurodevelopmental conditions (e.g., cerebral palsy, epilepsy,
                  stroke, seizures).

               6. Postinfectious or postvaccine neurological sequelae.

          2. Have close or household (i.e., share the same apartment or house) high-risk contacts
             including but not limited to:

               1. Persons greater than or equal to 65 years of age.

               2. Children less than or equal to 5 years of age.

               3. Residents of nursing homes.

               4. Persons of any age with significant chronic medical conditions such as:

                    -  Chronic pulmonary disease (e.g., asthma).

                    -  Chronic cardiovascular disease (e.g., cardiomyopathy, congestive heart
                       failure, cardiac surgery, ischemic heart disease, known anatomic defects).

                    -  Contacts who required medical follow-up or hospitalization during the past
                       5 years because of chronic metabolic disease (e.g., diabetes mellitus,
                       renal dysfunction, hemoglobinopathies).

                    -  Immunosuppression or cancer.

                    -  Neurological and neurodevelopmental conditions (e.g., cerebral palsy,
                       epilepsy, stroke, seizures).

                    -  Individuals who are receiving long-term aspirin therapy.

                    -  Women who are pregnant or who are trying to become pregnant.

          3. Individual with body mass index (BMI) less than or equal to 18.5 and greater than or
             equal to 40.

          4. Smokes more than 4 cigarettes or other tobacco products on weekly basis.

          5. Complete blood count (CBC) with differential outside of the NIH DLM normal reference
             range and deemed clinically significant by the PI.

          6. Chemistries in the acute care, mineral, and/or hepatic panels, and/or any of the
             following: lactate dehydrogenase, uric acid, creatine kinase, and total protein
             outside of the NIH DLM normal reference range and deemed clinically significant by
             the PI.

          7. Urinalysis outside of the NIH DLM normal reference range and deemed clinically
             significant by the PI.

          8. Clinically significant abnormality on electrocardiogram.

          9. Clinically significant abnormality as deemed by the PI on echocardiographic testing.

         10. Clinically significant abnormality as deemed by the PI on the Pulmonary Function Test
             (PFT).

         11. Recent acute illness within 1 week of admission to the isolation facility.

         12. Known allergy to treatments for influenza (including but not limited to oseltamivir,
             nonsteroidals).

         13. Known allergy to 2 or more classes of antibiotics (e.g., penicillins, cephalosporins,
             fluoroquinolones, or glycopeptides).

         14. Receipt of blood or blood products (including immunoglobulins) within 3 months prior
             to enrollment.

         15. Receipt of any unlicensed drug within 3 months or 5.5 half-lives (whichever is
             greater) prior to enrollment.

         16. Receipt of any non-influenza related unlicensed vaccine within 6 months prior to
             enrollment.

         17. Self-reported or known history of current alcoholism or drug abuse, or positive
             urine/serum test for drugs of abuse (i.e., amphetamines, cocaine, benzodiazepines,
             opiates, or metabolites, but not tetrahydrocannabinol (THC) or metabolites).

         18. Self-reported or known history of psychiatric or psychological issues deemed by the
             PI to be a contraindication to protocol participation

         19. Known close contact with anyone known to have influenza in the past 7 days.

         20. Any condition or event that, in the judgment of the PI, is a contraindication to
             protocol participation or impairs the volunteer   s ability to give informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Matthew J Memoli, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rani S Athota</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 594-0803</phone>
    <email>rani.athota@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Matthew J Memoli, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 443-5971</phone>
    <email>mm982v@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-I-0215.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stöhr K, Esveld M. Public health. Will vaccines be available for the next influenza pandemic? Science. 2004 Dec 24;306(5705):2195-6.</citation>
    <PMID>15618505</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thompson WW, Shay DK, Weintraub E, Brammer L, Cox N, Anderson LJ, Fukuda K. Mortality associated with influenza and respiratory syncytial virus in the United States. JAMA. 2003 Jan 8;289(2):179-86.</citation>
    <PMID>12517228</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cox RJ. Correlates of protection to influenza virus, where do we go from here? Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2013 Jan 4;9(2). [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>23291930</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 23, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Influenza A</keyword>
  <keyword>HAI</keyword>
  <keyword>H1N1</keyword>
  <keyword>Challenge Study</keyword>
  <keyword>Correlates of Protection</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hemagglutinins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
