<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="115891">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01776268</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>121760</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01776268</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Colostrum on Mucosal Immunity in Very Low Birth Weight (VLBWs) Premature Infants</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Colostrum on Innate Mucosal Immunity in Very Premature Infants</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Vanderbilt University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Thrasher Research Fund</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Vanderbilt University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Infection in preterm infants is a common, costly, and devastating problem frequently causing
      death or sequelae for survivors. An immature immune system underlies the frequency and
      severity of infections in this vulnerable population. The mouth is the site where microbes
      first meet the mucosal immune system. Antimicrobial proteins and peptides (APPs) in saliva
      kill microbes and improve immune cell function. Low APP levels increase the risk of
      developing infection. Colostrum and human milk reduce the risk of infection. This protective
      effect of human milk may come from supplying or stimulating infant production of APPs. No
      prior investigation has determined the concentration of APPs in saliva or the effect of
      human milk/formula on the APP concentrations in saliva.

      Objective(s) and Hypothesis(es):

      The investigators objectives are to identify and serially determine the concentrations of
      key APPs in colostrum, human milk, and preterm infant saliva using highly-sensitive and
      specific mass spectroscopy methods. The investigators study is designed to test the
      hypotheses that (a) all saliva APPs increase over time, (b) APP concentrations are higher in
      colostrum as compared to human milk, and (c) APPs are increased in saliva of infants that
      receive colostrum orally compared to those that do not.

      Potential Impact:

      If increased saliva APP levels are associated with oral colostrum priming, this discovery
      would advance understanding of the immune properties of human milk and identify oral APPs as
      important immune elements and potential therapeutic targets in this vulnerable population.
      This knowledge has the potential to alter feeding practices and provide a safe, low cost
      means to improve immune function and significantly improve outcomes for preterm infants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: Between 20 and 60% of very low birth weight (VLBW) infants are diagnosed with
      infection during their initial hospitalization2-9. Infection in preterm infants is a costly
      and devastating problem associated with high mortality and debilitating survivor morbidity.
      High infection rates are attributed to suboptimal preterm neonatal immune function. In depth
      investigation of the unique properties of the preterm neonatal immune function is necessary
      to identify novel interventions that can translate into improved neonatal outcomes.

      Mucosal surfaces are critical immune barriers that shield against host microbial invasion by
      surface-colonizing commensal or potentially pathogenic organisms. Antimicrobial proteins and
      peptides (APPs) on mucosal surfaces reduce microbial burden individually and synergistically
      by direct killing of microbes and by improving immune surveillance through activation of
      local sentinel cells. Deficiencies in these innate immune proteins predispose the host to
      infection or dysregulated inflammation. Two major classes of APPs (defensins and
      cathelicidin) are present on mucosal surfaces in adults. Colostrum and human milk (HM)
      contain some APPs that may play an adjuvant role on mucosal sites including the mouth. HM
      ingestion is associated with a decreased risk of developing sepsis and necrotizing
      enterocolitis in preterm infants. One potential mechanism behind the reduction in infection
      risk associated with HM feeding may be enhanced immunocompetence through provision of APPs
      and induction of neonatal APP production. Investigators are not aware of any investigation
      that has determined the neonatal salivary concentration of any APP or the effect of oral
      priming (OP) with colostrum on the concentration of salivary APPs. It is also unknown
      whether OP with formula modifies salivary APPs.

      Objectives and Hypotheses: Our objectives are to determine: 1) the concentration of salivary
      APPs from preterm infants at baseline and 7 days later, 2) the effect of oral priming (OP)
      with either human milk or formula on salivary APP concentrations, and 3) the concentration
      of APPs in colostrum as compared to milk. Our hypotheses are: 1) All salivary APPs increase
      over time in preterm infants (with or without OP) 2) Compared with formula OP or no OP,
      colostrum OP is associated with a significantly greater increase in salivary LL-37 and hBD2
      concentrations and 3) Colostrum contains a greater concentration of LL-37 compared to human
      milk.

      Design: Following the mother's decision to provide human milk or formula to her preterm
      newborn, VLBW infants will be randomized to receive OP or not. Investigators will compare
      the concentration of salivary APPs from VLBW infants that receive OP to VLBW infants that do
      not. Saliva will be sampled prior to and after 5 days of OP. Time-matched saliva samples
      will be obtained from the infants that do not receive OP. APP concentrations will be
      compared between the biological mother's colostrum (both whey and fat fractions) and her
      transitional milk (produced &gt;7 days after birth). To account for the heterogeneous VLBW
      population, investigators will study 200 infants (50 infants/group, 4 groups) to test our
      hypotheses. Both inborn and outborn VLBW infants are eligible. Exclusion criteria include
      infants with a medical contraindication for oral or enteral feeds, congenital anomalies or
      chromosomal disorders. Saliva and milk-based proteomes including APPs will be determined
      using Matrix Assisted Laser Desorption/Ionization Time-of-Flight (MALDI-TOF).

      Potential Impact: This is the first study of APPs in saliva of human neonates. If increased
      saliva APP levels are associated with colostrum OP, this discovery would add to our
      understanding of the immune properties of human milk. Identification of APPs as important
      elements that improve immune function is likely to alter the approach to infant nutrition
      and improve outcomes for premature infants. Ultimately, our goal is to determine whether
      there is an association between APP levels in neonatal saliva and the incidence of neonatal
      infection (including NEC) in an appropriately powered clinical study based on the data
      generated in this proposal.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>concentration of APPs before and after oral priming</measure>
    <time_frame>days 1-2 of life, then again on day 7-8 of life</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Saliva will be sampled on day 1-2 of life prior to oral priming, and again 24-48 hours after the 5-days of oral priming is completed. Investigators are assessing saliva for a change in the concentration of antimicrobial proteins.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Prematurity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Colostrum priming</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention:Mother's own colostrum is administered (0.1 mL to each cheek every 6 hours for 5 days) as soon as it is available from the mother regardless of when enteral feedings are initiated. Infants randomized to receive formula/donor milk OP will receive an identical volume of oral formula/donor milk with the start of OP matched by post-natal age.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>no priming</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Infants will be randomized to receive formula/donor milk oral priming and will receive an identical volume of oral formula/donor milk as those in the mother's colostrum group with the start of oral priming matched by post-natal age.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oral priming</intervention_name>
    <description>Intervention:Mother's own colostrum is administered (0.1 mL to each cheek every 6 hours for 5 days) as soon as it is available from the mother regardless of when enteral feedings are initiated. Infants randomized to receive formula/donor milk OP will receive an identical volume of oral formula/donor milk with the start of OP matched by post-natal age.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Colostrum priming</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No oral priming</intervention_name>
    <description>no intervention</description>
    <arm_group_label>no priming</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Very low birth weight (&lt;1500 g)

          -  Gestational age &lt;30 weeks

          -  Admission to NICU (born at Vanderbilt or transferred in for care)

          -  English or Spanish-speaking parents

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Does not meet inclusion criteria

          -  Parent does not give study consent

          -  Has congenital anomalies, chromosomal disorder or medical contraindication to
             oral/enteral feedings
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>1 Year</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James L Wynn, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Vanderbilt University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Monroe Carell Jr Children's Hospital at Vanderbilt University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232-0656</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>James L Wynn, MD</last_name>
      <phone>615-343-0206</phone>
      <email>james.wynn@vanderbilt.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James L Wynn, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 10, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 17, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Vanderbilt University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>James Wynn</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>antimicrobial proteins</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
