<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="106025">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02060162</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-2568</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02060162</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Antiretroviral Treatment Outcomes in HIV-HBV Co-infected Patients in Southern Africa</brief_title>
  <official_title>CIDRZ-1220 Antiretroviral Treatment Outcomes in HIV-HBV Co-infected Patients in Southern Africa: a Collaborative Multi-country Prospective Cohort Analysis for International Epidemiologic Databases to Evaluate AIDS- Southern Africa (HIV/HBV-coinfection in IeDEA-SA)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Carolyn Bolton Moore, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Zambia: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>Zambia: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to establish a cohort of patients starting antiretroviral therapy (ART) with
      chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection and study the effect of chronic HBV on HIV- and
      liver-related outcomes according to ART regimen and site.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will take place during routinely scheduled ART visits as per Ministry of Health.
      Routinely collected programmatic data will be used to assess general HIV outcomes (CD4
      response, loss to follow-up, death) as well as collecting study specific data (hepatitis
      testing, questionnaire regarding risk factors for hepatitis/liver disease, and non-invasive
      liver scan) to address other aims. The study will be implemented at three sites with a total
      enrollment across all sites of 3000 participants. However our site will only enroll 1000.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunological response</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>a linear mixed effect model will be used to evaluate immunological response</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Virological response</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Virological response will be evaluated using Cox regression analyses.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hepatotoxicity events</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>These events will be defined as an increase in the level of alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &gt; 5 time the upper limit within the first year of ART.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of liver fibrosis</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and one year after start of ART</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>the prevalence of liver fibrosis will be measured to compare HIV/hepatitis coinfected versus HIV monoinfected patients using transient elastography.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HBV drug resistance</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The presence of HBV drug resistance in co-infected patients who fail treatment after 1 year will be measured</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of HBV infection</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months post enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The incidence of HBV infection during the first year of ART will be measured.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of HIV/HCV coinfection</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months post enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Predictors of hepatitis coinfection and liver fibrosis</measure>
    <time_frame>enrollment, 6 and 12 months post</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Predictors such as heavy alcohol use, drug use, and sexual behaviors will be measured.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatitis B Virus</condition>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HIV/HBV infected</arm_group_label>
    <description>800 to 920 our site (1100 to 1230 in total) patients without chronic HBV infection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HIV infected, Non HBV infected</arm_group_label>
    <description>50 to 80 participants at our site (100 to 170 patients across all sites) with chronic HBV infection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard of care</intervention_name>
    <description>routine standard of care per Ministry of Health protocol including blood draws and examinations.</description>
    <arm_group_label>HIV/HBV infected</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>HIV infected, Non HBV infected</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      The laboratory will store any leftover blood specimens for up to 5 years for hepatitis
      related serologic, immunological, and virologic studies pending availability of funding. Use
      of specimens for any tests outside the realm of the goals and objectives of this study will
      require additional approval by the REC.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Enrollment of 1,000 consecutive patients starting ART at each of the three sites is
        planned.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV-infected

          -  Male or female aged ≥18 years

          -  ART naïve

          -  ART eligible as defined by Zambian or WHO treatment guidelines

          -  Initiating an ART regimen including at least 3 drugs at one of the study sites.

          -  Willing to provide signed informed consent and be followed at the clinical site.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who are not planning to remain in the catchment area from which they were
             recruited for the duration of the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carolyn Bolton-Moore, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centre for Infectious Disease Research in Zambia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael Vinikoor, MD</last_name>
    <phone>260 966921285</phone>
    <email>michael.vinikoor@cidrz.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre for Infectious Disease Research in Zambia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lusaka</city>
        <country>Zambia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Vinikoor, MD</last_name>
      <phone>260 966921285</phone>
      <email>michael.vinikoor@cidrz.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Caroloyn Bolton-Moore, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Zambia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.unc.edu</url>
    <description>University of North Carolina website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barth RE, Huijgen Q, Taljaard J, Hoepelman AI. Hepatitis B/C and HIV in sub-Saharan Africa: an association between highly prevalent infectious diseases. A systematic review and meta-analysis. Int J Infect Dis. 2010 Dec;14(12):e1024-31. doi: 10.1016/j.ijid.2010.06.013. Epub 2010 Sep 25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20870439</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chang TT, Gish RG, de Man R, Gadano A, Sollano J, Chao YC, Lok AS, Han KH, Goodman Z, Zhu J, Cross A, DeHertogh D, Wilber R, Colonno R, Apelian D; BEHoLD AI463022 Study Group. A comparison of entecavir and lamivudine for HBeAg-positive chronic hepatitis B. N Engl J Med. 2006 Mar 9;354(10):1001-10.</citation>
    <PMID>16525137</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Davies J, van Oosterhout JJ, Nyirenda M, Bowden J, Moore E, Hart IJ, Zijlstra EE, Chaponda M, Faragher B, Beeching NJ, Beadsworth MB. Reliability of rapid testing for hepatitis B in a region of high HIV endemicity. Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg. 2010 Feb;104(2):162-4. doi: 10.1016/j.trstmh.2009.10.010.</citation>
    <PMID>19931107</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>De Luca A, Bugarini R, Lepri AC, Puoti M, Girardi E, Antinori A, Poggio A, Pagano G, Tositti G, Cadeo G, Macor A, Toti M, D'Arminio Monforte A; Italian Cohort Naive Antiretrovirals Study Group. Coinfection with hepatitis viruses and outcome of initial antiretroviral regimens in previously naive HIV-infected subjects. Arch Intern Med. 2002 Oct 14;162(18):2125-32.</citation>
    <PMID>12374521</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Di Bisceglie AM, Maskew M, Schulze D, Reyneke A, McNamara L, Firnhaber C. HIV-HBV coinfection among South African patients receiving antiretroviral therapy. Antivir Ther. 2010;15(3 Pt B):499-503. doi: 10.3851/IMP1494. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20516571</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dienstag JL, Schiff ER, Wright TL, Perrillo RP, Hann HW, Goodman Z, Crowther L, Condreay LD, Woessner M, Rubin M, Brown NA. Lamivudine as initial treatment for chronic hepatitis B in the United States. N Engl J Med. 1999 Oct 21;341(17):1256-63.</citation>
    <PMID>10528035</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Firnhaber C, Reyneke A, Schulze D, Malope B, Maskew M, MacPhail P, Sanne I, Di Bisceglie A. The prevalence of hepatitis B co-infection in a South African urban government HIV clinic. S Afr Med J. 2008 Jul;98(7):541-4.</citation>
    <PMID>18785395</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoffmann CJ, Charalambous S, Martin DJ, Innes C, Churchyard GJ, Chaisson RE, Grant AD, Fielding KL, Thio CL. Hepatitis B virus infection and response to antiretroviral therapy (ART) in a South African ART program. Clin Infect Dis. 2008 Dec 1;47(11):1479-85. doi: 10.1086/593104.</citation>
    <PMID>18937580</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoffmann CJ, Charalambous S, Thio CL, Martin DJ, Pemba L, Fielding KL, Churchyard GJ, Chaisson RE, Grant AD. Hepatotoxicity in an African antiretroviral therapy cohort: the effect of tuberculosis and hepatitis B. AIDS. 2007 Jun 19;21(10):1301-8.</citation>
    <PMID>17545706</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lok AS, Lai CL, Leung N, Yao GB, Cui ZY, Schiff ER, Dienstag JL, Heathcote EJ, Little NR, Griffiths DA, Gardner SD, Castiglia M. Long-term safety of lamivudine treatment in patients with chronic hepatitis B. Gastroenterology. 2003 Dec;125(6):1714-22.</citation>
    <PMID>14724824</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lok AS, Zoulim F, Locarnini S, Bartholomeusz A, Ghany MG, Pawlotsky JM, Liaw YF, Mizokami M, Kuiken C; Hepatitis B Virus Drug Resistance Working Group. Antiviral drug-resistant HBV: standardization of nomenclature and assays and recommendations for management. Hepatology. 2007 Jul;46(1):254-65. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17596850</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marcellin P, Heathcote EJ, Buti M, Gane E, de Man RA, Krastev Z, Germanidis G, Lee SS, Flisiak R, Kaita K, Manns M, Kotzev I, Tchernev K, Buggisch P, Weilert F, Kurdas OO, Shiffman ML, Trinh H, Washington MK, Sorbel J, Anderson J, Snow-Lampart A, Mondou E, Quinn J, Rousseau F. Tenofovir disoproxil fumarate versus adefovir dipivoxil for chronic hepatitis B. N Engl J Med. 2008 Dec 4;359(23):2442-55.</citation>
    <PMID>19052126</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nagu TJ, Bakari M, Matee M. Hepatitis A, B and C viral co-infections among HIV-infected adults presenting for care and treatment at Muhimbili National Hospital in Dar es Salaam, Tanzania. BMC Public Health. 2008 Dec 19;8:416. doi: 10.1186/1471-2458-8-416.</citation>
    <PMID>19099553</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nikolopoulos GK, Paraskevis D, Hatzitheodorou E, Moschidis Z, Sypsa V, Zavitsanos X, Kalapothaki V, Hatzakis A. Impact of hepatitis B virus infection on the progression of AIDS and mortality in HIV-infected individuals: a cohort study and meta-analysis. Clin Infect Dis. 2009 Jun 15;48(12):1763-71. doi: 10.1086/599110.</citation>
    <PMID>19435436</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nyirenda M, Beadsworth MB, Stephany P, Hart CA, Hart IJ, Munthali C, Beeching NJ, Zijlstra EE. Prevalence of infection with hepatitis B and C virus and coinfection with HIV in medical inpatients in Malawi. J Infect. 2008 Jul;57(1):72-7. doi: 10.1016/j.jinf.2008.05.004. Epub 2008 Jun 13.</citation>
    <PMID>18555534</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oshitani H, Kasolo F, Tembo C, Mpabalwani M, Mizuta K, Luo N, Suzuki H, Numazaki Y. Hepatitis B virus infection among pregnant women in Zambia. East Afr Med J. 1995 Dec;72(12):813-5.</citation>
    <PMID>8689985</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Otegbayo JA, Taiwo BO, Akingbola TS, Odaibo GN, Adedapo KS, Penugonda S, Adewole IF, Olaleye DO, Murphy R, Kanki P. Prevalence of hepatitis B and C seropositivity in a Nigerian cohort of HIV-infected patients. Ann Hepatol. 2008 Apr-Jun;7(2):152-6.</citation>
    <PMID>18626434</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stabinski L, Reynolds SJ, Ocama P, Laeyendecker O, Ndyanabo A, Kiggundu V, Boaz I, Gray RH, Wawer M, Thio C, Thomas DL, Quinn TC, Kirk GD; Rakai Health Sciences Program. High prevalence of liver fibrosis associated with HIV infection: a study in rural Rakai, Uganda. Antivir Ther. 2011;16(3):405-11. doi: 10.3851/IMP1783.</citation>
    <PMID>21555823</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Selabe SG, Lukhwareni A, Song E, Leeuw YG, Burnett RJ, Mphahlele MJ. Mutations associated with lamivudine-resistance in therapy-naïve hepatitis B virus (HBV) infected patients with and without HIV co-infection: implications for antiretroviral therapy in HBV and HIV co-infected South African patients. J Med Virol. 2007 Nov;79(11):1650-4.</citation>
    <PMID>17854040</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 9, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 9, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carolyn Bolton Moore, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief Medical Officer</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>antiretroviral therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatitis C virus</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis B</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
