<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="53646">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01910831</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CCCR 28-2013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01910831</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Randomized, Double-Blind, Contralateral, Controlled Study to Assess the Efficacy of DerMend Moisturizing Bruise Formula in Improving the Appearance of Chronically Aged Mature Skin of the Forearms and Hands</brief_title>
  <acronym>CCCR 28-2013</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomized, Double-Blind, Contralateral, Controlled Study to Assess the Efficacy of DerMend Moisturizing Bruise Formula in Improving the Appearance of Chronically Aged Mature Skin of the Forearms and Hands</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Center for Clinical and Cosmetic Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Center for Clinical and Cosmetic Research</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine the efficacy (measured at 12 weeks) of DerMend Moisturizing Bruise Formula in
      improving the appearance of bruising and reducing the appearance of photoaging of the
      forearms and hands in mature skin. Assessments will be made through ongoing objective
      measurements and clinical ratings.

      To confirm the safety (local tolerance) of DerMend Moisturizing Bruise Formula.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Twenty subjects with mature skin, at one study center, with bruising and moderate to severe
      photodamage will be selected for the study.  At baseline, the Subject will be instructed to
      use the study cream on one forearm and hand while a control cream will be used on the other.
      Both the study cream and the control cream will be provided in containers labeled Left and
      Right so that the subjects are blinded.  Each cream labeled Left and Right will be
      randomized with either the treatment or control cream in the Left container and the opposite
      cream will be assigned to the Right container. Each subject will always get the control
      cream in one container and the treatment cream in the other container.  Each subject will be
      randomized to apply cream Right to the right forearm and hand. Subject will apply cream Left
      to the left forearm and hand.  At each visit, the Evaluator will count the total number of
      bruises, determine the size of each bruise and assess each forearm and hand for surface
      roughness, laxity and mottled hyperpigmentation.  Furthermore, subjective investigator and
      subject global assessments of bruising, skin roughness, wrinkling and pigmentation will be
      measured.  Subjects will be evaluated at weeks 0 (baseline), 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, and 12.
      Additionally, standardized, high-resolution digital photographs will be taken at each visit
      using the Vectra software..

      The following scales will be used for grading these features:  Roughness (degree of scaling
      and surface texture) - very smooth (1), mostly smooth (2), slightly rough (3), rough (4),
      very rough (5).  Laxity (ability to spring back after pinching the skin) - very tight (1),
      somewhat tight (2), somewhat loose (3), loose (4), very loose (5).  Mottled
      hyperpigmentation (a combination of lentigines and hyperpigmented and hypopigmented spots) -
      very even (1), mostly even with few blotches (2), blotchy (3), mostly blotchy (4), very
      blotchy (5).

      Secondary endpoints will be measured including the speed of healing (measured by the two
      week average percentage change in bruising) and a reduction in the Investigator's and
      Subject's Global Assessment compared to baseline after twelve weeks.  The following 5-point
      scale will be used for both the Investigator's and Subject's Global Assessments:  0, no
      improvement; 1, &lt;25% improvement; 2, 25% to 50% improvement; 3, 51% to 75% improvement; and
      4, &gt;75% improvement.

      Finally, adverse events, including but not limited to redness, swelling, blistering,
      ulceration, bleeding, itch or pain, will be monitored at each visit and assessed by both the
      Subject and the Evaluator.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction of Bruising</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the efficacy (measured at 12 weeks) of DerMend Moisturizing Bruise Formula in improving the appearance of bruising and reducing the appearance of photoaging of the forearms and hands in mature skin.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bruising Reduction Subject</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine efficacy with respect to the subject's self-assessment of improving the appearance of &quot;bruising&quot; and reducing the appearance of photoaging of the forearms and hands.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Bruise Reduction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DerMend Moisturizing Bruise Formula</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Apply LEFT treatment to LEFT arm or (vica versa) RIGHT treatment to RIGHT arm. Will not be known to the subject which arm is on the active treatment and which is on the placebo control. Applied twice daily for 12 weeks. Each subject will have one arm/hand that is either a)the experimental treatment or b) the placebo control.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-active placebo control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Apply LEFT treatment to LEFT arm or (vica versa) RIGHT treatment to RIGHT arm. Will not be known to the subject which arm is on the active treatment and which is on the placebo control. Each subject will have one arm/hand that is either a)the experimental treatment or b) the placebo control.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DerMend Moisturizing Bruise Formula</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>DerMend Moisturizing Bruise Formula</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who meet all of the following criteria are eligible for this study:

               1. Male and female subjects who are 60-80 years of age, with phototypes I to IV.

               2. Subjects who have provided written, informed consent.

               3. Subjects with multiple bruises on both forearms and hands.

               4. Subjects with moderate to severe photodamage on forearms and hands.

               5. Subjects with relatively equal photodamage on both forearms and hands.

               6. Subjects who are willing to follow the treatment schedule.

               7. Subjects who are willing to maintain their usual sunscreen or use of
                  photoprotective clothing during outdoor activities.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who meet any of the following criteria are not eligible for this study:

               1. Participation in a clinical drug or device research study within 30 days of
                  enrollment or participation in a research study concurrent with this study;

               2. Subjects with history of bleeding disorders;

               3. Subjects with use of isotretinoin in the past 12 months;

               4. Subjects with a pacemaker or internal defibrillator;

               5. Subjects who take more than 2 anticoagulant therapies.

               6. Treatment of any type of cancer within the last 6 months;

               7. Subjects who are unable to communicate or cooperate with the Investigator due to
                  language problems, poor mental development, or impaired cerebral function;

               8. History of hypersensitivity or allergic reactions to any of the study
                  preparations as described in the Investigator's Brochure, including known
                  sensitivities to any ingredient;

               9. Concomitant use of potentially irritating over-the-counter products that contain
                  ingredients such as arnica, alpha-hydroxy acid, salicylic acid, retinol or
                  glycolic acid;

              10. Subjects who present with one or more conditions which, in the opinion of the
                  investigator, making the subject unsuitable for participation.

              11. Subjects who apply any topicals other than the study treatment or their usual
                  sunscreen.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark S Nesotr, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Director</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brian Berman, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Co-director</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Julie A Santos, PA-C, CRC</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Study Coordinator</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrew C Frisina, MS</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Study Coordinator</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center for Clinical and Cosmetic Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aventura</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33180</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 11, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 25, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>bruising, reduction, older age, aging</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Contusions</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
