<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="163174">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01970696</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>International OTST Registry</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01970696</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>International Ovarian &amp; Testicular Stromal Tumor Registry</brief_title>
  <acronym>OTST</acronym>
  <official_title>International Ovarian &amp; Testicular Stromal Tumor Registry</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospitals and Clinics of Minnesota</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Children's Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospitals and Clinics of Minnesota</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Rare tumors are understudied, yet have the potential to shed light on vast areas of cancer
      research. Ovarian sex cord-stromal tumors, rare tumors of childhood and young adulthood,
      have recently been found to be associated with a lung cancer of early childhood called
      pleuropulmonary blastoma (PPB). The cause of these ovarian tumors is unknown. DICER1
      mutations are seen in the majority of children with PPB. Research shows DICER1 mutations are
      also seen in some patients with ovarian tumors. Like PPB, ovarian stromal tumors are highly
      curable when found in early stage; however, later forms of the disease are aggressive and
      often fatal. The International Ovarian Stromal Tumor Registry collects clinical and biologic
      data to understand why these tumors occur and how to treat them. Current work involves the
      study the role of DICER1 and miRNA expression in ovarian stromal tumors. Understanding the
      clinical history, predisposing factors and DICER1 and miRNA expression in these ovarian
      tumors of childhood will lead to targeted screening and risk stratification for
      evidence-based treatment and biologically rational therapies. These efforts will improve the
      lives of children by increasing survival and reducing late effects.

      The specific goals of the International Ovarian and Testicular Stromal Tumor Registry are:

        1. to understand risk factors by studying age, pathologic subtype, histopathologic
           features, tumor invasiveness, degree of differentiation, presence of metastasis

        2. to collect information on personal and family history in order to refine the clinical
           characteristics of patients and families with and without germline DICER1 mutations and
           other genetic predisposing factors

        3. to determine whether there is a pattern of gene expression or DNA alterations that
           correlate with predisposition to ovarian tumors, biologic behavior and clinical outcome

        4. to determine optimal screening regimens

        5. to use clinical data obtained through the Registry to refine treatment algorithms

        6. to establish a collection of annotated biology specimens (tumor tissue and germline
           DNA) for future research
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Registry collects and analyzes case-by-case data on ovarian stromal tumors.  Cases are
      identified:

        1. by referrals from clinicians or pathologists

        2. by families initiating contact with the Registry

        3. by Registry requests to authors of published cases to share further details

      The data collected include:

        1. clinical and laboratory findings

        2. family history

        3. imaging studies

        4. surgery records

        5. pathology records including review and study of pathology materials

        6. treatment (surgery, chemotherapy, radiation)

        7. recurrences or metastases

        8. long-term follow-up

      The demographic and clinical data are abstracted into a database secured by password
      protection. Each record in the database has a unique Registry number.

      Enrollment in the OTST Registry is based on local diagnosis, but central pathology review is
      offered as a part of Registry procedures. DICER1 testing is offered but not required.

      For each patient enrolled, the Registry will request 1) whole blood for DNA extraction and
      lymphoblastoid cell line generation  2) slides or snap frozen tumor tissue (if available),
      and 3) paraffin blocks. In some cases, saliva samples or buccal swab samples will be
      obtained for DNA extraction.

      Pathology materials are centrally reviewed when available. Any discrepancies in the
      diagnostic interpretation are discussed with the submitting pathologist or clinician. When
      the central review pathologist cannot confirm diagnosis of a stromal tumor, the referring
      physician is notified. The local pathologist retains responsibility for the final
      pathological diagnosis. It is the responsibility of the referring physician to notify the
      patient regarding any discrepancy found.

      DICER1 kits containing consents, medical testing requisition forms, as well as UN3373
      approved specimen shipping containers with two ACD tubes and instructions for collection and
      mailing are prepared and sent to families. Participants arrange for phlebotomy services with
      their physicians. Biologic specimens will be banked and stored for future research.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2011</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>N/A</study_design>
  <target_duration>10 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>DICER1 mutations in ovarian and testicular stromal tumors</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will analyze germline DNA from patients with gonadal stromal tumors to determine the presence of DICER1 mutations. The tumor tissue will also be sequenced. mRNA and miRNA expression will be analyzed on tumor tissue. Results of the above will be correlated with clinical outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical factors associated with outcome in ovarian and testicular stromal tumors</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will analyze the clinical records to determine which factors influence prognosis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pathologic and Genetic Correlations</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will correlate the pathologic and genetic data with clinical data to describe factors associated with poor prognosis. We will look for targetable mutations for later stage and recurrent tumors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Ovarian Stromal Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Testicular Stromal Tumors</condition>
  <condition>Ovarian Small Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ovarian Stromal Tumors</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Testicular Stromal Tumors</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ovarian Small Cell Carcinoma</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      1) whole blood for DNA extraction and lymphoblastoid cell line generation, 2) stained and
      unstained slides and snap frozen tumor tissue (if available), and 3) paraffin blocks.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Prospectively or retrospectively diagnosed patients with ovarian or testicular stromal
        tumors or ovarian small cell carcinoma
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous or current diagnosis of an ovarian sex cord stromal including but not
             limited to: Sertoli-Leydig cell tumor, gynandroblastoma, juvenile granulosa cell
             tumor, Sertoli cell tumor, sex cord stromal tumor with annular tubules or
             undifferentiated stromal tumor

          -  Previous or current diagnosis of a testicular stromal tumor including but not limited
             to: juvenile granulosa cell tumor, Sertoli cell tumor, Leydig cell tumor or
             undifferentiated stromal tumor

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No clinical or biologic material available for review

          -  Unable to provide informed consent/assent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kris Ann P Schultz, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital and Clinics of Minnesota</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital &amp; Clinics of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55404</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kris Ann P Schultz, MD</last_name>
      <phone>612-813-5940</phone>
      <email>OTST@childrensMN.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Anne K Harris</last_name>
      <phone>612-813-5861</phone>
      <email>OTST@childrensMN.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kris Ann P Schultz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.OTSTregistry.org</url>
    <description>International OTST Registry official website</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.PPBregistry.org</url>
    <description>International PPB Registry</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schultz KA, Schneider DT, Pashankar F, Ross J, Frazier L. Management of ovarian and testicular sex cord-stromal tumors in children and adolescents. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 2012 May;34 Suppl 2:S55-63. doi: 10.1097/MPH.0b013e31824e3867. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22525408</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Doros L, Yang J, Dehner L, Rossi CT, Skiver K, Jarzembowski JA, Messinger Y, Schultz KA, Williams G, André N, Hill DA. DICER1 mutations in embryonal rhabdomyosarcomas from children with and without familial PPB-tumor predisposition syndrome. Pediatr Blood Cancer. 2012 Sep;59(3):558-60. doi: 10.1002/pbc.24020. Epub 2011 Dec 16.</citation>
    <PMID>22180160</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schultz KA, Pacheco MC, Yang J, Williams GM, Messinger Y, Hill DA, Dehner LP, Priest JR. Ovarian sex cord-stromal tumors, pleuropulmonary blastoma and DICER1 mutations: a report from the International Pleuropulmonary Blastoma Registry. Gynecol Oncol. 2011 Aug;122(2):246-50. doi: 10.1016/j.ygyno.2011.03.024. Epub 2011 Apr 17.</citation>
    <PMID>21501861</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schultz KA, Sencer SF, Messinger Y, Neglia JP, Steiner ME. Pediatric ovarian tumors: a review of 67 cases. Pediatr Blood Cancer. 2005 Feb;44(2):167-73.</citation>
    <PMID>15490488</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schultz KA, Ness KK, Nagarajan R, Steiner ME. Adnexal masses in infancy and childhood. Clin Obstet Gynecol. 2006 Sep;49(3):464-79. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16885654</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rio Frio T, Bahubeshi A, Kanellopoulou C, Hamel N, Niedziela M, Sabbaghian N, Pouchet C, Gilbert L, O'Brien PK, Serfas K, Broderick P, Houlston RS, Lesueur F, Bonora E, Muljo S, Schimke RN, Bouron-Dal Soglio D, Arseneau J, Schultz KA, Priest JR, Nguyen VH, Harach HR, Livingston DM, Foulkes WD, Tischkowitz M. DICER1 mutations in familial multinodular goiter with and without ovarian Sertoli-Leydig cell tumors. JAMA. 2011 Jan 5;305(1):68-77. doi: 10.1001/jama.2010.1910.</citation>
    <PMID>21205968</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 23, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 23, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Children's Hospitals and Clinics of Minnesota</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kris Ann Schultz</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Kris Ann P. Schultz, MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ovarian</keyword>
  <keyword>testicular</keyword>
  <keyword>stromal</keyword>
  <keyword>Sertoli</keyword>
  <keyword>Leydig</keyword>
  <keyword>gynandroblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>granulosa cell tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>DICER1</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Small Cell Lung Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Small Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
